<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; A Continent's Lively Past and Uncertain Future</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="577135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAMPBELL, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CRYSTAL DESERT, THE: SUMMERS IN ANTARCTICA (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DF123CF934A25751C1A964958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; A Continent's Lively Past and Uncertain Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Crystal Desert</p>
        <p>Summers in Antarctica</p>
        <p>By David G. Campbell</p>
        <p>308 pages. Houghton Mifflin. $21.95.</p>
        <p>"I spent three summers in Antarctica, in places beyond the horizon of most of the rest of my species," writes David G. Campbell at the opening of his remarkable book, "The Crystal Desert: Summers in Antarctica."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Crystal Desert</p>
        <p>Summers in Antarctica</p>
        <p>By David G. Campbell</p>
        <p>308 pages. Houghton Mifflin. $21.95.</p>
        <p>"I spent three summers in Antarctica, in places beyond the horizon of most of the rest of my species," writes David G. Campbell at the opening of his remarkable book, "The Crystal Desert: Summers in Antarctica."</p>
        <p>"The journeys all took place during the single long day that begins in October and ends in March," he continues. "Sometimes, in the sere glaciated interior of the continent, Antarctica seemed to be a prebiotic place, as the world must have looked before the broth of life bubbled and popped into whales and tropical forests -- and humans. I was as lonely as an astronaut walking on the moon. But at other times, during the short, erotic summer along the ocean margins of the continent, Antarctica seemed to be a celebration of everything living, of unchecked DNA in all its procreative frenzy, transmuting sunlight and minerals into life itself, hatching, squabbling, swimming and soaring on the sea wind."</p>
        <p>Books of nature writing are sometimes static in their pace, perhaps because their panoramas are often too vast for prose narrative. Mr. Campbell, who teaches at Grinnell College in Iowa, avoids this problem by telling hypnotic stories and enfolding them within one another. There's the story of his summer in a Brazilian research station on King George Island in the South Shetlands, "an ocean-sculpted arc of islands" that lies in the water called Drake Passage just north of the Antarctic Peninsula. One episode in that story entailed a 2,000-foot climb up a mountain to change the light bulbs in a crucifix 20 feet high. Another involved a scuba dive 50 feet deep into near-freezing water to observe the surprisingly abundant aquatic life.</p>
        <p>Into his personal narrative, he folds the awesomely larger story of the enormous continent, posthumously named Gondwanaland, of which, fossil records suggest, Antarctica was once a part. Gondwanaland included what are now Australia, India, Africa, Madagascar and South America until tectonic forces began tearing it apart 150 million years ago, and Antarctica eventually moved from a more temperate clime to its present polar location.</p>
        <p>Then there is the dramatic history of polar exploration. At its most noble, it involves five men who in 1912 gave up their lives in an attempt to sled important but burdensome fossils out of the interior. But mainly it is a bloody story of commercial greed that has cost the lives of hundreds of thousands of animals and driven several species to the brink of extinction.</p>
        <p>But most arrestingly of all, Mr. Campbell tells the tales of the flora and fauna that came within his scientific ken, creatures as large as a female blue whale measuring almost 100 feet long, which was killed in 1923, "one of the largest animals ever to have existed in the long history of life on the planet," or as small as the diatoms he peered at through his microscope, "sexually sophisticated, producing eggs and spermatozoa, and therefore endowing their progeny with all the splendid array of recombinant genetic permutations that sex permits."</p>
        <p>He tells of terns that migrate all the way from the North Pole to the South Pole, about as far as bird can travel on the planet; of whales that change their complex tunes from season to season, and of krill that swarm to form what is "among the greatest biological phenomena on Earth . . .  the planktonic equivalent of a redwood forest, of migrating monarch butterflies, or of the migration of wildebeest and zebras across the Serengeti."</p>
        <p>He writes of penguins that fly through water instead of air; of the sea spider that isn't a spider, but an arthropod that composes its own subphylum, the Pycnogonida, many members of which use their proboscises "to suck up the tissues and fluids of their prey in a prolonged lethal kiss," and of his particular specialty, "the acanthocephalans, the so-called spiny-headed worms, a few millimeters long, that parasitize seals, fish and invertebrates."</p>
        <p>To insure that a fish will eat the amphipod, or flat-bodied crustacean, that the acanthocephalan occupies at one stage, its larva "addles the pigment of the amphipod, causing it to lose its cryptic gray coloration and turn brick red." The text continues: "Then, because its immune system is compromised, the amphipod becomes heavily colonized by white yeasts, giving it a mottled appearance. Finally, its instinct to hide beneath rocks and debris is overridden by a parasite-driven imperative to convulsively gyrate through the open water. Utterly conspicuous, it is eaten by a fish in no time."</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell makes poetry of science, sometimes brutal, sometimes sublime. Dispassionately, he evokes the lustiness of mating seals, the filth of a penguin rookery and the terrible stench of life aboard a 19th-century whaling vessel. Without a glimmer of anthropomorphism, he describes things in nature that would have made Charles Darwin weep in despair over what a God he considered "beneficent and omnipotent" could have designedly created.</p>
        <p>Yet toward the end of "The Crystal Desert," an anxious sadness does begin to pervade Mr. Campbell's narrative. Partly this results from his history of the whaling industry and his conclusion that the vestigial whale populations will probably not recover their former abundance. Partly it arises from foreboding over what the greenhouse effect and depletion of the ozone layer are already doing to Antarctica.</p>
        <p>And partly the sadness lies in the sense of vast time and huge forces his powerful book elicits. In the echo of a sentence from early in the narrative, "And unless we as a species somehow addle the tick and cycle of climate and glacier, all this will once more be scraped clean, the gouge that is Admiralty Bay will deepen, and the life that hauls itself out on the shore or coats the seafloor will once again retreat beyond the edge of cold or into the submarine canyons."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
