<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tree Grows In Architecture: 'Green' Design</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHITECTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENBERG, CARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D6103FF930A35751C1A964958260" item-length="1391" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tree Grows In Architecture: 'Green' Design</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARA GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENBERG, CARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE photovoltaic panels sprouting on the roof of every house, a fish farm in every kitchen and krypton gas "superwindows" instead of storm windows. Innovations like these, intended to minimize damage to the environment, may sound unlikely, but then, 20 years ago, so did recycling.</p>
        <p>There are signs that the architecture movement -- variously called "environmentally responsible," "environmentally sensitive," "sustainable" or "green" and meant to save energy, improve air quality, avoid chemicals, reduce waste and recycle materials -- is gaining momentum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE photovoltaic panels sprouting on the roof of every house, a fish farm in every kitchen and krypton gas "superwindows" instead of storm windows. Innovations like these, intended to minimize damage to the environment, may sound unlikely, but then, 20 years ago, so did recycling.</p>
        <p>There are signs that the architecture movement -- variously called "environmentally responsible," "environmentally sensitive," "sustainable" or "green" and meant to save energy, improve air quality, avoid chemicals, reduce waste and recycle materials -- is gaining momentum.</p>
        <p>Although there have been efforts to conserve fossil fuels at least since the oil crises of the 1970's and there has been an increased awareness of hazards like lead paint, the greening of the building industry has been sporadic. Now, however, more architects are educating themselves and their clients about "holistic" approaches to building that make the environment a priority, literally from the ground up.</p>
        <p>Kirsten Childs is director of interior design at Croxton Collaborative, an architectural firm that recently renovated the new headquarters of the National Audubon Society, 700 Broadway, at East Fourth Street in Greenwich Village. It is now one of the lowest energy-consuming office buildings in the country, Ms. Childs said, adding that a lot of the building's features, like maximized use of daylight and low-toxicity paints, are applicable to residential as well as commercial design.</p>
        <p>She and her partner, Randolph Croxton, an architect, specialize in environmental upgrades of buildings.  "If you build with your eye to the future and look at such things as maintenance, replacement, energy use and so on," she said, "it is not more expensive to build environmentally."</p>
        <p>William McDonough, a New York architect known for his commitment to environmentally sound design, said: "We're looking at a phenomenal shift in perception. People are recognizing that we are reaching the limits of the planet's ability to provide."</p>
        <p>That observation was echoed by Carl Costello, director of the American Institute of Architects Center for the Environment, which provides architects with information on the practice of architecture as it relates to the environment. "Environmentally responsible design and building is no longer a fringe idea," he said.</p>
        <p>Membership in the center's Committee on the Environment has doubled in the last year, to 1,200 interested architects, and subscriptions to its quarterly, Environmental Resource Guide, have tripled, to over 1,000, Mr. Costello said. And the American Institute of Architects has made "design for a sustainable future" the theme of its annual conference next June in Chicago.</p>
        <p>"The fact that Clinton picked Al Gore to be his running mate indicates he's interested in environmental issues," said Susan Maxman, a Philadelphia architect who will begin a one-year term as president of the institute on Saturday. The Vice President-elect's book "Earth in the Balance" (Houghton Mifflin), offers far-reaching plans for a unified global response to the environmental crisis.</p>
        <p>So far, however, the number of architects employing an integrated approach to environmental design is small. "You can count them on one hand," said Paul Bierman-Lytle, a New Canaan, Conn., architect and builder. His firm, the Masters Corporation, built a Victorian shingle-style home in the Massachusetts Berkshires that cost more than $3 million, and two homes in Malibu, Calif., that adhered to a list of principles for what Mr. Bierman-Lytle calls the 21st-century house. His house of the future would include features like:</p>
        <p>* Energy from photovoltaic panels made of silicon cells, which store the sun's energy in batteries and convert it to electric current.</p>
        <p>* Solar hot-water systems.</p>
        <p>* Standardized, rather than customized, lumber to minimize waste.</p>
        <p>* Wood whose harvesting does not contribute to the destruction of forests.</p>
        <p>* Equipment and appliances that make the least possible use of ozone-depleting chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>* Materials, equipment and furnishings with no hazardous chemicals.</p>
        <p>* Recycling of bath and toilet water for year-round hydroponic gardening.</p>
        <p>* Fish-farming in kitchen tanks.</p>
        <p>"Each time you add something from the list," Mr. Bierman-Lytle said, "you get further into the 21st century."</p>
        <p>Mr. McDonough has had many commissions in Europe, where green design has been around since the 1960's. For a day-care center in Frankfurt, he specified high-insulation argon-gas windows (which sandwich a layer of naturally occurring inert gas between panes of glass), solar heat, skylight shades that can be cranked open by the children and greenhouses on the roof.</p>
        <p>An office his firm designed for the Environmental Defense Fund on Park Avenue South in 1986 was one of the first projects in the United States to consider indoor air quality. "We avoided paints that have fungicides for shelf life," Mr. McDonough said. "We avoided carpet glues with formaldehyde, and tacked down the carpet. We looked at how to minimize waste during construction, and we looked for building materials packaged in recycled cardboard."</p>
        <p>For the interior of a Paul Stuart store on Madison Avenue, Mr. McDonough's firm used two old English oaks and planted 1,000 saplings to replace them. For a 120,000-square-foot Wal-Mart store being built in Lawrence, Kan., Mr. McDonough said, "We worked with forests that are managed for sustainable yield and species diversity." The store is skylighted, and its heating and cooling systems emit no chlorofluorocarbons, he said.</p>
        <p>A common perception is that environmentally sensitive design is more expensive than conventional design.</p>
        <p>"Builders don't like to experiment when they're building on speculation," said Bill Ellingsworth, senior vice president of public affairs at the National Association of Home Builders, based in Washington. "It's a little more expensive to build with environmentally sound materials and some things take longer to install."</p>
        <p>Toll Brothers, a Philadelphia developer, has a program that, instead of trucking construction waste to landfills, hires companies to turn waste wood into mulch and recycles plastics. But the company, which builds 1,200 homes a year on the East Coast, with an average price of $300,000, is not yet convinced environmental building methods are practical.</p>
        <p>"These 21st century technologies are not seen yet in our segment of the market," said Kira Hann, the company's marketing director. "They are still expensive. Once the kinks are worked out and prices become more reasonable, they can be integrated into our daily lives. We give the public what it wants. When we start to hear that it wants those things, then we'll jump right on."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bierman-Lytle said, "An environmental home for the 21st century would utilize more expensive technologies and products, but only initially." In the Northeast, for example, for an investment of $5,000 to $10,000, he continued, depending on the size of the house, you could put photovoltaic panels, which convert sunlight into electricity, on the roof.</p>
        <p>"The system would support all household electricity needs, except for baseboard heating," he said. "You'd need too many panels to produce that quantity of electricity."</p>
        <p>It would probably take 5 to 10 years to recoup the expense of making a house independent of fossil-fuel sources, Mr. Bierman-Lytle said. Other improvements cost no more. If you build with less toxic materials -- natural wood instead of chemical-laden plywood, carpet tacks instead of glue -- "you improve the quality of air in your house for almost no additional cost," he added.</p>
        <p>Getting architecture to benefit, and not harm, the earth, is a matter of finding our way back to ancient ideas, like optimal orientation toward the sun when initially siting a building. "Architects used to know where the sun was," Mr. McDonough said. "It's just since the advent of cheap fossil fuels they've forgotten."</p>
        <p>Nor is sustainability a novel idea. At New College in Oxford, England, Mr. McDonough recounted, 40-foot-long beams of 350-year-old English oak were suffering from dry rot.</p>
        <p>"It turned out," he went on, "that the original architects had ordered a forest planted and maintained." The stand of trees was still there, he said, adding, "They had foreseen the problem in the 1600's."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
