<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KENDALL-JACKSON WINERY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACKSON, JESS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEELE, JED</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D6113DF934A25755C0A964958260" item-length="1113" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IS wine made from a secret formula? Jess Jackson, a San Francisco lawyer who owns the Kendall-Jackson Winery in Lake County, Calif., says it is. Jed Steele, his former wine maker and one of the California wine industry's more colorful figures, says it isn't.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steele left Kendall-Jackson in 1990 after eight years to start his own winery and to work as a consultant. The parting was amicable, with Mr. Jackson agreeing to pay Mr. Steele severance of $400,000 plus $10,000 a month while he trained his successor.</p>
        <p>In May 1991, however, Mr. Jackson dismissed Mr. Steele as a consultant and refused to continue paying the settlement. He accused his former wine maker of revealing "trade secrets" to new clients and of luring away Kendall-Jackson grape suppliers. Mr. Steele sued to get $275,000 he said was still owed him; Mr. Jackson countersued to keep Mr. Steele from using information he gained while he was employed by Kendall-Jackson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IS wine made from a secret formula? Jess Jackson, a San Francisco lawyer who owns the Kendall-Jackson Winery in Lake County, Calif., says it is. Jed Steele, his former wine maker and one of the California wine industry's more colorful figures, says it isn't.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steele left Kendall-Jackson in 1990 after eight years to start his own winery and to work as a consultant. The parting was amicable, with Mr. Jackson agreeing to pay Mr. Steele severance of $400,000 plus $10,000 a month while he trained his successor.</p>
        <p>In May 1991, however, Mr. Jackson dismissed Mr. Steele as a consultant and refused to continue paying the settlement. He accused his former wine maker of revealing "trade secrets" to new clients and of luring away Kendall-Jackson grape suppliers. Mr. Steele sued to get $275,000 he said was still owed him; Mr. Jackson countersued to keep Mr. Steele from using information he gained while he was employed by Kendall-Jackson.</p>
        <p>A trial in Lake County Superior Court, which heard Mr. Steele's suit and the countersuit by Kendall-Jackson, was completed last month. The winery claimed that Mr. Steele disclosed trade secrets, interfered with its business relationships and was negligent in his wine-making duties while he was preparing to quit. Judge John Golden will render a decision in the fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Steele's partisans, who include many prominent wine makers and winery owners, say a ruling for Kendall-Jackson could alter the way wine is made in California. They say much of the considerable success California wines have had in recent years can be attributed to the free flow of ideas and technical information among the state's wine growers.</p>
        <p>"If Kendall-Jackson prevails," Robert Mondavi told Wine Industry Insider, a trade newsletter, "and I don't think it will, a wine maker won't know what to do. How would he practice his occupation?"</p>
        <p>Many of California's best-known wine makers graduated from the same schools of enology, have worked together in wineries and have followed one another in wine-making jobs as the industry has expanded. They call each other when technical problems arise. They lend each other equipment and even store one another's wine when space is short.</p>
        <p>"I would be amazed beyond belief if any winery could have any trade secrets whatsoever," Dr. Richard Peterson was quoted as saying in the same article. He has been the wine maker at Beaulieu Vineyards, Atlas Peak and Monterey Vineyards.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Chanin, a lawyer for Kendall-Jackson, insisted that there are indeed trade secrets in the wine business. "The wine world is changing," he told Wine Industry Insider. "Maybe some time ago there was a small group of wine makers who were sharing with each other all they knew," but that is no longer the case, he said.  In a case involving Mrs. Field's Cookies some years ago, Mr. Chanin argued successfully that the bakery's chocolate chip recipe was in fact a trade secret and could be withheld from competitors.</p>
        <p>And what is the "secret" that Jed Steele is said to have divulged? It is a technique for making a slightly sweet chardonnay. The white wines made from the chardonnay grape traditionally are made to be dry. Wine makers have discovered that although Americans like to think of the wines they drink as dry, they actually prefer them to be slightly sweet.</p>
        <p>These "off-dry" wines are made by stopping fermentation before all the natural grape sugar has been converted into alcohol and carbon dioxide. By one industry estimate, about 20 percent of California chardonnays, mostly at the lower end of the price scale, contain some residual sugar.</p>
        <p>"These processes are known to every wine maker in California," said Mr. Steele's lawyer, Thomas Brigham. "There never was a formula for making Kendall-Jackson wines."</p>
        <p>Mr. Chanin, however, said that there definitely was a formula and that it was filed with the court as part of the petition seeking an injunction against Mr. Steele. Citing the competitive nature of the business, Judge Golden sealed the petition.</p>
        <p>"We fully endorse and have always participated in the California wine industry's open and enthusiastic exchange of wine-making information," said Margaret Harding, a spokeswoman for Kendall-Jackson. "Kendall-Jackson has, however, developed specific technical wine-making procedures that are unique to our winery and that make their indelible Kendall-Jackson mark on our wines. These procedures are proprietary."</p>
        <p>Mr. Steele said he first made the wine in question, Kendall-Jackson's Vintner's Reserve Chardonnay, by accident. His first job at the winery, he said, was to "rescue" a large quantity of 1982 wines that had not fermented properly. By blending in other wines, he said, he was able to make a wine that was not only drinkable but that won several awards.</p>
        <p>That chardonnay, along with the rest of the Kendall-Jackson line, moved the winery from 35,000 cases a year when Mr. Steele arrived in 1983 to an estimated 700,000 cases last year.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Lake County winery and vineyards, Kendall-Jackson owns the former Zellerbach winery and vineyards in Sonoma, the former Edmeades Vineyards in Mendocino County and the former Cambria Winery in the central coast region of California. Kendall-Jackson is planning a second winery in Somona County with a capacity of about 360,000 cases.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Steele, he now owns and operates Steele Wines in Kelseyville, Calif., which is only a couple of vines down the road from Kendall-Jackson. It's a wine company with no winery and no vines. Mr. Steele buys his grapes from other wineries and makes his wine at Wildhurst Vineyards, a small winery nearby. He plans to release about 1,000 cases of Steele Wines chardonnay and 400 cases of zinfandel in the fall.  TASTINGS De Loach Vineyards Zinfandel 1990, Russian River; about $11.</p>
        <p>De Loach, in Sonoma County, California, is one of a growing number of wineries that have dedicated themselves to producing better and better zinfandels. This new release is a good example of the trend toward combining the natural intensity of the grape with a degree of refinement that was never expected in the rustic zinfandels of an earlier generation. The intensity comes from low-yielding old vines, the refinement from the wine maker's skills. This estate-bottled zinfandel may be young, but its pedigree is long; the grapes come from three vineyards whose vines range roughly from 60 to 100 years old. The wine is rich and deeply colored. It is perfect for robust dishes, which means it might be worth saving for the heartier meals that go with cooler weather. In fact, another year or two in the bottle might smooth its edges nicely.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
