<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Northeast's Strange Weather: Don't Blame It All on the Volcano</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT PINATUBO (PHILIPPINES)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D91139F937A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="2144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Northeast's Strange Weather: Don't Blame It All on the Volcano</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the New York Botanical Garden, the abnormally cool summer of 1992 has thrown the schedules of flowering plants thoroughly out of kilter. Throughout the Northeast, beaches and mountain campgrounds have been discouragingly cold. And around the Great Lakes and in northern New England, temperatures have lately dipped into the 30's.</p>
        <p>"I don't think I've ever seen that in July," Jim Wagner, a veteran analyst at the National Weather Service's Climate Analysis Center at Camp Springs, Md., said of the low readings in the North. "It's almost reminiscent of the year without a summer in 1816."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the New York Botanical Garden, the abnormally cool summer of 1992 has thrown the schedules of flowering plants thoroughly out of kilter. Throughout the Northeast, beaches and mountain campgrounds have been discouragingly cold. And around the Great Lakes and in northern New England, temperatures have lately dipped into the 30's.</p>
        <p>"I don't think I've ever seen that in July," Jim Wagner, a veteran analyst at the National Weather Service's Climate Analysis Center at Camp Springs, Md., said of the low readings in the North. "It's almost reminiscent of the year without a summer in 1816."</p>
        <p>That summer, one year after the Mount Tambora volcano in Indonesia erupted and blanketed the earth with sulfurous airborne particles that reflected sunlight and cooled the globe, upstate New York and New England suffered killing frosts every month of the season, and it snowed throughout New England in June. This year, another global volcanic haze, flung into the stratosphere by the eruption of Mount Pinatubo in the Philippines in June 1991, has turned the sky in some places from blue to milky white as it scatters the sun's rays.</p>
        <p>Preliminary data show that the Mount Pinatubo haze has caused a drop in the average surface temperature of the earth of as much as 1 degree Fahrenheit and a drop in the Northern Hemisphere of up to 1.5 degrees. So is the haze from Mount Pinatubo, as intuition might suggest, responsible for the cool summer of 1992 in the Northeastern United States? Tempting as that explanation may be, climate experts tend to discount it as a direct or primary cause.</p>
        <p>Whatever its cause, the recent cooling mostly cancels out, temporarily, the warming of the planet that scientists have observed in the last century. It also means that if global warming is taking place as a result of human-induced emissions of carbon dioxide, as many scientists believe, it will be offset for two or three more years.  After that, some scientists say, the planet's temperature will rebound to where it would have been had Mount Pinatubo not erupted.</p>
        <p>One of the reasons scientists doubt that the eruption is the primary cause of the cooling is that it has not been a cool summer everywhere. "The poor folks in the Northwestern U.S. have had a tremendously warm and dry summer," said Paul G. Knight, a meteorologist at the Pennsylvania State University's Weather Communications Group. For another, the direct effect of a 1.5-degree hemispheric cooling is too small to make any big difference to local weather.</p>
        <p>"You can't claim that the weather in any particular location is because of the volcano," said Dr. Alan Robock, a University of Maryland climatologist who studies volcanoes' effects on climate. Local and regional weather is determined by natural, shifting patterns of air circulation, like jet streams and areas of high and low air pressure. The influence of these phenomena at any one spot, at any one time, overwhelms any general global trend. The arrival of a cold front, for instance, or a shift in winds that pushes cool air and clouds from the ocean onto the land, causes temperature changes of many degrees, not just 1 or 2.</p>
        <p>It is these familiar elements, say Mr. Wagner and Mr. Knight, that have brought cool weather to the Northeast this summer.</p>
        <p>That said, some experts suspect that the Pinatubo haze, apart from its very modest overall cooling effect, could play some role in altering patterns of air circulation, indirectly affecting local weather. It might, for instance, strengthen and shift the position of the jet streams, the great rivers of air that girdle the globe in the Northern and Southern Hemispheres, with local and regional consequences. Scientists are just beginning to investigate the question of whether volcanoes can lead to the reorganization of atmospheric circulation into patterns that favor cool weather. But for now, Mr. Wagner said, it is a question that no one can answer for sure: "It will take very sophisticated research over a long period of time." March Switch for Northeast</p>
        <p>Still the experts can say a great deal about what has happened to the weather in North America this year.</p>
        <p>After a warm winter, the Northeast turned abruptly and unseasonably cool in March, and the weather has stayed that way ever since. Last month was the Northeast's second-coolest July in the 98 years of records at the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C., said William Brown, an analyst there. After a relatively normal spring, the upper Great Lakes states turned chilly as well.  The temperatures there last month were the coolest on record there for July, undercutting the previous record, set in 1915, by 1.5 degrees.</p>
        <p>In the Pacific Northwest, on the other hand, 1992 was among the warmest years on record until July, when the temperature dropped below normal. The Southeast, where July was the 13th-warmest on record, replaced the Northwest as the nation's hot region.</p>
        <p>The cooling trend has lasted longer in the Northeast than in any other region. In New York City, according to the Weather Bureau, each month from March through June was 1 to 2 degrees below normal. July was 2.5 degrees below normal, but that was not a record.</p>
        <p>Last winter, from December through February, most of the country was warmer than normal even though the global cooling caused by Mount Pinatubo had apparently already begun. In the North, an unusually strong jet stream carried warm Pacific air all the way across the country. While it cannot yet be proved, the Pinatubo effect may have had a paradoxical hand in the warm winter, Dr. Robock said.</p>
        <p>Airborne droplets from volcanoes, he explained, absorb solar energy, thereby heating the stratosphere.  This global heating increases the temperature difference between the stratosphere above the tropics and that above the North Pole, where, in winter, it is perpetually midnight and the stratosphere is cooler.</p>
        <p>The atmosphere has a natural tendency to eliminate any such imbalance between areas of cold and warm air. This creates a constant rush of air -- the planet's winds, in this case the jet stream. The greater the temperature difference, the stronger the winds. The North American jet stream was made strong enough last winter, Dr. Robock suggested, to push warm Pacific air all the way across the continent. Effects of El Nino</p>
        <p>At the same time, a second jet stream developed over the southern part of the country. That was one of a chain of global atmospheric events set off last year by El Nino, a huge pool of unusually warm sea water that periodically appears in the eastern part of the tropical Pacific Ocean.  The southerly jet stream contributed to the extremely wet winter that plagued Texas, New Mexico and northern and central Mexico. This year's warmth and drought in the Pacific Northwest is another manifestation of a global weather pattern associated with El Nino.</p>
        <p>This winter weather pattern ended abruptly on March 12. "The atmosphere snapped" that day, said Mr. Knight of Penn State. "For a reason unbeknownst to me, the pattern dramatically shifted." The southern jet stream weakened greatly and the northern jet stream veered northward over Alaska, then plunged down through the Great Lakes to the Northeast, bearing unusually cold air with it.</p>
        <p>That jet stream has borne a series of cool high-pressure systems from west to east, he said. When they reach the East Coast, their clockwise flow of air brings more cool, moist air ashore from the Atlantic, resulting in clouds and further coolness in the Northeast. Normally, there would be an interval of a few days between such systems, during which heat and humidity build up and the temperature rises. But this year, Mr. Knight said, the jet stream has been especially strong and is moving the systems through every other day or so.  Heat has had no chance to build up.</p>
        <p>Another factor in preventing a summertime heat buildup, said Mr. Wagner of the Climate Analysis Center, is a residual effect of El Nino. At times, the El Nino pattern that soaked Texas and the southern Plains earlier in the year also extended northward into the Mississippi Valley and parts of the upper Midwest. The ground remains wet there, and "this large area of wet ground is strongly opposed to the development of any heat wave," Mr. Wagner said.</p>
        <p>At the same time, he said, residual effects of the characteristic El Nino pattern have also kept it hotter than normal in the Pacific Northwest this summer.</p>
        <p>As for El Nino itself, the Pacific region that spawns the warm pool of water has cooled rapidly in recent weeks. "For all intents and purposes, the El Nino has pretty well ended," said Dr. Vernon Kousky of the Climate Analysis Center. While it lasted, it caused drier than normal conditions in the Philippines, Indonesia, northern Australia and northeastern Brazil, brought record drought to southeastern Africa, and dropped heavier than normal rains on southern Brazil, Uruguay and central Argentina. It also led to a weak start for the life-giving Indian monsoon, but El Nino's end could reverse that situation, Dr. Kousky said. Plants Lose Track of Time</p>
        <p>Back in the Northeastern United States, the abnormally cool summer has substantially disrupted vegetative rhythms, while allowing trees and lawns weakened by last year's heat and drought to recover and even luxuriate in the relative chill of 1992.</p>
        <p>"We're about two weeks late on all of our flowering," said Wayne Cahilly, the manager of the New York Botanical Garden arboretum and grounds in the Bronx. For instance, he said, the shrub roses bloomed about two weeks late this year, causing them to overlap with hybrid tea roses, which bloomed on time because they are less sensitive to cold.</p>
        <p>Annuals have been "sitting still" in the cool weather, he said, and meadow plants are going to grow to perhaps half their normal height of 7 to 8 feet. But the cool weather has given many trees the chance to make up the energy deficit they incurred in last year's drought and hot weather. The cool-season grasses typical of the Northeast have also flourished. "You drive around suburbia and these lawns look good," Mr. Cahilly said.</p>
        <p>Whatever the effect of Mount Pinatubo's haze on the fortunes of the flora, its global effect on temperature is becoming clearer. At its peak, according to measurements made by ground-based instruments at National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration observatories in Alaska, Hawaii, American Samoa and Antarctica, the haze reduced direct solar radiation reaching the earth by as much as 30 percent. The reduction is now about 10 to 15 percent, said Ellsworth Dutton, a meteorologist at N.O.A.A.'s Climate Monitoring and Diagnostics Laboratory in Boulder, Colo. Data Support Model So Far</p>
        <p>By analyzing satellite measurements of temperatures in the lower atmosphere, which correlate closely with surface temperatures, Mr. Dutton found that the average global temperature decreased by 1 degree from May 1991 to May 1992. It is "still falling a bit," he said, but should return to normal in two to three years.</p>
        <p>The temperature drop so far is about 1.5 degrees in the Northern Hemisphere and about four-tenths of a degree in the Southern Hemisphere.  A provisional analysis by Dr. Helene Wilson of the Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York indicates that the average global temperature, both at the surface and in the lower atmosphere, was about seven-tenths of a degree lower in the year following the Pinatubo eruption than in the year preceding it. But "we still need more months of observations before we can be more confident that the cooling trend is persisting," she said.</p>
        <p>The effect of the observed cooling trend on the weather of any particular region is not as important as its role in "helping us interpret greenhouse warming," Dr. Robock said.  Last year, Dr. James E. Hansen of the Goddard Institute predicted on the basis of a computerized simulation of the atmosphere that the Pinatubo haze would result in a 1-degree drop in the average global temperature.</p>
        <p>The computer model he used is also one of several that predict global warming in the range of 3 to 8 degrees if atmospheric concentrations of heat-trapping carbon dioxide, a product of the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil, double as expected in the next century. It predicted that after a 1-degree drop in temperature because of the Pinatubo effect, a global warming trend that began in the late 1970's would resume in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen has cast the prediction as a test of the model's accuracy, which has been questioned by opponents of strong action to counter the predicted global warming. Based on the observations so far, Dr. Robock said, Dr. Hansen's prediction about the Pinatubo effect "looks very close to what actually happened." He added, "It gives us more confidence" in the model.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
