<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Talk About a Slogan for the Back-to-Basics 90's: Electrify!</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="512630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWN MOWERS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLS, MARK P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1331F93BA35750C0A964958260" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Talk About a Slogan for the Back-to-Basics 90's: Electrify!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>All over the United States, utilities are diving into the technology of conservation, helping consumers install new light bulbs, electric motors and heating and cooling systems designed to use less electricity. The current thinking is that the nation should do the same work with less power, to allow generating stations that burn coal to be closed. These plants emit the ingredients of acid rain and also a high level of carbon dioxide, the single largest cause of the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>But according to a contrarian school, this approach is backward. If pollution or the greenhouse effect is really the problem, according to the counter-theory, there is a technical fix at hand. It is to use as much electricity as possible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>All over the United States, utilities are diving into the technology of conservation, helping consumers install new light bulbs, electric motors and heating and cooling systems designed to use less electricity. The current thinking is that the nation should do the same work with less power, to allow generating stations that burn coal to be closed. These plants emit the ingredients of acid rain and also a high level of carbon dioxide, the single largest cause of the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>But according to a contrarian school, this approach is backward. If pollution or the greenhouse effect is really the problem, according to the counter-theory, there is a technical fix at hand. It is to use as much electricity as possible.</p>
        <p>How can burning more coal, oil and gas in power plants help the environment? According to Mark P. Mills, a long-time energy consultant, some technologies can perform work better with electricity than with other fuels. The idea has been around for a few years, but Mr. Mills has refined it and given it a name: ecowatts.</p>
        <p>Ecowatts, he said, means using electricity instead of another fuel and gaining benefits for the global environment, often as a side effect of gains in convenience or economy or perhaps in alleviating local pollution. He points to lawn mowers.</p>
        <p>In southern California, air pollution officials have instituted strict rules on lawn mower emissions. According to Mr. Mills, to meet the rules mowers will come to resemble cars, with electronic fuel injection and catalytic converters. That, he said, means the debut of the $650 lawn mower, and prices that high will just turn the state into a magnet for all the nation's used mowers, defeating the regulation. The answer, he said, is electric mowers, a technology that is hardly new but, he said, is underappreciated.</p>
        <p>By Mr. Mills's calculation, the standard gasoline mower, at three horsepower, burns a quart in two hours. But the same job could be done with 2.2 kilowatt-hours of electricity. (A typical home uses about 20 kilowatt-hours a day.)</p>
        <p>Burning the gasoline releases 36,800 B.T.U.'s of heat, by Mr. Mills's calculation, taking into account the energy that was used to refine the gasoline. The electricity created 24,400 B.T.U.'s, for an increase in efficiency of about one-third.</p>
        <p>The savings in carbon dioxide emissions depends on the fuel used to make the electricity. If the fuel that was saved by retiring the mower -- in this case gasoline -- was used to make the electricity, then some of the oil used to make that gasoline would be left over, and total savings in carbon dioxide would be 2.1 pounds. If the kilowatts were the national average, made from nuclear power, natural gas, hydroelectricity, coal and oil, the savings would be 2.5 pounds, he said.</p>
        <p>The impetus for the homeowner to switch to an electric mower would not, of course, be carbon dioxide, but rules like those in California that aim to limit conventional pollutants, like carbon monoxide, hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxide. The power plant would also pollute, of course, but less.</p>
        <p>Electrification has planet-wide potential. Chauncey Starr, an energy expert and philosopher, is fond of telling audiences that cooking dinner over an open fire, as is often done in the third world, is only 2 percent efficient. If the same wood were burned in a boiler to make electricity, it would cook 10 or 15 dinners. Dr. Starr, who founded the Electric Power Research Institute, a nonprofit utility consortium in Palo Alto, Calif., uses the example to describe a strategy against deforestation, but it is obviously important as a greenhouse control strategy too.</p>
        <p>All of this is music to the electric-utility industry, which, with its prominent smokestacks, has become the whipping boy for greenhouse activists. In addition, while fuel use for transportation, heating, industry and other purposes has been roughly unchanged since 1973, the year of the first oil embargo, fuel use for electric utilities has been galloping ahead. Of all the fuel used in this country, about 36 percent is converted to electricity before it is used, and by the end of the decade this figure will approach 40 percent. Transportation is a distant second, at 27 percent.</p>
        <p>Outside experts generally agree Mr. Mills's examples are correct, although they often doubt his bottom line. But trivial as the lawn mower example may sound, the United States has about 84 million mowers.</p>
        <p>And many other electric technologies have great potential. Mr. Mills points out that the economy now produces far fewer pounds of carbon dioxide per dollar of gross national product. He credits electrification. For example, he cites gains from the electrification of steel, paint drying, glass production and a dozen other technologies, including document shipping, which these days often means a fax machine instead of Federal Express.</p>
        <p>Beyond convenience, he says, there could be another major incentive for switching to electric technologies: money. The lawn mower is a good example; nobody likes dragging a cord around and few people buy electric mowers. But over a seven-year lifetime, Mr. Mills says, using an electric lawn mower will cut carbon monoxide, hydrocarbons and other pollutants by an amount that has a dollar value. If the user could capture that value, said Mr. Mills, electric mowers would become far more tempting.</p>
        <p>Some technologies not in the marketplace yet and unlikely to make their entry primarily to save carbon dioxide would still achieve that goal, he said. These include the following:</p>
        <p>* Stabilizing toxic wastes. Instead of digging up contaminated soil and hauling it to a lined dump with a water collection system, put electrodes into the soil and zap it with so much power that the soil turns to glass, immobilizing the chemicals. That would cut energy use 20 percent.</p>
        <p>* "Flying" between cities by train. Compared with an airplane, a magnetic-levitation train moving at more than 300 miles per hour would use 76 percent less energy per passenger mile, Mr. Mills calculates.</p>
        <p>* Driving electric cars. A nine-mile trip would save 2.4 to 3.3 pounds of carbon dioxide, depending, once again, on whether the power plant used the oil that was saved from the car or the national average fuel mix.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Mills, electrification thus far is the major factor in improving the ratio of G.N.P to carbon dioxide, from 4 pounds per dollar in 1973 to about 2.3 pounds per dollar today. He recognizes two "structural changes" in the economy that helped the trend along: the construction since 1973 of a nuclear industry that provides about 20 percent of the nation's electricity without carbon dioxide production and the increase in auto fuel efficiency, with cars going 50 percent further on a gallon, on average. But those together account for only about 22 percent of the improvement, he said.</p>
        <p>Charles Komanoff, a utility expert and consultant in New York, described the ecowatts premise as "credible." But other factors muddy the waters, he said.</p>
        <p>One reason the American economy is 30 percent more energy efficient now than it was two decades ago is that lights and refrigerators do the same work with less power, Mr. Komanoff said. This is not electrical technologies substituting for technologies that use natural gas or coal; it is new electric refrigerators substituting for old electric refrigerators.</p>
        <p>And there are always innovations using other fuels. The Gas Research Institute, for example, will soon test a new glass melter, powered by natural gas, that is expected to be 20 percent more efficient than conventional gas furnaces and 40 percent cheaper than a conventional electric furnace.</p>
        <p>There are other factors. Steel making has largely moved abroad, so the carbon dioxide accrues to some other nation. And a bigger part of the mix in the American economy are goods and services that require less energy to make and did not exist a few years ago, like computer software.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
