<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romania Town's Prosperity Means Pollution</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="550673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEAD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR AND SULFUR COMPOUNDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BAIA MARE (ROMANIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROMANIA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D9113FF935A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romania Town's Prosperity Means Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>BAIA MARE, Romania</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The scruffy trees surrounding this old mining town in northwestern Romania bear the scars of Baia Mare's economic success amid Romania's poverty.</p>
        <p>The city is grappling with the same dilemma of prosperity versus environmental concerns faced by much of Eastern Europe, but it also is a victim of the legal vacuum that makes environmental damage virtually unstoppable in Romania today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The scruffy trees surrounding this old mining town in northwestern Romania bear the scars of Baia Mare's economic success amid Romania's poverty.</p>
        <p>The city is grappling with the same dilemma of prosperity versus environmental concerns faced by much of Eastern Europe, but it also is a victim of the legal vacuum that makes environmental damage virtually unstoppable in Romania today.</p>
        <p>A draft environmental law has languished in a parliamentary committee for two years. It will not be passed before the election of a new parliament, scheduled for Sept. 27.</p>
        <p>There is a 1973 environmental law on the books, but like many other old laws in Eastern Europe, it carries little weight and is not enforced.</p>
        <p>In the thick forests around Baia Mare, 240 miles northwest of Bucharest, the toxic emissions of this metallurgical center have cut plant growth in half. About one-third of the roughly 30,000 acres of forest have been devastated. Some trees have lost up to two-thirds of their foliage. Even in the least affected areas, acid rain has covered the leaves with brown spots.</p>
        <p>The human cost is appalling. For Baia Mare's 150,000 residents, life expectancy is 50, nearly 20 years below the Romanian average. Children in a health survey conducted by Unesco show high deposits of lead in their bones and teeth. Chronic bronchial diseases are endemic.</p>
        <p>The two main culprits, the state-owned Romplumb and Phoenix plants, are still operating, spewing sulfur dioxide and lead into the air at levels 100 to 200 percent over the Romanian norms.</p>
        <p>"We put out protests," Petre Marcuta, state secretary of the Ministry of Environment in Bucharest, said. "But given that we don't have legal rights and because of the grave economic situation generally, we'll have to wait a little longer for the necessary means to make a difference."</p>
        <p>Baia Mare is the second most polluted city in Romania, after Copsa Mica, a town of 10,000 about 125 miles south. Pollution here is less visible than in Copsa Mica, where even new shoots of grass are covered with a greasy black film.</p>
        <p>Scientists have known for years that the state-owned Phoenix and Romplumb plants were responsible for most of the pollution here. But they are also Baia Mare's main employers, providing paychecks to more than 10,000 at a time when up to 10 percent of Romanian workers are unemployed and countless others have been furloughed or put to work part time.</p>
        <p>"They are paid well for doing little work, so who wants to give up his job?" Mircea Marian, the son of a Romplumb engineer, said. His father earns about $140 a month, two and a half times the average Romanian wage.</p>
        <p>So far, the Government has opted to keep the plants open and make adjustments around the margins. Some machinery has been repaired to operate more efficiently. A 900-foot smokestack planned in the Communist era, before the 1989 revolution, is to carry Phoenix's emissions higher into the atmosphere. But that will only turn a local problem into a regional one.</p>
        <p>The city government has brought the two plants to court, seeking damages of $3,000 for each day of operation. But few people take the move seriously.</p>
        <p>"A trial cannot solve this," Dorel Chereches, director of Romsilva, said.  "The only solution is to get state subsidies, international help and investments here."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
