<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Plants Respond to Changes in Weather</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="505231"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAUST, JOAN LEE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D91530F931A35751C0A964958260" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Plants Respond to Changes in Weather</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAUST, JOAN LEE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS has been a fluky winter. In many ways it has seemed more like spring, because so many of the days have been mild. And where is that usual wintertime blizzard? Snow shovels and snow blowers have not had any workouts.</p>
        <p>The plants have reacted, too, if that is the word for it. Some have already bloomed. Many shrubs popped out with a few blooms last fall, particularly forsythias and lilacs. Some of the earliest bulbs have even pushed their leaves high above ground just as if it were spring. In some gardens the first of the witchhazels are in flower, and in others the snowdrops are out in full glory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS has been a fluky winter. In many ways it has seemed more like spring, because so many of the days have been mild. And where is that usual wintertime blizzard? Snow shovels and snow blowers have not had any workouts.</p>
        <p>The plants have reacted, too, if that is the word for it. Some have already bloomed. Many shrubs popped out with a few blooms last fall, particularly forsythias and lilacs. Some of the earliest bulbs have even pushed their leaves high above ground just as if it were spring. In some gardens the first of the witchhazels are in flower, and in others the snowdrops are out in full glory.</p>
        <p>Some gardeners have wondered if this sort of mild winter weather is what global warming is all about. Or is the Northeast caught in a peculiar pattern? Even the weather scientists are stumped for some sort of explanation.</p>
        <p>All of this speculation was quickly put to a halt, however, by the recent cold snap. Snap is just what it was. Temperatures dropped 30 to 40 degrees in a matter of a few hours. And without snow cover, nature's blanket, the plants were in a sort of shock, unprotected from these happenings.</p>
        <p>The plants that endure the biggest challenge are the shrubs and trees, those elegant woody-stemmed monarchs that have their limbs and twigs exposed. These plants usually appear to tough it out through these kinds of challenges, because their buds are tightly wrapped. They are kept securely dormant through any vagaries the weather has to offer. As long as these large woody plants had a suitable supply of moisture, ample rainfall during the fall season, they should come through unscathed.</p>
        <p>One thing is certain, though, any flower buds that opened last fall have finished their display and will not have had time to re-form flowers for this spring. What buds have already opened to flower in fall cannot bloom again this spring. If some of the shrubs appear motley in flower as soon as genuine mild weather comes, this would explain why.</p>
        <p>The plants that seem to be the hardest hit with this kind of cold snap are those that retain their leaves year-round, particularly the broadleaved evergreens. Rhododendrons, hollies, leucothoes, mountain laurels and pieris are among the popular landscape plants. All are subject to winter temperature stress and some more than others. Spring will tell. There is nothing gardeners can do now but keep their fingers crossed.</p>
        <p>Those who have rhododendrons on their property rarely need to consult a thermometer to know how cold it is. The rhododendrons have a weather gauge of their own. The colder it is outside, the tighter the leaves curl and hang down. There was a time when the temperature hovered near 10 degrees, and the rhododendron leaves, curled tightly inward, hung like long green pencils. When the temperatures began to ameliorate, toward 20 degrees, the leaves began to open a bit and look more like rhododendrons. But it was not until the thermometer was well above the freezing mark that the rhododendron leaves assumed their usual flat-out appearance and once again became the dramatic statement that these magnificent plants usually are.</p>
        <p>This phenomenon of nature is one of the best barometers of severe winter weather. And it is also one of the endowments of nature for a plant's winter survival. Few natural examples are as obvious as this one.</p>
        <p>No one can tell at this point just what spring will provide in the way of survival of some of these ornamental plants. The plants that are most subject to damage or outright winter kill are those plants that are marginal, the ones that may or may not survive the severest cold conditions. This is where the winter hardiness maps come into play.</p>
        <p>Those who chance it and try to grow plants distant from their gardens' hardiness zones, the so-called marginal plants, may be disappointed come spring and lose some plants. But gambling is part of what gardening is all about, and if these so-called tender plants are placed in safe havens, and cared for reasonably well, then sometimes the plant gamblers win.</p>
        <p>As for the perennials, these plants are usually quite safe underground when this sort of weather stress occurs. The roots are secure, well below the forzen surface of the soil, and the new shoots for this year will not appear above ground until the growing season begins.</p>
        <p>Some gardeners leave the tops of the perennials in place over the winter, to be able to find the plants or to provide upright stems to catch snow and leaves. If these weathered stems have not been cut back to ground level, this tidy-up chore will be one of the first to do.</p>
        <p>Sometimes bulb foliage pushes up too early, especially when there is an early mild spell in the winter months. If a cold snap follows again, or if there is a late winter snowfall, this foliage stays in place undamaged, and the flower buds, which are tucked well below in the bulbs, are safe.  GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
