<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economists Strive to Find Environment's Bottom Line</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="555146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED7173CF93BA3575AC0A964958260" item-length="1569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economists Strive to Find Environment's Bottom Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Does environmental protection hurt the economy or help it?</p>
        <p>The question is under hot dispute in the Presidential campaign. The Democratic Vice-Presidential nominee, Senator Al Gore, argues that environmental protection boosts the economy and creates jobs; Vice President Dan Quayle, whose White House Council on Competitiveness has sought to reduce environmental regulations, says the Democrats' environmental policies would cost jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Does environmental protection hurt the economy or help it?</p>
        <p>The question is under hot dispute in the Presidential campaign. The Democratic Vice-Presidential nominee, Senator Al Gore, argues that environmental protection boosts the economy and creates jobs; Vice President Dan Quayle, whose White House Council on Competitiveness has sought to reduce environmental regulations, says the Democrats' environmental policies would cost jobs.</p>
        <p>But the answer to the economy-vs.-ecology question, says an emerging group of environmental economists, is far more elusive.</p>
        <p>An Environmental Protection Agency analysis, for example, puts the cost of controlling and cleaning up pollution under Federal regulations at more than $100 billion a year, or about 2 percent of the nation's total annual output of goods and services. But like a number of other analyses, the study does not take into account the economic benefits of cleaner air and water. An analysis of benefits is under way, but not yet complete.</p>
        <p>Nor does the study include protection measures that do not involve pollution control, like conserving the ecosystems that underlie all economic activity, such as water, soil, forests, fisheries, wetlands, wild plant species and the complex biological web that supports life itself. Gauging the costs and benefits of such measures is hard but essential.</p>
        <p>Environmental economists argue that the economy is merely a subsystem of the planet's ecology, on which it depends for materials, energy and general sustenance.  "To me it's just as plain as the nose on your face," says Herman Daly, an economist at the World Bank and a proponent of the view that economies can flourish at steady state, without growth. Traditional economists, he and others contend, ignore this relationship, and with it the economic cost of depleting natural resources, degrading soils and otherwise insulting nature.</p>
        <p>Until these "external" costs are reflected both in company balance sheets and calculations of national wealth, say Mr. Daly and his allies, the benefits of environmental protection will be seriously underestimated and the basic health of the economy will be overestimated.</p>
        <p>This line of thought is starting to make some headway, as both the United Nations and the United States Department of Commerce move to include the costs of natural resource depletion as an adjunct to conventional accountings of national wealth. Also, regulatory commissions in New York and other states are starting to require electric utilities to factor in the cost of emitting heat-trapping carbon dioxide when deciding how to generate energy.</p>
        <p>Including such external costs favors Mr. Gore's side of the argument. But economic studies in general are not so clear cut. A number of economists say the value of environmental protection measures can be assessed only on a case-by-case basis. Benefits That Exceed Costs</p>
        <p>"I don't think you can make a broad, sweeping conclusion" about the economic value of environmental protection, said Dr. William Nordhaus of Yale University. "There are some net pluses and some net minuses."</p>
        <p>Among the "good buys" are the air pollution controls enacted in the first Clean Air Act of 1970, according to a cost-benefit analysis by Dr. Paul R. Portney, an economist at Resources for the Future, a Washington research institute. The act placed the first limits on air pollution from smokestacks and motor vehicles. Dr. Portney found the benefits of the Clean Air Act have exceeded the costs.</p>
        <p>His preliminary estimate suggests that the same is not true of the 1990 amendments to the Clean Air Act, designed to curb acid rain and air pollution in urban areas. Costs will be $29 billion to $36 billion a year by the year 2005, but benefits will probably range from $6 billion to $25 billion, he found. Since the analysis is preliminary, Dr. Portney does not rule out a different final result.</p>
        <p>Another good buy, in Dr. Portney's view, is the phasing out of chlorofluorocarbons that destroy the earth's protective ozone layer, which he calls "a small price to pay for insurance against what could be a pretty serious problem." Bad buys, in his book, include some toxic waste sites that pose little risk but will require tens of millions of dollars apiece to clean up.</p>
        <p>The issue of economy vs. ecology is also complicated by the fact that environmental regulation distributes both costs and benefits unevenly. Disproportionate Burden</p>
        <p>On costs, for instance, Dr. Dale W. Jorgenson of Harvard University and Dr. Peter J. Wilcoxen of the University of Texas estimate that all Federal environmental regulations adopted before 1990 will reduce the national economic output by 2.5 percent by the year 2000. But the economy does not suffer uniformly, they found; the burden is being borne disproportionately by the chemical, coal mining, motor vehicle, refining, primary metals and paper industries.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jorgenson and Dr. Wilcoxen calculate, for instance, that the long-run output of the automobile industry has been cut by about 15 percent as a consequence of controls on motor vehicle pollution.</p>
        <p>"The flip side of that is that some industries are going to benefit," Dr. Jorgenson said. An example is companies that produce pollution-control equipment and services, a market estimated at more than $100 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle says thousands of auto workers could be thrown out of work if automobile fuel-efficiency standards are raised, as Gov. Bill Clinton favors, to 40 miles per gallon, from 27.5 miles, to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide. Dr. Jorgenson agrees that achieving the standard would impose substantial costs and thereby cause industry employment to shrink.  But this does not take into account whatever environmental and economic benefits might result.</p>
        <p>Another difficulty in drawing up an economy-vs.-ecology bottom line is that there may be different answers for the short term and the long term, said Dr. H. Ronald Pulliam, an ecologist at the University of Georgia. "In the short term, there are certainly job losses" in some cases of environmental protection. "But in the long run, decades, there is probably very little conflict between maximizing economic goals and ecological goals."</p>
        <p>For instance, he said, some jobs would be lost if logging was prohibited in the old-growth forest habitat of the spotted owl in the Pacific Northwest. But if the old-growth forest is clear-cut "those jobs are going to be lost anyway in a decade or two," he said, while limiting logging so that biological diversity is preserved over the long haul "is going to provide for the needs of both the local economy and biodiversity." Looking for Short-Term Success</p>
        <p>In a study of the costs of global warming, Dr. William R. Cline of the Institute for International Economics finds that costs would roughly match benefits for the first 20 to 30 years but would then far outstrip them after the easy ways of abating carbon dioxide emissions had all been exploited. But in time, Dr. Cline found, the benefits would begin to outweigh the costs -- in the second half of the next century if the predicted warming were severe, a century later if it fell in the middle range of the predicted warming.</p>
        <p>Politicians, of course, do not generally look too far beyond the next election, a predilection that may be shared by their constituents. In a recent study by Resources for the Future and the University of Maryland, researchers asked people in 1,000 households which of two pollution-control programs they preferred, one that saved fewer lives now or one that saved more lives in the future. The researchers found that the respondents considered six lives saved 25 years in the future and 44 lives saved 100 years in the future equivalent to one life saved today.</p>
        <p>Economists find that it is especially hard to assign dollar values to some benefits of environmental protection -- for instance, saving a threatened species or ecosystem. They are trying but "I don't think anyone is particularly comfortable with how far they've gotten," Dr. Portney said.</p>
        <p>Environmental benefits have often been portrayed as harder to measure than costs. But Dr. Portney says: "Economists have been much too glib about how easy it is to nail down the cost; there are some economists who make it seem like there's nothing out there that we can't slap a dollar value on. We're making progress on some things, but there is a whole range of things that we're never going to be able to express comfortably in dollar terms."</p>
        <p>Dr. A. Myrick Freeman 3d of Bowdoin College, an expert on measuring environmental benefits, acknowledges the difficulties. But, he said: "We have methods that are able to measure within an order of magnitude, or within a factor of two, the benefits of many environmental improvements, and plus or minus 25 percent in some cases. The errors, the bounds, around cost estimates are arguably just as large."</p>
        <p>Dr. Freeman notes a philosophical objection raised by some critics to the use of cost-benefit analysis: it values the environment only in terms of its usefulness to people without giving "independent weight to nonhuman species or ecological systems" in their own right.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, he said, there is some information that says something about policy, imperfect as it is.  "And it's better than making policy in the dark, without any reference at all to costs and benefits," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
