<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S.S. Kentucky Journal; Run Silent, Run Deep, Beat Foes. (Where?)</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="504361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBMARINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KENTUCKY (SUBMARINE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIDENT II (MISSILE)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DF1F3BF933A05752C0A964958260" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S.S. Kentucky Journal; Run Silent, Run Deep, Beat Foes. (Where?)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>ABOARD THE SUBMARINE KENTUCKY, Jan. 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cold war is over and the Soviet Union has disintegrated, but Capt. Mike Riegel and his crew still lurk in the depths of the Atlantic Ocean daily rehearsing a nuclear attack on the former superpower.</p>
        <p>As the rest of the world adjusts to momentous changes, it is business as usual underwater for the men on the Navy's newest Trident II ballistic-missile submarine. The actions and thoughts of the crew, as though suspended in time, remain riveted to a drill -- and a world -- that seems obsolete. Within 30 minutes of receiving a coded order from the President, their mission would be to launch 24 missiles carrying as many as 192 warheads at preassigned military targets thousands of miles away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cold war is over and the Soviet Union has disintegrated, but Capt. Mike Riegel and his crew still lurk in the depths of the Atlantic Ocean daily rehearsing a nuclear attack on the former superpower.</p>
        <p>As the rest of the world adjusts to momentous changes, it is business as usual underwater for the men on the Navy's newest Trident II ballistic-missile submarine. The actions and thoughts of the crew, as though suspended in time, remain riveted to a drill -- and a world -- that seems obsolete. Within 30 minutes of receiving a coded order from the President, their mission would be to launch 24 missiles carrying as many as 192 warheads at preassigned military targets thousands of miles away.</p>
        <p>"We continue to practice something we pray we'll never have to do," said Captain Riegel, 48 years old.</p>
        <p>For three decades, America's doctrine to deter a Soviet nuclear attack has rested largely on the ability of ballistic-missile submarines to elude a first strike and retaliate with a devastating counterpunch. With the sudden collapse of the Soviet Union, the military faces challenges to justify the role of the $1.5 billion submarines that critics say are a cold-war relic.</p>
        <p>That the need for the Trident fleet itself could be challenged seems inconceivable to the men of the Kentucky, who are steeped in a Navy perspective that has yielded little to the changed threat. "The Soviet Union may not be around anymore," Captain Riegel said, "but the countries that made up the U.S.S.R. still exist and still have nuclear weapons."</p>
        <p>The Navy has two kinds of submarines, all nuclear powered. Attack submarines hunt and destroy their foes. The larger ballistic-missile submarines run and hide from enemy and friendly sensors, relying on stealth to survive.</p>
        <p>Four stories tall and 560 feet long, Tridents are self-sustaining cities designed to submerge on patrol for up to three months. Drinking water is distilled from the sea. Oxygen is extracted from the distilled water; carbon dioxide is chemically scrubbed from the air. Supplies stored in huge pantries and refrigerators include 1,800 pounds of coffee and 3,000 rolls of toilet paper for a typical patrol. No alcohol is allowed.</p>
        <p>The sleek, sinister-looking black submarines are the Navy's most potent weapon and potentially one of its most fragile. A serious fire, leak or explosion could cripple the vessel's engines or underwater balancing ability, plunging the ship to depths that would crush its two-inch-thick steel walls like eggshells.</p>
        <p>The 165-man crew volunteers for submarine duty and must pass rigorous academic, physical and psychological exams. The Navy does not allow women to serve on submarines. Life aboard ship is a series of routines, drills and inspections; it is an almost hermetically sealed world maintained by a group of men who want to keep it that way.</p>
        <p>Mail comes weekly in the form of 40-word "familygrams" flashed to the radio room. No replies are permitted.</p>
        <p>Commissioned last July and based in Kings Bay, Ga., the Kentucky is still conducting seaworthiness and weapons tests, including some off Florida today, before it is loaded with missiles for its first patrol this summer.</p>
        <p>Living quarters are cramped by normal standards but palatial by submariners'. Enlisted quarters are nestled between the fat, orange missile tubes that the crew calls "Sherwood Forest."</p>
        <p>Night and day are indistinguishable. When the ship is submerged at 300 feet and cruising at 15 miles an hour, it feels like a windowless, turbulence-free airplane ride with only the faint whirring of fans or an occasional squawk from the intercom audible.</p>
        <p>In the darkened sonar room, the eyes and ears of the sub, technicians stare intently at fluorescent green screens to detect sounds thousands of yards away. The slightest racket on board could give away the Kentucky's position, so reducing noise is a shipwide mania, even though the threat is largely phantom now. Equipment is lined in plastic or rubber to avoid pings or banging. Computers monitor and identify offending equipment. Signs in toilet stalls sternly warn crew members: "Don't Drop That Seat. Shhhhhh!"</p>
        <p>In the cramped command center, dials and digital displays blink at officers and sailors monitoring gray-metal banks of communication, navigation and ballast controls, the latter to make the ship rise or descend. Two crewmen drive the ship using hydraulic steering wheels that control fins and rudders; two periscopes allow peering near the surface.</p>
        <p>In the command center, Captain Riegel orders the daily "battle stations" drill. In a real nuclear emergency, cryptography experts would decode and authenticate the President's order, but in today's test that process is assumed. The ship quickly rises to its launch depth of 130 feet and hovers there with engines shut down. Missiles are fired only after the captain, his executive officer and the strategic weapons officer hear each other's command and turn keys they each safeguard, in launch boxes.</p>
        <p>"These boats won the cold war, but we still have a world out there that's not completely peaceful," said Petty Officer Arthur Tharp, 29, a fire control technician.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
