<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surprise for 'Flu'-Prone Skiers: It May Be Mountain Sickness</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="578365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALTITUDE SICKNESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INFLUENZA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILCHEY, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Influenza</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skiing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD1438F930A15751C1A964958260" item-length="1346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surprise for 'Flu'-Prone Skiers: It May Be Mountain Sickness</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM HILCHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILCHEY, TIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BARBARA SMOLEK LIPPIN, a 39-year-old New York City resident and avid skier, cannot wait to put skis to Rocky Mountain snow, but she also knows that for her there is a price to pay for the joys of high-altitude schussbooming: severe headaches, nausea and other effects of acute mountain sickness.</p>
        <p>"The first time I got sick, I thought I had the flu," she said. In the six years since she learned that she is susceptible to altitude sickness, she has taken medication to blunt its effects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BARBARA SMOLEK LIPPIN, a 39-year-old New York City resident and avid skier, cannot wait to put skis to Rocky Mountain snow, but she also knows that for her there is a price to pay for the joys of high-altitude schussbooming: severe headaches, nausea and other effects of acute mountain sickness.</p>
        <p>"The first time I got sick, I thought I had the flu," she said. In the six years since she learned that she is susceptible to altitude sickness, she has taken medication to blunt its effects.</p>
        <p>"I always take it easy the first day because I'm prepared for it to happen," she said. "Usually by the third day I'm pretty much myself, but my stomach is queasy throughout my stay." Costly for Colorado</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce Paton, a founding member of the Colorado Altitude Research Institute in Keystone, Colo., said: "Frequently people think they have the flu because the symptoms are not dissimilar. The symptoms of mild acute mountain sickness will usually go away in a couple of days, and this only reinforces the opinion that they have had a two-day flu."</p>
        <p>"We started the institute to study the effects of moderate altitude -- that is, 7,500 to 12,000 feet -- on normal people," Dr. Paton said. He said that altitude-related illness costs Colorado about $20 million a year.</p>
        <p>A range of altitude symptoms result from the body's complex response to the decreased barometric pressure and lack of oxygen at high elevations. It is like trying to run a high-performance automobile on low-octane gasoline.</p>
        <p>Dr. Drummond Rennie, chairman of the Medical Committee of the American Alpine Club, said: "In response to high-altitude conditions, your body tries to increase the oxygen level in your blood by increasing respiration. A result is that you increase oxygen intake but also 'blow off' carbon dioxide in your heavy breathing."</p>
        <p>This makes the blood more alkaline and alters the body's ability to exchange gases. Changes in the pressure and permeability of blood vessels can lead to fluid retention, particularly in the lungs and brain, he said. Symptoms of Illness</p>
        <p>Common symptoms of acute mountain sickness include headache, insomnia, nausea, loss of appetite, fatigue, labored or irregular breathing during sleep, coughing, reduced urine output, vomiting and loss of coordination. Swelling of the hands, feet and face may also occur.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rennie and Dr. Peter H. Hackett, an altitude specialist, author and professor at the University of Alaska at Anchorage, conducted studies in 1975 on hundreds of trekkers who passed through Pheriche, Nepal, which sits in the Himalayas at an altitude of 14,300 feet. More than half had mountain-sickness symptoms.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hackett said 25 percent of people experience at least three symptoms of altitude sickness within a few hours to a few days following ascent. Studies show it can occur at elevations of just 7,000 feet. Anyone can get it, but the faster the ascent, the greater the likelihood of illness, he said, adding that overall health does not appear to be a factor; 40 million Americans visited sites above 8,000 feet in 1989, and as many as eight million were probably affected.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rennie said: "Very simple things can prevent it, and in fact it's very difficult to get acute mountain sickness if you ascend slowly. And this is a disease that is invariably relieved by descent."</p>
        <p>A diuretic, Diamox, the prescription drug acetazolamide, is what Mrs. Smolek Lippin takes to relieve symptoms. It increases blood acidity and "respiration and oxygenation of the blood, particularly while you're sleeping," Dr. Rennie said. The prescription steroid dexamethasone is also used to treat altitude illness.</p>
        <p>A study reported in the Oct. 31, 1991 issue of The New England Journal of Medicine showed that the drug nifedipine, normally used for angina, could be taken before ascent to prevent fluid buildup in the lungs. New Portable Device</p>
        <p>Another recent development, a 14-pound portable hyperbaric chamber that looks like a sleeping bag with windows, brings low-altitude conditions to high places. Named for its developer, Dr. Igor Gamow (pronounced GAM-off), a chemical engineering professor at the University of Colorado in Boulder, the Gamow Bag "simulates actual descent" by compressing air so that the climber takes in more oxygen. He said the bag had brought people "from coma to consciousness in minutes."</p>
        <p>Jim Traverso, director of field operations at Overseas Adventure Travel of Cambridge, Mass., said trekkers who took part in his company's 27-day Mount Everest tour were well informed about the rigors of high-altitude hiking. Those who do participate are asked to get a prescription for Diamox.</p>
        <p>The trip begins with a five-night stay at one altitude to allow hikers to acclimatize. Each ascent is accompanied by two nights of sleep at the new elevation. In deference to the mountain maxim "climb high, sleep low," the ascent to the Everest viewing area at 18,450 feet is a day hike. Trekkers return to the camp at 16,175 feet to sleep.</p>
        <p>"There really is no way around this slow and gradual ascent," Mr. Traverso said. "Our whole orientation is to avoid an altitude emergency. When we do get people with sickness -- and we do get them -- they are invariably underhydrated."</p>
        <p>If illness persists after rest, the sick person is immediately evacuated on a yak to a lower altitude. Mr. Traverso said most tour companies were familiar with the Gamow Bag, but few, including his, carried them routinely. He said the Himalayan Rescue Association used the Gamow Bag and that others were available at various sites in Nepal. "For people who ascend too rapidly, they can be a lifesaver," he said.</p>
        <p>In his book "Mountain Sickness: Prevention, Recognition and Treatment," published by the American Alpine Club, Dr. Hackett divides acute mountain sickness into three categories: mild, moderate and severe.</p>
        <p>Mild acute mountain sickness is characterized by a few symptoms like a mild headache, nausea and loss of appetite, and it may feel like a hangover.</p>
        <p>Moderate acute mountain sickness is a progression of symptoms to the point of extreme discomfort. The headache may not be relieved by aspirin, and it is often accompanied by lethargy, weakness, anorexia, nausea and difficulty with coordination. Dr. Hackett said it was important to recognize this progression because people who developed fluid in the lungs or brain usually passed through this stage first.</p>
        <p>High-altitude pulmonary edema, or HAPE, is the most dangerous form of altitude sickness because it can progress to life-threatening seriousness in a matter of hours. The excess fluid in the lungs of a victim exacerbates the lack of oxygen. "It's like being five or six or seven thousand feet higher," Dr. Rennie said.</p>
        <p>Pronounced headache, loss of coordination and confusion -- often with severe nausea and vomiting -- are signs of high-altitude cerebral edema, or HACE. It usually develops after several days of exposure at very high altitude, and left untreated it can rapidly lead to coma and death. Urgency of Rapid Descent</p>
        <p>The treatment for both conditions is a rapid descent of several thousand feet, Dr. Hackett said. Waiting for a rescue team, a doctor or daylight is "malpractice" if descent is possible, he said. When supplemental oxygen is available, it should be used.</p>
        <p>In seven years at the Snake River Health Services clinic in Keystone, elevation 9,300 feet, Dr. Richard Nicholas said he had treated hundreds of people with altitude illness. Although most of his patients had mild to moderate mountain sickness, Dr. Nicholas, now an assistant professor at the University of Colorado Health Sciences Center in Denver, said he treated 50 to 70 cases of pulmonary edema a year.</p>
        <p>He said knowledge of altitude illness could mean the difference between enjoyment and agony. "For people who know they are susceptible, it's identical to the idea of seasickness," he said. "Since I get seasick, I wouldn't think about going on a boat without taking medication. I highly recommend talking to your doctor before traveling to high altitudes."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
