<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D81E30F934A25750C0A964958260" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>The Japanese stock market improved marginally today amid a tense atmosphere. Analysts said most players appeared to be watching for what, if anything, the Government would do to try to arrest the steady erosion in investor confidence.  [ Page D1. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Robert J. Eaton, who was named to replace Lee A. Iacocca when the chairman and chief executive of Chrysler retires at the end of the year, gives up a 29-year career at General Motors and takes his biggest risk yet in joining the No. 3 U.S. auto maker.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>The Japanese stock market improved marginally today amid a tense atmosphere. Analysts said most players appeared to be watching for what, if anything, the Government would do to try to arrest the steady erosion in investor confidence.  [ Page D1. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Robert J. Eaton, who was named to replace Lee A. Iacocca when the chairman and chief executive of Chrysler retires at the end of the year, gives up a 29-year career at General Motors and takes his biggest risk yet in joining the No. 3 U.S. auto maker.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Mr. Eaton was named Chrysler's chief operating officer and will join Mr. Iacocca in a new office of the chief executive. Robert A. Lutz said he would remain as president.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>G.E. threatened to sue a whistle-blowing employee to recover any monetary award he receives for bringing forward charges of wrongdoing in its sale of military jet engines to Israel.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Bell Atlantic plans a "one person, one number" service giving customers a single number in different locations.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Braun, which has thrived outside Germany by melding distinctive designs with the marketing power of its parent, Gillette, is counting on new products and refinements of best sellers.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Investcorp, a New-York investment bank, emerged as the leader of a group that has offered $425 million to buy the Circle K Corporation, the bankrupt convenience store chain.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Pfizer is negotiating to sell its Coty perfume and cosmetics unit to a German company for a reported $475 million.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Paramount Pictures was ordered to pay the columnist Art Buchwald $150,000 and his producing partner $750,000 for their contributions to the hit movie "Coming to America."  [ C13. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>The decision of the Taystee Bakery to move from Queens to Pennsylvania poses a classic question: How far should the city go to subsidize manufacturers to keep jobs in New York City?  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Public pension funds in many states are being urged by elected officials to invest in local businesses, housing and other ventures in to bolster the economy.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The Justice Department has told the White House that registered lobbyists for foreign governments and corporations can not serve on Federal advisory panels.  [ D21. ]</p>
        <p>A new study concludes that spending billions to reduce carbon dioxide emissions would save consumers and industry $5 trillion in lower fuel and electricity bills.  [ C1. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks ended mixed in lethargic trading. The Dow Jones industrial average gained 0.45 point, to 3,236.36.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities were narrowly mixed in fairly active trading. Market sentiment remained very negative.  [ D21. ]</p>
        <p>Gold dropped to its lowest price in more than five and a half years, falling $3.40 an ounce, to $343.30, on the spot market.  [ D22. ]  The dollar was marginally lower.  [ D22. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Employers and retirees could save millions of dollars because of new rules that limit what doctors in the Medicare program can charge. Milt Freudenheim: Business and Health.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The plunge in Tokyo's blue-chip stocks made one issue clear: Japan has become the make-or-break bet this year for many money managers and investors. Market Place.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>G.M. last changed one of its advertising agencies in 1958. It supports the long-term policy. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D23. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
