<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Seeks Third-World Ecology Aid</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="511007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE163BF931A35750C0A964958260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Seeks Third-World Ecology Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, March 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposal to give poor countries billions of dollars to help development without damaging the environment will be made on Monday at the opening of a major conference here.</p>
        <p>Industrialized countries would provide such "earth increments" through existing aid-giving institutions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A proposal to give poor countries billions of dollars to help development without damaging the environment will be made on Monday at the opening of a major conference here.</p>
        <p>Industrialized countries would provide such "earth increments" through existing aid-giving institutions.</p>
        <p>The conference was called to prepare for the world environmental summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro in June, the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development.</p>
        <p>The aid proposal, to be made by Maurice F. Strong, the Canadian who is Secretary General of the Rio meeting, highlights the major problem: how to pay the huge cost of the environmental cleanup that the Rio session is expected to endorse.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Strong said the developing countries would need about $125 billion a year in aid to pay for the new environmental programs, or $70 billion more than all the financial assistance they now receive.</p>
        <p>These new programs, intended to make economic development environmentally sustainable, include steps to stabilize the climate by reducing emissions of gases implicated in global warming and to protect threatened plant and animal species. In addition, the Rio conference is expected to adopt a general statement of ecological principles called the Earth Charter.</p>
        <p>As their price for accepting these goals, developing countries are demanding additional financing from the industrialized world.</p>
        <p>Mr. Strong said that asking for another $70 billion a year in aid was unrealistic in today's economy. But he said his consultations with governments suggested that developing countries would be satisfied if the industrialized nations offered "an initial commitment" to provide "$5 billion to $10 billion a year in extra aid.</p>
        <p>He said this money should be made available through several sources rather than from the single new Green Fund under third-world control that China and several developing countries favor.</p>
        <p>In his address Monday, Mr. Strong will suggest that industrialized countries agree to add $1 billion or $2 billion as an "earth increment" to the planned replenishment next year of the International Development Agency at the World Bank, which provides money virtually interest-free to the poorest countries.</p>
        <p>This money would be earmarked for environmental projects. Major aid-giving countries are discussing replenishing the development agency with some $17.5 billion over three years, starting in July 1993, when its current fund will be exhausted.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Strong said, he will call for rich countries to give more money to a new branch of the World Bank, the Global Environmental Facility, increasing the size of that fund to $5 billion or $6 billion, from $1.5 billion.</p>
        <p>The World Bank uses this fund to help pay for projects it thinks will benefit all countries. Its first loan went to Poland earlier this year to preserve an unspoiled forest. First No, Then Yes From U.S.</p>
        <p>Industrialized countries argue that the Global Environmental Facility constitutes the "new and additional resources" the developing world is asking for because the money they have put into it does not come from their regular aid budgets.</p>
        <p>After first refusing to contribute, the Bush Administration changed position last week and said it would provide $50 million to the global fund and $25 million to individual developing countries to help pay for environmental projects.</p>
        <p>In mid-April, immediately after the preparatory conference, former Prime Minister Noburu Takeshita of Japan will be the host of a high-level meeting in Tokyo to consider additional ways of financing the Rio conference's goals, including possible global taxes on energy and pollution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Strong said he had asked Japan to provide developing countries with substantial additional aid for environmental measures. Japanese newspapers have reported that the Government is considering a commitment similar to the $12 billion it gave toward the cost of the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>The Rio Earth Summit, as it has been termed, comes exactly 20 years after the first United Nations Environment Conference, held in Stockholm in 1972, at which Mr. Strong also presided.</p>
        <p>That meeting established environmental protection as an aim of government policy and led to the creation of environmental ministries in most developed countries.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
