<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INDUSTRIES GAINING BROAD FLEXIBILITY ON AIR POLLUTION</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COUNCIL ON COMPETITIVENESS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUAYLE, DAN (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WAXMAN, HENRY A (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Chronology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D81F31F935A15755C0A964958260" item-length="1584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INDUSTRIES GAINING BROAD FLEXIBILITY ON AIR POLLUTION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush Administration today issued a rule that will give manufacturers broad authority to increase substantially the amount of hazardous pollutants they can pour into the atmosphere beginning in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency reluctantly issued the new rule, which had been championed by the President's Council on Competitiveness, a Cabinet group headed by Vice President Dan Quayle. The rule will be central to a system of pollution permits that will be established over the next 10 years under the Clean Air Act of 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush Administration today issued a rule that will give manufacturers broad authority to increase substantially the amount of hazardous pollutants they can pour into the atmosphere beginning in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency reluctantly issued the new rule, which had been championed by the President's Council on Competitiveness, a Cabinet group headed by Vice President Dan Quayle. The rule will be central to a system of pollution permits that will be established over the next 10 years under the Clean Air Act of 1990.</p>
        <p>Chemical and drug manufacturers, concerned about the costs of meeting standards in the Clean Air Act, had sought the rule, saying they needed a flexible standard so they could make changes in equipment or production practices that might cause them to exceed air pollution limits. Discretion to Emit More</p>
        <p>Under the new rule, a company can increase the amount of pollution it emits into the atmosphere by up to 245 tons a year without public notice or hearings if it says it is forced to do so by a change in production methods. The company can do this by applying for an increase, and while the application is pending, it may go ahead with its plans.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes you have requirements issued by a state or the Federal government to change a product or a process," Dan Lacy, vice president for corporate communications at Ashland Oil said in explaining why the rule would be helpful. "You have certain restrictions on the amount of time you have to do it in. If you are facing that kind of deadline and you're waiting to get a permit to proceed, then that puts the business in a bind."</p>
        <p>A giant refinery typically emits millions of pounds of pollutants into the air each year, but small manufacturing plants generally discharge only a fraction of that amount.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has 45 days to reject or approve the application, while states have up to 90 days. Waxman Is Furious</p>
        <p>President Bush often cites the passage of the Clean Air Act as one of the singular achievements of his Presidency, a claim he repeated again on Wednesday in an interview. Enacted on Nov. 15, 1990, the law was designed to control virtually every important source of air pollution and substantially reduce health and environmental damage caused by acid rain, smog, urban ozone pollution, toxic chemicals and destruction of the earth's atmospheric ozone shield.</p>
        <p>But one of the principal authors of the act, Representative Henry A. Waxman, a Democrat of California, said that the rule issued today eviscerated the law.</p>
        <p>"This is a massive loophole, written for political purposes, that carves the heart out of the Clean Air Act," Mr. Waxman said. He called the rule illegal and predicted that it would be challenged in court.</p>
        <p>The new rule was also being cited by state air pollution-control officials, some Democrats in Congress and national environmental leaders as more evidence for their argument that the President has blunted the law's effect. He has done this, they said, by missing legal deadlines for issuing some important rules and by altering others to make them friendlier to business.</p>
        <p>The Council on Competitiveness, which has played a central role in the White House's management of the law, is already the defendant in separate lawsuits by New York State and Mr. Waxman.</p>
        <p>The final rule on permits will not begin to take effect until at least 1995, the E.P.A. said today. States have until November 1993 to complete their pemit programs and to submit them to the environmental agency for review. The agency has until November 1994 to approve state programs. Companies have until 1995 to begin applying for permits, which are to be issued from 1995 through the end of the decade.</p>
        <p>The Council on Competitiveness has attracted support from industrial executives and increasing criticism from environmental groups and Democrats because of its growing influence in reviewing, halting, and at times helping to write new regulations, particularly those concerned with environmental safeguards. Vote Called 'Harassment'</p>
        <p>Today, the House Appropriations Committee acted on a proposal by Representative David E. Skagg, Democrat of Colorado, and voted 30 to 18 to eliminate money for the council's eight-member staff.</p>
        <p>David C. Beckwith, the Vice President's spokesman, said today that the committee's vote was "harassment," and that the council would not waver in its objectives. "The same Congressional critics who allege the council was operating illegally have abandoned that tactic in favor of political harassment," said Mr. Beckwith. "The council will continue to uphold and enforce all laws at the least possible cost to jobs, consumers and the economy."</p>
        <p>The new rule sets up the framework for states to issue operating permits to roughly 35,000 factories, chemical and pharmaceutical plants, refineries, power plants and other important sources of air pollution. Forty states already have some form of permit program, according to the environmental agency. But under the Clean Air Act, the agency is required to set new minimum, uniform standards and to enforce them.</p>
        <p>The disagreement on the rule has produced one of the angriest political struggles in the Administration, between William K. Reilly, the E.P.A. Administrator and Vice President Quayle.</p>
        <p>Their disagreement focused on whether factories should be able to increase by small amounts the levels of pollution they are allowed to produce.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly argued that the increases should be small -- no more than five tons annually per company -- and that the public should have the right to review applications by companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle and the Council on Competitiveness said the increases do not have to be small and companies should be allowed to make them without public review. Mr. Quayle's position was strongly supported by the Chemical Manufacturers Association, drug makers, refiners and other large industries. Industrial executives said they should have the flexibility to make changes in their plants that would increase pollution without having to go through a long and exhausting public review. When Bush Intervened</p>
        <p>Last month, Mr. Bush intervened and decided the issue in favor of Mr. Quayle. At the time, the White House and the Environmental Protection Agency represented Mr. Bush's decision as one with minor pollution consequences. Administration officials said companies would not be allowed to increase their air pollution emissions by more than 40 tons each, or 80,000 pounds, a year. They also said it was likely that the final rule would include a provision allowing states to have a short review period to approve or disapprove the increased pollution.</p>
        <p>The final rule issued today goes much further. The rule allows any company to increase its air pollution by up to 245 tons, or 490,000 pounds a year, a significant amount for any manufacturing plant, state air pollution-control authorities said today. The rule also allows plants to make the increases as soon as they apply to states. The E.P.A. has 45 days to reject the application, and states have 90 days to approve or disapprove. The public will not be notified or have an opportunity to intervene unless states write such provisions on their own. Big Regional Effects</p>
        <p>In industrial regions, like the Mississippi River corridor between New Orleans and Baton Rouge or the Kanawha Valley west of Charleston, W. Va., such increases could total millions of extra pounds of pollutants in the air every year if a number of chemical plants and manufacturers take advantage of the waiver at once.</p>
        <p>Directors of state air pollution-control agencies today condemned the new rule, saying it was a giant loophole designed to allow companies to pollute without penalties. The state authorities also said the rule would make it exceedingly difficult to enforce portions of the Clean Air Act designed to control urban smog, and they predicted that many states would ignore the Administration's regulation and enact tougher standards.</p>
        <p>"We don't intend to put this regulation into effect; I don't think many states will," said Thomas C. Jorling, the Commissioner at the New York Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>But there are some states, like West Virginia, that are prohibited by state law from exceeding Federal environmental standards. "It's an awful rule," G. Dale Farley, the director of the West Virginia Air Pollution Control Commission, said of the new rule. "The whole point of requiring plants to get operating permits is to have some handle on overall air pollution emissions. It allows states to have a management scheme. With this provision, the only thing states can do to keep on top of the situation is just to have a rubber stamp that says, 'We object.' When the applications come in, we stamp them and that will prevent the extra emissions."</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman, in asserting that the new rule is illegal, said the Clean Air Act had directed the Administration to require public notification and review for any modifications in a company's permit. He said in an interview today that the provision for public notification had been included in the law to make it much more difficult for companies to exceed air pollution levels on their operating permits.</p>
        <p>But William G. Rosenberg, the E.P.A.'s assistant administrator for Air and Radiation, said today that the new rule would provide the nation with cleaner air by making it easier to enforce the law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
