<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Britain to Shut Most of Its Coal Mines</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS (LABOR)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH COAL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMIDT, WILLIAM E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF1038F937A25753C1A964958260" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Britain to Shut Most of Its Coal Mines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM E. SCHMIDT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMIDT, WILLIAM E</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Oct. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Crippled by rising imports of foreign coal and falling demand for its own product among utilities, British Coal announced today that it would close 31 of its remaining 50 mines and lay off 30,000 miners, nearly three-quarters of the industry's dwindling work force.</p>
        <p>The loss of the jobs is the latest in a series of recent setbacks to a British economy already bleeding jobs at an estimated rate of 8,000 a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Crippled by rising imports of foreign coal and falling demand for its own product among utilities, British Coal announced today that it would close 31 of its remaining 50 mines and lay off 30,000 miners, nearly three-quarters of the industry's dwindling work force.</p>
        <p>The loss of the jobs is the latest in a series of recent setbacks to a British economy already bleeding jobs at an estimated rate of 8,000 a week.</p>
        <p>Although the Goverment had been talking about closing some coal mines for several weeks, the huge scale of today's cutbacks is certain to compound the economic woes of Prime Minister John Major, whose Government is already under growing pressure to cut interest rates or retool its economic strategy in the face of Britain's worst economic recession since the 1930's.</p>
        <p>The scheduled closings by British Coal, which is to be sold off to private investors next year, will reduce an industry that during the 1920's employed more than one million people and was known across Britain as "King Coal" to a bare shadow of its former self.  Union Militants Call for Strike</p>
        <p>Of the 31 mines being closed, 27 will be shut outright and 4 will be mothballed. Of those that will be closed, 6 will be shut down by Friday and 19 more before Christmas. Next April, when the closings are completed, Britain's coal industry will consist of fewer than 13,000 miners at 19 mines.</p>
        <p>Facing a mortal threat to their own ranks, militant mine union leaders immediately called today for a nationwide strike to protest the decision by the state-owned company to close the mines.</p>
        <p>Despite attempts over the years to cut costs and increase productivity, Britain's coal industry has shrunk dramatically since 1947, when it was nationalized by the Government and coal producers employed more than 718,000 miners at 958 mines.</p>
        <p>More than 2.8 million people, or 9.9 percent of Britain's work force, are now unemployed, and one forecast today predicted that unemployment would top 3.4 million by next summer.</p>
        <p>Officials of British Coal said it had no choice but to close its least efficient mines, mainly as a result of shrinking demand from electrical producers, who have turned increasingly to natural gas.</p>
        <p>Although coal accounts for about 78 percent of all electricity now generated in England and Wales, Britain's two largest electrical utilities, National Power and PowerGen, have said they intend to rely increasingly on gas-fired generators, as well as foreign coal imports.</p>
        <p>The Government says power plants that consumed more than 70 million tons of coal in 1991 are expected to reduce their purchases to as little as 40 million tons next year, and 30 million tons annually for the next four years after that, under new five-year contracts being negotiated by British Coal. Growing Use of Imported Coal</p>
        <p>At the same time, British coal production has also been hurt by the growing use of imported coal, including American coal, which is mined in open pits and is much cheaper to produce than the British product, which is extracted from deep mines.  The British Coal Board says Britain will import about 20 million tons of coal through 1992, compared with 1.2 million tons in 1970.</p>
        <p>Demand for British coal has also been affected by stricter enviromental regulations, since British coal tends to produce higher levels of sulfur emissions when it is burned than foreign coal. The European Community has become more vigilant in monitoring the emissions of power stations across the Continent, in an effort to crack down on pollution and the effects of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Mine union leaders estimated that the mine closings could ultimately cost a total of 100,000 jobs, when layoffs among railroad employees and other workers in communities dependent on the mines are also added in.</p>
        <p>Arthur Scargill, the president of the National Union of Mineworkers, once one of Britain's most powerful and militant trade unions, described the closings as a "savage, brutal act of vandalism." He called on his members to "stand up and fight back," but stopped short of calling for a strike.</p>
        <p>To help absorb the impact of the closings on dozens of communities where the mines remain the principal source of employment, the Government said today that it would make available about $1.7 billion in emergency funds for severance benefits, job retraining and industrial redevelopment programs for local governments. Severe Shock to Miners</p>
        <p>Michael Heseltime, a member of the Cabinet, acknowledged that the announcement was "a severe shock to a great many miners and their families," even though the Government had been warning of cutbacks for several months.</p>
        <p>"But British Coal cannot go on producing coal which cannot be sold," Mr. Heseltine said.</p>
        <p>Neil Clarke, the chairman of British Coal, said that despite a doubling in productivity in the last six years, as a result of more efficient production techniques, the industry could not avoid what he called "the bear squeeze on demand."</p>
        <p>"I believe," he said, "though the price is heavy, that we are paving the way for a much more robust U.K. coal business to carry us through the 90's and beyond," he told a news conference in London.</p>
        <p>In an attempt to dilute anger among workers, which industry officials fear may result in a strike, Mr. Clarke said British Coal would be offering severance payments of as much as $63,000 to workers.</p>
        <p>But among many mine workers and officials in communities facing mine closings, there was sharp anger and appeals for Government help to keep the mines open.</p>
        <p>Hedley Salt, chairman of the Coalfield Communities Campaign, an organization that represents 75 local governments dependent on the coal industry, asked Prime Minister John Major to intervene personally. Justification Challenged</p>
        <p>"To close these pits would be folly of enormous national magnitude," Mr. Salt wrote in a letter released today. "I defy anyone to provide sound economic justification that such an act will be to the benefit of Britain."</p>
        <p>In the Rhondda Valley of south Wales, for example, where as many as 250,000 men used to work in 70 pits, the decision announced today will leave a single mine, employing just 370 workers.</p>
        <p>Local governments estimate that layoffs and closings over the last four years have already cost the area more than $340 million in wages.</p>
        <p>Ken Capstick, a militant union leader from Yorkshire, where several mines facing closing, criticized the utilities for switching to natural gas, which he said was 30 percent more expensive than coal. He said he would introduce a motion calling for job actions when union leaders convened on Thursday in Sheffield.</p>
        <p>The mine workers were a symbol of trade union militancy during the 1980's, when Mr. Scargill and his workers staged a yearlong pit strike in defiance of Margaret Thatcher, then the Prime Minister.</p>
        <p>Although the strike crippled British industry, the ranks of mineworkers and union power went into sharp decline in the late 1980's, with the number employed in the pits falling from 231,000 in 1980 to 57,000 in 1990.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
