<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheap Fuel Hurts Goal For Climate</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531511"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DA1F3BF936A15756C0A964958260" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheap Fuel Hurts Goal For Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The scientists who will gather at the United Nations Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro next month say that action is needed now to limit global warming. Their science may be right, but their timing could not be worse.</p>
        <p>Taking the most important step in slowing climate warming -- burning less fuel to cut heat-retaining carbon emissions into the atmosphere -- will be extremely difficult because fuel prices are now so low.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The scientists who will gather at the United Nations Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro next month say that action is needed now to limit global warming. Their science may be right, but their timing could not be worse.</p>
        <p>Taking the most important step in slowing climate warming -- burning less fuel to cut heat-retaining carbon emissions into the atmosphere -- will be extremely difficult because fuel prices are now so low.</p>
        <p>Ten years ago, planners were predicting oil at $75 or $100 a barrel in the 90's. Now, said Lee J. Schipper, senior scientist at the Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory International Energy Studies Group, the price is so stable that "there's nothing to predict."</p>
        <p>"It isn't interesting any more," he added. Unexpected Stability</p>
        <p>The price of oil -- now around $20 a barrel -- has proved in the last 18 months to be more stable than almost anyone had believed; even a war in the Persian Gulf did not move it higher for long.</p>
        <p>In addition, the price of coal is low and has remained stable, and the price of natural gas is declining in some areas, most notably in North America.</p>
        <p>None of this makes it impossible to cut fuel use; it just means that science and the energy market are completely out of step. And unlike a decade ago, when the world believed oil should be conserved because the supply was running out, any action today to limit fuel use runs against the economics of cheap energy. The White House's Mood</p>
        <p>Conservation also goes against the mood in the White House, which would have to lend its support for any global conservation action -- like a consumption tax -- to take hold.</p>
        <p>The world is like a patient with a cholesterol problem. Tofu and sprouts are available, but steak and lobster are plentiful, too. Consider the following:</p>
        <p>*The price of driving a car has never been lower, in inflation-adjusted terms. Partly as a result, the number of miles traveled each year on American roads has quadrupled in the last 40 years. The car population around the world is rising far faster than the human population.</p>
        <p>*Nuclear power, a source of energy that produces nearly no carbon emissions, will probably lose share in the world electricity market in coming years because of public unease with the technology and the low prices of other fuels.</p>
        <p>*Solar power and wind power are still under development, but the low price of oil has blunted the urgency of research.</p>
        <p>*Technology has improved the efficiency of the oil companies so that it costs far less now to find a barrel of oil than it did a few years ago.</p>
        <p>In fact, in the last 10 years, the amount of oil that has been found and is waiting to be pumped has doubled, to about one trillion barrels; natural gas projects are proliferating, and in most parts of the world engineers have long since given up looking for coal. With advancing technology, those fuels can now be substituted for each other to a growing degree. Plentiful Supplies</p>
        <p>The result is that fossil fuels, the "nonrenewable" energy sources, are hard to run out of. The May 15 issue of Science carries an article by three researchers from the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility research consortium based in Palo Alto, Calif., that states flatly, "There is little likelihood that a serious scarcity of fuels will develop during the next century on a global scale."</p>
        <p>The conclusion is startling because of the growth in demand. The researchers -- Chauncey Starr, who founded the institute and is an elder statesman of the electricity world; Milton F. Searl, and Sy Alport -- project that by 2060, global population will nearly double, and average output of goods and services per captia will increase 2.8 times. That means that economic activity will be more than five times as large as today.</p>
        <p>In the same period, the researchers say, energy consumption will increase slightly more slowly because of increased efficiency, rising to 4.5 times the current level if there are no major gains in efficiency, and 2.5 times if there are.</p>
        <p>That energy equation resembles the dismaying prospects laid out by Malthus that the population will grow faster than the food supply. In this case, energy efficiency increases arithmetically, but energy consumption increases geometrically.</p>
        <p>And prices will not help slow the growth of consumption.</p>
        <p>"The market is giving no assistance whatsoever," said Geoffrey M. Heal, an economist and specialist in energy and natural resources at the Columbia Business School. "For all of the basic energy sources, as a trend over the last 10 years, prices have fallen."</p>
        <p>Statistics collected by Conoco Inc., the oil company subsidiary of E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, illustrate the problem. Through the 1960's, America's oil bill was about 2 percent of gross national product, hardly worth worrying about. It jumped to 4 percent with the oil price shock of 1973, and 9 percent with the price shock of 1979-80. Now it is back down to about 2 percent.</p>
        <p>"The price of oil will not be one that makes the world want to develop with less oil," said John Sauer, Conoco's chief economist. And oil tends to drag the prices of other fuels up or down with it.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide output need not rise in lockstep with energy use; some energy could come from non-carbon sources. But the two largest such sources today -- hydroelectricity and nuclear power -- are growing only slightly because of environmental problems and public opposition.</p>
        <p>Other sources, like the direct conversion of sunlight to electricity, or generation of liquid fuels from crops or organic wastes, are not financially attractive on a large scale.</p>
        <p>The Earth Summit goal for limiting carbon emissions -- freezing emissions at 1990 levels -- seems ambitious. But even that goal is modest relative to the problem. Carbon emissions in 1990 were far larger than the earth's biosphere could absorb, so if emissions were stabilized at that level, the amount of carbon in the atmosphere would continue to rise. Room for Change</p>
        <p>The economics of natural resources could change again, of course. Professor Heal of Columbia points out that the warming of the earth is measured in decades, and some time in a decade or two, the world could want to cut fuel use to save costs.</p>
        <p>But if carbon emissions must be cut, there is a reason to begin with carbon-emission taxes now, he said. "From a government-policy position, it may be easier to start a tradition of raising prices with carbon taxes at a time of low prices," he said.</p>
        <p>But no industrial nation is likely to embark on this course alone, thus handing an economic advantage to its trading partners. And so far, the logic of instituting a tax now does not seem appealing in the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
