<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. TO PLEDGE AID TO FIGHT WARMING</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D91E3DF934A15751C0A964958260" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. TO PLEDGE AID TO FIGHT WARMING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush Administration will announce today the first change in its position on a critical issue affecting efforts to negotiate a multinational treaty to control global warming, a White House official said last night.</p>
        <p>The official, Michael Deland, the chairman of the White House Council on Environmental Quality, said the United States would pledge to contribute $75 million to help developing countries do their part in stabilizing atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases produced by human activity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush Administration will announce today the first change in its position on a critical issue affecting efforts to negotiate a multinational treaty to control global warming, a White House official said last night.</p>
        <p>The official, Michael Deland, the chairman of the White House Council on Environmental Quality, said the United States would pledge to contribute $75 million to help developing countries do their part in stabilizing atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases produced by human activity.</p>
        <p>Scientists have said the buildup of the gases could cause a catastrophic warming of the globe by the end of the next century.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries have said they would not sign a treaty that did not include financial aid. The issue is one of two important stumbling blocks in treaty negotiations now going on at the United Nations among more than 150 countries.</p>
        <p>The second issue, which has received more attention, is the United States' refusal so far to agree to European demands that carbon dioxide emissions be stabilized at 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Representatives of the European Community said yesterday at the negotiating session that their position remained unchanged.</p>
        <p>Discussions are going on within the Bush Administration to determine whether the stabilization target could be met without damaging the United States economy, which depends on the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil. The burning of fossil fuels produces carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deland said that, even though no conclusion had been reached on whether the United States should set 1990 levels as a goal, the Administration would announce today at the United Nations a number of measures aimed at achieving greater energy efficiency. These include, for example, more efficient lighting and Federal incentives for electric utilities to achieve greater efficiency rather without building new coal-burning power plants.</p>
        <p>"We will continue to push a number of measures that will result in energy efficiency," he said, "but we don't yet have solid numbers as to what they will achieve" in carbon dioxide emissions. Environmental Inventories</p>
        <p>The Administration will contribute $50 million to the Global Environment Facility, a new program for distributing environmental aid set up by the World Bank, the United Nations Environment Program and the United Nations Development Program. The program, under a proposal favored by the industrialized countries, would disburse funds donated by them for the use of developing countries in coping with global warming.</p>
        <p>Another $25 million is to be pledged over two years by the United States for direct aid to developing countries in producing precise inventories of their heat-trapping emissions, as well as of forests that might help absorb carbon dioxide. The funds would also help developing countries analyze their climates so that future changes can be gauged.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries oppose channeling money through the Global Environmental Facility because, they say, they would not have enough control over what is done with the funds.  Developing countries are represented on the facility's governing body, however, and discussions are under way on how it is to be administered.</p>
        <p>The United States has been under fire from many countries who see it as obstructing the creation of a global warming treaty in time for the "Earth Summit" meeting in Rio de Janeiro in June, where the agreement would be signed.</p>
        <p>The financial contributions the Administration is to announce today reflect "the President's commitment to working to see a successful conclusion in these ongoing negotiations so that a convention can be agreed on in time to be signed in Rio," Mr. Deland said.</p>
        <p>The present round of negotiations ends Friday. A final session is tentatively scheduled for late April and early May in New York or Geneva.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
