<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="572926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DB1330F935A15752C1A964958260" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-13  OZONE DEADLINE NOW 1996</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-13  OZONE DEADLINE NOW 1996</p>
        <p>Spurred by recent evidence that the earth's protective ozone layer is being depleted even more extensively than feared, the nations of the world agreed to bring forward again the deadline for halting production of the most important ozone-destroying chemicals. Representatives of 87 countries moved up the deadline from 2000 to Jan. 1, 1996.  A1  NO CIGARETTES IN ITALY</p>
        <p>It may be true that at no time since tobacco was introduced to Europe in the mid-16th century has a small group of people forced an entire country to contemplate giving up smoking. But that is what has happened in Italy after 20 days of a strike by the workers who control distribution from the state tobacco monopoly. There are no cigarettes to be had anywhere except from smugglers.  A1  FRENCH PARTIES DENOUNCE PACT</p>
        <p>France's political parties unanimously denounced a farm trade pact concluded last week by the United States and the European Community, but the main conservative opposition bloc refused to endorse the Government's strategy for reversing the agreement.  A3  U.N. OBSERVERS FOR MACEDONIA</p>
        <p>The United Nations Security Council is preparing to send military observers to the troubled Balkan republic of Macedonia, which most countries refuse to recognize and which is not yet even a United Nations member. Many fear a new and disastrous outbreak of fighting between Christians and Muslims there is imminent.  A6  CZECHOSLOVAK DIVISION APPROVED</p>
        <p>Parliament approved the division of Czechoslovakia into two nations at midnight on Dec. 31, ratifying a separation that was well on the way to becoming a reality.  A5  NEW PARLIAMENT FOR IRELAND</p>
        <p>Results are expected Thursday or Friday in the election of a new Parliament in Ireland, but details of the country's referendum on liberalizing the abortion law may come sooner.  A7  YELTSIN ACTS TO APPEASE FOES</p>
        <p>Having provoked a storm of criticism by dismissing the outspoken chief of central television, President Yeltsin of Russia took another step toward appeasing his opposition by accepting the resignation of his pugnacious information minister.  A8  Haiti's elite may now feel the pressure of a new wave of refugees.  A10  Israel has accused four journalists of violating censorship laws.  A11  In a gesture to the West, China frees a prominant dissident.  A13  London Journal: Royal family's relationship with public grows uneasy.  A4  National A16-21, B18-19, D15  THE ECONOMY RALLIES</p>
        <p>The Government reported that the gross domestic product jumped by 3.9 percent in the third quarter, by far the largest three-month increase since President Bush took office. President-elect Clinton said the surprising strength of the surge might cause him to rethink his short-term plans to spur the economy.  A1  THE FUTURE OF APPRENTICESHIPS</p>
        <p>Experts agree that for a lasting economic recovery, the nation must train better workers, especially young people who do not go on to college. But turning youth apprenticeships from a group of promising pilot projects into a common American experience will be a formidable task.  A1  BIG GAIN IN FETAL RESEARCH</p>
        <p>For the first time, doctors have repaired brain damage by implanting in patients the brain tissue from aborted fetuses. That success could prove to be a milestone in the search for treatment of a number of degenerative brain diseases, including Alzheimer's.  A1  MORE APPOINTMENTS BY CLINTON</p>
        <p>The President-elect chose nine "cluster coordinators," who will dig through each Federal department and agency to find out what, and who, is there.  A16  FOR TSONGAS, NEW CANCER FIGHT</p>
        <p>Preliminary results of a biopsy show that a lump in the abdomen of former Senator Tsongas, who spoke frequently of his triumph over lymphoma as he campaigned for the Presidency this year, is cancerous.  B19  ONE OUTCOME, TWO SPINS</p>
        <p>Republicans hailed the victory of Paul Coverdell over Wyche Fowler in a Senate election in Georgia as an admonition to the President-elect to temper some of his plans. The Democrats scoffed.  A20  LAND ACCORD HITS SNAG</p>
        <p>The Interior Department's proposal to transfer 400,000 acres of public land in Arizona to settle an ancient dispute between the Hopis and the Navajos came under sharp criticism from Federal officials, including a crucial member of Congress.  A16  BIG FINE ON DELTA AIR LINES</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. fined the carrier $2 million, the second-largest penalty ever levied against an airline for maintenance violations.  A17  A NASA PROGRAM UNDER FIRE</p>
        <p>In an assessment that dealt a blow to some arguments supporting construction of a space station, a team of scientists concluded that 10 years of experiments in growing protein crystals in the low-gravity environment of space had produced disappointing results.  B18  New England Journal: The wild turkey is back to stay.  A16  A judge sent the Los Angeles school dispute to arbitration.  D15  The E.P.A. and environmentalists reached a clean-air accord.  A19  Metro Digest B1  NEW AGENCY FOR THE HOMELESS</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins has decided to place New York City's system that aids the homeless under a new agency to operate city shelters and hire nonprofit groups to provide drug treatment and job training among other services for the homeless.  A1  DINKINS DEFENDS ROLE</p>
        <p>In a televised speech, Mayor Dinkins delivered a personal defense of his role in the Crown Heights racial disturbances last year and appealed for racial harmony and appreciation of the city's diversity.  A1  Business Digest D1  Home Section C1-11  Arts/Entertainment C12-20  Sports B20-26  Obituaries D16  Editorials/Op-Ed A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials  A stirring holiday sermon.  Presidential candidate's cancer.  The feast.  Dendranthema: mum for short.  Letters  William Safire: Rating world spookery.  Garrison Keillor: All you do is just sit down.  Margaret Visser: One strange bird.  James Thurber: The two turkeys.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
