<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ENERGY BILL GIVEN APPROVAL IN HOUSE</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFSHORE EXPLORATION AND INSTALLATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC NATIONAL WILDLIFE REFUGE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska/Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DE1538F93BA15756C0A964958260" item-length="1058" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ENERGY BILL GIVEN APPROVAL IN HOUSE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The House today overwhelmingly passed the most ambitious energy legislation in more than a decade, prohibiting new offshore drilling, toughening building codes to encourage conservation and granting incentives to stimulate solar power or other alternatives for homes and cars.</p>
        <p>Stitched together by conservation-minded liberals and by conservatives who hoped to reinvigorate the nuclear energy industry, the bill is a patchwork that few lawmakers were entirely happy with. But it is similar in most essential provisions to a Senate measure passed in February, and the end product is likely to touch the lives of virtually all Americans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The House today overwhelmingly passed the most ambitious energy legislation in more than a decade, prohibiting new offshore drilling, toughening building codes to encourage conservation and granting incentives to stimulate solar power or other alternatives for homes and cars.</p>
        <p>Stitched together by conservation-minded liberals and by conservatives who hoped to reinvigorate the nuclear energy industry, the bill is a patchwork that few lawmakers were entirely happy with. But it is similar in most essential provisions to a Senate measure passed in February, and the end product is likely to touch the lives of virtually all Americans.</p>
        <p>The bill passed by a vote of 381 to 37, with 135 Republicans joining 245 Democrats and 1 independent in favor.  Criticism by Energy Secretary</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary James D. Watkins issued a statement criticizing House provisions curtailing offshore drilling and including price increases for natural gas. But he added that he looked forward to House and Senate negotiators ironing out a version the Administration could support. President Bush is expected to sign the bill that eventually emerges.</p>
        <p>Because the bill strikes a compromise among the competing interests of environmentalists, the nuclear and petroleum industries, utilities and consumer groups, many of the most difficult and important energy and conservation issues are not addressed.</p>
        <p>For example, proposals to set more stringent efficiency standards for automobiles and to expand the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, the Federal oil stockpile for war or other emergencies, were set aside before the vote.</p>
        <p>"This is a modest stride forward toward decreasing our dependence on imported oil," Representative John D. Dingell of Michigan, chairman of the House Energy and Commerce Committee and principal sponsor of the bill, said in an interview shortly before the vote. "It has very significant conservation provisions and modest provisions for increasing energy production."</p>
        <p>The legislation aims to stimulate important changes in the automobile industry by requiring Government fleets to begin replacing cars and trucks with vehicles run on alternative fuels like natural gas, batteries and solar power. By setting stronger efficiency standards for buildings and electrical appliances, the bill would eventually affect the utility bills of consumers in many states.</p>
        <p>The bill aims to increase solar, wind, geothermal and other renewable sources by providing Federal incentives for producers of electricity from such sources. It also provides incentives for joint ventures between the Government and private industry to try to make renewable energy technologies commercially viable.</p>
        <p>It also grants at least a symbolic victory to the struggling nuclear power industry by speeding Federal studies of a potential nuclear waste depository in Nevada. And it combines into a single review the separate Nuclear Regulatory Commission licensing procedures for construction and operation. Although this would theoretically make it easier to get a license to operate a nuclear plant, lawmakers said other regulatory and financial obstacles are still likely to block or greatly delay the building of new plants for years. Lower Rates Possible</p>
        <p>Consumers in the New York area could eventually pay lower electricity bills under a provision that would revise Federal regulations of utilities. The bill would remove limitations on the growth of smaller independent producers by giving them access to transmission lines controlled by larger utilities.</p>
        <p>Representative Philip R. Sharp of Indiana, chairman of the Subcommittee on Energy and Power, predicted that if the House version survived the House-Senate conference committee, "it should bring competition to Con Ed from alternative producers."</p>
        <p>Business reaction to the bill varied widely. Smaller electric utilities saw opportunities for expansion. The natural gas industry expressed uneasiness with a new rule that prohibits gas-producing states from restricting production to keep prices high, but it was happy with another measure streamlining licensing for natural gas pipelines.</p>
        <p>Oil companies were unhappy with a provision in both House and Senate versions banning the issuance of new leases for offshore oil and gas development in many petroleum-rich areas of the outer continental shelf through 2002. But they were gratified that they succeeded with a strong lobbying effort to tear out of the bill a proposal to force them to contribute a portion of their oil to the Strategic Petroleum Reserve. Gain for Nuclear Lobby</p>
        <p>Nuclear power lobbyists called the bill their biggest victory in Congress since the Three Mile Island accident 14 years ago.</p>
        <p>Phillip Bayne, president of the United States Council for Energy Awareness, a nuclear power lobby group, said the House "put America on a new course toward a cleaner, more secure energy future."</p>
        <p>Environmentalists generally prefer the House version because its provisions mandating greater efficiency in buildings and lighting and heating equipment are somewhat stronger, and because it would require the Government to buy back existing offshore oil-drilling leases in North Carolina, the Florida Keys and Alaska's Bristol Bay. But they were disappointed that neither the House nor the Senate included regulations that would require auto companies to increase fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>"This is half a good energy bill," said Daniel Becker, a lawyer for the Sierra Club. "It has a gaping hole where more efficient cars should be." White House Rebuffed</p>
        <p>Like the Senate, the House refused to endorse the centerpiece of the White House energy strategy: permitting oil drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge. But the Administration is expected to endorse the legislation anyway, because it likes other provisions.</p>
        <p>Nevada's two Democratic Senators, Richard H. Bryan and Harry M. Reid, have threatened to block final passage of the energy legislation with a filibuster if a provision is included that lets the Energy Department override Nevada laws to determine if the Yucca Mountain storage site is suitable for the disposal of high-grade nuclear waste.</p>
        <p>But House leaders said privately that they would work to make sure the legislation would not include any provisions that would jeopardize final passage in either chamber.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
