<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Taxing Carbon: Taxing Politics</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB1F3FF935A15751C0A964958260" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Taxing Carbon: Taxing Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Western European governments at the United Nations meetings on the environment this month are not just talking about the greenhouse effect, they are on the verge of doing something about it. The catch, argue Alan Manne of Stanford University and Richard Richels of the Energy Power Research Insitute, the research arm of the electric power industry, is that part of what they are planning to do is likely to be self-defeating.</p>
        <p>That is not to say the plan, which could be put into effect as early as 1993, is necessarily foolish: There may be no better alternative for attracting a winning coalition of countries and interest groups within the European Community. But it does make plain there is more to coping with global greenhouse emissions than identifying least-cost abatement strategy and getting on with the job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Western European governments at the United Nations meetings on the environment this month are not just talking about the greenhouse effect, they are on the verge of doing something about it. The catch, argue Alan Manne of Stanford University and Richard Richels of the Energy Power Research Insitute, the research arm of the electric power industry, is that part of what they are planning to do is likely to be self-defeating.</p>
        <p>That is not to say the plan, which could be put into effect as early as 1993, is necessarily foolish: There may be no better alternative for attracting a winning coalition of countries and interest groups within the European Community. But it does make plain there is more to coping with global greenhouse emissions than identifying least-cost abatement strategy and getting on with the job.</p>
        <p>While Washington is still dithering about what to to and when, the pressure for a greenhouse fix in northern Europe -- notably Scandinavia, the Netherlands and Germany -- has become overwhelming. In December the European Community's energy and environment commissioners tentatively adopted a plan to tax energy in general, and nonrenewable carbon fuels in particular.</p>
        <p>The plan would phase in a tax on the carbon content of coal, lignite, natural gas and oil equivalent to $5 a barrel by the year 2000. There would also be a parallel tax of the same magnitude on all energy consumption.</p>
        <p>If something rings false here, you have a good ear. Carbon taxes make sense as an incentive because carbon dioxide emissions are the primary culprit in global warming. But why would taxing nuclear or hydropower help contain the greenhouse effect?</p>
        <p>No reason at all. Indeed, Mr. Manne and Mr. Richel, who pioneered the use of computer models to simulate the economic consequences of anti-warming policies, argue that the general energy tax would have a perverse effect, adding cost while actually reducing the net impact.</p>
        <p>Taxing carbon emissions, they note, induces both energy conservation and fuel switching. But taxing energy consumption as well reduces the incentive to move from the most carbon-intensive fuels (coal and lignite) to natural gas or carbon-free nuclear fuel. Thus the European plan gets far less greenhouse bang for a buck than a carbon tax alone.</p>
        <p>The number of bucks at risk is nothing to sneeze about. Higher energy taxes can be expected to reduce economic growth because they encourage investment in energy-saving equipment that might otherwise have gone into productive capacity. The economists estimate that the combination tax would reduce Europe's gross domestic product by $20 billion in the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Why, then, make the inherently costly solution to greenhouse warming even costlier? One reason is that European countries vary in both their production and dependence on high-carbon fuels. Taxing energy as well as carbon would reduce the differential economic impact and perhaps check national divisions over greenhouse policy. Another is that a tax on carbon alone might put the bloom back in the cheeks of the nuclear industry -- a consequence that would undermine the green coalition that is anti-nuke as well as anti-greenhouse.</p>
        <p>The easiest political sell within Europe may not be the easiest in the other great carbon-emitting continent, North America. The United States uses more energy per dollar of output than Europe. Thus, it should not be surprising that the Manne-Richels simulation shows that a broad-based energy tax would be even more expensive in America than in Europe. And while the broad tax might serve the parallel function of blurring the impact on regions and industries, the fact that Europe would end up with an overall economic advantage would surely depreciate its political currency in the United States.</p>
        <p>All this suggests that the political perils in attempting a single global anti-warming strategy exceed the benefits. It probably makes more sense to negotiate national commitments to emissions targets -- an X percent reduction in Y years -- and to leave it to individual countries to choose the means to the agreed end.</p>
        <p>Negotiated emissions limits would also open the door to an approach that many economists believe would sharply reduce the total cost of taming global warming: international emissions trading. Europe might, for example, find it cheaper to pay the Soviet Union to shut down coal-fired power plants than to save an equivalent amount of carbon emissions by, say, investing in more fuel-efficient cars. Or America might forgive Brazilian debt in return for a commitment to stop the deforestation of the Amazon.</p>
        <p>None of this, of course, addresses the murky scientific and economic issues of how much global warming is too much. But the world -- well, parts of the world -- are in no mood to wait for clearer answers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
