<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. CHIEF CHARTS DEFENSE OF NATURE</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOUTROS-GHALI, BOUTROS (SEC GEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D6163AF937A35755C0A964958260" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. CHIEF CHARTS DEFENSE OF NATURE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali of the United Nations opened the Earth Summit today by appealing to the nations of the world to embark on an era of "new collective security" by redirecting military spending toward environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Urging nations to draw from their defense budgets to prevent damage to the ecological capital on which the security of future generations depends, Mr. Boutros-Ghali said that the concept of world security was becoming less and less a military matter and "instead, is acquiring an economic and ecological dimension."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali of the United Nations opened the Earth Summit today by appealing to the nations of the world to embark on an era of "new collective security" by redirecting military spending toward environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Urging nations to draw from their defense budgets to prevent damage to the ecological capital on which the security of future generations depends, Mr. Boutros-Ghali said that the concept of world security was becoming less and less a military matter and "instead, is acquiring an economic and ecological dimension."</p>
        <p>He told delegates from 178 countries that the Rio meeting, formally called the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development, might be remembered in history as the time when humans realized that "nature no longer exists in the classic sense of the term" but that, instead, "henceforth nature lies within the hands of man."</p>
        <p>More than 100 heads of state or government are to attend the last two days of the 12-day meeting, making it the largest summit gathering in history. Germany Counters U.S. Stance</p>
        <p>Not long after the Secretary General spoke, Germany announced that it would counter the position of the United States and sign a treaty to protect the world's biological riches, one of the twin pillars of the summit meeting. Canada made the same announcement on Monday, and there were reports that Britain was preparing to do so as well. Britain has had strong reservations about some aspects of the treaty, but Prime Minister John Major was said to be under strong pressure from environmentalists at home.</p>
        <p>The German and Canadian announcements and a British decision to follow suit could be the first steps in isolating the United States on the issue.</p>
        <p>The biodiversity treaty gained another important supporter today when India announced that it would sign. It also said it would support the other pact to be signed here, one aimed at stabilizing atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide, methane and other heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>India was a leader of the developing countries in negotiations on both treaties, and there had been doubts about whether it would sign since it has not yet signed an international accord on protection of the earth's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The Indian decision to sign "may be the most important thing that's happened here so far," said Michael Oppenheimer, senior scientist of the Environmental Defense Fund, a private advocacy group. Backers of the climate treaty were predicting that more than the required 50 signatures would be obtained in Rio to put the treaty provisionally in force. It is to be presented for signature on Thursday, the biodiversity treaty on Friday.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups were lobbying hard for the biodiversity treaty, describing it as a breakthrough in the worldwide attempt to contain human destruction of natural ecosystems and habitats that, some scientists fear, could result in the extinction of a quarter of the planet's plant, animal and microbial species in the next half century.</p>
        <p>The treaty would require signers to consider the preservation of species as well as economics in their development decisions. The defection of many industrialized countries would cripple the treaty because they would provide the money to make it work.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, the head of the American delegation, arrived in Rio proclaiming the protection of the world's forests as his Government's primary objective for the summit meeting. President Bush announced last week that the United States would provide $150 million next year as a down payment on additional aid to developing countries in preserving their forests. The Americans say their focus advances the general aims of the two Earth Summit treaties because forests absorb carbon dioxide and contain the richest ecosystems.</p>
        <p>But Ting Wen Lian, a Malaysian delegate, has said in no uncertain terms that the developing countries will tolerate no infringement on their right to use their forests as they see fit. Malaysia, whose economy depends heavily on logging, has been a leader of the developing countries on the forest issue. A Debate on Forestry</p>
        <p>The battle is to be joined here in a debate over a set of principles to guide world forestry, with the United States advocating that the conference call for the future negotiation of a binding forest treaty. Many developing countries strongly resist the idea.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said today that if the biodiversity treaty had been restricted to conservation matters, "we would have signed it."</p>
        <p>The United States decided not to sign on grounds that the treaty fails to give adequate patent protection to American companies that transfer technology to developing countries, that it leaves unclear the way in which money would be transferred from North to South and that it tries to regulate genetically engineered materials, the production of which is a field in which the United States leads.</p>
        <p>The treaty leaves the amount of money to be determined by the conference of the parties to the agreement. If more developing countries than rich ones were to ratify it, as is possible, they would hold the majority vote and could, for example, require developed countries to put up more money than their domestic politics or policies would allow.</p>
        <p>Other industrialized countries expressed unease with the financing provision, and there was talk that many of them would follow the United States in rejecting the treaty. But the announcements by Canada and Germany appeared to blunt whatever momentum the treaty's opponents had brought to the summit meeting.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
