<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY NEWS: Inside the Global Greenhouse; Woodman, Spare That CO2 Eater</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND ELECTRIC SYSTEM</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF133EF937A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY NEWS: Inside the Global Greenhouse; Woodman, Spare That CO2 Eater</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Electric utilities looking for ways to recapture the carbon dioxide that their plants pump into the atmosphere have bought tropical rain forests in order to preserve them, or have planted new trees. But the New England Electric System announced a new approach yesterday. The utility plans to pay lumber companies to work more gently.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe that carbon dioxide, which is produced when fuel is burned, is helping to create a global greenhouse, although they disagree about the speed or importance of climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Electric utilities looking for ways to recapture the carbon dioxide that their plants pump into the atmosphere have bought tropical rain forests in order to preserve them, or have planted new trees. But the New England Electric System announced a new approach yesterday. The utility plans to pay lumber companies to work more gently.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe that carbon dioxide, which is produced when fuel is burned, is helping to create a global greenhouse, although they disagree about the speed or importance of climate change.</p>
        <p>Still, with European contries discussing the imposition of a "carbon tax," many companies that fear that such taxes may someday apply to themselves are exploring ways to recycle carbon, a process that trees carry out naturally by absorbing carbon dioxide and using the carbon as a raw material for wood.</p>
        <p>The thinking behind programs like New England Electric's is that because the earth has only one atmosphere, it does not matter where the carbon dioxide is produced or absorbed, as long as it is absorbed somewhere. It's a zero-sum game, global greenhouse-wise.</p>
        <p>New England Electric serves more than 1.2 million customers in three states and gets 40 percent of its power from coal, a prodigious producer of carbon dioxide. As part of a pilot project the utility will pay $450,000 to Innoprise, a forest products company in Sabah, Malaysia, to keep 300,000 to 600,000 tons of carbon dioxide in the trees instead of in the air.</p>
        <p>Innoprise will continue to produce tropical hardwood, between 2.5 million to 4 million cubic meters a year as part of the worldwide market of 90 million cubic meters. But on about 2 square miles, or 5 percent of its annual harvest area, it will strive to minimize what is known in forestry as "residual stand damage" (what the Pentagon would call collateral damage).</p>
        <p>"Maybe 10 percent of the trees in a forest are marketable, but to get that 10 percent, they destroy 40 to 50 percent of the forest -- sometimes higher," said R. Peter Calvert, the utility's principal fuels planner. Workers simply cut what they want, without regard to the other trees, he said, adding, "It's like being selective with a meat cleaver."</p>
        <p>Damage can be reduced by more than half, by cutting the vines off the tree crowns before they are felled, to avoid bringing down neighboring trees, and practicing "directional felling," so a tree does not break a neighbor as it falls. And if logging roads are better planned, there will be less erosion and less pollution of local rivers.</p>
        <p>The work will be monitored by the Rainforest Alliance, a nonprofit organization in New York. Richard Donovan, director of the alliance's timber project, said the logging company would also send foresters into the woods to mark the trees to be harvested, sparing those that are too small and leaving big ones to reseed the area.</p>
        <p>The result, Mr. Donovan said, will be a better forest when the loggers return for a second round, 15 to 30 years later.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
