<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playing It Safe; The Paralysis of No-Pain Politics</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="522576"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, H ROSS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TSONGAS, PAUL E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DF113AF93AA25757C0A964958260" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playing It Safe; The Paralysis of No-Pain Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In politics, 1992 seems to be the year of the ostrich. Most politicians are hiding their heads in the sand rather than addressing fundamental problems facing the country. And the few who raise the central issues do so at their peril.</p>
        <p>Americans in the past have often put off action on difficult political problems. But what is different nowadays is that basic questions are not just going unresolved, they are hardly being discussed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In politics, 1992 seems to be the year of the ostrich. Most politicians are hiding their heads in the sand rather than addressing fundamental problems facing the country. And the few who raise the central issues do so at their peril.</p>
        <p>Americans in the past have often put off action on difficult political problems. But what is different nowadays is that basic questions are not just going unresolved, they are hardly being discussed.</p>
        <p>President Bush and Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas, who is close to locking up the Democratic Presidential nomination, and even Ross Perot, the industrialist who is considering running for President as an independent, are ducking problems for which they cannot offer painless solutions. Congress is generally avoiding them too.</p>
        <p>The one Presidential candidate who suggested that bitter medicine might be necessary, Paul E. Tsongas, fell by the wayside after the first month of primaries. Mr. Clinton savaged Mr. Tsongas in advertisements and speeches because the former Massachusetts Senator had advocated measures that would gradually raise the gasoline tax and reduce Social Security payments to the wealthiest. His stated goal was to restrain the vast consumption of fossil fuels and reduce the deficit.  Over Consuming</p>
        <p>Most politicians of both parties acknowledge that these are grave problems. Energy consumption per person in the United States is about double what it is in Europe and Japan. Almost half of the oil used in the United States is imported, up from just over one-quarter in 1985. Over-consumption is harming the environment, and the reliance on foreign oil is against the country's political, diplomatic and economic interests.</p>
        <p>As for the budget deficit, at close to $400 billion this year, it is far and away the highest ever. The deficit will force the next generation to pay for today's profligacy.</p>
        <p>But solutions to these problems would require some sacrifice from voters. Controlling energy usage would probably require that people change their driving habits and pay more for gasoline, which is now cheaper in the United States than bottled water.</p>
        <p>Cutting the budget deficit would mean lower payments to the middle class or higher taxes, or both. About $700 billion, half the Federal budget, is now being spent on so-called entitlement programs that pay benefits to everyone who meets eligibility standards regardless of the total cost. Of this, only about one dollar in six goes to the poor. Most of the money is for Social Security, Medicare, farm supports and other payments that are awarded regardless of how well off the beneficiary is. But asking middle-class voters to relinquish some of their benefits seems to be out of the question.</p>
        <p>Senator Warren B. Rudman, a New Hampshire Republican who has announced that he will not seek re-election because of his frustration over Congress's inability to confront the deficit, said such issues have lawmakers ducking, fearing opponents' exploitation.</p>
        <p>"It has become increasingly easy," said Mr. Rudman in an interview, "to destroy a fine legislator with a series of very tightly drawn negative commercials."</p>
        <p>Representative Leon E. Panetta, the California Democrat who heads the House budget panel, said the problem of avoiding difficult subjects had worsened over the years. "Twenty years ago, the public expected discussion of the tough issues," he said. "But the Ronald Reagan legacy was not to tell people about what sacrifices have to be made but always to deliver good news and stick to a simple, 30-second message."</p>
        <p>Few politicians today would dare utter John F. Kennedy's line about asking not what your country can do for you. Seven senators and more than 45 representatives have announced they will not run for re-election this year, and many cite disillusionment with a political system that accomplishes so little of value. To be sure, some who spoke this way, like Senator Tim Wirth, a 52-year-old Colorado Democrat, faced such tough races in November that they might well have lost. Others, like Representative Vin Weber, a 39-year-old Republican from Minnesota, were embarrassed by large numbers of overdrafts on their House bank account.</p>
        <p>But some departing lawmakers are giving up safe seats, and the anguish in their voices is unmistakable. Senator Rudman, 61, is a case in point. "The system, the Government, this country, have become fundamentally flawed," he said. "Presidents and Congresses, Democrats and Republicans, have been unwilling to explain to the American people that there is no such thing as a free lunch. I do not want to be a part of this any longer."</p>
        <p>This country has a knack for skirting big issues. The historian James MacGregor Burns has observed that the necessary steps against slavery that were apparent in the 1840's and 1850's were finally taken at a devastating price in the 1860's. The social welfare measures of the New Deal probably should have been adopted in the 1900's. Involvement with allies in collective security came after World War II instead of after World War I.</p>
        <p>But slavery, social welfare and collective security were matters of political debate long before they were acted on. In the campaign four years ago, the rising number of savings and loan failures, now recognized as the worst financial disaster since the Great Depression, was all but ignored by Mr. Bush, his opponent, Michael S. Dukakis, and those running for Congress.</p>
        <p>Even today, politicians refuse to face up to the matter. Congress left for its two-week spring break without appropriating essential additional money for the savings and loan rescue. Lawmakers will have to allocate the money eventually, but they seemed to feel that if they put it off, they will not have to explain it to their constituents during the recess. The delay could increase the ultimate cost of the bailout by $200 million.</p>
        <p>To take another example, economists and political scientists almost without exception believe that the country allocates too great a share of resources to the old and too little to the young. About one child in five in the United States is growing up in poverty; it is about one in 10 for the elderly. But the Federal Government spends about 10 times as much for each person over 65 as it does for each person under 18. The Republican staff of the House Budget Committee has calculated that after inflation, Federal expenditures on children -- for education, health care and other programs -- fell by 4 percent from 1978 to 1987, as spending on the elderly, mostly for Social Security and Medicare, rose by 52 percent.</p>
        <p>Much of the public money spent on children comes from state and local governments -- for public schools, for instance. But social policy experts say this does not make up for the disparity in Federal expenditures.</p>
        <p>Politicians may agree that a change is needed. But nothing happens. Old people vote and children do not.</p>
        <p>Presumably, the time will someday be ripe to deal with issues like the deficit, energy and the needs of children, but based on the election campaign so far, that time is not at hand. "Short of a crisis," said Robert D. Reischauer, director of the Congressional Budget Office, "it's hard for people to look at immediate, certain pain and accept that for uncertain gains in the future."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
