<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; A Decline and Fall in the Northwest</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KITTREDGE, WILLIAM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HOLE IN THE SKY (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">BiographyReview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED9163AF93BA35755C0A964958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; A Decline and Fall in the Northwest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hole in the Sky  A Memoir  By William Kittredge  238 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $20.</p>
        <p>Confronted with the title of William Kittredge's bitter and biting memoir, "Hole in the Sky," one thinks first of the ozone layer. This is probably not unintended on the author's part, for the hell that this book envisions for the future of America's Northwest is framed in ecological terms.</p>
        <p>Yet what Mr. Kittredge specifically means by his title is twofold. In the first sense, Hole in the Sky is a ceremonial entrance through a totem pole to the family lodge that members of the Tsimshian Indian tribe, of British Columbia, believed was occupied by all their people, living or not, "the dead at least to the extent that they were remembered by anyone." Mr. Kittredge adds: "It is a lovely notion, the space inside the house connecting to the landscape of communal imagination, the actual place bound together with story and recollection."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hole in the Sky  A Memoir  By William Kittredge  238 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $20.</p>
        <p>Confronted with the title of William Kittredge's bitter and biting memoir, "Hole in the Sky," one thinks first of the ozone layer. This is probably not unintended on the author's part, for the hell that this book envisions for the future of America's Northwest is framed in ecological terms.</p>
        <p>Yet what Mr. Kittredge specifically means by his title is twofold. In the first sense, Hole in the Sky is a ceremonial entrance through a totem pole to the family lodge that members of the Tsimshian Indian tribe, of British Columbia, believed was occupied by all their people, living or not, "the dead at least to the extent that they were remembered by anyone." Mr. Kittredge adds: "It is a lovely notion, the space inside the house connecting to the landscape of communal imagination, the actual place bound together with story and recollection."</p>
        <p>In the second sense, a hole in the sky "is the simple emptiness we may take as a modernist idea of God." From the first hole to the second is the journey that Mr. Kittredge traces in his memoir. It is, obviously enough, a story of decline and fall.</p>
        <p>In the early 20th century, the author's grandfather developed an enormous cattle ranch in Klamath and Lake Counties, Oregon, in part of the sagebrush desert known as the Great Basin, which extends from Oregon into Nevada and California and is ringed by mountains where snows accumulate. Years later, his son, the author's father, built a 17-mile canal, drained the ranch's swampland and planted enough acres in oats to make a fortune. Grandfather and father thought the land was theirs, the author suggests. They believed they were building an empire.</p>
        <p>But in their hardness and ambition, Mr. Kittredge laments, his forebears lost their sense of the connectedness of things, their Hole in the Sky in the Tsimshian sense. And he and his generation inherited a curse on the land that he sees in Faulknerian terms. "In a family as unchurched as ours there was only one sacred story, and that was the one we told ourselves every day, the one about work and property and ownership, which is sad. We had lost track of stories like the one which tells us the world is to be cherished as if it exists inside our own skin. We were heedless people in a new country; we came and went in a couple of generations. But we plowed a lot of ground while we were there."</p>
        <p>Onto this lamentable history Mr. Kittredge splatters what he sees as his own abysmal failures. He married and had children heedlessly. He joined the Air Force to avoid infantry combat in Korea, "where I might die a meaningless and premature death."</p>
        <p>When he got out of the Air Force, he went back to his family ranch because, he insists, he wanted to avoid reality. Then, in 1961, he stared into the void, heard the fearful hum of his own life's meaninglessness, and descended into liquor and random sexual encounters. His wife left and took the children, and he lost his vocation as a rancher. Yet finally, out of these smoking ruins he rescued the career as a writer of which he had always dreamed. And he published two collections of stories, "The van Gogh Field" and "We Are Not in This Together"; a book of essays, "Owning It All," and the present memoir.</p>
        <p>It is told in a rugged prose-poetry that catches the wild character of the Great Basin terrain. "You could voyage into that faraway country and try sitting quiet alongside a seep spring deep in the hidden backlands, and study the singular beauty at the heart of a desert flower while long-legged insects walk the surface tension of the water. Your concern with the passage of time might ease, you might be inclined to attempt the slow day-to-day dance of creatures."</p>
        <p>But a reader keeps wondering what exactly went wrong with the author's life. He blames himself for everything. In a small but typical example, he describes how, as a child, he started whimpering and made a scene when an alcoholic uncle sitting next to him at dinner removed his false teeth and set them down to dry, "inextricably tangled with long strings of bright green spinach." His retrospective judgment of himself is harsh: "what a fool of a child I must have been."</p>
        <p>This seems extreme to the point of a perverse form of self-indulgence.  What child wouldn't be upset by such an incident? Once you start asking such questions of "Hole in the Sky," it's difficult to stop. Who doesn't marry and have children in relative innocence? Who wouldn't have gone back to a thriving family enterprise and tried to carry on the pattern of life that one had grown up with? Which Americans alive today are not living with the consequences of their forefathers' determination to tame the earth and build empires upon it? And who can seriously blame those ancestors for carrying out the manifest destiny for which history had prepared them?</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is a fault in most of us not to rail against the broader history that produced us. In a way, it is refreshing not to hear Mom and Dad blamed for one's troubles. Or the bad baby-sitter. Or even the wicked stepmother. But still, there is a huge hole in "Hole in the Sky." In the end, Mr. Kittredge condemns himself so strenuously that he has no energy left to understand himself. The result is a life without true psychology, and a world in which people are guilty of history before they have even the choice of failing their lives.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
