<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CHEMICAL A FACTOR IN MALE IMPOTENCE</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="499170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PENIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITRIC OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMPOTENCE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND JOURNAL OF MEDICINE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAJFER, JACOB (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DF1030F93AA35752C0A964958260" item-length="860" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CHEMICAL A FACTOR IN MALE IMPOTENCE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAKESLEE, SANDRA</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers say they have found the physiological explanation for the vast majority of cases of male impotence, a failure to produce a simple chemical that controls a wide variety of biological functions.</p>
        <p>The chemical, nitric oxide, initiates a series of events that cause the penis to become engorged with blood and remain erect, said Dr. Jacob Rajfer, a professor of urology at the University of California at Los Angeles who made the discovery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers say they have found the physiological explanation for the vast majority of cases of male impotence, a failure to produce a simple chemical that controls a wide variety of biological functions.</p>
        <p>The chemical, nitric oxide, initiates a series of events that cause the penis to become engorged with blood and remain erect, said Dr. Jacob Rajfer, a professor of urology at the University of California at Los Angeles who made the discovery.</p>
        <p>Defects in the nitric oxide system of the penis cause blood to leak out, which accounts for 7 million to 8 million of the 10 million cases of impotence among American men, he said. Improved Diagnosis Likely</p>
        <p>The finding will help urologists develop better methods for diagnosing impotence and may lead to new kinds of treatments, experts said, but it is not expected to lead to a pill that would cure the problem.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rajfer's research is described in today's issue of The New England Journal of Medicine.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Kessler, an associate professor of urology at Stanford University, called the research "an important piece in the overall process of how an erection is mediated," but added, "I don't know that it will be all that useful clinically, compared to what we have now."</p>
        <p>Medications injected directly into the penis are extremely popular for treating impotence, Dr. Kessler said, "but what you'd really like is a pill."</p>
        <p>The new research will not help make such a pill feasible, said Dr. Tom Lue, an associate professor of urology at the University of California at San Francisco, but it may lead to other kinds of treatment, like a removable patch that could be placed on a penis to bring on an erection.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rajfer said nitric oxide is emerging as one of the most powerful known biological substances.</p>
        <p>More familiar as a primary component of smog and acid rain, nitric oxide is produced in tiny amounts for fractions of a second throughout the body. The brain uses it to send messages and store memories. The immune system uses it to kill invading bacteria. And when it touches the muscles that encircle blood vessels, the muscles relax instantly.</p>
        <p>It was the latter observation that led Dr. Rajfer, an expert on impotence, to wonder if nitric oxide played a role in penile erections.</p>
        <p>An erection begins with a brain signal that travels down the spinal cord and into the penis along a special set of nerves, Dr. Rajfer said. These nerves make connections with the blood vessels and the smooth muscles of the penis.</p>
        <p>The smooth muscles are usually constricted, Dr. Rajfer said, keeping the penis flaccid. But when the smooth muscles relax, the blood vessels open and blood pours into spaces inside the penis. The rise in pressure blocks the veins that normally drain the penis, keeping it engorged.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rajfer took penis muscle from a patient who suffered a traumatic injury and found that it was similar to the smooth muscles in the major arteries of the body. Then, while walking down a corridor at the U.C.L.A. Medical Center, he saw a sign on a door: vascular pharmacology laboratory.</p>
        <p>"I walked in and asked, 'What are you guys doing?' " Dr. Rajfer said. "They said they worked on smooth muscle relaxation and had just discovered that nitric oxide is what makes smooth muscles relax."</p>
        <p>Joining forces, the two teams found that nitric oxide induces penis muscles to relax in rabbits, promoting erections.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lue said at least half of the nitric oxide is produced in the smooth lining of the blood vessels and diffuses to adjacent smooth muscles to make them relax. Nerve endings seem to make the rest of the nitric oxide, he said, adding that this explains why an erection can be lost when the mind wanders. Nerve signals from the brain no longer reach the penis, nitric oxide is no longer produced and the muscles contract, draining the penis of blood.</p>
        <p>Dr. Louis J. Ignarro, a professor of pharmacology at U.C.L.A. who collaborated on the research, said the findings shed light on why certain drugs injected into the penis achieve erections.</p>
        <p>Tens of thousands of men in the United States routinely give themselves such injections with one of four drugs, he said. The drugs, papavarine, phentolamine, prostaglandin E1 and nitroprusside, are generic compounds that work by raising nitric oxide levels or relaxing smooth muscle through other pathways.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lue said the the major cause of impotence is failure of the muscles to relax because of insufficient nitric oxide production, perhaps brought on by natural aging of the enzyme systems that produce the chemical in the penis.</p>
        <p>By injecting themselves at the base of the penis with a drug that relaxes those muscles, men can bring on an erection for a half hour or longer. If the drugs were taken orally, he said, all the blood vessels in the body would dilate and the man would pass out.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ignarro said that because of various side effects about half of all patients stop injecting themselves after a year or so. For this reason, drug companies are looking for ways to put "nitric oxide donors" on patches that can be placed on the penis, he said, adding, "It would be a spectacular treatment for impotence."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
