<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="524652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D9173AF93AA15757C0A964958260" item-length="1050" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-10  A NEW ORDER IN KABUL</p>
        <p>The leader of a coalition of victorious rebel groups swept into the Afghan capital, announcing the creation of an Islamic republic and declaring amnesty for everyone except the former President, Najibullah.  A1  FEAR AND OPTIMISM IN MYANMAR</p>
        <p>Everything is shifting in Myanmar's Government, but the Burmese people are not convinced the changes are real, lasting or significant.  A3  ISRAEL IS ADAMANT ON TALKS</p>
        <p>Israel says it won't take part in regional talks as long as the U.S. insists that Palestinians from outside the West Bank and the Gaza Strip be allowed to attend.  A6  MUSICAL SEATS IN GERMAN CABINET</p>
        <p>Members of Parliament from the German Free Democratic Party overrode the choice by party leaders and selected Justice Minister Klaus Kinkel to replace Hans-Dietrich Genscher as Foreign Minister. Housing Minister Irmgard Schwaetzerhad been nominated by the party leadership.  A5  PANAMA'S ZIGZAG RECOVERY</p>
        <p>Traffic is heavy, construction is thriving, but so are unemployment and crime in the years after the U.S. invasion of Panama.  A6  AMMUNITION FOR LABOR PARTY</p>
        <p>As Israel's elections approach, a report that accuses the ruling Likud Party of waste, mismanagement and corruption is likely to become campaign ammunition.  A7  THE ATROPHY OF ECONOMIC MUSCLE</p>
        <p>In the new economic order, the U.S. has less to flex than in its days as a financial superhero.  A8  WEAPONS AGREEMENT REACHED</p>
        <p>Four former Soviet lands have reached an agreement that will expedite the ratification of the strategic arms reduction treaty.  A9</p>
        <p>Bosnians find little to trust in the new Yugoslavia.  A10  STEP IN THE GLOBAL WARMING WAR</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration has made an offer to curb the increase in gases that contribute to global warming, but still refuses to join in a treaty to stabilize 1990 levels.  A10  National A14-22, D23-24  CLINTON KEEPS ROLLING</p>
        <p>Governor Clinton gained a commanding victory in the Democratic primary in Pennsylvania.A1  WOMAN TO CHALLENGE SPECTER</p>
        <p>Lynn Yeakel, a fund-raiser for women's charities and a political newcomer, scored an upset victory in Democratic Senate primary in Pennsylvania.  A1</p>
        <p>Woman in the News: Capturing the anger from the Thomas hearings.  A19</p>
        <p>News analysis: Pennsylvania's voters confirmed two trends.  A18</p>
        <p>A California poll found Perot even with Bush, ahead of Clinton.  A19  STEEP TAB AT G.O.P. DINNER</p>
        <p>A dinner featuring President Bush raised $7 million for the Republican Party, but it could create political problems for the President.  A19  THE WAR ON REGULATIONS</p>
        <p>In some cases, the Administration has cut red tape in the last three months with its 90-day moratorium on new Federal regulations and review of existing rules. In other cases, the red tape has merely been fluttered by political hot air. Either way, his current posture toward Federal rule-making marks a full-circle turnabout by the President.  A1  A TRULY PERSONAL PHONE NUMBER</p>
        <p>People who want to be reached anywhere they go -- at home, the office, a friend's residence or a vacation house -- can sign up with A.T.&amp;T. for a single telephone number. The service begins in June.  A1  HOUSE SPLIT GROWS OVER CHECKS</p>
        <p>Congressional Republicans said they wanted the House to turn over all bank records subpoenaed by the Justice Department.  D23</p>
        <p>House Republicans opened a new initiative on domestic policy.  D23  EX-H.U.D. AIDE INDICTED</p>
        <p>Deborah Gore Dean, executive assistant to the Reagan Administration's Housing Secretary, was charged with accepting an illegal gratuity and making a false statement to the Senate.  A14  OF TWO KILLINGS</p>
        <p>From the start, a brutal attack on a suburban couple in a deserted Milwaukee parking lot last week had a sad and familiar ring to it, one that immediately recalled the fatal shooting of Carol Stuart in Boston three years ago. But this time the response of the authorities was decidedly different.  A14  AFTER QUAKES, NOT ALL SHAKE</p>
        <p>The recent series of strong earthquakes at both the north end and the south end of California has stirred a bad case of jitters in some residents and inspired in others the sort of insouciance that keeps millions of people living atop an unstable fault line that periodically shifts and shudders.  A14  Lawmakers issued a warning on nonprescription-drug labels.  D24  The test model of a new Stealth fighter crashed in California.  D24  An insurance company paid $157 to settle a sex-bias case.  A22 Education Page B8  Maharish International University mixes meditation and courses.  Metropolitan Digest, B1 Business Digest, D1  Obituaries D24-25  FRANCIS BACON, ARTIST</p>
        <p>The London-based painter, whose abstract images of psychological and physical brutality made him one of the most exalted, and most disliked, postwar artists, died in Madrid at the age of 82.  A1  OLIVIER MESSIAEN, COMPOSER</p>
        <p>One of the most influential French composers of the 20th century, he drew on such diverse sources as bird song, Indian and Balinese rhythmic modes, and more conventional Western forms, in a career of more than 60 years.  D24  The Living Section C1-12  Only nature makes truffles better than a chocolatier's.  C1  At lunch with Dolly Parton.  C1  There in the crystal ball, forecasters are thriving.  C1  The big stars go out to eat, but it's the caterer who shines.  C3  Wine Talk C8  Health Page C13  Personal Health: Different approaches to warding off rape.</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C15-20  Pat on back for Seville's elite.  C15  National Gallery names its new director.  C15  Film: A Ukrainian's metaphor for Chernobyl.  C15  Sports B9-15  Baseball: Cone loses no-hitter in 8th.  B9  Yanks beaten, 1-0.  B11  Basketball:Knicks top Pistons.  B9  Nets stay alive.  B9  Mahoney to coach St. John's.  B12  Editorials/Op-Ed A24-25  Editorials A24  Crazy on the House Bank. Dinkins and the silver lining. Movement in Myanmar. David C. Anderson: Guns. Letters A24  Anna Quindlen: Believing the children.  A25  Henry A. Waxman: The environmental pollution President.  A25  David Mura: Bashed in the U.S.A.  A25</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-10  A NEW ORDER IN KABUL</p>
        <p>The leader of a coalition of victorious rebel groups swept into the Afghan capital, announcing the creation of an Islamic republic and declaring amnesty for everyone except the former President, Najibullah.  A1  FEAR AND OPTIMISM IN MYANMAR</p>
        <p>Everything is shifting in Myanmar's Government, but the Burmese people are not convinced the changes are real, lasting or significant.  A3  ISRAEL IS ADAMANT ON TALKS</p>
        <p>Israel says it won't take part in regional talks as long as the U.S. insists that Palestinians from outside the West Bank and the Gaza Strip be allowed to attend.  A6  MUSICAL SEATS IN GERMAN CABINET</p>
        <p>Members of Parliament from the German Free Democratic Party overrode the choice by party leaders and selected Justice Minister Klaus Kinkel to replace Hans-Dietrich Genscher as Foreign Minister. Housing Minister Irmgard Schwaetzerhad been nominated by the party leadership.  A5  PANAMA'S ZIGZAG RECOVERY</p>
        <p>Traffic is heavy, construction is thriving, but so are unemployment and crime in the years after the U.S. invasion of Panama.  A6  AMMUNITION FOR LABOR PARTY</p>
        <p>As Israel's elections approach, a report that accuses the ruling Likud Party of waste, mismanagement and corruption is likely to become campaign ammunition.  A7  THE ATROPHY OF ECONOMIC MUSCLE</p>
        <p>In the new economic order, the U.S. has less to flex than in its days as a financial superhero.  A8  WEAPONS AGREEMENT REACHED</p>
        <p>Four former Soviet lands have reached an agreement that will expedite the ratification of the strategic arms reduction treaty.  A9</p>
        <p>Bosnians find little to trust in the new Yugoslavia.  A10  STEP IN THE GLOBAL WARMING WAR</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration has made an offer to curb the increase in gases that contribute to global warming, but still refuses to join in a treaty to stabilize 1990 levels.  A10  National A14-22, D23-24  CLINTON KEEPS ROLLING</p>
        <p>Governor Clinton gained a commanding victory in the Democratic primary in Pennsylvania.A1  WOMAN TO CHALLENGE SPECTER</p>
        <p>Lynn Yeakel, a fund-raiser for women's charities and a political newcomer, scored an upset victory in Democratic Senate primary in Pennsylvania.  A1</p>
        <p>Woman in the News: Capturing the anger from the Thomas hearings.  A19</p>
        <p>News analysis: Pennsylvania's voters confirmed two trends.  A18</p>
        <p>A California poll found Perot even with Bush, ahead of Clinton.  A19  STEEP TAB AT G.O.P. DINNER</p>
        <p>A dinner featuring President Bush raised $7 million for the Republican Party, but it could create political problems for the President.  A19  THE WAR ON REGULATIONS</p>
        <p>In some cases, the Administration has cut red tape in the last three months with its 90-day moratorium on new Federal regulations and review of existing rules. In other cases, the red tape has merely been fluttered by political hot air. Either way, his current posture toward Federal rule-making marks a full-circle turnabout by the President.  A1  A TRULY PERSONAL PHONE NUMBER</p>
        <p>People who want to be reached anywhere they go -- at home, the office, a friend's residence or a vacation house -- can sign up with A.T.&amp;T. for a single telephone number. The service begins in June.  A1  HOUSE SPLIT GROWS OVER CHECKS</p>
        <p>Congressional Republicans said they wanted the House to turn over all bank records subpoenaed by the Justice Department.  D23</p>
        <p>House Republicans opened a new initiative on domestic policy.  D23  EX-H.U.D. AIDE INDICTED</p>
        <p>Deborah Gore Dean, executive assistant to the Reagan Administration's Housing Secretary, was charged with accepting an illegal gratuity and making a false statement to the Senate.  A14  OF TWO KILLINGS</p>
        <p>From the start, a brutal attack on a suburban couple in a deserted Milwaukee parking lot last week had a sad and familiar ring to it, one that immediately recalled the fatal shooting of Carol Stuart in Boston three years ago. But this time the response of the authorities was decidedly different.  A14  AFTER QUAKES, NOT ALL SHAKE</p>
        <p>The recent series of strong earthquakes at both the north end and the south end of California has stirred a bad case of jitters in some residents and inspired in others the sort of insouciance that keeps millions of people living atop an unstable fault line that periodically shifts and shudders.  A14  Lawmakers issued a warning on nonprescription-drug labels.  D24  The test model of a new Stealth fighter crashed in California.  D24  An insurance company paid $157 to settle a sex-bias case.  A22 Education Page B8  Maharish International University mixes meditation and courses.  Metropolitan Digest, B1 Business Digest, D1  Obituaries D24-25  FRANCIS BACON, ARTIST</p>
        <p>The London-based painter, whose abstract images of psychological and physical brutality made him one of the most exalted, and most disliked, postwar artists, died in Madrid at the age of 82.  A1  OLIVIER MESSIAEN, COMPOSER</p>
        <p>One of the most influential French composers of the 20th century, he drew on such diverse sources as bird song, Indian and Balinese rhythmic modes, and more conventional Western forms, in a career of more than 60 years.  D24  The Living Section C1-12  Only nature makes truffles better than a chocolatier's.  C1  At lunch with Dolly Parton.  C1  There in the crystal ball, forecasters are thriving.  C1  The big stars go out to eat, but it's the caterer who shines.  C3  Wine Talk C8  Health Page C13  Personal Health: Different approaches to warding off rape.</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C15-20  Pat on back for Seville's elite.  C15  National Gallery names its new director.  C15  Film: A Ukrainian's metaphor for Chernobyl.  C15  Sports B9-15  Baseball: Cone loses no-hitter in 8th.  B9  Yanks beaten, 1-0.  B11  Basketball:Knicks top Pistons.  B9  Nets stay alive.  B9  Mahoney to coach St. John's.  B12  Editorials/Op-Ed A24-25  Editorials A24  Crazy on the House Bank. Dinkins and the silver lining. Movement in Myanmar. David C. Anderson: Guns. Letters A24  Anna Quindlen: Believing the children.  A25  Henry A. Waxman: The environmental pollution President.  A25  David Mura: Bashed in the U.S.A.  A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
