<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preserved in Ice, Meteorites Yield Rich History</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METEORS AND METEORITES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENOIT, PAUL H (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEARS, DEREK W G (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DD133FF931A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preserved in Ice, Meteorites Yield Rich History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE bottles washed up from the cosmic sea, meteorites bring to Earth tantalizing scraps of information about the early solar system, the composition of the Moon and Mars, the nature of stardust, and even, perhaps, the possibility of extraterrestrial life. But meteoritic information is written in a complex code that touches off as many debates as it settles.</p>
        <p>In a new round of debate, two scientists report evidence from Antarctica that a spray of meteorites struck Earth about 300,000 years ago after an asteroid broke up. Their conclusion reopens one of the more contentious issues in planetary science: whether or not meteorites found in Antarctica are somehow different from meteorites found elsewhere. If so, a peculiar group of Antarctic meteorites may have something important to say about how the solar system environment has changed over the passing millennia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE bottles washed up from the cosmic sea, meteorites bring to Earth tantalizing scraps of information about the early solar system, the composition of the Moon and Mars, the nature of stardust, and even, perhaps, the possibility of extraterrestrial life. But meteoritic information is written in a complex code that touches off as many debates as it settles.</p>
        <p>In a new round of debate, two scientists report evidence from Antarctica that a spray of meteorites struck Earth about 300,000 years ago after an asteroid broke up. Their conclusion reopens one of the more contentious issues in planetary science: whether or not meteorites found in Antarctica are somehow different from meteorites found elsewhere. If so, a peculiar group of Antarctic meteorites may have something important to say about how the solar system environment has changed over the passing millennia.</p>
        <p>Dr. Paul H. Benoit and Dr. Derek W. G. Sears of the cosmochemistry group at the University of Arkansas suggest that some peculiar meteorites recently collected in Antarctica came from an asteroid. The asteroid itself, they believe, broke up some eight million years earlier. The study so far has provided no hint of how large the asteroid was or why it broke up.</p>
        <p>Besides its bitter cold, Antarctic ice has another quality that makes it an ideal collecting trap for meteorites. When a meteorite hits one of Antarctica's great ice sheets it rapidly sinks below the surface to a depth at which glacial "rivers" constantly flow, some at speeds of several hundred feet a year. In some places, these glacial flows encounter rocky terrain features that force them upward. On reaching the surface, the flowing ice is exposed to the erosion of the continent's ferocious winds and the ice is swiftly worn away, leaving a surface so smooth and transparent that the ice beneath it looks dark blue.</p>
        <p>From beneath expanses of blue ice, like those near the Allan Hills and the Yamato Mountains, meteorites are swept up to the surface by ice streams. As the ice is worn away, the meteorites, of all different ages, collect on the surface in great numbers, some having spent up to a million years entombed in ice and virtually unchanged since the time they struck Earth.</p>
        <p>Each year, teams of scientists using snow tractors and aircraft with radar comb the ice fields for these meteorites, and Dr. Benoit said so many specimens have been found that the organization of data has become very complex. 10,000 Meteorites Found</p>
        <p>"During this last season alone, some 600 meteorites were harvested in Antarctica," Dr. Benoit said. "Meteorites give us a powerful tool for interpreting solar system history, and there seem to be plenty more where we've harvested thousands already."</p>
        <p>More than 10,000 meteorites have been gathered from Antarctica. They are generally much older than the sparser crop of meteorites found in other parts of the world. Analyses recently reported by Dr. Benoit and Dr. Sears in the journal Science suggest that some Antarctic meteorites are not just older but indeed significantly different from meteorites found elsewhere, and that one type of unusual meteorite probably came from a single asteroid.</p>
        <p>The meteorite shower studied by the University of Arkansas scientists apparently lasted 10,000 years, judging from the range of ages of the specimens collected, Dr. Benoit said in an interview. Although the bombardment was heavy and protracted, he said, its effects on life were probably minimal. Most of the meteorites were probably too small to cause extensive environmental damage. Technique Used in Study</p>
        <p>The destruction of the asteroid may have also produced meteorites large enough to have survived weathering even in temperate regions of the world. But they would not be easy to identify because the skins of these rocks from the sky would have eroded away, and the skin contains the needed information.</p>
        <p>Chemical and physical studies of meteorites can extract a surprising wealth of data about their history. Part of the Arkansas researchers' study made use of a technique called induced thermoluminescence, a variant of a test devised in the 1960's to determine the age of pottery and other archeological ceramics.</p>
        <p>In this test, heating a sample to a certain temperature causes it to emit a pulse of light that releases electronic energy stored from radioactive decay, cosmic rays or laboratory-made radiation. The intensity of this light is a measure of the energy stored -- and hence the age of an ancient ceramic object. The spectrum of the light pulse also contains clues to the mineral composition of the object. Meteorites' Unusual Feature</p>
        <p>The Antarctic meteorites on which Dr. Benoit focused were stony meteorites of a class known as H5 chondrites. These are commonly found in all parts of Earth, but some of the specimens found in Antarctica, he discovered, display a feature not found in meteorites anywhere else. That feature is the extraordinarily high temperature to which they must be heated before emitting a thermoluminescence light flash after having been charged with energy from laboratory radiation.</p>
        <p>Ordinary H5 chondrites glow brightly for a few seconds when heated to about 190 degrees Celsius (374 degrees Fahrenheit). But some Antarctic meteorites tested by the scientists glowed only when heated well above that temperature. The reason for the difference, the scientists believe, is based on differences in the mineral composition of the two groups.</p>
        <p>Dr. Benoit said he believed the unusual meteorites were distinguished from ordinary H5 chondrites by the extreme shock they must have sustained, causing disruptions in the crystal structure of one of their minerals, feldspar.</p>
        <p>Testing the meteorites for the radioactive transformation of isotopes of helium and neon, the scientists determined that the special H5 chondrites drifted through space for nearly eight million years after the breakup of the asteroid.</p>
        <p>Throughout that time the meteorites were bombarded by cosmic rays, one effect of which was to produce a radioactive element, chlorine 36, in their outer layers. Once they hit Earth they were shielded from cosmic rays, and no more of this isotope was produced. Since it is radioactive, the chlorine isotope then decays at a steady rate. By measuring the remaining amount of it in the meteorites, the scientists were able to estimate the time at which most of them hit Earth as 300,000 years ago. Reason for Far Older Age</p>
        <p>This age is much greater than the time similar meteorites could survive destruction by erosion in a temperate climate, and that may explain why none of the high-temperature thermoluminescent meteorites has ever been found outside Antarctica.</p>
        <p>Dr. Benoit concludes that the rate of meteorites hitting Earth and their types change from time to time, and that these changes deserve further study. But he acknowledges that his major premise, that Antarctic meteorites are different from those found elsewhere, is "accepted by only about half the scientists who have studied the question."</p>
        <p>One who does not is Dr. John Wasson of the University of California at Los Angeles. "My view," he said, "is that there is not a difference between Antarctic meteorites and those found elsewhere, if one examines meteorites of the same size." Apparent differences between the two groups are caused by skewed statistics rather than real effects, he suggests.</p>
        <p>Certainly, the uniquely efficient meteorite-collecting mechanism of the Antarctic ice sheet creates problems for statistical analysts, although the ice has yielded immensely important discoveries in recent years. Chunks of the Moon</p>
        <p>Among the meteorites found in Antarctica in the last 10 years are fragments of the Moon that were blasted loose by meteorite impacts and hurled earthward. Although identification of these rocks as lunar in origin was controversial at first, direct comparison of their mineral structure with that of lunar rocks collected by astronauts eventually laid all doubts to rest.</p>
        <p>Another group of Antarctic meteorites are believed by most scientists to have reached Earth from Mars, propelled by the impact of a meteorite.</p>
        <p>Although the Martian origin of some Antarctic meteorites cannot be proved until rock can be brought back from the planet itself for comparison, most scientists now believe that one class of meteorites almost certainly came from Mars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
