<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It Pays to Complain: Detroit's 'Secret Warranties'</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538103"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECALLS AND BANS OF PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GUARANTEES AND WARRANTIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAINTS AND PAINTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEFECTIVE PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTER FOR AUTO SAFETY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORD MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defective Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD8123AF930A15755C0A964958260" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It Pays to Complain: Detroit's 'Secret Warranties'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When an auto maker decides to repair defects no longer covered by warranty -- without directly notifying owners -- does this demonstrate good will or a cynical policy of trying to save money by compensating only those who complain?</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company, like other auto makers, has faced this issue before. Now a consumer advocacy group is accusing Ford of maintaining a "secret warranty" to cover what it says are a large number of defectively painted Ford full-size pickup trucks, the auto maker's best-selling model and one of the most popular vehicles of any kind sold in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When an auto maker decides to repair defects no longer covered by warranty -- without directly notifying owners -- does this demonstrate good will or a cynical policy of trying to save money by compensating only those who complain?</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company, like other auto makers, has faced this issue before. Now a consumer advocacy group is accusing Ford of maintaining a "secret warranty" to cover what it says are a large number of defectively painted Ford full-size pickup trucks, the auto maker's best-selling model and one of the most popular vehicles of any kind sold in the United States.</p>
        <p>The Center for Auto Safety, citing evidence provided by consumers, Ford documents and the testimony of a former Ford employee, said it would file a petition Tuesday asking the Federal Trade Commission to investigate and charge Ford with unfair and deceptive trade practices.</p>
        <p>The consumer organization charges that as many as 400,000 of the full-size pickups, built from 1985 through this year, have paint jobs that peel or fade. The problem seems to affect mostly blue, silver and gray pickups after they are a year or two old. Repainting a vehicle typically costs $1,000, implying a potential liability of almost half a billion dollars for Ford, the group said in its filing.</p>
        <p>Ford acknowledged that of its four million pickups on the road, some 250,000 have had paint problems of one kind or another, either repaired under warranty, repaired after the warranty expired or simply reported.  The auto maker also recognizes that "blue, gray and silver trucks do seem to have a higher rate of concern," said a spokesman, John Ochs. Those colors make up about a third of the four million pickups built since 1985.</p>
        <p>But Ford said many factors, from acid rain to bird droppings, might have caused the problems. The auto maker denied any "secret warranty." But Mr. Ochs said Ford was getting in touch with pickup owners to find out if they were satisfied "and to actively address their concerns."</p>
        <p>For Ford, the stakes could be greater than financial liability or a public relations black eye. American auto makers have worked doggedly to regain customers who defected to Japanese rivals because they were dissatisfied with the quality of domestic models. Beyond just improving the quality of their vehicles, the Big Three have spent heavily to assure that customers are satisfied, even after warranties expire.</p>
        <p>As a result, Ford in particular has been able to increase its market share to 24.5 percent through the first five months of this year from a low of 19.7 percent in 1981, while Japanese auto makers as a group have been losing share.</p>
        <p>Ford has spent billions of dollars to build successful models like the Taurus and Explorer, and hundreds of millions more on advertising to reinforce an impression that "Quality is Job One."</p>
        <p>But the Big Three have an uncanny knack for landing in imbroglios that portray them as anti-consumer, like the Pinto litigation of the 1970's. When an auto maker discovers a safety-related defect, it has little choice but to recall every affected vehicle by notifying owners directly. The Government can order recalls if auto makers drag their feet.</p>
        <p>But when safety is not compromised -- as in this case -- an auto maker may legally try to evade widespread notice that it is willing to pay for repairs.</p>
        <p>In 1988, for instance, after discovering that power steering units wore out prematurely on millions of its front-wheel-drive cars for model years 1982 through 1986, the General Motors Corporation extended the warranty on the power steering units to five years or 50,000 miles, from one year or 12,000 miles. It notified dealers and put out a press release, but did not write to owners, as it would have been obliged to in a safety recall.</p>
        <p>After a leak of internal documents to the press, the Toyota Motor Corporation acknowledged in 1988 that it had agreed to reimburse customers who complained for 41 components that were out of warranty but were failing at a high rate. But a Toyota spokesman denied the program constituted a secret warranty.</p>
        <p>In 1980 the F.T.C. required Ford to disclose a secret warranty on worn pistons in some Ford engines. The ruling expired in 1988, but Ford has said it continues to notify consumers of any warranty actions it is taking. Repainting Without Charge</p>
        <p>In this case, Ford seems to be spending prodigiously to compensate pickup truck owners with paint problems. Many Ford dealers and independent body shops chosen at random could cite numerous instances of paint problems affecting pickup trucks built starting in 1985. Other pickup brands had paint problems as well, they said, but Ford's seemed to be the most pervasive.</p>
        <p>"There definitely is a problem with the paint and it gets paid for" by Ford, said Ron Gutierrez, who works for the service department at McMahon Ford in St. Louis. Wayne Schilling, the service manager at McMahon Ford, said that peeling paint might be partly Ford's fault and partly the fault of consumers who do not follow prescribed maintenance procedures, like applying wax to their trucks. In any case, he said, "The gray gets real hot in the sun, it's a real bad color."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ochs, the Ford spokesman, said that in the mid-1980's Ford began substituting what it called an "E coat" for the normal primer that is applied to the surface of pickups before the paint. The E coat was meant to protect against corrosion, but it also caused certain colors to be negatively "affected by long-term exposure to ultraviolet light," he said.</p>
        <p>Kurt Chadwell, 27 years old, who worked from 1989 to 1991 as a field representative for customer service for Ford in the Los Angeles area, said he processed about 15 complaints a month of badly painted pickup trucks while working for Ford. Mr. Chadwell, who quit Ford to attend law school in 1991, and currently works as a legal intern at the Center for Auto Safety, said he provided information about his belief that Ford had a secret warranty to the attorneys general of five states.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
