<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Say Logging Of Vast Siberian Forest Could Foster Warming</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="503898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JOINT VENTURES AND CONSORTIUMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TAIGA FOREST (SIBERIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Siberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD1F3CF93BA15752C0A964958260" item-length="1525" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Say Logging Of Vast Siberian Forest Could Foster Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE forests of the Amazon and other tropical regions have been getting attention for some time, and understandably so. They are home to a disproportionate share of the world's living species, they absorb huge amounts of atmospheric carbon dioxide that would otherwise exert a big heating effect on the earth's climate and they are rapidly being destroyed.</p>
        <p>Less well known is the vast stretch of fir, larch, spruce and pine that girdles the continents at far northern latitudes and is known as the taiga.  The word is derived from the Russian, appropriately enough since the Siberian part of the taiga is the largest forest in the world, far larger than the Brazilian Amazon. At more than two million square miles, it would cover the entire continental United States excepting Alaska. Like the tropical forests, it is a major absorber of atmospheric carbon dioxide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE forests of the Amazon and other tropical regions have been getting attention for some time, and understandably so. They are home to a disproportionate share of the world's living species, they absorb huge amounts of atmospheric carbon dioxide that would otherwise exert a big heating effect on the earth's climate and they are rapidly being destroyed.</p>
        <p>Less well known is the vast stretch of fir, larch, spruce and pine that girdles the continents at far northern latitudes and is known as the taiga.  The word is derived from the Russian, appropriately enough since the Siberian part of the taiga is the largest forest in the world, far larger than the Brazilian Amazon. At more than two million square miles, it would cover the entire continental United States excepting Alaska. Like the tropical forests, it is a major absorber of atmospheric carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Now, with Russia economically devastated and hungry for hard currency as it converts to a market economy, environmentalists are raising fears that joint ventures between the Russians and American, Japanese or Korean timber companies could lead to extensive deforestation of the Siberian taiga. This, the environmentalists warn, could contribute significantly to global warming.</p>
        <p>If carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases continue to build up in the atmosphere at the present rate, the earth's average surface temperature will rise by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit in the next century with possibly catastrophic results, many scientists predict. The rate of buildup would presumably increase if Siberia were deforested.</p>
        <p>The possibility is raised in an article in the current issue of the British journal Nature by Dr. Armin Rosencranz and Antony Scott of the Pacific Energy and Resources Center in Sausalito, Calif., a nonprofit environmental research and education center that works with Russian environmentalists to defend the Siberian forests.</p>
        <p>The forests "have a large role to play in mitigating global warming," they wrote, emphasizing that this "must be communicated to the negotiators of international agreements" aimed at limiting or reversing the buildup of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Negotiators from 130 countries are to meet in New York next month in the fourth of five sessions aimed at producing a binding international convention on the control of heat-trapping gases. Participants say the session is crucial, since there is not much time left before the scheduled signing of the pact in June in Rio de Janeiro, and the United States and other industrial nations differ over whether to set specific targets for limiting carbon dioxide emissions.  Less attention has been given to the important role of deforestation in global warming, and particularly to the role of the taiga.</p>
        <p>Some forestry experts question whether large-scale logging will ever catch on in Siberia, given its inaccessibility, generally high costs and a short growing season for the regeneration of trees.</p>
        <p>But the pressures of economic survival in the former Soviet Union, and particularly in hard-pressed Siberia, are causing Russians to "look to natural resources for conversion into cash, and people in the United States, the West and Korea and Japan are waiting to use these natural resources," Dr. Rosencranz, the president of the Pacific Energy and Resources Center, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>He and Mr. Scott noted in the Nature article that the recent completion of a new Siberian railway helps make expansion of the timber industry possible. Thousands of people sent to Siberia to work on the railway are now jobless, they wrote, adding to the pressure to speed up development of other industries, like timber.</p>
        <p>The article asserted that the Louisiana-Pacific Corporation, the Georgia-Pacific Corporation and the Weyerhaeuser Company, three American timber giants, have begun negotiations to cut Siberian forests. Any agreements, the authors wrote, "will almost certainly increase the rate of logging." Weyerhaeuser, said Dr. Rosencranz, has built a large loading dock near Khabarovsk, a major Siberian city.</p>
        <p>The authors wrote also that Hyundai Inc., the South Korean conglomerate, "is said to have contracted to log roughly half a million acres" in eastern Siberia and that C. Itoh and Company, a Japanese concern, had already begun harvesting trees there.</p>
        <p>S. S. Chae, senior executive vice president of Hyundai Resources Development Company Ltd. of Seoul, confirmed that his company had entered into a joint venture to log the half-million acres and that the company was considering expanding its Siberian operations.</p>
        <p>C. Itoh imported 100,000 cubic meters of softwood logs from Siberia last year and has also invested in a "small-scale sawmill" in Siberia, said Yoshiharu Matsumoto, a spokesman for the company in Tokyo.</p>
        <p>Georgia-Pacific representatives have been to Siberia to investigate the long-term potential of the timber resource, but the company has not begun any joint-venture negotiations, said Sheila Weidman, a company spokeswoman. With 50 percent of the world's inventory of softwood, she said, Siberia could in time be a major competitor on the world market.</p>
        <p>But roads, railroads and other infrastructure necessary to develop Siberian forestry are insufficient, and the convertibility of the ruble is still a big question, she pointed out. For these reasons, she said, Georgia-Pacific sees the Siberian forests "as a possible opportunity well into the future but is not considering it in the short term at all."</p>
        <p>Similarly, Louisiana-Pacific has looked at the Siberian forests but has no present plans to exploit them, said Barry Lacter, a spokesman at the company headquarters in Portland, Ore.</p>
        <p>Weyerhaeuser has "explored the feasibility" of logging operations in territory of Khabarovsk, in eastern Siberia, and has considered how to ship wood out of the territory, said Scott Marshall, a spokesman in Tacoma, Wash. While "we're not doing anything yet," he said, it is possible the company will enter Siberia in the next 5 to 10 years. "Certainly," he said, "there is a likelihood that someone will.</p>
        <p>Despite interest from timber companies, "it's hard to see much happening in the next decade" in Siberian timbering, said Dr. Roger Sedjo, an expert in world forests at Resources for the Future, an independent research organization in Washington.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rosencranz and Mr. Scott acknowledge that short-term prospects for investment in Siberian timber might not be good because of economics, transporation difficulties, red tape, non-convertibility of the ruble and especially political instability and doubt about who will own and control the forests. But they insist that it is essential to insure that "the allure of hard currency and modern technology does not outweigh the long-term health of the forests." Difference With Tropics</p>
        <p>While recognizing the possibility of both local and global environmental damage, Dr. Sedjo pointed out some important differences between the taiga and tropical forests. In the tropics, he said, deforestation proceeds mostly because forests are being converted to agriculture and other forms of development in a region where population pressures are acute.</p>
        <p>By contrast, he said, unoccupied timberlands regenerate. In fact, he said, there has been a net gain in forest acreage in the heavily logged temperate regions of the Northern Hemisphere. Moreover, he said, trees converted to wood products like houses and furniture do not release carbon dioxide to the atmosphere as tropical forests do when they are burned. It is even likely, he said, that regenerating forests would remove more carbon dioxide from the atmosphere than the mature ones they replace, since young, growing trees absorb the gas at a higher rate.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rosencranz and Mr. Scott argue that regeneration would be slow in Siberia because the growing season is so short, and that clear-cutting -- the most economical way to log -- would cause erosion. This, they fear, would further inhibit regeneration and destroy aquatic ecosystems on which native Siberian people depend for fish they eat.</p>
        <p>While regeneration does take longer in the far north, said Mr. Marshall of Weyerhaeuser, it has been done successfully in the taiga of Canada and Scandinavia for decades. Moreover, he said, some parts of Siberia are warmer and more favorable for tree growth than others.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sedjo said that Siberian logging operations would be among the costliest in the world, despite the new railway. Subsidies by the Russian or local governments, unlikely in the present economic climate, might overcome the timber companies' cost objections, he said. Successful efforts in the United States and elsewhere to prohibit logging on conservation grounds could also drive up the world price of wood, he said, making Siberian logging more attractive.</p>
        <p>But, he said, large increases in Siberian timber production "may never occur."</p>
        <p>To whatever degree the Siberian forests are exploited, Dr. Rosencranz and Mr. Scott wrote, they ought to be exploited in a sound way so that the resource itself, "an economic, climatic and wilderness resource of global significance," is preserved.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
