<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Icy Words on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDA1131F933A05750C0A964958260" item-length="460" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Icy Words on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Words matter, words wound. Asked last week whether he planned to attend the "Earth Summit" in Rio de Janeiro in June, Mr. Bush replied that "running for the Presidency" might keep him at home. Asked whether he would sign a treaty limiting the emission of gases that contribute to the threat of global warming, the President said not if it threatens American jobs.</p>
        <p>It's true that stricter controls on fossil fuels could affect economic growth. But Mr. Bush's comments conveyed a parochial indifference and dismayed a universe of friends -- developing countries seeking Western assistance, European allies willing to take risks for a cleaner environment and the 105 heads of state who will attend the conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Words matter, words wound. Asked last week whether he planned to attend the "Earth Summit" in Rio de Janeiro in June, Mr. Bush replied that "running for the Presidency" might keep him at home. Asked whether he would sign a treaty limiting the emission of gases that contribute to the threat of global warming, the President said not if it threatens American jobs.</p>
        <p>It's true that stricter controls on fossil fuels could affect economic growth. But Mr. Bush's comments conveyed a parochial indifference and dismayed a universe of friends -- developing countries seeking Western assistance, European allies willing to take risks for a cleaner environment and the 105 heads of state who will attend the conference.</p>
        <p>As the President surely knows, those leaders confront the same tough choices he does. The Rio meeting has one central theme: "sustainable development." That means finding ways to build the economies of rich and poor nations alike without wrecking the environment.</p>
        <p>No easy task, especially for the poor. For example, the conference seeks to slow the wanton destruction of the world's rain forests. Poor countries, however, see the forests as sources of jobs and revenue. Thus the U.S. is not the only country which fears that environmental restrictions will limit growth. Yet the U.S. has been uniquely sluggish in the pre-Rio negotiations. Why? The main problem is a proposed binding treaty on global warming.  Several European countries and Japan have urged that by the year 2000 all nations cap emissions of carbon dioxide -- the chief gas implicated in trapping heat in the atmosphere -- at 1990 levels. That scares White House officials, who fear that restricting fuels that produce carbon dioxide, like oil and coal, would be too costly.</p>
        <p>Yet if the U.S., the world's largest emitter of carbon dioxide, doesn't move, what incentive is there for poor countries, whose development depends on fossil fuels, to make sacrifices?</p>
        <p>It should not be impossible for the U.S. to sign the treaty. Data available to Mr. Bush suggest that even if the U.S. did nothing new, greenhouse gases would increase by only 5 percent by the year 2000. A few additional measures -- wider use of clean fuels like natural gas or further conservation incentives for utilities -- might do the trick with little pain.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bush still refuses to accept the cap, the language of diplomacy might help. The treaty could simply call for measures that aim at, but do not guarantee, carbon dioxide stabilization by the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>In any case, there's no longer much doubt that global warming is a worrisome prospect. What is in doubt is America's resolve. Mr. Bush should go to the conference, carrying a commitment to the well-being of the earth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
