<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Burden of Commuter Smog Falls on Employers</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="550490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORKING HOURS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMMUTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAR POOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Working Hours</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Car Pools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA1138F935A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="1832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Burden of Commuter Smog Falls on Employers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONNECTICUT employers must now start thinking about how their employees get to work, as much as how hard they work. This is because an updated and revised version of a 1970 Federal law, whose provisions are being phased in throughout this decade, makes large companies in areas as polluted as Connecticut responsible for curbing the pollution associated with commuting.</p>
        <p>A draft plan prepared by the state Department of Transportation calls for large employers to consider such measures as sharing the cost of van-pooling and mass transit with commuters, providing preferential parking for car poolers and permitting flexible work hours to encourage car pooling. Although there has been much criticism of Federal delays in developing regulations needed to meet the goals of the new legislation known as the Clean Air Act of 1990, the Transportation Department, trade groups and planning agencies are joining together to help companies prepare to meet the letter of the law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONNECTICUT employers must now start thinking about how their employees get to work, as much as how hard they work. This is because an updated and revised version of a 1970 Federal law, whose provisions are being phased in throughout this decade, makes large companies in areas as polluted as Connecticut responsible for curbing the pollution associated with commuting.</p>
        <p>A draft plan prepared by the state Department of Transportation calls for large employers to consider such measures as sharing the cost of van-pooling and mass transit with commuters, providing preferential parking for car poolers and permitting flexible work hours to encourage car pooling. Although there has been much criticism of Federal delays in developing regulations needed to meet the goals of the new legislation known as the Clean Air Act of 1990, the Transportation Department, trade groups and planning agencies are joining together to help companies prepare to meet the letter of the law.</p>
        <p>"This could really change business, because it makes them responsible for something that we've always taken for granted as being a personal decision -- how we get to work," said William H. Messner, a planning director for the Transportation Department. "It could even result in significant social changes, if employers adopt things like four-day work weeks and telecommuting to reduce pollution."</p>
        <p>Under the original Clean Air Act adopted in 1970, only so-called smokestack industries were held accountable for pollution. But air experts estimate that 70 percent of the smog in Connecticut comes from automobile tailpipes. So, in areas like Fairfield County, classified as severely polluted, any company with more than 100 employees will have to develop a policy to reduce the number of commuter trips. .</p>
        <p>"Companies that have never had to think about the Clean Air Act before, now they're going to have to start paying attention," said Joseph M. Ercolano, vice president of the Southwestern Area Commerce and Industry Association. Under the new law, compliance is based on commuting, he said, "and every business has commuters." More Comprehensive Than Old Act</p>
        <p>Although the Federal act affects only large businesses, it could change the way all commuters think, said Liz E. Navarro, director of sales for Metro Pool, a transportation management company based in Stamford.</p>
        <p>"We want to say, 'You, Mr. Corporation, you fix this problem,' but what can happen is the corporations become trendsetters, and things will get done," Ms. Navarro said. "It does spread, and that is, of course, what it's meant to do."</p>
        <p>The revised Clean Air Act, signed into law Nov. 15, 1990, is far more comprehensive than its predecessor, and the impact on commuting is one way it is expected to make itself felt in Connecticut. The act seeks to reduce toxic emissions into the air by as much as 90 percent.</p>
        <p>The 1990 legislation is almost 800 pages long, compared with 65 pages for the 1970 version. It regulates 189 chemicals, up from 7, and where the 1970 act regulated any company putting more than 100 tons of pollutants into the air each year, the 1990 act governs a company emitting 25 tons, or 10 tons of any one pollutant. In 1970, violations of the act were misdemeanors; the 1990 legislation makes many violations felonies, with fines as high as $1 million.</p>
        <p>The legislation puts new restrictions on chemicals that cause acid rain, that damage the protective ozone layer or that create smog. Industry estimates it will cost the nation's businesses $51 billion a year to comply with the 1990 provisions. Government analysts put the cost lower, at $25 billion to $35 billion.</p>
        <p>But advocates say there could still be a net savings. The American Lung Association estimates that there will be 1,750 to 3,000 fewer deaths each year from pollution if the air is clean and that health care costs will decrease $40 billion to $50 billion a year. Damage to buildings will diminish, and the productivity of farm and forest land should be enhanced as acid rain is brought under control. The expanded Clean Air Act could even spur the creation of a new environmental engineering industry and prop up the price of corn if farmers use it to make alcohol, a cleaner-burning fuel than gasoline. Deadlines for State Improvement</p>
        <p>The state was divided into two areas for the purposes of the act. Fairfield County is classified as "severely polluted," which means it will be under tighter restrictions than the rest of the state, which is classified as "seriously polluted." Air quality in Fairfield County must be improved to healthy levels by the year 2007; in the rest of the state, by 1999.</p>
        <p>Joseph A. Belanger, the state Department of Environmental Protection director of planning for implementing the Clean Air Act, said people might be surprised at some of the measures that would go into effect to meet those goals.</p>
        <p>Lawn mowers might have to be controlled because they contribute as much as 5 percent of the hydrocarbons that cause smog. Power boats, and even back yard barbecues, might have to be regulated. 'A Regional Problem'</p>
        <p>Mr. Belanger said the state's rules, in many instances, went beyond what was required at the Federal level. For instance, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency will require that only cleaner burning gasoline be sold in Fairfield and Hartford Counties by 1996. Connecticut extends that requirement to include the entire state.</p>
        <p>"We're sort of out in front in this area, and we hope the Federal government adopts our position as it develops its own regulations," Mr. Belanger said. "Pollution is a regional problem, and it will do Connecticut no good to have rigorous policies if neighboring states don't."</p>
        <p>Some business groups think provisions of the Federal legislation go too far, and could strangle economic development. Because of restrictions in seriously or severely polluted areas -- which covers the entire state -- companies now must go through an extensive review for permits to put in new or expanded operations. In order to receive a permit to emit chemicals at one site, a business will have to reduce pollution at other plants, or "buy" pollution credits from plants that are reducing pollution, said Richard A. Miller, a staff attorney for the Connecticut Business and Industry Association. U.S. Rejects Petition</p>
        <p>The state argued that eastern Connecticut, which has cleaner air, should be classified only as moderately polluted, which would have allowed some economic development to take place without meeting the strict new pollution control requirements, Mr. Miller said. The Federal government rejected the petition.</p>
        <p>The designation, Mr. Miller said, "wasn't necessarily based on science as much as it was based on a feeling there should be uniformity in such a small state. I think the Clean Air Act went a little too far in that it didn't look at some of these issues completely fairly."</p>
        <p>In Fairfield County to obtain a permit to emit 100 tons of material a year, a company would have to cut back 130 tons somewhere else; in the rest of the state, by 120 tons.</p>
        <p>"That's going to cause a real backlog at D.E.P., and that may mean some businesses will go to a state where they can get a permit faster and be up and running sooner," Mr. Miller said. Enforcement Challenged</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, however, take the opposite view. Michael Stern, a staff attorney for the Connecticut Fund for the Environment, said he was particularly concerned about the pollutant that was of greatest concern in Connecticut: smog, or ozone.</p>
        <p>"I think it could have been stricter about ozone," Mr. Stern said. The act sets up regional ozone transport commissions that will review each state's progress in meeting reduction efforts. If one state is not meeting goals, the other states report the violation to the Environmental Protection Agency. Mr. Stern asserted that the commissions should have had the power to take action themselves.</p>
        <p>"Every one of these steps you add allows someone to put more political pressure on the process," he said.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, while the Clean Air Act sets many new requirements for business, it affords a liberal timetable -- businesses do not have to show any results for two to four years -- and there are no penalties for businesses that do not meet their goals. They simply have to submit a new commuter trip reduction plan.</p>
        <p>"The act is real short on enforcement in many respects," Mr. Stern said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Messner of the Transportation Department said it was a balancing act. "You don't want to make employers in Connecticut non-competitive because the burden is too onerous, and you don't want to compromise your health standards," he said. Timetables Required</p>
        <p>The most widely felt impact of the legislation, however, will be on commuting. The state Department of Economic Development estimates there are 2,200 businesses in Connecticut with more than 100 employees, with more than 25 percent of them in 7 of the state's 169 towns: Hartford (156); Stamford (109); Bridgeport (88); New Haven (85); Waterbury (77); Danbury (60), and Norwalk (59).</p>
        <p>The Transportation Department has a draft known as the State Implementation Plan for the Clean Air Act, with a final copy scheduled to be ready by Nov. 1, Mr. Messner said. Early next year large companies will get copies of the plan, and a timetable for submitting their own programs to increase average vehicle occupancy to at least 25 percent over the area's average.</p>
        <p>Transit planners hope that as the provisions of the law go into effect over the next couple of years, more people will be encouraged to take advantage of systems that are already in place. Bea Friedman, a spokeswoman for Metro Pool, said her company's new shuttle system in Greenwich ran between the trains and major employers, with a capacity of more than 300 people, but is used by only about 60 people each day.</p>
        <p>"We'd like to be able to say before long that we have 200 riders," Ms. Friedman said. "And I think that can be achieved, but we have to get the employers behind it." Uncrowded Shuttle</p>
        <p>Peter S. Smichenko, a property manager for Hines Interests Ltd., which operates a 225,000-square-foot office complex on High Ridge Road in Stamford, said a shuttle to the railroad station was offered to tenants. Although only 15 or 20 people use it each day, of the 500 people working at the complex, he said he expected use to climb as employers came under the pressure of the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>"Even now, it's a very important service to the people who use it," Mr. Smichenko said. "It's their only way to get to work."</p>
        <p>Ms. Navarra, of Metro Pool, said many businesses knew what would be required of them under the Clean Air Act, but they also knew they had some time to comply.</p>
        <p>"There will be some companies, probably a lot of companies, that will wait until the last minute," Ms. Navarra said. "We need to remind people that this is coming, that it has to be done, so start now."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
