<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Noah's Ark of the North</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARLING, KARAL ANN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRINGHURST, ROBERT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BLACK CANOE, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DA1F31F93AA35751C0A964958260" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Noah's Ark of the North</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Karal Ann Marling;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARLING, KARAL ANN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE BLACK CANOE</p>
        <p>Bill Reid and the Spirit of Haida Gwaii. By Robert Bringhurst. Photographs by Ulli Steltzer.  173 pp. Seattle: University of Washington Press. $45.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE BLACK CANOE</p>
        <p>Bill Reid and the Spirit of Haida Gwaii. By Robert Bringhurst. Photographs by Ulli Steltzer.  173 pp. Seattle: University of Washington Press. $45.</p>
        <p>THE black canoe called "The Spirit of Haida Gwaii" is a bronze boat, some 20 feet in length, filled to overflowing with figures who wield the paddles doggedly -- two men, including a somber chieftain; three women, two of them with animal features; and eight mythological creatures in animal guise. They bite and claw one another as they glide along; one entity merges with another in a welter of eyes and beaks and nostrils until they form a unitary mass of teeming life.</p>
        <p>The vessel and its strange cargo of passengers ply the waters of a reflecting pool in the courtyard of the new Canadian Embassy in Washington. But for all the signs of furious activity aboard, according to the Canadian poet and cultural historian Robert Bringhurst, who once collaborated with the sculptor Bill Reid on a volume of the narratives of the coastal peoples of British Columbia that are embedded in the work, "these figures are now as motionless as the canoe: caught in mid-stroke by the black bronze, while the water -- so long as the pumps work -- skirls beneath them." They are art, now: public art, rhetoric, a symbol of Canada.</p>
        <p>For readers of "The Black Canoe: Bill Reid and the Spirit of Haida Gwaii" in the United States, the emblematic function may be the main point of interest of Bill Reid's sculptural grouping, given its prominent location on Pennsylvania Avenue across the way from the National Gallery of Art, at the very heart of symbolic America. We expect grand totemic statements in three dimensions in a city defined by its ideological and historical icons, from the Lincoln Memorial and the Washington Monument to the giant Iwo Jima statue and the Vietnam Wall. Indeed, the site of the chancery, close to the centers of power, was granted to Canada in visible recognition of its close relationship with the United States. Arthur Erickson, the Vancouver architect who designed the building and who invited Bill Reid to become its principal sculptor in 1985, has been criticized both for missing the opportunity to represent somehow a Canadian identity in the fabric of his building and for being so dazzled by the grandiose Federal Classicism and Official Modernism of the capital that his Embassy became an empty pastiche of borrowed American motifs.</p>
        <p>"The Black Canoe" seems to offer a powerful corrective to the symbolic shortcomings of the structure -- with its native iconography and defiantly unassimilated forms, its hints at the Canadian Government's continuing troubles with Indian tribal rights, the essential separatism of its oddly assorted constituent parts and its rejection of the uniformity of the melting pot.</p>
        <p>During most of 1987, in fact, Mr. Reid stopped work to protest a dispute between Canada and the provincial government of British Columbia over logging in the southern half of Haida Gwaii ("Haida land," the Haida Indians' name for the Queen Charlotte Islands, the archipelago occupied by the tribe to which Mr. Reid's maternal grandparents belonged). It was a dispute in which both governments tended to ignore the claims and interests of the Haida people. Yet, for Prime Minister Brian Mulroney's fractious Canada, obsessed with its near neighbor to the south, symbol making is plainly no easy business. If the black canoe is a sort of Noah's Ark of the North, full of doubt and tension, it is also a backhanded tribute to the nation-making fortitude conjured up in the Emanuel Leutze painting "Washington Crossing the Delaware."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bringhurst is aware of these artistic quotations and resonances; although he knows that, as official Canadian art, the sculpture exists in a social and political context in which the competing claims of artist, nation and tribe must ultimately find their balance (like paddlers in a Haida canoe), his story concerns the deepest spiritual meanings of the piece. Or rather, it concerns Bill Reid's voyage of exploration through the Bear and Raven and Beaver myths of the first Canadians -- myths of earth, sky and water -- to a new sense of selfhood, to an ecology of humanness that puts people back in the world of their fellow creatures.</p>
        <p>Neither Mr. Reid nor the attentive poet say so, but the concept of nationhood, if it ever figured among the sculptor's motivations, pales in comparison to the demands of lifehood. As "The Black Canoe" finally shows, we're all -- Canadian</p>
        <p>and</p>
        <p>Americans -- in the very same boat, afloat on an ancient sea of biological interdependence that forms our common North American heritage. A salutary scripture, that, to preach along Pennsylvania Avenue as nuclear waste storage and offshore drilling and the disposition of public lands are being debated up on the Hill, as industrial smoke from American chimneys befouls Canada with acid rain.</p>
        <p>But the sculpture is not that simple, either. It is as complicated as the life of Bill Reid, a former CBC radio announcer who worked his way out of white Canadian culture and back into the imagistic world of his grandparents through a study of Haida art. Both historical components of his personality -- the contemporary and the essentially timeless; English-Canadian texts and the oral tradition of his forebears -- are intertwined in his work. Mr. Reid even appears in the canoe in the guise of what he calls "the Ancient Reluctant Conscript," a grudging oarsman of the ship of state, a participant in a drama of cultural interpenetration and violence begun in 1787 with the British "discovery" of Haida Gwaii.</p>
        <p>The style of the ensemble, explored in the series of searching work-in-process photos by Ulli Steltzer, reinforces the notion of complex layers of time, meaning and feeling knit together in an uneasy whole. Following the practice of Celtic manuscript illumination of the seventh and eighth centuries, which Mr. Reid appropriates to his own ends, the body of one animal bears the pictorial likeness of another (the wing of the Raven contains the face of a salmon, for example), conflating their stories and blurring distinctions between one order of reality and another. The end result is neither Celtic nor Haida. It is, perhaps, Canadian.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bringhurst never insists that this is so. There is nothing narrowly chauvinistic about the book. But by treating public art as art rather than polemic -- by insisting that the creator and his beliefs remain central to the genesis of the black canoe -- he reminds us that the democratic state is an aggregate of pungent individuals like Bill Reid and the remarkable bronze spirits who share his voyage of life.</p>
        <p>Karal Ann Marling writes about American icons. Her latest book, written with John Wetenhall, is "Iwo Jima: Monuments, Memories, and the American Hero."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Karal Ann Marling writes about American icons. Her latest book, written with John Wetenhall, is "Iwo Jima: Monuments, Memories, and the American Hero."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
