<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Every Day Is a Day for Roses</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="NEW JERSEY Q &amp; A: ART HEYL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROSES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREEN VILLAGE (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, JOYCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEYL, ART</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED7123CF93AA35751C0A964958260" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Every Day Is a Day for Roses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JONES, JOYCE</byline>
      <dateline>GREEN VILLAGE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YEARS ago on Feb. 14, in places like Derbyshire, England, it was the custom for an unmarried woman to tap her forehead with a folded rose petal. If the petal cracked, she knew that her valentine loved her.</p>
        <p>Today, assessing a person's ardor on Valentine's Day is gauged not by petals, but rather the entire rose, preferably red, long-stemmed and 12 in number.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YEARS ago on Feb. 14, in places like Derbyshire, England, it was the custom for an unmarried woman to tap her forehead with a folded rose petal. If the petal cracked, she knew that her valentine loved her.</p>
        <p>Today, assessing a person's ardor on Valentine's Day is gauged not by petals, but rather the entire rose, preferably red, long-stemmed and 12 in number.</p>
        <p>In readiness for the day, Art Heyl, owner of Heyl Roses in Green Village, has grown more than 100,000 roses, which he will deliver to florists in northern New Jersey. The year round, he tends to 66,500 rose plants in 90,000 square feet of greenhouses, where, growing in stately array, the blossoms attest to the designation of the rose as the nation's floral symbol.</p>
        <p>Popular among the 30 varieties Mr. Heyl grows are red roses with names like Preference, Royalty, Samantha and Cardinal. Roses gaining in favor are the pale pink Lady Diana, the bright yellow Golden Fantasy and the brilliant pink Hot Spot.</p>
        <p>Heyl Roses was founded 63 years ago by Mr. Heyl's grandfather, Louis Heyl, and his father, Arthur. Today, his sons, Tom, a graduate of Cook College of Rutgers University, and Doug, who will graduate from Cook College in May, have joined the family business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heyl said his satisfaction came from growing a quality product. But his business has to contend, he said, with the ever rising cost of operating the greenhouses and with the increasing influx of imported roses sold on the American market.</p>
        <p>The number of wholesalers who grow their own roses in New Jersey has dwindled to just a few. This is in marked contrast to the early 1900's, when Madison, a community adjacent to Green Village, raised the most roses in the country, earning it the name the Rose City.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the biggest issue facing you and the 300 other rose growers in the United States?</p>
        <p>A. We are in the business right now of competing with imported roses from places like Mexico and Colombia, where the growers are subsidized by their governments. The position the American Government has taken is that if these people are encouraged to form an alternate crop, like roses, it may cut down on their growing coca, the source of cocaine.</p>
        <p>The roses raised in South America, in unheated greenhouses, produce heavy wooded stems that have trouble drawing up water. Once cut, premature wilting can result.</p>
        <p>Also, if a cut rose is without water for a long period of time, the flowering mechanism is affected which hinders it from opening up to full bloom. The imported roses that are flown into Miami and held on their loading docks are out of water for a lengthy spell.</p>
        <p>Q.  Why do these factors hurt your business?</p>
        <p>A. If the rose does not open up and lasts a week to 10 days, the buyer's expectation for roses have been lowered. He may come to the conclusion that roses are supposed to die. Even if the person pays supermarket prices, if the roses aren't enjoyed for a week or more, the buyer should go back to where they were purchased and raise heck.</p>
        <p>The longer the rose is out of water, the more its quality declines. If that rose dies, my credibility as a rose grower is hurt by something over which I have no control. The better I can make my roses and the longer they last, the more people will buy flowers. It is not a reflection on what I am doing, but a reflection on the generic rose.</p>
        <p>Q.  What is the process you use to assure a buyer that the rose will perform in the vase as if it were still on the plant?</p>
        <p>A. From the time our roses are cut until the time the florist may box them, our roses are out of water only 20 minutes. It takes about 10 minutes for the cutter to go up and down the greenhouse aisles to clip a crop, and an additional 10 minutes accrue when the roses are in the sorting machine.</p>
        <p>The cut rose is put immediately in a bucket which is filled with a solution and then refrigerated for 24 hours. After grading, they are put back in the solution and the buckets are transported in our refrigerated trucks to florists.</p>
        <p>Q. How should the rose be cared for once it arrives in the home?</p>
        <p>A. If roses arrive in a box, mix the accompanying packet of floral preservative, which contains nutriments for the roses' continued growth, with a recommended amount of water. Prior to putting the roses in the solution, take each stem and, holding it under running water, clip off about an inch. Replenish, when needed, the water that the rose intakes.</p>
        <p>Q. How have technical advances changed your operation?</p>
        <p>A. Jobs done by our employees five years ago, today are being handled by an environmentally programmed computer. We establish the parameters to insure optimum growing conditions, like the temperature of the greenhouses, amount of carbon dioxide in the air, the humidity and the amount of light. The computer opens the vents in the greenhouses depending upon the direction of the wind.</p>
        <p>Because of new information on soils, we are constantly changing the growing medium. Now we are using more sand.</p>
        <p>We use drip irrigation, which is controlled by the computer. It analyzes the intensity of the sun and how much water the plant is taking up. On a bright day, it might water 10 times. Food is generated in with the water. If the photosynthesis is slow, the computer compensates by turning up the heat.</p>
        <p>Q. You seem to be in control of the organic part of growing roses. What facet may be beyond your control?</p>
        <p>A. Five years ago, it was the whitefly, the same insect that is plaguing farmers in California. The research facility at the Agricultural Station at Rutgers University was baffled by how it got into the greenhouses. At first, it was resistant to spray and appeared uncontrollable. We have to watch for it all the time; it seems particularly attracted to pink roses.  Along with having to control more insects than you can imagine, a recent problem has been the Western flower thrip, which lays its eggs in the developing bud.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you planning to add to the 30 varieties of roses you currently grow?</p>
        <p>A. We continually test new plants from flower sources, like Jackson Perkins. Labeled only as No. 3, a rose we are currently growing in one of our flower beds opens up to six inches in diameter. It doesn't, however, have a whole lot of petals, and people prefer roses with many petals.</p>
        <p>When a hybridizer tries to develop a new rose, there is concern about bud formation and how well it will ship. Over 1,000 crosses may have to be made before a rose is suitable for selling.</p>
        <p>Q. Along with a new color, is the traditional rose fragrance being enhanced?</p>
        <p>A. Interestingly, in hybridization the first thing to disappear is the fragrance. The gene that carries fragrance must be genetically one of the weaker. A very fragrant rose doesn't last as long as one that isn't. There is some relationship between the gene that keeps the petals from falling off and the gene that gives fragrance.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the allure of long-stemmed roses?</p>
        <p>A. Long-stemmed roses are usually about 22 to 24 inches. On Valentine's Day, 60 percent of the roses we sell are that length. Some say that 90 percent of reality is in the perception. People think a Cadillac is better because it's bigger. Many purchasers of roses believe longer is better.</p>
        <p>Q. What is your favorite floral arrangement?</p>
        <p>A. When my wife, Val, and I bring roses to friends, we prefer to select 10 to 15 different varieties. As they open, the different properties of each rose can be enjoyed, all in one bouquet.  NEW JERSEY Q &amp; A: ART HEYL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
