<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 'Lab Mouse' of Coral May Be Several Species</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="503929"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KNOWLTON, NANCY (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1530F93BA15752C0A964958260" item-length="408" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 'Lab Mouse' of Coral May Be Several Species</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A COMMONLY studied species of coral, the "lab mouse" of marine biology, has been found to be three species rather than one, according to a new study.</p>
        <p>The finding, reported in the Jan. 17 issue of the journal Science, may compel scientists to review their previous research involving star coral.  The lead investigator, Dr. Nancy Knowlton, a staff scientist of the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama, said past research commonly attributed differences in the coral to environmental factors.  But the discrepancies might have actually been based on genetics if the researchers were unknowingly comparing different species, she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A COMMONLY studied species of coral, the "lab mouse" of marine biology, has been found to be three species rather than one, according to a new study.</p>
        <p>The finding, reported in the Jan. 17 issue of the journal Science, may compel scientists to review their previous research involving star coral.  The lead investigator, Dr. Nancy Knowlton, a staff scientist of the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama, said past research commonly attributed differences in the coral to environmental factors.  But the discrepancies might have actually been based on genetics if the researchers were unknowingly comparing different species, she said.</p>
        <p>Star coral, Montastraea annularis, is the most abundant reef-building coral in the tropical western Atlantic Ocean. Dr. Knowlton's team defined the three new species based on their genetic, biochemical and behavioral properties. Differences in protein compositions, growth rates, chemical ratios and protective behaviors demonstrated the presence of at least three distinct species, the team said.</p>
        <p>Since a species is a group of organisms that can interbreed, studies of reproductive compatibility are the conventional method of distinguishing between species. Dr. Knowlton's data do not include studies of the reproductive compatibility.</p>
        <p>Dr. John Ogden, director of the Florida Institute of Oceanography, said, "Without reproductive evidence in the study, there's a point where conclusions become subjective." Dr. Knowlton plans to begin a study of the star coral's reproductive compatibility, but she believes new data would support her present conclusions. She said she would submit an article with new names for two of the species to The Bulletin of Marine Science.</p>
        <p>Scientists have been frustrated by the physical variations between star coral samples, she said. As a result of the new species definitions, they will be able to select samples that are genetically more uniform.</p>
        <p>Dr. Knowlton said genetic variations might have led to confusion in coral bleaching studies, which have linked the coral's loss of pigment to environmental factors like global warming or the water's low saline content. She does not doubt the existence of some cases of coral bleaching but questions some studies that compared nonbleached with partly bleached samples. Those studies, while describing variations in organisms, may have contained descriptions of at least two species, she said.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
