<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe Orders Reduction of Pollution From Fuel</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19920325T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="516523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D91030F937A15750C0A964958260" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe Orders Reduction of Pollution From Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, March 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environmental ministers of the European Community ordered a sharp cutback today in the sulfur content of all diesel and heating oil within two and a half years.</p>
        <p>The decision will make the fuel used to heat homes and drive the vast fleet of trucks and buses that crowd European roads cleaner but more expensive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Environmental ministers of the European Community ordered a sharp cutback today in the sulfur content of all diesel and heating oil within two and a half years.</p>
        <p>The decision will make the fuel used to heat homes and drive the vast fleet of trucks and buses that crowd European roads cleaner but more expensive.</p>
        <p>Sulfur dioxide from coal and oil burning has covered cities with soot, corroded metal and stone, affected people's lungs, and, in acid rain, has damaged nearly 75 percent of Europe's forests.</p>
        <p>European officials say the need for cleaner diesel fuel has gained all the more urgency because new studies predict a trade boom in the coming single European market, a development that could increase truck traffic and the resulting pollution by as much as 30 percent.  Two Target Dates</p>
        <p>Under the new restrictions issued in Brussels today, sulfur content in oil by October 1994 must be down to 0.2 percent, almost half of levels in fuel used today in several countries. By 1996 sulfur must be cut by an additional 80 percent. In the United States, the Clean Air Act requires that sulfur content in fuel be no more than 0.5 percent by October 1993.</p>
        <p>The tighter standards will force many European refineries to make large new investments in equipment almost immediately. They will prove particularly costly in the short term to companies in southern Europe, which in contrast to those in Belgium, Denmark, Germany, Luxembourg and the Netherlands still produce highly polluting fuel oil. The cuts in sulfur level will also apply to fuel used by boats.</p>
        <p>Officials said Spain and Greece had prevented the community from imposing similar sulfur cuts in fuel used in airplanes.</p>
        <p>Once the limits are in effect, community officials say, they will reduce the sulfur emissions by one million tons a year.</p>
        <p>But the new restrictions will not affect about 13 million tons of sulfur a year that are produced by power plants and industrial boilers using oil and coal. This accounts for almost 13 percent of the world's output of sulfur oxides. The United States accounts for close to 21 percent.</p>
        <p>The new rules still need approval by the European Parliament, which has criticized them as too lenient and wants to move the changes up by another year, to 1993. Some scientists want immediate drastic cuts in all forms of oil and coal burning.  Called 'Far From Enough'</p>
        <p>"This will improve the sitution a bit, but it's far from enough," said Sten Nilsson, a specialist in pollution effects on forests at the International Institute of Applied Systems Analysis in Laxenburg, Austria.</p>
        <p>Sulfur, he said, is the main chemical component of acid rain, which is making European forests "sick and stressed." More than 75 percent of Europe's forests, he added, "are receiving more sulfur than the ecosystem can bear in the long run."</p>
        <p>Part of the pressure for change has come from Switzerland and Austria, which at the heart of Europe bear the brunt of the constant and enormous flow of north-south traffic. Citizens groups here, exasperated with the noise and pollution, have at times blocked the highways. The two Governments have demanded far-reaching changes from the truck owners and threatened to shut the vital tunnels through the Alps. Switzerland has already banned trucks heavier than 28 tons from entering the country.</p>
        <p>Swiss environmentalists have forced the Government to hold a referendum before it signs an agreement with the European Community on transit rights through the Alps.  Transport System Questioned</p>
        <p>Last year, the European Community cut noxious pollution from heavy trucks by imposing strict new limits on their carbon and nitrogen emissions. But officials in Brussels say Europe needs to rethink its entire transport system to prevent the highways of a new, barrier-free Europe from becoming completely congested.</p>
        <p>For the last three decades, governments have favored road traffic by covering western Europe with large networks of roads and undercharging cars and trucks for upkeep and other costs. But environmental advocates make the expansion of major new highway systems difficult. Community officials have proposed major extensions of railroad networks and even putting the trucks on trains.</p>
        <p>The powerful truck owners' associations have lobbied hard against any changes affecting their interests, arguing that they are Europe's lifeline. But Brussels officials argue that road transport must become more rational. Trucks must contend with intricate transport routes, cannot load cargo where they want and often return empty from their hauls. "This is madness," a German official said. "We have to improve the rules."</p>
        <p>Specialists said that despite today's new sulfur rules, the community's efforts to improve the environment cannot be fully effective without cutbacks in the enormous pollution produced by poor neighbors to the east. Poland alone emits almost 35 percent as much sulfur dioxide as the entire 12-nation European Community.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 25, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a decision by the European Community to require reductions in the sulfur content of fuel misstated a requirement of the United States Clean Air Act. Under the law, the level of sulfur in fuel must be held to 0.05 percent or less by October 1993, not 0.5 percent or less.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 25, 1992, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a decision by the European Community to require reductions in the sulfur content of fuel misstated a requirement of the United States Clean Air Act. Under the law, the level of sulfur in fuel must be held to 0.05 percent or less by October 1993, not 0.5 percent or less.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
