<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Tree Grows in Brooklyn, but Maybe Not for Long</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="499396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8123BF932A25752C0A964958260" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Tree Grows in Brooklyn, but Maybe Not for Long</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They hide acorns from squirrels. They plant spindly little tulip trees next to Norway maples (and later cut the maples down). They chain saw groves of ailanthus trees of "A Tree Grows in Brooklyn" fame and eradicate jungles of porcelainberry and oriental bittersweet.</p>
        <p>It looks like destruction, but it's restoration. Over the years, New York City's forests -- yes, 5,000 acres still exist -- have become home to exotic species that in many cases have overwhelmed the native ones. City foresters are now trying to bring the native ones back.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They hide acorns from squirrels. They plant spindly little tulip trees next to Norway maples (and later cut the maples down). They chain saw groves of ailanthus trees of "A Tree Grows in Brooklyn" fame and eradicate jungles of porcelainberry and oriental bittersweet.</p>
        <p>It looks like destruction, but it's restoration. Over the years, New York City's forests -- yes, 5,000 acres still exist -- have become home to exotic species that in many cases have overwhelmed the native ones. City foresters are now trying to bring the native ones back.</p>
        <p>Many of the new species are there by accident: Little did anyone dream that a nice shade tree on a rolling lawn would become a hog in the forest. Or that oriental bittersweet, that graceful vine with the pretty orange berries carried by birds or the wind, would become the Godzilla of the plant world.</p>
        <p>"Bittersweet can literally pull down trees," said Dr. William A. Niering, an ecologist at Connecticut College in New London who has helped map the vegetation of the city forests. "It climbs up over them and shades out the canopy. And when a storm blows up and all that weight is intercepted by the wind, it just blows down. But the vine keeps growing and forms an impenetrable thicket." Tulips vs. Maples</p>
        <p>City foresters are working slowly to reintroduce native plants and give them an edge against the exotics. The city is also removing hundreds of cars dumped for years in these wooded areas.</p>
        <p>In the middle of Inwood Hill Park in Manhattan, Tony Emmerich, the forestry program's project manager, watched a work crew plant tulip seedlings among a grove of Norway maples. A few 200-year-old tulip trees soared 100 feet into the sky. But these venerable natives -- the tulips and the oaks -- have trouble reproducing.</p>
        <p>If a seed germinates and takes root, it's shaded out by a faster-growing maple. So the foresters help out by removing the aggressors.</p>
        <p>"It's a gradual process," Mr. Emmerich said. "We don't clear out to ground zero. First we plant the natives we want -- oaks, tulips, red maples, hickories -- and let them get established." Then the crews thin out the the non-native species that were planted long ago on the grand old estates that once stood here.</p>
        <p>Many of the imports left the pests and diseases that kept them under control back home, so they run rampant here. They were brought in by wealthy landowners like William Hamilton of Pennsylvania, who imported the Norway maple and the Chinese ailanthus in the 18th century; they were also planted by the city's first parks commissioner.</p>
        <p>"Frederick Law Olmsted was quite a fancier of non-native species, but nobody ever imagined the ripple effect, and it's probably the greatest single threat to our natural resources," said Paul Berizzi, chief of environmental services.</p>
        <p>When plant diversity is limited, it reduces the value to animals and birds, said Mr. Emmerich. "We're seeing fewer scarlet tanagers and red-eyed vireos, warblers and birds that prefer the forest cover," he said.</p>
        <p>All fall, about 30 city workers trained in forestry were at work in Inwood Hill Park, Van Cortlandt and Pelham Bay Parks in the Bronx, Forest Park in Queens, Prospect Park in Brooklyn and the Greenbelt in Staten Island, cutting down 8-foot curtains of porcelainberry, knotweed and bittersweet and injecting the remaining stems with herbicides. In the cleared areas, they planted Eastern white pine and red maple, which are supposed to shade out the vines.</p>
        <p>Forest scientists say they have no choice but to use herbicides, because time and money are limited.</p>
        <p>"We could pull them out manually, but we don't have the manpower, so there is a need to use an herbicide, and they are taking a conservative approach," said Mark J. McDonnell, an ecologist at the Institute of Ecosystems at Millbrook, N.Y., who has been working with the foresters.</p>
        <p>These mighty oaks are also besieged by voracious squirrels who eat acorns before they can germinate.</p>
        <p>"The only way to get ahead of them is to grow seedlings out of the acorns or try to outsmart them by planting them where the squirrels are less likely to look for them," said Mr. Emmerich. "They don't usually take the acorns more than 200 yards from the seed trees." 100,000 New Trees</p>
        <p>The crews have collected 40,000 seeds of oaks, tulips, sweet gum and maple from all over the city's forests and planted many of them at the nursery in Van Cortlandt Park.</p>
        <p>In this same forest, they discovered a jungle of young sugar maples and potted them up for planting elsewhere. They found hundreds of sweet-gum seedlings in the clogged gutters of a city building; these, too, will be spread about the forests.</p>
        <p>Native shrubs like azalea, blueberry, chokecherry and mapleleaf viburnum are rescued from construction sites. White pine and pitch pine are planted to increase the habitat for owls and hawks. Eventually 100,000 new trees will be planted.</p>
        <p>The massive project was begun last year with $6.5 million from the Lila Wallace-Reader's Digest Fund.</p>
        <p>High on the ridge at Inwood Hill, 200-year-old oaks tower over the Hudson River and shade the old Indian caves carved out of the rocks by glaciers 12,000 years ago. If you wander here, where crows call high in the canopy, the city seems to vanish. A few miles north, owls roost in the tall pines of the old Hunter estate in Pelham Bay Park.</p>
        <p>There are other signs of civilization: Porcelainberry winds around the rusting hulk of a Lincoln Continental, its wheels sunk in the forest floor. Over in LaTourette Park on Staten Island, a Chrysler Imperial is half buried in oak leaves. A stack of crumpled steel tops a wooded ridge; it's been there so long it has a certain eloquence.</p>
        <p>About 3,000 cars were pulled out of city parks in 1990 alone. Most of them are dumped by thieves who drive them into the woods, strip them and then set them afire. It is a major threat to the ecosystem.</p>
        <p>"Fires destroy the saplings of the same species, and the trees can't regenerate," said Mr. Emmerich, standing in a 70-year-old pine forest on the former Hunter estate. "They also wound the trunks of the mature trees and open them up to fungus, infection and rot." 20 miles of Fence</p>
        <p>The trees show the scars of fires long ago, but the soil has been bared so that the trees can reseed. Nearby, workers have taken out a thicket of ailanthus and planted a new stand of white pine and hemlock, the favorite nesting sites for raptors.</p>
        <p>On the perimeter of the forests, work crews are putting up 20 miles of steel guardrails and wooden bollards to stop the dumping and fires. Barriers were first set in place in Pelham Bay Park about four years ago. "And we haven't had a significant fire there since," said Mr. Berizzi.</p>
        <p>But changing the attitude that the woods is a dumping ground and scavenging site takes time. Preservation goes against the very principles on which the country was founded.</p>
        <p>"Almost all the forest was removed before the end of the Revolutionary War for logging or fuel or farmland or military reasons," said Mr. Emmerich, standing on a ridge in LaTourette Park where the British once watched for colonists to come up Richmond Creek.</p>
        <p>It took 12,000 years for the forest to establish itself after the glacier melted, said Dr. Niering. "Then the colonists came and cut everything down," he said. Then they moved west to cut down more forests.</p>
        <p>And now foresters must deal with the more complex and hidden problems of the industrial age.</p>
        <p>Acid rain affects the chemistry of the soil, locking up nutrients that can no longer be absorbed by tree roots. There are more heavy metals in the ground from the combustion of fossil fuels; ozone deteriorates the very structure of the leaves. There is no more lichen growing on tree trunks because lichen, which pulls its nutrients from the air, needs a certain level of purity.</p>
        <p>Yet these great woods, compared to the air downtown and the squeal of subway cars, evoke the peace and quiet of a wilderness. Or the last vestiges of one. And that is what the foresters are trying to keep.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
