<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="511304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUNTERFEITING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLORINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D6133CF930A35750C0A964958260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. CLAIBORNE RAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAY, C CLAIBORNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chlorinated Water</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Does the chlorine in chlorinated water contribute to the destruction of the earth's protective ozone layer?</p>
        <p>A.  No, said Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland, the Donald Bren Professor of chemistry at the University of California at Irvine, because it does not last long enough to get a chance to do so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chlorinated Water</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Does the chlorine in chlorinated water contribute to the destruction of the earth's protective ozone layer?</p>
        <p>A.  No, said Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland, the Donald Bren Professor of chemistry at the University of California at Irvine, because it does not last long enough to get a chance to do so.</p>
        <p>The key problem in ozone destruction, he said, is not chlorine in the atmosphere, but chlorine in the stratosphere, and the key question, he continued, is how the chlorine in chlorinated water would get into the stratosphere.</p>
        <p>Chlorination to kill organisms in drinking water uses chemical forms related to pure molecular chlorine, Cl2 , a green gas, Dr. Rowland said. If it is given off into the atmosphere, it would ordinarily be decomposed by sunlight within hours, not leaving it enough time to reach the stratosphere. The related chlorine compounds are all easily removed by rainfall.</p>
        <p>Some of the chlorine does react with organic materials, he continued, but it produces organic compounds, like methyl chloride, that mostly have lifetimes in the atmosphere of a year or so, Dr. Rowland said, so only a very small fraction would get to the stratosphere.</p>
        <p>Methyl chloride is in fact a natural component of the atmosphere, in far larger quantities than would come from the chlorination of water, and the ozone layer has long been adjusted to its presence, Dr. Rowland said.</p>
        <p>Chlorofluorocarbons, on the other hand, have several characteristics that ideally suit them to destroying ozone in the stratosphere, Dr. Rowland said. First, they are not soluble in water, so they cannot be removed by rain. Second, they are transparent, and unlike the highly reactive green molecular chlorine gas, they cannot be transformed by available sunlight. And third, they are completely unreactive toward oxidizing agents in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>For all these reasons, Dr. Rowland said, chlorofluorocarbons can last for 50, 100 or even 150 years in the atmosphere, randomly drifting up to the stratosphere.</p>
        <p>"The ozone layer not only protects us, it protects chlorofluorocarbons," Dr. Rowland said, "but when they are above the ozone, short-length ultraviolet radiation from the sun can cause them to split, releasing atomic chlorine, which destroys the ozone in a chain reaction." Catching Counterfeits</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>How do bill changers tell that the money isn't counterfeit?</p>
        <p>A.  Many of the specific techniques machines use to detect counterfeit money are closely guarded secrets, since once counterfeiters know how the machines work, they try to foil them.</p>
        <p>But Lisa Mendheim, a spokeswoman for the Maytag Corporation, whose subsidiary Ardac Inc. makes bill-changing equipment, said that two common means of identifying paper money were magnetic sensing and optical sensing.</p>
        <p>Inks used to print notes have certain magnetic properties, which can be sensed by a magnetic head in a bill changer, she explained. A computer can recognize the electronic signature of specific tracks along the money and accept or reject it.</p>
        <p>In optical sensing, light is passed through or reflected from a bill, she said. Some inks absorb light and others reflect it. The computer can analyze these patterns and determine if the bill is acceptable.</p>
        <p>In either case, Ms. Mendheim said, the scanning takes about one second.</p>
        <p>Readers are invited to submit questions about science to Questions, Science Times, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions of general interest will be answered in this column, but requests for medical advice cannot be honored and unpublished letters cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
