<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Electric Power: A Help . . . Or a Hindrance?</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="552235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN ELECTRIC POWER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HELME, NED</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD8103EF930A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Electric Power: A Help . . . Or a Hindrance?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>American Electric Power paint itself green? The problem is identified in the article's subhead: "But a wildlife preserve and new light bulb may not be enough." It's not.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>American Electric Power paint itself green? The problem is identified in the article's subhead: "But a wildlife preserve and new light bulb may not be enough." It's not.</p>
        <p>A.E.P. seems to expect kudos for spending $1 billion to meet acid rain requirements of the Clean Air Act. That would be noble except for two key points. First, it's spending $1 billion of rate-payers' money, not its own. Second, it can meet the act's requirements at less than one-third that cost.</p>
        <p>As noted in the article, a key component lacking in all A.E.P. planning is commitment to any energy conservation programs. In fact, A.E.P. doesn't plan to distribute the e-lamp to its own customers. Central to A.E.P.'s compliance plan is building a scrubber at its Gavin plant. But there is an alternative plan -- including a combined strategy of energy conservation programs linked to reduced utilization of its high-emitting plants, fuel-switching at several other units and a small number of emission allowance purchases -- that would save consumers $820 million by 1999.</p>
        <p>The A.E.P. plan doesn't only hit consumers in their household budgets, it could also end up costing them their jobs. It is estimated that repercussions from the 3.9 percent rate increase (to pay for the $1 billion scrubber) include the loss of almost 7,000 jobs in the A.E.P. service territory. Our plan would save more than 5,500 jobs and raise rates only 1 percent.</p>
        <p>With all the negative economic impacts of the A.E.P. plan, one would think that it was a model of environmental planning. Not so. The scrubber plan, while reducing SO2 emissions, will create a 383-acre landfill of scrubber sludge, destroying 14 acres of wetlands.</p>
        <p>A.E.P. also expressed concern about present legislative trends toward reductions in CO2 emissions. It is ignoring a potential first step: Reducing utilization at high-emitting plants would cut all emissions -- SO2, NOx, CO2 and air toxics. This would be of much greater environmental benefit than over-controlling one pollutant -- SO2 -- while maintaining or actually increasing other pollutants.</p>
        <p>While a wildlife preserve is exciting, and the e-lamp shows promise, A.E.P. is missing the boat. Consumers and the environment are the big losers.  NED HELME Washington, Aug. 10  The writer is executive director, Center for Clean Air Policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
