<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At 100 Below Zero, Scientists Seek Evidence of Radiation From Space</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELESCOPES AND OBSERVATORIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEUTRINOS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDD163FF93BA25751C0A964958260" item-length="1375" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At 100 Below Zero, Scientists Seek Evidence of Radiation From Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
      <dateline>MCMURDO SOUND, Antarctica</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE South Pole, goal of heroic treks in the early years of the century, is emerging as the site for a multitude of scientific observations.</p>
        <p>For the 20 or so researchers who winter over at the pole, conditions are harsh, especially during the long winter night. Temperatures can drop to more than 100 degrees below zero Fahrenheit and the sun never rises above the horizon. But the rewards are rich, for the work done there cannot be done anywhere else on earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE South Pole, goal of heroic treks in the early years of the century, is emerging as the site for a multitude of scientific observations.</p>
        <p>For the 20 or so researchers who winter over at the pole, conditions are harsh, especially during the long winter night. Temperatures can drop to more than 100 degrees below zero Fahrenheit and the sun never rises above the horizon. But the rewards are rich, for the work done there cannot be done anywhere else on earth.</p>
        <p>No other observatory is directly on the earth's rotational axis. As a result, the sun, stars and other sources of celestial radiation rotate overhead in a circle; all but the sun remain at the same height above the horizon throughout the year. At other observatories much of the sky is only visible part time and, furthermore, as light from a rising and setting star passes through different thicknesses of atmosphere, researchers must constantly correct for atmospheric distortion.</p>
        <p>This year a complex of new observing systems has been built. Search for Neutrinos</p>
        <p>Several are measuring radiation from space. In one project, directed by Dr. Douglas M. Lowder of the University of California at Berkeley, a hot water jet has drilled two holes 2,600 feet deep in the ice to test the possibility of detecting the elusive particles called neutrinos that after traveling through space, traverse the entire earth to emerge at the pole.</p>
        <p>Scientists hope scanners in a series of such holes will be able to identify the sources of neutrinos in the Arctic sky, on the opposite side of the earth. Observing them after they pass through the earth eliminates confusion from other radiation coming from the heavens.</p>
        <p>The scanners will detect flashes created by subatomic particles called muons set off at high velocity by neutrino collisions. Because such collisions are extremely rare, a large volume of material is needed. Earlier attempts used large tanks of water, cleaning fluid and other substances, but never detectors whose volume approached that of the polar ice.</p>
        <p>Initial observations in the 2,600-foot holes, said Dr. Lowder, seem to show that at such depth the ice is free of bubbles and thus transparent enough to make a large volume of ice observable.</p>
        <p>As Dr. John Lynch, scientific leader at the pole earlier this season, said in an interview, it looks as though the ice covering Antarctica, miles deep and hundreds of miles in extent, is like a giant crystal of quartz or other transparent material.  Data on Gamma Rays</p>
        <p>In another project, researchers have installed new instruments to aid detectors already at the station seeking the origin of high energy gamma rays from space. This included constructing a "swimming pool" eight feet on a side, packed with photo sensors. It detects directional information on gamma rays at an energy not accessible to other detectors at the pole. The photo sensors were installed in a blue, water-filled plastic tub -- "a big blue swimming pool" Dr. Lynch called it. The water was then allowed to freeze.</p>
        <p>Like neutrinos, gamma rays, having no electric charge, presumably travel to earth directly from their source, without being bent by magnetic fields like other radiation. Some astrophysicists suspect that a substantial percentage of gammas, produced by some unknown process, may be coming from a specific source in the southern sky, but this remains controversial.</p>
        <p>As gamma rays, the most powerful radiation in nature, strike the atmosphere, they produce fragments, chiefly electrons and positrons, that continue earthward in the same direction. To detect the resulting "air shower" and the direction of its source, 24 widely spaced boxes have for several years been standing on legs near the pole station.</p>
        <p>The project is based on proposals made several years ago by Dr. Martin Pomerantz of the Bartol Research Institute at the University of Delaware and Dr. Michael Hillas of the University of Leeds in England. They argued that, if the gammas were coming intermittently from certain spots in the heavens, those spots could be monitored continuously from the South Pole.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. Thomas Geiser of the Bartol group, showers produced by other types of very powerful radiation produce 10 times more muons than gamma showers. Since muons can penetrate ice, detectors embedded in the ice should reveal those showers too rich in muons to be of gamma ray origin.</p>
        <p>In another scientific project at the pole, a cluster of telescopes is to be installed by the Center for Astrophysical Research in Antarctica, a consortium of astrophysicists led by Dr. Doyal Alexander Harper Jr. of the University of Chicago. With a five-year grant of $13.6 million from the National Science Foundation, the investigators will take advantage of the high altitude and dry air at the pole for clear observation of infrared and submillimeter wavelengths.</p>
        <p>Foundations for the center have been laid and completion is planned for next year. The consortium's "tipper," an antenna that measures microwaves from space, has already operated. Scientists hope the instrument will help assess how much microwaves from space are affected by different thicknesses of atmosphere.</p>
        <p>A mile away a Princeton University reflector, shielded against sunlight, has sought variations in brightness of the residual radiation attributed to the Big Bang, the hypothetical explosion from which the universe originated. Scientists from the University of California at Berkeley and the University of Milan in Italy used an antenna 10 feet in diameter to determine how much radiation from the Milky Way is superimposed on that from the Big Bang. Antennas designed for specific frequencies made recordings to see how the Big Bang radiation varied with frequency.</p>
        <p>Another special advantage of the pole station is in earthquake detection. Roger Barlow, who operates seismic detectors at the site, directly on the earth's spin axis, said in an interview that the detectors make it possible to record tremors from distant earthquakes whose travel times have been unaffected by the earth's rotation. There can be no comparable station at the North Pole, which is on drifting ice.</p>
        <p>This summer two flights of giant balloons have been conducted from the main base at McMurdo Sound and one, according to Dr. Lynch, was able to record radiation from the sun continuously for 13 1/2 days. At lower latitudes, the altitude of such balloons varies with the day-night cycle. Here it remained constantly at 130,000 feet as winds carried it in a broad spiraling circle around the pole.</p>
        <p>After the balloons dropped to the ice, both were recovered by ski-equipped aircraft. The second flight, however, landed on ice about 13,000 feet above sea level, where the air is very thin. A four-engined Hercules turbojet landed, loaded the fallen balloon and its payload, and tried to take off. After 12 attempts failed, because of the thin air, the load was dumped and later had to be recovered by a twin-engine Otter plane.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lynch noted, however, that such balloon flights demonstrated how much could be learned, compared with missions dependent on costly space shuttles.</p>
        <p>Long-standing observations from the pole include those of the aurora, ionosphere, weather, thinning of the earth's protective ozone layer, ultraviolet radiation penetrating through it and the fluorocarbons blamed for the loss of ozone. They are made both outdoors on the frigid plateau and inside the buildings of the main base, protected from wind by an unheated geodesic dome 200 feet wide and 50 feet high.</p>
        <p>Researchers from other countries are also taking advantage of Antarctica's unique features. At Dome C, an abandoned camp 1,100 miles from the pole in the direction of Australia where the ice is 11,240 feet above sea level and 13,780 feet thick, French scientists hope to extract samples of ice formed by snow that fell during the next-to-last ice age and determine the carbon dioxide composition of air trapped in that snow.</p>
        <p>The Russians are doing similar work at Vostok, 400 miles to the southwest of Dome C, but, lacking aircraft capable of reaching there, are bringing their relief crew to the main American base at McMurdo Sound. From there they will be flown in by an American plane.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
