<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Acts the Spoiler in Global Climate Talks; Telltale Coral Stress</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOREAU, THOMAS J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC1130F937A15756C0A964958260" item-length="410" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Acts the Spoiler in Global Climate Talks; Telltale Coral Stress</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"The World's Oceans Are Sending an S O S" (The Week in Review, May 3) rightly notes the importance of coral bleaching as an early warning sign of global degradation, but misidentifies the nature of this alarming phenomenon and its major cause.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"The World's Oceans Are Sending an S O S" (The Week in Review, May 3) rightly notes the importance of coral bleaching as an early warning sign of global degradation, but misidentifies the nature of this alarming phenomenon and its major cause.</p>
        <p>Coral bleaching results from stress-induced expulsion of microscopic algae from coral tissues, which obtain most of their food and color from the tiny algae. Bleached corals turn transparent, exposing the white limestone skeleton beneath. They are starving and cannot grow or reproduce, but not necessarily dead.</p>
        <p>Like trees defoliated by caterpillars, corals can recover if the stress is sufficiently mild, brief and infrequent. Increasingly they are dying, as bleaching hits reefs again and again. Dead corals are quickly overgrown by other organisms, so even complete coral mortality does not result in "death of the entire ecosystem." But it wipes out the only organisms capable of building the dynamic wave-resistant framework on which all other reef species depend.</p>
        <p>While sewage, erosion, boat damage and unsustainable harvesting methods are devastating reefs near population centers and have caused some local bleaching, they are not the cause of recent mass bleaching episodes. Many such events occurred in years not marked by the damaging El Nino currents of the southern Pacific and at sites remote from human influence. They took place following months of ocean temperatures more than 1 degree Celsius above average during the hottest months.</p>
        <p>Mass bleaching events are increasing in frequency and severity: they took place in four out of the last five years in the Caribbean, after being unknown in the 1950's, 60's and 70's. Many corals around the world are now at risk from heat shock, irrespective of local pollution or stresses.</p>
        <p>Like the ozone hole, coral bleaching is an unanticipated observation that clearly shows the effects of climate change are more severe and immediate than we thought, and suggests that action to control climatically active gases is far more urgent. Failure to control all stresses to reefs, including global warming, may destroy key components of our natural heritage if the exceptionally high temperatures of the last decade continue.</p>
        <p>The costs to tropical fisheries, tourism, shore protection and biodiversity will be vast if action is not prompt. THOMAS J. GOREAU President, Global Coral Reef Alliance Chappaqua, N.Y., May 10, 1992</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
