<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Region: Connecticut and Westchester; More Home Builders Sparing the Trees</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MADISON (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN FORESTRY ASSN</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ASSN OF HOME BUILDERS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA1738F936A25750C0A964958260" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Region: Connecticut and Westchester; More Home Builders Sparing the Trees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR decades, the American Forestry Association and the National Association of Homebuilders have been perceived as mortal enemies, with the foresters urging tree conservation and the home builders clear-cutting the land for easier and cheaper construction.</p>
        <p>But two years ago, in response to environmental concerns, a program was developed in a joint effort by the two adversaries. It is called Global Releaf, and it seeks to teach developers how to achieve more tree preservation, thereby reducing energy costs, absorbing carbon dioxide, slowing erosion, and making properties more salable. Participation is voluntary, and information is distributed through the National Homebuilders Association in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR decades, the American Forestry Association and the National Association of Homebuilders have been perceived as mortal enemies, with the foresters urging tree conservation and the home builders clear-cutting the land for easier and cheaper construction.</p>
        <p>But two years ago, in response to environmental concerns, a program was developed in a joint effort by the two adversaries. It is called Global Releaf, and it seeks to teach developers how to achieve more tree preservation, thereby reducing energy costs, absorbing carbon dioxide, slowing erosion, and making properties more salable. Participation is voluntary, and information is distributed through the National Homebuilders Association in Washington.</p>
        <p>"A home with trees is more likely to sell, and sell faster than one without," said Phillip D. Rodbell of the American Forestry Association in Washington. "It's not just beautification. Homeowners can save 20 percent on heating and 40 percent on air-conditioning with strategically positioned trees that provide shade and block the wind."</p>
        <p>Because the program is so new, only one project, in Indiana, has been completed and certified to date. But 75 developers have submitted applications nationwide and programs are active in Canada, Britain, Germany, Costa Rica, Hungary, Ukraine and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Projects in the Northeast include one each in Maine, Massachusetts, New York and Connecticut. In the last, lots of just over an acre are being sited, graded and landscaped according to Global Releaf guidelines in Stanton Court, a nine-lot subdivision in Madison.</p>
        <p>"This is an instance where a developer has not gone in and raped the land," said James Keane, who works for Southern New England Telephone in New Haven.</p>
        <p>He and his wife, Judy, are building a house at Stanton Court designed by their own architect and scheduled for completion this fall.</p>
        <p>As in all Global Releaf projects, the Keanes agreed to accept the developer's oversight on all aspects of building and landscaping.</p>
        <p>"The tree work adds to the cost of the house," Mr. Keane said, "but the homeowner would have to landscape eventually anyway. Here you don't have to wait for the trees to grow."</p>
        <p>Most of the land at Stanton Court will remain forested naturally or by enhancement. Robert E. Dowler, the developer, has transplanted 3,000 Douglas firs, 6 to 35 feet in height, and 350 native specimen trees and shrubs from his own nursery onto the nine lots at a cost of $75,000 for labor alone.</p>
        <p>"WE are just getting back to basics," he said. "In Europe and New England, homes were clustered around a green or square, surrounded by farms and woods. It was a practical use of space. But we got away from that with the ugly grids of the 50's through the 70's, when people needed housing."</p>
        <p>He does the planning for the Strathmore Group Ltd., a family firm in a building next to his home in Stanton Court. His son, Christopher, is in charge of construction, his wife, Allyce, and daughter-in-law, Donna, handle the administrative chores, keeping salaries within the family.</p>
        <p>Landscaping costs are minimized by growing nursery stock on limited parcels of the 150 acres that the Dowlers own in Madison and Killingworth, supplying plant material for Stanton Court and the company's three other subdivisions.</p>
        <p>Father and son usually design the houses and employ a draftsman to draw up the plans, thus avoiding architectural fees. And, Mr. Dowler says, "I bought real estate in down markets during the early 1980's and in recent foreclosure sales."</p>
        <p>The cost to developers participating in Global Releaf, eventually getting certification and public recognition for the effort, is $300 for 25 acres or less and up to $1,550 for 101 acres. The costs cover processing applications, random spot checks and final review for certification.</p>
        <p>Developers must also hire a natural-resource expert to develop a master plan, tag trees for conservation, work with municipal departments in laying out roads, setbacks, rights of way and easements and be present through the construction period.</p>
        <p>Terry Deshefy-Longhi, Stanton Court's natural-resource expert, added: "We make sure that there is ground cover to keep the soil warm enough for indigenous plant, insect and animal life. We know which trees supply habitat for owls; that clumps of evergreens provide shelter for red fox nests, and how to insure suitable nesting places for deer, chipmunks, possum and raccoons."</p>
        <p>Her other duties include supervising tree replacement where clearing is necessary, transplanting indigenous species, recycling or composting excess material within the site and preparing a manual on the care of trees and plantings for each homeowner.</p>
        <p>The houses, all center-hall colonials, are priced at $350,000 to $450,000 and range from 2,800 square feet to 4,800 square feet. They have imposing circular stairways, three to four bedrooms, two and a half to three and a half baths, large closets, dressing-sitting rooms, decks and living rooms with sliding doors that open onto family rooms and country kitchens complete with appliances.</p>
        <p>Two houses have been sold and a third is available. There are no furnished models.</p>
        <p>"Too expensive," Chris Dowler said.</p>
        <p>Exterior colors are muted and doors, windows and corners are embellished with decorative wood trim, but the siding is aluminum in response to what Mr. Dowler says is the public's choice. Since the Government banned the use of mercury in house paint about five years ago, mildew and other problems have made frequent repainting of wood siding costly.</p>
        <p>GLOBAL RELEAF'S program is available to anyone, and it has a fund available for nonprofit affordable housing through the support of some 80 corporations. Texaco is the largest contributor, at $1 million a year, while Reebok, Amway, the Dayton-Hudson Department Store in Detroit, Mr. Coffee, the American Mortgage Banking Company on Long Island and others participate with money, marketing and tree-planting by volunteer employees.</p>
        <p>Building-code officials might not agree, but Debra Bassert, land-use planner for the National Homebuilders Association, finds that "some developers who want to save trees can't, because of antiquated local regulations."</p>
        <p>"It might be beneficial to ease old standards for road widths, grade requirements, curb and gutter installations without sacrificing safety," she added. "It's expensive to snake roads through trees, but less so if they are narrower."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
