<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Westminster Abbey, 7 Centuries New</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="552005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTMINSTER ABBEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC163AF930A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Westminster Abbey, 7 Centuries New</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH its great west front surrounded by a latticework of scaffolding for much of the past few years, like the nearby tower of the Palace of Westminster looming over the House of Lords, Westminster Abbey has long looked like a building that was still under construction, though it's seven centuries old.</p>
        <p>But with a 20-year restoration of the external stone of the entire vast structure finally beginning to draw to a close, the scaffolding has come down, revealing an astonishing white facade whose every detail stands out brilliantly, after years of crumbling away under acid rain and black 19th-century soot.  Like Notre Dame in Paris, the abbey, though in the English capital, is one of the world's great French Gothic buildings. Its patron, Henry III, and his master mason, Henry de Reyns, were clearly inspired by the buildings at Paris and Rheims when they designed the replacement of the existing Romanesque abbey in the mid-13th century. The architects prized the soaring vaults and clean lines of the French models of the era, though the purity has been cluttered up inside by the many monuments to English history that tourists come to see today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH its great west front surrounded by a latticework of scaffolding for much of the past few years, like the nearby tower of the Palace of Westminster looming over the House of Lords, Westminster Abbey has long looked like a building that was still under construction, though it's seven centuries old.</p>
        <p>But with a 20-year restoration of the external stone of the entire vast structure finally beginning to draw to a close, the scaffolding has come down, revealing an astonishing white facade whose every detail stands out brilliantly, after years of crumbling away under acid rain and black 19th-century soot.  Like Notre Dame in Paris, the abbey, though in the English capital, is one of the world's great French Gothic buildings. Its patron, Henry III, and his master mason, Henry de Reyns, were clearly inspired by the buildings at Paris and Rheims when they designed the replacement of the existing Romanesque abbey in the mid-13th century. The architects prized the soaring vaults and clean lines of the French models of the era, though the purity has been cluttered up inside by the many monuments to English history that tourists come to see today.</p>
        <p>The restoration, and clean-air legislation that has banned the burning of coal or wood in London's city limits, have allowed the abbey to be reborn. A building that generations of visitors probably thought had always been black is emerging as something else altogether, in gleaming ocher and white limestone.</p>
        <p>The external restoration will have cost $:25 million, or about $48 million at today's exchange rates, by the time it is finished in 1995. The nave and the two transepts are now clean, and the west front, the tallest in Britain at 225 feet from the tips of the towers that Sir Christopher Wren finally had built (in distinctly English, not French, style, and arguably not Gothic at all) to the base, is mostly clean, though some repair work continues on the lower portals.</p>
        <p>Now the last phase of the restoration has begun, on the last major addition to the abbey. This is the early 16th-century Henry VII Chapel, a completely Tudor addition to the original French-inspired abbey. The chapel juts like a dark finger from the apse toward the medieval Westminster Hall in the Houses of Parliament.</p>
        <p>Until now, most of the chapel, one of the glories of the uniquely English Perpendicular style of Gothic, has remained pockmarked and blackened as a consequence of the thousands of London fogs in the 19th and early 20th centuries.</p>
        <p>"The restoration that has been going on since 1973 of most of the external fabric of the abbey is the most thorough it has ever had," said the man who has the job of keeping it in order, the Surveyor of the Fabric, appropriately named Donald R. Buttress. Mr. Buttress, a bearded North Countryman whose opinions about architecture and the abbey are strong enough to lean up against, said the work on the Henry VII Chapel was urgently needed and would take most of the next three years.</p>
        <p>Last done over in Bath stone around 1820 at a cost to the government of the day of $:20,000, the chapel's exterior has suffered greatly in the intervening years. The parapets and pinnacles and the fantastical greyhounds, lions and grotesque beasts that the Tudors carved into the tops of the chapel buttresses are worn down and leprous-looking. "Some of the pollution we're taking off is two to three inches thick," Mr. Buttress said.</p>
        <p>The massive job of restoring the abbey was first undertaken, 400 years after its construction, by Wren, the first Surveyor. Wren rebuilt and refaced much of the abbey in creamy-brown Burford stone. But his 19th-century successors, Edward Blore, Sir Gilbert Scott and later J. L. Pearson, refaced it in softer stone from Chilmark, near Salisbury. This had stood up well at Salisbury Cathedral, which is faced with it, but was, in Mr. Buttress's words, "an explosive disaster" in the polluted atmosphere of industrial London.</p>
        <p>Sulfur in the air combined with moisture in the atmosphere and the stone to eat away at it like cancer, an effect that can also be seen in the soft Caen stone from Normandy used in the Henry VII Chapel.</p>
        <p>This time white Portland stone will replace the chapel's octagonal turret tops, from which gilded weather vanes, as originally planned, will fly. The stone, from the island off Dorset, will also bring out the beasts as the proud Tudors intended these emblems to be seen. "It's the stone that St. Paul's Cathedral, and Wren's City churches, are built of," his successor said.</p>
        <p>Wren, in fact, had wanted to give the abbey, formally the Collegiate Church of St. Peter, a tower over the crossing of the transepts of the nave, but the money went instead to build his design for St. Paul's -- "robbing Peter to pay Paul."</p>
        <p>Mr. Buttress would love to have been able to replace the statues that used to stand in niches toward the top of the chapel, but even the $7.6 million that this restoration will cost is not enough to do that.</p>
        <p>All of the money for the abbey's restoration has so far been privately raised by a committee headed by the Duke of Edinburgh, husband of Queen Elizabeth II. Since the Reformation, the abbey, which was a monastery in the Middle Ages, has been a "royal peculiar" directly dependent on the monarch, who is head of the Church of England.</p>
        <p>The philanthropist Sir John Templeton has already donated nearly $2 million to the restoration of the Henry VII Chapel, the home of the Order of the Bath. He will be memorialized with a stained glass heraldic window at the west end; most of the original glass was destroyed during the Reformation and in World War II.</p>
        <p>The abbey is hoping to raise an additional $3.7 million for the chapel and for the west front restoration from donors in the United States and Canada. Those who want to seize the opportunity to immortalize themselves along with those commemorated in Poets' Corner can do so, with panels of stained glass bearing their names ($150,000 apiece), and nameplates in brass plates in the narthex ($50,000). For $10,000 a donor's initials will be carved into one of 130 of the stone shields, about six inches wide, that decorate the outside walls, just above head level on top of the stone foundation.</p>
        <p>All, of course, as a token of gratitude for contributing to the cost of the restoration, said the Very Rev. Colin Semper, one of the canons of the abbey, who will take the appeal to the United States this fall with the famous choir of men and boys.</p>
        <p>The chapel, originally intended as a shrine to the Virgin Mary, is decorated with a uniquely English fan-vaulted ceiling and a splendid set of 16th-century oak choir stalls, with the flags of the Order of the Bath. VISITING A SHRINE Getting In</p>
        <p>The abbey's interior can be visited free, though a donation of about $2 is suggested. To see the interior of the Henry VII Chapel and the other royal chapels there is an admission fee of $6, which covers the coronation throne, the 12th-century shrine to Edward the Confessor and Poets' Corner. Musical Tour</p>
        <p>Under the direction of Martin Neary, organist and master of the Choristers, the Westminster Abbey choir, one of the best of those in the nearly milennium-old English choral tradition, will begin a United States tour this fall by singing Evensong on Sept. 22 at St. Thomas Church on Fifth Avenue and 53d Street in New York. Other stops will include Atlanta, Huntsville, Ala., Omaha, Lincoln, Neb., Minneapolis, Denver, San Francisco, Houston, Dallas and Charlotte, N.C. The tour will end in New York on Oct. 11 with a concert at 4 P.M. in Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center. More information: Karen McFarlane Artists Inc., (216) 721-9095.</p>
        <p>CRAIG R. WHITNEY is head of the London bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">CRAIG R. WHITNEY is head of the London bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
