<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; A Flock of Warnings</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GUSSOW, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WELLMAN, MAC</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MURDER OF CROWS, A (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DD173AF932A35756C0A964958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; A Flock of Warnings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GUSSOW, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Mac Wellman's apocalyptic vision, civilization is facing a Love Canal of the mind and body. The view is as urgent as it is fearful. It is an ecological nightmare, as weather reports from past centuries become auguries of approaching climatic catastrophe. No matter where we are, "we are downwind of something peculiar." Mr. Wellman's scathing new comedy, "A Murder of Crows" (at Primary Stages), is a red alert, to be ignored at one's peril. Acid rain is coming, and the playwright is our caustic commentator and meteorologist.</p>
        <p>The medium for his warning is a Middle-American mire. The people in this anonymous small town have moved past hard times to desperate days. As one character says, with full symbolism intended, "It's lucky the shallow end is near the beach." Otherwise everyone would drown in sludge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Mac Wellman's apocalyptic vision, civilization is facing a Love Canal of the mind and body. The view is as urgent as it is fearful. It is an ecological nightmare, as weather reports from past centuries become auguries of approaching climatic catastrophe. No matter where we are, "we are downwind of something peculiar." Mr. Wellman's scathing new comedy, "A Murder of Crows" (at Primary Stages), is a red alert, to be ignored at one's peril. Acid rain is coming, and the playwright is our caustic commentator and meteorologist.</p>
        <p>The medium for his warning is a Middle-American mire. The people in this anonymous small town have moved past hard times to desperate days. As one character says, with full symbolism intended, "It's lucky the shallow end is near the beach." Otherwise everyone would drown in sludge.</p>
        <p>In free-flowing Wellman fashion, there is a sense of surrealism afoot, which to cynics among us may seem scandalously close to reality. A prophet of misfortune, the author pinpoints the poisons in everyday life, describing how mankind is polluting the planet. He is also out to smash that other American dream, of getting something for nothing, and, with devilish glee, he mocks our hypocrisy about true and false heroics. A survivor of the war in the Persian Gulf comes home and literally turns into a public monument. He is gold-leafed and frozen on a pedestal.</p>
        <p>Watching the grotesqueries unfold, one may ask why the play is so amusing. The answer is easy. Mr. Wellman has a gymnast's sense of equilibrium and a clownish sense of comedy. In virtuosic form in this new play, he never allows his danse macabre to become a dirge. There are hints of early Sam Shepard and of the socially conscious side of Franz Xaver Kroetz, but with the author's original voice.</p>
        <p>Characters exorcise their anxieties, sometimes in direct address to the audience. Confessionals become riffs: from mother, daughter, crusty uncle Howard and his Klan-leaning wife (who could be a fugitive from Mr. Wellman's redneck romp, "Sincerity Forever"). Even the statuesque war hero finally takes the opportunity to talk back. And a father who seemed to be dead magically returns to life, looking as encrusted as if he had been weekending in a Dumpster. In the background are three scavenger crows, mocking and baiting what is left of humanity.</p>
        <p>"A Murder of Crows" is an exact meeting of play and production, as the director Jim Simpson animates a devious text into a dexterous performance. Many of the actors are experienced Wellman interpreters. The cast knows that in this comic territory overstatement would be damaging. The bizarre becomes matter-of-fact and the matter-of-fact seems bizarre.</p>
        <p>Annie O'Sullivan and Jan Leslie Harding are distorted mirror images as embattled mother and daughter. William Mesnik is dryly bemused as Uncle Howard, even as his wife (Lauren Hamilton) waxes prejudiciously. That essential Wellman spokesman, Steve Mellor, expounds with a customary loop-the-loop circumlocution. In the hands of the actors, words fly fast.</p>
        <p>Among the crows is David Van Tieghem, who is also responsible for the music and sound, a synchronized tapestry that ranges from sitcom strains to a pulsating beat that would be equally at home in Hitchcock. The designer, Kyle Chepulis, outdoes his previous Wellman efforts with an imaginative setting that poses its own danger.</p>
        <p>The stage is seeping, as water drains ominously toward the front row of the audience. The dripping is incessant. This play needs a plumber! At one point, there is a sudden shower. Actors raise umbrellas, but, like the characters they are playing, they are unable to duck for cover. In Mr. Wellman's ringing incitement, the world ends not with another big bang, but with a chorus of crows mischievously tapping and singing their way through the metaphorical landscape. A Murder of Crows  By Mac Wellman; directed by Jim Simpson; scenery designer, Kyle Chepulis; costume designer, Bruce Goodrich; lighting by Brian Aldous; composer and sound designer, David Van Tieghem; choreography, Tina Dudek; production stage manager, Melanie White; production assistant, Amy Gaipa; associate artist director, Janet Reed. Presented by Casey Childs, artistic director, Primary Stages Company, in association with Douglas Durst. At Primary Stages, 354 West 45th Street, Manhattan. Nella . . . Anne O'Sullivan Susannah . . . Jan Leslie Harding Howard . . . William Mesnik Georgia . . . Lauren Hamilton Raymond . . . Steve Mellor Andy . . . Reed Birney Crow No. 1 . . . Tina Dudek Crow No. 2 . . . Ray Xifo Crow No. 3 . . . David Van Tieghem</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
