<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Problems at White House Persist 2 Months Into New Chief's Tenure</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506884"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIDES AND EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SKINNER, SAMUEL K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DARMAN, RICHARD G (BUDGET DIR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DA1639F932A25751C0A964958260" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Problems at White House Persist 2 Months Into New Chief's Tenure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSENTHAL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENTHAL, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two months after John H. Sununu's removal, Administration officials and Republican advisers say the organizational and political problems that the former chief of staff left behind still plague the White House.</p>
        <p>The new chief of staff, Samuel K. Skinner, has tried to make his mark by smoothing relations between the White House and the campaign and by undertaking a much-advertised reorganization of the White House staff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two months after John H. Sununu's removal, Administration officials and Republican advisers say the organizational and political problems that the former chief of staff left behind still plague the White House.</p>
        <p>The new chief of staff, Samuel K. Skinner, has tried to make his mark by smoothing relations between the White House and the campaign and by undertaking a much-advertised reorganization of the White House staff.</p>
        <p>The reorganization, like the chief of staff himself, is too fresh to be judged fully. But Mr. Skinner's influence has been evident in Mr. Bush's sudden willingness to recognize the reality of the current recession and to compromise with Congress where Mr. Sununu had been unbending, as on a 13-week extension of unemployment benefits and on restrictions on chemicals that damage the atmospheric ozone layer. 'Pretty Substantial Team'</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner said he had appointed a "pretty substantial team." Since he has been in the job he has helped President Bush produce an economic growth plan and a proposal for health care changes that Republicans were demanding of the White House for months.</p>
        <p>But the economic plan has received as much criticism as praise, with critics saying it reflects the continued influence of Richard G. Darman, the budget director, rather than any new direction.</p>
        <p>A number of Administration officials and Republicans say President Bush is still hobbled by disjointed communications, poorly planned campaign trips, squabbling over domestic policy and rivalries among policy makers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner is known to be frustrated by what he regards as the marginal competence of some holdovers from the Sununu period, but feels that he cannot clean house too abruptly for reasons of public relations and morale.</p>
        <p>The overall picture that emerges is that of a rocky first month of an election year, with Republican strategists and some Administration officials giving Mr. Skinner's performance mediocre grades but hoping that the President, Mr. Skinner and the campaign team can restore the political edge and efficiency of Mr. Bush's 1988 operation.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the White House reorganization is the appointment of Clayton K. Yeutter, the former Agriculture Secretary, to a new post charged with centralizing what had been a diffuse policy-making apparatus. But even before Mr. Yeutter takes office, Mr. Skinner has made clear that his job will be as a "broker" of ideas, not as the architect of policy.</p>
        <p>And many Republicans questioned whether the appointment of Mr. Yeutter gave Mr. Bush much political benefit externally or extra policy muscle internally. Similarly, many of Mr. Bush's aides and advisers questioned the appointment of Andrew H. Card Jr., a White House aide, as Transportation Secretary in an election year when Mr. Bush might have benefited from choosing a woman, a member of a minority or someone who also came from outside the department but who represented some useful political constituency.</p>
        <p>On the political side, Mr. Skinner has formed a potentially powerful partnership with Mr. Bush's campaign chairman, Robert M. Teeter, which both men are counting on to give them influence over policy in the campaign. The two men have put together a more aggressive schedule for Mr. Bush in the week remaining before the New Hampshire primary. The President plans to announce his candidacy formally on Wednesday at two events, one in Washington and the other in New Hampshire. He will spend the entire weekend in New Hampshire instead of just Saturday, as originally planned.</p>
        <p>Disappointed officials and party strategists called the White House reorganization a series of compromises and half-measures that reflected Mr. Bush's basic conviction that there was nothing wrong with his staff or his policies, that the economy would soon right itself and that he would be re-elected in November.</p>
        <p>"The President is not panicked enough to think things really have to change," one official said.</p>
        <p>Officials and party strategists said Mr. Skinner had also not challenged the dominance of Mr. Darman and Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady.</p>
        <p>Nor have Mr. Skinner's changes filled what a senior Republican called a "vacuum" in the White House: No one has emerged to fill James A. Baker 3d's role of previous campaigns -- giving Mr. Bush unvarnished counsel and carrying the weight, as one strategist put it, "to make him stick to the script when he has to." On the Campaign Trail</p>
        <p>This absence of direction seems evident in Mr. Bush's performance on the campaign trail, where he has stumbled through several erratic speeches with little in the way of a coherent political message. The President, never a master ad-libber, has ad-libbed his way through small-bore appearances -- looking out of touch as he marveled at electronic scanners at a mock supermarket or, as he did in New Hampshire last month, repeating his stage directions ("Message: I care").</p>
        <p>In Washington, Cabinet members continue to question major policy decisions, sometimes in public. Housing Secretary Jack F. Kemp Jr. calledsome of the President's budget proposals "gimmicks" and was then forced to apologize.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Darman openly challenged Mr. Yeutter. "I work for the President," Mr. Darman snapped when asked if Mr. Yeutter would have authority over him.</p>
        <p>John P. Sears, a former campaign manager for President Ronald Reagan, said: "They don't have any politicians in the place. Politicians used to be those guys who didn't run for office and helped those who did. There was another category of people that used to be called candidates, who ran for office. That's what they've got, candidates and no politicians."</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner, who is concerned enough about his image to call a reporter back the day after an interview to offer names of lawmakers who would say he is doing a good job, tersely dismissed criticism of his performance as "carping."</p>
        <p>He said his new team would mend President Bush's ailing domestic policy apparatus. "The President gave me the latitude to backfill in some key positions," he said, "and we believe with the talent that's here we've put together a team that will do a great job for him. The President would not have made a change like this if he didn't think there was a problem."</p>
        <p>Administration officials credit Mr. Skinner with ending a reign of fear under Mr. Sununu, permitting more voices to be heard in Mr. Bush's councils and stopping short of a clean sweep through the White House staff.</p>
        <p>But officials said that the openness often produced a cacophony, not new ideas, and that Mr. Skinner was still groping for control under intense pressure from the unfolding campaign.</p>
        <p>Officials also said it was not compassion that prevented wholesale dismissals at the White House but the pressures of the budget and the campaign, coupled with a reluctance by Mr. Skinner to take on Mr. Darman and Mr. Brady.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Yeutter, who was named a counselor to the President for domestic affairs, Mr. Skinner, acting with Mr. Bush's approval, named Henson Moore, the Deputy Secretary of Energy, as the deputy chief of staff, and Sherrie Rollins as director of public liaison. He added the job of coordinating all White House communications to the portfolio of Marlin Fitzwater, the White House spokesman. 'Fresh New Advice'</p>
        <p>"When you have two former Cabinet officers with records of their own in top staff jobs," Mr. Skinner said, "plus one of the strongest deputies in the Cabinet, who is a former Congressman, you're going to bring into the process some fresh new advice and counsel."</p>
        <p>But Bush advisers and aides said moving Mr. Yeutter to the White House from chairman of the Republican National Committee was primarily intended to make a space at the top of the party for Richard N. Bond, a longtime Bush aide considered a more able political tactician and spokesman.</p>
        <p>Many Administration officials and Bush advisers doubt Mr. Yeutter will be able to exert his will over Mr. Darman.</p>
        <p>Last week, at a breakfast with reporters, Mr. Darman offered this characteristically complex locution when asked if Mr. Skinner's reorganization would diminish his authority:</p>
        <p>"I can't think of an answer to that question that would not cause me a problem," he said. "If I were to say that I thought my influence would increase, you would write that Darman is characteristically arrogant and who knows what else. If I were to say that I thought my influence would decrease, you would say, Darman's, well, diminished. If I were to say about the same, it would make a whole lot of people unhappy."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
