<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Under Fire In Talks at U.N. On Environment</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="516509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1E31F937A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Under Fire In Talks at U.N. On Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, March 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rich and poor countries attending a five-week conference here say the United States is endangering prospects for the international environmental meeting planned for Rio de Janeiro next June.</p>
        <p>These countries say that by refusing to promise more environmental aid to the third world or to set limits for emissions of gases that contribute to global warming, the United States threatens to sabotage the two most important agreements to be taken up at the Rio meeting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rich and poor countries attending a five-week conference here say the United States is endangering prospects for the international environmental meeting planned for Rio de Janeiro next June.</p>
        <p>These countries say that by refusing to promise more environmental aid to the third world or to set limits for emissions of gases that contribute to global warming, the United States threatens to sabotage the two most important agreements to be taken up at the Rio meeting.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the Rio talks, which are expected to draw thousands of participants from more than 170 countries, is to plan for a world economy that can continue to grow without irreversible ecological damage. Cleanup Plan Threated</p>
        <p>The American stand threatens Agenda 21, an ambitious, international environmental cleanup plan for the next century, because of third world requests for additional aid and new environmental technologies from industrialized northern countries.</p>
        <p>The 12 European Community countries as well as Canada and Scandinavia are ready to give additional aid, but have not committed themselves to specific amounts.</p>
        <p>There has been no visible result so far from a meeting last week of the conference's Secretary General, Maurice F. Strong of Canada, with Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady, the national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft, and the the White House chief of staff, Samuel P. Skinner, in an effort to change the American position.</p>
        <p>Today Senator Al Gore, a Democrat from Tennessee who will lead the Senate contingent to the Rio meetings, told delegates that the United States must exercise leadership to insure their success, saying that at a minimum agreement must be reached on "new and additional" aid to the third world and on the stabilization of emissions.</p>
        <p>"The United States must use its moral authority, its political and economic strength and its leadership skills to resolve the impasses that are frustrating progress," Senator Gore said.</p>
        <p>America's reluctance to commit itself to freezing its emissions of "greenhouse" gases at 1990 levels by the year 2000 imperils agreement on the planned new international convention on stabilizing the global climate, which is supposed to be the centerpiece of the Rio agreement.</p>
        <p>Last week the Environmental Protection Agency administrator, William K. Reilly, told the conference that the Administration planned no fundamental changes in its position on climate change, saying it would continue to resist "top down directives or commitments and targets, the costs and consequences of which we have not yet fully assessed."</p>
        <p>While Washington opposes specific, binding commitments on cutting emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases, Mr. Reilly said that the United States was still committed to reducing these emissions through practical action. 'A Futile Exercise'</p>
        <p>In an effort to save the separate negotiations on the climate treaty, the United States and about 20 other countries have been invited to a meeting in Paris on April 15, Portugal, the current president of the European Community, announced today. The participants will try to resolve the standoff before the final round of negotiations opens in New York on April 30.</p>
        <p>"It would be a pity if the convention had to be postponed until after Rio," Portugal's representative to the United Nations, Joao Pereira Bastos, said at a news conference, adding that Europe would find an American-style convention that did not require detailed commitments unacceptably weak. In a clear reference to the United States, Mr. Bastos said it would be "a futile exercise" for Europe to press ahead with its own climate stabilization plan unless "other regions" joined in.</p>
        <p>Partly because of these disagreements, the conference of more than 170 countries meeting here to prepare the agenda for the Rio meeting has entered its fourth week with little progress to report.</p>
        <p>But progress is also being slowed, delegates say, by the breadth and complexity of the agenda because it identifies poverty and its effects as a fundamental environmental threat and says that only when it has been abolished will the global environment be safe. As a result, the conference is bogged down in quarrels over economic and social issues that at first sight seem far removed from the environment, including debt relief, slum clearance, the Uruguay Round of trade talks and subsidies for northern farmers that block the agricultural exports of poor countries.</p>
        <p>These issues complicate the negotiating process by taking up time and reopening old quarrels between the North and the South. The fact that many of these questions are the subject of continuing negotiations in other international forums makes the discussions here even more complex.</p>
        <p>"With 60 percent of our time gone, we've only negotiated 5 to 10 percent of the output," Canada's chief delegate, John Bell, who is chairman of the group dealing with financial questions, said last week. "Increased funding for the developing world is absolutely central. It's frustrating we haven't even started negotiations."</p>
        <p>Asked about America's reluctance to provide aid, Pakistan's United Nations representative, Jamsheed K. A. Marker, current president of the Group of 77, as the developing countries call themselves, said that he did not wish to single out the policies of any individual countries for public criticism. But in an interview he made clear that the developing world remained unhappy with Washington's stance, saying: "Without financial commitments it is difficult to know how this will all end. That's the biggest stumbling block for the developing world."</p>
        <p>Chile's delegate, Vincent Sanchez, said: "This conference could fail. We've agreed absolutely nothing of real significance so far."</p>
        <p>Already, an important attempt to draft a convention to save the world's rain forests has collapsed because mainly northern, industrial countries and southern, undeveloped countries cannot agree on who is to blame for their destruction. Progress Is Expected</p>
        <p>While few delegates deny that the Rio preparatory conference has reached a critical phase, some say progress will pick up in the two remaining weeks as countries realize time is running out. "These big conferences usually reach a low point about now," said Britain's delegate, Fiona McConnell. "It's often darkest just before the dawn."</p>
        <p>But increasingly participants here say that the Rio meetings must be judged less on concrete agreements than on broad global initiatives to make economic development environmentally sustainable.</p>
        <p>"Rio must be seen as the start of a process, not the end," Mr. Strong, the conference's Secretary General, said today.</p>
        <p>The last world environmental conference, held in Stockholm 20 years ago, resulted in most governments' creating environmental ministries.</p>
        <p>Agenda 21, the 800-page global environmental action plan, lays down new goals in virtually every field.</p>
        <p>To carry out their part of this agenda, developing countries say they will require $70 billion in additional aid each year over the $55 billion they now receive from northern industrialized countries. Relations Embittered</p>
        <p>Most industrialized nations are ready to make firm pledges of new resources and access to technology that will allow developing countries to make a safe transition to industrialization. But the United States continues to resist even a general commitment, even though it recently made an additional $75 million available in environmental aid for developing countries.</p>
        <p>The result, many delegates say, has been a general embittering of North-South relations at the conference, with the Group of 77 pushing a number of demands the northern countries consider extreme, politicized and unacceptable.</p>
        <p>In Rio, heads of state hope to adopt what is being called an "earth charter," a document northern countries foresee as a relatively short statement committing everyone to taking greater care of the environment -- "the sort of thing you hang on a classroom wall," one diplomat said.</p>
        <p>But the Group of 77 has submitted a long draft accusing northern countries of selfishly pushing the world toward ecological disaster through their greed. The draft demands sweeping changes in life styles and consumption patterns.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
