<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. PROGRESS SEEN IN REDUCING GASES</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="523753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D71E3AF936A15757C0A964958260" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. PROGRESS SEEN IN REDUCING GASES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new analysis by the Federal Government says that American emissions of gases believed to cause global warming may stabilize by the year 2000 at 1990 levels, because of steps to save energy or reduce pollution that are already planned or under way.</p>
        <p>The analysis is significant because the Bush Administration has consistently opposed signing an international agreement that would commit the United States to achieve such a goal, partly because of concern about costs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new analysis by the Federal Government says that American emissions of gases believed to cause global warming may stabilize by the year 2000 at 1990 levels, because of steps to save energy or reduce pollution that are already planned or under way.</p>
        <p>The analysis is significant because the Bush Administration has consistently opposed signing an international agreement that would commit the United States to achieve such a goal, partly because of concern about costs.</p>
        <p>But many of the actions analyzed in the new report are being undertaken to save money. "These are things you would do because they make good sense to do," said Eileen B. Claussen, director of the Office of Atmospheric and Indoor Air Programs at the Environmental Protection Agency, which collaborated with the Department of Energy, the State Department and other agencies to produce the analysis.</p>
        <p>The analysis says the steps that have been planned or already taken will reduce emissions of man-made, or "greenhouse," gases by 7 to 11 percent by the year 2000 below what they would otherwise have been. The main gas created by human activity is carbon dioxide, but smog, methane from landfills, nitrous oxide from combustion processes and chlorofluorocarbons used for refrigeration and other purposes also contribute to the problem. Greenhouse Theory Endorsed</p>
        <p>Scientists believe global temperatures are rising because increasing levels of such gases will trap and retain heat from the sun in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse. The new Federal analysis endorsed this theory. Global warming could cause sea levels to rise and disrupt the earth's biological system.</p>
        <p>In negotiations under the auspices of the United Nations that are scheduled to resume next week in New York, several European nations are seeking a pledge to freeze emissions at the 1990 levels by the turn of the century. That would mean a reduction of about 12 percent for the United States, according to Rafe Pomerance, a climate change expert at the World Resources Institute, a nonprofit environmental organization based in Washington.</p>
        <p>The steps analyzed by Federal scientists include an initiative by the Environmental Protection Agency to have companies use more efficient lights and motors; provisions of the National Energy Strategy, now before the Congress, to improve the efficiency of energy use and increase the use of natural gas, which produces less carbon dioxide, and research and development of renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>The total reductions are estimated at 125 million to 200 million metric tons in the year 2000. The carbon reduction is put at 87 million to 121 million tons, which could put carbon dioxide emissions below 1990's levels.</p>
        <p>Alden Meyer of the Union of Concerned Scientists, which has been active in issues involving global climate change, said said the United States had a great deal to gain by promising to do what it was likely to do anyway, because its willingness to sign a treaty would lead other nations to sign.</p>
        <p>American support is "the linchpin to a successful global warming treaty," Mr. Meyer said. While the current negotiations involve only industrialized nations, they must agree before third world countries will follow, he said.</p>
        <p>The study may add to international pressure on the Bush Administration to agree to a freeze in emissions, and is likely to generate more support in Congress for the move.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
