<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Studies Link Extinctions To Impact of Space Objects</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="551666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALEONTOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DINOSAURS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCE (MAGAZINE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARGOLIS, STANLEY V (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAEYS, PHILIPPE (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CASIER, JEAN-GEORGES (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLUM, JOEL D (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHAMBERLAIN, C PAGE (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D8133EF932A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Studies Link Extinctions To Impact of Space Objects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two teams of scientists are reporting new evidence that speeding objects from space struck the Earth 370 million and 65 million years ago, possibly disrupting the global climate and causing mass extinctions.</p>
        <p>The report on the 370-million-year-old impact raises to three the number of celestial collisions linked to major extinctions of life on Earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two teams of scientists are reporting new evidence that speeding objects from space struck the Earth 370 million and 65 million years ago, possibly disrupting the global climate and causing mass extinctions.</p>
        <p>The report on the 370-million-year-old impact raises to three the number of celestial collisions linked to major extinctions of life on Earth.</p>
        <p>"This is quite exciting," said Dr. David M. Raup, a paleontologist at the University of Chicago who believes periodic strikes from space have shaped the evolution of life.</p>
        <p>"When added to other clues," he said, "it's beginning to open up our thinking to the idea that impact is a much more pervasive cause of extinction" than is usually thought to be the case. Dispute Over Theories</p>
        <p>Scientific skeptics hold that natural causes, like volcanoes or slow climate change, are mainly responsible for the five mass extinctions revealed in the geologic record. At best, they say, the impact of large asteroids or comets may have contributed to mass exterminations already in progress by kicking up clouds of dust to block sunlight.</p>
        <p>The two new reports on extraterrestrial linkages appear in today's issue of the journal Science. The first is by three geologists, Dr. Stanley V. Margolis and Dr. Philippe Claeys at the University of California at Davis, and Dr. Jean-Georges Casier of the Belgian Royal Institute of Natural Sciences, in Brussels.</p>
        <p>It reports the discovery of tiny glass beads, called microtektites, in Belgium shale. They were deposited some 370 million years ago in the late Devonian period, when 70 percent of Earth's marine species mysteriously vanished. Among the hardest hit species were corals and trilobites, primitive creatures with segmented bodies that once dominated the oceans.</p>
        <p>While some glassy beads found in nature are volcanic in origin, the authors report that these tektites have varying shapes and a lack of bubbles that attest to their formation during a catastrophic impact, when molten rock was thrown skyward and then cooled in a rain of glassy debris.</p>
        <p>The beads, of which more than 400 were found in a rock layer two to four inches thick, are reported to have round, elongated, teardrop and dumbbell shapes. The authors said geochemical analysis strongly suggested that they were produced from a cosmic collision.</p>
        <p>While strikes from space have previously been suggested as the cause of the late Devonian extinction, with one proposal made as early as 1970, until now searches for geological evidence have always come up short.</p>
        <p>The discovery, the Science article said, strengthens the case for extraterrestrial impacts as the cause of worldwide mass extinctions of marine life during the late Devonian.</p>
        <p>The authors cited two craters as possible sources of the Belgian microtektites. One is the Siljan Ring in central Sweden, which is some 368 million years old and, at a diameter of 32 miles, is the largest known impact feature in Europe. Another candidate is the 29-mile Charlevoix Crater in Quebec, which is believed to be 350 million to 370 million years old.</p>
        <p>The second Science paper addresses the most recent and famous of the five great mass extinctions: the one at the end of the Cretaceous period, 65 million years ago, when the dinosaurs and two-thirds of all marine animal species were wiped out. Revealing Chemical Analysis</p>
        <p>Two geologists from Dartmouth College, Dr. Joel D. Blum and Dr. C. Page Chamberlain, report an analysis of 20 Haitian microtektites from that period that shows their chemistry is very similar to that of a crater some 110 miles in diameter beneath the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico. Both tektites and crater are largely made of limestone. Although the Haitian beads and the Yucatan crater have previously been linked by age, this report strengthens their chemical resemblance.</p>
        <p>The Dartmouth geologists also say that limestone melted by the cosmic impact probably released large amounts of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere, producing a greenhouse effect that, after impact dust cooled Earth for several years, could have increased global temperatures up to 10 degrees Fahrenheit over a period of 10,000 to 100,000 years.</p>
        <p>Such major shifts in Earth's climate, Dr. Blum said in a Dartmouth statement, "might have led to mass extinctions."</p>
        <p>In January, scientists tied another of the five main exterminations, at the end of the Triassic geological period some 200 million years ago, to a cosmic impact. They reported in Science the discovery of shattered quartz crystals embedded in Italian shale of the right age. The shocked quartz, as scientists call it, is considered one of the most distinctive clues of a collision between Earth and a large asteroid or comet.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
