<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmentalists Accuse U.S. Of Trying to Weaken Global Treaty</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="529983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOTECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biotechnology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DD1730F93AA25756C0A964958260" item-length="1141" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmentalists Accuse U.S. Of Trying to Weaken Global Treaty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE PERLEZ,</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, May 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As negotiations draw to a close here on an international treaty to slow the world's steady loss of plant, animal and microbial species, the United States is being accused by environmental groups of trying to weaken the agreement due to be signed at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro next month.</p>
        <p>Biologists have warned that unless international action is taken to curb the destruction of species, a mass extinction of epic proportions will result within a few decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As negotiations draw to a close here on an international treaty to slow the world's steady loss of plant, animal and microbial species, the United States is being accused by environmental groups of trying to weaken the agreement due to be signed at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro next month.</p>
        <p>Biologists have warned that unless international action is taken to curb the destruction of species, a mass extinction of epic proportions will result within a few decades.</p>
        <p>American officials involved in the negotiations said it was possible that the completed version would be unacceptable to the Bush Administration. If so, they said, President Bush will not sign it when he attends the meeting in Brazil with other heads of government. Bush Administration's Objections</p>
        <p>"The chances are only 50-50 that the treaty will have satisfactory language on the issues fundamental to the United States," said E. Curtis Bohlen, Assistant Secretary of State for the environment.</p>
        <p>He said the Administration had a wide range of objections, including concerns about provisions that would adversely affect the growing biotechnology industry in the United States.</p>
        <p>Representatives of the World Wide Fund for Nature, which is based in Switzerland, and the Washington-based Defenders of Wildlife said the United States delegation was trying to eliminate the requirement that each country adopt regulations to conserve its wildlife and to eliminate procedures to make one nation responsible for insuring that its private companies do not harm the wildlife of other nations.</p>
        <p>The groups circulated a memorandum from the office of Vice President Dan Quayle that said the draft treaty was so "extensively flawed" that it was "highly unlikely" the negotiations here would resolve the Administration's concerns.</p>
        <p>Delegates from European nations and Japan, as well as most developing countries, have indicated that their heads of government will sign the biodiversity treaty if agreement on its contents is reached here.</p>
        <p>The United States agreed this month to sign a climate treaty aimed at limiting emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases that contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>The climate and biodiversity treaties, intended to be binding agreements that would require nations to take conserving actions, are regarded as the most important substantive matters at the Brazil gathering.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the discussions here are the measures that nations would be required to take in conserving species, habitats and ecosystems.</p>
        <p>The United Nations, whose environmental program is based in this East African capital, has said that without special efforts the world faces a "wave of extinctions unmatched in 60 million years."</p>
        <p>"It has been suggested that up to 25 percent of the species now living will become extinct within a single human lifetime," said the executive director of the United Nations Environment Program, Mostafa K. Tolba of Egypt.</p>
        <p>The biodiversity treaty draws special attention to the conservation of species in developing countries, where most of the world's biodiversity is found. In the last decade, more than 90 percent of the varieties of wild seeds that have been collected were found in the third world, United Nations ecologists say.</p>
        <p>Seeking to help these impoverished countries preserve their ecosystems and wildlife, the treaty includes financial help. This would be done through the Global Environmental Facility, a new mechanism to channel funds for environmental protection from developed countries to poorer ones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bohlen, who is not attending the Nairobi negotiations but talks to the American delegation by phone, said from Washington that the United States had a number of objections to the draft treaty as now formulated.</p>
        <p>He said the treaty would force the Federal Government to take the primary responsibility for the conservation of wildlife away from the states. The Government has the responsibility only for endangered and migratory species, Mr. Bohlen said. The Bush Administration objections to the transfer were not the only obstacle: the Senate would never ratify a treaty with such a provision, he said.</p>
        <p>Seeking to limit the degradation by wealthy corporations of the oceans and ecosystems in developing countries, the treaty makes nations responsible for the environmental effects of their private companies' activities in other countries. Thus, if an American company wanted to log in an African forest, the United States would be responsible for insuring that an environmental impact assessment was completed.</p>
        <p>The two senior members of the Congressional delegation to Rio, Senators Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, and John H. Chafee, Republican of Rhode Island, wrote to Mr. Bush that they strongly supported the principle that a country should be responsible for actions under its control, whether inside or outside the boundaries of the country.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bohlen said the Administration opposed the provision.</p>
        <p>On biotechnology provisions of the treaty, Mr. Bohlen said the United States objected to efforts to regulate the industry. "We believe biotechnology should be addressed separately from biodiversity," he said. He said Washington disliked what it regarded to be a premise in the treaty that all genetically altered organisms were inherently unsafe.</p>
        <p>A major issue under the rubric of biotechnology is the ownership of genetic material. Historically, seeds, germ plasm and specimens of individual species have been in the public domain. Anyone could exploit them without compensating the nation of origin.</p>
        <p>Thus, the rosy periwinkle, a plant found only in the tropical rain forests of eastern Madagascar, has provided the basis for a drug used to combat childhood leukemia and Hodgkin's disease. Madagascar, a country of widespread hunger and unemployment, has received virtually no compensation for the plant, according to the United Nations.  Paying for Genetic Material</p>
        <p>The draft treaty seeks to insure compensation to underdeveloped countries for their genetic materials. Mr. Bohlen said the United States agreed with the principle that such nations should share in the economic benefits, but said the question was how that was to accomplished.</p>
        <p>He said the United States was favored the principle of including compensation in the treaty but believed the mechanisms should be arranged by the countries concerned.</p>
        <p>And one of the most contentious issues in the treaty between the rich countries of the north and the generally indigent nations of the south is the question of technology transfer. The developing countries are asking for transfers of biotechnology advances on a concessionary basis.</p>
        <p>"The United States cannot agree on behalf of a private company to this, and we have a strong commitment to intellectual property rights," Mr. Bohlen said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
