<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debate on Buildings: To Scrub Or Not</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="500123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDINGS (STRUCTURES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANITATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL PARK SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANGIER, NATALIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DC103AF937A25752C0A964958260" item-length="2541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debate on Buildings: To Scrub Or Not</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATALIE ANGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANGIER, NATALIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the next three to five years, the Lincoln and Jefferson Memorials in Washington, those soaring marble arias to democracy and inspiration for thousands of tourists each week, will be partly obscured by decidedly unpoetic girdles of scaffolding, fences and thick green nets, as workers struggle to shore up the crumbling monuments and restore a bit of their dimming grandeur.</p>
        <p>The monuments are suffering, not so much because they have been battered by grit, grime and acid rain or even because pigeons shamelessly roost on the heads of the Presidential statues within, but because in the half century since the monuments were built they have been kept so meticulously clean. To help assure the appearance of unsullied timelessness at the monuments, the National Park Service hoses down the entire structures twice a year and swabs off the Lincoln statue with detergent and water every other day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the next three to five years, the Lincoln and Jefferson Memorials in Washington, those soaring marble arias to democracy and inspiration for thousands of tourists each week, will be partly obscured by decidedly unpoetic girdles of scaffolding, fences and thick green nets, as workers struggle to shore up the crumbling monuments and restore a bit of their dimming grandeur.</p>
        <p>The monuments are suffering, not so much because they have been battered by grit, grime and acid rain or even because pigeons shamelessly roost on the heads of the Presidential statues within, but because in the half century since the monuments were built they have been kept so meticulously clean. To help assure the appearance of unsullied timelessness at the monuments, the National Park Service hoses down the entire structures twice a year and swabs off the Lincoln statue with detergent and water every other day.</p>
        <p>Partly as a result of the constant washing, the marble has eroded so badly in spots that last year a chunk of one 42-foot column at the Jefferson Memorial crashed to the ground and other columns were found to be teetering dangerously. Now the National Park Service is racing to gauge the extent of the deterioration and how best to correct it.</p>
        <p>The fragile condition of two of America's most treasured monuments underscores an ongoing and often vitriolic debate among preservationists, engineers, real estate developers and those who simply feel passionate about architecture: is it best to scrub a building now and again, or simply leave it alone?</p>
        <p>Some argue that a building coated with dirt or graffiti or bird droppings is an offense and that a city of grimy buildings is a dark, unsavory place, bespeaking economic and social disintegration. They also say that pollution and filth are harmful to a building and that surely the expeditious removal of grime is in the building's best interest.</p>
        <p>Others insist that cleaning a building almost always does more harm than good, driving water deep into the capillaries of the stone, where it can expand if it freezes and crack the masonry. They say a spattering of grease and graffiti on the facade is far preferable to deep structural damage that can follow a cleaning, and they say cities are full of buildings that have been mangled by cleanings past.</p>
        <p>The critics of cleaning, echoing with the 19th-century architect and neo-medievalist John Ruskin, argue that there is something pleasing about "the sweetness of line the wind and rain have brought" to buildings that have been around long enough to qualify as landmarks. They decry the desire to clean, clean, clean as evidence of America's restless obsession with novelty and youth.</p>
        <p>Yet a third camp, composed of preservationists with a strong background in engineering, chemistry and even geology, sits between the two extremes, saying the technology for cleaning and restoring buildings has progressed so far in just the last several years that even the most delicate of structures can sometimes benefit from a deft and carefully executed cleaning.</p>
        <p>Using methods like electron microscopy, infrared spectroscopy and gas chromatography, preservationists can now determine whether dirt on a building is merely smudging the stone on the outermost layer or has pervaded the pores like a sickness and thus threatens the whole structure. The preservationists say it is now possible to combine the best of both worlds, removing deleterious dirt without compromising the craftsmanship and subtleties of a beloved landmark.</p>
        <p>"We're moving from a macroscopic to a microscopic point of view," said Kate B. Ottavino, a preservation specialist with Ehrenkrantz &amp; Eckstut Associates in New York. "The debates in the past were romantic and esthetic, but now there is so much science to work with that we're trying to make the theory of preservation catch up with the technology."  New Methods  Caution Becomes The Watchword</p>
        <p>Some recent refurbishings of famous buildings that have used the new technology have nevertheless given passersby a shock. For as long as most New Yorkers can remember, Trinity Church in lower Manhattan had been a looming black tower, a somber gothic meditation amid the controlled bedlam of Wall Street. But a gentle cleansing removed the accreted soot from the 19th-century church and returned it to its original color, a light and confectionary pinkish tone that some New Yorkers actively dislike.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Manhattan, the first cleaning in its history is about to commence on the century-old Dakota, a brooding Beaux-Arts apartment house on Central Park where the movie "Rosemary's Baby" was filmed and where John Lennon was shot to death. As a test patch on the building reveals, the operation will transform the streaky, espresso-brown building into something the color of fawnskin. Hardcore antiquarians compare cleaning up the Dakota to painting over the Sistine Chapel, but preservationists in charge of the project insist the building will be healthier and comelier as a result.</p>
        <p>"In the early days, I felt the dirt had this wonderful romance about it, and I didn't want to touch it," said Joseph Bresnan, an architect, longtime preservationist and president of Remco, the New York company that will be cleaning the Dakota. "But as we investigated the exterior and saw the conditions up close, I realized the building must be cleaned. And it is going to look more beautiful, no doubt about it."</p>
        <p>For most people, buildings seem indestructible, designed to withstand the abuses of the elements and certainly far more stoic than the mortals who create them. But conservationists compare their specialty to medicine, using the same terms to describe damage and decay in a building as might be applied to a patient.  They talk about whether the building suffers from any "pathology" and they ask whether or not its stone can breathe and sweat.</p>
        <p>Restorationists also take the position increasingly favored by doctors that if you do not have to go in and poke around or do any sort of emergency surgery, stay away.</p>
        <p>"The most important principle in medicine is, first do no harm," said Nicolas F. Veloz, who works on protecting and restoring monuments for the National Park Service. "The same goes for buildings. You generally do the least amount of intervention possible."</p>
        <p>Mr. Veloz takes the analogy to medicine quite seriously, speeding to the scene of a decaying building or a graffiti-marred monument in a refitted ambulance. Past Sins  An Excess of Zeal Brought Damage</p>
        <p>Conservationists are especially wary of being too aggressive in cleaning a building in the wake of the extensive damage that has been done by overzealous grooming squads in the past.</p>
        <p>In the 1960's and 1970's, many buildings whose stones or bricks had merely begun to weather a little were sandblasted with an abrasive spray shot at the facade at a wilting pressure of about 150 pounds per square inch to strip off dirt the quickest way possible. The practice was viewed as sanitizing a building, but the results were devastating.</p>
        <p>"When you sandblast, you lose most of the surface, and all the decorative details that give a building character," said Martin Weaver, director of the Center for Preservation Research and a professor of architecture at Columbia University in New York. "You strip the building down to something that looks like molten candy."  Giving Statues the Measles</p>
        <p>Another popular cleaning item was hydrofluoric acid, a compound so powerful it is used to etch glass. Masonry buildings, with their craggy surfaces, were thought to be able to withstand an acidic drizzle, and the treatment did have the seemingly miraculous effect of instantly lifting away filth without any immediate impact on the stone. But many building materials, particularly those with a base of calcium or magnesium carbonate, like marble and limestone, were later shown to be able to dissolve in acid as sugar does in a cup of tea. And whenever these compounds were bathed in hydrofluoric acid, portions of the structure's skin gradually turned to dust and blew away.</p>
        <p>Compulsive cleaning crews would try anything, scrubbing at dirty marble with a steel wire brush, for example, which had an immediate brightening effect that eventually turned into a horror show.</p>
        <p>"A lot of marble statues were given measles," Mr. Weaver said. "Invisible steel fibers were deposited below the surface, where they rusted. The statue would be white one day, and all of a sudden these brown spots would appear everywhere."'</p>
        <p>A related problem plagued St. Patrick's Cathedral in New York when the marble neo-Gothic landmark was cleaned in the mid-1980's with water dripped gently from hoses strung along its roof. As the water flowed over the surface, natural iron pigments deep in the marble began migrating outward, turning the huge white cathedral a rusty brown. Eventually, further water applications washed the iron away and restored St. Patrick to its creamy sheen.</p>
        <p>At Trinity Church, a building of sandstone, which is naturally porous, conservators in the 1920's decided they would try to waterproof the masonry by coating it in paraffin, as one might wax a car. But the clever notion proved disastrous. The paraffin immediately absorbed far more soot, coal dust and grime than the building would have otherwise, until New Yorkers came to believe that any church so thoroughly black must have been designed to be funereal.</p>
        <p>When decomposition of parts of the tower forced preservationists to clean the church recently, the paraffin was stripped off with a mild solvent revealing a shockingly rosy stone beneath. "None of us expected that the stone would be so pink," said Alex Herrera, director of the Landmarks Preservation Society in New York. "The coating of paraffin had been a really bad idea, and now the architect's orginal intentions come through more clearly."</p>
        <p>Conservationists complain that rotten cleaning jobs are still commonplace, usually as a result of ignorance. Mr. Veloz said that he was recently out on a job attempting to remove lewd graffiti from a public statue. He and other workers applied a combination of mild chemicals, but the best the team could manage was to lighten the graffiti, not erase it altogether. One member of the team suggested sandblasting.</p>
        <p>"I told him, I can show you four instances of graffiti in Washington where the graffiti is absolutely permanent and indelible, because it was sandblasted," Mr. Veloz said. "Instead of having painted letters that are half an inch wide, you get sandblasted outlines that are two inches wide, and that will never weather off."  Case Histories  Moving Ahead One Stone at Time</p>
        <p>Leery of quick solutions, most conservationists today begin by asking what the dirt on a building is, and how it is bonding with the architectural material. Sometimes the dirt turns out to be beneficial to the stone, and restorationists may recommend leaving it alone. The wall surrounding Central Park in New York, for example, is covered with dirt that extensive tests have shown is able to repel moisture and thus protect the stone, and during recent restorations of the park preservationists opted not to scrub the wall at all.</p>
        <p>But dirt can sometimes be as rotten as it appears. At the New York Public Library, a grand Beaux Arts temple on Fifth Avenue, conservationists examined samples of surface dirt by using X-ray diffraction analysis and infrared spectroscopy, which broke down the gray smears into their constituent elements. The researchers found that the sculptural details on the building, including the bas-relief lions, had interacted with pollutants from acid rain. As a result, the calcium carbonate on the surface had been transformed into calcium sulfate, or gypsum, and the pathology was spreading in fungal fashion through the stone.</p>
        <p>"It was migrating inward, invading the lion's ear like a disease," said Ms. Ottavino. "The gypsum had formed a scab, and underneath the scab it was turning to powder. We had to clean to extend the life of the building."</p>
        <p>Sometimes preservationists must clean a building just to get in and do emergency surgery to save the structure from collapse. At the City and County Building in Salt Lake City, a magnificent dark Victorian building, researchers recently took core samples from significant spots on the building. Through measurements of the porosity of the stone and its plasticity, the preservationists determined that the masonry was crumbling from within.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem was that the building had been constructed of brownstone, a material too delicate for the extremes of temperature found in Utah, and over time the stone had been freezing, thawing and freezing again. With each cycle of expansion and contraction, moisture and dirt had penetrated deeper into the sandstone, causing hairline cracks and crevices and forcing salts from within the stone up to the surface, where they crystallized into ugly white shadows called efflorescences.</p>
        <p>To shore up the decaying brownstone through the addition of supportive consolidating materials, the restorationists first removed several layers of pollutants. Fighting the Food Chain</p>
        <p>In Washington, the National Park Service researchers are desperate to figure out how to keep the nation's treasured monuments presentable enough without resorting to regular scrubs, which are still part of the routine. Their investigations have revealed that at the Lincoln Memorial, a peculiar cross between technology and the food chain is to blame for some of the untidiness. Each day at sunset, small insects called midges emerge en masse to mate. At the same time, flood lights are switched on to bathe the building in a noble aura, and the excited midges fly toward the lights, smashing against the wall and forming a great proteinous mess.</p>
        <p>Large spiders are attracted to the scent of decaying midge bodies, and they sully the structure with cobwebs and spider droppings. The spiders in turn beckon sparrows, which also defecate against the memorial.</p>
        <p>"We've got quite an ecosystem going, and it's unsightly," said Rebecca Stevens of the Park Service. But neither spider feces nor midge bodies harm the building as much as attempts to wash the mess off with water. The saturated stone absorbs particles from automobile exhaust, and the mixture infiltrates the marble.</p>
        <p>For the next several years, the Park Service preservationists will be analyzing every block of marble to determine in each case whether aggressive steps are necessary, like consolidating a weak stone with the addition of new binding materials.  But they already have learned that a simple change in their lighting practice may help prevent future filth at the monument.</p>
        <p>A year ago, the Park Service experimented with postponing the floodlighting of the memorial until an hour after sunset, when the midges' mating frenzy had already subsided. Entomologists were sent forth to count midge fatalies, and they discovered that the delayed lighting reduced the body count by 80 to 90 percent. The Park Service is now considering whether or not to delay lighting the memorial every night, cutting down not only on the midge problem, but its electricity bill as well.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
