<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>116-Year-Old Company Thrives on Innovation</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WINDSOR (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STANADYNE INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D61238F931A25757C0A964958260" item-length="1390" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>116-Year-Old Company Thrives on Innovation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT A. HAMILTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAMILTON, ROBERT A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE 30 years of decline among Connecticut manufacturers, optimism reigns at Stanadyne Inc. in Windsor. To understand why, it helps to consider the company's history.</p>
        <p>Many other Connecticut business are just starting to learn about diversification and international markets. But in 1947 the Hartford Machine Screw Company was adjusting to the slowdown in military contracts after the war and began making diesel-fuel injection pumps for cars and trucks. In the 1980's, with the number of American-made diesel-powered cars dwindling, the company, now called Stanadyne, started selling its injectors in Japan and Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE 30 years of decline among Connecticut manufacturers, optimism reigns at Stanadyne Inc. in Windsor. To understand why, it helps to consider the company's history.</p>
        <p>Many other Connecticut business are just starting to learn about diversification and international markets. But in 1947 the Hartford Machine Screw Company was adjusting to the slowdown in military contracts after the war and began making diesel-fuel injection pumps for cars and trucks. In the 1980's, with the number of American-made diesel-powered cars dwindling, the company, now called Stanadyne, started selling its injectors in Japan and Europe.</p>
        <p>And as I.B.M. starts what it has heralded as a 1990's management innovation, spinning off small entrepreneurial units within the larger company, Stanadyne is readying the first in a series of products it developed through the same process, started three years ago. One is a unit to recycle antifreeze that can be used by operators of cab and bus fleets to reclaim 90 percent of what used to be thrown out. Another is a new type of oil pump for the Northstar 4.6-liter V-8 engine that will be used in the 1993 Cadillac Allante sports car. 'We're Here to Stay'</p>
        <p>"Within a relatively short time we got some products we think are going to do very, very well," said the director of power products at Stanadyne, Lee P. Janik.</p>
        <p>The company's executive vice president, William D. Gurley, said, "We're here to stay."</p>
        <p>The company's work force in Windsor, site of its largest installation, is going to grow significantly "over the next two to three years," he said. "We've actually been hiring over the last year, in some key skills."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurley said Stanadyne employed 2,250 people worldwide, about 950 of them in Windsor. Mr. Janik said the success of Stanadyne's manufacturing operation in Connecticut, a state where manufacturing has been on the wane, was propelled "by self-preservation."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurley said success was, "a matter of being able to recognize when you've got to do things differently, and then making the change." The company has "been willing to try things that are different," he said.</p>
        <p>Brian V. Beaudin, senior vice president of the Connecticut Business and Industry Association and director of its Manufacturers' Council, said other companies will have to follow Stanadyne's example, if they hope to survive.</p>
        <p>"There's a lot more innovation going on in manufacturing now, compared to three or four years ago," Mr. Beaudin said. "The defense business that has been the meat and potatoes of a lot of manufacturers is gone, so they're saying, 'How can I take the equipment I've got, and the processes I have, and do something else?' " Proof of State's Strength</p>
        <p>Mr. Beaudin said that necessity often propelled manufacturing companies to become pioneers of new management styles. In the 1980;s manufacturers went through the efficiencies and cutbacks that banks and insurance companies are pursuing now, he said.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the State Department of Economic Development, Joseph Cohen, said Stanadyne "is proof that among Connecticut's strengths are its research and development capabilities and the transfer of technologies into new products." He added, "It's why we believe that, with its skilled labor forces and a history of innovation, Connecticut is going to come through these tough times with our jobs base and our business stronger than ever."</p>
        <p>Hartford Machine Screw was established in 1876 to develop what became the first automatic screw machine. It produced screws for the sewing-machine industry and, in the late 1800's, a booming bicycle business. By the early 1920's it phased out production of standard screws and began manufacturing custom-designed ones, for businesses like nearby Pratt &amp; Whitney, which used the screws in the first successful air-cooled aircraft engine.</p>
        <p>During the military buildup before and during World War II the company prospered in the fastener business, but with the demand for fighter planes down after the war, it began to look to other markets. In 1947 it recruited Vernon Roosa, an inventor with an idea for a diesel-fuel injection pump. The following year it moved to the plant on 27 acres in Windsor, still its home.</p>
        <p>The company's diesel-pump technology, including products like diesel filters and water separators, has been used in automotive, agricultural, and heavy-equipment engines. During the 1970's, when the fuel crisis curtailed gasoline supplies and domestic use of diesel engines climbed, the company expanded its Windsor plant and bought two others in North Carolina. The company's name, which had earlier been changed to Standard Screw, had now become Stanadyne, the "dyne" coming from dynamometer, a device for measuring an engine's power.</p>
        <p>The same qualities that made diesels attractive during the fuel crisis make them better engines from an environmental perspective, Mr. Gurley said.</p>
        <p>"If you're worried about global warming, diesels make more sense," he said, noting that diesel engines burn 30 to 40 percent less fuel than gasoline engines, with corresponding reductions in emissions of carbon dioxide and nitrous oxide. Selling in Japan</p>
        <p>Diesel engines, Mr. Gurley said, last longer. The typical diesel car does not need major engine service for 150,000 miles, he said, and big trucks routinely go 500,000, get a rebuilding and proceed to 1 million miles.</p>
        <p>When gasoline supplies eased in the 1980's, Americans wanted to return to the quicker pickup that a gasoline engine offers. So Stanadyne turned its attention to overseas markets, including Japan.</p>
        <p>"We've seen nothing in that market in terms of the protection or the other barriers you read about," Mr. Gurley said. "We've only faced the usual rigors of competition -- quality issues, technical issues and value."</p>
        <p>In 1988, with the help of investment bankers, a group of Stanadyne executives bought the company from the stockholders. The previous year the company established a foothold in Europe by buying a United Technologies plant in Brescia, Italy, and a business owned by Altecna, a division of Fiat.</p>
        <p>"So if 'Fortress Europe' slams closed, which is looking less likely but could still be possible, we're now inside the European Economic Community and ready to expand our operations there," Mr. Gurley said.</p>
        <p>But with its international operations growing, Stanadyne was facing a shrinking market at home. "We recognized that our business in the U.S. would be fairly flat," Mr. Janik said. "So we got together a small resource group of engineers, marketing people and so on, to do entrepreneurial work."</p>
        <p>Recalling how Stanadyne got into the filter business 20 years ago, because no one else was making diesel-fuel filters sophisticated enough for its fuel pumps, the group started talking about other uses of filtering technology. Some members recalled hearing about the problem with spent antifreeze.</p>
        <p>After long use in an engine, antifreeze is contaminated by sludge and other materials that rob it of its ability to keep the engine's temperature within strict limits. It had to be drained out, disposed of as hazardous waste and replaced.</p>
        <p>The Stanadyne team designed a system that draws off ethylene glycol, the active ingredient in antifreeze, and leaves a sludge behind, Mr. Janik said.</p>
        <p>Operating at its full capacity of 100 gallons a day, the $10,000 machine, which uses a process called reverse osmosis to cleanse the antifreeze, pays for itself in a year through reduced replacement cost for antifreeze, he said. The oil pump for the new Cadillac Allante is another example of the entrepreneurial group's work. "We got in line behind three others who wanted to provide that pump," Mr. Janik said. "But our design got us in the door."</p>
        <p>Stanadyne's engineering group proved itself willing to make changes to accommodate different engine designs, he said.</p>
        <p>"A couple of times the engineers would talk to Cadillac on the phone about some changes, come out here and set up and have the new part on the way to them the next day," Mr. Janik said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gurley said: "The business has changed over the years, and it's going through another transition now. I could claim it was vision, but it was really the realities of the market that pushed us to do what we've done throughout our history. And that's what's pushing us still."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
