<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Increasing Plants' Yields With Sun and Diluted Methanol</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="567443"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ACADEMY OF SCIENCES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NONOMURA, ARTHUR (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENSON, ANDREW (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA1239F930A35752C1A964958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Increasing Plants' Yields With Sun and Diluted Methanol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CROP plants sprayed with diluted methanol, or wood alcohol, showed significantly greater yields while requiring less water than a comparison group of plants, two researchers say.</p>
        <p>The crops in Arizona were sprayed under the brightest summer sun by Dr. Arthur Nonomura, a botanist turned farmer, and Dr. Andrew Benson, professor emeritus at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography. They found that cabbages doubled in size, wheat seeds doubled in weight and number, and the water needs of cotton crops dropped by half. Likewise, tomatoes grew faster and were significantly sweeter, roses grew faster and produced more flowers, and strawberries, eggplants and watermelons gave better yields.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CROP plants sprayed with diluted methanol, or wood alcohol, showed significantly greater yields while requiring less water than a comparison group of plants, two researchers say.</p>
        <p>The crops in Arizona were sprayed under the brightest summer sun by Dr. Arthur Nonomura, a botanist turned farmer, and Dr. Andrew Benson, professor emeritus at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography. They found that cabbages doubled in size, wheat seeds doubled in weight and number, and the water needs of cotton crops dropped by half. Likewise, tomatoes grew faster and were significantly sweeter, roses grew faster and produced more flowers, and strawberries, eggplants and watermelons gave better yields.</p>
        <p>"It's a most surprising discovery," Dr. Benson said of the findings reported last month in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. "We didn't anticipate anything like this. Nobody would've dreamed that we would have increased the yields this way. For $3.20 worth of methanol on one hectare, 2.5 acres, you would get 12 tons extra of melons. It's hard to believe."</p>
        <p>Indeed, some other researchers cautioned that additional studies would be needed before the significance of the study could be confirmed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jay Jacobson, plant physiologist at the Boyce Thompson Institute for Plant Research at Cornell University, said he was particularly surprised that methanol could be so beneficial since the study also found it could be highly toxic to plants. "It is so surprising," he said. "Consequently it will be very important to have the data verified in order to generalize from these results." 'Agricultural Revolution'</p>
        <p>Dr. James A. Bassham, a plant physiologist and a pioneer in the early studies of photosynthesis, said: "It's a complex business when you put chemicals on plants and a lot depends on conditions and circumstances. But it looks potentially very significant. This should be looked on as a first study. It'll have to be checked out by more studies before we can know if it's as significant as it looks."</p>
        <p>Dr. Nonomura said the methanol spray appears to help make plants more efficient at making and using energy. "I think we're about to embark on an agricultural revolution," he said. Dr. Nonomura has established his farm as a corporation, Photon Inc., and plans to market the discovery.</p>
        <p>Methanol spraying, however, does not boost the growth of all plants. Corn, sorghum and the weeds, Johnson and Bermuda grass, were unaffected. In addition, because the methanol appears effective only when sprayed under very bright light, winter crops and crops grown in less sunny areas are unlikely to benefit.</p>
        <p>Normally when plants use sunlight to make sugars during photosynthesis they use carbon dioxide as their source of carbon. But in the early 1980's, Dr. Nonomura and Dr. Benson found that algae, when given methanol as a carbon source, could grow twice as fast, producing twice as many carbon-containing molecules like sugar and proteins.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Nonomura became a farmer he applied methanol to boost the growth of his crops, but said he found much more growth than could be accounted for simply by the addition of another carbon source. By spraying one gram of methanol on a plant, he said he found that a plant could grow an additional 200 to 400 grams.</p>
        <p>The researchers say they suspect the methanol is giving the plants a boost by inhibiting a natural process known as photorespiration during which a plant typically throws away much of the energy it has acquired during photosynthesis. Dr. Nonomura said this wasteful reaction appeared to be curtailed under methanol treatments, allowing the plants to retain more of the sunlight energy that they have captured in sugars.</p>
        <p>Researchers say the methanol's effect on energy efficiency may explain why the treatment does not help plants like corn and sorghum, members of a class of plants known as C4 plants, which are already much more energy efficient than C3 plants like tomatoes and cotton.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
