<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Use Debt to Save Russian Forests</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="503943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D91330F93BA15752C0A964958260" item-length="366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Use Debt to Save Russian Forests</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The United States has agreed to support Russia's inclusion in the International Monetary Fund and World Bank (front page, Jan. 4), to suspend Russia's debt payments until 1993 and to provide millions of dollars in direct aid. For little or no additional cost, the United States and the international community can use debt restructuring and foreign aid to help protect Russian forests, vital to offset the greenhouse effect and maintain the world's air quality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The United States has agreed to support Russia's inclusion in the International Monetary Fund and World Bank (front page, Jan. 4), to suspend Russia's debt payments until 1993 and to provide millions of dollars in direct aid. For little or no additional cost, the United States and the international community can use debt restructuring and foreign aid to help protect Russian forests, vital to offset the greenhouse effect and maintain the world's air quality.</p>
        <p>Russia contains more than half the world's remaining evergreen forests and one-quarter of the world's timber supply. The forests, covering an area the size of the continental United States, absorb three-quarters as much carbon as the Amazon rain forests and produce equivalent amounts of oxygen.</p>
        <p>Although many of Russia's forests are still pristine, economic and political instability have caused a veritable timber rush. Government officials, newly privatized timber consortiums and hundreds of commodities exchanges are eager to sell off the forests for hard currency, technology, food and fuel.</p>
        <p>To help Russia's economic difficulties, the United States and 16 other lender nations have agreed to suspend Russian debt payments until the end of 1992. If the I.M.F. and World Bank admit Russia, they would further restructure Russia's debt and provide billions of dollars in development loans and technical aid. The United States and the international community have an opportunity to protect the world's environment while bolstering Russia's economy. The I.M.F. and creditor nations can require Russia to preserve designated forest lands in exchange for debt restructuring and foreign aid.</p>
        <p>Exchanging debt for nature conservation is not new. There are more than 15 debt-for-nature agreements, mostly to preserve Central and South American rain forests. Private or sovereign lenders sell or donate debt to a conservation organization, which uses or forgives the debt in exchange for nature protection. Sovereign lenders can also negotiate directly with debtor nations. JULIA LEVIN  San Francisco, Jan. 14, 1992</p>
        <p>The writer, a lawyer, has served as a consultant on forestry law in Russia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
