<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth Summit Finds The Years of Optimism Are a Fading Memory</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS CONFERENCE ON ENVIRONMENT AND DEVELOPMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC143AF93AA35755C0A964958260" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth Summit Finds The Years of Optimism Are a Fading Memory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>IO DE JANEIRO, June 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The representatives of 178 countries gathered here for the Earth Summit confront a far more sobering task than did the intellectual and political predecessors who, in a landmark meeting, gathered in Stockholm 20 years ago last week and put the cause of the environment on the world's formal agenda for the first time.</p>
        <p>In those palmy save-the-whales years, full of hope and idealism, the delegates to the United Nations Environment Conference in Sweden asserted confidently that "the capability of man to improve the environment increases with each passing day."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The representatives of 178 countries gathered here for the Earth Summit confront a far more sobering task than did the intellectual and political predecessors who, in a landmark meeting, gathered in Stockholm 20 years ago last week and put the cause of the environment on the world's formal agenda for the first time.</p>
        <p>In those palmy save-the-whales years, full of hope and idealism, the delegates to the United Nations Environment Conference in Sweden asserted confidently that "the capability of man to improve the environment increases with each passing day."</p>
        <p>Here, the optimism of 1972 has been replaced by a hard realism. The delegates in Rio have discovered how hard it is for nations to unite on fundamental environmental problems facing them.</p>
        <p>Differences between the rich countries of the industrialized world and the poor ones of the developing world, for instance, today threatened the summit with its first big, clear-cut failure as talks on a statement of principles for managing the world's forests seemed headed toward an inconclusive result.</p>
        <p>The rich nations had hoped that the summit would produce a call for a treaty on protection of forests to be negotiated after the talks in Rio. But that hope appeared doomed, delegates and official observers said today, and it seemed highly possible that no statement at all would emerge.  An Isolated U.S.</p>
        <p>The difficulties are also reflected in the isolation of the United States, the world's biggest environmental actor, on the two big summit issues of biodiversity and climate change. It appeared today that all the other industrialized countries would sign a treaty strengthening the world's efforts to protect living species, leaving the United States as the major dissenter.</p>
        <p>The United States agrees with the treaty's provisions on protection of species as such, but demurs on grounds of finances and intellectual property rights. Other rich countries share the objections, but say that it is important to get the treaty in force. It can be modified after it is ratified, they say.</p>
        <p>And the argument between the United States and Europe over whether to adopt specific targets and timetables for stabilizing emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases, which were thought to have been resolved when a treaty aimed at controlling the gases was negotiated in New York last month, has carried over to the summit.</p>
        <p>The Europeans wish to see the treaty altered soon after it goes into effect so as to include the specific targets and timetables. The United States disagrees, saying that the threat of warming is not yet scientifically clear enough to move that far just yet. The Europeans say it is clear enough to them.</p>
        <p>The tougher job of the Rio delegates stems from two underlying causes: the environmental problem itself has worsened since Stockholm, and the world has grown more serious about dealing with it.</p>
        <p>Human activity has continued to put relentless pressure on the biosphere, the earth's life support system, in the last 20 years. Between Stockholm and Rio, population has grown by more than 40 percent, or more than 1.5 billion.</p>
        <p>New scientific measurements have limned the fragile character of the biosphere, as emphasized by the depletion of the earth's protective ozone shield, far more clearly than the Stockholm conferees could have known or appreciated.</p>
        <p>The delegates in Rio are far more aware of the prospect of climate change, given that emissions of carbon dioxide, the heat-trapping gas that scientists fear will cause global warming, have grown by 35 percent over the two decades.  Protecting Future Generations</p>
        <p>Moreover, the Rio negotiators have come to grips with the problem of "sustainable development," how to serve the economic needs of the world without damaging the biosphere and its vital resources and thereby compromising the well-being of future generations.</p>
        <p>The concept had barely germinated in Stockholm, but now, as thinking has evolved over the last two decades, it has acquired a sort of orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>"You're getting into terribly difficult areas to negotiate," said Russell E. Train, who was the chief United States delegate at Stockholm and is to attend the Earth Summit this week as president of the World Wildlife Fund of the United States. "I think they're going to take a long time to work out. This is a continuing process."</p>
        <p>Stockholm set in motion a chain of intellectual and political events that led directly to Rio, and together the two conferences constitute benchmarks in international environmentalism.</p>
        <p>In 1972, the world was nowhere near confronting the hard questions that are being debated here. At Stockholm, environmental protection was conceived relatively narrowly, primarily in terms of physical pollution and the endangerment of popular species.</p>
        <p>Several concrete developments were propelled ahead by the Stockholm meeting: the successful negotiation of a treaty on trade and endangered species; a treaty on ocean dumping; a moratorium on the hunting of whales; and the establishment of the United Nations Environmental Program, which has tried to serve as a catalyst for environmental action.</p>
        <p>But more than that, said Mr. Train, Stockholm was itself a "catalytic event that raised consciousness about the issue and energized politicians."</p>
        <p>This shift in consciousness has led most of the world's governments to establish departments of the environment since 1972. International aid programs are developing an environmental dimension. A new fund, the Global Environmental Facility, was established last year to channel money for environmental protection from rich countries to poor ones. Environmental advocacy groups have grown enormously in number, expertise and force, exerting pressure on governments around the world.</p>
        <p>"There's been a huge institutional evolution since Stockholm," said Mr. Train.</p>
        <p>But science has revealed new threats in the meantime and changed the perceived shape of old ones. From concern over creatures with devoted public supportlike whales, for instance, the attention of conservationists has broadened and shifted to encompass the concept of preserving biological diversity and protecting whole ecosystems rather than focusing on a single popular, but not necessarily critical, species at a time. This more comprehensive approach is embodied in the biodiversity treaty that countries are signing here.</p>
        <p>And it has only been in the last decade or less that the twin issues of global warming and depletion of the earth's protective ozone layer have appeared.</p>
        <p>The Vienna Convention of 1985 established an institutional framework for protection of the ozone layer, followed in 1987 by the creation under the convention of the Montreal Protocol. Both are widely cited as landmark acts. They have led to the outright banning by the end of this decade of chemicals that destroy ozone, and the deadline will probably be moved up later this year.</p>
        <p>Only in the last six years has the question of climate change -- global warming, or the greenhouse effect -- vaulted to the top of the international agenda.</p>
        <p>"In 1986, the world wasn't working on greenhouse at all; now all heads of government have had to deal with it," said Rafe Pomerance, a specialist on the issue at the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based research and advocacy organization.</p>
        <p>In 1982, the United Nations held a second environmental conference, this one in Nairobi, Kenya. The successor to Stockholm and predecessor to Rio, it reaffirmed the ideals of Stockholm but revealed clearly that there was a huge gap between the theory and the practice of environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Out of this conference grew the World Commission on Environment and Development, headed by Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland of Norway.</p>
        <p>The 1987 Brundtland Report, as the commission's product is called, changed the terms of the debate by giving economics equal consideration with the environment. A manifesto for sustainable development, it said that economics and environment were inextricably linked and that economic development and reduction of poverty were essential to protecting the environment.</p>
        <p>Those ideas are central to the Earth Summit, and are perhaps the biggest reason why the going here is so difficult.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
