<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington May Change Its Position On Climate</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DA1F3CF93BA25751C0A964958260" item-length="1858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington May Change Its Position On Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS delegates from around the world meet at the United Nations today to try to avert the threat of global warming, the Bush Administration finds itself in the hot seat, but there are signs that it may be preparing to wiggle out.</p>
        <p>Negotiators from Europe and Japan are expected to continue putting pressure on the United States to agree that all industrialized countries should accept a limit on their emissions of carbon dioxide, the chief heat-trapping gas that scientists fear will bring on a possibly catastrophic warming of the earth's climate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS delegates from around the world meet at the United Nations today to try to avert the threat of global warming, the Bush Administration finds itself in the hot seat, but there are signs that it may be preparing to wiggle out.</p>
        <p>Negotiators from Europe and Japan are expected to continue putting pressure on the United States to agree that all industrialized countries should accept a limit on their emissions of carbon dioxide, the chief heat-trapping gas that scientists fear will bring on a possibly catastrophic warming of the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>The limit proposed is that by the year 2000 each country should reduce its emissions to 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>The United States, the largest producer of carbon dioxide, has long resisted the concept of a limit. Under John H. Sununu, the recently departed White House chief of staff, Washington was committed to a position that the scientific basis for believing in global warming was flawed, that curbing carbon dioxide would restrain economic growth, and that in any case the United States had already taken all necessary actions to stabilize its contribution of world-warming gases by 2000.</p>
        <p>Today's climate conference is the fifth negotiating session in a series leading up to the "Earth Summit" in Rio de Janeiro this June. Although one more session is planned, for April, many experts believe a breakthrough must come now if there is to be time to achieve a treaty for signature at the June meeting.</p>
        <p>New scientific findings about the role of ozone-destroying CFC chemicals in global warming have undercut one of the Administration's principal arguments, that this nation's sharp cutback on these gases would significantly reduce its contribution to greenhouse warming. The Environmental Protection Agency has dusted off economic analyses, shelved in the days of Mr. Sununu, that indicate the proposed cap might not be so costly to the United States.  And all five Democratic Presidential candidates support caps on carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Under all these pressures, Washington is taking another look at the issue. "It's on the scope now," said an official close to the situation who spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>Pressure is also being brought on behalf of the Administration's present stance, however, by energy and energy-related industries. Officials familiar with the discussions within the Administration say that the situation is fluid and that no decision on any policy change has yet been made. Nor, they say, will any change materialize when the treaty talks begin today in New York.</p>
        <p>The American position paper for the opening of the session, made public on Sunday in a document obtained by Senator Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, includes no reference to targets and timetables. Rather, it calls for nations to take "cost-effective measures" to limit emissions of heat-trapping gases "in accordance with their national circumstances, development priorities and capabilities."</p>
        <p>It is possible, some officials say, that a change in the United States position could take place before the New York session ends on Feb. 28. Otherwise it would have to surface, if at all, at a sixth session expected at the United Nations in April.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and some Europeans fear that this will not allow enough time to reach a meaningful convention on global warming that could be signed, as planned, at the Earth Summit dealing with a range of global environmental questions in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
        <p>"In April it may be too late," said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, a climate specialist at the Environmental Defense Fund in New York. "We're not leaving enough time to build an intelligent agreement unless the U.S. switches its position during this negotiation." Possible Catastrophic Effects</p>
        <p>If scientists are right, the stakes in the global warming talks are high. Carbon dioxide and other gases emitted as a result of human activity trap heat in the atmosphere much as glass panes trap it in a greenhouse.</p>
        <p>Scientists convened by the United Nations to advise the negotiations predict that at present rates of emission, the buildup of greenhouse gases will increase the earth's average surface temperature by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit by the end of the next century, with possibly catastrophic effects. These could include a rise in sea level, a shifting of climatic and agricultural zones, more frequent droughts, and severe ecological disruption.</p>
        <p>Some dissenting scientists say that the predictions exaggerate the warming, and others say that whatever warming does come could be benign, occurring mostly at night and in the winter. But a panel of the National Academy of Sciences has concluded that the threat, though uncertain in severity and timing, is sufficient to justify a prompt response.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists see the United States as essential to a climate convention with any teeth. As the world's biggest economy and largest single emitter of carbon dioxide, they say, the United States must take a leading role -- not only because of its part in whatever greenhouse warming occurs but also as an example for developing countries.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries, whose use of fossil fuels is rapidly expanding, have expressed skepticism about the global warming threat. Collectively, they are demanding that the developed countries foot the bill for their conversion to energy sources that produce less greenhouse gas. But many say they are reluctant to make commitments unless the United States makes them as well.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are casting Washington's performance in the climate talks, and at the Rio conference, as a litmus test of the Administration's willingness to take a leadership role on global environmental questions that are moving to prominence with the end of the cold war.</p>
        <p>As discussion has opened up within the Administration, environmentalists have been able to follow the action much more closely than when Mr. Sununu controlled the debate. Several of them met last week with Samuel K. Skinner, the current White House chief of staff, to discuss global warming. Although Mr. Skinner reportedly made no commitments and said that industry pressure to avoid caps on carbon dioxide emissions had intensified, the meeting itself would have been inconceivable under Mr. Sununu.</p>
        <p>Everything considered, "there will likely be a change" in the Administration's position in the climate negotiations, "but it has not been resolved yet," said another Administration official who, like others, spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency's analyses of the economic effects of a carbon dioxide cap, long in preparation against the day when they might be needed, are now being scrutinized in the White House. They indicate that under private forecasts of economic growth for the next decade, carbon dioxide emissions in the United States will grow only slightly or, on a per capita basis, not at all. Hopes for a Treaty</p>
        <p>The analyses indicate that a variety of actions now under way to promote energy efficiency, not taken into account by the economic forecasts, could rein in carbon dioxide enough to make it possible for the United States to sign a treaty that pledges to stabilize carbon dioxide emissions. The actions include, for example, the adoption of more efficient lighting and appliances, incentives for public utilities to promote the more efficient use of electricity rather than build new power plants and the planting of a billion trees, which absorb carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Advocates of caps on carbon dioxide see them as a first step toward an eventual cut in the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. Environmentalists have long promoted energy efficiency as a way to make a start on the control of global warming while reaping savings on energy, reducing air pollution and promoting energy independence.</p>
        <p>Until now, the Administration has been arguing that any attempt to limit the emission of greenhouse gases should focus not on carbon dioxide but on the "full basket" of gases.  These include methane, nitrous oxides and especially chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's. The manufacture of CFC's, which are used as refrigerants and propellants in aerosol cans, is being phased out under a previous international agreement because they are destroying the stratospheric ozone shield. The shield protects living things from the sun's harmful ultraviolet rays. Administration's Position</p>
        <p>On the basis of earlier analyses, the Administration has argued that although carbon dioxide emissions will rise somewhat in this country, the reduction in CFC's would stabilize this country's overall contribution to global warming by the end of the decade.</p>
        <p>But a more recent scientific finding indicates that the greenhouse warming caused by CFC's is approximately offset by a cooling brought on by ozone depletion, also caused by CFC's. The CFC's, in effect, cancel out their own contribution to global warming. The finding has been cited in a report to be released soon by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the international group of scientists convened by the United Nations to advise the climate negotiations.</p>
        <p>"This undercuts the Administration position that it's not so important to concentrate on carbon dioxide," Dr. Oppenheimer said.</p>
        <p>The panel also cited recent findings that sulfate aerosols created by the burning of the same fossil fuels that produce carbon dioxide are scattering sunlight and helping clouds to form, thereby cooling the Northern Hemisphere and limiting the warming there in recent decades.</p>
        <p>Computerized mathematical models that simulate the workings of the atmosphere say the earth's climate should have warmed by about 2 degrees Fahrenheit in the last 100 years. In fact, it has warmed by about half that amount. Opponents of early action to combat global warming, including those in the Administration, have cited this discrepancy as evidence that the models, which are the main tool in forecasting future warming, are too crude to be believed. Accuracy of Models</p>
        <p>The international panel, however, says the discrepancy could have been accounted for by the cooling effect of the sulfate aerosols. If so, it could mean that the models are more accurate than the critics say. The sulfates, which also cause acid rain, are being eliminated in the United States and Europe. As this is being done, the panel said, aerosol concentrations will rapidly diminish and no longer mask the warming. Carbon dioxide, by contrast, remains in the atmosphere for decades and will continue to warm the earth.</p>
        <p>In large measure, the debate about a climate convention has moved beyond the science and is now verging on the purely political. In part, this may be because the Administration, despite the uncertainty of future warming, now accepts the basic science and sees warming as a potential problem.</p>
        <p>"The line that science says 'do nothing' has sort of gone by the board," said Rafe Pomerance of the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based environmental organization. "They're not saying it's not a problem. They're just saying 'We don't know what our policy is going to be.' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
