<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Expert on Shifts in Climate Through the Ages: the Lowly Fish</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROCK AND STONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CALCIUM</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D91E31F932A35751C1A964958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Expert on Shifts in Climate Through the Ages: the Lowly Fish</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEAVY-FOOTED anglers know from hard experience that fish can hear their steps on the river bank and dart away to safety.</p>
        <p>The vibrations in the ground propagate through the water, impinge on bones of the fish and then travel to chambers inside the skull on either side of the brain and just behind the eyes. There the sound waves rattle tiny stones resting in beds of nerve hairs, which communicate signals of the disturbance to the brain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEAVY-FOOTED anglers know from hard experience that fish can hear their steps on the river bank and dart away to safety.</p>
        <p>The vibrations in the ground propagate through the water, impinge on bones of the fish and then travel to chambers inside the skull on either side of the brain and just behind the eyes. There the sound waves rattle tiny stones resting in beds of nerve hairs, which communicate signals of the disturbance to the brain.</p>
        <p>This is the way fish hear, with two entirely internal ears each containing three pairs of calcium carbonate stones called otoliths, ear stones. An Unsuspected Function</p>
        <p>Now scientists are finding in fish ears a new and previously unsuspected function, not for the fish themselves but for research into the world's climate history. The otoliths from fish that lived long ago, they have discovered, preserve an amazingly detailed record of seasonal temperature variations over the past 200 million years. These stones can be, in effect, paleothermometers.</p>
        <p>"What we've developed is an important new tool for studying global change," said Dr. Gerald J. Smith, a zoologist at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor.</p>
        <p>Of particular importance, analysis of otoliths promises to fill a serious gap in knowledge of climate history. The usual sources of information about past climates are fossils of one-celled organisms called foraminifera. Since these are found only in ocean sediments, they provide clues only to ocean temperatures. They may reflect general climatic conditions of a certain period, but only on very large time and geographic scales.</p>
        <p>By examining otoliths from fresh-water fish, Dr. Smith and his colleagues were able to learn about past temperatures in midcontinental regions, which are especially sensitive to seasonal climate changes. Thin growth layers inside the stones, like the rings of a tree, contain evidence of weekly, sometimes daily, changes in water temperature over the life of the fish, whether it died last week or a million years ago. Museum Collections Studied</p>
        <p>William P. Patterson, a graduate student in geology at Michigan, learned to read this record by studying museum collections of otoliths, some of which dated to the time of the dinosaurs more than 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Stones from small fish are like grains of sand, barely visible to the unaided eye. Those from larger fish can be more than half an inch wide, about the size of small marbles. Each species produces otoliths that are identifiably different in size and shape.</p>
        <p>Contrary to an opinion sometimes expressed, people do not have rocks in their heads, although their inner ears do contain some microscopic grains of calcium carbonate called otoconia. Bones in the inner ear, not the otoconia, serve much the same function for humans as the otoliths do for fish.</p>
        <p>Many of the museum specimens of otoliths had been collected by geologists and paleontologists from layers of ancient sediments. Others were found in archeological excavations of American Indian settlements. The larger, more beautiful ones seem to have been prized "collectibles" among Indians in the Great Lakes area.</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson sliced open some of these stones to count the microscopic growth rings and analyze the ratio of certain oxygen components in the minerals of each ring. This ratio of oxygen isotopes is the key to using otoliths as paleothermometers.</p>
        <p>"Because we can reconstruct average weekly temperatures with this technique, we can accurately track seasonality -- the difference between winter low and summer high temperatures," Mr. Patterson said. "Seasonality is the most significant factor in determining which plants and animals can survive in a particular area."</p>
        <p>Mr. Patterson, Dr. Smith and Dr. Kyger C. Lohmann, another geologist at Michigan, described their otolith research at recent meetings of the Geological Society of America in Cincinnati and the Society of Vertebrate Paleontology in Toronto. Isotopes Tell Story</p>
        <p>Each day a fish synthesizes the calcium carbonate mineral known as aragonite, which includes oxygen from the surrounding water, and so gradually builds up the size of its ear stones. Most of the oxygen atoms in the mineral are in the form of oxygen-16 isotopes. A tiny fraction is oxygen-18, which is a slightly heavier atom because it contains two extra neutrons.</p>
        <p>In a study of modern fish from the Great Lakes, particularly a large species of drum, Mr. Patterson and Dr. Smith found that the ratio of these oxygen isotopes deposited each day in the otolith corresponded to prevailing conditions in the lake.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Patterson explained: "When the water and the fish are cold, the fish absorbs more of the heavier isotopes. When the water is warmer, more of the lighter isotopes are absorbed and incorporated in the otolith. The ratio of the two isotopes varies directly with the temperature of the water. If we know the isotopic composition of the water as stored in the otolith, we can infer past water temperatures."</p>
        <p>Variations in the width of the rings, the scientists said, can also reveal ecological and physiological stresses like starvation, mating or especially cool winter temperatures.</p>
        <p>The Michigan researchers have already extended their investigation and identified isotope fluctuations in 3.5-million-year-old otoliths from Florida and Idaho. One of the earliest known otoliths, a 200-million-year-old specimen from England, has yet to be analyzed.</p>
        <p>The more immediate objective is to examine stones from fish ears to chart seasonal temperatures in the Great Lakes region over the past 11,000 years. With otoliths as their paleothermometers, the scientists expect to learn enough about past climates to make more meaningful predictions of future climate change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
