<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone Depletion Threatening Latin Sun Worshipers</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517043"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CANCER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNBURN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Skin Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8133EF934A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone Depletion Threatening Latin Sun Worshipers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>PUNTA DEL ESTE, Uruguay</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eduardo Betancourt has worked for 13 years as a lifeguard on these golden beaches. Seven hours a day, he says, he watches his Uruguayan compatriots and vacationers from Argentina lie out in the sun developing tans the color of coffee beans.</p>
        <p>But now, Mr. Betancourt says, he is worried: The sun has felt hotter in recent years, he believes, and he says it now "stings." For the first time this year, his skin peeled. Others here also say they have noticed the change, which Mr. Betancourt attributes to the ozone destruction scientists say has lessened the earth's natural protection from the sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eduardo Betancourt has worked for 13 years as a lifeguard on these golden beaches. Seven hours a day, he says, he watches his Uruguayan compatriots and vacationers from Argentina lie out in the sun developing tans the color of coffee beans.</p>
        <p>But now, Mr. Betancourt says, he is worried: The sun has felt hotter in recent years, he believes, and he says it now "stings." For the first time this year, his skin peeled. Others here also say they have noticed the change, which Mr. Betancourt attributes to the ozone destruction scientists say has lessened the earth's natural protection from the sun.</p>
        <p>"But you don't see much change in the people," said Mr. Betancourt, who is 29 years old. "Before they didn't use creams. Now they say they're a little worried about the ozone, so they put a lot of cream on. They think cream will protect them totally.</p>
        <p>"They still come at 10 in the morning and lie baking in the sun until 5 in the afternoon," he said.  Ultraviolet Rays Rise</p>
        <p>As the Southern Hemisphere's summer draws to an end, taking with it the days of windsurfing, jet skiing and beach volleyball, it is hard for many people here to focus on the news that it is time to end their love affair with the sun because ozone-destroying chemicals have significantly depleted the ozone layer in this and other parts of the world, increasing the level of dangerous ultraviolet rays that reach the earth.</p>
        <p>Scientists generally agree that there has been a certain level of ozone depletion, including a hole in the ozone layer that opens up over Antarctica in August and stretches to areas like Punta Arenas, Chile, and Ushuiah, Argentina. When it starts to close in November and December, it can shoot spikes of ozone-depleted air north for hundreds of miles, scientists add. But there have been no real, consistent international efforts so far to accurately study that depletion or what is thought to be one of its primary effects on people -- long exposure to ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>Charles Booth, president of Biospherical Instruments in San Diego, operates the only instruments in the Southern Cone that accurately measure ultraviolet radiation as a result of ozone loss. In a telephone interview he said, "It is generally accepted that the loss of ozone in the Southern Hemisphere is greater than that in the Northern Hemisphere."</p>
        <p>Some local governments and vacationers seem slowly to be awakening to the fact that maybe the days of endless sun should come to an end, as many dermatologists recommend. The Argentine and Uruguayan Governments, for instance, have mounted tiny public health campaigns warning about the summer sun. But the practical effects have been spotty.</p>
        <p>Luis Enrique, an Argentine vacationing here with his wife, said: "We are not doing a lot different. Maybe we try not to come during the middle of the day."</p>
        <p>At Amelia's Perfume Shop on the main shopping strip, Golero, there are signs of some change. Hawaiian Tropic 30 Ozone Sunblock, imported from the United States, is in great demand, even though it costs a whopping $21 for four ounces. 'Dark, Dark, Dark' the Goal</p>
        <p>"You come here to be on vacation," said Manuel David. "You don't want to be told not to go into the sun. The people still want to be burned. They want to go back to Buenos Aires dark, dark, dark."</p>
        <p>In San Roque's cosmetic shop across the street, they say that the only women they find who do not continue with their intense sunbathing are those who have had cosmetic surgery, and that their motivation is fear that their skin will be restretched by the effects of the sun.</p>
        <p>Indeed, most people here acknowledge that it is hard to change national habits.</p>
        <p>"In this part of the world people are still mainly concerned about whether they have enough money and if their paycheck will buy the same," said Roberto Gonzalez, an Uruguayan journalist.</p>
        <p>Still, there are ominous signs, at least anecdotally, that would seem to suggest the wisdom of serious changes in sunbathing on these beaches.</p>
        <p>Dr. Anna-Maria Salazar, a dermatologist at the Mautone Clinic in Punta del Este, says she has seen dramatic changes in patients in recent years.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, she saw one case of the often-fatal melanoma skin cancer every year and a half. Now, she is seeing 10 cases a year. The more treatable form of skin cancer, basal and squamous skin cancers, used to be confined only to patients above 60 years old. Now, she says, she sees this kind of cancer in the 25-to-35-year-old age group.</p>
        <p>Also, she says that five years ago 80 percent of the skin problems she saw were related to infection. Now, 90 percent of the problems are sun related.</p>
        <p>"Other doctors may have different statistics, but those colleagues I talk to all confirm these trends," Dr. Salazar said. Efforts by Chile</p>
        <p>One country that may be more on its way to changing sunbathing habits is Chile. Last December, the Health Ministry began a serious public awareness campaign to persuade Chileans to "enjoy the sun in a healthy way," warning people to stay out of the sun between 10 A.M. and 2 P.M.</p>
        <p>The National Commission on the Environment has begun a study about ozone-depleting chemicals used in the country and ways to replace them with safer products. Next month, the Chilean Air Force plans to start a study of how serious the ozone depletion has been.</p>
        <p>In January, the University of Chile began measuring ultraviolent radiation levels in various parts of the country. A private research organization, the Institute for Political Ecology, set up a telephone hot line that answers questions about the ozone depletion and recommends how to protect against ultraviolet rays. Officials say they get 20 calls a day.</p>
        <p>"They talk a lot about this on the beach," said Claudia Rozic, a physical therapist at Catholic University, as she sunned herself on the Maitencillo beach, some two and a half hours northwest of Santiago. "Also I don't see the dark, burned faces I used to see." A Natural Laboratory</p>
        <p>One reason for the awareness may be that in Chile's extreme south, the city of Punta Arenas is one of the largest urban populations where the so-called ozone hole from the Antarctic opens for several months between September and November.</p>
        <p>Researchers say Punta Arenas offers a stunning natural laboratory about the effects of the problem on both plant, animal and human life.</p>
        <p>Though little serious study has yet to be done, the recent past has seen an increase in Twilight Zone-type reports of sheep and rabbits with cataracts, changes in plants' patterns of blooming and the need of schoolchildren for glasses at early ages. These reports have created a low-grade panic among some of the population and have been widely circulated throughout Chile.</p>
        <p>A typical reaction is that of Cecilia Garcia, a tanned woman who was enjoying the Maintencillo beach not long ago with her husband and three children -- all five under the cover of sun block. "Before I was concerned about not getting red during the first days," she said. "And when I got tanned, I relaxed. Now, however, I'm worried all the time."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
