<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where You Are What You Wear; At the Sunglass Hut, Selling Image and Status by the Pair</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Modern Mecca -- Fourth in a series of occasional visits to a regional shoppinf mall." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520112"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOPPING CENTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNGLASSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DANBURY FAIR (SHOPPING MALL)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUNGLASS HUT CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eyes and Eyesight</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D9123FF93AA35757C0A964958260" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where You Are What You Wear; At the Sunglass Hut, Selling Image and Status by the Pair</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</byline>
      <dateline>DANBURY, Conn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A stylish woman swept past Kristian Matz at the mall.</p>
        <p>"Christian Dior, $275," he said.</p>
        <p>He meant the sunglasses.</p>
        <p>He would.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A stylish woman swept past Kristian Matz at the mall.</p>
        <p>"Christian Dior, $275," he said.</p>
        <p>He meant the sunglasses.</p>
        <p>He would.</p>
        <p>Malls have given a whole new meaning to the term "specialist." There are stores that sell only shirts. There are sneaker shops, jeans joints and pocketbook parlors. Each is staffed by people who cultivate an unusually narrow expertise and tend to get distracted by particular passing body coverings.</p>
        <p>At the dawn of the consumer age, Vance Packard's 1957 book "The Hidden Persuaders" detailed how automobile dealers peddled hope, status and sexual image. In the day of the mall, the new persuaders are places like the specialty shop where 21-year-old Kristian Matz works: Sunglass Hut.</p>
        <p>The Hut, in some 540 mall locations from coast to coast -- including two here at the Danbury Fair Mall -- decrees that shades are the "health product of the 90's." It seems to scream that, sags and bulges notwithstanding, anyone can look like Tom Cruise (in "Rainman," L.A. Eyeworks, Botta, $120) or Susan Sarandon (in "Thelma &amp; Louise" L.A. Eyeworks, Cornu, $150) or, should the need arise, Arnold Schwarzenegger (in "Terminator 2," Persol Wraparounds $198).</p>
        <p>"Our goal is to make sunglasses like owning shoes," said Jack B. Chadsey, the president of the Sunglass Hut Corporation, which is based in Miami. "Men could have four to five pairs. You tell me how many pairs women could have."</p>
        <p>If the Hut fails to make sunglasses essential, it will not be for lack of trying, recent visits to Danbury Fair proved. From the bottom of the organization, to the top, the sunglass mantra rings.</p>
        <p>"Sunglasses are mysterious. They're sexy. It's a fun product," said Steve Lemack, the Sunglass Hut regional director, whose territory includes the Danbury Fair stores.</p>
        <p>At the Danbury mall, Kristian Matz and the other sunglass sales associates, whose average age is 21.8 and who all look as though they just came in from the beach, can deliver a sunglass spiel in person that is nearly as convincing as the ones Mr. Chadsey and Mr. Lemack made over the telephone.</p>
        <p>They analyze the "function" and "fashion" components of sunglass desirability. They explain the relationship between the depletion of the ozone layer and the need for sunglasses. And they provide fashion advice. But with the accent on the positive.</p>
        <p>There is the occasional double-chinned customer, just sliding toward middle age, who is intent on the surfer's specs (like Bausch &amp; Lomb's Killer Loops with polycarbonite lenses, $89). Such a prospect, Mr. Matz said, is likely to receive the advice that a tamer pair might look, well, better with his features and skin pigmentation.</p>
        <p>"You don't want to put down your product," Mr. Matz said. Different Perspectives</p>
        <p>All the attention on sunglasses, some of the Hutmen admitted, does slightly skew their view of the world. Leo D. Mueller, an earnest 23-year-old who is the manager of both of the Danbury Fair's Sunglass Huts, recently went to Florida on vacation. Along the route, he said, he stopped at other Huts just to visit. And on the beach, he said, "You look at 'em. Everyone's got 'em on. 'He's got $200 ones on; she's wearing cheap ones.' "</p>
        <p>Edward Wheeler, who is, at 25, the oldest of Danbury Fair's Hut salesmen, says Leo Mueller sometimes gets carried away with his sunglass zealotry. "He likes 'em," Mr. Wheeler said of his young boss. "He wants you to like 'em. 'Everyone has sunglasses? The world is great,' " according to Leo, Mr. Wheeler said.  "I can't get that worked up about them"</p>
        <p>Mr. Wheeler and Mr. Mueller, it is true, do not have much in common.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Mr. Wheeler has a college degree in economics and says he is working at Sunglass Hut "in between" jobs as a junior accountant. Mr. Mueller has temporarily suspended his college studies and is "shooting," he said, to be the president of a company like Sunglass Hut someday. Different Specs</p>
        <p>For another, Mr. Wheeler wears Revo's modified cat's-eye style graphite sunglasses, while Mr. Mueller has Revo's Shapes Combo Round in mock tortoise shell with orange lenses.</p>
        <p>Despite this gulf between them, however, when tested, Mr. Wheeler showed a true Hutster's ability to discern the link between personality and sunglass preference.</p>
        <p>Behind the counter at the Hut's lower level location at Danbury Fair, called Sunglass Place, even though it is really a Sunglass Hut, Mr. Wheeler looked down at the selection. In the display case, where an ordinary person might see only plastic and glass, Ed Wheeler saw much of the human condition.</p>
        <p>To him the Serengeti graphite goggle represented "an older guy, whose looks aren't primary, conservatively dressed." The Ray-Ban Clubmaster: "That's going to probably be a lady in her late 20's, who's fairly well-off." The 60's retro-look wire rims, like one manufacturer's John Lennon line, brought to Mr. Wheeler's eye this picture: "Late teens, early 20's. Jeans. Sweatshirts. Flannel."</p>
        <p>But, despite the Hut's carefully crafted health pitch, another point of common ground between Mr. Wheeler and Mr. Mueller is their experience that something other than ozone-layer anxiety is the real persuader. "The No. 1 factor: Looks," Mr. Wheeler said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mueller agreed. "We have a lot of girls," he said, "who come in and say, 'What would make a guy look at me in a car?' "</p>
        <p>Back when Vance Packard was writing, car dealers had a way of exploiting people's secret yearnings. They would, he wrote, put buffed convertibles in their windows. One study he cited said men were drawn into the showrooms by this "possible symbolic mistress," though most ended up buying practical, clunky sedans.</p>
        <p>Sunglass Hut has its own version of the '57 red Cadillac Eldorado convertible with the big fins.</p>
        <p>Always glowing in the display cases of the Danbury Fair's Sunglass Huts, are the shields of Oakley's Mumbo Heaters ($135) that come in Blue and Red Iridium and other electric colors. Mumbos are the M-shaped wraparound high-tech shades ("effective against wind, rain, mud, snow and thermonuclear explosion," according to their maker) that are favored by the speed-skater Bonnie Blair, who wore them in the Olympics, and the skier Glen Plake, who sometimes adds iridescent colors to his shoulder-length hair.</p>
        <p>"Your introvert will not get a pair of Mumbos," Mr. Wheeler has concluded. A Dose of Hut Reality</p>
        <p>Yet, all day long at the Danbury Huts, the Heaters' Plutonite lenses draw people willing to try on danger. They even draw people who are not in the Hut's prime demographic target group, which consists, according to Mr. Chadsey, of relatively young, white-collar people with "a strong fashion sense."</p>
        <p>Tino Sinap, 15, from Brewster, N.Y., went for the Heaters right away the other day. "It goes with good hair," he said. "On the beach, you see guys with lots of muscles wearing 'em."</p>
        <p>When Tino was finished, a man who had been spending a good deal of time around the Hut finally stepped up to the counter to take the Heater challenge. The man had come to think of himself as part of the Hut's target demographic group.</p>
        <p>Leo Mueller put the Heaters on the counter.</p>
        <p>Then, he put out a much tamer pair.</p>
        <p>The man tried them both.</p>
        <p>Leo Mueller studied him.</p>
        <p>Then came the dose of Hut reality. The tamer pair, Leo Mueller said, looked, well, better with the man's features and skin pigmentation.</p>
        <p>Defeated, the man put the Heaters with the Blue Iridium lenses back on the counter. He had really thought, until then -- even though he remembered when John Lennon was a Beatle and not a line of sunglasses -- that he was still young enough to be a Mumbo man.</p>
        <p>But he did not say anything.</p>
        <p>Until now.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Series So Far</p>
        <p>The first article in this series about the Danbury Fair Mall appeared on March 27. It described the mall, in Danbury, Conn., as one of the region's new "town squares," a place that draws people not only to buy, but to stroll and to meet friends, a place where some succeed and others fail. The second article, on April 1, told of a woman who became a successful drapery saleswoman at the mall after her husband lost his job. The third article, on April 5, described the young people who have made the mall the center of their social life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
