<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adrift on the Bottom of the World</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="566935"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICEBREAKERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATHANIEL B PALMER (ICEBREAKER)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEDDELL SEA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Icebreakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DB113BF932A35752C1A964958260" item-length="4093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adrift on the Bottom of the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Sullivan;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For four months this year, 16 Russians and 16 Americans lived in a "town" of 30 huts on an ice floe adrift in the least-explored body of water on earth. The crushing ice of the western Weddell Sea had long been the nemesis of any ship that ventured into it, including, in 1915, that of Sir Ernest Shackleton. Until May, when the new American icebreaker Nathaniel B. Palmer came within 45 miles of Ice Station Weddell, as the floating town was named, no ship had reached this area and survived.</p>
        <p>Although the Weddell Sea is comparable in size to the Gulf of Mexico, it is so far south that it does not show up on many maps of the world. Yet it plays an important role in circulation of the world's oceans and atmosphere. Frigid water flows from its depths into the deep waters of the southern oceans, eventually creeping north past the Equator and forming a frigid layer that underlies all the oceans except the Arctic. It is thought to play a role in circulation of the planet's entire watery envelope, which keeps Europe warm, the Pacific Northwest damp and the west coast of South America dry. Recent evidence from southern-ocean sediments, from the Greenland icecap and from a deep oceanic trench off Norway shows that, particularly near the end of the last ice age, climate and ocean circulation underwent several sudden, drastic changes. Each took place over only a few decades. The scientists at Ice Station Weddell hoped to learn what caused them, and whether they might recur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For four months this year, 16 Russians and 16 Americans lived in a "town" of 30 huts on an ice floe adrift in the least-explored body of water on earth. The crushing ice of the western Weddell Sea had long been the nemesis of any ship that ventured into it, including, in 1915, that of Sir Ernest Shackleton. Until May, when the new American icebreaker Nathaniel B. Palmer came within 45 miles of Ice Station Weddell, as the floating town was named, no ship had reached this area and survived.</p>
        <p>Although the Weddell Sea is comparable in size to the Gulf of Mexico, it is so far south that it does not show up on many maps of the world. Yet it plays an important role in circulation of the world's oceans and atmosphere. Frigid water flows from its depths into the deep waters of the southern oceans, eventually creeping north past the Equator and forming a frigid layer that underlies all the oceans except the Arctic. It is thought to play a role in circulation of the planet's entire watery envelope, which keeps Europe warm, the Pacific Northwest damp and the west coast of South America dry. Recent evidence from southern-ocean sediments, from the Greenland icecap and from a deep oceanic trench off Norway shows that, particularly near the end of the last ice age, climate and ocean circulation underwent several sudden, drastic changes. Each took place over only a few decades. The scientists at Ice Station Weddell hoped to learn what caused them, and whether they might recur.</p>
        <p>In May, I made a midseason visit to the camp, traveling on the Nathaniel B. Palmer on her maiden voyage. The fight through the pack was grueling, and 45 miles from the camp the captain gave up the battle and we made the rest of the trip by helicopter. With eight laboratories, four aquariums, staterooms for 37 scientists, state-of-the-art electronics and computers and a helicopter deck, the Palmer is primarily a research station. Named for the 20-year-old Connecticut seal hunter who first caught sight of the Antarctic mainland, in 1820, it has a horsepower of 12,700 and the ability to cut through three feet of ice at three knots. It might well have been able to rescue Shackleton's trapped ship, the Endurance. It is not the most powerful of the icebreakers. Russia's nuclear-powered ships have 75,000-horsepower engines. The nonnuclear Polar Star and Polar Sea, both of the United States, are almost as strong, but their full-power fuel consumption is very high.</p>
        <p>This was the fifth icebreaker I had ridden into the pack. Each time I have been struck by the beauty of the ice. Its gleaming whiteness extends in all directions, broken only by heaps of fractured ice, volcano-shaped hummocks, drifts of snow and occasional icebergs. Here, as in the open sea, you recognize the horizon-to-horizon seascape as the surface of a great globe, this being a particularly unsullied part of it.</p>
        <p>There are many sights peculiar to this region. The crenelated patterns where two sheets of new ice, pushed together, have broken into patterns like interfingering hands form what resemble a striking abstract art. Ahead of the advancing ship, fractures in very thin ice propagate almost instantaneously, like jagged bolts of lightning.</p>
        <p>New ice assumes many shapes: "grease" ice so flexible that small waves bend, rather than break it; "pancake" ice, looking more like lily pads, whose edges have been crumpled by collisions with other pancakes; "frazil" ice, whose loose crystals act as filters, trapping drifting algae for later incorporation into floes.</p>
        <p>Wherever there are openings in the ice there is wildlife. We passed one floe with seven massive crabeater seals, which with Herculean effort wiggled into the water as we advanced. Flocks of Adelie penguins, after watching our unfamiliar intrusion, started waddling out of the way, then in panic fell on their bellies to propel themselves with feet and vestigial wings. The emperor penguins, as befits their more portly figures, shuffled sedately until the ship became too threatening, then fell to their bellies and fled. We were hundreds of miles from land, where the following winter these penguins would go to lay their eggs among rocks or on coastal ice.</p>
        <p>Groups of snowy petrels circled the ship and, after dark, flashed white in the ship's headlights, drawn by good fishing prospects in the newly opened water astern. We saw breathing holes kept open by crabeater seals in the frozen-over channels, and sometimes larger pools created by whales. Small minke whales sometimes poked their heads out to see the advancing monster.</p>
        <p>Almost constantly on the bridge was our "ice pilot," Ewald Brune, a German, who periodically climbed a succession of three ladders from the bridge to an enclosed, heated perch in the "ice tower." There he could scan the horizon for "water sky" -- low clouds darkened by reflection from open water beneath. In heavy pack, the ship, with its twin screws pounding the ice, vibrated wildly. In the mess hall, which is at water level, the sound of crashing ice floes was like a lion house in which the animals, roaring, screaming and growling, had gone berserk. Conversation was hopeless.</p>
        <p>Our running time was limited, for the sun set in midafternoon, and it was too dark to pick a route until 6:30 the following morning. Some days we received satellite images of the region, giving us hints of possible leads through the ice. But often the view from space was obstructed by clouds, and sometimes we were brought to a halt when ice fog brought visibility to zero.</p>
        <p>During the last week of the ship's attempt to reach the camp there were no ice-free leads in any direction. The floes, many square miles in area and covered with pressure ridges and hummocks, extended unbroken to all horizons. Pressing the ship from both sides, they blocked its efforts to advance. Over and over the ship backed and charged, only to advance no more than a few feet. New snow made the going more difficult, for it cushioned the blow each time. It seemed as though we were doing battle with ice that had taken on a character of its own, and we were losing.</p>
        <p>Finally the ship seemed permanently stuck. I could not but recall the ships that had already come to grief in this sea. The master ordered that a crane lift a heavy load over the side, then hoist it up and down, hoping that, with the engines backing at full power, this would roll the ship free. It did not. Like many icebreakers, the ship has heeling tanks on each side that can be flooded alternately to make it roll, but this being a maiden voyage, the system had never been used. When finally operated, the ship slipped free, but it was destined to get stuck several more times.</p>
        <p>WHEN WE FINALLY came within flying range of the camp, all plans to reach it by ship in our allotted time and deliver provisions were abandoned. Helicopters from the camp, landing on a floe next to the ship, ferried people and priority items in and out. At the camp, we were greeted by Valery V. Lukin of the Arctic and Antarctic Research Institute in St. Petersburg. He wore a classic Russian beard and was leader of the Russian contingent and the camp chief.</p>
        <p>The camp had been set up by a Russian icebreaker, Akademik Fedorov, in February, far to the south and in a more accessible area than its current location. The team used helicopters and bulldozers to spread the huts and supplies over the floe, lest uneven weight crack it. The American contingent, most of whom came in with the Russians, included, in addition to biologists and ice specialists, experts in top-to-bottom measurements of water beneath the floe.</p>
        <p>Life on the floe was comfortable but far from luxurious. Most of the inhabitants lived two to a shelter, including one for the expedition's two women, Suzanne O'Hara and Amy Ffield, both with the Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory. Arnold L. Gordon, a Lamont scientist who arrived in June, had helped set up the scientific aspects of the project. Many huts were Russian 7-by-9-foot prefabs formed by panels clipped together. They were snug, but temperature on the floor was sometimes 10 to 15 degrees colder than at shoulder height.</p>
        <p>Each hut was heated by a diesel stove, on which there was usually a pot of melting snow. The resulting water was poured into a vessel suspended over a basin. A spigot under the vessel provided water for personal use. Sometimes heat from a hut melted the ice beneath it, causing the hut to tilt, and it had to be moved.</p>
        <p>Some of the Americans lived in semicylindrical heavy canvas shelters, where each morning beds were made carefully, not from a passion for neatness but to insure that the bedding did not freeze to the walls.</p>
        <p>Small gestures helped make life seem normal. When someone had a birthday, token gifts materialized, the Russians providing not only vodka but also medals, commemorative pins, envelopes with exotic postage stamps. On Easter morning, Easter candy was found on each bunk, lying on imitation grass. Chris Fritsen, an American biologist, had been seen loitering near the huts, provoking suspicion about his role. The Russian Orthodox Easter came a week later, and the Russians greeted each other with "Christ is risen," followed by the traditional response: "Indeed, He is risen."</p>
        <p>Dave Cotter, one of the expedition's cooks, from Park City, Utah, prepared most of the meals, but his Russian counterpart, Yevgeny Novokhatsky, produced breakfast and special meals.</p>
        <p>The camp was divided into "North Town" and "South Town," with huts at either end and, in between, the mess hall, the one-person latrine hut and the food storage depot. The Russian flag flew side by side with the Stars and Stripes. For recreation, there was a sauna, where the Russians liked to retire to smoke and talk politics, and videotaped movies in the mess hall. James Bond and the "Godfather" movies were popular with the Russians.</p>
        <p>In February, after the camp was built, the ice opened into a "lead," splitting the camp in two and destroying an airstrip that had been smoothed so ski-equipped planes could land. After that, supplies were brought in by air drop and boats were kept on the snow in both "towns," lest the floe split some more. If necessary, the camp's two helicopters (assuming they were functional) could lift everyone to a nearby iceberg, where the ice is more durable. Icebergs are sections of continental ice hundreds of feet thick, whereas the floe was a slab of frozen ocean 6 feet to 10 feet thick.</p>
        <p>When the Fedorov set up the camp, it pumped diesel oil for operating and heating the camp into huge bladders on the ice. From these a mobile "gas station" on a sled was filled and towed by snowmobiles to whichever hut needed fuel. In the deep cold, however, wax began forming in the oil. Heaters clogged and occupants woke each morning in frigid shelters. Waxing was finally prevented by an additive that was flown in before the airstrip split.</p>
        <p>After the split, supplies were delivered by air drop. The Air Force C-141 cargo plane originated in South Carolina and refueled in Chile and again by aerial tanker. When it sighted the drop zone, marked at each end by a pot belching orange smoke, it made a practice run and then dropped a string of parachutes each attached to four specially cushioned drums full of fuel, forming a 1,600-pound cluster. Hitting the snow at 40 miles per hour, the clusters bounced wildly. One seemed headed straight for the onlookers, who fled in all directions. All 115 drums landed intact and most were lifted by helicopter to a central depot.</p>
        <p>THROUGH FOUR LARGE holes, each under a heated hut, divers and scientists had access from the camp to the underlying ocean they were there to study. Additional holes were cut in new ice that formed in the new channel.</p>
        <p>The behavior of the ice covering the Weddell Sea is perplexing. For two years in the mid-70's, satellite images showed, a region of the eastern Weddell Sea as large as the Black Sea was completely free of ice -- in winter as well as summer. If in the future the ice on the entire Weddell Sea -- one-third of all ice on Antarctic waters -- were to melt, this would greatly reduce the amount of sunlight reflected into space and surely alter world climate.</p>
        <p>Scientists at the ice station measured growth of the ice floe by boring into it and, as the season progressed, measuring changing conditions in the thousands of feet of water underneath. Igor Melnikov, a Russian ice diver, made video pictures of the bottom side of the floe, revealing a world of upside-down valleys, mountains and caverns rounded by erosion, with upended slabs left from ice that had been overrun. Long, salt-dripping pinnacles, or stalactites, had formed as the sea water froze, shedding salt through tiny channels in the ice.</p>
        <p>Swarms of krill -- the tiny shrimplike</p>
        <p>Euphausia su</p>
        <p>perba</p>
        <p>, which are eaten by the largest animals that have ever lived, the great whales -- penetrated the channels, trying to reach algae within the ice. Below the ice, feeding on the krill, were small icefish with outsize fins and heads so transparent that one could see a newly ingested krill inside the fish's mouth. Ctenophores -- jellyfish 4 inches to 6 inches long -- used their even longer antennae to sting and capture their prey. The ice was so thick in algae that when the Palmer had upended huge blocks as it fought south toward the camp they looked like frozen caramel custard with a thin frosting of snow.</p>
        <p>Although Melnikov is one of Russia's most experienced ice divers, on one of his first dives he had the panicky feeling that something was inexorably dragging him into the depths. It proved not to be some undersea monster but the sinking of a long electric cable that was feeding his floodlight and camera. For each dive, as a safety precaution, the Russian doctor, Dmitri Kirjunichev, was on hand.</p>
        <p>Every 10 or 15 miles, as the floe drifted northward, observations were made by dropping a cable with a measuring device through one of the sheltered holes. In places the water was as much as two miles deep. Attached to the cable were water sampling bottles, which were open when lowered, and then closed by a weight sliding down the cable when they reached the depth the scientists wanted to sample. On days of good flying weather, the scientists made measurements at sites up to 50 miles away. They hope eventually to produce a cross-section of water movements into and out of the Weddell Sea, by making observations across its entire width. Earlier attempts to do so by the German research ship Polarstern were blocked by the heavy ice.</p>
        <p>The water samples were analyzed for dissolved oxygen, as well as tritium derived from nuclear-weapons tests (indicating the amount of time since that water was near the surface). Also measured were three nutrients (nitrates, phosphates and silicates) to indicate consumption by organisms in each collection area. The abundances of various radioactive isotopes provided further clues to the water's history, such as whether it previously circulated through the Pacific, Indian or Atlantic Oceans. Other techniques were used to measure turbulence and the effect of salt and heat and ice drift on the water.</p>
        <p>That the floe itself is alternately squeezed and stretched was evident in the water channel that opened through the former airstrip. Overnight it sometimes widened 10 to 20 yards, then closed, creating a ridge of ice 10 feet high. When the lead opened up again, a skim of new ice developed, often covered with "frost flowers," each composed of tiny clustered ice crystals. A flower field may cover many acres and is extraordinarily beautiful. The floe, a mile long and a half mile wide, had probably formed in the ice pack about two years before, and was similar in age to most of the floes in the western Weddell Sea.</p>
        <p>As it drifts, the floe becomes thicker, a process that, as the scientists discovered, occurs not at the bottom of the floe but under the snow layer. As snow accumulates during the long, circuitous drift, and as other floes are piled on it by compression, it begins to sink and water penetrates between the ice and snow, producing a slush layer that attracts algae. That layer evenually freezes and, as the process repeats, a succession of algae-rich layers are formed. This floe had grown to more than 6 feet in depth, with parts squeezed into pressure ridges 15 to 20 feet high, some of whose "keels" extended more than 100 feet under water. Eventually it would drift north, melt and become part of the South Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Much of the research was aimed at determining the Weddell Sea's role in global circulation. As the pack ice sheds its salt, the water beneath it becomes more salty and heavy, and eventually sinks thousands of feet to the bottom and begins flowing north. It is this frigid Antarctic bottom water, which to a lesser extent also originates around the rest of Antarctica, that eventually reaches the deepest parts of all oceans except that at the North Pole. As the water sinks, it is replaced by warmer water from more northerly oceans, which rises to the surface in the Antarctic, where it cools and interacts with both the ice and atmosphere. The world's climate is thought to be partly subject to subtle changes in this circulation and its modification by the extent of sea ice.</p>
        <p>Gordon's team wanted to determine what factors were responsible for the clearing of the ice in the eastern Weddell Sea from 1974 to 1976. Gordon, an authority on circulation of the oceans, has proposed that this may have been caused by "chimneys" of rising warm water. Trying to understand the probable response of the pack to global warming is a major goal of the project, and at the Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York, part of NASA, Douglas Martinson, of Lamont-Doherty, who for a time led the Americans on the floe, is participating in an effort to "model" the factors that control world climate. The biggest uncertainties, he says, are the roles of pack ice and clouds in altering climate by reflecting solar energy back into space.</p>
        <p>Another factor in climate control is the extent to which the ocean in this region absorbs (or releases) carbon dioxide, the "greenhouse gas." As Martinson points out, the atmosphere contains 700 billion tons of that gas and the oceans hold more than 50 times that much. "If the oceans so much as hiccuped," he says, they could absorb or discharge enough of the gas to have a major effect.</p>
        <p>"We don't know," he adds, "whether the Weddell Sea is a net contributor or absorber."</p>
        <p>According to Peter E. Wilkniss of the National Science Foundation, which financed the American part of the project, such processes are too important a part of the world's climate system to ignore. To predict change, he said, "we at least have to know how it's working now," and this was essentially the goal in the Weddell Sea.</p>
        <p>BATTLING WITH THE Antarctic pack has a venerable history. Ice Station Weddell had been established close to where the Endurance became trapped before Shackleton could land his expedition on the continent. His ship was then carried helplessly in the same drift that governed the camp and was finally crushed as the pressure become intolerable.</p>
        <p>Thirteen years before Shackleton's trip, on the other side of the Antarctic peninsula, the Belgica had been trapped; both Frederick A. Cook and Roald Amundsen were aboard -- the former later claimed to have been first at the North Pole, the latter would be first to reach the South Pole. Between 1901 and 1904 two more expeditions became trapped: the first was a German ship, which, like the Belgica, was beset on the far side of the continent. During the long winter that followed, their steam-powered vessel exhausted its coal and they escaped only by burning the fatty bodies of penguins.</p>
        <p>The story of the second expedition is one of the less well known Antarctic adventures. In 1903, the Swedish ship Antarctic had landed its leader, Otto Nordenskjold, and five companions on Snow Hill Island, near the tip of the Antarctic peninsula. The ship was to pick them up the next summer, but it never came. After the Swedes endured a second winter, Nordenskjold and a companion, sledging across ice between the island and the mainland, experienced a remarkable encounter.</p>
        <p>Coming toward them were two men who, Nordenskjold wrote in his account, were "black as soot, with black clothes from head to foot, black faces and tall black caps." Their eyes were covered with strange boxes which, according to Nordenskjold, "blended so closely with the black facial color that the whole seemed like some kind of silken mask with wooden openings for eyes. . . . Never before had I been confronted with such a mixture of civilization and the most utterly conceivable degree of savageness. My capacity for speculation was transfixed as I endeavored to discern what sort of men these might be." Antarctica was then almost totally unexplored, much less inhabited. Nordenskjold's companion suggested that they might be confronted with "unknown Antarctic aborigines."</p>
        <p>The "natives" proved to be three colleagues who, when ice conditions blocked efforts by the Antarctic to reach Nordenskjold, had been landed on the tip of the Antarctic peninsula to cross the intervening pack and tell him the situation. Open water had made this impossible and the hardy Swedes, equipped only for a trail journey, built a stone hut and endured the next winter, living on seals and blackened by smoke from burning blubber.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile the Antarctic itself became beset and eventually sank. The crew camped on the ice until drift carried them within reach of Paulet Island, east of the peninsula, where they built a hut whose walls are still standing. They needed 3,000 to 4,000 penguins and as many seals to survive the next winter, using seal skins to roof the hut. The surviving members of the expedition were eventually rescued by an Argentine ship, outfitted in part by a young Ernest Shackleton who, more than a decade later, led what is by now the most famous escape of all from the Weddell Sea, after the Endurance was beset.</p>
        <p>By the time Ice Station Weddell was closed down, in June, the floe and surrounding pack had drifted almost due north along 53 degrees east longitude at an average of four miles a day. Before it turned north, however, the clockwise flow, or gyre, that governs ice in the Weddell Sea carried it westward. Wind and current drove the pack westward against the Antarctic peninsula, which is the longest peninsula on earth.</p>
        <p>Because of international provisions against degradation of Antarctica's pristine beauty, all elements of the camp had to be removed in June when the Akademik Fedorov and Nathaniel B. Palmer reached the floe as it drifted toward the South Atlantic. Tin cans were stamped flat and bottles saved. So were garbage and nonburnable waste.</p>
        <p>After the Weddell camp had been evacuated, Lukin and Gordon summarized some of their findings: The special environmental setting of the Weddell Sea, they concluded, "makes it a key constituent of the global climate system." They noted that their studies had revealed vigorous vertical movements of heat, salt, dissolved gases and nutrients in the water beneath the ice. These, they believed, could influence the atmosphere, the ice cover and the region's biology and inject cold, oxygen-rich water into the depths.</p>
        <p>They had found that the western Weddell Sea basin, from which the bottom water originates, is far larger than had been supposed, extending 60 miles farther west. The continental shelf nearer the coast, however, is 300 feet below sea level, rather than the 500 feet showing on maps. Current estimates are that 20 to 30 million cubic meters of bottom water flow out of the Weddell Sea basin</p>
        <p>every second.</p>
        <p>The Weddell studies are not over. The readings obtained so far cover only part of that sea. More such floating bases are anticipated, as indicated by the official name of this one: Ice Station Weddell 1. Numerical designations of Russian stations now adrift near the North Pole run into the 30's.</p>
        <p>Understanding the many-layered ocean currents and countercurrents that determine the world's climate depends on top-to-bottom measurements in all the oceans. Those recently conducted in the Weddell Sea fill a major gap, but are far from complete. Knowledge of what controls water movements throughout the world is still fragmentary and stands as a challenge to those who sail the seas and, in particular, venture to the southern extremities of the world ocean.</p>
        <p>Walter Sullivan is a former science editor of The New York Times and the author of "Quest for a Continent." This was his sixth trip to Antarctica.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Sullivan is a former science editor of The New York Times and the author of "Quest for a Continent." This was his sixth trip to Antarctica.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
