<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Playtime, Learning to Save the Earth</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALL, TRISH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DE173BF933A25753C1A964958260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Playtime, Learning to Save the Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISH HALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HALL, TRISH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The values and habits of society are always represented in the toys that children use, whether it be a Barbie doll in a feather boa or a miniature fast-food restaurant with its plastic burgers and fries.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, environmental themes are increasingly showing up in products marketed to children. In many cases, the toys are made of recycled materials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The values and habits of society are always represented in the toys that children use, whether it be a Barbie doll in a feather boa or a miniature fast-food restaurant with its plastic burgers and fries.</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, environmental themes are increasingly showing up in products marketed to children. In many cases, the toys are made of recycled materials.</p>
        <p>There are, for instance, crayons wrapped in twigs that have been "gathered from fallen limbs and roots found in road and ditch clearings" and hand puppets of animals that live in the rain forest, made of waste fabric and stuffed with the innards of old Futons.</p>
        <p>Toys with direct, overt environmental messages are also becoming more common. They range from videos in which the characters talk about saving the earth to science kits that allow children to detect acid rain or measure air pollution. Many books also teach about the earth's cycles.</p>
        <p>For younger children, it may be best to teach about the earth in a gentle, nonfrightening way.</p>
        <p>"To read a story to a young child about whales disappearing would be scary," said Nancy Balaban, director of the infant and parent development program at the Bank Street Graduate School of Education in New York. "If a whale could disappear, your mother could disappear."</p>
        <p>John Quinney, owner of the Seventh Generation store in Burlington, Vt., which carries more toys than its catalogue of the same name, likes toys that teach the value of re-use by the very fact that they are sturdy and inexpensive. One of his favorites is White Wings, offered in the Hearthsong catalogue, which is available by calling (800) 325-2502. It is a simple paper and balsam kit for making airplanes that, Mr. Quinney said fly forever and can be mended. "Durability is an environmental value," he said, "and repairability is as well."</p>
        <p>In his store, some of his favorite toys are a construction kit for making a helicopter, airplane or water mill that uses a solar cell for power ($19.95); the Hugg-a-Planet, a soft ball that displays topographic landmarks (in two sizes, $19.95 and $11.95); the Green Game, a board game that allows advancement after questions about the environment are correctly answered ($29.95), and endangered-species jigsaw puzzles, with animals on one side and maps and educational information on the other ($12.95). All are available through mail order by calling (802) 658-7770.</p>
        <p>Older children might like some of the science kits that teach about the earth, although parents who are ecological purists should be warned that many of them are made from virgin rather than recycled materials. The kit called Exploring Ecology lets children grow a pine tree and learn about deforestation, filter polluted water, test for air pollution and find out about acid rain. The kit, from Educational Insights, is $36.75 at Penny Whistle in New York and is available at similar small toy stores throughout the country. Information on stores that carry items from Education Insights is available from the company by calling (800) 933-3277.</p>
        <p>The Ecology Kit, from the Nature Company, illustrates home activities like measuring household water use and looking for drafts. It is $19.95. Earthlab, from the same company, has instructions for experiments that help children address environmental issues like acid rain, toxic spills and recycling. It is $24.95. Both toys are available through mail order by calling (800) 227-1114.</p>
        <p>Toys "R" Us carries a game for children 6 to 12 years old called Captain Planet and the Planeteers, made from recycled materials, for $12.99. It has the fierce tone superheros: Captain Planet tries to capture Eco-Villains like Sly Sludge, Verminous Skumm and Hoggish Greedly. The player who most quickly cleans up environmentzal disasters wins.  An Eco-Conscious Dinosaur</p>
        <p>For younger children, the celebrity of the moment, Barney the Dinosaur, wears a "Protect Our Earth" T-shirt in a video called "Rock With Barney." In the 30-minute tape, Barney and his friends touch on environmental themes as they have adventures in a movie studio. The tape, which is $14.95, is available at video stores or can be ordered from the producer, the Lyons Group, at (800) 527-4747.</p>
        <p>Old tunes are recyled in an audiotape called "Recycled Songs," by Don Cooper, for children 3 to 8. The tape includes songs like "Recycle" and "Smog From the Diesel," sung to the tune of "Pop Goes the Weasel." The tape, for $7.99, is available at Origins, which has stores in New York and Boston, and through mail order at (800) 723-7310.</p>
        <p>Books are a fertile area for the environmentally conscious. "We're seeing a lot of books, some good, some didactic and preachy," said Peter Glassman, founder of Books of Wonder, a chain of two stores in New York and one in Beverly Hills, Calif.  Fiction and Nonfiction</p>
        <p>Among his suggestions are "Hey! Get Off Our Train," about a little boy who takes a night journey and encounters endangered animals, by John Burningham (Crown Publishers, 1990; $15); "Antarctica," by Helen Cowcher (Farrar, Strauss &amp; Giroux, 1990; $14.95), and "Rain Forest," by Barbara Taylor with photographs by Frank Greenaway (Dorling Kindersley, 1992; $9.95).</p>
        <p>Some of the best environmental books, Mr. Glassman said, are so subtle that adults might overlook them. In "Miss Rumphius," by Barbara Cooney (Viking, 1982; $14.95), a woman travels the world, and when she finally settles down, she proceeds to make good on her grandfather's suggestion that she make the world a more beautiful place.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
