<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trees Aren't a 'Magic Answer' on Warming</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1E3FF931A35755C0A964958260" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trees Aren't a 'Magic Answer' on Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INCREASED growth of trees in forests is not likely to stem rising levels of carbon dioxide, one of the heat-trapping gases associated with global warming, several studies have found.</p>
        <p>Previous studies indicated that some trees could respond to increased levels of carbon dioxide by taking it up and growing substantially. That offered hope that the world's forests might act as a sink for the CO2 released into the atmosphere by the burning of fossil fuels. Scientists have warned that increases in carbon dioxide and the other heat-trapping gases could lead to a rise in global temperatures with potentially devastating effects on ecosystems.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INCREASED growth of trees in forests is not likely to stem rising levels of carbon dioxide, one of the heat-trapping gases associated with global warming, several studies have found.</p>
        <p>Previous studies indicated that some trees could respond to increased levels of carbon dioxide by taking it up and growing substantially. That offered hope that the world's forests might act as a sink for the CO2 released into the atmosphere by the burning of fossil fuels. Scientists have warned that increases in carbon dioxide and the other heat-trapping gases could lead to a rise in global temperatures with potentially devastating effects on ecosystems.</p>
        <p>But a study in the current issue of the journal Nature, as well as others to be published soon, indicates what forest ecologists had long suspected. Unlike the cultivar trees that were well fertilized and irrigated in the earlier studies, trees under natural conditions appear to be unable to respond sharply to higher levels of atmospheric carbon dioxide because of limits on other nutrients.</p>
        <p>Most of the world's trees are not being irrigated and fertilized, and scientists say significant uptake of increased atmospheric carbon dioxide is likely to be limited to the minority of trees in cultivation. Search for Magic Answer</p>
        <p>"There's been a desire to find a magic answer," said Dr. Richard J. Norby, a researcher who worked on the new study in Nature on tulip-poplar trees, "and trees soaking up CO2 out of the atmosphere is an attractive answer to some. That makes it possible not to worry about it as a problem. The trees clearly have some positive responses to increases in CO2 , but it's not the spectacular increases in growth that allow us to ignore the whole problem."</p>
        <p>Dr. Boyd Strain, a professor of botany at Duke University who is studying the effects of increased atmospheric carbon dioxide on the growth of pines, said of the new study: "I think it is a rather important finding. I think we'll find most of the world's forest will respond this same way and only the more exceptional cases will show some stimulation."</p>
        <p>His work with pines indicates that unless fertilized and irrigated, trees will not respond to increased atmospheric carbon dioxide by increased growth and storage of carbon.</p>
        <p>Dr. Norby and his colleagues at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee studied tulip-poplar trees growing in the forest that were given different amounts of atmospheric carbon dioxide. Tulip-poplars, also known as tulip trees, are important forest trees and are commonly used in landscaping. Researchers found a decrease in leaf size and an increase in ephemeral root growth but not an increase in the growth of the tree's trunk and branches above ground.</p>
        <p>Carbon can be stored more permanently in growth above ground than in the roots, which soon degrade, allowing the carbon dioxide to return to the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>With increased attention to atmospheric carbon dioxide and global warming, the subject of carbon dioxide uptake by forests is contentious.</p>
        <p>"If you talk with a dyed-in-the-wool agriculturalist who believes man can manage anything, they'll say the trees will sequester the CO2 ," Dr. Strain said. "If you talk to an ecologist who works with unmanaged systems, that person will tell you that it's impossible to get any kind of response. The problem is that all forests and natural systems are different and we don't have enough data on the great variation out there."</p>
        <p>Other long-term studies soon to be published indicate that there are variations among different tree species in the amount and type of response to increased carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>As the number of studies increases, scientists agree that the picture of how trees respond to increased carbon dioxide may get murkier. In addition to differences among species and natural conditions, the multiple effects of increased concentrations of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere will have to be taken into account.</p>
        <p>But despite the complexity, researchers agree that most species are unlikely to show any substantial uptake and storage of increased atmospheric carbon dioxide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
