<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ducking the Environment</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="554650"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD123AF935A3575AC0A964958260" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ducking the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator Al Gore says George Bush has "turned his back" on the environment. The influential Sierra Club says the President has compiled an "anti-environment record that is the equal of Ronald Reagan's." Meanwhile, Republican spokesmen describe Mr. Gore as an extremist whose "hysterical" views would strangle the country in regulation and cost thousands of jobs.</p>
        <p>These are caricatures. Mr. Bush's record is mixed, but his efforts to clean the air, protect the ozone layer and preserve Antarctica suggest a level of concern far higher than Mr. Reagan's indifference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator Al Gore says George Bush has "turned his back" on the environment. The influential Sierra Club says the President has compiled an "anti-environment record that is the equal of Ronald Reagan's." Meanwhile, Republican spokesmen describe Mr. Gore as an extremist whose "hysterical" views would strangle the country in regulation and cost thousands of jobs.</p>
        <p>These are caricatures. Mr. Bush's record is mixed, but his efforts to clean the air, protect the ozone layer and preserve Antarctica suggest a level of concern far higher than Mr. Reagan's indifference.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Gore is capable of hyperventilating on almost any ecological subject. Still, he discovered these issues before they became fashionable and has spent more time worrying about the trade-offs between jobs and a cleaner planet than almost anyone in government.</p>
        <p>If the debate stays at this silly level, Election Day will arrive without either party addressing important questions or educating the public on tough choices. The winner will emerge with neither an environmental agenda nor a mandate.</p>
        <p>This is not, of course, a convenient time for any politician to talk about the environment. Back in 1988, flush times, Mr. Bush could grandly promise to be the "environment President." No more.</p>
        <p>Reeling from recession, and using Vice President Quayle as his point man, Mr. Bush has remade himself into a champion of environmental deregulation -- all in the name of jobs. Republicans accuse the Democrats of caring more about the spotted owl than unemployed loggers, more about fuel efficiency than auto workers.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Gore is feeling the heat. The Tennessee Democrat has long argued that the nation doesn't inevitably have to choose between jobs and a cleaner environment, and in many cases he's right. There's no reason, for example, why the richest country on earth cannot save its old-growth forests and retrain the relatively small number of workers who would lose their jobs.</p>
        <p>Yet Bill Clinton's strategists have reportedly asked Mr. Gore to talk less about trees and more about the economy -- another sign that issues badly in need of intelligent discussion won't get it.</p>
        <p>What would the candidates do, for example, to reconcile energy needs with environmental protection? Surely a vigorous commitment to energy efficiency could reduce pollution and serve as a hedge against global warming while improving the long-term competitiveness of American industry. The only issues are cost, and how best to do it.</p>
        <p>The Democratic platform spends one sentence on the subject; the G.O.P. platform, none.</p>
        <p>Nor is there much discussion of problems that are global in nature -- greenhouse warming, for example, or the exploitation of valuable rain forests. The loudest single message from the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro was that the third world wants the West to help pay for the environmental costs of its industrialization.</p>
        <p>This is the sort of issue that Mr. Gore and William Reilly, Mr. Bush's environmental chief, think about all the time. But it does not fit conveniently into sound bites.</p>
        <p>The electorate needs to know how the candidates would handle a wide range of environmental questions. Yet the recession has both parties running away -- the Republicans from their early achievements, the Democrats from their promise of an even better policy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
