<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After '10,000 Mistakes,' Biosphere Is in Hot Pursuit of Credibility</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="558228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOSPHERE 2 (ORACLE, ARIZ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D91131F931A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="1384" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After '10,000 Mistakes,' Biosphere Is in Hot Pursuit of Credibility</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE leaders of a $150 million experiment in human life support are struggling to save it from scandal, accusations of fakery and what they now admit were a series of administrative and scientific blunders.</p>
        <p>The private project in the foothills north of Tucson, Ariz., began a year ago with considerable fanfare as four men and four women sealed themselves inside a 3.15-acre greenhouse, proclaiming it a utopian planet-in-a-bottle where everything would be recycled for two years. The structure was billed as the first large habitat for humans that would live and breathe on its own, as cut off from the earth as a spaceship.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE leaders of a $150 million experiment in human life support are struggling to save it from scandal, accusations of fakery and what they now admit were a series of administrative and scientific blunders.</p>
        <p>The private project in the foothills north of Tucson, Ariz., began a year ago with considerable fanfare as four men and four women sealed themselves inside a 3.15-acre greenhouse, proclaiming it a utopian planet-in-a-bottle where everything would be recycled for two years. The structure was billed as the first large habitat for humans that would live and breathe on its own, as cut off from the earth as a spaceship.</p>
        <p>But the project, Biosphere 2, was soon under siege. Scientists ridiculed it. Members of the support team resigned, charging publicly that the enterprise was awash in deception. And even some crew members living under the glass domes, gaunt after considerable loss of weight, tempers flaring, this winter threatened to mutiny if management did not repair a growing blot on the project's reputation.</p>
        <p>Central to the discord was an embarrassing succession of disclosures, often grudgingly admitted to by secretive project leaders after news reports. Yes, they were removing excess carbon dioxide from the greenhouse's atmosphere. Yes, they had pumped in fresh air. Yes, they had slipped in a duffel bag of supplies. In typical style, the last paragraph of a January press release revealed that, yes, the showy experiment in self-sufficiency had begun with an 89-day supply of stored food. Admitting to Mistakes</p>
        <p>Today, after a high-level panel made pointed criticisms of the project's scientific structure, and after a management shake-up, Biosphere 2 is striving to re-establish public and scientific trust.</p>
        <p>A hunt is on for a science czar. New department heads have been hired. A solicitous new public affairs director is eager to dispense facts.</p>
        <p>The project's leaders say they are learning from their mistakes and striving to regain their credibility. Time is on their side, they say. The overall experiment could last 100 years or more. Substantial findings, they assert, will eventually replace early fumblings.</p>
        <p>"Astounding mistakes," John Allen, a leader of the project, said of the rocky start in an interview. "I plead guilty. We're not the greatest public-relations experts." The biggest gaffes, he said, were in not being more forthcoming about the project's technical workings and failing to anticipate widespread interest in them.</p>
        <p>"It can be turned completely around," he said of the project's reputation. "We have a fantastic apparatus that has proved itself. It has unlimited potential."</p>
        <p>Mr. Allen, a poet, playwright and former head of a New Mexican commune who holds degrees in business administration and mining metallurgy, is Biosphere 2's director of research and development. The Test of Time</p>
        <p>Margaret Augustine, the project's chief administrator, conceded "10,000 mistakes" in an interview but said some troubles were inevitable in a novel undertaking. The real question, she added, was whether the project would withstand the test of time.</p>
        <p>"Are we going to be here five years from now?" she asked. "What are our scientific publications going to look like? There are a lot of areas we're just touching on now that are going to attract some of the top scientists in the world. There's incredible potential."</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas E. Lovejoy, an ecologist and vice president for external affairs at the Smithsonian Institution, who recently led an eight-person critique of Biosphere 2, said the scientific jury was still out and probably would be for some time.</p>
        <p>"It's unrealistic to expect an instantaneous transformation," he said. "Even with the best of luck, it will take considerable time to implement the recommendations of our report."</p>
        <p>From the start, Biosphere 2 has been a quirky hodgepodge of style, substance, smoke and theater. Skeptics dismiss the whole thing as new-age flakiness. The harshest critics say any scientific elements are ancillary to a survivalist cult bent on using high technology to outlive what its sees as the impending death of the planet Earth, which the group calls Biosphere 1. The leaders dismiss such accusations. Links to Outside World</p>
        <p>The eight Biospherians, as they are known, were sealed inside the eight-story, glass-and-steel structure on Sept. 26 last year, all single and free to form whatever sexual relationships they wished. Their only links with the outside world were to be sunlight, electricity and electronic communications.</p>
        <p>"You're going to have to drag me out in two years," cried Jane Poynter just before she entered, capturing the team's optimism.</p>
        <p>The inhabitants were to thrive for two years, living among 3,800 species of plants and animals. But things went downhill fast.</p>
        <p>In October Ms. Poynter cut off a fingertip in a threshing accident, leaving the structure for surgery and returning within hours. It took three months for managers to disclose that she took back with her a duffel bag of supplies, including plastic bags, two reference books, maps showing plant locations, color film, hydrochloric acid and spare computer parts.</p>
        <p>A wave of bad publicity started in early November when The Village Voice reported that just before the project was closed up, its managers had installed a device that scrubs carbon dioxide from the air and turns it into a solid for storage inside Biosphere 2. Carbon dioxide is exhaled by humans and metabolized by plants, but less so inside the Biosphere during the wintertime drop in sunlight.</p>
        <p>Project officials dismissed The Voice's charges that carbon dioxide levels were dangerously high, saying the scrubber was a minor aid to stabilizing the atmosphere during its initial fluctuations. Replacement of Air</p>
        <p>On Dec. 9 came an event that reportedly prompted a near insurrection by crew members, who had become increasingly upset about how the endeavor was publicly portrayed. After plugging a few holes, officials pumped 600,000 cubic feet of outside air into the domes, replacing 10 percent that had leaked out. No public disclosure was made until 10 days later, reportedly after crew protests. The vague announcement of the air replacement came at the end of a statement describing the crew's holiday activities.</p>
        <p>Adding to unrest inside the domes was a gnawing hunger as crew members unexpectedly lost up to 20 percent of their body weight, prompting much debate on whether to tap naturally grown food stores built up before the Biosphere was sealed. Finally, the decision was made to indulge.</p>
        <p>"The result was highly gratifying," Linda Leigh, one of the crew members said in a recent article. "I started regaining the weight I had lost. Tempers seemed far less volatile." The final straw was apparently when former employees began to allege fraud and deception; for instance, asserting that computer programs were designed to allow data tampering. "I've seen too many instances of them lying and covering up," Rocky Stewart, a Biosphere computer designer until he resigned last September, was quoted as saying by The Village Voice. "Having worked with these people for two years, personally I wouldn't believe a word they say." Outside Review Ordered</p>
        <p>Biosphere officials denied the charges. But in February Edward P. Bass, the Texas billionaire and oil heir who financed the project, called for an outside review.</p>
        <p>The Lovejoy panel's 14-page report, delivered in July, was an understated but pointed indictment. It said the project was hobbled by secrecy, poorly defined goals and a lack of qualified personnel, noting that the eight-person crew had but one Ph.D. It recommended ways to beef up the science and insure its integrity, including the publishing of results in major peer-reviewed journals and, paradoxically, the easing of rules for sealing and unsealing the domes.</p>
        <p>Dozens of samples of soil, blood, urine, cement, water and slime were soon shipped out for analysis. At least two major papers are in progress. And in August, the project began advertising for a scientific director.</p>
        <p>But the project's leaders concede that it may be 1993 before a scientific director is selected and installed, leaving him or her little time to marshal a grand research plan before the two-year experiment is over.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
