<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Organic Architecture: The Office as Oasis</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="ARCHITECTURE VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AUDUBON SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUSCHAMP, HERBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD123BF935A15754C0A964958260" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Organic Architecture: The Office as Oasis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert Muschamp</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MUSCHAMP, HERBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Recessions are hard times for architects, but they can be enriching times for architecture. In the early 1970's, a lull in real estate development offered a chance to absorb new ways of thinking about urban context. When building resumed toward the end of the decade, architects had largely abandoned the modernist view of the city as a messy slate to be rubbed clean. They had come to value the mess as history: a rich heritage of ideas.</p>
        <p>Yesterday history, today biology. Now we've got a real mess on our hands: the environmental crisis that summoned the world's leaders to Rio last month. It's time architects were summoned to address this issue as well. Cars and factories aren't the only big polluters. Homes and office buildings consume energy, release toxic fumes, send mountains of garbage out into a world that is short on dumps -- or fast becoming one. How can design protect the environment from the impact of urban growth? There may be no more pressing question for architects to ponder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Recessions are hard times for architects, but they can be enriching times for architecture. In the early 1970's, a lull in real estate development offered a chance to absorb new ways of thinking about urban context. When building resumed toward the end of the decade, architects had largely abandoned the modernist view of the city as a messy slate to be rubbed clean. They had come to value the mess as history: a rich heritage of ideas.</p>
        <p>Yesterday history, today biology. Now we've got a real mess on our hands: the environmental crisis that summoned the world's leaders to Rio last month. It's time architects were summoned to address this issue as well. Cars and factories aren't the only big polluters. Homes and office buildings consume energy, release toxic fumes, send mountains of garbage out into a world that is short on dumps -- or fast becoming one. How can design protect the environment from the impact of urban growth? There may be no more pressing question for architects to ponder.</p>
        <p>Randolph Croxton and Kirsten Childs, partners in the Croxton Collaborative, a New York firm, are wizards at making something worthwhile out of a mess. They are taking a wreck of a building at Broadway and East Fourth Street and converting it into a $24 million showcase for ecologically sound design. The new building, which will be called Audubon House and will serve as headquarters for the National Audubon Society, has already aroused wide interest for its innovative techniques dealing with lighting, refuse treatment and climate control. Mr. Croxton and Ms. Childs aren't just renovating a building here. They're turning pollution control into an art form.</p>
        <p>One of the beauties of Audubon House is the ease with which it joins the lessons of the 1970's to the solutions needed today. Lodged in a century-old Romanesque loft building designed by George B. Post, architect of the New York Stock Exchange, this is no space-age Biosphere. It is a tribute to the preservation movement that gave old buildings new life. And it is "recycling" on a giant scale.</p>
        <p>Mr. Croxton, an architect, and Ms. Childs, an interior designer, tried out some of their ideas three years ago in another loft renovation, the New York offices of the Natural Resources Defense Center. The main goal there was to reduce energy consumption. Many of Mr. Croxton's energy-saving techniques rival in ingenuity those of the Gothic builders in their resourceful use of light. Clerestory windows admit natural light into private offices. Artificial lighting is shut off by motion detectors when offices are unoccupied. Pendant fixtures eliminate the loss of overhead light into ceiling recesses. Pale wood and painted surfaces magnify ambient light without creating glare. Files are placed near windows.</p>
        <p>Two sets of judges have tested the results. Consolidated Edison, which awarded N.R.D.C. a grant to implement these methods, has monitored the offices for three years. Power consumption for lighting has been cut to less than a quarter of the level classified "energy efficient."</p>
        <p>But the toughest judges are the people who work there. Not all of them looked forward to becoming Croxton guinea pigs. Some feared having to endure winter chills, summer heat, and eyestrain from peering over dimly lighted desks. They are breathing easier now in more ways than one. The air they inhale is free of formaldehyde and other chemicals that commonly pollute office interiors. And comfort has not been sacrificed to environmental correctness. With their neutral palette of off-white walls and soft green carpets, washed by the natural light that cascades from skylights down a central stairwell, these offices are an urban oasis.</p>
        <p>Audubon House expands the oasis to the scale of a small green island. Although the National Audubon Society will occupy only the top five of the building's eight stories, it owns the entire property. This has allowed Mr. Croxton and Ms. Childs to overhaul the building from the ground up. Actually, from below the ground: a central recycling depot in the building's subbasement is the renovation's most imposing feature. With chutes running from the floors above, the system collects and separates four types of refuse, from organic matter (dispatched as compost to a rooftop garden) to paper (some 42 tons will be bundled for recycling each year).</p>
        <p>Organic material and paper will also be used to insulate the building. Walls are injected with a thick pink foam based on whipped sea water. Floors are lined with cellulose made from recycled newsprint. It would take a small truckload of unrecycled newsprint to list the building's other features. Yet even a complete inventory could overlook the point of this design. What counts here is the design methodology -- how the parts fit together. This design is about connections: between the gas-fired heating and cooling system and the sun's transit overhead, between the thermal resistance of glass, the moisture content of air, and the height, placement and colors of office partitions.</p>
        <p>The unity of this design surpasses the organic architecture of Frank Lloyd Wright because it unifies a far more complex set of parts. Most of those parts are invisible. They consist of information rather than tangible forms. What we will see at Audubon House is one stage in a comprehensive planning process that begins with research into each material used and continues as materials leave the building to be recycled. Mr. Croxton and Ms. Childs carry this kind of thinking to an extreme degree. They not only want to know what materials are made of, and how well they function, but they've also looked into the environmental standards of their suppliers' factories, their impact on local economies, even how they treat their workers.</p>
        <p>It's tempting to ridicule an approach that differs so radically from conventional design. Is this architecture, or is it plumbing? Design or economics? Building or evangelism? Mr. Croxton's lighting may relieve headaches, but his puritanical philosophy can bring on a migraine. Who left the lights on? Save the tin foil! It's hard enough to separate the trash. Do we have to analyze it also?</p>
        <p>Yet if this is an obsession, it is a magnificent one. And its benefits aren't limited to lower Con Ed bills, cleaner air and a more robust ozone layer. Audubon House also enlarges our conception of history. Some designers boast of the rare woods used in fancy marquetry. Ms. Childs boasts that her wood comes from "nonendangered" sources. Yet she turns humble wood into a precious material by reminding us of its rich history: the people, land, energy, ideas, and time it takes to grow a tree and fashion it into tables or pencils. History, in other words, isn't just a matter of landmark buildings and period styles. It is also a record of the ordinary objects that circulate through daily life.</p>
        <p>Mr. Croxton takes the same approach with the building's exterior. The old brick-and-terra-cotta walls will retain the marks of age. Yes, Mr. Croxton is reluctant to commit the energy it would take to remove them -- but also to rub out the history those marks represent. If the walls look the worse for wear, fine. That will make the point that what he advocates is conservation, not restoration.</p>
        <p>The result is that many people will walk past Audubon House without realizing that something revolutionary is going on inside. Indeed, if this project is any indication, there's a good chance that as the revolution spreads, few of us will even see it. But we will breathe it.</p>
        <p>ARCHITECTURE VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
