<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Really Cool Cars</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVENTIONS AND INVENTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROGEN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAZLETON, LESLEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB1539F93AA15750C0A964958260" item-length="4097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Really Cool Cars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lesley Hazleton;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAZLETON, LESLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT LOOKS LIKE A FUTURISTIC SHOW CAR: SILVER, with swooping aerodynamic lines. Just another sporty "concept" car, you think, until you get behind the wheel.</p>
        <p>Then comes a moment of disorientation. There's no gearshift, you learn, because there's no clutch and no transmission. Just two small electric motors, one for each of the front wheels. A long hump down the center floor of the car looks rather like the one in old sports cars; but instead of a driveshaft there's a line of 32 lead-acid batteries under it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT LOOKS LIKE A FUTURISTIC SHOW CAR: SILVER, with swooping aerodynamic lines. Just another sporty "concept" car, you think, until you get behind the wheel.</p>
        <p>Then comes a moment of disorientation. There's no gearshift, you learn, because there's no clutch and no transmission. Just two small electric motors, one for each of the front wheels. A long hump down the center floor of the car looks rather like the one in old sports cars; but instead of a driveshaft there's a line of 32 lead-acid batteries under it.</p>
        <p>Now you see the dials, which are centered just below the steeply raked windshield. Motor temperature, check. Miles per hour, fine. But then there's a dial for battery charge, marked in percentages. And another -- the ammeter -- marked in amps. Driving this car, you realize, requires a different frame of mind.</p>
        <p>Turn the key, and nothing seems to happen. No sound, no vibration. But press the button marked F for forward and step on what you can't help thinking of as the gas pedal, and the force of acceleration suddenly has you pushed back against the seat.</p>
        <p>You didn't expect this. You realize you're smiling. Surely a sexy electric car is an oxymoron.</p>
        <p>Until this car's debut in 1990, it was. The car is the Impact, a General Motors prototype designed to break the conceptual mold of electric cars as glorified golf carts. Though there's some way to go before it will be fit for the market -- the suspension is rock hard and the motors whine like an animal in pain -- G.M. has scheduled it for production in the mid-1990's, at a price reportedly about $25,000.</p>
        <p>The Impact is a major precursor of what appears to be an impending new era in cars: a radical change from gasoline to electricity. Even as auto makers struggle through the recession, they have been forced into an expensive, high-stakes race to determine the future.</p>
        <p>Fueling the race, as it were, are new environmental regulations introduced by California and now under consideration in 10 Northeastern states, including New York -- potentially, a total of just over a third of the United States new-car market.</p>
        <p>The aim of the regulations is to clean up cars, which by most accounts produce up to two-thirds of all urban smog and a quarter of the greenhouse gas carbon dioxide. The California program mandates progressively lower emissions standards, starting two years from now. At first, these can be met with alternative fuels -- reformulated gasoline, compressed natural gas, alcohols like ethanol and methanol -- and with improved combustion technologies.</p>
        <p>But these measures will probably only produce a holding pattern on smog and greenhouse gases. As James J. MacKenzie of the World Resources Institute notes, "with auto ownership worldwide forecast to rise by up to 50 percent in the next 20 years, we simply cannot conserve our way out of the problem." Thus, the ultimate requirement of the new regulations: By 1998, 2 percent of all new cars sold by auto makers with California sales exceeding 3,000 a year will have to be Z.E.V.'s, or zero-emission vehicles; by 2001, 5 percent; and by 2003, 10 percent will have to be Z.E.V.'s.</p>
        <p>"The die has been cast," MacKenzie says. "The only way to do this is an absolutely fundamental change in the character of the auto: its propulsion system." The hot technology of the internal-combustion engine -- known in electro-speak without any apparent irony as ICE -- will have to give way to the cool one of electricity, the mechanical engine to the electrochemical one.</p>
        <p>As developments in major industrial markets go, all this has happened very fast, and most auto makers are now scrambling to catch up, investing heavily in R.&amp;D. for what they still consider an uncertain market. Much of the research is directed at batteries, because at this stage no purely electric car can go more than about 100 miles before stopping for several hours to recharge. As a result, it looks as though many of the first electrics will be "hybrids" -- electric-drive cars using batteries together with small gasoline engines to recharge the batteries and extend the car's range. Some researchers say that a battery powerful enough to drive a pure electric as fast and as far as a gasoline car may well be on the market by 1998. And in the longer run, researchers are looking to hydrogen-powered fuel cells to replace batteries.</p>
        <p>"THIS DECADE IS GOING TO BE BY FAR the most exciting ever in cars," says Paul MacCready, head of Aerovironment, the company that led the Impact development team. "It's going to be somewhat like the 30's in aviation, when you went from canvas and sticks to airliners and fighters in just a few years."</p>
        <p>MacCready is not the kind of man you would expect G.M. to trust farther than it can see: too iconoclastic, you would think, for a major American corporation. A three-time United States national soaring champion, he designed a series of solar-powered planes in the late 70's. Then, in what seemed the height of eccentricity, he led a team that built a huge radio-controlled, wing-flapping, flying replica of the largest animal ever to have flown -- the dinosaur-age</p>
        <p>Quetzal</p>
        <p>coatlus northropi,</p>
        <p>or pterodactyl, with a 36-foot wingspan. That, he said, was to show the connection between the evolution of natural flight and technological flight.</p>
        <p>Far from a mad scientist, though, MacCready is a restrained, cerebral, intensely practical engineer with a Ph.D. in aeronautics from Caltech and a long string of awards and honors. No fewer than five Aerovironment inventions have been acquired by the Smithsonian, including the Gossamer Condor plane -- the first plane powered solely by a human to achieve sustained, controlled flight -- and the Sunraycer car, G.M.'s record-breaking entry to the first World Solar Challenge Race in Australia in 1987.</p>
        <p>After the Sunraycer's success, G.M. bought 15 percent of MacCready's company and gave him and his team the go-ahead to develop an electric car. They were apparently thinking of it primarily as a show car, but MacCready had other ideas. In just under a year, his team developed the Impact, with its top speed of more than 100 m.p.h. and acceleration from 0 to 60 m.p.h. in eight seconds.</p>
        <p>Most electric cars developed in the previous 20 years had been conversions of gasoline cars. They worked, but not very well. By redesigning the car from the ground up, MacCready's team transformed the electric car from a technological oddity into a stylish practicality.</p>
        <p>They literally reinvented the wheels: made out of aluminum, with tires specially designed to reduce drag, they help make the Impact so energy-efficient that if it were to run on gasoline, it would use only one-third the amount required by a typical internal-combustion car. And in a process known as regenerative braking, the brakes themselves act as small generators, feeding energy back into the batteries and recharging them.</p>
        <p>"We had to rethink the whole question of automotive design from the point of view of efficiency the way it's pursued in the aerospace industry," MacCready says, sitting in his sparse office in Monrovia, Calif. "And the odd thing is that nobody had ever looked at a car from that point of view before. There'd never been any need to."</p>
        <p>MacCready is no car enthusiast. He puts down the American obsession with high-powered, energy-intensive cars in his low-key, slightly sardonic manner: "If you look at birds like the albatross, you'll see they can spend days soaring over the ocean, with magnificent maneuverability. Then at the other end of the spectrum, there's the peacock, stuck on the ground, flying at most up to a low branch. The mechanical part of a peacock's flying function is minimal, so much effort goes into other things like the large tail, which hampers flying but boy, does it make the females quiver."</p>
        <p>The Impact promptly made a lot of auto journalists quiver, a thing they normally do only for peacock cars. The Impact's team had created the automotive equivalent of a peacock that could fly like an albatross, proving, as MacCready says, that "styling and efficiency don't have to be incompatible." And the very fact of its existence undoubtedly influenced California's decision to go ahead with electric-vehicle regulations. MacCready had demonstrated that the technology already existed.</p>
        <p>WITH SEVERAL MORE STATES looking closely at the California program, support for electric car production seems to have already "passed critical mass," as one advocate puts it. The European Community will probably adopt a similar measure in the next few years, as will Japan, which already aims to have 200,000 electric cars on the road by the year 2000. Meanwhile, in February the Senate overwhelming passed a bipartisan energy bill mandating the use of alternative fuels or electricity for all government fleets and most commercial ones by 2000. A similar if somewhat weaker House bill is expected before the Easter recess.</p>
        <p>But some critics call this unseemly haste. Rushing a new technology onto the market may be counterproductive, they say. David E. Cole, director of the University of Michigan Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation, argues that scientific research on pollution and the greenhouse effect is still contradictory. He warns that demanding that Detroit right now invest in a whole new technology could further jeopardize the position of the American auto industry.</p>
        <p>James P. Womack, a principal research scientist in technological policy at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, cautions that Detroit's problems could yet undermine the new regulations. "There's always the possibility that laws can get changed," he says. "It's true there hasn't been much inclination to believe Detroit when they've said they couldn't do something, and then done it under the regulatory gun, as with catalytic converters. But if you get to the late 90's and Detroit says they can't make the deadlines for financial reasons, it's quite possible there'll be delays in the mandates. So I don't know how much voltage there is, so to speak, behind the regulatory drive for electronics. There's a lot of room for poker-playing here."</p>
        <p>Now that the Japanese have entered the poker game, however, nobody can afford to drop out. "A whole electric-vehicle industry has suddenly come into being," one auto executive says. "Our Rolodexes have been transformed in the past year." And even though the regulations call only for a gradual conversion to Z.E.V.'s, the major producers know they will have to be there when the laws kick in.</p>
        <p>Some companies, including Ford and Chrysler, are working on electric vans rather than cars. Their assumption is that Federal legislation and market signals virtually guarantee that the initial demand for electrics is more likely to be for service and delivery vehicles than for private cars. But many others are going straight for the far larger private market, and their cars are attracting a lot of attention, both from potential buyers and from other companies.</p>
        <p>The first modern electric car to come onto the American market is scheduled to start production a year from now. Code-named the LA301, it was commissioned by the city of Los Angeles and will be built by a small British-Swedish consortium called Clean Air Transport. A four-passenger hybrid commuter car, it runs on lead-acid batteries plus a small gasoline engine that cuts in above 30 m.p.h. or when peak power is needed, extending the car's 60-mile electric range to over 150 miles. It doesn't have the flair or technical sophistication of the Impact. And because of its small production run -- 1,000 in 1993 and 5,000 in each of the two succeeding years -- its projected cost is $25,000.</p>
        <p>A prime contender for the mid-90's is the Volkswagen Chico, a small city runabout. Another hybrid, it uses a two-cylinder gasoline engine to recharge nickel-hydride batteries. The batteries alone give it a range of 12 to 13 miles for nonpolluting city driving, while the gasoline range is about 300 miles, with a top speed of 81 m.p.h. Some early reports price it at a very attractive $7,000, but initially it is likely to cost far more.</p>
        <p>Volkswagen is also working on a joint venture with Swatch to produce electric cars, capitalizing on the Swiss watchmaker's reputation for inexpensive quality.</p>
        <p>In Japan, radical prototypes have pointed the way to a more powerful electric future. Nissan introduced its F.E.V. (future electric vehicle) last year, with nickel-cadmium batteries fully rechargeable in just 15 minutes, compared with a minimum of three hours for most other batteries. That, however, is at 440 volts, which is far beyond home capacity and therefore impractical right now.</p>
        <p>Another Japanese prototype is setting an interesting precedent: it was developed not by an auto maker but by Tokyo Power and Electric, the largest privately owned utility in the world. Its Iza is a sleek four-seater with nickel-cadmium batteries, a top speed of 109 m.p.h. and a record-breaking range of 340 miles. The Iza is an expensive proposition, however, and is not scheduled for production.</p>
        <p>BMW intends to produce two sophisticated electrics -- the E1, promptly dubbed "the electric egg" by the automotive press because of its shape, and the larger E2 sedan unveiled in January at the Los Angeles Auto Show, with sodium-sulfur batteries, rear-wheel drive, a top speed of 75 m.p.h. and a maximum range of 267 miles. To Americans, one of the most striking features of the E1 and E2 is that they are the first BMW's to be powered by American-made motors. And these come not from a major supplier, but from a small company called Unique Mobility.</p>
        <p>AT FIRST BLUSH, RAY A. GEDDES, THE mustachioed chairman of Unique Mobility, is an unlikely proponent of electric technology. A lawyer with an M.B.A. from the University of Michigan, he spent 12 years as Ford's GT and sports-car manager, supervising Shelby Cobras, high-performance Mustangs and the like. In 1981, he got a call from his cousin, a radiologist who had invested in Unique Mobility. "He was worried about the way the company was going," Geddes says. "He wanted me to come help protect his investment." Like all good Detroit people at the time, Geddes scorned the very idea of electric cars. "I had to be dragged in," he says, grinning. "Definitely under duress." Yet what he saw was so interesting that by 1983 he was working full time at the firm's headquarters in Englewood, Colo.</p>
        <p>Unique had built a novel direct-current motor that looked so promising that Geddes decided to sell off the company's real estate -- including a race track -- to concentrate on its development.</p>
        <p>Standard electric motors pose a difficult trade-off for engineers. They can be designed for torque, which provides acceleration, or for power, which allows steady operation at high speed. But getting both characteristics -- which is what most American drivers expect in a car -- in a motor that is sufficiently small, light and inexpensive for a mass-marketed automobile is a vexing problem.</p>
        <p>The patented Unique motor uses less iron and copper than regular electric motors, making it lighter. More important, the motor's copper wire is wrapped in a special configuration and the current is controlled electronically to provide acceleration or high-speed cruising power as needed, and without a transmission. It is thus extraordinarily efficient, producing up to two horsepower per pound of motor weight -- almost twice as much as the Impact's variable-speed AC motors and more than five times that of conventional DC motors.</p>
        <p>Though Geddes may have gotten out of racing, the racing hasn't gotten out of him. Pinned to his office wall are engineering drawings for an electric Grand Prix race car. "Racing can accelerate this technology," he says, "just as it did for gasoline technology. Eventually, electric-drive race cars with a motor in each wheel will run circles around other kinds."</p>
        <p>With the legendary racing figure Carroll Shelby a former board member of Unique Mobility and still a shareholder, it may not be that long until the drawings move from Geddes's wall to the production studio. And another future indicator is the fact that the company's largest shareholder, Alcan, is working on an aluminum-air battery with 10 times the energy density of lead-acid, and far longer life due to an exchangeable aluminum cassette that can simply be inserted into the battery casing.</p>
        <p>The battery connection is important. Electric motors are well advanced, but batteries have a long way to go. In fact the phrase most used about batteries is "the Achilles' heel of the electric car." Right now, they provide too limited a range, take too long to recharge and have too short a life to make electrics fully competitive in cost and performance with gasoline cars.</p>
        <p>The range problem is more psychological than practical, but none the less real for that. The average daily trip of an American car is 22 miles, well within the range of even the most modest electrics. But drivers don't like to think of themselves as average. And the limitations challenge a basic piece of American mythology: the freedom to range.</p>
        <p>The energy and durability of batteries present more serious problems. Right now, new batteries mean an expenditure of some $1,500 every two years or so. And no single kind of battery seems to do everything that's needed. Sodium sulfur, for instance, holds about three times the energy per pound weight as lead acid but typically delivers that energy to the motors less than half as fast.</p>
        <p>The lead-acid batteries in the Impact produce nearly twice the energy per pound weight of current car batteries -- "we think our battery people sneaked some kryptonite in there," jokes one of the engineers working on the production model -- and take only three hours to recharge. But three hours is about 2 hours and 57 minutes too long when compared with the "recharge" time for gasoline motors.</p>
        <p>Detroit's Big Three have joined with major utilities and the Department of Energy to form the Advanced Battery Consortium, a billion-dollar effort to develop the ideal battery. The group's goal is to extend battery life to 5 years by 1994 and to 10 years by the end of the decade, while simultaneously bringing down costs and extending range.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, auto makers and utilities are on the verge of agreement on a standard charging system, while the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration has begun setting safety standards for electric cars. For a change, auto makers are hoping the agency acts swiftly; nobody wants to put a car on the market that suddenly has to meet new safety standards.</p>
        <p>The standards are likely to include disabling mechanisms to disconnect the batteries from the rest of the car automatically during servicing and in crashes, thus preventing electric shock. They may also require that batteries be sealed and packed behind flame barriers to prevent explosions and keep toxic and often highly corrosive acids from spraying the cars' inhabitants in an accident.</p>
        <p>Despite the intensive investment of time and money, batteries may be only an interim means of powering the electric car. The ultimate problem is that the electricity to charge them still has to be produced somewhere. In the first few years, as electric cars are phased onto the market, the present power capacity will suffice. But eventually, more will be required, and that means either more nuclear plants, which seem highly unlikely in the United States, more coal and gas-fired plants, or solar generation.</p>
        <p>In the long run, though, most experts predict that this whole issue will be resolved by the use of a far more promising energy source: hydrogen. In fact, it could be the ultimate clean fuel.</p>
        <p>HYDROGEN IS THE space-age fuel par excellence. The space shuttle uses hydrogen fuel cells to provide on-board electricity and drinking water. Yet one of the leading firms working on hydrogen-powered cars developed its technology not hundreds of miles above the earth, but below it: specifically, underwater.</p>
        <p>Energy Partners, based in West Palm Beach, Fla., was founded by John H. Perry Jr., a former newspaper and cable television owner who introduced computerized typesetting into the newsroom. In the 60's, Perry began producing small manned submarines for the offshore oil industry, eventually cornering 90 percent of the market. He also built the hydrogen fuel-cell-powered Hydrolab, in which astronauts trained underwater for the weightlessness of space, and began to experiment with fuel cells in submarines.</p>
        <p>Now 74 years old and looking more like a retired naval captain than a captain of industry, Perry is high on hydrogen, and curiously, considering that the source of a considerable part of his fortune is in the oil-drilling business, on the idea of clean energy. "The fuel cell," he says, "is the silicon chip of the hydrogen age."</p>
        <p>Fuel cells were bulky and very expensive until the development some years ago of proton exchange membranes, or P.E.M.'s for short. A P.E.M. is a variety of Teflon that looks like a regular sheet of transparent plastic. When treated with platinum as a catalyst, it splits hydrogen and separates out its electrons to form electricity. A series of P.E.M.'s stacked one on top of another like layers of meat in a sandwich produces a fuel cell that is light, small and potentially cheap enough to use in a car.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen can be burned in an internal-combustion engine -- BMW, Mercedes-Benz and Mazda all have prototype internal-combustion cars working on hydrogen fuel -- but when used instead to produce electricity in a fuel cell, it will take that same car twice as far. A fuel cell in an electric car as aerodynamic as the Impact could increase its range to about 400 miles, and reduce its recharge time to two or three minutes.</p>
        <p>Energy Partners plans to build a "proof of concept" car, rather than a production prototype, running on two hydrogen fuel cells.With it, Perry hopes to demonstrate that such cars can be ready for the mass market by the end of the decade, rather than 20 years from now, as most experts predict.</p>
        <p>Though the car will use gaseous hydrogen as its fuel for now, a better and safer option for the future would be to store the hydrogen in an on-board tank containing a granular metal alloy that holds hydrogen gas in nonvolatile form, releasing it to the fuel cell as required.</p>
        <p>One of the many advantages of hydrogen as an energy carrier is fuel flexibility: hydrogen can be made from just about anything. It could be reformed either aboard the car or at the service station from methanol, ethanol or natural gas. It could even be produced by using solar power to electrolyze water.</p>
        <p>It seems the perfect fantasy: a car running, basically, on sun and water. But outside Munich, Germany, an experimental power plant is already producing hydrogen from solar power and water. Solar technology may be nowhere near the stage where it could power a family car directly, but its potential to power the car indirectly, by producing hydrogen, has now been established.</p>
        <p>THE TECHNOLOGY for a new era in cars already exists. The problem now is building a market large enough to justify the large production runs that will make electric cars more economical. Some of the options include regulation, as is being done right now, and incentives, like higher gas taxes or tax breaks for buyers of electric cars.</p>
        <p>"Economics underlies this whole issue," MacCready says. "Cars are not airplanes. You have to make them affordable. The challenge is how to get some of the efficiency of the culture of aviation into the mass-market car culture, which is all the trickier when gasoline is cheaper than bottled water.</p>
        <p>"If some fearless politician with enough charisma to carry it off could introduce a slowly rising tax on gasoline to, say, $4 a gallon by the end of the decade, the national debt would be pretty much taken care of, the economy would be revitalized, everyone's health would be better, and we'd be free of independence on foreign oil," he says. "But it's not going to happen."</p>
        <p>With a clear Federal policy still missing, the coming decade will be one of rapid development and high risk for auto makers. State regulations have set the pace. Now the question is whether consumers are ready to make the leap. If they are, it seems certain that within the next 10 years, cars will finally emerge from the century-old technology of gasoline and begin to catch up with the level of technology we use in the rest of our lives. Within 20 years, they may even catch up with the space age.</p>
        <p>Lesley Hazleton is the auto columnist for Lear's magazine. Her book "Confessions of a Fast Woman" will be published by Addison-Wesley in September.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Lesley Hazleton is the auto columnist for Lear's magazine. Her book "Confessions of a Fast Woman" will be published by Addison-Wesley in September.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
