<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary/May 30-June 7</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC1631F934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1583" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary/May 30-June 7</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joel Kurtzman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMPANIES Life Styles of the Rich, Famous Insider Traders</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMPANIES Life Styles of the Rich, Famous Insider Traders</p>
        <p>The seven investors charged last week with insider trading by the Securities and Exchange Commission were part of the celebrity set. Among them: Edward R. Downe Jr., husband of the automobile heiress Charlotte Ford and a major collector of American art. Martin E. Revson was co-founder of Revlon cosmetics. Steven A. Greenberg is a flashy public relations executive. The S.E.C. charged that from 1987 to 1989 Mr. Downe and Mr. Greenberg exploited their access to inside information to generate at least $23 million in illegal gains. One instance involved contracts for call options for the Bally Manufacturing Corporation, whose shares soared 45 percent. The S.E.C. says Mr. Greenberg slipped Mr. Downe information on his yacht in the Caribbean and at his Southampton house. "This is a classic -- very significant -- insider trading case," said Richard Walker, the New York regional S.E.C. administrator. Travelmania  By all accounts, the airline industry's half-price summer sale, which ended last week, was an overwhelming success. During the 10-day sale, American Airlines sold out almost its entire allotment of discounted seats. Delta Airlines sold more than five million tickets during the sale. Telephone traffic to ticket agents was so overwhelming some customers were put on hold for hours. Altogether, the airlines sold 25 million tickets worth $2.6 billion. And since passengers need somewhere to stay once they reach their destinations, hotel reservations are up. For the nation's ailing airlines -- they lost $4.5 billion last year -- the sales could be a boon since other fares have actually risen. They "could even end up making a few bucks," said Richard P. Firese, publisher of Travel Agent magazine. Elvis, the Thin Version  It was a question only an organization like the Postal Service could pose to the nation: Which image of Elvis Presley do you prefer? A paunchy, middle-aged king, wearing glasses and a too-tight spandex suit, or the young, hip-swiveling Elvis clutching the mike. The Postal Service asked people to send in post cards to register their votes. Last week, at a ceremony at Graceland, Elvis's palatial home in Memphis, the winning image was revealed. Not surprisingly, the svelte Elvis won. That image will be the first in a series called Legends in American Music. The Postal Service makes about $200 million a year from commemorative stamp sales. Perot Campaign Goes Pro  In the political consulting business, they may be the dream ticket: spin-doctor Edward J. Rollins, who managed Ronald Reagan's 1984 re-election campaign, and Hamilton Jordan, the strategist who managed Jimmy Carter's successful 1976 Presidential race. Though Mr. Jordan is a Democrat and Mr. Rollins a Republican, last week they signed on as co-managers of billionaire Ross Perot's still-undeclared Presidential campaign. Mr. Jordan will handle strategy; Mr. Rollins will take over day-to-day tactics. The two consultants will be rewarded handsomely. Rumors have been circulating that Mr. Perot would pay them each $5 million, but Mr. Perot said, "When you're spending your own money, you don't do things like that." The Inscrutable Buffett  For weeks Wall Street was speculating over who would replace Warren E. Buffett, the Omaha investor who took over as interim chairman of Salomon Brothers Inc., after the firm admitted manipulating the Treasury-bill market. Mr. Buffett worked tirelessly to change Solly's kamikaze corporate culture and rehabilitate its name. Last week, he stunned the street by appointing Robert E. Denham, Salomon's general counsel, as chairman. Mr. Denham has guided Salomon through investigations, which ended in a settlement for $290 million. "It was a classic Warren Buffett move," said Deryck C. Maughan, chairman Salomon's investment banking subsidiary. "Everybody's predicting one thing and he thinks in a new way." Punishing G.E.  For the General Electric Company, the nation's third-largest military contractor, justice was swift. At the beginning of the week, G.E., which sold the Pentagon $2.7 billion of jet engines last year, was barred from renewing engine contracts with the Pentagon and from negotiating new ones. The ban resulted from charges that G.E. executives bribed Gen. Rami Dotan of Israel to help the company sell its engines there. The Pentagon asked G.E. to tighten up internal controls and discipline its employees. But after only five days, the Pentagon lifted its ban. A Justice Department criminal investigation is under way.  INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>The Villain of Rio  Last week, William K. Reilly, administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said the United States "will have one of the less desirable jobs of the Earth Summit, that of party pooper." That's because the White House said it would boycott the global warming treaty unless the carbon dioxide emissions cap was removed (it was) and that it would not sign the biodiversity treaty -- which Mr. Reilly supported. Just before the summit meeting opened President Bush offered a plan to save forests. He said the White House would increase aid to other nations' forestry programs by $150 million to $270 million. But environmentalists were not impressed. They pointed out that the White House recently agreed to clear-cutting of the nation's old-growth forests. If President Bush is the Earth Summit's villain -- "Uncle Grubby," the Brazilian press calls him -- the Europeans and Japanese are its heroes. Europe announced a "carbon tax" on oil last week and Japan pledged $773 million to Brazil to help clean up Guanabara Bay off Rio de Janeiro. From Bread Line to Ruble Line  The latest shortage in Russia is not bread but money. The Government has run out of 5,000-ruble notes and other forms of cash. The shortage is so bad that on a recent trip to Siberia, Russia's President, Boris N. Yeltsin, had to load his plane with 500 million rubles to pay workers' salaries there. The Government -- Russia's main employer -- owes workers a trillion rubles. Yegor T. Gaidar, Moscow's top economist, went on TV last week to tell the nation that relief was on the way: Russia's presses would turn out new notes worth 142 billion rubles by July, 2.5 times the amount printed last month, and they would keep running until 270 billion rubles were printed. When the ink is dry, Russian workers will get their pay, he said, plus an 80 percent annual interest rate on the money past due. Western economists blanched. With prices rising at a 300 percent rate, they fear hyperinflation. The former Soviet President, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, warned that economic reforms had put Russia on "the verge of an explosion."  Are Japan's Banks Too Big?</p>
        <p>Japanese banks, like many Japanese companies, have favored market share over profits. Their share of international lending rose to 40 percent in 1989. But now they are hitting the brakes. Japan's biggest banks have a record number of corporate bankruptcies to contend with. Their share of international lending is now about 30 percent. "We may need to think more about profits than expansion," said Hisao Kobayahi, a managing director of Dai-Ichi Kangyo Bank An Uncertain Community  Until last week, the European Community's march toward political and monetary union seemed like a certainty. Then the Danes went to the polls and voted down the Maastricht treaty, which provides a timetable for creating a single currency. That's a problem for Europe's leaders since the treaty, which was signed last December, requires approval by all 12 E.C. members. "It's a bad blow at a sensitive time," said Dominique Moisi, of the French Institute for International Relations. Slimmer Trade Gap  The nation's first-quarter trade gap declined by 4.48 percent to $14.9 billion, the Commerce Department said. THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Bad Economic News for Bush  When the Labor Department reported last week that unemployment moved up to 7.5 percent in May from 7.2 in April, it was bad news, but not just for the economy. It "will also create some flak for President Bush," said Richard D. Rippe, chief economist at Prudential Securities Inc. According to the Labor Department, although the economy is recovering, job growth has been sluggish. Jobs in the Works  According to a quarterly survey by Dun &amp; Bradstreet of 3,000 companies, businesses may soon start hiring. The survey reported that 60 percent of the chief executives polled were optimistic about business conditions this summer and about hiring. But there are jobs and there are jobs. "The larger the firm, the higher the wages and benefits," said Charles McMillion, president of MBG, a business information firm in Washington. "One mass layoff can overwhelm the hiring plans of many smaller companies."  When Not to Balance the Budget  At his news conference last week, President Bush urged passage of the balanced budget amendment. But last week a petition against that amendment was delivered to Congress by the Economic Policy Institute; it was signed by 447 economists, including seven Nobel Prize winners. The statement said: "When the private economy is in recession, a constitutional requirement that would force cuts in public spending or tax increases could worsen the economic downturn causing greater loss of jobs, production and income."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
