<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Environmental Debate Expected as U.N. Convenes</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="556787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BULGARIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL ASSEMBLY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GREENPEACE (ORGN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION ((UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GANEV, STOYAN (MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bulgaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DB173EF935A2575AC0A964958260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Environmental Debate Expected as U.N. Convenes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Sept. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new round of disputes over environmental issues, pitting the United States and Western Europe against developing countries, is expected to be a major theme of the 47th United Nations General Assembly, which opened today.</p>
        <p>One of the Assembly's major undertakings this fall is expected to be the creation of an international agency to hear and assess criticism of the way governments treat the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new round of disputes over environmental issues, pitting the United States and Western Europe against developing countries, is expected to be a major theme of the 47th United Nations General Assembly, which opened today.</p>
        <p>One of the Assembly's major undertakings this fall is expected to be the creation of an international agency to hear and assess criticism of the way governments treat the environment.</p>
        <p>Creation of the body, to be known as the Sustainable Development Commission, was one of the recommendations of the Earth Summit held in Rio de Janeiro in June. The new commission will be charged with insuring that nations comply with the pledges they gave there that future economic development would not cause irreparable damage to the world's oceans, forests and atmosphere. The Power of Shame</p>
        <p>The commission will have no legal power to compel governments to change their environmental policies. Instead, it will rely on the force of publicity and shame to encourage them to live up to their Rio undertakings.</p>
        <p>Northern industrial countries hope to model the new body on the 53-country United Nations Human Rights Commission in Geneva, which uses moral pressure to persuade governments to treat their citizens properly. It does this by hearing complaints by private watchdog groups like Amnesty International, sending inspectors to investigate abuses, publishing reports and publicly rebuking offenders.</p>
        <p>Diplomats here say that North-South tensions are likely to flare up over the details of how the commission will work. Some industrial nations, under pressure from domestic environmental lobbies, want advocacy groups, like Friends of the Earth or Greenpeace, to play a central prosecutorial role. These groups would file complaints against governments they feel are not keeping their Rio commitments.</p>
        <p>In addition, governments will be encouraged to submit periodic reports to the commission on what they are doing to meet the ambitious goals established in Rio. These included a new international convention to combat global warming and stabilize climate, a blueprint for a wide-ranging environmental cleanup called Agenda 21, and another convention on protecting the diversity of living things -- something that President Bush refused to sign.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the United States often found itself isolated, both at the Rio conference and in the protracted negotiations here that preceded it. In addition to Mr. Bush's refusal to countenance the so-called biodiversity treaty, American negotiators initially were at odds with the Western Europeans on the extent of the commitment necessary to combat global warming.</p>
        <p>At this General Assembly session, many developing countries are expected to try to insulate themselves against outside criticism, which they regard as interference in their internal affairs. They would try to restrict the commission's powers and to limit the right of private environmental organizations to appear before it.</p>
        <p>At the same time, these nations are likely to press the United States and others to make good on the still-vague pledges they made in Rio to give them more money and technology to help meet the cost of industrialization without damaging the environment.</p>
        <p>The General Assembly got under way today by electing Bulgaria's Foreign Minister, Stoyan Ganev, as its president for the session, succeeding Samir S. Shihabi of Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>The United States, the 12 European Community countries and Islamic nations immediately demanded the suspension of the delegation of Yugoslavia. The Security Council is considering a resolution urging Yugoslavia's suspension from this year's Assembly as a way of putting pressure on the Serbian-dominated Government in Belgrade to do more to promote peace in Bosnia and Herzegovina. Further Polarization Feared</p>
        <p>But Russia, which could veto such a move, fears that punishing Belgrade in this way would only strengthen the more extreme Serbian nationalists.</p>
        <p>Next Monday, President Bush is to address the 179-member Assembly at the start of a two-week general debate when heads of state and foreign ministers will set out their concerns in formal speeches.</p>
        <p>Many of these speakers are expected to focus on sweeping proposals for strengthening the United Nations' peacekeeping and peacemaking roles, as set out earlier this year by Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali.</p>
        <p>European delegates may introduce a resolution later in the session adopting at least one of these suggestions by setting up a $50 million fund to pay start-up costs of new peacekeeping operations so that the operations can be launched more quickly.</p>
        <p>But it remains unclear how much support the United States and other big nations will give to some of the Secretary General's other proposals, which include a controversial call for heavily armed "peace enforcement units" that would police cease-fires, as well as a suggestion that governments might pay peacekeeping bills more promptly if they made them items in their defense budgets.</p>
        <p>While the end of the cold war has enabled the United Nations to play a more influential role in world affairs, this has principally benefited the Security Council, which is no longer paralyzed by the continuing threat of a Soviet veto.</p>
        <p>The General Assembly has sought in recent years to rid itself of a reputation in the West as a debating society where third-world countries used their built-in majority to ram through unenforceable resolutions criticizing the industrial democracies.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, the Assembly is trying to make its decisions unanimous. And at last year's session, a number of widely praised steps were taken, including a ban on drift-net fishing, which threatened to deplete stocks, and the appointment of a new official to coordinate international disaster relief.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
