<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ATTRACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Spring Times Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="514233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEASONS AND MONTHS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED9123DF936A25750C0A964958260" item-length="6578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ATTRACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a sampling of attractions, some featuring special spring activities, in New York City. Times and dates are subject to change. Museums and Historic Sites</p>
        <p>ABIGAIL ADAMS SMITH MUSEUM, 421 East 61st Street, Manhattan. A landmark house dating from 1799 features rooms furnished in the Federal and Empire styles of the early 19th century. Special events include "Celebration! The Spirit of America in Song," a musical program with Janet Frank, singer, and Thomas Schilling, pianist. May 17 at 2 P.M. Open Monday to Friday, noon to 5 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Admission: $2 ($1 students and the elderly; free under age 13). Information: (212) 838-6878.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a sampling of attractions, some featuring special spring activities, in New York City. Times and dates are subject to change. Museums and Historic Sites</p>
        <p>ABIGAIL ADAMS SMITH MUSEUM, 421 East 61st Street, Manhattan. A landmark house dating from 1799 features rooms furnished in the Federal and Empire styles of the early 19th century. Special events include "Celebration! The Spirit of America in Song," a musical program with Janet Frank, singer, and Thomas Schilling, pianist. May 17 at 2 P.M. Open Monday to Friday, noon to 5 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Admission: $2 ($1 students and the elderly; free under age 13). Information: (212) 838-6878.</p>
        <p>ALICE AUSTEN HOUSE, 2 Hylan Boulevard, Rosebank, S.I. An 18th-century farmhouse, converted in the 19th century to a Victorian cottage, which was the home of the photographer Alice Austen. On view are period furniture and "The World's Columbian Exposition," a collection of photographs and memorabilia from the 1893 fair (April 10 through Dec. 31). Also planned are a "Victorian Lawn Tea Party" (June 13, with rain date June 14; reservations, $30) and "Pug Dog Day -- Fun Match," a dog show sponsored by the Pug Dog Club of Greater New York (June 20). Winning entries in a photography competition for Staten Island students will be on view through today. Hours: Thursday to Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Admission: $2. "Austen's New York," an exhibition of photographs by Austen, will be on view 24 hours a day through April at the St. George Ferry Terminal of Staten Island Rapid Transit. Information: (718) 816-4506.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF THE MOVING IMAGE, 35th Avenue at 36th Street, Astoria, Queens. On permanent display are costumes, set pieces, filming equipment and other items relating to film, television and video. Special exhibitions include "Changing Faces," more than 450 photographs and artifacts that examine the work of hair stylists and makeup artists (through October); "Recent Celebrity Photography 1979-1991," featuring works by Helmut Newton, Herb Ritts and Annie Leibovitz (May 16 through Sept. 6); a retrospective of films by the cinematographer Vittorio Storaro (through March 29); "Chicanos in Hollywood Film," a retrospective of films from the 1940's and 50's (April 4 to 19); "Russian Cinema Before the Revolution," silent films made before 1917 (April 25 to May 31); "Echoes of Discontent," films and videos that explore social and political themes in Korea and the Philippines (June 6 to 13); "Burt Lancaster: The Tough Guy," a retrospective of the actor's career (June 13 to 28). Museum hours are Tuesday to Friday, noon to 4 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday, noon to 6 P.M. All activities are free with museum admission: $5 ( $4 for the elderly; $2.50 for students and children under age 12). Information: (718) 784-0077.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY, Central Park West at 79th Street, Manhattan. Exhibitions include "Barosaurus," a new display featuring a freestanding dinosaur more than 40 feet high; "The Streets of Dai Fau: Arnold Genthe's Photographs of San Francisco's Old Chinatown" (begins March 20); "Otavipithecus: Ape or Ancestor," the 13-million-year-old remains of a newly discovered species of pre-human (from March 31 through the fall); "Global Warming: Understanding the Forecast," an exhibition that examines the Earth's changing climate (begins May 15); "Ring of Fire," a film about the unpredictability of volcanos, shown on a screen four stories tall (through 1993). Screenings daily every hour on the half-hour from 10:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Admission: $5 ($2.50 under age 12). On Friday and Saturday evenings, a double-bill features "Ring of Fire" and "We Are Born of Stars," a 3-D film that takes audiences on a five-billion-year journey through evolution and the solar system. The films are shown at 6 and 7:30 P.M.  Admission: $7 ($3.50 under age 12.) Sunday to Thursday, 10 A.M. to 5:45 P.M., and Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 8:45 P.M. Admission: $5 ($2.50 under age 12). Information (212) 769-5000.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Manhattan. Contains the most extensive coin collection in North America. On permanent display is "American Numismatic Design, 1892-1922," which includes all coins issued during this period. Special exhibitions include "Medals of the World's Columbian Exposition" (through April 11) and "The Memory of Alexander the Great in Roman Asia Minor," which includes a lecture today at 3 P.M. by Prof. Peter R. Franke, an ancient-coin expert from the University of Saarlands, Saarbruchen, Germany. Admission to the museum and most activities is free. Tuesday to Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Information: (212) 234-3130.</p>
        <p>ASIAN AMERICAN ARTS CENTER, 26 Bowery, Manhattan. "Ik-Joong Kang: Collection of Buddhas," an exhibition of paintings, is on view through April 2. "Quincentennial: Denial of History: Alternatives to the Story of Columbus Today," a group exhibition featuring works by the artists Jorge Tacla, Arian Huang, Young K, Mo Bahc and Willie Cole will be on view May 7 through June 18. Open Monday to Friday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.; closed holidays. Free. Information: (212) 233-2154.</p>
        <p>BARTOW-PELL MANSION, 895 Shore Road North, Pelham Bay Park, northeast Bronx. The museum, on a nine-acre site, displays fine and decorative arts from the 19th century. "First Sunday Tea," a series of lectures, will be held on April 5, May 3 and June 7 at 1:30 P.M.; admission to each is $4 ($2 for those under 12). Open Wednesday, Saturday and Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. Admission: $2. Information: (212) 885-1461.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN'S HISTORY MUSEUM, 128 Pierrepont Street, Brooklyn Heights. On permanent display are photographs, paintings, drawings and memorabilia relating to Brooklyn. Special events include a walking tour of Williamsburg that passes bodegas, Caribbean spice stores, and a tour of a tortilla factory (March 21 at 1:30 P.M.; $8; meets at All Saints Church, 115 Throop Avenue, at Flushing Avenue, Williamsburg); "Forging a New Voice," a lecture that will examine Walt Whitman's poetry and its expression of physical experience and sexuality (March 31 at 7 P.M.); "Whitman's Sexuality," a discussion (May 12 at 7 P.M.); "Allen Ginsberg: An Evening of Readings," with the poet reading from Whitman and others, as well as his own work (May 29 at 7 P.M.). All Whitman programs are free with museum admission: $2.50 ($1 under age 12). Hours: Wednesday to Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Information (718) 624-0890.</p>
        <p>CARNEGIE HALL. "One Hundred Years at Carnegie Hall," a permanent exhibition of photographs, letters, newspaper articles and other memorabilia, including an autographed program from the Beatles' Carnegie debut in 1964, Arturo Toscanini's baton and Benny Goodman's clarinet. Open daily 11 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; closed holidays. Free. Information: (212) 903-9629. Tours are every Monday, Tuesday and Thursday at 11:30 A.M., 2 and 3 P.M. Fee: $6 ($5 for students and $3 under age 12). On tour days tickets are available from the tour ticket window in the lobby. Information: (212) 903-9790.</p>
        <p>CHINATOWN HISTORY MUSEUM, 70 Mulberry Street, Manhattan. On permanent display is "Remembering New York Chinatown," a collection of oral histories, photographs and other artifacts. On view through June 30: "Red Boat on the Canal: Cantonese Operatic Arts in New York City Chinatown," an exhibition of oral histories, memorabilia and music from Chinatown's Cantonese opera clubs. In the program "Reading and Book Signing," the author Gish Jen will read from her novel "Typical American," March 28 at 4 P.M. Admission: $7. The museum also offers group walking tours of the area, by appointment, that begin with a 20-minute slide show and lecture on the history of Chinatown, followed by an hourlong guided tour. Fee: $8. Open Sunday to Wednesday, noon to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Museum admission: $1 (free under age 12). Information: (212) 619-4785.</p>
        <p>THE CLOISTERS, Margaret Corbin Drive, Fort Tryon Park, Washington Heights, Manhattan. Exhibitions of medieval art and architecture, including sculpture, tapestries, manuscripts and crafts in a medieval-style branch of the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Saturday gallery talks, at noon and 2 P.M., will feature: "Medieval Enamels" (March 21); "Hail Mary, Full of Grace: Images of the Annunciation" (March 28); "Inscriptions: The Role of Medieval Art" (April 4); "Signes Triumphall: Plants and Flowers for the Passion and Resurrection" (April 11); "The Liturgy of the Easter Vigil" (April 18); "Music for the Easter Season" (April 25); "Elements of Late Medieval Architecture at the Cloisters" (May 2); "The Significance of the Book in Medieval Art" (May 9); "Lions" (May 16); "The History of the Cloisters" (May 23); "The Heroes Tapestries" (May 30); "The Triumph of the Light: Medieval Stained Glass" (June 6); "Making Stained Glass" (June 13); "Images of the Hebrew and Christian Bibles: Harmony and Confrontation" (June 20). Tuesday to Sunday, 9:30 A.M. to 5:15 P.M.; closed Monday and holidays. Suggested admission: $6 ($3 for the elderly and students; free under age 12 accompanied by an adult). Information: (212) 923-3700.</p>
        <p>CONEY ISLAND, Astroland Amusement Park, 1000 Surf Avenue, Brooklyn. On April 12 reopens weekends, noon to 8 P.M.; starting June 19, open daily, noon to midnight. Rides are from $1.50 to $3; a pay-one-price admission of $11.99 allows unlimited access to the major rides in scheduled sessions. Information: (718) 265-2100.</p>
        <p>DYCKMAN HOUSE, 4881 Broadway, at 204th Street, Inwood, Manhattan. The last 18th-century Dutch colonial farmhouse in Manhattan, with period rooms and antiques. Special programs include a lecture on growing tulip bulbs (April 12 at 2 P.M., free), a historic walking tour of Inwood (May 3 at 1 P.M.; $14) and a concert (May 24 at 2 P.M.; free). Open Tuesday to Sunday, 11 A.M. to noon and 1 to 4 P.M. Suggested admission: $1. Information: (212) 304-9422.</p>
        <p>ELLIS ISLAND IMMIGRATION MUSEUM. Photographs, artifacts and displays document the immigration process from 1892 to 1924. On display through Aug. 10 are paintings by Sherry Avares Sanabria of the island's buildings before restoration. Circle Line ferries to Ellis Island leave Battery Park in lower Manhattan every 45 minutes from 9:30 A.M. to 3:30 P.M.; boats also leave Liberty State Park in Jersey City daily every 75 minutes from 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. En route to Ellis Island all ferries stop at Liberty Island. Round-trip fare: $6 ($5 for the elderly; $3 for ages 3 to 17; free under age 3). Admission to the island and museum is free. Information: (212) 269-5755 or (201) 435-9499.</p>
        <p>EMPIRE STATE BUILDING OBSERVATORY, Fifth Avenue at 34th Street, Manhattan. Views of the metropolitan region from more than 1,000 feet above street level. King Kong is expected to be roaming the observatory April 19 to 26. The observatory is open daily from 9:30 A.M. to 11:30 P.M. Admission: $3.50 ($1.75 for the elderly and ages 5 to 12; free under age 5). Information: (212) 736-3100.</p>
        <p>FEDERAL HALL NATIONAL MEMORIAL, 26 Wall Street, Manhattan. The site of George Washington's inauguration and the drafting of the Bill of Rights. The railing from the first Capitol building, which was at the site of Federal Hall and was demolished in 1812, is on view, along with the suit Washington wore to his inauguration. Special events include: "Walt Whitman and Slavery," a reading and discussion of Whitman's writing, featuring Arnold Rampersad, Galway Kinnell and David Ignatow (April 12 at 4 P.M.), and "90 Seasons in the City," celebrating New York Yankees baseball with memorabilia, uniforms and equipment, photographs and filmed highlights (April 23 through May 15). Free concerts every Wednesday at 12:30 P.M. Monday to Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Free. Information: (212) 264-8701.</p>
        <p>GARIBALDI-MEUCCI MUSEUM, 420 Tompkins Avenue, at Chestnut Avenue, Rosebank, S.I. The museum houses the memorabilia of the Italian patriot Giuseppe Garibaldi and the Italian-American inventor Antonio Meucci, who some believe experimented with the telephone before Alexander Graham Bell received his patent. Lectures at the museum include "Gauguin and Lautrec: Alternative Life Styles and Their Effect on Art" (March 17 at 7:30 P.M.); "Cezanne and Seurat: The New Formalism in Art, Pre-Cubism and Neo-Impressionism" (April 14 at 7:30 P.M.); "Metropolitan Museum of Art Tour: 19th-Century Galleries," which features a trip to the Met and meets at the Staten Island Ferry Terminal (May 16 at 9:30 A.M.). All lectures, $3; the tour to the Met requires separate admission to the museum, which is $4. Open Tuesday to Friday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday from 1 to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Free. Information: (718) 442-1608.</p>
        <p>GENERAL GRANT NATIONAL MEMORIAL, Riverside Drive at 122d Street, Manhattan. The classic domed tomb containing the sarcophagi of the general and and his wife, Julia, overlooks the Hudson River. The site includes exhibits about Grant's career and other material from the Civil War. Open Wednesday to Sunday from 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; open Federal holidays. Free. Information: (212) 666-1640.</p>
        <p>HAMILTON GRANGE NATIONAL MEMORIAL, 287 Convent Avenue, between 141st and 142d Streets, Manhattan. Home of Alexander Hamilton, the first Secretary of the Treasury and co-author of the Federalist Papers. Colonial furnishings and Hamilton's belongings are on view. Open Wednesday to Sunday from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; open Federal holidays. Free. Information: (212) 283-5154.</p>
        <p>HARBOR DEFENSE MUSEUM, Fort Hamilton, Brooklyn. The museum, in a fort built in 1825, has uniforms, weapons and artillery pieces from all American wars. An exhibition of Desert Storm weapons, including rifles, uniforms and a Russian-made anti-aircraft gun captured in Kuwait, will open June 12 and run through December. Open Monday, Thursday and Friday from 1 to 4 P.M.; Saturday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday from 1 to 5 P.M.; closed holidays except Memorial Day, July 4 and Veterans Day. Free. Information: (718) 630-4349.</p>
        <p>HAYDEN PLANETARIUM, American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 81st Street, Manhattan. "Amazing Worlds of Weather," which runs through November, features slides and special effects that simulate tornadoes, blizzards and other extreme weather conditions. Open Monday to Friday at 1:30 and 3:30 P.M.; Saturday at 11 A.M. and hourly from 1 to 5 P.M. and Sunday hourly from 1 to 5 P.M.; admission, $5 ($3.75 for the elderly and students; $2.50 for children 2 to 12 ). "Art of the Cosmos," an exhibition of more than 70 paintings, is on display through June 30. "National Astronomy Day" will be observed on May 2 from 10:30 A.M. to 5:45 P.M. and feature science magic tricks, sun-spot viewing and workshops in making weather instruments. Lectures, all at 7:30 P.M., include "Blueprint for Space: A Public Forum" (March 23); "The Latest Scientific Results From the Hubble Space Telescope" (April 29); "U.S. Astronomers' Wish List for the 1990's" (May 19); "Changes in the Sun's Energy Output and Global Climate Change" (June 2; $8). All other lectures are $6 each. Information: (212) 769-5900 or (212) 769-5920.</p>
        <p>HISPANIC SOCIETY OF AMERICA, Audubon Terrace, Broadway at 155th Street, Manhattan. A museum dedicated to Hispanic culture with fine and decorative arts of the Iberian Peninsula from pre-history to the present.  "Maps, Charts, Globes: Five Centuries of Exploration," an exhibition celebrating the 500th anniversary of Columbus's voyage, includes 120 items (through May 8). Open Tuesday to Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday 1 to 4 P.M.; closed holidays. Free. Information: (212) 926-2234.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. GALLERY OF SCIENCE AND ART, 590 Madison Avenue, at 56th Street, Manhattan. Exhibitions on view include "Sport in Art From American Museums," more than 70 paintings and sculptures relating to sports (through March 28) and "Blueprint for Space: Science Fiction to Science Fact," with books, engravings and film clips illustrating how art and literature have influenced space exploration (through March 28). Coming displays are "Theater in Revolution: Russian Avant-Garde Stage Design 1913-1935," with drawings, costume and set designs, scale models and other artifacts from the collection of the Bakhrushin State Central Theatrical Museum, and "Korean Costumes and Textiles," with more than 200 examples of costumes and wrapping cloths drawn from the late Choson period. Both displays will be on view from April 14 to June 13. Open Tuesday to Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Free. Information: (212) 745-6100 or 745-3500.</p>
        <p>INTREPID SEA-AIR-SPACE MUSEUM, Pier 86, 46th Street at the Hudson River, Manhattan. Converted World War II aircraft carrier featuring the world's fastest plane, the A12 Lockheed Blackbird. Exhibits from the Persian Gulf war include Patriot missiles and Scud missile wreckage. On May 20, a procession of 13 United States naval ships and 7 vessels from European fleets will begin Fifth Fleet Week, with special events running through May 26. Present and future exhibitions include "The Age of Exploration," (May 14 through June 1993); "The Normandie Disaster" (now through May 12); "The Navy of the Future," (opens March 31 for an indefinite period). Open Wednesday through Sunday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Admission: $7 ($6 for the elderly; $4 for ages 6 to 11; free under age 6). Information: (212) 245-0072.</p>
        <p>JEWISH MUSEUM, at the New-York Historical Society, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, Manhattan. Opening on March 22 is "Bridges and Boundaries: African American and American Jews," an exhibition of photographs, documents and artworks (through July 19). Open Sunday, Tuesday and Wednesday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursday, 11 A.M. to 8 P.M. and Friday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M.; closed holidays. Admission: $4.50 ($3 for the elderly and students; $1 under age 12). Information (212) 399-3344 or 399-3430.</p>
        <p>MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY, 457 Madison Avenue, at 50th Street, Manhattan. "Sacrificial Ornament," a display of sculpture by Spring Hurlbut, will be on view May 21 to June 26; "Transmission Towers of the Long Island Expressway," a collection of drawings and anecdotal histories describing the numerous antennas found along the expressway, will be displayed from May 29 to June 26. Open daily, except Thursday and Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Free. Information: (212) 935-3960.</p>
        <p>MUSEUM OF TELEVISION AND RADIO, 25 West 52d Street, Manhattan. A collection of taped historic radio and television broadcasts, as well as exhibitions of other media, including drawings, posters and photographs. Current shows include "Jack Benny: The Radio and Television Work" (through April 5); "Perspectives on the Collection: The Artist at Work," documentaries illustrating radio and television interpretations of artists like Picasso (through today); "Perspectives on the Collection: From Stage and Screen," with radio and television performances by actors like Laurence Olivier, Katharine Hepburn and Helen Hayes (through today); "The Television of Dennis Potter," a retrospective of drama by the British writer (through May 31); "Bob and Ray" a tribute to the radio team that created the Piel Brothers, Mary Backstage, and the McBeebee Twins (April 7 through Sept. 20). Open Tuesday to Sunday, noon to 6 P.M.; until 8 Thursday. Admission: $5 ($4 for students; $3 for the elderly and under age 13). Information: (212) 621-6800.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL MUSEUM OF THE AMERICAN INDIAN, Broadway at 155th Street, Manhattan. One of the world's largest collections of artifacts. Special exhibitions include "Beadwork, Cornhusk Dolls and Cradleboards," (ends today); "Weaving a Mayan Heritage" (March 18 to July 12), and "Indians as Children See Them," an art exhibition (through April 19). There will also be demonstrations in quillwork and featherwork (March 17, 18 and 31; April 1 to 3 and 28 to 30; May 1, 19, 20 and 26 to 29); Andean music (March 19 to 21; April 4 and 18; May 2, 16, 21, 22 and 30), and beadwork, quilt making and rawhide painting (April 7 to 10, May 5 to 9, June 16 to 20). Open Tuesday to Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Admission: $3 ($2 for the elderly and students; free under age 7). Information: (212) 283-2420.</p>
        <p>NELLIE BLY AMUSEMENT PARK, 1824 Shore Parkway, off the Belt Parkway, Bensonhurst, Brooklyn. Open weekends through April 12, noon to 8 P.M. Beginning April 13, Tuesday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to midnight; Monday, Wednesday, Friday, Saturday and Sunday, noon to midnight. Rides are $1 to $1.25. Information: (718) 996-4002.</p>
        <p>NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY, 170 Central Park West, at 77th Street, Manhattan. On view are "While They Fought: The Home Front in New York City," a collection of drawings, posters, photographs and other items to commemorate the 50th anniversary of the United States entry into World War II (through April 5); and "Building City Hall," an exhibition of architectural drawings, watercolors, prints, manuscripts and models relating to the construction of the 1802 building in lower Manhattan (through June 28). "Forever Wild: The Adirondack Experience" will include works by such Hudson River School artists as Jasper Cropsey and Thomas Cole, as well as architectural plans, furniture, boats, and sporting equipment from the area (May 6 to June 12). Open Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursday, 11 A.M. to 8 P.M.; closed Monday, Saturday and holidays. Admission: $4.50 ($3 for students and the elderly; $1 under age 12). Information: (212) 873-3400.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY, Central Research Library, Fifth Avenue and 42d Street, Manhattan. "Dorothea Tanning: Illustrated Books and Prints" will exhibit more than 50 works by the artist (May 9 to July 18) in the Third Floor Gallery; also on view will be "Shelley: Unacknowledged Poet and Legislator," an exhibition of letters, manuscripts, books and personal artifacts commemorating the bicentennial of the poet's birth (April 25 to Aug. 8). Open Tuesday and Wednesday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Thursday to Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; closed Monday. Information: (212) 869-8089.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY FOR THE PERFORMING ARTS, Lincoln Center. Exhibitions include "Fool's Fire" by Julie Taymor, with story boards, scripts, models and puppet figures from the original video production of the same title (through April 25); "Body and Soul: The Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater," with programs, posters, correspondence and set pieces (through May 23); "Judy Garland: A Celebration," with costumes, posters, photographs and sheet music (April 1 to June 13). Open Monday and Thursday, noon to 8 P.M.; Wednesday and Friday, noon to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; closed Sunday and Tuesday. Free. Information: (212) 870-1630.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE, 20 Broad Street, lower Manhattan. Exhibits and a film that explains stock and bond trading and a self-guided tour of the Stock Exchange Visitor's Center. Open Monday to Friday, 9:15 A.M. to 4 P.M.; closed holidays. Free. Tickets are distributed beginning at 9 A.M. Information: (212) 656-5167.</p>
        <p>PIERPONT MORGAN LIBRARY, 29 East 36th Street, Manhattan. Exhibitions include "17th-Century Dutch Drawings," with more than 120 works (through April 26) and "Sketching at Home and Abroad: British Landscape Drawing 1750-1850," featuring watercolors and sketches by such artists as Thomas Girtin, Joshua Cristall and J. M. W. Turner (May 6 to Aug. 2); "Puss in Boots: Three Centuries of the Master Cat," original watercolors by the illustrator Alain Vaes. Open Tuesday to Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Admission: $5 ($3 for the elderly and students). Information: (212) 685-0008.</p>
        <p>QUEENS MUSEUM OF ART, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park. Permanent home of the Panorama of New York City, a large architectural scale model of the five boroughs, covering 9,335 square feet and including more than 865,000 miniature buildings. Completed in 1964, it is touted as the world's largest scale model. Also on view is a multi-media installation by Ik-Joong Kang (through March 29); "Art Beyond Sight," an exhibition of sculpture and paintings sponsored by National Exhibits by Blind Artists (through March 29); a photography display by Sarah Charlesworth (through April 12); "Focus on the Figure: Henrietta Montooth and Willy Lenski," an exhibition of paintings (through April 12), and "Sergei Bugayev: Afrika," a multi-media installation by the Russian artist (April 23 through June 14). A lecture series, "Isms of the Modern Period," by Miriam Brumer of the museum staff, includes "Cubism" (March 18); "Dada and Surrealism" (March 25); "Abstract Expressionism" (April 1); "Hard-Edge, Minimalism, Pop Art, Op Art" (April 15); "Political Art, Conceptualism" (April 29); "Neo-Expressionism and Photo Realism,' (May 13), and "A Hybrid of Isms" (May 27). Lecture information: (718) 592-9700. Open Tuesday to Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M.; closed Monday. Suggested admission: $2 ($1 for students, the elderly and ages 5 to 12; free under age 5). Information: (718) 592-5555.</p>
        <p>QUEENS MUSEUM OF ART AT BULOVA CORPORATE CENTER, 75-20 Astoria Boulevard, Jackson Heights, Queens. "From Metal to Myth," an exhibition of sculpture by Carol Goebel, will be on display from March 23 to May 25. Open Monday to Friday, 7 A.M. to 7 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; closed Sunday. Free. Information: (718) 899-0700.</p>
        <p>RICHMONDTOWN RESTORATION, Staten Island Historical Society, 441 Clarke Avenue, Richmondtown, S.I. "The Threads that Bind: Samplers of Staten Island," more than 20 embroideries from the Staten Island Historical Society's permanent collection, will be on view from May 10 to May 1993; "Civil War Weekend," a re-enactment of an encampment, will be held June 13 and 14, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; admission, $5 a day; at "The Regimental Ball," with Victorian music and dancing, visitors will wear 1860's costumes (June 13, 8 to 11 P.M.; admission, $16). Open Wednesday to Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M.; closed holidays. Admission: $4 ($2.50 for the elderly and ages 6 to 18; free under age 6). Information: (718) 351-1611.</p>
        <p>ROCKEFELLER CENTER, Rockefeller Plaza, from 47th to 52d Street west of Fifth Avenue, Manhattan. Hourlong tours of the NBC Television Studios, Monday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; closed holidays. Tickets: $7.75. Tour information: (212) 664-4000.</p>
        <p>SCHOMBURG CENTER FOR RESEARCH IN BLACK CULTURE, 515 Lenox Avenue, at 135th Street, Manhattan. The center's holdings include audio tapes of W. E. B. Du Bois and Booker T. Washington; the original manuscript of Richard Wright's novel "Native Son," and thousands of other documents, paintings and photographs. On view is "Jazz Arts," an exhibition of paintings and photographs inspired by jazz (through June 30), and "New World Africans," a collection of photographs from the 19th and early 20th centuries (through June 30). Open Monday and Tuesday, noon to 8 P.M.; Wednesday and Friday, noon to 6 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; closed Sunday, Thursday and holidays. Free. Information: (212) 491-2200.</p>
        <p>SOUTH STREET SEAPORT MUSEUM AND MARKETPLACE, 14 Fulton Street, lower Manhattan. The 19th-century port district has an array of restaurants, shops and bars. The centennial of Herman Melville's death is commemorated with a display of artifacts, coins, candy molds, paintings and woodcuts depicting whales through the centuries (through March 22). In the museum's gallery at 213 Water Street is "Hemm'd Thick with Sail Ships," an exhibition focusing on New York Harbor in the 19th century (open indefinitely). "Thor Heyerdahl" will feature a ship visiting from Norway (April 4 to 7, Pier 17 South). "25th Anniversary Exhibit" will include items from the museum's permanent collection, including oil paintings, ship models, watercolors, prints and nautical memorabilia (April 28 to Jan. 3). The "New York Wooden Boat Festival" will have displays and demonstrations of boat building by hand (May 23 to 25). "19th-Century Picnic and Boat Launching," with the launching of the newly restored 1893 fishing schooner Lettie G. Howard, will be followed by an old-fashioned picnic (May 30, launching at noon and picnic from 1 to 3; tickets are $40 and reservations are required; information: 212-669-9416). Museum is open daily from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; beginning May 23, open till 6 P.M.; closed holidays. Admission: $6 ($3 under age 12). Information: (212) 669-9400 for the museum; (212) 732-7678 for the marketplace.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND INSTITUTE OF ARTS AND SCIENCES, 75 Stuyvesant Place, St. George, S.I. Cultural museum and library with artistic, scientific and environmental collections. Exhibitions include "From Cicadas to Chagall: A Century of Collecting" (through April 12); "Animation Art From the Collection of Peter Merolo" (through June 7); "The Fine Art of Dining: Silver and China From the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences Collection" (through July 19); "Tutovoh: Learning the Hopi Way," a collection of contemporary and turn-of-the-century photographs and artifacts, (May 8 to Aug. 23). Open Monday to Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: $2.50 ($1.50 for students and the elderly). Information: (718) 727-1135.</p>
        <p>STATUE OF LIBERTY, on Liberty Island. Visitors can climb stairs to the statue's crown daily from 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M. Circle Line ferries to Liberty Island leave Battery Park in lower Manhattan every 45 minutes from 9:30 A.M. to 3:30 P.M.; ferries also leave from Liberty State Park in Jersey City every 45 minutes from 9:15 A.M. to 3:30 P.M. All ferries returning from Liberty Island stop at Ellis Island. Round-trip fare is $6 ($5 for the elderly; $3 ages 3 to 17; free under age 3). Admission to Liberty Island is free. Information: (212) 269-5755 or (201) 435-9499.</p>
        <p>THEODORE ROOSEVELT BIRTHPLACE, 28 East 20th Street, Manhattan. Exhibitions, artifacts and memorabilia about the only United States President born in New York City. Free concerts Saturdays and most Sundays at 2 P.M. Open Wednesday to Sunday from 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; open holidays. Admission: $1 (elderly and children free). Information: (212) 260-1616.</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS HEADQUARTERS, entrance at First Avenue and 46th Street, Manhattan. Hourlong tours with visits to the Security Council and the General Assembly leave every 15 minutes from 9:15 A.M. to 4:45 P.M. daily. Changing exhibitions sponsored by Unicef and other world organizations are featured in the lobby. Admission: $6.50 ($3.50 for children 5 to 14; $4.50 for high school and college students). Information: (212) 963-4440.</p>
        <p>WINTER GARDEN, World Financial Center, West Street, south of Vesey Street, lower Manhattan. Exhibitions include "Underwater Cities: The World of the Coral Reef," a display from the New York Aquarium and Wildlife Conservation International that will have 11 large tanks of living coral, exotic fish and invertebrates (through March 31 in the Courtyard Gallery); open Monday through Friday, 11 A.M. to 7 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M.; "Brian Eno Tropical Rain Forest Sound Installation," which incorporates bird, animal and natural sounds from the Colombian rain forest (through March 31, daily, 1 to 3 P.M. and 7 to 9 P.M., except March 16 and 18); "Ecological Rescue of Xochimilco," an exhibition of photographs by Jean-Gerard Sidaner, a Mexican-French artist and environmentalist (through March 31 in the North Bridge); "Liz Phillips: "Mer Sonic Illuminations," an interactive sound and neon installation that involves a large fish tank (through March 31, daily, noon to 6 P.M. in the Lecture Room at 225 Liberty Street). Information: (212) 945-0505.</p>
        <p>THE WORLD TRADE CENTER AND OBSERVATION DECK, 2 World Trade Center, between Vesey and Liberty Streets, lower Manhattan. Entrance on the mezzanine level. One of the highest open observation platforms in the world, the observation deck on the 107th floor has views of New York City and New Jersey. Open daily, 9:30 A.M. to 9:30 P.M. Observation deck admission is $3.50 ($1.75 for children and the elderly). Information: (212) 435-7377. Cruises</p>
        <p>PETREL, operated by Bring Sailing Back Inc., Battery Park, lower Manhattan. Built in New York in 1938, the Petrel is a 70-foot yacht, formerly owned by the Coast Guard and a favorite sailboat of President John F. Kennedy. Hourlong or evening sails in New York Harbor and around the Statue of Liberty are available. Season begins April 20 and runs through October. Sails begin at noon Monday to Friday and at 1 P.M. on Saturday and Sunday; fees range from $8 to $20. Information: (212) 825-1976.</p>
        <p>CIRCLE LINE CRUISES, leaving from Pier 83, Hudson River, near 43d Street. Three-hour, 35-mile cruises around Manhattan, passing such landmarks as Ellis Island and the United Nations. Sailings today through March 20, 10:30 A.M. and 2; March 21 to May 1, daily at 10 A.M., 11 A.M., 1:30 P.M. and 2:30 P.M.; on Saturday and Sunday there are additional sails at noon, 3:30 and 7 P.M. From May 2 to June 19, sails are available daily on the half hour from 9:30 A.M. to 3:30 P.M. (except at 12:30) and evening cruises begin at 7 P.M. with additional cruises on Saturday and Sunday at 12:30 P.M. and 4:30 P.M. Tickets are $16 for all cruises ($8 under age 12). Information: (212) 563-3200.</p>
        <p>WORLD YACHT, leaving from Pier 62, 23d Street at the Hudson River, Manhattan. Daily dinner cruises year-round along the West Side of Manhattan from 7 to 10 P.M., boarding at 6 P.M. Sunday to Thursday, $62; Friday and Saturday, $69.50. Lunch cruises from noon to 2 P.M., boarding Monday to Saturday at 11 A.M.; $27.50 ($16 under age 12). Sunday brunch cruises from 12:30 to 2:30 P.M., boarding at 11:30 A.M.; $39.95 ($25 under age 12). Reservations and information: (212) 929-7090. Zoos</p>
        <p>BRONX ZOO, Bronx River Parkway and Fordham Road, Fordham, the Bronx. A vast array of animals in both indoor and outdoor habitats; special areas include Jungle World, Wild Asia, African Plains, featuring lions, giraffes, cheetahs and Arabian oryx. Baboon Reserve, the World of Birds, the Great Apes, and the Children's Zoo. Wild Asia features a monorail ride through more than 35 acres of park; opens May 1; fare: $1.50. Camel rides are $2. Special events include "Polar Bear Weekend," with bear fact trivia, bear talks, Snowball the costumed bear available for photos and a name-the-polar-bear contest (April 25 and 26 11 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.); a "Great Gorilla Gala," featuring traditional African dancers and drummers, craftmaking and storytelling for youngsters (May 16 to 17, 11 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.), and "Zoo Babies Weekend," with appearances by baby animals born in the zoo, videotapes, origami demonstrations and crafts, and an animal scavenger hunt throughout the reopened World of Birds, for children (June 20 and 21). The zoo also offers education courses for adults and children. Information and registration: (212) 220-6854. Zoo hours are 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. daily, (5:30 weekends and holidays). Admission through March 31: $2.50 ($1 for the elderly and ages 2 to 12); April 1 through Oct. 31, $5.75 ($2 for elderly and ages 2 to 12). Parking: $5. Information: (212) 367-1010.</p>
        <p>CENTRAL PARK ZOO, entrance at Fifth Avenue and 64th Street. Two pairs of golden-headed lion tamarins and an endangered species of monkey from Brazil are in residence, along with polar bears, colobus monkeys, gentoo penguins and red pandas. Special events include "Spring Break Celebration," focusing on animal celebrations of spring, including migration and mating (April 18 through 26); "Cool Jazz Beneath the Stars," outdoor concerts (June 1, 8, 15, 22 and 29). Tickets: $8 in advance through Ticketmaster, (212) 307-7171, or the zoo gift shop; $10 at the door. (Adult education courses are also available. Information: 212-439-6538.) Open daily, including holidays, from 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; beginning April 1, open till 5 P.M. weekdays and 5:30 P.M. weekends and holidays. Admission: $2.50 ($1.25 for the elderly; 50 cents for ages 3 to 12; free under age 3). Information: (212) 861-6030.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK AQUARIUM, West Eighth Street and the Boardwalk, Coney Island, Brooklyn. "Coral Reef Initiative," a new exhibition, features 11 large tanks of living coral, exotic fish and invertebrates (May 15 through Dec. 31); special events include "Behind the Scenes Tour," a look at the working world behind the aquarium tanks (March 21, 9:30 to 11:30 A.M.; $18.50); "Fulton Fish Market Tour" (April 9, 6 to 8 A.M.; $9.50); "Above and Beneath the Red Sea," a research report from a collecting trip (April 11, 11 A.M. to 1 P.M.; $13.50); "Breakfast With the Animals," featuring morning meal preparations and feedings (May 17, 9 to 11 A.M.; $18.50); "Morning in the Marsh," with participants collecting plankton, crab and shrimp for microscope viewing (June 6, 9 to 11 A.M.; $14). Special events require reservations: (718) 265-3454. Daily, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., including holidays. Admission: $5.75 ($2 for the elderly and ages 2 to 12; free under age 2). Information: (718) 265-3474.</p>
        <p>STATEN ISLAND ZOOLOGICAL SOCIETY, 614 Broadway, West Brighton. Among the highlights are a serpentarium with turtles and a large collection of North American rattlesnakes. Special events include a "Moonlight Safari," an after-dark tour of the zoo for those 8 and older (May 14, 8:30 to 10 P.M.; $7), and "Arbor Day at the Zoo," with hourlong tours past the varied trees that provide shelter for animals (April 18, 10 A.M., 2 P.M. and 3 P.M.; $3, reservations required). Daily, 10 A.M. to 4:45 P.M. Admission: $3 ($2 for ages 3 to 11; free under age 2). Free Wednesday after 2 P.M. Information: (718) 442-3100. Other Sights</p>
        <p>CATHEDRAL OF ST. JOHN THE DIVINE, 1047 Amsterdam Avenue, at 112th Street, Manhattan. The largest Neo-Gothic cathedral in the world, designed by the architect Ralph Adams Cram. The cathedral has seven chapels and a vaulted ceiling that rises 12 stories. Special events include "Manhattan Choral Festival," a performance by a 400-member youth choir with chamber orchestra (April 5, 3:30 P.M.); a concert by the Orchestra of the Sky (May 10, 4 P.M.), and Benjamin Britten's "War Requiem" by the New York Philharmonic Orchestra, conducted by Kurt Masur (May 25, 8 P.M.) Free, donation requested. Information: (212) 662-2133. General cathedral hours are Monday to Saturday, 7 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Sunday, 7 A.M. to 8 P.M. Tours are given Tuesday to Saturday at 11 A.M. and Sunday at 12:45 P.M.; suggested donation: $2. Tour information: (212) 932-7314. General information: (212) 316-7540.</p>
        <p>RAINBOW AND STARS, 30 Rockefeller Plaza, 65th floor, Manhattan. Helen Schneider will perform through March 28 with shows Tuesday through Saturday at 9 and 11:15 P.M.; $35 cover, no minimum. " 'S Wonderful, 'S Marvelous, 'S Gershwin," a musical revue, will run from March 31 through May 9, with shows Tuesday to Saturday at 9 and 11:15 P.M. There is a $35 cover charge but no minimum. Also at 30 Rockefeller Plaza is THE RAINBOW ROOM, an Art Deco dining room with panoramic views and a revolving dance floor. Dinner and supper shows feature pop and show music by Mauricio Smith and his Latin Ensemble, and the Rainbow Room Orchestra with Steven Davis. Pre-theater shows feature a pianist. Pre-theater dinner: 5:30 to 6:15 P.M.; $38.50. Dinner, 7 to 10 P.M.; supper, 10:30 to midnight; each about $100 a person. Sunday dinner, noon to 3 P.M. and 5 to 9 P.M.; $35. Information and reservations: (212) 632-5000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
