<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: The Media; For the Most Negative Ads, Turn On the Nearest Radio</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="566584"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICAL ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D9153DF933A05753C1A964958260" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: The Media; For the Most Negative Ads, Turn On the Nearest Radio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH KOLBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's the Great Invisible Attack campaign.</p>
        <p>Heading into the final days of the Presidential race, the Bush campaign is running a series of highly critical, carefully aimed radio advertisements aimed at undermining Gov. Bill Clinton's support in crucial states. Over the weekend, when it will be almost impossible for the Clinton campaign to respond, the Bush campaign is planning to put more attack advertisements on the radio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's the Great Invisible Attack campaign.</p>
        <p>Heading into the final days of the Presidential race, the Bush campaign is running a series of highly critical, carefully aimed radio advertisements aimed at undermining Gov. Bill Clinton's support in crucial states. Over the weekend, when it will be almost impossible for the Clinton campaign to respond, the Bush campaign is planning to put more attack advertisements on the radio.</p>
        <p>Far cheaper than television, radio advertising is also widely regarded as less effective. But radio, which receives far less press scrutiny than television, is often the medium that candidates use to deliver their most scathing -- and sometimes misleading -- critiques.</p>
        <p>As the campaign moves toward the close, all three leading candidates -- Mr. Clinton, President Bush and Ross Perot -- are planning heavy advertising blitzes over the weekend on both radio and television.</p>
        <p>On television, both the Clinton and the Bush campaigns are expected to continue broadcasting a mixture of positive and negative messages. But on radio the message is likely to be unremittingly downbeat. 'Hard-Hitting Attacks'</p>
        <p>"Radio is a great medium for delivering hard-hitting attacks," said Darrell West, a professor of political science at Brown University who studies campaign advertising. "It's a risk-free type of advertising. You can be incredibly obnoxious without being blamed for it."</p>
        <p>Many of the television advertisements that have been broadcast during the Presidential campaign have been based on information that could, at best, be called questionable. But it is on the radio that the truth has been treated the most casually.</p>
        <p>Several of the Bush campaign's radio commercials are variations on a single theme -- that Mr. Clinton will impose a tax on energy, a "carbon tax," that would drive up utility bills and cost jobs.</p>
        <p>"He's said he's for change, but look at the change he's really talking about," says an advertisement running in states like Maine, Michigan, Maryland and Illinois. "An independent analysis says that Clinton-Gore radical environmental taxes will drive up our annual utility bills over $350." Great Leap in Logic</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has not proposed a carbon tax, and aides to the Governor call the advertisements grossly misleading. But the Bush campaign says the commercials are justified because Mr. Clinton's running mate, Senator Al Gore, advocates such a tax in his best-selling book, "Earth in the Balance." Also, they note, the Governor himself has said that the nation's carbon dioxide emissions should be reduced, something, Bush aides insist in a leap of logic, that can be achieved only with a carbon tax.</p>
        <p>"Governor Clinton has very specifically said he'll entertain the idea," said Bill Lacy, a senior political adviser to the Bush campaign.</p>
        <p>Acting on the belief that any attack that goes unanswered is taken by voters to be true, the Clinton campaign has tried to reply to each of the Bush campaign's radio commercials within 24 hours. In their responses, the Clinton campaign has tried to inoculate the Governor against future attacks as well by planting doubts about the President's credibility.</p>
        <p>"It's the same old story: George Bush will say anything to get elected," says a Clinton radio commercial that, with minor adjustments, is running in several states. "He said so himself."</p>
        <p>The commercial ends, "So the next time you hear a George Bush ad, ask yourself, isn't it time for a President who will fight for Americans' jobs?'</p>
        <p>The most recent Bush radio advertisement, which is running in New Jersey as well as in several other states, purports to "examine the facts" about Governor Clinton's record on child welfare and on crime.</p>
        <p>"If he can't care for children and keep the public safety in his own state," the commercial asks, "how can he expect a promotion?"</p>
        <p>The Clinton campaign has responded with an advertisement that says: "George Bush is at it again. Because he can't run on his own record, Bush is resorting to negative attacks against Bill Clinton."</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot's radio advertisements do not mention either Mr. Bush or Mr. Clinton by name. Instead they offer the message of a pox on both your houses.</p>
        <p>"Now here's an extreme case that just shows you how goofy things are in Washington," Mr. Perot says in one of his advertisements. "In order to find a Christmas tree, the White House decided it was necessary to send two people all the way to Oregon to look at the tree at taxpayers' expense. They are in the piggy bank that you and I created with our taxpayer money. We need to get 'em out." New Bush Ads Planned</p>
        <p>Yesterday, aides to the President would not say what new radio advertisements were planned for the weekend. But when a reporter asked whether such commercials could be expected, Sig Rogich, who is coordinating the President's media campaign, said simply, "Yup." And because it is so difficult to respond to new advertisements over a weekend, when station offices are closed, the Clinton campaign is especially concerned about any last-minute attacks.</p>
        <p>"Local radio is where the vilification and fear-mongering takes place," one adviser to Mr. Clinton said. The Clinton campaign has prepared several new radio advertisements, which aides to the Governor say they will broadcast, depending on what the Bush campaign has on radio.</p>
        <p>To close its advertising campaign, the Clinton team is planning to air at least two new television commercials before Election Day. One is expected to continue the campaign's attacks on the President's economic record, while the other is supposed to be more positive, featuring either scenes from Clinton campaign bus trips or Mr. Clinton making a direct appeal to voters.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the Clinton campaign began broadcasting a new television advertisement in Michigan and Ohio that describes how Japanese mini-vans that were labeled cars avoided import duties.</p>
        <p>For its part, the Bush campaign has begun broadcasting two new television commercials, one that features spooky black and white landscapes and attacks Mr. Clinton's record in Arkansas and another that touts Mr. Bush's qualifications for the nation's highest office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
