<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why the Nuclear Debate May Be Mostly Hot Air</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="512337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TSONGAS, PAUL E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDB1139F93BA35750C0A964958260" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why the Nuclear Debate May Be Mostly Hot Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul E. Tsongas's support for nuclear power has thrust the issue into the center of the Presidential primary campaign for the first time in many years. But many people who follow the fortunes of the nuclear industry, which has been in sharp decline for a decade despite backing from the White House, say it may not make much difference who the President is.</p>
        <p>"It sure is a manufactured issue," said Irwin Stelzer, an energy expert at the American Enterprise Institute, a Washington research organization. "You tell me who's going to build one? The utilities, the intelligent ones, are not pounding the table for the right to build nuclear plants."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul E. Tsongas's support for nuclear power has thrust the issue into the center of the Presidential primary campaign for the first time in many years. But many people who follow the fortunes of the nuclear industry, which has been in sharp decline for a decade despite backing from the White House, say it may not make much difference who the President is.</p>
        <p>"It sure is a manufactured issue," said Irwin Stelzer, an energy expert at the American Enterprise Institute, a Washington research organization. "You tell me who's going to build one? The utilities, the intelligent ones, are not pounding the table for the right to build nuclear plants."</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsongas has been describing nuclear power as painful but in the long run essential. His campaign manifesto, "An Economic Call to Arms," describes a world with dwindling fuel resources and rising pollution. "Accepting this was excruciating," he wrote. "Politically, it was all downside."</p>
        <p>His Democratic opponents are trying to prove him right on that last remark. Bill Clinton attacked at a debate in Denver on Feb. 29, saying that Mr. Tsongas wanted to build "hundreds more" reactors. At present, 110 are operating. Mr. Tsongas replied, "That is a lie, that is a lie, that is a lie."</p>
        <p>Though part of Mr. Tsongas's strategy has been to cultivate an image as the candidate who dares to take unpopular but necessary positions, the Tsongas campaign recently issued a one-page statement, "Setting the Record Straight," which states: "He only favors research into whether smaller, safer, better-sited nuclear plants can be developed, if they are someday needed. And he hopes they are not." According to the statement, Mr. Tsongas believes the choice may come to coal and nuclear "and he is very concerned about the effect that massive reliance on coal would have on air quality and global warming."</p>
        <p>A spokesman, Brad MacKenzie, said, "The sound bite is, 'Pick your poison.' "  Ganging Up on Tsongas</p>
        <p>A Republican campaign official said that he doubted nuclear power would be much of an issue in the general election campaign "unless there's some sort of Chernobyl." But in the Democratic race, he said, "more by fluke and happenstance than anything else, it's the one issue all four of them can gang up on Tsongas on."</p>
        <p>Jerry Brown campaigned in Maine stressing his anti-nuclear record as governor of California, and Bob Kerrey also attacked Mr. Tsongas' position. Tom Harkin ran ads before the New Hampshire primary using the Seabrook plant as a backdrop and attacking Mr. Tsongas for supporting nuclear power. "There is no such thing as a pro-nuclear environmentalist," he said in the ads.</p>
        <p>Nuclear power has angered millions of electricity customers because of its cost and made others uneasy over its safety. It has also won the backing of thousands of construction workers and scores of prominent engineers and scientists. But it is seldom more than mentioned in Presidential campaigns.</p>
        <p>In 1980, for example, the year after the Three Mile Island accident, Jimmy Carter, a former nuclear submarine officer who as President took several steps considered hostile to the industry, was opposed by Ronald Reagan, a former spokesman for a reactor maker, General Electric, and a supporter of the technology. But the topic barely surfaced.</p>
        <p>In the 1988 New Hampshire primary, the Seabrook reactor was a factor because Michael S. Dukakis, then governor of neighboring Massachusetts, was trying to prevent its opening. But the issue did not divide the Democrats. In fact, in the New York primary a few weeks later, all the Democratic candidates favored closing the Shoreham nuclear plant on Long Island.</p>
        <p>President Bush favored opening Seabrook and Shoreham, and John H. Sununu, his New Hampshire campaign manager and later White House chief of staff, was a force behind Seabrook's opening. But the question never became an important issue in the general election campaign.</p>
        <p>This year nuclear power is on Congress's agenda. The Senate voted last month to approve a simplified licensing system for new reactors, as part of President Bush's National Energy Strategy. The House bill has no such provision at the moment, however, so the issue may be a major point of contention in a major legislative package.</p>
        <p>Utilities do not seem to think that the fate of the industry will depend much on who is in the White House. John E. Lobbia, the chief executive of Detroit Edison, said, "None of these guys has said that as a matter of national policy, we're going to go nuclear." Executives in the nuclear industry say the talk on the campaign trail is mostly for show. "Whatever the President says one way or the other doesn't seem to make a lot of difference," said James K. Asselstine, a utility analyst with Lehman Brothers and a former commissioner at the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. Whether new plants are built, he said, depends "much more on the regulatory process and a whole series of issues that go to economics."</p>
        <p>At the U.S. Council for Energy Awareness, the nuclear industry's public relations arm, Carl Goldstein, a spokesman, agreed. "Substantively, we're at the whim of a lot of things other than who's in the White House." All the President, does, he said, is "set the tone."</p>
        <p>"It'll fade once the primaries are over," he said. While other Democrats may attack Mr. Tsongas, he continued, "I don't think it has any resonance among the voters."  THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
