<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pollution Blights Investment, Too, in East Europe</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="528271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVATIZATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT (IBRD)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ORGANIZATION FOR ECONOMIC COOPERATION AND DEVELOPMENT (OECD)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN BANK FOR RECONSTRUCTION AND DEVELOPMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D7103FF930A25756C0A964958260" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pollution Blights Investment, Too, in East Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>BUDAPEST</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Decades of unbridled pollution under Communist Governments are beginning to haunt their successors as more and more foreigners find that contamination of the environment is a deterrent to investment in Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>In some regions pollution has rendered water and soil unusable by Western standards. Elsewhere, government officials say they have had to reduce the asking prices for businesses they wish to sell to allow for the cost of cleaning up. And bankers, business executives and other experts say a major obstacle to investment is the absence of any firm rules defining responsibilities for past ecological damage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Decades of unbridled pollution under Communist Governments are beginning to haunt their successors as more and more foreigners find that contamination of the environment is a deterrent to investment in Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>In some regions pollution has rendered water and soil unusable by Western standards. Elsewhere, government officials say they have had to reduce the asking prices for businesses they wish to sell to allow for the cost of cleaning up. And bankers, business executives and other experts say a major obstacle to investment is the absence of any firm rules defining responsibilities for past ecological damage.</p>
        <p>"People have been put off," said Jaap Kool, general manager of NMB Postbank of Vienna, which is active in Eastern Europe. "If they find the land is dirty, they often stop pursuing a project, even just to buy offices or real estate."</p>
        <p>Printing plants, breweries and automobile and chemical plants are being scrutinized by liability-conscious Westerners worried about having to pay for Communism's dirty legacy.</p>
        <p>"Everyone is extremely sensitive about this subject," said the area manager of a giant chemical corporation that is shopping for investment opportunities. "The first question anyone asks is not, 'Show me your balance sheet,' but, 'Show me your environmental audit.' "</p>
        <p>Although Eastern European governments are now engaged in the most ambitious privatization drive ever, until recently they paid scant attention to the environmental variable. "Ministers in charge of privatization weren't even talking to environment ministers," said a United States Government lawyer who has researched the issue here.</p>
        <p>But now the concerns of potential investors are bringing the issue to the attention not only of Eastern European governments but also of the World Bank, the new European Bank for Development and Reconstruction and the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development.</p>
        <p>The three organizations are sponsoring a major conference in Warsaw on May 19 to discuss the relationship between privatization and environmental liability.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the vast scale of the environmental disaster bequeathed by Communism is still being uncovered: Highly toxic chemicals were routinely dumped into the soil, air and water, and many such emissions continue today. No government has yet drawn up a complete inventory of these chemical ills. Foul Water Threatens Machines</p>
        <p>Easier to measure is the air, which is often heavily laced with carbon dioxide and sulfur from low-quality fuel. Poland, for example, emits almost 35 percent as much sulfur dioxide as the 12-nation European Community.</p>
        <p>Groundwater used for drinking in many areas is also contaminated, while rivers are sometimes so foul that Westerners say the water poses a risk to industrial machinery.</p>
        <p>"We come across badly stored chemicals, asbestos, dumps in backyards, leaking underground storage tanks," said a Dutch consultant in soil quality, adding that cleanup problems are often so severe that many investors prefer to start afresh on new land rather than take over a polluted site.</p>
        <p>Eager to keep up the momentum of privatization, governments are offering environmental discounts ad hoc. "In principle, the price of the cleanup is deducted from the purchase price," said Petr Horacek, a policy director at the Environment Ministry of the Czech republic. Similar rules apply in Poland.  Activity in Hungary</p>
        <p>In Hungary, which has received almost half of the new investments made in the East, an Indian company recently dropped plans to buy a textile plant, in part because of chemical pollution. When a Dutch insurance company, Aegon, bought a Hungarian state insurance company two months ago, the deal nearly fell through because of fear of environmental claims.</p>
        <p>Even in the former East Germany, where new rules have been developed, the environment is an obstacle to investment. So far, the Government's privatization agency has been unable to sell a single state company in the Bitterfeld region, a polluted area of eastern Germany where brown coal and chemical industries have covered land and water with hazardous wastes.</p>
        <p>Agfa, the German film manufacturer, turned down the chance to recover its old plant near Bitterfeld, which was confiscated under Communism. "Agfa has said the place is too dirty," a Government official said. Damage Limits Set</p>
        <p>In other parts of eastern Germany, though, polluting companies are among the 6,000 or so already sold. Brigitta Kauers, a spokeswoman for the privatization agency, said that in these cases, buyers assume liability for environmental damage up to a fixed amount, which is deducted from the purchase price. If damage exceeds that sum, the agency assumes the extra cost.</p>
        <p>Experts said pollution is only one of several factors making privatization much slower than expected. They cite uncertain ownership of property, poor communications, bureaucratic red tape and unclear rules about repatriation of profits. Further, some products that once had captive markets in the East have lost their markets or are not competitive in the West.</p>
        <p>Yet pollution represents a less predictable risk, particularly since business executives have been unable to obtain insurance to protect them against liability for past pollution. Political-risk insurance for the East bloc is expensive, but environmental insurance is impossible.</p>
        <p>"Major insurance companies won't touch environmental risks," said Elizabeth Smith, a London banker. "They won't even come up with rules."</p>
        <p>Westerners also worry about uncertain future liability for health problems among workers. Studies show that in some industrial regions of Eastern Europe, life expectancy is three to six years below the national average, which is already five years lower than in Western Europe. Deals Made Nevertheless</p>
        <p>Despite the uncertainties, tenacious entrepreneurs have been striking deals. Ruth Greenspan Bell, an adviser to Poland from the United States Environmental Protection Agency, said Unilever had bought one company at a sizable discount in exchange for assuming cleanup costs, while Phillips Lighting, an affiliate of the Dutch giant, obtained a larger number of shares in another company in compensation for pollution problems.</p>
        <p>"In the most interesting deal," she said, "the Government and the investor set up a separate escrow account to fund the cleanup. If after five years it has not been used, the money reverts to the Government. This provides an incentive to clean up fast."</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Smith, who is in charge of environmental audits at the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development, said at the bank's first annual meeting in Budapest in April that it was difficult to estimate how many privatizations had been postponed or lost because of pollution. Absence of Rules Cited</p>
        <p>Analysts, bankers and business executives at the Budapest meeting said one important problem was the absence of rules to protect investors from retroactive laws that could one day bring higher health or cleanup bills than envisioned today.</p>
        <p>In Poland, Czechoslovakia and Bulgaria, parliaments have begun debating different formulas for coping with environmental degradation, with foreign experts helping to draft new laws and norms that match standards in the European Community.</p>
        <p>In Copsa Mica, Romania, the Government has recently closed a coal-processing and rubber plant because its air and soil pollution posed severe health hazards.</p>
        <p>"People are slowly beginning to understand that norms and liabilities for pollution are a crucial part of privatization and making deals," said Delcho Vichev, a program manager at the Environmental Center for Central and Eastern Europe, in Budapest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
