<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ecology and Self-Esteem At Fresh Air Fund Course</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="534253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAMPS AND CAMPING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FRESH AIR FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNET, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D81F3DF934A35755C0A964958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ecology and Self-Esteem At Fresh Air Fund Course</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BENNET, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dumar Wade faced a daunting task. On a recent sunny Saturday morning, he set out to teach 37 children, aged 11 to 15, something about everything from classified advertisements to the ozone layer. The leaves beyond the open windows whispered temptingly in the summer breeze and the children contemplated an afternoon sail on the Hudson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wade was sweating, just a little. But he managed to get the children's attention by trying to poison one of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dumar Wade faced a daunting task. On a recent sunny Saturday morning, he set out to teach 37 children, aged 11 to 15, something about everything from classified advertisements to the ozone layer. The leaves beyond the open windows whispered temptingly in the summer breeze and the children contemplated an afternoon sail on the Hudson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wade was sweating, just a little. But he managed to get the children's attention by trying to poison one of them.</p>
        <p>The children were among 100 students from New York City participating in the Fresh Air Fund's Career Awareness Program. The program, which began in 1989, assigns the students to follow professionals during a day at the office and buses them up to the Fresh Air Camp in Fishkill, N.Y., on weekends in the spring and fall and for three weeks during the summer. There, guest speakers introduce them to various careers, and the students take classes in drama, in resisting peer pressure and in other skills. Orange Peels and Detergent</p>
        <p>The children also go to Fishkill for sailing trips on the Hudson, stories around campfires and impromptu rap concerts with the counselors.</p>
        <p>The fund will break ground this summer for a permanent Career Awareness Camp in Fishkill. For now, the program relies on a cluster of wood-shingled, barn-like buildings. And it was in one these that Mr. Wade, who is director of Positive Education Achievement through a Correct Environment, a group based in Brooklyn, was hatching his plot, mixing orange peels and detergent into a cupful of water.</p>
        <p>"Do you all care about Antoine?" he asked the group, while Antoine Carr, a seventh-grader from Far Rockaway, Queens, waited out of earshot beyond the door.</p>
        <p>"No!" they answered, chortling.</p>
        <p>But when Antoine, blindfolded with a white towel, stumbled back into the room, and Mr. Wade held out the cup, some children cried out and one batted Mr. Wade's hand away.</p>
        <p>And suddenly Mr. Wade started talking about vacant lots, and how the lots could not see or defend themselves as people filled them with garbage. And the vacant lots led to the importance of trees, which led (somewhat dizzyingly) to the importance of self-esteem, which led to the skills needed to land a job.</p>
        <p>Waving his hands and barking orders like a drill sergeant, Mr. Wade ordered five students, on pain of doing push-ups, to translate at least six of 10 samples of classified-advertisement code (Acctg, Adv, Agcy) he had listed on a piece of poster paper.</p>
        <p>And he dragged Kamal Williams, a 13-year-old from Red Hook, Brooklyn, in a Pittsburgh Pirates baseball cap and intricate braces, in front of the group for a mock interview for an unspecified job. After a few tentative answers, Kamal warmed to the assignment, as Mr. Wade fought unsuccessfully to suppress a grin.</p>
        <p>"Could you tell me some of your strengths and weaknesses?" asked Mr. Wade, looking up from an imaginary resume and trying to glare.</p>
        <p>"I don't have any weaknesses," replied Kamal, poker-faced. "As far as strengths, I've done some baby-sitting."</p>
        <p>By the end of the 75-minute session, some children were talking like a cross between John Denver and Horatio Alger -- about how much they loved trees and sitting up straight during job interviews. The rest seemed to be talking mostly about lunch and that afternoon's boat ride.</p>
        <p>For his part, Kamal, who dreams of being an orthodontist, was glorying in his interview performance. "I was nervous," he confided. But, he added with a smile, "He said I would have got the job."</p>
        <p>Those who wish more information about the Career Awareness Program should call the Fund at (212) 221-0900.</p>
        <p>Tax-deductible contributions may be sent to the Fresh Air Fund, 1040 Avenue of the Americas, New York, N.Y. 10018. Information: (212) 221-0900 or (800) 367-0003.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
