<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Unveils Cleanest-Running Cars for California</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="521653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORD MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REINHOLD, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB1031F936A25757C0A964958260" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Unveils Cleanest-Running Cars for California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT REINHOLD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REINHOLD, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>EL MONTE, Calif., April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California state smog officials and the Ford Motor Company unveiled two new automobile models today that they said were the cleanest-running cars ever approved for mass production in the world.</p>
        <p>They were updated versions of the Ford Escort and the Mercury Tracer, engineered to meet pollutant emission standards California has set for 1997 models, four years ahead of schedule. The new cars are to go on sale at Ford dealers in California starting May 21, when the 1993 models are introduced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California state smog officials and the Ford Motor Company unveiled two new automobile models today that they said were the cleanest-running cars ever approved for mass production in the world.</p>
        <p>They were updated versions of the Ford Escort and the Mercury Tracer, engineered to meet pollutant emission standards California has set for 1997 models, four years ahead of schedule. The new cars are to go on sale at Ford dealers in California starting May 21, when the 1993 models are introduced.</p>
        <p>Leaders of the state's powerful Air Resources Board said the introduction of the cars vindicated their controversial act of September 1990, when they adopted a demanding timetable for manufacturers to begin introducing ultra-clean vehicles if they wanted to continue selling in the huge California automobile market.</p>
        <p>The cars will sell for the same price as regular models sold in other states, though the cost to Ford will be $100 more for each vehicle. They will get one mile per gallon less in fuel efficiency and produce about half the noxious emissions permitted under current California standards, which are the strictest in the nation. Stretching Current Technology</p>
        <p>The Ford vehicles are the first certified by the state under that plan, which was an attempt to force new smog-control technologies by establishing a four-step timetable for introduction of progressively cleaner-running cars from 1997 until 2003, leading ultimately to mass produced zero-emission electric cars.</p>
        <p>The models will not immediately be available outside California, which has the worst smog problems in the country. Three Northeastern states, New York, Connecticut and Massachusetts, have adopted the California emission standards, but on a slower timetable. Six other Northeastern states, including New Jersey, as well as Maryland, Virginia and the District of Columbia, are considering adopting it.</p>
        <p>"Today's car shows that these goals are definitely within reach," said Jananne Sharpless, chairwoman of the Air Resources Board.</p>
        <p>Tests showed the new Ford cars emitted smog-producing hydrocarbons, carbon monoxide and nitrogen oxides at half or less of the current California standards for the 1993 model year, which are already the strictest in the nation.</p>
        <p>Based on past sales, Ford expects to sell about 30,000 of the Escorts, whose base price is $8,802, and 4,000 of the Tracers, whose base price is $10,530. That would represent 3.4 percent of the million-plus passenger vehicles sold each year in California.</p>
        <p>Today's announcement involved no major advance in pollution technology. Rather, according to Donald R. Buist, director of Ford's automotive emissions and fuel economy office, the company stretched existing catalytic converter technology to new limits as an interim measure while it develops alternative fuel, electric and other new propulsion systems.</p>
        <p>The other major American and foreign auto makers are all developing new vehicles to meet the California rules, which will require 25 percent of all cars sold by each maker to conform to the new ultra-clean emission levels starting in 1997.</p>
        <p>By the year 2003, 100 percent of vehicles would have to meet the levels, and 10 percent must have zero emissions.</p>
        <p>Ford spokesmen said they did not plan to sell the new models in other states because the air is not as dirty elsewhere and they did not want to saddle buyers with the additional cost.</p>
        <p>The Ford cars use conventional unleaded gasoline in a 1.9-liter internal combustion engine. The additional pollution controls were obtained mainly by enlarging the catalytic converter and moving it closer to the engine. The converter is filled with semi-precious metals that serve as catalysts to convert unburned hydrocarbons into water, carbon monoxide into carbon dioxide and nitrogen oxides into nitrogen and oxygen. Ford said it had used more of these metals than normal to raise the efficiency of the converter. Increase in Efficiency</p>
        <p>In addition, the company said the engine was designed to use fuel more efficiently and the converter was altered to reach optimum temperature more quickly. About 95 percent of all noxious automobile emissions are created during the first few minutes after starting the car before the engine and converter are operating fully.</p>
        <p>Current California standards limit emissions to .25 grams per mile of hydrocarbons, .4 grams for nitrogen oxide and 3.4 grams for carbon monoxide. In tests, the new Ford cars performed at .062 grams of hydrocarbons, .2 grams of nitrogen oxide and 1.3 grams of carbon monoxide. This met the 1997 standard of .075 grams, .2 grams and 1.7 grams, respectively. In addition, the cars are the first to meet California's strict new durability rules, which require that anti-smog systems continue to meet emission standards for 100,000 miles of driving, double the previous rule.</p>
        <p>Under the plan approved by the Air Resources Board in 1990, low-emission vehicles, or LEV's, must be gradually introduced beginning in 1997, increasing to 96 percent of all cars sold by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>The board also expects a new generation of clean-running cars, called ULEV's, or ultra low-emission vehicles, to start to be introduced in 1997 in small numbers. The plan specifies that 2 percent of all new cars should be ULEV's in 1997, rising to 15 percent in 2003. The final stage will begin with the introduction of ZEV's, or zero-emission vehicles, meaning electric cars. Makers must start to introduce them in 1998 and raise the proportion to 10 percent by 2003.</p>
        <p>Except for electric cars, the board has not specified the type of technology to be used.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers can use any combination of new emission controls, engine designs and fuel types to attain the required emission levels.</p>
        <p>When the plan was imposed in 1990, many automobile experts said it was based on unrealistic expectations about new technology. Today air board staff members said, if anything, the standards may have been too lenient inasmuch as Ford met the initial requirements four years early.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
