<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Norway's Border, Russian Arctic in Crisis</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="527274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COMMONWEALTH OF INDEPENDENT STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORWAY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SWEDEN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FINLAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA (RUSSIAN REPUBLIC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DA173AF933A25756C0A964958260" item-length="1448" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Norway's Border, Russian Arctic in Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>KIRKENES, Norway</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since the end of the cold war, the military might of the former Soviet empire has actually grown modestly in size just across from this Arctic border outpost. The heavily armored divisions protecting the old Soviet northern flank have not withdrawn as they have in Central Europe.</p>
        <p>But in all other ways, the cold war seems as dead here as anywhere and security in the Nordic countries facing the old empire to the east is being defined increasingly in nonmilitary terms, like environmental security, economic and social stability in Russia and the improvement of Arctic trade. And if anything, these new security challenges are no less daunting than the old and familiar ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since the end of the cold war, the military might of the former Soviet empire has actually grown modestly in size just across from this Arctic border outpost. The heavily armored divisions protecting the old Soviet northern flank have not withdrawn as they have in Central Europe.</p>
        <p>But in all other ways, the cold war seems as dead here as anywhere and security in the Nordic countries facing the old empire to the east is being defined increasingly in nonmilitary terms, like environmental security, economic and social stability in Russia and the improvement of Arctic trade. And if anything, these new security challenges are no less daunting than the old and familiar ones.</p>
        <p>A half-hour's drive from here into Russia, a traveler comes upon one of the symbols of the new definition of security: the hellish sight of a towering, three-stack nickel smelter, one of the largest in the world, which belches out more sulphur dioxide than all sources combined in Norway. The sulphuric acid rain that descends from the factory's triple plumes has turned thousands of acres of Norwegian and Russian woods into wasteland.</p>
        <p>Other factors are also making Norwegian politicians look nervously across the border. For example, Russian politicians visiting Oslo have told Norwegian cabinet ministers that Russian officers cannot feed their wives and children. These politicians have asked Norway's military unions to lend humanitarian aid in hopes this will quell the resentment that is building against Moscow's economic reforms.</p>
        <p>On the environmental front, Norway, Finland and Sweden are in the process of deciding whether the environmental security of the region demands that they help finance part of the cleanup necessary to prevent the nickel plant from doing more damage.</p>
        <p>Farther east are two more sites of constant concern in Norway: two former Soviet nuclear power reactors that have been producing steam for electricity for more than 20 years. Norway's Government is constantly concerned about their safety, and not only because reindeer meat in certain Norwegian mountain ranges is still off limits because of radioactivity from the Chernobyl cloud that passed over Norway in 1986.</p>
        <p>Shutting down these plants would cut power to the 1.2 million military men and civilians in northwest Russia who cannot survive the winters there without a stable power supply. This situation raises not only purely humanitarian concerns but also fears of a wave of immigration to Norway.</p>
        <p>Last month Russian officials acknowledged that the former Soviet navy and ice-breaking fleet dumped much of its radioactive waste in shallow Arctic seas that are part of the region's bountiful fishing grounds. A team of scientists will spend this summer trying to assess the damage. Threats to Norway</p>
        <p>Beyond threats to the environment, Norwegian officials assert the major economic and social dislocations that loom across the border pose threats to stability that are equally significant.</p>
        <p>In a month, one of the largest components of the former Soviet military will begin the largest reduction in forces in three decades and almost no one is willing to predict the social and economic consequences for northwest Russia.</p>
        <p>Norway's Foreign Minister, Thorvald Stoltenberg, convened a meeting last month in Tromso of Russian and Norwegian municipal officials in the region to promote a local common market and to build bridges across four decades of suspicion and military orientation.</p>
        <p>"If the day comes when hundreds of thousands of Russian refugees come across our border, it will not be a problem of Norway," he warned, "but a crisis for Europe and the rest of the world."</p>
        <p>Ivan I. Menshikov, who is President Boris N. Yeltsin's personal political representative in Murmansk, a three hour drive from here, is predicting that tens of thousands of Russian officers involuntarily discharged from the military will hit the local economy beginning June 1 without jobs, apartments or adequate pensions and the situation will get, as he said, "ugly."</p>
        <p>How this could affect Norway remains mostly a matter of dark speculation.</p>
        <p>"We do not know the socioeconomic situation of the Russian military in the north, and we have three concerns," Defense Minister Johan Joergan Holst said in an interview in Oslo. "The first is pure humanitarian. We don't want women and children going hungry. The second is, we don't want a restive Russian military, and third, we want to build a long-term relationship with the Russian military in a way that will help keep the military out of politics."</p>
        <p>To add to Russia's difficulties, Mr. Menshikov, a former colonel in the Soviet Army, said that the military leadership that has long dominated the northern region was undermining Mr. Yeltsin's reform process. In Oslo one day not long ago, the Russian member of Parliament who represents the northern military region, Leonid B. Gurevich, said he feared instability in the officer ranks this summer. "Some of them have told me directly, 'We spit on your reforms,' " he said.</p>
        <p>The prospect that the military force reductions in Russia could bring political chaos on Norway's northern border has touched off a debate in Oslo over the Russian politicians' request for aid from this NATO country's military unions for Russian military families.  Undecided on Aid</p>
        <p>So far, Norway's top military officer, Adm. Torolf Rein, has replied that Moscow should stop flying its war planes and testing its ballistic missiles if it needs more money for food.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland remains undecided about the aid proposal because, she said in an interview, she is uncertain of its impact on Russia's military establishment and whether it would help or hurt the forces of democracy.</p>
        <p>People here understand that the cold war is over but many among the four million Norwegians remember the destruction wrought by Germany when it overran Norway in World War II.</p>
        <p>"We are afraid," said Ragnar Toender, harbormaster in Bodo, a city that was leveled by German bombing and from which U-2 spy planes were flown against the Soviet Union in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>"We are afraid that something will happen, like Russia going to war with Ukraine and then NATO will have to go to war," he said, "The Russians have atomic bombs and rockets and they have old atomic power stations, and we are afraid of them because we still cannot eat reindeer meat from the mountains that were contaminated by Chernobyl."</p>
        <p>Sixty percent of Russia's submarine-based strategic nuclear forces are based on the Kola Peninsula. In 1990, more bombers came from Hungary to the northern bases with the collapse of the Warsaw Pact. The first Soviet aircraft carrier steamed out of the Black Sea and joined the northern fleet last winter.</p>
        <p>But even with a modest buildup, there are overwhelming signs of contraction.</p>
        <p>On the streets of Murmansk, Russian officers are ambivalent about reform but proud of their military legacy. The plan to shrink the former northern fleet by 40 percent over the next three years comes none too soon for those already clamoring to get out.</p>
        <p>The new commander of the northern fleet, Vice Adm. Oleg Yerofeyev, told the local press that in reducing the fleet by a third, he will deactivate 25 to 30 warships. But his biggest problem will be the transition in personnel. Some Can't Leave</p>
        <p>Many officers in the northern fleet are frustrated that their service has not delivered them a future. "I personally cannot leave the armed forces because I have no place to live," said Senior Lieut. Vasily Belov, 26, rushing down the street last week in a gray trenchcoat and white scarf. "If I had a place to live, I would leave. I would like to have a second child but I can't afford one now."</p>
        <p>Building a new economy in northwest Russia is perhaps the most daunting of the challenges facing the civil authorities in Murmansk and in Moscow. The road between northern Norway and Murmansk is carrying 10 times the traffic it did a year ago. Trading companies are bringing in Western goods and taking Russian fish, timber and ore in payment.</p>
        <p>But the Russian Arctic zone is a creature of the Soviet state, and it will take more than barter trade to transform it. The largest enterprises have been the Soviet military, fishing industry, mining and timber industries and shipping. Fishing, mining and timber will continue to prosper and reap hard currency for the region and for Moscow. But other industries seem doomed.</p>
        <p>The big submarine construction yard at Severodvinsk has just begun to study conversion, but no one in Norway believes that any private enterprise could support the work force of 120,000 that used to be there.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
