<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Paris Works</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="543989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PARIS (FRANCE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Paris</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD7153EF93AA25754C0A964958260" item-length="5062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Paris Works</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Steven Greenhouse;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a hidden, walled-off area, just west of the Boulevard St.-Michel, Paul Rissel looks like a figure borrowed from the 19th century as he opens the door to the lush greenhouse. Wearing a rough brown tweed sport coat and a long camel-colored scarf, he pushes past some ficus and stops next to a dozen unobtrusive black trays. These trays, he points out, are one of the secrets behind the ageless beauty of Paris's ornate Jardin du Luxembourg, which was built for Queen Marie de Medicis some 370 years ago. Rissel, one of the two chief gardeners, explains that the trays produce seedlings for the tens of thousands of geraniums, dahlias and petunias that the Jardin's 80 gardeners meticulously replant each May around the majestic central fountain.</p>
        <p>The resplendent array of flowers gives the garden the idyllic air of a Renoir painting. During the gentle rains of spring, lovers stroll hand in hand, and when the sun breaks through, 5-year-olds scamper around the fountain to chase after their toy sailboats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a hidden, walled-off area, just west of the Boulevard St.-Michel, Paul Rissel looks like a figure borrowed from the 19th century as he opens the door to the lush greenhouse. Wearing a rough brown tweed sport coat and a long camel-colored scarf, he pushes past some ficus and stops next to a dozen unobtrusive black trays. These trays, he points out, are one of the secrets behind the ageless beauty of Paris's ornate Jardin du Luxembourg, which was built for Queen Marie de Medicis some 370 years ago. Rissel, one of the two chief gardeners, explains that the trays produce seedlings for the tens of thousands of geraniums, dahlias and petunias that the Jardin's 80 gardeners meticulously replant each May around the majestic central fountain.</p>
        <p>The resplendent array of flowers gives the garden the idyllic air of a Renoir painting. During the gentle rains of spring, lovers stroll hand in hand, and when the sun breaks through, 5-year-olds scamper around the fountain to chase after their toy sailboats.</p>
        <p>"People just love this garden," says Rissel, with a pride nurtured by 38 years of working at the Jardin. "In most big cities, the natives lack contact with nature, and that's what we're trying to give them."</p>
        <p>A soft-spoken man with soft hands and long gray sideburns, Rissel heads a small army of gardeners. Each year they plant or transplant 350,000 flowers, and each spring they cart out 150 palm and orange trees, some of them 200 years old, that were lovingly sheltered from the winter cold.</p>
        <p>At a time when cities from Lagos to Los Angeles are afflicted by homelessness, crime and budget traumas, Paris's famed garden is an oasis from urban turmoil. Mayors around the world may be screaming for cash, but the Jardin du Luxembourg is awash in money. It boasts more than one gardener per acre, which allows for an attention to detail and beauty that is rare in modern cities. One gardener devoted two full months to scooping out the rot from the trunk of a beech tree that the gardeners were eager to save because it stood eloquently alongside a small Bartholdi Statue of Liberty. "We function like the gardeners of an old house of the bourgeoisie," Rissel says. "We do much more by hand."</p>
        <p>Rissel and the garden he nurses are just one gilded strand in the tapestry of cobbled streets, quaint quays and medieval churches that make Paris one of the world's most beautiful, best-run cities. Although many cities appear to be breaking down from poverty and decaying infrastructure, Paris seems to be improving with age.</p>
        <p>FOR MANY OF THE CITY'S 2.2 million residents and many of the 20 million tourists who visit each year, Paris remains a magical, even transcendent, place. While many Americans shun their own cities as if they were places suffering from the plague, Paris is a city with which countless people still have a passionate love affair.</p>
        <p>The people who run Paris know that if their city relied on just the charms of its past, it would lose its magic. Thus, they have sought to superimpose a smoothly running, modern metropolis on the city bequeathed them by medieval kings and 18th-century revolutionaries. And they have succeeded royally.</p>
        <p>Garbage is picked up seven days a week, mail is delivered three times a day and all of Paris's 800 miles of streets are swept by hand each day. At rush hour, the subways come once every 80 seconds, and many Metro stops are decorated with mosaics and murals. Affluent families are rushing not to flee for the suburbs, but to buy apartments in Paris's choicest neighborhoods and to send their children to public schools.</p>
        <p>There is no single explanation for why Paris works so well. Rather, Paris has become a shining model for urban planners thanks to numerous ingredients lacking in many other cities: ample financing, sound administration, farsighted planning, technological ingenuity, a flair for design and an ambition to always improve.</p>
        <p>It would be wrong to single out Paris from other French cities as a success story, because Toulouse, Lyons, Nice, Bordeaux and Strasbourg have worked just as hard to keep their beauty, build a vibrant cultural life and remain attractive for families. Nonetheless, Paris, whose metropolitan area includes 10.5 million people (one-fifth of France's population), is undeniably the Olympus of French cities.</p>
        <p>Parisians have two major complaints. Traffic congestion has created a miasma of noise, pollution and stress, helping to make Paris's high-strung population even more irritable. The other is that crime is growing, although the roughest parts of Paris seem no more dangerous than the safest parts of many American cities. Paris had 80 murders last year, compared with 482 in Washington, which has about one-fourth the population.</p>
        <p>Homelessness is another problem, although it does not seem one of the Parisians' main concerns, perhaps because the city has long romanticized the</p>
        <p>clochards</p>
        <p>who sleep along the Seine. The homeless, estimated at between 6,000 and 15,000, can stay for up to six months in 60 government-run or private shelters where they receive free room, board, medical care and job training. Most go to these shelters voluntarily, but the police often round up sleeping drunks to protect them from the cold.</p>
        <p>"Paris's streets are cleaner than American cities, its garbage is picked up more regularly, its streets are paved more often and its bureaucracy is more efficient," says Michel Rousseau, an economics professor who studies urban problems. "But all this costs a lot of money."</p>
        <p>Fortunately for Paris, the national Government contributes more than half the city's revenues. Because the state pays so much, Paris's affluent families do not shoulder a huge fiscal burden of caring for the immigrants and poor living in the city. This is one reason Paris has not suffered from the middle-class flight that has hurt so many American cities.</p>
        <p>As one urban planner puts it: "One reason Paris has so few problems is that the type of people who make problems can't afford to live in Paris." Economic realities force the poor to live in suburbs ringing Paris, but even there, in the</p>
        <p>ban</p>
        <p>lieue</p>
        <p>, the levels of poverty, violence and drugs are a fraction of those in American cities.</p>
        <p>"Because of France's republican traditions, there is a real sense of solidarity, a real desire to help the less-well-off," says Roland Castro, director of the national Government's efforts to help the suburbs. "People often point to American cities as a model to avoid. They say, 'That can happen to us if we let things slide.' "</p>
        <p>AT ONE OF THE 50 MAHOGANY TABLES under the gaze of two austere Chinese statues, Francois Dupin is scribbling on a napkin to explain why his cafe, Les Deux Magots, remains a mecca for Paris's beau monde. "The Chamber of Deputies is over there," says the short, dapper cafe manager, drawing a short black arrow to the west. "The students come from over there," he says, aiming an arrow to the east. "And all the artists and antique dealers come from down there." His last arrow points north to the Seine.</p>
        <p>On the cream-colored wall behind him is a photograph of Simone de Beauvoir hunched over a table, writing at the famed cafe on the Boulevard St.-Germain. Nearby is a photo of a debonair, mustached young Ernest Hemingway, reading a newspaper at the cafe. Partly to imbibe the legend of such famous writers, partly to taste its flavorful coffee and atmosphere, camera-toting Japanese tourists, chain-smoking French intellectuals and lanky American Hemingway-wannabes crowd into Les Deux Magots each day. Many rush to the sidewalk tables, next to artists selling lithographs and in the shadow of the 12th-century towers of the church of St.-Germain-des-Pres.</p>
        <p>"We're in a privileged neighborhood," Mr. Dupin says.</p>
        <p>In one way or another all of Paris's 20</p>
        <p>arron</p>
        <p>dissements</p>
        <p>, or districts, are privileged. The first arrondissement has the Palais Royal and Louvre; the fourth has the Place des Vosges and the Ile St.-Louis; the fifth has the Sorbonne; the sixth, the Jardin du Luxembourg and Ecole des Beaux-Arts; the seventh, the Invalides and the Eiffel Tower. The eighth is known for the Champs-Elysees, the Elysee Palace and world-famous shops like Hermes and Christian Lacroix. The ninth has the grandiose 19th-century Palais Garnier opera house, and the plush 16th is renowned for its opulent fin-de-siecle mansions.</p>
        <p>Everyone wants to live in these neighborhoods, but only the privileged few need apply. One reason is that Paris is small, about half the size of Brooklyn. Rents have been pushed sky-high by limits on building heights and a shortage of land for new housing, caused in part by all the space used for parks, businesses and government. Not wanting Paris to become Manhattan-sur-Seine, the city's planners have generally limited building heights to seven stories in the historic center and relegated skyscrapers to the outskirts.</p>
        <p>A two-bedroom apartment in central Paris often costs $2,500 a month, about the same as in Manhattan and some 60 percent more than in Chicago.  Parking a car costs about $250 a month, roughly the same as in Manhattan. Cleaning a suit is around $15 and a good chicken runs $2.30 a pound. About the only things cheaper in Paris than in America are baguettes, Beaujolais and Christian Dior gowns.</p>
        <p>"I love to live in Paris -- I love the possibilities it offers," says Francoise Romand, a 36-year-old film maker. "The Metro is great, the buses are great and the city's very safe. If you get lost anywhere, there's hardly any risk."</p>
        <p>In her view, there is nowhere else to live in France for people in film. Paris gives her the cultural fix she needs day after day. She recently went to a dance concert by Dominique Bagouet's French troupe, an experimental farce about a restaurant, "Lapin Chasseur," and a rock concert at the Cigalle, one of Paris's hottest nightclubs. She also visited Sophie Calle's photography exhibit at the Museum of Modern Art and Nicholas Garnier's avant-garde show at an art gallery near the Boulevard Montparnasse.</p>
        <p>And that's not to mention exhibitions at the Grand Palais, Louvre, Picasso Museum and Musee d'Orsay. The money the national and city governments spend on Paris's cultural life is probably equal to the overall budgets of some third world nations.</p>
        <p>"The French remain very attached to the idea of culture and education," says Francoise Cachin, director of the Musee d'Orsay. She says that both the left and the right agree it is important to finance museums generously to improve Paris's cultural life and to keep the tourists coming.</p>
        <p>"There is a rivalry between the national and city governments about who can sponsor the best shows," Cachin says. "It's very positive for the museums and museumgoers."</p>
        <p>Notwithstanding the impressive array of museums and municipal services, Parisians' local taxes are not astronomical. The reason: L'Etat, the national Government, pays 40 percent of the city's $23 billion operating budget. The national Government also pays half of most large projects, like schools, sewers and day-care centers. In addition, the state finances Paris's public hospitals, covers almost all welfare costs and pays the salaries of Paris's 24,650 teachers and 26,000 police officers and firefighters.</p>
        <p>"In almost every European country, the central Government plays an important role in supporting the cities," says Leo van den Berg, director of the European Institute for Comparative Urban Research at the University of Rotterdam. "Europe's cities are very dependent on central money, and not so much on local fiscal circumstances."</p>
        <p>That the cost of running Paris is spread throughout France means the city's residents are not socked with exorbitant taxes, although overall the French pay a greater share of their income for national taxes than Americans do. Indeed, the main taxes in Paris -- the apartment tax and the business tax -- are lower than in many country towns, causing some provincial politicians to complain that they are subsidizing Paris's elite.</p>
        <p>Paris is probably far more spoiled by the state than are other European cities because it is the seat of Government and the capital of French finance, industry, entertainment and mass communication. Not only that, it is the cradle of French culture and history, the city of Voltaire, Napoleon, Pasteur, Hugo, Proust, de Gaulle and Sartre.</p>
        <p>No one will ever see a headline like "Mitterrand to Paris: Drop Dead," because one of President Francois Mitterrand's preoccupations is adding new baubles to the capital. The French press has dubbed him Mitterramses I because of the huge monuments he has built, including the $400 million Bastille Opera, the I. M. Pei glass pyramid at the Louvre, the gigantic new finance ministry and the 350-foot-tall Grande Arche de la Defense. And that doesn't include the $1.3 billion Bibliotheque de France that Mitterrand has commissioned, which is slated to be the world's largest library.</p>
        <p>Mitterrand's presidential projects, with a price tag of $3 billion, follow similarly grandiose schemes by his predecessors: Valery Giscard d'Estaing masterminded the Musee d'Orsay and the Cite des Sciences museum, while Georges Pompidou fathered the Pompidou Center, the hugely popular art museum.</p>
        <p>Although many critics deride these buildings as monuments to presidential egos, these projects have undeniably increased Paris's stature as a city of art, culture and architecture. The Musee d'Orsay, for instance, attracts almost four million visitors a year, and art critics from around the world have hailed its recent exhibitions on Seurat, Munch and Gauguin. The museum, which used to be a train station, was slated for demolition until President Giscard d'Estaing moved to save it. "It was a project that couldn't be done without the will of the State," says Cachin, the museum's director. "I can only rejoice."</p>
        <p>TOURISTS strolling along Quai de Montebello near Notre Dame often pass a man in a green uniform who is intently sweeping the street with what looks like a large twig broom. Street cleaners like him are ubiquitous in Paris -- of the city's 38,000 employees, 4,500 are sweepers, most of them Arab or African immigrants. They sweep each of Paris's streets daily, and heavily trafficked business and tourist streets are swept twice.</p>
        <p>All this work by hand shows Paris's efficiency, obsession with detail and willingness to spend money to achieve its goals. Each year Paris spends 10 percent of its budget, or about $2.2 billion, on cleanliness, which translates to $1,000 for every resident.</p>
        <p>"The broom remains irreplaceable," says Alain Le Troquet, technical director for Paris's department of sanitation and the environment. "You can't do everything with a machine."</p>
        <p>Astute observers will notice a curious thing. The brooms no longer have crude brown branches, but instead bright green plastic fingers. Engineers in Paris's sanitation department had long appreciated how efficiently peasants' twig brooms swept debris along, but they were frustrated by how much the brooms cost and how often the twigs broke.</p>
        <p>So Paris's sanitation department, considered Europe's most innovative, asked manufacturers to develop a broom that used sturdy plastic fingers rather than wood. The new plastic brooms cost one-fifth as much as the wooden ones and last seven times as long.</p>
        <p>This is just one way Paris's administrators have demonstrated their technological ingenuity. The city's water system churns out a foot-wide stream that runs alongside the city's curbs to wash away litter. Paris has worked with industry to develop a vehicle to clean up the animal oil left from all the poultry, rabbit and beef sold at open-air markets.</p>
        <p>Voila</p>
        <p>, the Gyrolave squirts steaming, swirling soapy water onto the pavement and then sweeps the street.</p>
        <p>Another truck shoots compressed water under cars to remove the litter beneath them, while a second vehicle has long arms with five joints to pick up leaves. The newest vehicle has an elephantlike trunk that vacuums up sidewalk litter. The city soon hopes to introduce a robotic, unmanned version of this contraption.</p>
        <p>"You have to give the French credit for being innovative," says van den Berg, the urban expert in Rotterdam.</p>
        <p>Parisians say the city has become much cleaner since 1977 when Jacques Chirac became their first democratically elected mayor in a century. Previously Paris had been run by a prefect appointed by the Interior Minister, but residents often argued that a mayor held accountable in regular elections would be more attentive to their needs. (The prefect still runs the police department.)</p>
        <p>When Parisians talk about cleanliness, their main complaint is canine excrement, notwithstanding the city's vaunted new motor scooters that vacuum up dog droppings. Not wanting to alienate dog owners, who represent a powerful voting bloc, the city for years refused to fine owners who did not clean up after their poodles. But with complaints growing, Philippe Galy, director of the department of sanitation and the environment, started ordering fines in May: $110 for the first offense and $230 for the second. "It's absurd," he says. "With all the serious environmental problems, like global warming, the ozone layer, Chernobyl and nuclear waste, it's unbelievable that the No. 1 subject of conversation at every Paris dinner party is dog doo."</p>
        <p>PUBLIC HIGH school like Lycee Janson-de-Sailly, built with busts of Pascal, Hugo and other luminaries along its majestic 200-yard facade, simply does not exist in an American city. The 109-year-old institution is in the 16th arrondissement, the Paris equivalent of Park Avenue, and the bankers, diplomats and high government officials who live there scurry to send their children to Janson.</p>
        <p>Janson has 3,200 students, a lengthy waiting list and a substantial number of students from Paris's rich western suburbs, who are attracted by the school's reputation. The school has 250 teachers, several of them accomplished novelists and historians. Janson's alumni include former President Giscard d'Estaing, former Prime Minister Laurent Fabius and the Attali twins -- Jacques, president of the European Bank for Reconstruction and Development and Bernard, chairman of Air France.</p>
        <p>Its paint may be peeling, its long, primitive desks may be gnarled from decades of use and abuse, but its student body continues to excel. About 95 percent of Janson's graduates pass the forbidding, all-important</p>
        <p>bacca</p>
        <p>laureat</p>
        <p>examination that is the ticket to a university.</p>
        <p>"The school is excellent in many ways," says Francoise Rietsch, who heads one of Janson's parent associations. "There is a lot of discipline, self-discipline, among the students."</p>
        <p>Sitting behind the old wooden desk in her tidy office, Yvonne Cluzet, the school's earnest principal, makes clear that her main concern is academics and not the woes often associated with urban schools.</p>
        <p>"Drugs just aren't a problem here," she says. "And we don't have problems with teen-age pregnancy. Our students are mature." The biggest problem she could think of was that two years ago bands of teen-agers from the suburbs stole pocketbooks, wallets and expensive coats from Janson students as they left school. The police quickly stopped it.</p>
        <p>Janson and other Parisian schools do not suffer from a vicious cycle in which the middle class pulls its children out of public schools, tilting the balance toward poorer immigrant children and causing more middle-class families to send their children elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Jean-Marie Demade, manager at a metallurgy company, moved his family from Rueil-Malmaison, a suburb, back to Paris so his son Julien could attend Janson. "I returned because of the quality of the education," he says. "And life for children is more interesting and lively in Paris, with the movies, museums, theaters and concerts, than it is in the suburbs."</p>
        <p>Twenty-four percent of Paris's high-school students go to private schools. Parents choose those schools because they want their children to receive a religious education or because they have underachieving children and think that private schools will be stricter. The overachievers are sent to public schools like Janson, which, good as it is, doesn't even rank at the top of Paris's public lycees. Most teachers rate Louis-le-Grand and Henri IV even higher.</p>
        <p>"The middle class flocking to private schools just isn't a problem here," says Michele Gendreau-Massalou, the rector of Paris's school system. "In terms of passing the</p>
        <p>baccalaureat</p>
        <p>, public schools produce better results than private schools."</p>
        <p>Schools are just one of the quality services that keep families in Paris. The city has begun building moderately priced three-bedroom apartments because many couples have complained that once they have two or three children they can no longer afford Parisian rents. The city issues a "Paris-Famille" card to parents of three or more children entitling them to $400 in annual discounts on a range of activities, including transport, school meals and college tuition.</p>
        <p>Another magnet for families is the city-run day-care system, which cares for 20,000 children a day, attracting rich and poor alike. The day-care center at 54 rue St.-Maur is typical of the 250 city-run centers except for its bold architecture: it has a spiraling concrete facade that resembles the Guggenheim Museum. Its front is windowless to keep out street noise and pollution, while its back is filled with sun-drenched floor-to-ceiling windows.</p>
        <p>The center on the rue St.-Maur has a staff of 25 to watch over 87 children, aged 3 months to 3 years. Each of its three floors has a glass-enclosed nap area, and the staff has painted pink and blue rabbits and stars on the see-through walls. Each week, one of the center's aides stages a marionette show; the city offers special courses to teach day-care workers how to do such shows.</p>
        <p>"I can afford my own au pair, but I much prefer the day-care center," says Patricia Fayet, a radiologist, as she watches her 1-year-old son, Yann, play in a bright blue plastic tub filled with hundreds of striped balls. "At the day-care center, the children get professional care and learn how to live with others."</p>
        <p>Each center has a director who lives on the site and is trained as a licensed nurse and specialist in early child development. All the day-care workers must have spent a year in college studying care of children under age 3. A doctor visits each center once a week.</p>
        <p>At the center on the rue St.-Maur, parents can leave their children from 7:30 A.M. to 6:30 P.M., but France Galas, the director, chides parents who leave a child for more than eight hours. Payments are on a sliding scale, ranging from $30 to $400 a month per child, with the city picking up half the cost of running the centers.</p>
        <p>The centers are so successful that there is a waiting list of thousands of children, and the city is struggling to keep up by building one new day-care center a month.</p>
        <p>"A few years ago mothers thought it was bad to put their children in a public day-care center because they felt guilty they weren't doing enough for their kids," says Elisabeth Allaire, director of social services, children and health for Paris. "Now mothers have heard so many good things about our day-care centers that they think they are bad mothers if they</p>
        <p>don't</p>
        <p>send their kids to our centers."</p>
        <p>IN MANY WAYS, Paris is a tale of two cities. There is the Paris of the travel guides: the city of three-star restaurants and Yves Saint Laurent boutiques, the city of the 2.2 million privileged souls who live within the 22-mile ring road, the Boulevard Peripherique.</p>
        <p>Then there is the other Paris, the outer ring where the working classes live, often in anonymous 1960's tower blocks. These are the suburbs where gangs of immigrant teen-agers clash with the police, where the sons of Algerian and Moroccan workers have a 25 percent jobless rate and where the native French tilt heavily toward Jean-Marie Le Pen, the far-right, anti-immigrant leader. These suburbs include Sartrouville, Montfermeil, Mantes-la-Jolie and Gennevilliers.</p>
        <p>"One important reason why Paris is successful is that it's a fantastically elitist city," says Christopher Brooks, an economist specializing in urban issues at the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development in Paris. "While a lot of people would like to live there, lots of people can't afford to. The social composition is skewed as a result. The poor are forced to live in the outskirts."</p>
        <p>The Quartier du Luth in Gennevilliers is neither the worst nor the best of the banlieue. It is a United Nations of immigrants from Algeria, the Antilles, the Ivory Coast, Morocco, Tunisia, Turkey, Zaire and a dozen other countries. About 40 percent of its 10,000 residents are immigrants, and fewer than half the children finish high school. Teachers complain that they find syringes near the school gates.</p>
        <p>"This isn't the greatest neighborhood," says Ahmet Ersoy, a 30-year-old unemployed refugee from Turkey. "We'd like to move on to another neighborhood eventually." Ersoy lives in a nondescript, 14-story, 500-yard-long block that could have won a Stalinist design contest. Its graffiti-splattered walls say "Momo" and "Chaka Chaoui." Social agencies steer immigrants to districts like the Luth, four miles northwest of Paris, because they have the cheapest housing in the region. A modest two-bedroom apartment is $350, about one-seventh the cost in central Paris.</p>
        <p>In the Luth, France's activist Government works hard to improve living conditions. There are playgrounds with bright red swings and slides, and an office has been set up where four social workers counsel the Luth's residents.</p>
        <p>The district has been designated a "Priority Education Zone." This means its schools receive extra money and teachers to help integrate immigrant children and provide special help to the laggards. At Guy Moquet Middle School, Claude Naveau, the principal, is proud that his school, filled with Botticelli and Manet posters, has a computer room and its own radio station.</p>
        <p>"We have a lot of children who don't have a good family environment, who don't have someone asking them, 'Are you doing your homework?' " says Naveau, whose heavy glasses and thick beard make him look like an archetypal intellectual. "Children love our school because it's an oasis from the chaos outside."</p>
        <p>To be sure, Paris proper also has its less chic neighborhoods, most notably the 18th, 19th and 20th arrondissements in the north and east. These have a large North African population, much of it second generation, many of whom work in small businesses, especially textiles.</p>
        <p>The epicenter of Arab Paris is Barbes-Rochechouart, the intersection of two bustling avenues, which seems a cross between a Moroccan souk and Manhattan's 14th Street. Elevated trains rumble by as people squeeze past a 200-yard line of sidewalk stalls. Nearby, young toughs wait until sundown to begin their purse snatchings.</p>
        <p>"A lot of young kids come up from the Maghreb, can't find jobs and start creating trouble," says Youssef Karoui, who runs the Eslem restaurant.</p>
        <p>The problem in these neighborhoods, residents say, is not violent crime, but purse-snatchings, burglaries and car thefts. Fortunately for Paris, crack has not made inroads and drug addiction is far less prevalent than in American cities.</p>
        <p>THE ENTRANCE TO THE concrete, 1960's building on the Boulevard Bourdon, 250 yards south of the Bastille, could not be more nondescript. There isn't even a nameplate. But deep inside, behind the security guards, is a cavernous room filled with display panels and flashing lights that looks like the Pentagon's war room.</p>
        <p>Welcome to the central command post for Paris's subway system, an intricate web with 434 stations, 686 escalators and 1.6 billion riders a year.</p>
        <p>At rush hour, 560 trains snake through the city, and on the command center's 13 display panels, each as long as a baseball scoreboard, orange lights show the location and progress of every single train. If there is a subway fire or someone jumps in front of a train -- there are about 150 such suicides each year -- a subway line manager leaps up from his console and runs to his display panel to switch off power for his line.</p>
        <p>"We have already extended this display panel to include some new stations that we still haven't opened," says Jean-Pierre Renard, a longtime manager at the command center. The panel shows two stations to be added when line No. 1 is extended under the Seine to La Defense, the ultramodern office district west of Paris.</p>
        <p>Probably better than anything else, the Metro demonstrates Paris's devotion to constant improvement: to improve through planning, bold engineering and a willingness to spend money. The Metro recently added a conductorless train that connects Orly Airport with the main subway line. The express suburban rail system, known as the R.E.R., has been extended east to Euro-Disneyland, which opened in April. There are plans for a six-mile-long tramway that will connect blue-collar suburbs north of Paris and for an express subway connecting the southernmost part of Paris to the St.-Lazare train station on the right bank.</p>
        <p>The budget for these and other transit projects -- which are selected by a regional transportation board -- will total $3 billion over the next five years. The financing comes from ticket revenues and from the city, regional and national governments.</p>
        <p>Thanks to a solid flow of funds, the subway cars undergo maintenance once a week, and as a result mechanical failures are responsible for less than a third of line shutdowns. Usually the problem is human failures, like fights between passengers or pranksters pulling the emergency cord.</p>
        <p>"If our trains ran without passengers, we'd hardly have any problems," jokes Renard, a short, dapper man in a blue bow tie and charcoal-striped suit.</p>
        <p>Like many Parisian civil servants, Renard exudes an extreme pride in his work and his city. He boasts about a new varnish that helps keep the Metro graffiti-free. He brags about the system's safety record, saying he cannot remember the last time there was a fatal accident.</p>
        <p>"I'm a modest man, so don't expect me to say that our Metro is the best in the world," he says, with a twinkle in his eye. "Let's just say it's one of the best.</p>
        <p>"We plan to keep it that way."  Steven Greenhouse was a correspondent in The New York Times Paris bureau for five years and recently joined the Washington bureau.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Steven Greenhouse was a correspondent in The New York Times Paris bureau for five years and recently joined the Washington bureau.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
