<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carbon Tax: Green Twist on Oil Price</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA133AF935A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carbon Tax: Green Twist on Oil Price</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Preparing for the Earth Summit that opened in Rio de Janeiro this week, representatives of the European Community's 12 nations proposed a carbon tax -- a tax tied to the amount of carbon dioxide that burning the fuel creates.</p>
        <p>That step reopened an old dispute over the pricing of oil: When the importing nations talk of raising prices to hold down consumption, exporting nations threaten to do the job for them and keep the revenue for themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Preparing for the Earth Summit that opened in Rio de Janeiro this week, representatives of the European Community's 12 nations proposed a carbon tax -- a tax tied to the amount of carbon dioxide that burning the fuel creates.</p>
        <p>That step reopened an old dispute over the pricing of oil: When the importing nations talk of raising prices to hold down consumption, exporting nations threaten to do the job for them and keep the revenue for themselves.</p>
        <p>After the commissioners of the European Community conditionally approved a carbon tax that would amount to $3 a barrel on oil, and would rise to $10 a barrel by 2000, Saudi Arabia, the world's largest oil exporter, quickly responded that it would simply freeze its level of production, which would force up the price of oil. And sure enough, as soon as the Saudis spoke, the price rose $1 a barrel.  As it happens, the European tax is contingent upon the United States and Japan going along -- such a huge "if" that it will probably be a stopper. The tax would be based in part on carbon-dioxide creation and in part on fuel costs, covering coal, oil, natural gas and, oddly, nuclear energy, which produces no carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>From the Saudis' point of view, these latest events must be exasperating. For years the governments of countries that import oil pleaded with Riyadh to invest in new pumping capacity, to permit price stability and allow the importers' economies to grow. That request became urgent after Iraq invaded Kuwait, and Saudi Arabia quickly obliged by raising its production to 8.5 million barrels a day, from 5.5 million.</p>
        <p>Now, suddenly, at least in the European Community, governments want to increase the price of oil, to cut consumption.</p>
        <p>There is not much new in the struggle over who will grow rich on oil. Daniel Yergin, an energy historian, pointed out that oil producers sought higher prices in the 1960's and 1970's after European countries raised taxes on oil as a means of raising revenue. "It's deja vu, but seen through green-tinted sunglasses," he said, noting that consumers might feel good about a "green tax" meant to help the environment.</p>
        <p>But even if the industrial world eventually agrees on a carbon tax, its effects are not so clear. It might not hurt exporters, at least not as badly as it looks at first glance. And the weapon chosen by Saudi Arabia, a pre-emptive price rise, may not be useful to the kingdom.</p>
        <p>For one thing, Saudi Arabia's thinking for a decade has been to assure a future demand for oil, because it has a supply in the ground that would last for decades. Thus in every price move it tries to engineer, it will want to avoid making oil so costly that the alternatives are economically attractive. Oil May Do Well</p>
        <p>Even if a carbon tax emerges from the Rio meeting, oil may not do so badly. If drafted the way scientists want, such a tax would hit hardest not at oil but at coal.</p>
        <p>Roger Dower, a climate change expert at the World Resources Institute, suggested that the European Community might soon move to reorganize its taxes, keeping total revenue constant but gathering more from high-carbon fuels like coal and less from low-carbon ones like natural gas. If fuels are taxed on the basis of their carbon content, oil is in a strong position relative to coal. "Oil could hardly lose," he said.</p>
        <p>The proposal the European Community has on the table in Rio is essentially hypothetical, given the unlikelihood that the United States and Japan will go along. Even some members of the community may balk.</p>
        <p>Peter Beutel, an analyst at Pegasus Econometric Associates, described the sudden price run-up in the oil markets as "a series of emotional reactions to emotional reactions."</p>
        <p>Even if the developed world eventually imposes such a tax, this alone does not imply lower oil sales, at least not for long, although it might mean a loss of income to oil-exporting nations.</p>
        <p>Anthony E. Reinsch, vice president of the Canadian Energy Research Institute, in Calgary, Alberta, ran a computer simulation that assumed a tax of 10 percent on light-oil products, like gasoline and diesel oil, in the major industrial countries. The result, he said, was to depress demand and therefore the world price of oil, which stimulated demand in countries that did not impose a tax. Undercutting the Logic</p>
        <p>"The net impact from a volume standpoint was zero," he said. "There was a dip and then a recovery."</p>
        <p>If the world economy behaved like the model, that would undercut the logic of a carbon tax, because it would put the countries that imposed the tax at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reinsch described Saudi Arabia's recent move as "a little bit of soap-boxing," and Mr. Beutel suggested that if the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries actually raised the price $2 or $3 a barrel, the higher price would coax forth new supplies that would bring the price back down anyway.</p>
        <p>But all this gives more credence to the carbon tax proposal than it may deserve. Agreeing on the details of such a tax will always be difficult for the world, and even for Europe alone.</p>
        <p>"Because of the difference in the fuel mix, different countries have quite distinct and different perceptions of where the balance should be set," said Irving Mintzer, the coordinator of the Stockholm Environmental Institute's Climate Change and Sustainable Development Program.</p>
        <p>A tax based strictly on carbon content would be seen by some members of the European Community as too favorable to France and its policy of nuclear power, he said. Other countries, including the United States, have politically powerful coal interests. No country relishes seeing its energy prices rise higher than its neighbor's, handicapping its industries. Fear of Saudi Action</p>
        <p>At present, the logic that prevails in the market is the Saudi threat, with about $1 of the current price of oil representing anticipation of constricted supply. "This has very definitely affected the psychology of the market," Mr. Yergin said.</p>
        <p>The factors that contribute to the price increase, he pointed out, include expectations for a global economic recovery and rising demand, along with anticipation of the normal increase in demand in the third quarter of every year.</p>
        <p>Separating the other factors from the fear of Saudi action is difficult. By the time the Earth Summit ends, the possibility of a carbon tax may have faded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
