<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. Signs an Accord With Environmentalists</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="541501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL DEFENSE FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D8123EF93AA35754C0A964958260" item-length="548" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. Signs an Accord With Environmentalists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an unusual expression of detente between industry and environmentalists, General Motors and the Environmental Defense Fund announced yesterday that they had signed an agreement to hold formal discussions on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>"Over the last 20 years, it's been each side preaching to the heathen on the other side," said Joseph Goffman, a lawyer with the environmental group. "We've decided to skip the great conversion speeches and talk about what we can talk about."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an unusual expression of detente between industry and environmentalists, General Motors and the Environmental Defense Fund announced yesterday that they had signed an agreement to hold formal discussions on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>"Over the last 20 years, it's been each side preaching to the heathen on the other side," said Joseph Goffman, a lawyer with the environmental group. "We've decided to skip the great conversion speeches and talk about what we can talk about."</p>
        <p>G.M., the world's largest car maker, is at the center of a wide range of such environmental issues as urban smog, destruction of the ozone layer and the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Defense Fund, a New York-based nonprofit group with 200,000 members, often sues polluters. Last November, however, it negotiated an agreement with the McDonald's Corporation under which, among other things, the fast-food company replaced its plastic "clamshell" packaging with biodegradable cardboard. .</p>
        <p>The dialogue required a formal agreement, said Samuel A. Leonard, G.M.'s director of automotive emissions control, so the environmentalists "could not be accused of selling out."</p>
        <p>The agreement specifies that the environmental group will not accept funds from G.M. and that G.M. cannot publicize the dialogue in advertising, marketing or point-of-purchase materials, without the group's permission. The fund would be unlikely to give such permission, Mr. Goffman said.</p>
        <p>Informal collaboration has been going on since January and has already produced a proposal presented to the Federal Environmental Protection Agency on running a program for scrapping old cars.</p>
        <p>President Bush proposed such a program in November, in which a company that faced a requirement to cut air pollution at a factory it owned could instead buy old, high-pollution cars and scrap them, taking credit against other obligations to cut pollution. 2 Heads Better . . .</p>
        <p>Both G.M. and the Environmental Defense Fund have said the joint proposal is better than each could have come up with on its own. The Environmental Defense Fund proposed that pollution-reduction credit be limited to 90 percent of the actual reduction.</p>
        <p>"It makes eminent sense when you think about it," Mr. Leonard of G.M. said in a telephone interview yesterday.</p>
        <p>G.M., Mr. Leonard said, had added that the vehicles to be scrapped be selected by actual measurement of tailpipe emissions, rather than simply by their age.</p>
        <p>"The process we've gone through on vehicle scrapping has increased our respect for what the other brings to the table," Mr. Leonard said.</p>
        <p>The two sides plan to discuss ways to encourage the use of clean vehicles that run on other than gasoline, ways to measure automotive emissions, cost-effectiveness of new fuels and new standards on vehicle emissions, the role of vehicles in global warming and the impact of regulatory requirements on vehicle design.</p>
        <p>But they will avoid some long-standing areas of dispute, including fuel economy standards and installing larger canisters on cars to filter the polluting gases that evaporate from fuel tanks.</p>
        <p>"We will have to use more traditional methods to solve those," he said, alluding to lobbying in Congress and arguing before the administrative agencies and the courts.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
