<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Senate Backs Faster Protection Of Ozone Layer as Bush Relents</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILTS, PHILIP J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REILLY, WILLIAM K (ADMR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D8153FF934A35751C0A964958260" item-length="1283" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Senate Backs Faster Protection Of Ozone Layer as Bush Relents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILTS, PHILIP J</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush Administration, in a surprise reversal of its public position, today supported a Senate action to phase out much faster the chemicals that damage the protective ozone layer high in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>A proposal to cease production of the chemicals as fast as possible passed the Senate today by 96 to 0, a vote that would have been unthinkable without the change of attitude at the White House. Only three months ago the measure was prevented from even reaching the floor by Republican senators acting on behalf of the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush Administration, in a surprise reversal of its public position, today supported a Senate action to phase out much faster the chemicals that damage the protective ozone layer high in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>A proposal to cease production of the chemicals as fast as possible passed the Senate today by 96 to 0, a vote that would have been unthinkable without the change of attitude at the White House. Only three months ago the measure was prevented from even reaching the floor by Republican senators acting on behalf of the White House.</p>
        <p>The White House's change in position comes after efforts by the Environmental Protection Agency. With John H. Sununu no longer White House chief of staff and in a position to oppose its initiatives, the agency took advantage of new data released this week that portray a threat much worse than expected.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, the E.P.A. Administrator, said today: "President Bush is very concerned about ozone depletion and takes seriously the recent scientific discovery that it is worse than we thought. I expect that the Administration, which is currently reviewing the information, will support moving up the phaseout schedule for various ozone-depleting chemicals by three, four or in some cases five years." Chemicals Are Widespread</p>
        <p>The chemicals, a family known as chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, are widespread. They are used as industrial solvents and as the coolant in refrigerators and air-conditioners, among other things. The trend toward halting the manufacture of CFC's is likely to force many industries to redouble their efforts to find substitutes while they recycle those CFC's already in use.</p>
        <p>An international agreement, the Montreal Protocol, signed in 1987, calls for production of CFC's to cease by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Eileen Claussen, director of the E.P.A.'s Office of Atmospheric and Indoor Air Programs, said today: "It is obvious we have to move up the dates. The Senate resolution says to move them up as fast as we can. To the extent there is debate, and there isn't much, the debate is over just how early we can fix these dates."</p>
        <p>The proposal passed by the Senate today, an amendment to the energy bill, declares that the ozone depletion is occurring at twice the rate previously believed, is occurring both in the Southern and Northern Hemispheres and is occurring over both the poles and populated areas. The Senate's work on the energy bill is expected to be finished within a week, and the House's work by the end of March. Support for the ozone-protection measure is also known to be strong in the House.</p>
        <p>Some scientists have said it could take decades to reverse damage to the ozone layer caused by the chemicals over the years.</p>
        <p>Senator Al Gore, Democrat of Tennessee, who was the author of the amendment passed today and who has long urged that CFC production be halted as quickly as possible, told the Senate today: "The President has abdicated his responsibility. This amendment is a wake-up call."</p>
        <p>"It is easy enough, after the ozone hole is pointed to and predicted above Kennebunkport, to say, 'O. K., we will now think seriously about doing something,' " Mr. Gore continued. "Where was the President when the warnings came through so loudly and clearly for the last several years?"</p>
        <p>White House officials countered that the Administration has aggressively pursued the issue, and that Mr. Reilly has been working out a proposal to hasten the end of production.</p>
        <p>One consequence of phasing out CFC's faster is that industries with existing refrigeration equipment are likely to intensify efforts to conserve the refrigerants already in use. Instead of simply venting CFC refrigerants into the atmosphere, as was often done in the past, companies are now collecting the materials and sending them to chemical companies, like du Pont, for processing and re-use.</p>
        <p>All the substitutes that have been developed for CFC's will require modifications in refrigerators, air conditioners and industrial chillers. New appliances will contain the needed changes, but industrial equipment which has a 30-year life span can operated on recycled CFC's until modifications are made. Banking on Substitutes</p>
        <p>The quicker phaseout had been strongly advocated by environmental groups and some European nations. Chemical companies, including du Pont, Allied-Signal and the British company ICI, have been building plants to produce the substitutes, which are hydroclorofluorocarbons, or HCFC's, and hydrofluorocarbons, or HFC's.</p>
        <p>HCF's are believed to attack the ozone layer as well, but not as strongly as CFC's. One issue still to be resolved is whether production of HCFC's will be permitted until completely benign substitutes can be developed.</p>
        <p>Some industries have been moving in advance of international agreements to eliminate CFC's. Some plastics manufacturers have said they will cease using the chemicals in foam packaging by 1993 and in insulation by 1995.</p>
        <p>Scientists of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration reported this week that a satellite had detected exceptionally high levels of an ozone-killing chemical derived from CFC's over a wide area of the Northern Hemisphere, including large populated areas of Europe and Canada.  Hole Over the Antarctic</p>
        <p>The chemical, known as chlorine monoxide, was detected in concentrations of one part per billion, a matter of serious concern since it is comparable to the levels observed within the Antarctic ozone hole.</p>
        <p>The Antarctic hole, which has been observed for the last several years, is depleted of about half its ozone. The effect of clorine monoxide in Northern latitudes cannot be predicted with certainty. Researchers will not know until summer to what extent winds, temperatures and sunlight permit the chlorine molecules to open up a "hole" over the North.</p>
        <p>In addition to the Antarctic ozone hole, scientists had already noted that the ozone over such temperate latitudes as North America has also been depleted, although by smaller amounts -- by about 3 percent in summer and 5 to 8 percent in winter, compared with a decade ago.</p>
        <p>Activity to reduce CFC production was already under way before today's vote. The Clean Air Act requires United States policy to be reviewed if any new threat to the ozone shield is perceived. Under that procedure, an environmental group, the Natural Resources Defense Council, submitted in December a proposal to accelerate the phaseout.</p>
        <p>The chief group representing industry, the Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, also has developed a quicker phaseout policy, which it is ready to submit to the E.P.A. The group did not endorse or oppose Senator Gore's amendment. But the alliance's executive director, Kevin Fay, said today: "Although the amendment contains no dates, in many respects it is consistent with actions we have been recommending. We believe the schedule can be accelerated."</p>
        <p>The difference between the industry and environmental group proposals are slight: the N.R.D.C. proposal suggests phasing out CFC production by 1995, while industry suggests 1996.</p>
        <p>Similar differences of date exist for the numerous other chemicals of the same family, differences that E.P.A. officials say should not be difficult to resolve. Substitutes Identified</p>
        <p>Mr. Fay said that industry had already identified a number of chemical substitutes for the CFC's, which may do the same work in refrigeration, air-conditioning and other uses but without the same atmospheric effects.</p>
        <p>The United States is using half the amount of CFC's used in 1986. He said that if older appliances were replaced gradually, then by 1996 or so, only 10 to 15 percent of the 1986 production will be necessary.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
