<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Seeks Rules to Lift Sales of Gas</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="512255"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DA173AF934A35750C0A964958260" item-length="756" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Seeks Rules to Lift Sales of Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush announced his support yesterday for four regulatory changes that he said would raise demand for natural gas and help an industry that has been badly hurt by low prices.</p>
        <p>The gas industry applauded the announcement, which came shortly before the primary election in Texas, a leading gas-producing state. But environmentalists and consumer advocates said it was not clear whether the changes, all of them under discussion in Washington for months or years, would mean that more gas would be sold, at least in the near future. They also said that one proposed change could cut gas sales and increase pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush announced his support yesterday for four regulatory changes that he said would raise demand for natural gas and help an industry that has been badly hurt by low prices.</p>
        <p>The gas industry applauded the announcement, which came shortly before the primary election in Texas, a leading gas-producing state. But environmentalists and consumer advocates said it was not clear whether the changes, all of them under discussion in Washington for months or years, would mean that more gas would be sold, at least in the near future. They also said that one proposed change could cut gas sales and increase pollution.</p>
        <p>The changes are intended to lower costs or remove regulatory barriers. They could result in greater use of natural gas in cars and power plants. 2 Problems Not Addressed</p>
        <p>Edwin Rothschild, an energy expert at Citizen Action, a consumer organization, said some of the proposed changes were desirable because they would promote use of natural-gas vehicles, lowering pollution and reliance on imported oil. But the natural-gas industry's real problems, he said, are two phenomena beyond White House control: warm weather and recession.</p>
        <p>"I don't see this as stimulating a lot of demand quickly," he said.</p>
        <p>But the president of the American Gas Association, Michael Baly 3d, said his industry was "deeply grateful."</p>
        <p>Possibly the least controversial proposal was the President's announcement that the Environmental Protection Agency would soon issue an emissions standard for natural-gas vehicles that would help them compete. Federal standards for gasoline vehicles set a limit on hydrocarbon emissions as a way to control smog, but proponents of natural-gas vehicles complain that natural gas itself, while a hydrocarbon, is not an ingredient of smog. So the E.P.A. will issue a standard for emissions of hydrocarbons other than natural gas.</p>
        <p>There are now no standards for the vehicles. Mr. Baly of the gas association said yesterday, "If you want to start mass-producing these, major equipment manufacturers want a standard." A Greenhouse Gas</p>
        <p>But even if emissions of unburned natural gas do not contribute to smog, they are still a pollutant, environmentalists say, because natural gas is a greenhouse gas, contributing to global warming.</p>
        <p>David G. Hawkins, an air-pollution expert at the Natural Resources Defense Council, said that allowing natural-gas emissions because they did not cause smog was "an example of tunnel vision," adding, "You could say the same thing about CFC's," which destroy the earth's protective layer of ozone.</p>
        <p>The White House also said that the environmental agency would change the rules on when changes to a power plant become so extensive that the plant is considered new, and therefore subject to stricter pollution standards. Named after a case involving the Wisconsin Electric Power Company, the "Wepco fix" -- as it is known on Capitol Hill -- would allow utilities to make major changes to dirty old plants without becoming subject to the strict regulations governing new ones. But the fix was rejected by Congress in the debate over the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>If utilities were not subject to rules on new sources of pollution, according to the gas industry, they might take inexpensive steps that would significantly reduce pollution, like "co-firing" coal with natural gas. In co-firing -- when the two fuels are burned together in the boiler -- chemical reactions reduce the total pollution, although the plant is still dirtier than a new one. The Opposite Case</p>
        <p>But environmentalists say the Wepco fix might not help gas sales at all. Without it, they say, many utilities would be forced to scrap dirty coal-fired plants and build new ones that run entirely on gas; with the fix, they can continue to rely heavily on coal.</p>
        <p>A third change would give gas-pipeline companies the option to be regulated under an incentive system, rather than the cost-based system that now prevails, but the details have not been established.</p>
        <p>A fourth would remove a regulatory wrinkle that some people have said could hurt natural-gas vehicles: the issue of interstate regulation. In theory, according to some natural-gas executives, if a car were fueled with natural gas in one state and driven to another, the sale would be interstate and thus subject to Federal regulation, although in practice the issue has not arisen, experts said.</p>
        <p>The proposed change would make it clear that sales of natural gas for vehicles were not subject to Federal regulation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
