<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD61431F93BA25751C0A964958260" item-length="1032" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A2-9  SHADOW WARS DRAW SKEPTICISM</p>
        <p>The "threat of the unknown" that may form the basis for post-cold-war Pentagon spending is likely to inspire conflict in Congress.  A1  HELP IN DISMANTLING NUCLEAR PAST</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Baker, visiting Moscow, offers aid in the form of rail cars to transport nuclear weapons and a program to find jobs for nuclear scientists.  A1</p>
        <p>Russia-bound boxcars are retired but seemingly impenetrable.  A6  COURT BARS RAPE VICTIM'S TRAVEL</p>
        <p>The case of a 14-year-old Irish rape victim barred from traveling to England for an abortion has stirred on debate over how far Ireland can go in prohibiting abortion.  A1  TRADE SKIRMISH WITH CANADA</p>
        <p>Beer, lumber and cars are the issues in a new round of confrontations as Washington and Ottawa trade accusations of protectionist ways despite a free-trade agreement.  A1  AFTERMATH OF AN ASSASSINATION</p>
        <p>Israeli forces and Muslim militiamen traded fire in southern Lebanon after Israel's assassination of a Lebanese Shiite leader, Sheik Abbas Musawi.  A8  U.N.'S YUGOSLAVIA AGENDA</p>
        <p>The U.N. Secretary General wants assurances that peacekeepers that may be sent to Yugoslavia are prepared to stay until a political settlement is reached.  A3  A DIET OF HUNGER AND ANGER</p>
        <p>North Koreans are living on little more than rice and in private are indulging in anger at their Communist leaders, visitors who cross the border from China are saying.  A9  ETHIOPIA'S MYSTERY UNRAVELS</p>
        <p>The remains of Emperor Haile Selassie were found beneath the office of the man who overthrew him, but the cause of death has not been determined.  A13  VISIT FROM A ZAMBIAN LEADER</p>
        <p>Frederick Chiluba, Zambia's President for barely 100 days, brings to the U.S. his enthusiasm and requests for help with the nation's debt and democratic institutions.  A3  Arcadia Journal: Two villages, one withering, one prospering.  A4  Japan's new Ambassador to the U.S. sees a period of adjustment.  A7</p>
        <p>Putting the brakes on the ruble's freefall.  A7</p>
        <p>Two ex-Prime Ministers compete to lead Israel's Labor Party.  A8</p>
        <p>The U.S. and the Vatican reportedly cooperated to aid Solidarity.  A5  National A14-20, D10  MOMENT OF DECISION</p>
        <p>As the New Hampshire primary contest rolled into its final, frantic hours, the five Democratic candidates stormed the state and President Bush fought against embarrassment at the hands of Patrick Buchanan.  A1  PUSHING THEM TO THE POLLS</p>
        <p>In a state where a few thousand votes can be crucial, the candidates sought to press, even to hound, their supporters to the polls.  A17  EXPOSING THE FAULT LINES</p>
        <p>Patrick Buchanan's challenge exposed President Bush's political vulnerability, and the results of the New Hampshire primary will show the extent of the problem.  A17  MY MAN WON. REALLY.</p>
        <p>Spin, the blatant art of bending the truth, reached new intensities after the Democratic debate Sunday.  A16  WRITING IN A NONCANDIDATE</p>
        <p>Ralph Nader said he doesn't want to be President, but he has asked voters to write in his name as a vote for "none of the above." A17  HARKIN'S CALM HOMETOWN</p>
        <p>Cumming Journal: Though Senator Harkin counts a quarter of this Iowa town's residents as relatives, most people weren't too excited yet about his Presidential bid.  A14  HIGH RISK TO HISPANIC WORKERS</p>
        <p>Endangered by inexperience, ignorance of English and predatory employers, Hispanic factory workers get hurt on the job more often and more seriously than non-Hispanic Americans, researchers and officials said.  A1  NO PAROLE FOR DAHMER</p>
        <p>A judge sentenced Jeffrey Dahmer to 15 consecutive life terms in prison, making him eligible for parole only after 900 years.  A14  A TENTATIVE DREXEL DEAL</p>
        <p>Michael R. Milken has agreed to pay an additional $500 million and his former colleagues at Drexel Burnham Lambert, the Wall Street firm, have agreed to pay $300 million to settle lawsuits.  A1  MINNESOTA TACKLES HEALTH CARE</p>
        <p>Minnesota legislators said they were determined to create a universal health-care plan that would subsidize the working poor, force insurers to cover people in high-risk groups and require greater cost efficiency.  A14  KEEPING DANGERS A SECRET</p>
        <p>Court orders sealing evidence in liability, malpractice and other suits are proliferating wildly, to the dismay of some lawyers, judges and government agencies.  D10</p>
        <p>A Federal panel will gather for new hearings on breast implants.  D10  CHIEF DISMISSED IN HOUSTON</p>
        <p>The only woman to head a police force in a major American city was removed from office a little more than two years after she took over the Houston department.  A20  Neighbors of Arlo Guthrie said he misled them.  A20  Metropolitan Digest, B1 Business Digest, D1 Science Times C1-11  U.S. may be on the verge of changing its stance on climate change.  C1  Heavyweight astronomy on a featherweight budget in Georgia.  C1  Male dolphins team up to get what they want in mating.  C1  The Doctor's World: Bush's physician gets lots of advice.  C3  Sports B9-17  Olympics: U.S. and Sweden tie in hockey.  B9  Ice-dance pair from Unified Team wins.  B9  U.S. might look to courts for ski jumpers.  B10  Basketball: Knicks barely get past Heat.  B14  Seton Hall defeats Pitt.  B13  Michigan's lively freshmen.  B13  Hockey: Rangers tie Canucks in last second of regulation.  B9  Islanders beat Jets, 5-4.  B17  Obituaries D12  Les Trautmann, editor of the Staten Island Advance.</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C13-18  Berlin Film Festival.  C13  Hollywood self-portrait: ugly.  C13  Music: De La Soul.  C13  Classical Music in Review.  C14  Word and Image: Stories in the first person.  C17  Fashion Page B8  Skirts that swing.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A18-19  Editorials A18  Global snub on warming. Re-inventing debate wheel. Tuesday night live. Shrinking on garbage reform. Letters A18  A. M. Rosenthal: Running from the world.  A19  Peter Jenkins: New Hampshire -- does Europe care?  A19  Pat Oliphant: The day before the morning after.  A19  Joseph Nocera: Shut up and vote.  A19</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A2-9  SHADOW WARS DRAW SKEPTICISM</p>
        <p>The "threat of the unknown" that may form the basis for post-cold-war Pentagon spending is likely to inspire conflict in Congress.  A1  HELP IN DISMANTLING NUCLEAR PAST</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Baker, visiting Moscow, offers aid in the form of rail cars to transport nuclear weapons and a program to find jobs for nuclear scientists.  A1</p>
        <p>Russia-bound boxcars are retired but seemingly impenetrable.  A6  COURT BARS RAPE VICTIM'S TRAVEL</p>
        <p>The case of a 14-year-old Irish rape victim barred from traveling to England for an abortion has stirred on debate over how far Ireland can go in prohibiting abortion.  A1  TRADE SKIRMISH WITH CANADA</p>
        <p>Beer, lumber and cars are the issues in a new round of confrontations as Washington and Ottawa trade accusations of protectionist ways despite a free-trade agreement.  A1  AFTERMATH OF AN ASSASSINATION</p>
        <p>Israeli forces and Muslim militiamen traded fire in southern Lebanon after Israel's assassination of a Lebanese Shiite leader, Sheik Abbas Musawi.  A8  U.N.'S YUGOSLAVIA AGENDA</p>
        <p>The U.N. Secretary General wants assurances that peacekeepers that may be sent to Yugoslavia are prepared to stay until a political settlement is reached.  A3  A DIET OF HUNGER AND ANGER</p>
        <p>North Koreans are living on little more than rice and in private are indulging in anger at their Communist leaders, visitors who cross the border from China are saying.  A9  ETHIOPIA'S MYSTERY UNRAVELS</p>
        <p>The remains of Emperor Haile Selassie were found beneath the office of the man who overthrew him, but the cause of death has not been determined.  A13  VISIT FROM A ZAMBIAN LEADER</p>
        <p>Frederick Chiluba, Zambia's President for barely 100 days, brings to the U.S. his enthusiasm and requests for help with the nation's debt and democratic institutions.  A3  Arcadia Journal: Two villages, one withering, one prospering.  A4  Japan's new Ambassador to the U.S. sees a period of adjustment.  A7</p>
        <p>Putting the brakes on the ruble's freefall.  A7</p>
        <p>Two ex-Prime Ministers compete to lead Israel's Labor Party.  A8</p>
        <p>The U.S. and the Vatican reportedly cooperated to aid Solidarity.  A5  National A14-20, D10  MOMENT OF DECISION</p>
        <p>As the New Hampshire primary contest rolled into its final, frantic hours, the five Democratic candidates stormed the state and President Bush fought against embarrassment at the hands of Patrick Buchanan.  A1  PUSHING THEM TO THE POLLS</p>
        <p>In a state where a few thousand votes can be crucial, the candidates sought to press, even to hound, their supporters to the polls.  A17  EXPOSING THE FAULT LINES</p>
        <p>Patrick Buchanan's challenge exposed President Bush's political vulnerability, and the results of the New Hampshire primary will show the extent of the problem.  A17  MY MAN WON. REALLY.</p>
        <p>Spin, the blatant art of bending the truth, reached new intensities after the Democratic debate Sunday.  A16  WRITING IN A NONCANDIDATE</p>
        <p>Ralph Nader said he doesn't want to be President, but he has asked voters to write in his name as a vote for "none of the above." A17  HARKIN'S CALM HOMETOWN</p>
        <p>Cumming Journal: Though Senator Harkin counts a quarter of this Iowa town's residents as relatives, most people weren't too excited yet about his Presidential bid.  A14  HIGH RISK TO HISPANIC WORKERS</p>
        <p>Endangered by inexperience, ignorance of English and predatory employers, Hispanic factory workers get hurt on the job more often and more seriously than non-Hispanic Americans, researchers and officials said.  A1  NO PAROLE FOR DAHMER</p>
        <p>A judge sentenced Jeffrey Dahmer to 15 consecutive life terms in prison, making him eligible for parole only after 900 years.  A14  A TENTATIVE DREXEL DEAL</p>
        <p>Michael R. Milken has agreed to pay an additional $500 million and his former colleagues at Drexel Burnham Lambert, the Wall Street firm, have agreed to pay $300 million to settle lawsuits.  A1  MINNESOTA TACKLES HEALTH CARE</p>
        <p>Minnesota legislators said they were determined to create a universal health-care plan that would subsidize the working poor, force insurers to cover people in high-risk groups and require greater cost efficiency.  A14  KEEPING DANGERS A SECRET</p>
        <p>Court orders sealing evidence in liability, malpractice and other suits are proliferating wildly, to the dismay of some lawyers, judges and government agencies.  D10</p>
        <p>A Federal panel will gather for new hearings on breast implants.  D10  CHIEF DISMISSED IN HOUSTON</p>
        <p>The only woman to head a police force in a major American city was removed from office a little more than two years after she took over the Houston department.  A20  Neighbors of Arlo Guthrie said he misled them.  A20  Metropolitan Digest, B1 Business Digest, D1 Science Times C1-11  U.S. may be on the verge of changing its stance on climate change.  C1  Heavyweight astronomy on a featherweight budget in Georgia.  C1  Male dolphins team up to get what they want in mating.  C1  The Doctor's World: Bush's physician gets lots of advice.  C3  Sports B9-17  Olympics: U.S. and Sweden tie in hockey.  B9  Ice-dance pair from Unified Team wins.  B9  U.S. might look to courts for ski jumpers.  B10  Basketball: Knicks barely get past Heat.  B14  Seton Hall defeats Pitt.  B13  Michigan's lively freshmen.  B13  Hockey: Rangers tie Canucks in last second of regulation.  B9  Islanders beat Jets, 5-4.  B17  Obituaries D12  Les Trautmann, editor of the Staten Island Advance.</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C13-18  Berlin Film Festival.  C13  Hollywood self-portrait: ugly.  C13  Music: De La Soul.  C13  Classical Music in Review.  C14  Word and Image: Stories in the first person.  C17  Fashion Page B8  Skirts that swing.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A18-19  Editorials A18  Global snub on warming. Re-inventing debate wheel. Tuesday night live. Shrinking on garbage reform. Letters A18  A. M. Rosenthal: Running from the world.  A19  Peter Jenkins: New Hampshire -- does Europe care?  A19  Pat Oliphant: The day before the morning after.  A19  Joseph Nocera: Shut up and vote.  A19</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
