<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Candidate's Record; Brown Opened Doors but Failed to Build Coalitions</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519119"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROSS, JANE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BISHOP, KATHERINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, JERRY (EDMUND G BROWN JR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DE173DF936A35757C0A964958260" item-length="2259" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Candidate's Record; Brown Opened Doors but Failed to Build Coalitions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE GROSS with KATHERINE BISHOP,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GROSS, JANE; BISHOP, KATHERINE</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Edmund G. Brown Jr. left an unmistakable imprint on California in his two terms as Governor, with a record of far-sighted achievement when he could realize his own vision, but grand failure in matters requiring him to cooperate with other branches of government.</p>
        <p>There is broad consensus here, where the Brown legacy can still provoke emotional debate, that the Governor's greatest accomplishment was opening the doors of government to women and minorities and truly integrating the state's highest offices, boards, commissions and judiciary. Mr. Brown served from 1975 through 1982, and his appointees have put in motion pioneering air quality standards, energy conservation programs and consumer protections that became models for the rest of the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Edmund G. Brown Jr. left an unmistakable imprint on California in his two terms as Governor, with a record of far-sighted achievement when he could realize his own vision, but grand failure in matters requiring him to cooperate with other branches of government.</p>
        <p>There is broad consensus here, where the Brown legacy can still provoke emotional debate, that the Governor's greatest accomplishment was opening the doors of government to women and minorities and truly integrating the state's highest offices, boards, commissions and judiciary. Mr. Brown served from 1975 through 1982, and his appointees have put in motion pioneering air quality standards, energy conservation programs and consumer protections that became models for the rest of the nation.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the ledger, Mr. Brown is widely criticized for not heading off a taxpayers' revolt that produced Proposition 13, the ballot measure that in 1978 slashed property taxes and sent the state's finances reeling.  Had Governor Brown been more attentive to angry citizens whose property taxes were soaring at a time of huge government surplus, critics say, he might have crafted tax relief legislation that was less severe. The loss in revenue from Proposition 13 has been blamed for contributing to crumbling infrastructure, overcrowded schools and understaffed law enforcement and public health departments.</p>
        <p>"He was bold and innovative in the areas where he could just do it," said William Schneider, a political analyst at the American Enterprise Institute in Washington. "But he cannot construct a coalition. All he can say is, 'I'm right, follow me,' and that doesn't work in politics." Appointments Talent for Tapping Diverse Nominees</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown often said as Governor that the power to appoint was the most significant part of his job, and by all accounts he did it well and innovatively, with the dramatic exception of Rose Bird, an obscure lawyer with no judicial experience whom the Governor made Chief Justice of the State Supreme Court. After overturning every death sentence conviction that came before her, Ms. Bird was recalled in 1986, along with two other liberal judges appointed with her. This populist purge opened three seats on the court for the conservative appointees of Gov. George Deukmejian, Mr. Brown's Republican successor in the statehouse.</p>
        <p>Overall, Mr. Brown's appointments created what was probably the most diverse administration anywhere in the nation. According to the California Almanac, 49 percent of Mr. Brown's 6,866 executive appointments and 40 percent of his 800 judicial nominations were women or minority members.</p>
        <p>Diversity under Mr. Brown was not limited to lowly posts. Half of his Cabinet officers were women, as well as his press secretary, finance director and transportation chief. He appointed a Hispanic secretary of health and welfare and named the first two black state Supreme Court justices.</p>
        <p>Besides integrating the government, Mr. Brown brought in fresh (some would say inexperienced) faces and new (some would say crazy) ideas.</p>
        <p>In choosing judges, he bypassed the established law firms and instead reached into legal aid offices and public-interest firms. He made a former astronaut his science and technology adviser, an expert on compost toilets the state architect, a quadriplegic the chief of the Department of Rehabilitation and a beat poet the head of the Arts Commission.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown was in his element when such appointees gathered for all-night intellectual salons: government by dialectic, it was called then, with far more questions asked then answered. But the Governor's weakness as a manager and coalition builder became insidious at other times, particularly in budget- making season. Budget and Taxes Misread, Then Fed Taxpayers' Anger</p>
        <p>In 1978, as Mr. Brown ended his first term, the growing protest over taxes was exploding into a full-fledged taxpayer's revolt. The state budget surplus swelled to nearly $4 billion, fueled in part by the income tax indexing measures of Ronald Reagan's previous administration, which forced workers into ever-higher tax brackets even as their pay raises only kept up with inflation.</p>
        <p>Homeowners saw their property tax bills growing up to 50 percent a year as California housing rapidly inflated in value. For many low-income and retired people the huge tax bills threatened their very ability to remain in their homes.</p>
        <p>For all his vaunted powers as a prophet, Mr. Brown utterly failed to read the mood of the public accurately and work with the Legislature toward a solution.</p>
        <p>As an organized effort grew to place a property tax-cutting measure, Proposition 13, on the June 1978 ballot, Mr. Brown remained convinced it would not pass and proposed more unusual solutions, like a 55 percent tax credit to homeowners who installed solar heating.</p>
        <p>Belatedly, Mr. Brown joined in supporting an alternative to Proposition 13 that would have offered partial property tax rebates. The voters defeated it and passed Proposition 13 by 65 percent. Spent Surplus on Schools</p>
        <p>With Proposition 13 a fait accompli, Mr. Brown directed $2.2 billion of the state surplus to the schools and $1.85 million to the counties and cities as emergency relief, actions which make it possible for him to accurately make the campaign claim today that taxes were cut and financing for schools increased in his administration.</p>
        <p>But seeing that government's response to their demands for limits was resulting in a handout of the surplus, voters rose up again in 1979. They passed another ballot measure that placed a lid on government spending, tying it to inflation and forcing government to receive voter approval for increased taxes.</p>
        <p>Because the state constitution grants the governor the power to veto appropriations, Mr. Brown was eventually able to slash $2 billion from various budgets. But overall, state spending increased by nearly 120 percent during the Brown years after Proposition 13, even as the measure pushed down the individual state taxpayer's burden from $158 per thousand of taxable income in 1978 to $108 per thousand when Mr. Brown left office in 1982.</p>
        <p>By that time, Proposition 13 had cut average property tax rates to $1.13 per $100 of assessed valuation in 1982 from $11.24 per $100 in 1972, and forced $7 billion in spending cuts. The budget surplus had evaporated into a deficit of more than $1 billion and the state's general fund reserve had fallen from nearly $2 billion to zero. The unemployment rate, worsened by a national recession, had risen to a record high of 9.9 percent.</p>
        <p>Today, over a decade after Mr. Brown left office, the state faces a budget deficit of more than $14 billion, county governments are on the verge of bankruptcy and homeowners face wildly disparate property tax levels, depending on whether they bought their homes before or after Proposition 13 was passed. Policy Much Innovation, But Some Setbacks</p>
        <p>On policy matters, Mr. Brown's record is quirky, reflective of a man with a pattern of becoming absorbed in one issue to the neglect of all others. He was strongest, experts agree, on environmental and energy matters, far ahead of other states and setting a model for regulation and legislation elsewhere.</p>
        <p>During the Brown years, California tightened air quality standards, which cut pollution by 25 percent and forced Detroit automakers to design new exhaust systems for the nation's largest car market.</p>
        <p>Also, through tax incentives and tough action by his apointees to the Energy Commission and the Public Utilities Commisssion, Mr. Brown encouraged alternative, renewable energy sources, like generating electricity by burning industrial waste and woodchips and by using windmills, which now dot the California landscape. The Energy Commission he created also blocked construction of new nuclear power plants.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Brown's most widely respected monuments is the California Conservation Corps, which put men and women to work, New Deal-style, fighting fires and floods, restoring streambeds and the like.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Brown had one notable collision with environmental groups, involving the notorious Mediterranean fruit fly, which infested farms and orchards in the state late in his second term. Pressed from both sides, by environmentalists who predicted disaster if there was aerial pesticide spraying, and by farmers who predicted economic doom, Mr. Brown dragged his feet and the pesky medfly wrecked havoc. Finally, he authorized the spraying, but by then had lost friends on both sides of the issue, and it weighed heavily in his 1982 race for a Senate seat, when Mr. Brown took a thumping at the hands of Pete Wilson. Union for Farm Workers</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown's most heralded legislative success, early in his administration, gave farm workers organizing and bargaining rights for the first time in United States history. Prodded by his friend, Cesar Chavez, leader of the United Farmworkers Union, Mr. Brown ended a decade of boycotts and bloodshed in the lettuce and grape fields by pushing through a bill establishing the Agriculture Labor Relations Board, which supervised union elections.</p>
        <p>Analysts suggest that Mr. Brown was weakest in the areas where his father had earlier made his mark as a two-term governor. Edmund G. (Pat) Brown, an affable man who led the state from 1959 to 1967, is best known here as the master builder of California's highway, university and water systems. His son, by contrast, preached "small is beautiful" and is widely faulted for letting highways decay and cutting public education budgets early in his administration.</p>
        <p>An examination of Mr. Brown's record involving highways and education indicates that he was more hostile in word than in deed, although hardly a champion of either roads or schools.</p>
        <p>Consistent with his ideas about the environment and energy, the Governor sought to de-emphasize the automobile. Some new highways were built in Mr. Brown's tenure, apparently on the drawing board from the Reagan Administration, but older highways deteriorated. The Governor focused instead on modest mass transit projects, including a few commuter train lines, a trolley across the Mexican border and a fleet of experimental state cars that ran on methanol. Ahead of His Time</p>
        <p>A major dispute of Mr. Brown's tenure involved a proposal to put car pool lanes on the Santa Monica Freeway, an experiment that was stalled by public protest. As with many ideas, including the proposed launching of a state telecommunications satellite, Mr. Brown was a few years ahead of his time. The so-called diamond lanes, then considered a heretical encroachment on motorists' rights, are now an accepted part of life here.</p>
        <p>Public education fared poorly in the Brown years, even before the stringencies of Proposition 13 and a series of court rulings that altered education spending formulas. Mr. Brown threatened early to squeeze school budgets to inspire "reform." When asked what he had in mind, the Governor said, "I don't know yet" and never clarified the issue. California slipped from 18th to 31st nationally in per pupil school financing.</p>
        <p>At the university level, Governor Brown froze faculty salaries, arguing that professors were compensated by their "psychic income."</p>
        <p>The journalistic record of the Brown administration reveals little about the Governor's health policy, which was not a looming issue then as it is now. So, too, on crime the Brown years were relatively quiescent. The Governor signed several tough bills regarding mandatory prison terms for certain serious crimes. As a result, the number of felons sent to prison each year more than doubled in the Brown years. Political Record  As Popularity Fell, G.O.P. Gained Entry</p>
        <p>Some people say the singular contribution Mr. Brown made in state office was a political reorganization measure that was passed by voters here in the same year they elected him Governor. The Political Reform Act of 1974, while far from inclusive, fundamentally changed the nature of politics in the state capitol of Sacramento by limiting the influence of lobbyists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, then Secretary of State, was the act's principal author and touted it as the "two hamburgers and a Coke" measure. He rode to victory on a tide of post-Watergate disgust with politics as usual. Political observers here note, with a sense of deja vu, that the passage of the act depended on Mr. Brown's gift for galvanizing angry voters and showed him to be an effective agent for change, outside the confines of executive office.</p>
        <p>Much of the criticism of Mr. Brown's tenure as Governor involves style more than substance, although it was style that many people say impeded his ability to govern. People who worked with him say he had a difficult personality.</p>
        <p>The citizens of California also lost patience and changed from adoring to bemused to downright unhappy about their Governor. Fourteen months into his first term, according to The California Poll, Mr. Brown's job performance was rated as excellent or fair by 85 percent of those polled. When he left office in 1982, that approval rating had dropped to 58 percent.</p>
        <p>Shortly thereafter, with Mr. Brown as the opponent, California voters elected Mr. Wilson to the United States Senate. The governor's chair was filled by Mr. Deukmejian. Mr. Schneider of the American Enterprise Institute said, "Jerry Brown was so disliked in his home state that he elected two Republicans on the same day and singlehandedly created a fashion for boring politicians."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
