<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Striving for Balance</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D9153DF937A15756C0A964958260" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Striving for Balance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Weak and wobbly though it may be in some ways, the treaty on preserving the world's biological species adopted on Friday in Nairobi, Kenya, is being characterized by some conservationists as a bona fide breakthrough in dealing with the central problem to be addressed at next week's Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro: how to accommodate economic development without damaging the planet's life support system.</p>
        <p>As the global economy expands and the population of developing countries soars, humans are destroying natural ecosystems and habitats at a rate that some biologists fear will result in the extinction of perhaps a quarter of the world's plant, animal and microbial species in the next 50 years. The organisms are part of the interdependent web of life vital to all species, including Homo sapiens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Weak and wobbly though it may be in some ways, the treaty on preserving the world's biological species adopted on Friday in Nairobi, Kenya, is being characterized by some conservationists as a bona fide breakthrough in dealing with the central problem to be addressed at next week's Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro: how to accommodate economic development without damaging the planet's life support system.</p>
        <p>As the global economy expands and the population of developing countries soars, humans are destroying natural ecosystems and habitats at a rate that some biologists fear will result in the extinction of perhaps a quarter of the world's plant, animal and microbial species in the next 50 years. The organisms are part of the interdependent web of life vital to all species, including Homo sapiens.</p>
        <p>Now, for the first time, 98 nations have taken formal steps to deal with the situation. The United States, Japan and perhaps other countries object to some aspects of the agreement and may not sign it, but if 30 or more countries ratify the treaty it will take effect and be binding on them. 'Breaks New Ground'</p>
        <p>The treaty aims to reconcile the twin imperatives of economic development and the protection of species and ecosystems. It "is the first attempt to marry the two concepts in practice," said Richard Mott, the treaties officer of the World Wildlife Fund, who attended the Nairobi talks. "It is a treaty that truly breaks new ground. It will not put an end to the extinction of plant and animal species overnight, but it is the first attempt by governments to tackle the problem at its root causes in a systematic manner."</p>
        <p>The treaty, he said, also institutionalizes a new concept that many conservationists are beginning to embrace: conservation will fail unless it is integrated with human activity.</p>
        <p>The agreement was reached after two weeks of talks that turned chaotic near the end because of pressure to have the treaty ready for heads of state to sign in Rio. The biodiversity treaty is one of two pillars of the summit; the other, a treaty committing its ratifiers to stablize emissions of gases believed to cause global warming, was negotiated earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Critics say both cases represent a lowest-common-demoninator approach to the problem and therefore fall far short of the ideal. But many experts, including some critics, also say that each nevertheless establishes a framework that could provide the basis for dealing with the two global problems over the long term. Commits Nations to Act</p>
        <p>The biodiversity treaty commits nations that ratify it to take actions aimed at preserving species and ecosystems while pursuing economic development and attacking poverty.</p>
        <p>The nations would develop national strategies to integrate conservation into their planning in the hope that species and ecosystem protection would become an everyday component of economic and social policy. They would also set up protected areas, promote the protection of whole ecosystems as well as individual species, manage biological resources with the aim of protecting them both inside and outside formal preserves and restore degraded ecosystems.</p>
        <p>The treaty requires countries to inventory and monitor their biological assets and calls for signers to meet periodically to assess progress. They could take further action if necessary.</p>
        <p>While most of the concern about species protection has been voiced by the rich industrialized nations, most of the species themselves are found in the developing countries of the tropics, where economic survival is by far the top preoccupation. So the specific conservation actions required are hedged about with qualifiers like "as far as possible" and "as appropriate." Helping Poor Countries</p>
        <p>The treaty says conservation should take fully into account that economic and social development and the eradication of poverty are the first priority of the developing countries. It says that any conservation efforts they undertake will depend on the flow of money from rich nations. And it calls for the poorer, species-rich countries to reap a fair share of the profits when enterprises in rich countries exploit their biological resources.</p>
        <p>"There will be those who will say the convention is too weak, barely addressing the magnitude of the threat to the global web of life," said Dr. Mostafa K. Tolba, executive director of the United Nations Environment Program, under whose auspices the treaty was negotiated. But, he said, "the process of international environmental law requires us, for better or for worse, to walk before we can run and to crawl before we walk."</p>
        <p>As precedent, he cited the 1985 Vienna treaty -- "not strong in itself" -- that established a process and framework for dealing with depletion of the earth's protective ozone layer. That treaty later led to a series of later measures that have culminated in the banning the production of ozone-destroying chemicals.</p>
        <p>The United States, which had pressed for strong conservation measures in the talks, would have preferred stronger measures than those that emerged, said E. U. Curtis Bohlen the Assistant Secretary of State for the Environment. But it is on other grounds that the United States is expressing serious doubts about whether it will sign the treaty. Worries on U.S. Patents</p>
        <p>For instance, he said, it fails to give adequate patent protection to American companies that transfer biotechnology to developing countries, it leaves unclear the long-term mechanism for transferring money to the poor nations and it tries to regulate genetically engineered materials, a competitive area in which the United States leads.</p>
        <p>Historically, conservationists have set aside nature preserves and let nature take its course. Despite this, species loss and ecosystem damage have continued apace. The new treaty, Mr. Mott of the World Wildlife Fund said, makes it incumbent on the signers to develop and promote conservation projects that combine both conservation and development goals. Such measures might include, for instance, the environmentally friendly and potentially lucrative exploitation of forests for medicine, food and tourism.</p>
        <p>Dr. Tolba of the United Nations said described the treaty as a "two-way street." If either the rich countries or the poor countries renege on their part of the bargain, he said, it will fail.</p>
        <p>How well it is carried out, Mr. Mott said, "is part of a great experiment in finding ways to bring human activity into balance with nature."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
