<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>He Doesn't Call Them Dirty Deals</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="528336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1990</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TENNESSEE VALLEY AUTHORITY AND PROJECT (TVA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WISCONSIN POWER &amp; LIGHT CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HENRY, JOHN B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D71030F930A25756C0A964958260" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>He Doesn't Call Them Dirty Deals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many entrepreneurs have tried to pull off emissions-trading deals under the acid rain provisions of the Clean Air Act of 1990. Apparently the first to be successful, with the agreement between the Tennessee Valley Authority and Wisconsin Power and Light, is a small Washington-based investment banking firm, Clean Air Capital Markets, established by John B. Henry 2d shortly after passage of the act.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henry, 43 years old, said in a telephone interview that his approach was different from many competitors, who were acting as consultants. He is an investment banker, paid only if a deal is signed. He did not disclose the fee for the T.V.A.-Wisconsin deal, but said he and his partners had spent more than $1 million "establishing the franchise," or setting themselves up to arrange such deals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Many entrepreneurs have tried to pull off emissions-trading deals under the acid rain provisions of the Clean Air Act of 1990. Apparently the first to be successful, with the agreement between the Tennessee Valley Authority and Wisconsin Power and Light, is a small Washington-based investment banking firm, Clean Air Capital Markets, established by John B. Henry 2d shortly after passage of the act.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henry, 43 years old, said in a telephone interview that his approach was different from many competitors, who were acting as consultants. He is an investment banker, paid only if a deal is signed. He did not disclose the fee for the T.V.A.-Wisconsin deal, but said he and his partners had spent more than $1 million "establishing the franchise," or setting themselves up to arrange such deals.</p>
        <p>The size of the potential market is huge; by Mr. Henry's calculation, if all the emission reductions were achieved by trades -- which is unlikely -- the value would equal one-third the capitalization of all the companies on the American Stock Exchange. "We're not shooting mice here," he said. "It's an elephant hunt." Making Them Cringe</p>
        <p>Mr. Henry and others in the field cringe at the idea that utilities are buying the right to pollute. "Utilities are buying clean air," he said. No utility would rely exclusively on allowance purchases, rather than cleaning itself up, he said; for one thing, that would be politically impossible.</p>
        <p>But if buying allowances is cheaper than cutting emissions, then utilities should buy, to help hold their rates down, he said. Electric rates increased by environmental requirements are like a regressive tax, Mr. Henry believes, falling more heavily on the poor.</p>
        <p>A second such deal was announced yesterday by Wisconsin Power; the company said that in addition to T.V.A., it was also selling allowances to the Duquesne Light Company, with headquarters in Pittsburgh. Mr. Henry was not involved in that deal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henry, a graduate of Columbia Law School, describes Clean Air Capital Markets as his second environmental company. From 1981 to 1990 he was chief executive of Crop Genetics International, an agricultural biotechnology company traded over-the-counter.</p>
        <p>Clean Air Capital Markets' vice president is Ernest G. Ellingson, formerly in charge of strategic planning at Georgia Power. The company's lawyer is Andrew D. Weissman, who specializes in air pollution law.</p>
        <p>While economists have hailed the emissions trading concept, utilities, which are inherently conservative, have been slow to warm to the concept. "They have an extraordinary bias to on-system compliance, cleaning up your own system," he said. One reason, he said, is that each utility has a fuel department, which would handle the arrangements if the company chose fuel-switching, an engineering staff that would negotiate with companies that install scrubbers or other pollution control equipment.  But, he said, "generally there are no constituents inside for buying compliance outside your own system."</p>
        <p>But buying allowances is the most conservative option, he argued. "What a scrubber really is, is a decision to buy a 30-year stream of allowances," he said, meaning that the scrubber would generate emission reductions for that long. But if the scrubber went into service in 1995 and ran until 2025, he said, that committed the utility to that option for all those years. If the price of allowances declines in future years, he said, the scrubber would look like a bad buy.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
