<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEGOTIATORS IN RIO AGREE TO INCREASE AID TO THIRD WORLD</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="535996"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE EARTH SUMMIT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB113FF937A25755C0A964958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEGOTIATORS IN RIO AGREE TO INCREASE AID TO THIRD WORLD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less than 24 hours before the end of the Earth Summit, North and South finally compromised today on principles that encourage richer countries to increase aid to the third world, clearing the way for formal approval of the global cleanup plan that is the centerpiece of the conference.</p>
        <p>After 13 days of negotiations, third-world countries finally abandoned their campaign to extract a specific commitment from the industrialized world to nearly double aid to poorer countries by the year 2000. The money would help guarantee that the third world's development is environmentally sound. The compromise, worked out in a small group and approved in an informal general session this evening, will be formally adopted on Sunday. Accepting U.S. Position</p>
        <p>Under the compromise, instead of pressing their demands for precise commitments of money, the third-world countries accepted that the United States was unwilling to be bound by a longstanding United Nations goal of raising aid levels to 0.7 percent of a country's economic output and that Britain, Japan, Germany and several other big aid donors refuse to commit themselves to that target by any particular date.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less than 24 hours before the end of the Earth Summit, North and South finally compromised today on principles that encourage richer countries to increase aid to the third world, clearing the way for formal approval of the global cleanup plan that is the centerpiece of the conference.</p>
        <p>After 13 days of negotiations, third-world countries finally abandoned their campaign to extract a specific commitment from the industrialized world to nearly double aid to poorer countries by the year 2000. The money would help guarantee that the third world's development is environmentally sound. The compromise, worked out in a small group and approved in an informal general session this evening, will be formally adopted on Sunday. Accepting U.S. Position</p>
        <p>Under the compromise, instead of pressing their demands for precise commitments of money, the third-world countries accepted that the United States was unwilling to be bound by a longstanding United Nations goal of raising aid levels to 0.7 percent of a country's economic output and that Britain, Japan, Germany and several other big aid donors refuse to commit themselves to that target by any particular date.</p>
        <p>President Bush left the conference defending his environmental record and the Administration's stance on the major treaties at the Earth Summit, saying Americans are "the leaders, not the followers," on environmental issues and will be "pre-eminent" in carrying out accords signed at the conference.  [ Page 10. ] Japan Vows Leading Role</p>
        <p>Japan, too, made a promise today to "play a leading role" in future world pollution control. Japan's Prime Minister, Kiichi Miyazawa, in a speech circulated here, promised to increase foreign aid for environmental projects and embrace pollution control as a scientific challenge. He did not join the other leaders gathered here because of debates in Japan's Parliament.</p>
        <p>Japan's environmental aid will average $1.45 billion a year, compared with the $1 billion level of the last three years. Japan now contributes 0.3 percent of its gross domestic product.</p>
        <p>In today's unusual North-South exchange, one of the rare occasions on which the third world enjoyed genuine leverage, the industrialized Northern countries committed themselves to reach the 0.7 percent target "as soon as possible" and pledged to see that the environmental goals in the plan, known as Agenda 21, are fully met. Implicit in the compromise is that the North must find more money for the third world.</p>
        <p>The agreement notes that the planned Commission on Sustainable Development will monitor progress toward the aid target. And it says that a "review process" should "systematically combine the monitoring of implementation of Agenda 21 with the review of the financial resources available for such implementation."</p>
        <p>Although the third-world countries accepted the compromise, they have serious reservations about the success of Agenda 21 without specific commitments of money. On Sunday, during the concluding session, Pakistan, the current chairman of the Group of 77, as the third-world countries are known at United Nations meetings, will express the bloc's disappointment at the financial offers the North has made so far. A Warning on Financing</p>
        <p>And Pakistan will implicitly remind the North that it cannot significantly improve the environment without Southern cooperation. The statement will warn that without the additional assistance, the developing South will be unable to develop in an environmentally sound manner.</p>
        <p>"We are saying we cannot generate the new resources needed to start up Agenda 21 without new help, so if the North wants us to meet those goals they must treat us more generously," Pakistan's United Nations representative, Jamsheed A. Marker said.</p>
        <p>Third-world countries say they are owed that assistance because the developed Northern nations are responsible for most of the damage industrialization has inflicted on ecological systems so far. Third-world countries say the North should be willing to pay for the limits it has imposed on the development of poorer countries.</p>
        <p>Other countries have their objections as well. Britain, Germany, Spain, Portugal, Greece and Ireland are reluctant to commit themselves to reach the target by the year 2000, saying it would be unrealistic. Germany also said it wanted the summit meeting to acknowledge that it faces an exceptional financial burden as a result of unification, which leaves it short of funds for the third world. That irritates developing countries that have long feared that Communism's collapse would divert Western aid to Eastern Europe.</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia is continuing to object to passages in Agenda 21 that commit the world to save oil by using such "economic measures" as carbon energy taxes. Saudi Arabia, backed by several other oil producers including Kuwait, Iran and Libya, argue that those pledges, which threaten to reduce demand for their oil, are no longer necessary now that the Earth Summit has approved a new convention on stabilizing the atmosphere by curbing emissions of warming gases created by burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Western and most third-world countries oppose the Saudi stand and many delegates say that if Saudi Arabia persists in its opposition it may be voted down at Sunday's closing session.</p>
        <p>Delegates also agreed today to give "special consideration" to a proposal put forward by the World Bank president, Lewis T. Preston, to replenish the International Development Agency, which lends on favorable terms to the poorest countries, at a level of $18 billion over the next three years and to add an "earth increment" of about $5 billion to provide inexpensive loans for environmental projects.</p>
        <p>But they refused to give any specific commitment to adopt the World Bank president's proposals as the Group of 77 has demanded, saying that to do so would prejudice the outcome of the separate replenishment negotiations scheduled for next month in Dublin.</p>
        <p>The 12 European Community countries have also said they will provide about $4 billion in environmental financing to insure that Agenda 21 gets off to a quick start in the third world, but it remains unclear how much new money is included in that offer.</p>
        <p>THE EARTH SUMMIT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
