<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Art Slips on Thin Ice</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506158"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCULPTURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CENTRAL PARK (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sculpture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DC1239F93BA35751C0A964958260" item-length="696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Art Slips on Thin Ice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The chainsaws were buzzing, the planers were planing away the rough spots, the measuring tapes were measuring. Finally, a week late, 35 Chinese ice sculptors were stacking and shaping their giant see-through bricks into two giant melting phoenixes.</p>
        <p>Creating a pair of birds like the one in ancient Egyptian mythology that consumed itself in fire only to rise from its own ashes, was somehow the right metaphor for a group of artists whose uncertain path to Central Park had been paved with a series of "if onlys": If only the import-export company in New York that promised to pay their way had not gone out of business. If only their tools had not been impounded by customs agents at Kennedy International Airport. And if only it hadn't been so unbearably warm yesterday in Central Park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The chainsaws were buzzing, the planers were planing away the rough spots, the measuring tapes were measuring. Finally, a week late, 35 Chinese ice sculptors were stacking and shaping their giant see-through bricks into two giant melting phoenixes.</p>
        <p>Creating a pair of birds like the one in ancient Egyptian mythology that consumed itself in fire only to rise from its own ashes, was somehow the right metaphor for a group of artists whose uncertain path to Central Park had been paved with a series of "if onlys": If only the import-export company in New York that promised to pay their way had not gone out of business. If only their tools had not been impounded by customs agents at Kennedy International Airport. And if only it hadn't been so unbearably warm yesterday in Central Park.</p>
        <p>So maybe this is a story about global warming. Then again, maybe not. One man carrying cross-country skis looked across the Great Lawn yesterday and suggested that the too-warm sculptors should simply peel off a layer of underwear.</p>
        <p>"In our hometown," responded Anna Wong, a three-year ice-sculpting veteran of the group from Harbin, an industrial city and river port about 800 miles northeast of Beijing, "the temperature is 20 below, Fahrenheit. No, centigrade. No, Fahrenheit."</p>
        <p>Whatever. It has not been a bleak midwinter in New York. To borrow a line or two from the poet Christina G. Rossetti, there hasn't been much frosty wind moaning. The earth hasn't been as hard as iron, and the water hasn't been like a stone. "Danger -- thin ice," read the sign at the edge of the pond below Belvedere Castle, a few steps from where the ice sculptors were at work.</p>
        <p>But even in the see-your-breath cold of a 34-degree afternoon, the sculptors had that frustrated look. There they were, masters of an ephemeral medium, carvers who can transform ice into structures with the near-permanence and perfection lacking in a front-lawn Frosty the Snowman. They are keepers of fanciful creatures and snowy flowers, pavilions and frozen tableaus from Chinese legends, strutting peacocks and erupting volcanos. And there they were, shedding their jackets while New Yorkers shivered. Pagodas and Towers of Ice</p>
        <p>Miss Wong pulled out photographs of pagodas they had built in Canada and towers they had built in Hong Kong. The elaborate architecture was enough to trigger a reader's long memory into summoning up the belle in an F. Scott Fitzgerald short story who kept repeating this rhyme: "It was a miracle of rare device, a sunny pleasure-dome with caves of ice."</p>
        <p>Looking across the landscape, out beyond the nearly barren expanse of the Great Lawn, Miss Wong said it would be a snap to build that kind of pleasure dome, an ice palace as tall as the San Remo, the apartment building with the twin towers at Central Park West and 73d Street. But it was too warm for a building that tall, and there were other problems.</p>
        <p>"No fork lift," she said. "No scaffold."</p>
        <p>The group's improbable journey from northern China to Manhattan began when the trading company called the Parks Department, which was planning a winter festival, and offered to pay for their trip. Chris Wangro, a Parks Department official planning the festival, said a figure of $50,000 was mentioned. He asked if the trading company intended to donate that in a way that would cover the sculptors' expenses.</p>
        <p>"They said, 'No, $50,000 for your personal account.' "</p>
        <p>End of conversation, he said. And end of the ice escapade until a couple of weeks ago, when the official heard that the sculptors were in New York after all and that the trading company had gone out of business. He started lining up corporate sponsors. What with weather that, even by New York standards, was warm last week, he sent them to a place that felt more like home and where a week in a hotel was cheaper: Platkill, N.Y., near Newburgh.</p>
        <p>Then, after returning to Manhattan yesterday, Miss Wong discovered another if only: If only people came to Central Park at night.</p>
        <p>"We put lights into the sculpture," she said. "They say no visitors come to Central Park at night, so we canceled the light. But I think pure light from the moon is better."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
