<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Political Memo; Pulling Punches on the Environment</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SURO, ROBERTO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDA1430F936A35753C1A964958260" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Political Memo; Pulling Punches on the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTO SURO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SURO, ROBERTO</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON, Wis., Oct. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mounds of radioactive dirt and heaps of old plastic milk jugs often turn up as backdrops for the speeches of Senator Al Gore because he puts more emphasis on environmental issues than anyone else who has ever run for national office.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Gore is pulling his punches on the environment as he campaigns for Vice President. He knows that he is doing it. He readily admits that he is doing it, and he says that sound political judgment requires it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mounds of radioactive dirt and heaps of old plastic milk jugs often turn up as backdrops for the speeches of Senator Al Gore because he puts more emphasis on environmental issues than anyone else who has ever run for national office.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Gore is pulling his punches on the environment as he campaigns for Vice President. He knows that he is doing it. He readily admits that he is doing it, and he says that sound political judgment requires it.</p>
        <p>"I am making the environment the single most prominent part of my campaign message," he said in an interview this week, speaking slowly and carefully. "I am doing my best to elevate it to a position it has never before had in national politics, but I have a responsibility to do more than that beside. My focus in these next 30-some-odd days is to do everything I can to help Bill Clinton win this election, and that means delivering a broader message as well."</p>
        <p>Near the beginning of his best-selling book, "Earth in the Balance," Mr. Gore says he, like other politicians, was guilty of "failures of candor" about environmental issues. During his unsuccessful Presidential campaign in 1988, he said, "I simply lacked the strength to keep on talking about the environment" in the face of a lack of interest from the reporters and advice from poll takers that it did not play as an issue. Book Rarely Mentioned</p>
        <p>These days the 393-page book is often mentioned by speakers who introduce him to crowds as a famous defender of the environment, but in his own speeches the Senator rarely mentions the book's central theme: mankind, he argues, is destroying the earth and only fundamental changes in human civilization will save it.</p>
        <p>On the stump, the Tennessee Senator never discusses many of the book's specific proposals, like a tax on fossil fuels based on how much carbon dioxide each releases into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>These are the ideas that Republicans seize on when they denounce Mr. Gore as an environmental extremist. Campaigning in Michigan last week, President Bush said the Democrats' proposals for stringent automobile fuel-efficiency standards "would toss 40,000 auto workers out on the unemployment lines."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore insists that the environmental issue is working to the Democrats' advantage.</p>
        <p>"Bush sounds schizophrenic every time he opens his mouth on the environment," Mr. Gore said. "He can't attack me on the environment without in the same breath claiming to be environmentally sensitive."</p>
        <p>When Mr. Gore explains why he is toning down his environmental message, he looks far beyond the November election.</p>
        <p>"I said in my book that the maximum that is politically feasible today still falls short of the minimum of what is really effective in solving the global crisis, but that doesn't lead me to hopelessness and despair," he said. "It just leads me to the conclusion that we have to patiently and effectively expand the definition of what is politically feasible, and that is part of the reason I'm in this campaign."</p>
        <p>The subtle message has gotten through to at least some of his readers. Maureen Flynn waited several hours on a cold sidewalk in Hartford, Conn., on Wednesday, so Mr. Gore could autograph her copy of the book. "I wouldn't use the word radical to describe what he says because he's talking about plans not just for right now but for the future," she said.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gore is confident that his running mate understands.</p>
        <p>"Bill Clinton endorses the general thrust and the central premise of my book," the Senator said, "but I have not, and would not, ask him to endorse every detail of the plan that I propose." The Presidential candidate has not adopted all of Mr. Gore's tax proposals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore closely coordinates his efforts with the Clinton campaign, and there is a distinct note of deference towards the Governor when he talks about their proposals in areas like health care or student loans.</p>
        <p>But on the environment, it is clear he speaks on his own authority, at least within an agreed-upon agenda. When the running mates appeared here together on Thursday night on "Rockline," a call-in interview program broadcast by college radio stations, it was Mr. Clinton who deferred on this subject. An Environmental Theme</p>
        <p>Almost every day Mr. Gore travels to some kind of campaign event built around an environmental theme. One day this week he extolled the virtues of a recycling plant near Scranton, Pa., and the next morning he deplored the pollution caused by a former atomic weapons factory near Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>These appearances usually revolve around three criteria, he said. A grass-roots environmental group is involved. Or jobs are being created by environmental action. Or lastly, as he put it, "I am following the trail of broken promises the 'environmental President' has left all over the country."</p>
        <p>His speeches start out on local matters and then become an indictment of the Bush Administration's environmental policies, but they rarely proceed to more than a brief mention of what his book calls strategic environmental issues, like global warming, that affect the entire planet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore seems increasingly confident this will change.</p>
        <p>"In the debate about the environment, the most basic argument is still in play: do we shift our basic attitudes or not?" he said. "We have a direct conflict with Bush and Quayle on that question. If we win that argument, and we are in the midst of winning it big time, then we have the basis for moving the debate to the next level of detail. Then we can start looking at the best way of achieving our goals."</p>
        <p>Beyond its sweeping policy proposals, Mr. Gore's book argues for a deeply personal, almost spiritual change in attitude toward the planet. It is a measure of Mr. Gore's growing confidence that this theme is now starting to appear in his speeches.</p>
        <p>Late Thursday night after four hours of appearances before big, enthusiastic crowds around Madison, Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore addressed more than 1,000 people in a darkened courtyard on the University of Wisconsin campus here. Starkly illuminated by television lights, each delivered impromptu and emotional speeches. When Mr. Gore finally hit on the theme of his book, the crowd roared with approval:</p>
        <p>"What this election is about," he said, "is developing a new understanding of yourself and how you relate to your community and how you relate to the earth."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
