<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Vows Action to Cut U.S. Global Warming Gases</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDD1630F93BA15751C0A964958260" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Vows Action to Cut U.S. Global Warming Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Feb. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush Administration said today that it was taking actions that would significantly limit the United States' contribution to global warming and help developing countries address the problem.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists said the statement could lead to an agreement between the United States and the European Community on an issue that has deadlocked talks here on global warming: whether industrialized countries should commit themselves to stabilizing carbon dioxide emissions at 1990 levels by the year 2000 as the first step toward ultimately reducing them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush Administration said today that it was taking actions that would significantly limit the United States' contribution to global warming and help developing countries address the problem.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists said the statement could lead to an agreement between the United States and the European Community on an issue that has deadlocked talks here on global warming: whether industrialized countries should commit themselves to stabilizing carbon dioxide emissions at 1990 levels by the year 2000 as the first step toward ultimately reducing them.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide, methane and other gases, whose atmospheric concentrations are growing as a result of human activity, trap heat in the atmosphere.  Scientists fear that this could lead to a catastrophic warming of the earth in the 21st century.</p>
        <p>The talks are aimed at producing a multinational treaty on steps to contain global warming that would be signed at a meeting called the "Earth Summit" in Rio de Janeiro in June. U.S. Opposes Goals</p>
        <p>The Europeans have been insisting on the year 2000 deadline for stabilizing emissions of carbon dioxide, the chief heat-trapping gas, while the Americans have been resisting any targets and timetables. But Robert A. Reinstein, the chief American negotiator at the talks, told delegates from around the world that the measures he listed would produce limits on heat-trapping gases that "compare favorably" with those planned by European countries.</p>
        <p>Most of the American measures are being undertaken for reasons other than global warming, like improving energy efficiency and reducing ground-level air pollution. But they also reduce emissions of carbon dioxide, which is produced by the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil. Some of the main energy efficiency measures are included in the energy bill that has just passed the Senate but has not yet been acted on in the House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reinstein listed several dozen measures that he said together would significantly reduce emissions. The measures include strengthened efficiency standards for appliances and equipment; incentives for electric utilities to improve efficiency rather than build coal power plants; increasing Federal purchases of alternative-fuel vehicles; capturing methane from landfills; planting more trees, which absorb carbon dioxide, and establishing voluntary public-private programs to install more efficient lighting.</p>
        <p>If the measures do result in carbon dioxide reductions comparable to those planned by the Europeans, it would put the Europeans and the Americans "in the same ballpark" in the negotiations, said Rafe Pomerance of the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based environmental organization. The present round of negotiations ends Friday, but substantive talks concluded today. A final session before the Rio de Janeiro conference is tentatively scheduled to start on April 30 in either New York or Geneva.</p>
        <p>The United States also announced today that it would unilaterally provide $75 million to help developing countries deal with emissions of the heat-trapping gases. Some delegates from developing countries, while reserving ultimate judgment, noted with approval that the United States was reversing a position in which it had opposed the principle of aid. Emissions caps and finances have been the central issues at the talks.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists reacted to the American statement with qualified approval. "At least we now have a signal that people at high levels in the White House are beginning to think about how to limit global warming, and that's a good sign," said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, a climate expert with the Environmental Defense Fund. "But if it's the last thing we hear out of the Administration on global warming," he said, "then it's a sham."</p>
        <p>The head of the British delegation, Dr. David Fisk, said the American announcement "was received by everyone as a very encouraging first step." But, he said, "We want to hear more."</p>
        <p>Daniel F. Becker, a global-warming expert for the Sierra Club, said the measures described by Mr. Reinstein were still subject to testing. But "it is really clear that the President has abandoned the Flat Earth Society approach to global warming," he said, "and for that we should all be happy."</p>
        <p>The American initiative comes in a political year when environmentalists are casting the talks as a litmus test of the Administration's ability to show leadership on global environmental issues. All five major Democratic Presidential candidates have endorsed the European position on targets and timetables for carbon dioxide reduction, and Mr. Bush would be open for harsh criticism if the United States were perceived as torpedoing the treaty.</p>
        <p>Industry groups praised the Administration's move. "I think the U.S. is putting its money where its mouth is," said John Shlaes, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition.</p>
        <p>The coalition, which consists of trade associations, supports a policy in which steps taken to limit emissions of the gases also have other benefits, like controlling ground-level air pollution or achieving greater energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>The measures listed by Mr. Reinstein fit that description. The Administration would focus on a policy of "do-able" actions that "have whatever results they have," he said.</p>
        <p>"If it achieves stabilization, that's wonderful."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
