<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Worriers Vs. Wallowers</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GELB, LESLIE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1F3EF933A25751C0A964958260" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Worriers Vs. Wallowers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE H. GELB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GELB, LESLIE H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environmentalists are saying that the Bush Administration will do nothing about gases dangerously warming the planet. And Administration officials are saying that it is the environmentalists who are full of impractical hot air.</p>
        <p>While the warming worriers are demanding urgent action, the officials are wrestling with -- and alas, wallowing in -- the practical problems of doing something.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Environmentalists are saying that the Bush Administration will do nothing about gases dangerously warming the planet. And Administration officials are saying that it is the environmentalists who are full of impractical hot air.</p>
        <p>While the warming worriers are demanding urgent action, the officials are wrestling with -- and alas, wallowing in -- the practical problems of doing something.</p>
        <p>Too bad for us all that President Bush is not knocking their talented heads together. Yoked to common purpose, they could make extraordinary contributions to the critical working session of the U.N. "Earth Summit" in New York next week.</p>
        <p>With ominous news of the ozone layer depleting faster than expected, Mr. Bush managed to reverse himself last week and accept Senate plans to phase out the offending gases. But on greenhouse gases, he stands by as the warring parties continue to spend more time proselytizing baffled journalists than talking to each other about viable solutions.</p>
        <p>The first point warming worriers make is that science sits on their side. Experts generally do agree that greenhouse gases, mainly carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels, are trapping heat and warming the earth's temperature. How warm and how fast are arguable matters, but scientists are alarmed now.</p>
        <p>The worriers, led by the governments of Western Europe and Japan, have a two-point plan. They call for setting targets and timetables (T.&amp; T.) for reducing CO2 , principally by conserving energy. And they propose giving money to poorer countries to make environmental measures affordable along with economic development.</p>
        <p>The U.S., they say, is isolated among industrialized nations in resisting these moves. They see the New York meeting as the last chance to set the world on track toward solutions in time for the U.N. summit meeting this June in Brazil. They are dismayed that Mr. Bush still has not promised to attend in June.</p>
        <p>With few exceptions, Administration officials question the scientific consensus. They also insist that European leaders know the practical difficulties of reducing CO2 and are playing games to court their own environmentalists (using the U.S. as an excuse for their own inaction) and gain economic advantages (given their lead in energy efficiency).</p>
        <p>The officials argue that realistic strategies for controlling warming gases have to be tailored to individual countries and must be comprehensive and flexible. But they would not venture to say whether this approach would limit CO2 increases. They say they are working on new meaty proposals. But these will not include legally mandated targets and timetables for CO2 reductions. Too artificial and difficult to define on a national basis, they believe -- and not without good reasons.</p>
        <p>Yet, some officials say they are entertaining the idea of targets and timetables as general goals. To this end, officials told of an ingenious bureaucratic game tied to the fact that CO2 growth is pegged to general economic growth: given Administration projections of average annual growth for the rest of the decade of about 2.9 percent, there is little hope of reducing CO2 levels. So the pro-T.&amp; T. crowd proposes lowering the projections to what most non-governmental economists realistically predict, about 1.9 percent. This would bring the U.S. within shouting distance of European T.&amp; T. levels. But it would also be an admission of slower economic growth and thus a failure of White House economic policies. So, stalemate.</p>
        <p>In any event, this scheme would only change abstract numbers without actually holding down CO2 output. Which is why officials say they are looking at other ideas, like longer- lasting light bulbs -- a good idea, but it would not put a big dent in CO2 growth.</p>
        <p>Even if industrialized countries found ways to limit CO2 output, these efforts would be offset by increases in developing countries. Officials are well aware of this and know poor countries will need aid to square the circle. But they say the present budget contained no money for a World Bank environmental/development fund. They say they are still looking.</p>
        <p>George Bush was not nearly so cautious when he spoke of global warming in the 1988 Presidential campaign. "Those who think we're powerless to do anything about the greenhouse effect are forgetting the White House effect," he said. Those welcome words are not forgotten by many worriers and wallowers who wait for him to bring them together -- for planet's sake.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
