<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>REPUBLICANS IN HOUSTON: The Houston Thing; Mrs. Bush and the Call Of Author! Author!</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Convention" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="551411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS, NATIONAL (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOWD, MAUREEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICH, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Frank Rich</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDE173CF933A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="1095" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>REPUBLICANS IN HOUSTON: The Houston Thing; Mrs. Bush and the Call Of Author! Author!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Maureen Dowd and Frank Rich,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DOWD, MAUREEN; RICH, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Aug. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Attention must be paid.</p>
        <p>Barbara Bush, giving assembly-line interviews to local television stations, had finally had enough of her stereotype as the custodian of maternal, stay-at-home family values.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Attention must be paid.</p>
        <p>Barbara Bush, giving assembly-line interviews to local television stations, had finally had enough of her stereotype as the custodian of maternal, stay-at-home family values.</p>
        <p>In an interview with Bill Nigut of WSB-TV in Atlanta, Mrs. Bush abruptly metamorphosed into Ms. Bush, career woman.</p>
        <p>Asked solicitously about her choice to be a homemaker, the First Lady snapped back indignantly: "Would you say that to Arthur Miller, who wrote two plays? Would you say you choose to be a homemaker to him? I've written two books."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bush's two books, of course, are her canine memoirs, "C. Fred's Story, a Dog's Life" (1984) and "Millie's Book" (1990). It was not clear which two of Mr. Miller's many plays she was likening to this literary output.</p>
        <p>Her comments led to good-natured conjecture that the playwright's "All My Sons" (1947) was initially titled "All My Dogs." But dogged textual analysis failed to reveal that any satanic pets were incinerated in the Salem witch trials dramatized in "The Crucible" (1953).</p>
        <p>There are parallels between Willy Loman, the protagonist of "Death of a Salesman," and Millie Bush, even though Millie is very well liked as the Bush family's top wage earner. As Willy got through life with a shoeshine and a smile, so Millie relies on a bark and a wag.</p>
        <p>But "Millie's Book" takes a far more optimistic view of the American dream than Mr. Miller's play, ending not with death, but with fireworks: "The Prez told me that if I'd stick with him, he'd show me my name in a THOUSAND POINTS OF LIGHT," Millie says, "and he did." Birthday Wishes For a Political Trio</p>
        <p>Today was a trifecta of birthdays: Bill Clinton and Tipper Gore on the Democratic side and Mary Matalin, the sharp-tongued Bush campaign official, on the Republican.</p>
        <p>What would be their ideal birthday presents?</p>
        <p>James Carville, the Clinton campaign strategist who is romantically linked with Ms. Matalin, laughed uncomfortably at first and then said jokingly, "I sent Mary an autographed picture of Bill and Tipper."</p>
        <p>From Torie Clarke, the Bush campaign aide, to Gov. Clinton: "Courage, brain and a heart."</p>
        <p>From Ozzy Osborne, former lead singer of Black Sabbath, to Mrs. Gore, the crusader against dirty rock lyrics: "A romantic dinner with Ice T."</p>
        <p>And to all the birthday celebrants, here is your joint Leo horoscope, courtesy of the syndicated astrologist Sidney Omarr: "You'll travel in September . . . Your name could almost become a household word . . . Major domestic adjustment takes place in December, could include change of residence or marital status." Though Speaking Softly, Still Look for the Mike</p>
        <p>In the Republican Party of rigid family values, even the harmless flirtation that was once the best part of politicians' lives is fraught with peril.</p>
        <p>Jack F. Kemp, the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development who also has his eye on the 1996 Presidential race, was feeling good today. "I'm in a spunky mood," he said as he entered the booth where he was conducting a series of local television interviews.</p>
        <p>The spunk swiftly turned into a funk when Mr. Kemp discovered that an open microphone in a television booth had captured his honeyed compliments, some of them whispered, to Liz Mathis, a reporter from KWWL-TV of Waterloo-Cedar Rapids, Iowa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kemp demanded that the male reporter in possession of the mike keep the recorded remarks off the air and threatened to call his news director to enforce the request.</p>
        <p>The contretemps would make for a perfect episode in television's favorite sitcom about television journalism, "Murphy Brown." An Unconventional Note From the Boys in the Band</p>
        <p>Family Values Out of the Closet:</p>
        <p>As George Bush joined his extended family on stage to acknowledge the convention's cheers tonight, the band struck up "The Best of Times," a song from Broadway's first musical to depict openly gay lovers, "La Cage Aux Folles." A Nice Try, Dan, But Still a Bit Off</p>
        <p>The New Dan Quayle Watch:</p>
        <p>Speaking before supporters of term-limitation proposals in 15 states, the Vice President noted that Democrats and political independents join Republicans in endorsing term limits.</p>
        <p>"This is not a bipartisan issue," Mr. Quayle concluded.  Surprise Signs Of a New Thelma and Louise</p>
        <p>Of all the pariahs at the Republican convention, surely one of the most unloved must be Nina Totenberg, the National Public Radio correspondent who first broadcast news of Anita Hill's allegations, and who later, in a street-corner spat, cursed out Senator Alan K. Simpson of Wyoming.</p>
        <p>It was therefore a surprise to Ms. Totenberg to make a friend in Mary Matalin, the Bush deputy campaign manager known for her scathing attacks on the Democrats. "She came up to me on the convention floor and introduced herself," Ms. Totenberg said. "She said, "I admire you. You and I probably don't agree on much, but we women who curse out men have got to stick together.' " The Climax at Last: Bring on the Yawns</p>
        <p>What do you say about a night that builds and builds and builds to . . . a speech by Senator Phil Gramm?</p>
        <p>After only a few hours, Tuesday night's program was legendary as the most tedious night in modern convention history.</p>
        <p>The evening opened with a song, "America My Home," written and sung by David King, whose lyrics had even the Statue of Liberty holding her ears: "Give me your huddled masses yearning to be free. Yes, the tired, the proud, the hungry, yes, bring them all to me."</p>
        <p>Soon came William K. Reilly, the beaten-down Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, whose oratorical hot air threatened to add to global warming.</p>
        <p>Then the piece de resistance: Phil Gramm. The junior Senator from Texas and Presidential hopeful was likened by Al Franken, the Comedy Central anchor, to a bombing comedian desperately recycling jokes that had worked years earlier.</p>
        <p>"At one point, I suddenly realized that over the course of 15 minutes, I'd had six fascinating conversations, and I hadn't any clue as to what Phil Gramm had been saying," said a Bush campaign aide when asked if there was any truth to the rumor that Bill Clinton had written Senator Gramm's endless keynote address.</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Gramm wrapped it up, the dwindled ranks of the party faithful were so eager to bolt the hall that even the closing benediction couldn't slow the mass exodus. In a convention of conspicuous Christianity, only the most pious delegates froze in embarrassment once Bishop Carl A. Fisher of the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Los Angeles started to pray.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
