<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="567782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW ZEALAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ITALY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WINE TALK (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/New Zealand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D61038F937A35752C1A964958260" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE British, who have no more than a token wine industry of their own, have long been important arbiters in the European wine market. They practically invented port and sherry; they made Bordeaux respectable and Champagne rich and were, for the longest time, far greater enthusiasts for the wines of the Rhine and Mosel than the Germans themselves.</p>
        <p>They even gave these wines dreadful English names. Sherry is, of course, Jerez, anglicized; claret is a simple version of clairet, an old French name for Bordeaux wine, and there is that truly execrable name for German wine: hock.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE British, who have no more than a token wine industry of their own, have long been important arbiters in the European wine market. They practically invented port and sherry; they made Bordeaux respectable and Champagne rich and were, for the longest time, far greater enthusiasts for the wines of the Rhine and Mosel than the Germans themselves.</p>
        <p>They even gave these wines dreadful English names. Sherry is, of course, Jerez, anglicized; claret is a simple version of clairet, an old French name for Bordeaux wine, and there is that truly execrable name for German wine: hock.</p>
        <p>But . . . what is this? No less authoritative a taker of the British pulse than The Financial Times seems to be saying this pre-eminance is over.</p>
        <p>"Britain's wine market," Philip Rawstorne wrote in that newspaper recently, "seems to have been affected by a touch of Euro-skepticism." The demand for traditional wines, from France, Germany and Italy, is falling, he said, while British consumers are developing a taste for what he called "New World wines."</p>
        <p>New World wines, Mr. Rawstorne said, come from Australia and New Zealand, South Africa and California.</p>
        <p>He offered figures. The amount of Australian wines entering Britain grew to 18.2 million liters last year, up from 800,000 liters in 1985; volumes for July and August of this year were 88 percent higher than the same two months in 1991. United States wineries shipped 10.5 million liters of wine to Britain in the first six months of 1992, a 25.5 percent increase over the same period in 1991.</p>
        <p>The lifting of economic sanctions against South Africa has had a big effect on that country's wine exports to Britain. Shipments in 1991 rose 65 percent above those in 1990, to 2.8 million liters, as against 1.7 million.</p>
        <p>New Zealand established an office in London last year with a 12-month goal of selling 1.8 million liters, The Financial Times said. It sold twice that, the newspaper added.</p>
        <p>Imports from France were down 7.4 percent in Britain last year; from Italy, down 6 percent, and from Germany, 4.4 percent. Mr. Rawstorne offered several hypotheses. French wines are overpriced, he said, while German wines are poorly promoted. But he suggested that "New World" wines may actually taste better.</p>
        <p>For example, he said that South African producers "put a lot of research into discovering what consumers wanted." What they discovered, he said, was that the British did not fancy mean, acidic stuff like Muscadet or -- this idea must have raised an eyebrow or two -- what he called "the leathery taste of a Burgundy." Leathery? Burgundy?</p>
        <p>He is talking about what are called "user friendly" wines in this country, although the South Africans and the Australians don't seem to have become as friendly as some bigger California producers. American wine makers don't hesitate to add a bit of sugar to their supposedly dry wines, particularly chardonnay. They know they are trying to appeal to a populace raised on sweet soft drinks.</p>
        <p>A closely followed court case in California ended recently with a wine maker's being prohibited from taking the "secret" formula for adding sugar to chardonnay from one winery to his new job at another.</p>
        <p>It's no secret that millions of potential wine drinkers are turned away by what they perceive to be "sour" and "bitter" tastes. In fact, the wines are neither sour nor bitter; they just aren't as sweet as Pepsi-Cola or Coke.</p>
        <p>There are two ways to make a wine sweeter: add sugar after fermentation or stop the fermentation before all the sugar from the grapes has been converted to alcohol and carbon dioxide. I have seen no evidence that the Australians or South Africans are doing either. But even without sugar, many New World wines are much easier to drink than their European counterparts. The difference is partly a function of warmer climates, partly of wine-making techniques. The result is softer, more rounded wines, without the astringency of many red and white European wines.</p>
        <p>Intelligent labeling is an important asset for the New World wines, Mr. Rawstorne suggested. "Just decoding a German wine label, cluttered with Gothic script, or identifying yet another French chateau inhibits many potential customers," he said. Labeling wines with the variety of the grape, like chardonnay or cabernet sauvignon, has made selecting a bottle much easier, he added.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, he said, the similarities between an Australian cabernet and one from California would "reassure the drinker that if he has enjoyed one, he will enjoy the other."</p>
        <p>European wine makers have made some attempts at varietal wines, which is what Americans call wines that bear the name of the grape they are made from. But it is their very particularity that is the glory of the best European vineyards. All the great red wines from Burgundy are made from pinot noir grapes, but three vineyards less than 100 yards apart will make three different wines.</p>
        <p>The Germans are bringing their labels into the 20th century, but slowly, while Italy, which produces literally thousands of different wines, could never truly simplify its labels.</p>
        <p>Prices are certainly a factor, probably the biggest one. Prices for European wines got out of hand in the 1980's. Many consumers were driven into the arms of the eager New World producers by outrageous prices for medium-quality European wines. The recent devaluation of the pound certainly won't help the British market.</p>
        <p>In this market, there are signs that some of these trends have been reversed. Sales of better European wines did well in the United States in the first half of this year, in spite of a continued drop in overall wine consumption.</p>
        <p>British wine drinkers, no more than American wine drinkers, are not about to abandon Europe's great wines; it has been a long and ardent love affair. On the other hand, it's difficult to love someone who charges you $14 for a bottle of Beaujolais. TASTINGS  Chateau Giscours 1989, Margaux, Bordeaux; about $24.</p>
        <p>In some recent tastings of Bordeaux wines from the 1988, 1989 and 1990 vintages, it quickly became evident that the 1989's would be the first to mature. It also appeared that although they would not be long-lived wines, during their good years they would be very good, indeed. Some, including this medium-bodied, supple Giscours, are just about ready to drink now. Giscours was a problematic wine in the 1960's and 1970's, when its owners, the Tari family, were waiting for their vineyards to mature and deciding what kind of wine to make. In the 1980's, Giscours came into its own. Even the 1987 vintage, underrated by many critics, was a delightful wine. The 1989, bought now, should continue to develop in the bottle for a year or two and be good to drink for 5 or 10 years after that. Not every Bordeaux has to be spectacular; some should be good, solid workaday wines like this one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
