<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Far From Old Hat, Headwear Is Back</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="557842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HATS AND CAPS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBINSON, RUTH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CREECH, DARCY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ITIN, ALEXANDRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALCARNE, MARILYN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DE1430F933A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="1084" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Far From Old Hat, Headwear Is Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH ROBINSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBINSON, RUTH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIME was when no self-respecting American dared venture into town without a hat. Hats managed to survive the Depression, and even World War II when a large percentage of the population was in uniform and dressing down was considered patriotic. Then, in the 60's, with bouffant hairstyles and a more informal life style, women's hats began to disappear from the sartorial scene. The men's hat industry was dealt a severe blow when in January 1961, President John F. Kennedy appeared bareheaded at his Inauguration on the steps of the Capitol despite freezing temperatures.</p>
        <p>Now hats are making a comeback. "Hats are hot," said Casey Bush, executive director of the Millinery Information Bureau in New York, adding that sales of women's hats have been increasing at an annual rate of 10 to 20 percent since the middle of the 80's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIME was when no self-respecting American dared venture into town without a hat. Hats managed to survive the Depression, and even World War II when a large percentage of the population was in uniform and dressing down was considered patriotic. Then, in the 60's, with bouffant hairstyles and a more informal life style, women's hats began to disappear from the sartorial scene. The men's hat industry was dealt a severe blow when in January 1961, President John F. Kennedy appeared bareheaded at his Inauguration on the steps of the Capitol despite freezing temperatures.</p>
        <p>Now hats are making a comeback. "Hats are hot," said Casey Bush, executive director of the Millinery Information Bureau in New York, adding that sales of women's hats have been increasing at an annual rate of 10 to 20 percent since the middle of the 80's.</p>
        <p>"Hats are a necessity, not just a fashion accessory," said Marilyn Malcarne of Deep River, a milliner. Because of the dangers of the depletion of the ozone layer, American men and women, like the Australians, are donning brims and visors to protect their complexions against premature aging and skin cancer. Used as a Sun Barrier</p>
        <p>Darcy Creech of Southport, a hat designer, agreed. "It is beginning to sink in that the sun is not good for you," she said. "When you see a person with a deep tan you don't admire it. You think, 'Oh my gosh, aren't they aware of what they're doing to themselves?' " With impeccable timing, Ms. Creech brought out her first collection in the spring of 1990.</p>
        <p>She aims for the classic country look with emphasis on natural materials -- handmade flowers of parchment paper, for example, and leather rather than vinyl bands. Her 600 accounts include major department stores like Neiman Marcus and Nordstrom. She also does custom work and shows up weekends for the polo matches at Conyer Farm in Greenwich with a display of hats.</p>
        <p>Ms. Creech's signature hat remains popular. She tells how, unable to find the right straw to wear to a party several years ago, she made one herself, trimming an unblocked Panama with a cotton damask bow, parchment flowers, berries and leaves. The compliments and demands for one like it catapulted her into the millinery business. Rather theatrical, the hat has been described as "Laura Ashley pirate."</p>
        <p>Flower-trimmed hats bearing the Darcy Creech label retail from $100 to $450. Men are not forgotten in the fall collection, which includes Western suedes in six colors and baseball caps with corduroy crowns and contrasting suede visors, both considered unisex styles, along with more feminine velours trimmed with flowers and feathers. Fedoras and Bowlers for Fall</p>
        <p>For Dotty Smith of Lakeville, another designer, hats are just one segment of an accessories business with annual retail sales estimated at $10 million, but it is a segment that is growing each year. While the natural straws offered for summer were trimmed with flowers or madras puggrees, the fall collection in felt is more restrained. Included are boaters, fedoras, bowlers, sailors and Stetsons in colors like magenta, plum and goldenrod in addition to standard navy, black, camel and taupe. These retail for about $50 at specialty stores across the nation.</p>
        <p>Like many of today's successful milliners, Ms. Malcarne received a certificate in millinery from the Fashion Institute of Technology in Manhattan. She does not have a production line; instead she creates sculptured hats and headpieces that are one of a kind and usually made to order. "If you can imagine it you can make it," is her philosophy. Artists Cross Over</p>
        <p>Her creations, which range in price from $75 to $500, tend to be dressy, a beaded Art Deco headpiece in turquoise and gold, for example, or an exotic brocade turban with Austrian crystal fringe. Ms. Malcarne is often called on to design bridal headpieces as well as period hats for owners of antique cars. She is particularly proud of an elegant tricorner made for the Lord Mayor of London, who she met when in England performing with a fife and drum corps. This model of black felt was set off by a plume fashioned of black lace anchored by an antique black button.</p>
        <p>Some of Connecticut's artists are finding hats a creative way of subsidizing their serious work. Alexandre Itin of Stamford, for instance, paints bold colorful designs on straw and felt hats of all varieties and sells them through outlets like the Gayle Willson Gallery in Southampton, L.I., and Julie Artisans' Gallery in New York. Prices range from $130 to $250. Many of the Itin designs are abstract, usually in primary colors, while others relate to landscape painting. They are practical to wear, even in damp weather, because the acrylic paint is sprayed to make it water resistant. Some of the painted hats stem from Mr. Itin's figurative three-dimensional paintings and sport faces built up of modeling paste on the crown. Seen from the front these are innocuous, but from the back they resemble grotesque masks.</p>
        <p>Irene Reed of Hartford, a sculptor in fiber and mixed media, tries to give her pieces some function to make buying them justifiable. "I've always been hat and bag oriented," she said. Her first step into the realm of millinery was a practical but funky number resembling an aviator's helmet, complete with goggles. She used her favorite technique, crochet, for these cozy caps of wool or cotton starting out with khaki for a military look, but soon branching out into colors. An immediate success, they were snapped up by people like the actress Mia Farrow. No Comeback for Hatting Capital</p>
        <p>These days Ms. Reed builds her headpieces up like sculptures, and though they can actually be worn, to a costume party perhaps, they are are more likely to show up in a gallery or museum than on someone's head. All kinds of materials are enlisted. Scraps of paper, painted and covered with fiberglass screen, are crocheted together with exotic threads and lavish use is made of found objects -- bones, beads and little plastic objects. Such increasingly elaborate pieces range in price from $700 to $1,200.</p>
        <p>Despite the surge in popularity of hats, Danbury -- once known as the Hatter Capital of the world -- today is identified with diverse high-technology companies. The hat industry, which flourished through the turn of the century and came to a halt in the 1960's, has not come back there, or in Norwalk, another city whose economy once depended to some extent on the manufacture of headwear.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
