<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Turning a Stew of Old Tires Into Energy</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="579369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TIRES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEXACO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD1431F934A15751C1A964958260" item-length="1103" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Turning a Stew of Old Tires Into Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>HARRISON, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OIL companies think of automobile tires as a petrochemical product, but earlier this month, Texaco Inc. tested a process using tires as a feedstock, in a multi-stage process for making electricity cleanly.</p>
        <p>The process, which Texaco says is technically viable and, it believes, economically viable as well, recasts tires as an interim stage between crude oil and useful energy. It also gives a starring role to worn-out lubricating oil, thus addressing two headaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OIL companies think of automobile tires as a petrochemical product, but earlier this month, Texaco Inc. tested a process using tires as a feedstock, in a multi-stage process for making electricity cleanly.</p>
        <p>The process, which Texaco says is technically viable and, it believes, economically viable as well, recasts tires as an interim stage between crude oil and useful energy. It also gives a starring role to worn-out lubricating oil, thus addressing two headaches.</p>
        <p>Texaco is one of the last oil companies that maintains a substantial alternative energy program. Much of the effort, including this new machine, is built around gasification. The idea is that cooking hydrocarbon fuels into a gas before burning them results in far cleaner combustion and far more energy than is possible in traditional combustion.</p>
        <p>The burning takes place in gas turbine engines, which resemble jet-airplane engines, only bolted to the ground. Most gas turbines today run on methane gas or burn diesel oil, which vaporizes easily. But Texaco has been commercially successful in gasifying less valuable hydrocarbons, notably heavy crude oil that is generally difficult to burn because of its high sulfur content. The company has 40 gasifiers and has sold licenses for 100 more.</p>
        <p>With Government subsidies, Texaco has also shown promising results in gasifying high-sulfur coal. Now, making gasification technology more valuable, the company is moving to less attractive fuels.</p>
        <p>Recently it signed an agreement with Petroleos de Venezuela, the General Electric Company and the Teco Power Service Company, a corporate cousin of Tampa Electric, to build a 250-megawatt power station in Puerto Rico that will gasify Orimulsion, one of the most abundant and promising fuel resources in this hemisphere, if only someone could figure out how to use it.</p>
        <p>"It's perfect for us," said David C. Crikelair, a Texaco vice president who heads the company's alternate energy department.  Orimulsion comes from the Orinoco tar deposit, which is more like asphalt than oil. Drillers push water into the ground so they can pump the material to the surface. The product is 28 percent water, which is acceptable, and 8 percent sulfur, which can present difficulties.</p>
        <p>Texaco also recently signed a major gasification deal with China, to provide gas for domestic and industrial use in Shanghai.</p>
        <p>The tire project is a concatenation of technologies, building a system to produce fuel for the gasifier, which in turn produces fuel for the turbine, which makes electricity.</p>
        <p>This chain of processes took a new twist in early December when Texaco successfully tested a device that cooks old tires into a liquid. It does so in a bath of waste oil, like old lubricating or transmission oil or even antifreeze from cars.</p>
        <p>At a laboratory in Montebello, Calif., in Los Angeles County (and, appropriately enough, overlooking a landfill), the company built a processing unit that takes chunks of tires and cooks them at 700 degrees Fahrenheit, for half an hour. The system, which the company hopes to sell for about $2 million, handles 1,000 to 2,000 tires a day, the number produced daily by a city of 250,000 to 500,000 people. The machine also requires an equal amount of waste oil, by weight.</p>
        <p>The tires have an energy content of about 15,000 British Thermal Units per pound, nearly 80 percent as much as crude oil. That means that a single 20-pound tire has as much energy as 2.5 gallons of gasoline.</p>
        <p>One difficulty is that tires are laced with steel belts, which must be removed with a rotating screw. The steel goes to a metal recycler.</p>
        <p>In the main reaction tank, the heat not only liquefies the tires, but also breaks down some of the largest, heaviest hydrocarbons, which are the least desirable, into gases, like methane and other light products that can be used in a refinery or burned immediately.</p>
        <p>The finished product from the liquefier is energy-rich, containing 85 percent to 90 percent of the energy in the tires and oil, but being heavily contaminated with sulfur and heavy metals, it is not attractive.</p>
        <p>One of the strengths of gasification is that dirty fuels can then be cleaned up. In a gasifier, hydrocarbon feedstock is combined with oxygen at controlled temperatures and pressures and broken down into hydrogen and carbon monoxide, which in this case is used as fuel, giving off energy and combining with oxygen as it burns to form carbon dioxide, a clean combustion product that is released into the atmosphere. Molecules of other ingredients, like hydrogen sulfide and heavy metals, are removed before burning with a sieve or by other methods.</p>
        <p>The most common use for the cleaned-up gas is a "combined-cycle turbine." The turbine sends its mechanical power to an electric generator and its exhaust gases to a steam generator, which captures much of the heat from the exhaust to boil water. The steam thus produced turns a steam turbine, making more mechanical power, which runs a separate electrical generator. Combined cycle plants have achieved efficiencies of up to 52 percent (meaning that the electricity produced has 52 percent as much energy as the gas did.) Traditional boilers achieve efficiencies of only about 33 percent.</p>
        <p>In addition, according to Texaco, its gasifiers, teamed with combined-cycle plants, are far cleaner than required by Environmental Protection Agency standards. They produce two pounds or less of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, and nitrogen oxides, which cause smog, per megawatt-hour of electricity produced. In contrast, conventional coal burning, even with scrubbers, produces eight pounds. The E.P.A. standard is 12 pounds.</p>
        <p>THE gasifier's output of hydrogen and carbon monoxide does not have to go to a power plant. Those gases are also the building blocks of ammonia and methanol, and the free hydrogen is also useful in a refinery, where demand for hydrogen is increasing because of process changes required to make new, cleaner gasolines.</p>
        <p>There are obstacles to building tire liquifiers, even if the technology works flawlessly. A key question is commercial structure, which is not nearly so tidy as a vertically integrated oil company.</p>
        <p>The raw material, tires and oil, start out as the property of a municipality or a private merchant. At the other end, the power is sold by a utility. In between there is probably an independent power generator, who may or may not own the gasifier; the producer of the liquefied tires might be independent of the other parties, too.</p>
        <p>The ownership issues may get sorted out in 1993; Texaco hopes for several sales in the coming year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
