<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. to Reject Pact on Protection Of Wildlife and Global Resources</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532412"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETIC ENGINEERING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVENTIONS AND INVENTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATURAL RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE1F30F933A05756C0A964958260" item-length="1577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. to Reject Pact on Protection Of Wildlife and Global Resources</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less than a week before the start of a global environmental summit conference, the Bush Administration said today that it would not sign an international treaty recently negotiated by 98 countries to preserve the world's plants, animals and natural resources.</p>
        <p>The treaty, the product of almost two weeks of intense negotiations in Nairobi, Kenya, this month, is considered one of the two main achievements of the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development, which begins on Wednesday in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less than a week before the start of a global environmental summit conference, the Bush Administration said today that it would not sign an international treaty recently negotiated by 98 countries to preserve the world's plants, animals and natural resources.</p>
        <p>The treaty, the product of almost two weeks of intense negotiations in Nairobi, Kenya, this month, is considered one of the two main achievements of the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development, which begins on Wednesday in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
        <p>The other focus, a proposed treaty to combat global warming, was accepted by the United States, but only after the Administration persuaded other countries to drop their insistence on a strict timetable for curbing emissions of carbon dioxide. Others to Follow U.S. Lead</p>
        <p>The Administration's decision on the treaty preserving plants, animals and natural resources, known as the biological diversity treaty, is almost certain to be followed by Japan and many European nations, according to preliminary indications from officials in those countries.</p>
        <p>The actions by the President and other leaders of the industrialized world is likely to further roil an international conference that many world leaders and environmentalists had hoped would make repairing the planet a central organizing political force in the post-cold-war period.</p>
        <p>But the American refusal to sign the biodiversity treaty is not expected to be a fatal blow. Unlike the case of the climate treaty, to which the United States is essential because it is the world's largest industrial emitter of carbon dioxide, the biodiversity treaty protects natural resources that are distributed among many nations. The treaty will come into force when it has been ratified by 30 nations.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the Administration appeared to be sensitive to criticism of its refusal to sign the treaty. As if anticipating the criticism, the Administration announced its rejection late this afternoon, too late for the deadlines of some news organizations, particularly television.</p>
        <p>And then, almost simultaneously, the White House announced that the United States and Germany were preparing a separate international plan to develop economic and technical practices for preserving the world's forests. President Bush is expected to announce on Monday that the United States will contribute more than $100 million annually to put it into effect.</p>
        <p>The cause of protecting forests is expected to be a major point of contention at the Earth Summit, with Malaysia and other developing countries opposed to curbs on their use of forest land for economic development.</p>
        <p>The forestry and species preservation issues are only two of several that are pitting rich nations against poor nations and stirring criticism among environmental groups of the leadership of the United States.</p>
        <p>One major theme of these disputes is the demand by developing countries to be compensated for any curbs on their use of their natural resources. The United States has resisted such demands, and aides to Mr. Bush had advised him against going to Rio for fear that he would come under pressure to sign agreements deemed objectionable.  Patent Protection Cited</p>
        <p>In explaining why the President would not sign the treaty for preserving species, the State Department said the text was "seriously flawed" because it failed to give adequate patent protection to American companies that would transfer biological inventions to developing countries.</p>
        <p>The State Department also said the United States had concerns with how money for putting the treaty into effect would be disbursed.</p>
        <p>Lastly, the United States said it disagreed with the treaty's attempt to regulate the safety of genetically engineered products that would be used in developing countries. The State Department said it did not believe such products pose an environmental threat.</p>
        <p>"In every negotiation, no matter how important the subject matter, the actual outcome must always be considered," the State Department said. "The United States does not and can not sign an agreement that is fundamentally flawed merely for the sake of having that agreement."</p>
        <p>Scientists and ecologists have warned for more than a decade that the rate of extinction of plants, animals and microbes is accelerating as pollution and the destruction of forests and other habitats take their toll. The United States and other nations had expressed great interest in developing an international treaty to provide protections because new medical, agricultural and industrial inventions also would be lost as species vanished.</p>
        <p>Many of the world's medicines were developed from plants. Many genetically engineered food crops expected in the future will incorporate genes collected from plant and microbial species in the tropics.</p>
        <p>Countries that signed the treaty on May 22 in Nairobi committed themselves to developing programs to conserve the diversity of biological resources, set up protected habitats and restore habitats that had been destroyed or degraded by industrial development. The treaty called for the signers to meet periodically to review progress, but it did not specify how much money the richer countries would provide to the poorer ones.</p>
        <p>The Administration said it was skeptical of the treaty long before today's announcement, provoking criticism from environmentalists and foreign leaders. In what was seen as an effort to deflect still more criticism, the President presented the new United States-German plan for the world's forests during a speech on Monday at the Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., just outside Washington.</p>
        <p>The proposal on forests follows the broad outlines of a plan for improving management of the world's forests that Mr. Bush and Chancellor Helmut Kohl introduced in Houston nearly two years at an economic summit meeting. The new proposal has been prepared with the help of Mr. Kohl.</p>
        <p>"There is no time to present something for signature at Rio," C. Boyden Gray, the President's counsel, said in an interview. "The hope is to elevate it above what else will happen in Rio and get it on a faster track than it has been for resolution sometime soon."</p>
        <p>Like the other issues to be discussed at the Earth Summit, the forest initiative is certain to become embroiled in disputes between industrialized and less developed nations over a country's right to control its own resources. Malaysia, an important exporter of tropical hardwoods, has resisted proposals that would limit cutting.</p>
        <p>"If this initiative helps break the negotiating log jam on forests, then it would be very useful," said Rafe Pomerance, senior associate with the World Resources Institute, an environmental research group in Washington.</p>
        <p>The proposed treaty will offer ideas to slow cutting and burning of the world's tropical forests, develop improved methods of reforestation and encourage an approach to harvesting trees that would insure that more trees are planted than cut.</p>
        <p>The forestry issue was discussed in preliminary talks last year, when negotiators agreed that a draft treaty could not be agreed on in time for the Earth Summit. Instead, they agreed to work for a statement of principles on forests at Rio, laying the groundwork for subsequent negotiations on a draft treaty.</p>
        <p>Plans for even a set of principles have run into problems, however, with heavily forested nations expressing opposition.</p>
        <p>Along with the Administration's decision not to sign the biological diversity treaty, European leaders and many environmentalists in the United States have expressed dismay over the Administration's successful effort to thwart aggressive measures to set limits and deadlines for emissions of carbon dioxide, a gas linked to global climate change. Instead, the United States negotiated a treaty that aims at, but does not require, reductions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases. U.S. Eases Restriction</p>
        <p>Just two weeks ago, five Cabinet-level officials voted to exempt the Government from the Endangered Species Act and allow cutting of 1,700 acres of Oregon forests that are home to the threatened northern spotted owl. The same day, the Administration introduced legislation to cut roughly four million acres of ancient forests in the Pacific Northwest. It is unclear how the international treaty Mr. Bush plans to propose would affect the management of forests in the United States.</p>
        <p>Ecologists say the world's forests play a central biological role in maintaining the Earth's environment. They are the Earth's lungs, taking in carbon dioxide and then separating the carbon for storage as plant tissue and releasing the oxygen. Forests also provide habitats for hundreds of thousands of species of plants, animals and microbes. They hold the soil, filter water, nurture soil and provide wood for industrial uses and fuel.</p>
        <p>Forests, especially in the tropics, are disappearing under saw and fire. Scientists estimate that about half the forests that covered the developing world in 1900 have vanished, an area roughly the size of the continental United States.</p>
        <p>Deforestation contributes more than 1 billion tons of carbon dioxide to the atmosphere each year, according to a study by the World Resources Institute, adding to the 5.8 billion tons produced by burning coal, oil and natural gas. Concentrations of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere have risen from 275 parts per million a century ago to 355 last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
