<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Need a Global Warming Treaty With Clout</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="513049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DE113CF933A25750C0A964958260" item-length="465" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Need a Global Warming Treaty With Clout</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "Global Snub on Global Warming" (editorial, Feb. 18), you call on the Bush Administration to adopt "a more reasonable course" on global warming, but voluntary goals are not adequate. Most European governments adopted such goals for limiting carbon dioxide emissions in 1989, but the Bush Administration refused to go along, saying that mere goals could not be taken seriously without measures to back them up.</p>
        <p>Since then the Europeans have called for legally binding limits on carbon dioxide as part of the international climate treaty. The Europeans are well along in implementing their own commitments. It is too little and too late for the United States to adopt merely a goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "Global Snub on Global Warming" (editorial, Feb. 18), you call on the Bush Administration to adopt "a more reasonable course" on global warming, but voluntary goals are not adequate. Most European governments adopted such goals for limiting carbon dioxide emissions in 1989, but the Bush Administration refused to go along, saying that mere goals could not be taken seriously without measures to back them up.</p>
        <p>Since then the Europeans have called for legally binding limits on carbon dioxide as part of the international climate treaty. The Europeans are well along in implementing their own commitments. It is too little and too late for the United States to adopt merely a goal.</p>
        <p>You cautiously state it is uncertain whether or not global warming will be dangerous. Yet "Washington May Change Its Position on Climate," a Science Times article the same day, notes that both the international science panel of the United Nations and the National Academy of Sciences have concluded that the threat is sufficiently clear and present to warrant a prompt response.</p>
        <p>Low-lying countries and island states, whose very existence is at stake, have no doubt that sea-level rise from global warming would be dangerous, indeed, catastrophic. The same can be said for the grain belt, temperate forests, wetlands, coral reefs and other natural ecosystems, all of which face devastation unless the world eventually reduces carbon dioxide emissions and other greenhouse gases by more than 60 percent to stabilize the climate.</p>
        <p>You have misplaced worries about the cost of curbing carbon dioxide emissions. Inaction on carbon dioxide costs us billions of dollars a year. The energy efficiency and renewable energy investments needed to reduce emissions would create jobs and make the United States more competitive on world markets.</p>
        <p>Our research shows that carbon dioxide emissions can be cut 25 percent by the year 2005 and 70 percent by 2030 at a</p>
        <p>net profit</p>
        <p>of $2.3 trillion. The Environmental Protection Agency analysis you mention is more conservative, but also concludes that carbon dioxide emissions in 2000 can be limited to 1990 levels at a profit. Only economic models that assume our economy is functioning perfectly reach the conclusion that cutting emissions might be expensive.</p>
        <p>The time for voluntary goals is past. There is too great a risk that, like the President's education goals, they will simply be ignored. If President Bush really wants to lead a new world order in which global environmental dangers number among the great threats to our collective security, he must move now to negotiate a global warming treaty with enforceable emission limits. JOHN ADAMS Executive Director Natural Resources Defense Council New York, Feb. 20, 1992</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
