<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reebok Fights to Be No. 1 Again</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="513475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOES AND BOOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNEAKERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">REEBOK INTERNATIONAL LTD</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NIKE INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOLTZ, KIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUERDEN, JOHN H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shoes and Boots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF113BF931A25750C0A964958260" item-length="1401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reebok Fights to Be No. 1 Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIM FOLTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FOLTZ, KIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most days, weather permitting, several Reebok executives spend their lunchtime playing pickup basketball on the asphalt court at the edge of the company's parking lot near Boston. The game is friendly, but serious, as the men and women players join in for the exercise and to promote corporate camaraderie.</p>
        <p>But most of all, it is a practical training ground in the competitive spirit driving the company these days: Reebok wants to be a winner again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most days, weather permitting, several Reebok executives spend their lunchtime playing pickup basketball on the asphalt court at the edge of the company's parking lot near Boston. The game is friendly, but serious, as the men and women players join in for the exercise and to promote corporate camaraderie.</p>
        <p>But most of all, it is a practical training ground in the competitive spirit driving the company these days: Reebok wants to be a winner again.</p>
        <p>Ever since Nike took away its title in 1989 as the nation's No. 1 seller of athletic shoes, Reebok has been waging a fierce marketing battle to win back the prestige and sales appropriated by its rival.</p>
        <p>It is continuing the fight this year with a new ad campaign called "Life Is Short. Play Hard," and it is gambling that a steady stream of new shoe designs and gimmicks will catapult it back into first place.</p>
        <p>"We hadn't been hitting on all cylinders during the last few years," said Angel Martinez, Reebok's corporate vice president for new business development. "But we are starting to now."</p>
        <p>In the last two years, Reebok International Ltd., based in Stoughton, Mass., has increased its share of the domestic market to 24 percent from 22 percent. Nike Inc.'s share, meanwhile, has held steady at 30 percent of the $5.82 billion athletic shoe market.</p>
        <p>"Reebok is getting closer and closer to Nike by beating up the other players in the marketplace," said John Horan, editor and publisher of the Sporting Goods Intelligence Management News, an industry publication. "Reebok has a huge advantage because it can afford expensive promotional campaigns."</p>
        <p>Reebok's current campaign is tied to the coming Summer Olympics. Like much of Reebok's past offbeat advertising, the new commercials feature a humorous competition between two members of the United States Olympic team, the decathletes Dave Johnson and Don O'Brien, both of whom boast they are the world's best athletes. And as with some of Reebok's past campaigns, this one has also been criticized as not being focused enough on the shoes.</p>
        <p>Although Nike is a sponsor of the Summer Olympics, Reebok will be the exclusive athletic shoe and active-wear advertiser during Olympic broadcasts. In addition, the company has designed the uniform that American winners will wear when they step up to accept their medals.  Battle of Inflatable Shoes</p>
        <p>Nike's Air series of shoes with pre-filled air cushions helped the company move into first place. In turn, Reebok began to revitalize its sagging image with the Pump inflatable shoe, which allows for a more custom-fit by pumping air into inflatable chambers in the shoe.</p>
        <p>But company executives know the popular Pump cannot do the job alone. Since its introduction, the Pump has accounted for about 16 percent of Reebok's annual sales. So far, some six million pairs of Pump shoes have been sold for a total of $750 million.</p>
        <p>The Pump's popularity has helped to give the company bottom line a healthy boost. Last year, Reebok's worldwide sales increased by 26.6 percent, to $2.7 billion. Profits also jumped to $234.7 million in 1991, compared with $176.6 million the previous year.</p>
        <p>As the market for the Pump matures, sales are expected to drop by as much as 30 percent this year. "The Pump got the energy flowing again at Reebok," said Bob Meers, president of United States operations. "But it's only part of Reebok, it has to evolve."</p>
        <p>To help offset that decline, Paul Fireman, Reebok's chairman, said the company would spend about $220 million on advertising this year, substantially more than the $140 million it allocated in 1991. Some analysts said that level of spending might help Reebok slow the Nike juggernaut a little. This year, Nike plans to spend about $150 million.</p>
        <p>To keep customers' interest, especially prime ones in the 12-to-18-year-old group who continually change their taste in shoes, Reebok last year introduced several redesigned shoes. Among them is a double-pump version with two inflation gadgets to pump air into more areas of the shoe. Another is a sturdier shoe called the Blacktop, which the company says is made for playing basketball on the rough surfaces of outdoor courts.</p>
        <p>In January, at a trade show for sporting-goods manufacturers and retailers in Atlanta, Reebok introduced an advanced version of the Pump that makes it easier to inflate the interior of the shoe around the foot. The Insta-Pump, which is inflated using a small canister of carbon dioxide, instead of manually, is intended to give greater support for runners and tennis players. If the Insta-Pump proves to be popular, Reebok plans to use the technology in all of its athletic shoes eventually.</p>
        <p>With the Insta-Pump, some analysts say Reebok may have taken the lead in technology. "The Insta-Pump is on the cutting edge in athletic shoe technology," Mr. Horan of Sporting Goods Intelligence said. "Reebok has demonstated that it can make a better shoe. The other brands will be forced to follow suit."</p>
        <p>But making headway in the women's market will not be easy for Nike. Reebok first made its reputation with hot-selling aerobics shoes mainly aimed at women. Reebok still dominates the women's athletic shoe market with a 49 percent share, company executives said, and its Step Aerobics, a new exercise program intended to replace the more old-fashioned jump-and-kick aerobics, is helping it to keep market share.</p>
        <p>Not coincidentally, Reebok sells Step aerobics shoes and also markets the portable plastic steps that exercisers sometimes stack up three or four at a time.</p>
        <p>The company has also begun to branch out into other areas of athletic wear that it hopes will be as rich as footwear has been. The company has put a greater emphasis on its apparel division, which includes casual and athletic wear for adults under the Reebok, Allesse and Rockport brands, as well as Weebok, a new line of clothes and shoes for children.</p>
        <p>"In the past, we had not made apparel a serious business," said Marilyn Tam, president of the apparel products group. "Now we have some of the top people in the business." Chief Executive's Role</p>
        <p>Many Reebok executives attribute the company's revival to John Duerden, who became the president and chief executive of the company in 1990. A former Xerox executive, Mr. Duerden has used his buttoned-down corporate style to temper Reebok's entrepreneurial zeal. "This was a big company that needed some discipline," he said. "You can't just make shoes at random."</p>
        <p>Mr. Duerden streamlined the company's management so that only 12 executives report to him. Now, the company feels it can move more quickly to accommodate the company's core of fickle customers, who love new types of shoes. "To keep up with the marketplace, we now have to change one-third of the products we produce two times each year," Mr. Duerdan said.</p>
        <p>He has also mandated that pleasing customers is as important as designing shoes. Reebok now keeps closer tabs on whether retailers are getting enough of the right merchandise on time. Even Mr. Duerdan calls 10 retailers each week to listen to their complaints or bask in their praise.</p>
        <p>In a sort of marketing show-and-tell, Reebok has begun to open its own stores that company executives say are intended to demonstrate to retailers the best way to sell Reebok shoes, clothing and other athletic gear. The first Reebok Concept store opened in Boston last year and the next one is scheduled to be completed in May in Manhattan. "These shops are not intended to compete with other retailers," Mr. Meers said. "These are living merchandising laboratories." Nike has opened similar stores. Some Traditions Survive</p>
        <p>But Mr. Duerdan did not tamper with some Reebok traditions. On his first day at Reebok's headquarters, an unsuspecting Mr. Duerdan walked into the third-floor conference room to sit in on what he thought would be a run-of-the-mill meeting about new products. The room was jammed with employees from every level of the company. The scene was chaotic as executives shouted at co-workers, waving new shoes and sometimes hurling them at each other to make a particular point. One designer had been reduced to tears by a particularly scathing review.</p>
        <p>"I couldn't believe it," Mr. Duerdan said. "I tried to put limitations on these meetings, but I realized I couldn't because they were too much a part of the company's culture."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
