<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Says He Seeks Balance on the Environment</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD143BF932A05756C0A964958260" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Says He Seeks Balance on the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>FRESNO, Calif., May 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush today defended his rejection of a treaty to protect biological species that will have broad support at the Earth Summit opening next week in Rio de Janeiro, saying he is "fighting for balance" between environmental needs and the health of the American economy.</p>
        <p>"We cannot accept standards that are not based on the soundest of science," Mr. Bush said. "And we cannot shut down the lives of thousands of Americans by going to extremes" on environmental policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush today defended his rejection of a treaty to protect biological species that will have broad support at the Earth Summit opening next week in Rio de Janeiro, saying he is "fighting for balance" between environmental needs and the health of the American economy.</p>
        <p>"We cannot accept standards that are not based on the soundest of science," Mr. Bush said. "And we cannot shut down the lives of thousands of Americans by going to extremes" on environmental policy.</p>
        <p>He spoke a day after the Administration announced that it would not sign a global convention on preserving biological diversity, to be offered at the Earth Summit because of concern that it would require the United States to strengthen laws protecting endangered species.</p>
        <p>The Administration has recently increased efforts to limit the Endangered Species Act, one of the oldest American environmental laws.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the timber industry and others have campaigned against the law, arguing that it does not fairly balance environmental and economic interests.</p>
        <p>The State Department issued a written defense today of the decision not to sign the biodiversity treaty.</p>
        <p>It argued that the United States' record in preserving threatened plants and animals is "unparalleled" and that the treaty, which was negotiated with the approval of 98 nations last week, violates earlier agreements on the means by which developed nations would help finance environmental programs in poorer countries.</p>
        <p>"The United States is prepared to help others protect our world's biological resources," the statement said, "but the funding must be workable."</p>
        <p>The State Department said the proposed treaty would impinge on world patent and copyright agreements and would unfairly penalize the developing biotechnology industry.</p>
        <p>The White House said on Friday that Mr. Bush would attend the Earth Summit in mid-June, a day or two after a stop in Panama on June 11.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush responded to questions here in Fresno, in the San Joaquin Valley of California, one of the nation's most productive agricultural areas. He said he had earlier withheld a decision on whether to attend the Earth Summit because he "also wanted sound economic policy" to be written into its treaties.</p>
        <p>The President said he would attend after negotiators agreed to strike language in a second treaty, aimed at curbing global warming, that would have set goals and timetables for nations to cut their emissions of certain industrial pollutants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said today that the United Nations-sponsored conference "started off getting requirements that nobody could keep" because they were unreasonably stringent. But now, he said, "we've got something really sound" to which he could pledge adherence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has come under sharp criticism from some environmental leaders in this country and abroad for his positions. Critics say the United States' refusal to support stronger controls on pollution and other environmental hazards has undercut a consensus among most of the world's other nations to slow or reverse damage to the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush disagreed today. "My general philosophy is that we've got a good, sound environmental practice," he said. "I think we've got something to be really proud of and to take to Rio."</p>
        <p>The President also announced a program that would encourage property owners to restore wetlands lost to development.</p>
        <p>The Administration has proposed spending $160.9 million in Agriculture Department funds next year on the program, which would purchase up to a million acres in land easements from property owners who agree to convert unused acreage to the original wetlands state.</p>
        <p>The pilot program would cover nine states and restore about 50,000 acres of wetlands.</p>
        <p>The White House said that the United States has lost about half its 221 million acres of wetlands since colonists began arriving in the 17th century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
