<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kentucky Chickens With Je Ne Sais Quoi</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="574011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POULTRY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WILSON FIELDS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILSON, DAVID (CHICKEN FARMER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D61E31F931A35751C1A964958260" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kentucky Chickens With Je Ne Sais Quoi</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBIA, Ky.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the last year or so, flocks of French chickens have been pecking and scratching their way from the gentle hills of southern Kentucky to some fine dinner tables. They are the only French chickens being raised commercially in this country.</p>
        <p>It was the doggedness of David Wilson, a former squab farmer, that brought these chickens here. Mr. Wilson, whose easy bluegrass twang is peppered with phrases like "raison d'etre," became intrigued with French chickens nearly five years ago after some of the chefs who were buying his squabs kept telling him how good they were.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the last year or so, flocks of French chickens have been pecking and scratching their way from the gentle hills of southern Kentucky to some fine dinner tables. They are the only French chickens being raised commercially in this country.</p>
        <p>It was the doggedness of David Wilson, a former squab farmer, that brought these chickens here. Mr. Wilson, whose easy bluegrass twang is peppered with phrases like "raison d'etre," became intrigued with French chickens nearly five years ago after some of the chefs who were buying his squabs kept telling him how good they were.</p>
        <p>"I went to France and also to England to see what this was all about," he said. "I came back very impressed with what they were doing."</p>
        <p>After a trip to Europe in 1988 he tried raising American chickens a la Francaise for about a year and a half but was not satisfied with the results. "American chickens are bred for their breast meat, so they look like small turkeys," he said. "They don't have the flavor and texture of French chickens."</p>
        <p>So now he is importing French chickens, which are being raised with plenty of room to run around outdoors. They are not fed antibiotics or other chemicals, nor are their beaks and claws clipped. The day-old chicks land first in Quebec, where they spend four weeks in quarantine before they are allowed to cross the American border.</p>
        <p>"You really have to want to do this," Mr. Wilson said. "Our poultry industry has wisely set up barriers to protect against disease and also for economic reasons. We were fortunate to find a quarantine facility in Canada that we could work with."</p>
        <p>Wilson Fields, the company based in Louisville that Mr. Wilson organized with a group of investors, brings in 4,500 hybrid Breton chickens every 18 weeks. Mr. Wilson explained that livestock breeding must be very carefully controlled, which is why he continues to import the chicks instead of simply breeding his own.</p>
        <p>"The breeding part is best left to the experts," he said. "We are bringing in the parent flocks and we sell the chickens we grow from their eggs." Each flock can breed for 40 weeks, producing up to 700,000 chickens, or about 17,000 chickens a week. Currently, 60 percent of the chickens are sold in Canada, with the rest going to restaurants and supermarkets, mainly in Kentucky.</p>
        <p>These chickens require 66 days to reach market weight of about three-and-a-half pounds dressed, compared with 39 to 42 days for American chickens. The difference is due to the breed and their diet of corn and wheat, which contains no growth-inducing drugs.</p>
        <p>The Wilson Fields flocks are distributed among 17 farmers in the southern part of the state near Bowling Green who had been raising industrial chickens. The Kentucky Department of Agriculture played matchmaker between the farmers and Wilson Fields.</p>
        <p>It appears to be a very happy marriage, said Leon and Laverne Kessler of Exie, whose farm just happens to be off Fry Ridge Road.</p>
        <p>"We've been in the chicken business for 30 years," Mrs. Kessler said. "I like doing this, with 2,000 birds in a barn and letting them run outside, much better than having 13,000 inside all the time with the ammonia odor. We used to have six fans running all the time, and now we only need two, so it uses less energy."</p>
        <p>When the doors to the Quonset hut-style barn opened, the mostly white chickens milled around outside, some pecking at gravel, others venturing out into the carefully fenced green meadow beyond.</p>
        <p>"There is enough room at each farm to give every chicken two square meters of space," said Missy Camp, vice president of the company. "That's the minimum standard the French allow for free range. There are very few farms in this country that comply with that."</p>
        <p>The Kesslers also have a small flock of handsome black chickens called acco noir, also from France, and some purebred brown Breton chickens. These take 81 days to reach market weight and are being raised on a very limited basis.</p>
        <p>Not only is Mr. Wilson breaking new ground when it comes to raising chickens in the United States; his new federally inspected processing plant here, about 50 miles east of Bowling Green, also operates differently from any other plant in the country.</p>
        <p>The chickens are first anesthetized with carbon dioxide before killing, which Wilson Fields says relaxes them and improves their texture. The birds are briefly scalded three times in progressively cleaner water to facilitate the removal of the feathers. This process is said to minimize bacterial contamination, compared with the usual single scalding.</p>
        <p>The United States Department of Agriculture requires that the internal temperature of chickens be cooled to 38 degrees in no more than 16 hours after slaughtering, to prevent deterioration. The quickest method is to plunge the birds into cold water, which reduces the temperature sufficiently in less than an hour. But there is the potential for bacterial contamination, even in cold water.</p>
        <p>At Wilson Fields, the chickens are placed on V-shaped racks for two hours in a room with circulating chilled air. The racks prevent the chickens from resting in any fluids. As a result, there is almost no excess moisture when a package is opened.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Wilson is doing seems to be worth the effort. The chicken is extremely flavorful, with a succulence unmatched by the typical American chicken. Tests at the University of Kentucky have shown that the chickens have thinner skins, less exterior fat and juicier flesh than standard American chickens.</p>
        <p>The chickens, labeled Wilson Fields la Belle Rouge (brown chickens are called reds in the industry), are mostly sold whole, trussed for roasting and without giblets, and mostly to restaurants. The chickens are also sold at a few Kroger stores in the Louisville area for $2.69 a pound; typical commercial chickens are less than a dollar a pound.</p>
        <p>Some chefs who are using the chickens include Kathy Cary, who owns La Peche and Lilly's in Louisville, Mark Militello of Mark's Place in Miami and Dean Fearing of the Mansion at Turtle Creek in Dallas. "You can even tell the difference in a chicken pot pie," Ms. Cary said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
