<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broad Effort Under Way to Track Ozone Hole's Effects</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="498589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ULTRAVIOLET LIGHT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDB1139F934A35752C0A964958260" item-length="1809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broad Effort Under Way to Track Ozone Hole's Effects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>TENIENTE MARSH BASE, Antarctica</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DESPITE growing anxiety about the "ozone hole" that has begun appearing each year in the stratosphere above Antarctica, inhabitants of the white continent seem to be taking the resulting seasonal blasts of solar ultraviolet radiation in stride -- the wildlife, by producing protective pigments, and the humans, by wearing dark glasses, heavy clothing and sun-blocking lotions.</p>
        <p>But while scientists say the dangers of exposure to intense ultraviolet are presently under control, the hazard is expected to increase sharply in the coming years, and experts have begun the most comprehensive environmental monitoring study of its kind to keep track of it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DESPITE growing anxiety about the "ozone hole" that has begun appearing each year in the stratosphere above Antarctica, inhabitants of the white continent seem to be taking the resulting seasonal blasts of solar ultraviolet radiation in stride -- the wildlife, by producing protective pigments, and the humans, by wearing dark glasses, heavy clothing and sun-blocking lotions.</p>
        <p>But while scientists say the dangers of exposure to intense ultraviolet are presently under control, the hazard is expected to increase sharply in the coming years, and experts have begun the most comprehensive environmental monitoring study of its kind to keep track of it.</p>
        <p>Dangerously intense solar radiation is not new to our planet. The risk posed by ultraviolet radiation from the sun has become serious many times during the long history of life on earth, as the protective ozone layer has thinned out or disappeared altogether.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric ozone, a compound consisting of three oxygen atoms, is created primarily by the exposure of oxygen to intense ultraviolet radiation from the sun. But it can be destroyed by a variety of chemical processes; some occur naturally, others are fueled by chemicals let into the atmosphere by people.</p>
        <p>Nature has met the challenge posed by the unreliability of the ozone layer by evolving a variety of protective sun-blocking compounds. But many scientists believe that the protection of the ozone layer may be diminishing so rapidly that many species will fail to adapt quickly enough to survive.</p>
        <p>The vegetable plankton at the base of Antarctica's food chain, as well as many of the organisms that feed on it, have developed a wide range of special pigments that absorb ultraviolet radiation and prevent it from damaging the cellular mechanisms essential to life. At least one major chemical company is investigating the use of natural sun-blocking compounds as the basis of new protective lotions for human beings.</p>
        <p>But coping with ultraviolet is likely to be increasingly difficult for wildlife and people in the coming years, scientists believe. The threat created by ultraviolet penetration of the infamous annual ozone hole, as well as the overall depletion of the global shield of stratospheric ozone, is certain to worsen, they agree. Almost every year since its first major appearance in 1986, the Antarctic ozone hole has become more severe during the several weeks it persists, and the episode last October was the worst since records have been kept.</p>
        <p>The holes are regions in which chlorine atoms or compounds interact in complicated ways with ozone, destroying it. Nearly all of this chlorine, scientists believe, results from decomposition of chlorofluorocarbons, called CFC's, released into the atmosphere by various human activities and products.</p>
        <p>Most nations of the world have agreed to phase out the manufacture and use of CFC's by the end of the century, although some of the proposed substitutes also tend to destroy stratospheric ozone. CFC's are used as refrigerants in air-conditioners and refrigerators, as thermal insulators, as foaming agents in plastics and as cleaning solvents.</p>
        <p>The Antarcticans themselves -- Chilean and Argentine families who live in Antarctica for years at a time -- have become wary, though not fearful. These families are settled in Antarctica by the Chilean and Argentine governments, mainly to support the rival territorial claims of the two countries to a large sector of the continent.</p>
        <p>"In summer, my husband and I don't let any of our three children out the door without their sunglasses," said Laurette Brahm Gilabert, one of the women living at this Chilean Air Force base on King George Island. "In winter, of course, even when they're outdoors for a barbecue or football game or snowball fight, the sun never rises, so there's no danger. In summer, it's still cold enough that we all bundle up, so there's very little skin exposed to the sun." 'This Is Not Surprising'</p>
        <p>Scientists and doctors discount stories circulating in rural Chile that sheep, rabbits and other animals have been blinded by solar radiation leaking through the damaged ozone layer, although such rumors are widely believed by laymen. In any case, clinical studies have found evidence of a link between excessive exposure to ultraviolet radiation and cataracts. Chileans take this evidence seriously; throughout the country during this Southern Hemisphere summer, most Chileans seem to have taken to wearing sunglasses.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jaime Abarca of Punta Arenas, the only dermatologist practicing in southern Chile, says there has been no increase in Chile or Antarctica in the rate of skin cancer caused by solar radiation since the ozone hole appeared. "This is not surprising," he said, "because we would not expect to see any effect in less than 10 or 20 years. But we have every reason to worry about the possibility of a future epidemic of skin cancer."</p>
        <p>Medical experts are not particularly worried that ultraviolet radiation will harm the Antarcticans themselves, or the thousands of tourists who come to Antarctica by ship each year or who stay for a few days at the Villa las Estrellas Hotel at Chile's Marsh Base. "As the depletion of the ozone layer spreads to lower latitudes," Dr. Abarca said, "the real danger is for sunbathers at such beach resorts as Chile's Vina del Mar, where people go on exposing their skin, even in the face of dangerous radiation."</p>
        <p>But many scientists worry about the potential vulnerability of many Antarctic plants and animals to changing environmental conditions, including the increase in ultraviolet radiation. To explore these vulnerabilities and to establish benchmarks against which the collective health of wildlife colonies can be measured, American scientists at Palmer Station in Antarctica have embarked on a six-year "long-term environmental research" program financed mostly by the National Science Foundation.</p>
        <p>Although the results of this study will not be directly applicable to terrestrial environments where major human food crops may be at risk from ultraviolet exposure, marine experiments in Antarctica may at least reveal fruitful directions for future terrestrial research. Children Not Permitted</p>
        <p>Among the principle scientists involved are Dr. Langdon Quetin, a marine biologist, and his wife, Dr. Robin Ross, an oceanographer, both of the University of California at Santa Barbara. Among their special interests are krill -- the shrimplike herbivores that are the main food of Antarctic seabirds, mammals and many fish.</p>
        <p>Two other key investigators, also from the University of California at Santa Barbara, are Dr. Raymond C. Smith, a former high-energy physicist who is an expert in remote-sensing underwater instruments, and Dr. Barbara Prezelin, who evaluates the effects of underwater currents and temperature gradients on the flow of nutrients and the prosperity of colonies of algae and higher organisms.</p>
        <p>The increase in ultraviolet radiation, has produced a dilemma for marine organisms, Dr. Prezelin says. On one hand, algae must be near enough the ocean's surface to obtain the solar energy needed for photosynthesis, in which carbon dioxide and water are converted into carbohydrates. But on the other, the closer an organism is to the surface, the more intense is the potentially dangerous ultraviolet radiation to which it is exposed.</p>
        <p>Ultraviolet-B, the most dangerous kind, has been found to have biological effects on organisms as deep as 100 feet below the surface.</p>
        <p>Among the animals at risk are krill. According to Dr. Ross, when krill lay their eggs, the eggs sink to great depths, where they develop in darkness into larvae. But eventually the larvae must rise to the surface to feed on phytoplankton, and at that stage they are vulnerable to ultraviolet.</p>
        <p>"It may be," Dr. Ross said, "that if levels of ultraviolet begin to exceed certain amounts, we will begin to see major declines in the breeding success of krill and many other organisms. One of our present objects is to determine just where the danger point may be." Pigments of Many Colors</p>
        <p>Another principle member of the Palmer Station team, Dr. Deneb Karentz of the University of California at San Francisco, has devoted much of her career to the study of colored compounds called "micosporine-like amino acids." Of 57 species of Antarctic organisms, including invertebrates, fish and algae that Dr. Karentz and her colleagues have studied, some 90 percent contained micosporine-like amino acid pigments, all of them believed to offer protection against ultraviolet radiation. These pigments come in many colors, green, blue-green, red and brown among them, lending color to plankton, sea urchins and countless other organisms.</p>
        <p>The pigments are produced by such plant organisms as algae, and when the algae are eaten by herbivores, notably krill, the krill incorporate the pigments in their own pigment-bearing structures or chromatophores. These, Dr. Karentz said, have proved to serve much the same biological function as that of the melanin pigments in human skin created by tanning: they absorb ultraviolet radiation, preventing it from damaging DNA and other substances essential to life.</p>
        <p>Dr. Karentz and her colleagues have found convincing evidence that increased ultraviolet exposure stimulates marine organisms to produce more micosporine-like amino acid pigments, thereby strengthening their own defenses. More of these chemicals, for instance, are found in the exposed upper parts of barrier reefs than in less exposed parts.</p>
        <p>"The big question is this," she said. "At what point will phytoplankton and other organisms no longer be able to cope with increasing ultraviolet? We know that there must be such a point. We're not yet seeing any collapse of the ecosystem, but we know some organisms are being affected, and any effect is environmentally unacceptable."</p>
        <p>Another member of the Palmer Station group, Dr. Walter C. Dunlap of the Australian Institute of Marine Science, said he believed that natural ultraviolet-absorbing pigments derived from coral reef organisms could be put to use in new commercial products. The Australian branch of the British chemical giant Imperial Chemical Industries has already contended that pigments derived from coral organisms may "revolutionize" the effectiveness of sun-tan products and the durability of automotive paints.</p>
        <p>"Life probably originated in an environment saturated by ultraviolet radiation," Dr. Ross said, "and nature has always found ways to adapt. The trouble is that UV exposure caused by human contamination of the upper atmosphere may be increasing faster now than was normally the case in past episodes. Just how much UV-induced stress can organisms withstand without suffering great harm? We hope Antarctica will soon answer such fundamental questions."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
