<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reporter's Notebook; Networks Focus on Next Season's Upheavals</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="500570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BROADCASTING CO (NBC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CBS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARTER, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANSBURY, ANGELA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COSBY, BILL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DRIVING MISS DAISY (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">COSBY SHOW, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MURDER, SHE WROTE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DB1239F935A25752C0A964958260" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reporter's Notebook; Networks Focus on Next Season's Upheavals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARTER, BILL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although the television season has four months to run and each network has a batch of new series to introduce, the prevailing philosophy among all three big networks is: Wait until next year.</p>
        <p>Several circumstances have combined to shift the focus toward next season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although the television season has four months to run and each network has a batch of new series to introduce, the prevailing philosophy among all three big networks is: Wait until next year.</p>
        <p>Several circumstances have combined to shift the focus toward next season.</p>
        <p>Primary is the conclusion that this season will belong to CBS. Another is the prospect of significant changes in the prime-time landscape next season. One of television's longest-running power sources, Bill Cosby, has confirmed that this will be the last season for his NBC sitcom, "The Cosby Show."</p>
        <p>CBS may drop its hit show "Murder, She Wrote" in favor of another vehicle for its star, Angela Lansbury. The new show would be a television version of "Driving Miss Daisy."</p>
        <p>And though NBC executives said they expected their highest-rated series, "Cheers," to be back for an 11th season, programmers at both the other networks questioned whether NBC would be able to hang on to the show. Jeff Sagansky, president of CBS Entertainment, tried to deal NBC a blow when he hired away the three head writers and executive producers on "Cheers" for a new Bob Newhart comedy.</p>
        <p>Both Robert A. Iger, the president of ABC Entertainment, and Mr. Sagansky said they were considering assaults on NBC with new shows in the 8 P.M. time period that "Cosby" has monopolized for eight years. But NBC is hardly ready to give it up. Warren Littlefield, president of NBC Entertainment, said he planned to create one and maybe two series using stars from the "Cosby" cast. NBC has already made a deal with the 6-year-old actress Raven-Symone and hopes to conclude one with Malcolm-Jamal Warner, who plays Mr. Cosby's son, Theo, on the series.</p>
        <p>In an effort to maintain its dominance of Thursday night, NBC is likely to move its 8:30 hit, "A Different World," to 8 in the fall, followed by a new comedy starring Raven-Symone.</p>
        <p>NBC plans a special final episode for "'The Cosby Show," Mr. Littlefield said, probably longer than half an hour. He said the details would be up to Mr. Cosby.</p>
        <p>As for "Cheers," NBC does not have a deal with the show for next season, but network officials say it can be produced without the current executive-producing team as long as the original creative team of Glen and Les Charles and Jim Burrows is involved.</p>
        <p>During a news conference, Mr. Lit tlefield said that "differences are emerging" among the networks in terms of the styles of shows they are putting on the air and that NBC was emphasizing series "the audience makes a connection to" emotionally.</p>
        <p>He denigrated some recent stop-gap programming by his competitors, each of whom has resurrected a series from the past. CBS now has old episodes of "All in the Family" running on Saturday nights, and ABC is using old "Columbo" movies on Thursdays.</p>
        <p>But programmers at other networks said these shows filled tough time periods with programming that cost much less than a new series.</p>
        <p>Mr. Iger said that ABC had tried to find ways to prevent its lowest-rated shows from hurting the network financially. Re-running old "Columbos" is inexpensive, he said, and so far is improving ABC's ratings on Thursday nights.</p>
        <p>But reviving old programs is not ABC's overall strategy, Mr. Iger said. He pointed to the network's new "Indiana Jones" series as the one new attempt at what he called "event television," or shows that are themselves events.</p>
        <p>"We still believe in 'event' series," he said, citing such recent efforts as "Cop Rock" and "Twin Peaks." "It revitalizes our business. It gets the press talking. It gets audiences really thinking that network television is still quite alive and exciting."</p>
        <p>ABC has also invited several top film makers to create what Mr. Iger called "finite event series," or extended mini-series of up to 11 episodes. The idea would be to tell longer, more ambitious stories that would come to a definite end.</p>
        <p>He said he was not ready to announce any of these series but was close to making a deal with one prominent film maker.</p>
        <p>Another prominent film maker, Steven Spielberg, does have a deal with ABC, Mr. Iger said, for an event series, though not one with a limited run. Mr. Spielberg is preparing a show called "Class of '61," a series set during the Civil War and featuring characters from the West Point graduating class of 1861.</p>
        <p>CBS has its own plans for television event-making, including a significant comeback for the mini-series. Mr. Sagansky announced six of them.</p>
        <p>On the list were the television version of "Scarlett," the "Gone With the Wind" sequel; a sequel to the latest big mini-series success, "Lonesome Dove"; a futuristic examination of the effects of global warming called "The Fire Next Time"; a story of extraterrestrial invaders called "The Intruders"; a follow-up to "Roots" from Alex Haley, about his grandmother, called "Queen," and a biography of Frank Sinatra, which Mr. Sagansky said would not be a "puff piece or whitewash."</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Sagansky announced a slate of series for next fall to be produced by a group of the most respected writer-producers in television, including a romantic comedy from Diane English, the creator of "Murphy Brown"; a political comedy from Linda Bloodworth-Thomason; a comedy-drama from the film maker Robert Zemeckis, and a new drama from the two-time Emmy Award-winning writer and producer of "L.A. Law," David E. Kelley. That one, called "Picket Fences," is an account of small-town life in Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>One reason for CBS's heavy emphasis on its program plans for next fall may be to de-emphasize its midseason replacements, which include one show featuring a dragon puppet and another about a talking dog.</p>
        <p>One CBS executive, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said, "We just have to get through this stuff and get to next fall when we have some shows we're excited about."</p>
        <p>No one at ABC or NBC disputes CBS's claim that it will win the rating race this season, although the point is conceded grudgingly.</p>
        <p>Executives at NBC and ABC tried to undercut CBS's rise from third place in the ratings to first by pointing to the cost for CBS: heavy losses, largely from the high cost of the very sports programs -- the World Series, the Super Bowl, the Winter Olympics -- that will insure CBS's ratings advantage.</p>
        <p>CBS, on the other hand, strongly resists and resents having its turnaround diminished.</p>
        <p>In a press conference here, Howard Stringer, the president of the CBS Broadcast Group, cited the buoyant mood at his network at being the first network to accomplish the feat of climbing from third place to first in one season, an achievement he said was being somewhat obscured by all the talk of financial losses at the network.</p>
        <p>Still, he admitted, CBS, like its competitors, is mainly looking toward the longer-range future. "It's just a beginning," he said. "We've a long way to go before we can even presume to be arrogant."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
