<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Cold War Over, Scientists Are Turning To 'Greener' Pastures</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="566034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LAWRENCE LIVERMORE NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DB1E3AF934A15753C1A964958260" item-length="1264" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Cold War Over, Scientists Are Turning To 'Greener' Pastures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DR. WILLIAM DANNEVIK, Dr. John Ambrosiano and Dr. Mike Wehner are physicists who used to work on nuclear weapons at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California. They have now switched their skills to the task of making better forecasts about global warming.</p>
        <p>Dr. Henry W. Kendall, a 1990 winner of the Nobel Prize in Physics and a longtime anti-nuclear activist, has taken a leave from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology to learn more about human impact on the global environment. His goal is to galvanize the scientific community in the cause of environmental protection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DR. WILLIAM DANNEVIK, Dr. John Ambrosiano and Dr. Mike Wehner are physicists who used to work on nuclear weapons at Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California. They have now switched their skills to the task of making better forecasts about global warming.</p>
        <p>Dr. Henry W. Kendall, a 1990 winner of the Nobel Prize in Physics and a longtime anti-nuclear activist, has taken a leave from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology to learn more about human impact on the global environment. His goal is to galvanize the scientific community in the cause of environmental protection.</p>
        <p>With the cold war over, many scientists are converting both their professional skills and their activist convictions from national security and nuclear weapons to other issues, particularly the environment. This intellectual shift is driven variously by principle, by a growing interest in the environment among younger scientists, by the hunger for new challeges and -- not least -- by the search for new sources of financial support.</p>
        <p>The change comes at a time when the Pentagon is opening up intelligence files to scientists in search of environmental data and when the environment bids to achieve equal billing with national security and economics on the international agenda, as demonstrated by forums like the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro last June. From 'Star Wars' to Global Warming</p>
        <p>Since just after World War II, national security has been a driving force behind American science, the main wellspring of money, the main attracter of talent in many important fields and the main lightning rod for scientists concerned about public issues.</p>
        <p>But now, said Dr. Sidney Drell of Stanford University, "I see more young scientists who are informing themselves and working with environmental issues, and being more attracted to that and less attracted to the traditional bombs and arms-control issues."</p>
        <p>"Being an old warhorse, I still stay with arms issues," said Dr. Drell, one of a group of arms experts who actively opposed the Reagan Administration's "Star Wars" missile-defense plan. "I would be very unhappy if I found everyone was abandoning ship," given the dangers of nuclear proliferation. "But among my colleagues, particularly the younger ones, the interest is certainly shifting."</p>
        <p>In one sign of the times, Dr. Drell added his signature to those of more than 750 scientists who subscribed to a 1990 appeal, organized by the Union of Concerned Scientists, to prevent global warming. "I rarely sign general statements," he said, "but you can see I thought it was important."</p>
        <p>Dr. Kendall believes that human activities "are undermining the life-support capacity of the most important global support systems we have." In line with this thinking, the Union of Concerned Scientists has sharply shifted its emphasis. Three years ago more than three-quarters of its budget went to arms control or national security issues; now about three-quarters is focused on climate change and related issues, said Howard Ris, the executive director.  Skepticism and Diversity</p>
        <p>As with nuclear arms, scientists are divided on environmental issues.  Some, for example, believe that fears about global warming are overblown.</p>
        <p>One prominent doubter is Dr. Robert Jastrow, director of the Mount Wilson Observatory in California and an outspoken promoter of the Star Wars concept in the mid-80's. His skepticism on global warming is often expressed through the George C. Marshall Institute in Washington, of which he is president, and it carried weight with the Bush Administration when John H. Sununu, formerly the President's chief of staff, controlled White House debate on the issue.</p>
        <p>Concerns other than the environment -- health and economic competitiveness, for instance -- are also vying for the attention of scientists shifting from the cold war agenda.</p>
        <p>Lawrence Livermore and Los Alamos, two premier national laboratories that are citadels of nuclear weaponry, have put more emphasis on a wide range of other activities as the nuclear enterprise shrinks. Both are pursuing diverse lines of research, from computer and software development to materials, lasers and sensors, from chaos theory to biomedical projects. Together with Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, they have become major centers of research on mapping the human genetic structure. But the environment and related energy questions stand out, if only because of their prominence as public policy issues.</p>
        <p>At Livermore, Dr. Dannevik, Dr. Ambrosiano and Dr. Wehner still write computer codes for mathematical models. Once the models simulated nuclear explosions; now they simulate the workings of the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>As a Department of Energy installation, Livermore has been trying for some time, as Dr. Dannevik put it, "to develop a next generation of the climate simulation model" in the hope of making better policy decisions on national energy strategy. "The new ingredient," he said, "is the involvement of former weapons and code developers in the area."</p>
        <p>The three physicists, whose ages range from 35 to 44, see their new pursuit as a natural magnet. "It's what people generally call a grand challenge," said Dr. Ambrosiano.</p>
        <p>For Dr. Wehner, the switch has been "like going back to school -- I've had to learn very basic science that normally you'd take as an undergraduate." But he said the transition had been eased by a remarkable similarity between nuclear physics and atmospheric physics: both are complex systems that involve radiation transfer, the flow of gases and fluid dynamics, and both are approached through similar mathematical formulations.</p>
        <p>Given the existence of nuclear weapons elsewhere in the world, those who build bombs often see them as a force for stability and peace. "I share that view," said Dr. Ambrosiano, adding that he saw both his past and present pursuits as constructive.</p>
        <p>And Dr. Wehner said, "I certainly don't regard myself as a peace dividend or as some bomber-turned-green." Climate modeling is appealing, he went on, simply because "it's extremely interesting and it's a very current and relevant interest."</p>
        <p>Similarly, some computer modelers at Los Alamos who used to work on weapons are now working full time on improving models of the workings of the ocean as part of the global climate system. Like Livermore, Los Alamos has diversified its efforts into a variety of fields, like clean energy use.</p>
        <p>At the national laboratories, said Dr. Lou Rosocho, deputy leader of Los Alamos's advanced laser and systems technology group, "there was a whole culture based on the cold war."</p>
        <p>"A lot of people sold their services to the weapons program to do interesting science," he went on. With the winding down of the cold war, the culture was left "wondering just what the hell it was going to do." Out of this identity crisis is emerging a new set of missions in the national interest, he said.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Rosocho joined Los Alamos in 1981 with a private-industry background in developing technologies for clean air and water, he thought he could promote those technologies. "But I discovered very abruptly that no one was interested," he said. "If you had an idea about Star Wars, you got an enthusiastic reception."</p>
        <p>So he went to work trying to help use laser beams to initiate a fusion reaction. A decade later, he works on ways of cleaning up air and water and says that "we've been making significant inroads" on that enterprise.</p>
        <p>"I've come full circle," he said, "and the realization of the need for many of these environmental technologies is here."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
