<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton's Last Selections for the Cabinet Reflect His Quest for Diversity</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="578917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE TRANSITION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERIOR DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BABBITT, BRUCE (BIOGRAPHICAL SKETCH)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DE133FF936A15751C1A964958260" item-length="464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton's Last Selections for the Cabinet Reflect His Quest for Diversity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Babbitt</p>
        <p>Secretary of the Interior</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bruce Babbitt</p>
        <p>Secretary of the Interior</p>
        <p>Bruce Babbitt, the man President-elect Bill Clinton has chosen to be Secretary of the Interior, inherited his interest in the outdoors.</p>
        <p>His forebears were frontier merchants in the canyon country of northern Arizona, and he is now president of the League of Conservation Voters.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups rejoiced today at the selection of Mr. Babbitt, saying they could think of no one better qualified to serve as custodian of the nation's natural resources. 'Excellent Relationship'</p>
        <p>In Arizona, where he was Governor from March 1978 to January 1987, business executives spoke highly of Mr. Babbitt. Wayne M. Kaplan, a spokesman for the Arizona Public Service Company, the state's largest utility, said, "We've had an excellent working relationship with him."</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt, who was also considered for the job of United States Trade Representative in the Clinton Administration, is fluent in Spanish and often expresses his concern about Washington's neglect of Latin America. His wife, Hattie, serves on the board of the Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund. They have two sons.</p>
        <p>Fred Krupp, executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund, said: "As Governor of Arizona, Bruce participated in a real campaign to crack down on the copper smelters. Few governors would have been so concerned about air pollution, the emerging acid rain problem, to make sure that modern technology was installed on each and every copper smelter. That removed a million tons of sulfur dioxide that would have been pouring into Western air every year."</p>
        <p>Mr. Krupp described Mr. Babbitt as "a new-style leader who understands that economic and environmental concerns must be integrated." Less Popular With Labor</p>
        <p>But Mr. Babbitt is less popular with organized labor, which harshly criticized his decision in 1983 to send the National Guard to a Phelps Dodge plant during a strike by the United Steelworkers union.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt, 54, graduated from the University of Notre Dame, where he studied geology, and from Harvard Law School. He sought the Democratic nomination for President in 1988 and was praised for discussing difficult issues, but his style was too thoughtful for most voters. He withdrew from the race after finishing fifth in the Iowa caucuses and sixth in the New Hampshire primary.</p>
        <p>As a Presidential candidate, Mr. Babbitt provided a detailed accounting of his plans to reduce the Federal budget deficit. He had no use for political orthodoxy, and often stated his intention to impose a national sales tax, limit the deduction for home mortgage interest and eliminate some farm subsidies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Babbitt is a partner at the law firm of Steptoe &amp; Johnson, which has offices in Phoenix and Washington.</p>
        <p>THE TRANSITION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
