<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; V.P. Morning Line</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="528535"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DA163CF937A25756C0A964958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; V.P. Morning Line</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because this is Pundits' Ratings Week, issues of substance cannot be discussed here. Only subjects fit for a TV food fight can be considered, which limits us to gee-whizzing meaningless polls or wild speculation about who will be chosen by Presidential nominees to be their running mates.</p>
        <p>I choose the latter because my last experience with polls led to Prime Minister Kinnock, and because of my responsibility as a Great Mentioner, in Russell Baker's classic construct. Anybody mentioned herein will be identified elsewhere for years in yellowing clips as "mentioned for Vice President." (The latest software yellows scanned-in clips.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because this is Pundits' Ratings Week, issues of substance cannot be discussed here. Only subjects fit for a TV food fight can be considered, which limits us to gee-whizzing meaningless polls or wild speculation about who will be chosen by Presidential nominees to be their running mates.</p>
        <p>I choose the latter because my last experience with polls led to Prime Minister Kinnock, and because of my responsibility as a Great Mentioner, in Russell Baker's classic construct. Anybody mentioned herein will be identified elsewhere for years in yellowing clips as "mentioned for Vice President." (The latest software yellows scanned-in clips.)</p>
        <p>Start with the easiest: There will be no dump-Quayle movement at the Republican Convention in Houston. That is because the weak end of the Bush-Quayle team is Mr. Bush, who should be grateful that the confident Dan Quayle is not trying to dump him. It is now the President whose expression is being equated with that of a deer caught in the headlights.</p>
        <p>The Democratic Convention in New York should be a livelier forum for a Veepstakes.</p>
        <p>Conventional conventioneers think that Bill Clinton's choice will be Bill Bradley, but such double-billing is unlikely because Senator Bradley is a political Rip Van Winkle with his alarm clock set for the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Bob Kerrey of Nebraska was media-vetted in the primaries, and can energize the old Gary Hart reformers; his war-hero record would help Mr. Clinton against combat-service Bush and the militaristic Ross Perot.</p>
        <p>But Clinton has an opportunity to exploit the Perot candidacy, which is splitting the Bush vote in Texas.</p>
        <p>Gov. Ann Richards is both a Texas winner and a woman. A safer choice, to give Democrats a real shot at taking that pivotal state's 32 electoral votes, is to put Senator Lloyd Bentsen on the ticket again. He is no spring chicken and would have to quit some golf clubs, but no Democrat wins without Texas and this year's three-way race offers a golden opportunity.</p>
        <p>Other Clinton mentionees are Al Gore and Sam Nunn, both strong in the South, both respectably humorless, with Gore right on Desert Storm and hot on global warming. If Clinton wants to make health care a big deal, he can take Senator Jay Rockefeller, who can also match Mr. Perot's too-rich-to-steal bumper stickers.</p>
        <p>The Clinton camp has assigned Warren Christopher, his putative Secretary of State, to head the "screening process"; in fact, veepstaking is a device to get people thinking of Clinton as a real nominee, facing his first Presidential-class choice, rather than as a press punching bag.</p>
        <p>That's also why Perot is said to be thinking about hiring Gen. Norman Schwarzkopf to be his running mate. (This would panic Mr. Bush into getting Mr. Quayle and Gen. Colin Powell to switch jobs, a daring counterstroke, also cooling L.A.)</p>
        <p>More likely, the Perot machine would turn to somebody who could handle detailed governmental questions on "Meet the Press," the most tough-minded panel show.</p>
        <p>Former Gov. George Deukmejian of California is one possibility. Another is Don Rumsfeld of Illinois, who has been Defense Secretary and White House chief of staff and is now a C.E.O. Senator Warren Rudman of New Hampshire is suitably disgusted with Washington. Wild Perot card: TV's Bill Moyers.</p>
        <p>But if he's smart, our jug-eared jingo will go after Bush's soft underbelly: conservative Republican women, half of whom are angered by the President's anti-abortion position.</p>
        <p>Perot operatives have sounded out Ann McLaughlin, the Reagan Secretary of Labor, named by Fortune magazine as one of the key G.M. directors; she took up the reforming fight that Perot abandoned.</p>
        <p>And last week, when our former U.N. delegate Jeane Kirkpatrick was asked if she would consider being the Clinton running mate, she said no, but added, "if Ross Perot were to ask me, that would be very serious." Her fluent Spanish would help in Florida, Texas, New York and California.</p>
        <p>Best running mate in anybody's campaign this year would be a pro-choice Catholic Hispanic woman from California steeped in foreign affairs who is running a business creating jobs and tax bases in inner cities.</p>
        <p>If anybody with those qualifications turns up, I'll let you know during the next pundits' ratings sweep.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
