<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wasted Energy? Call In the Young Scientists</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="530265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE ENERGY RESEARCH &amp; DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DB1539F932A15756C0A964958260" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wasted Energy? Call In the Young Scientists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Of the more than 200 finalists in a research contest who came here today to display their solutions to the world's energy problems, none had ever waited in a gasoline line, except maybe while in a child safety seat.</p>
        <p>But maybe science students are born with an interest in the subject. Maybe they think an energy crisis will come back in a country that imports half its oil. Or maybe they worry that global energy use may set off catastrophic climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Of the more than 200 finalists in a research contest who came here today to display their solutions to the world's energy problems, none had ever waited in a gasoline line, except maybe while in a child safety seat.</p>
        <p>But maybe science students are born with an interest in the subject. Maybe they think an energy crisis will come back in a country that imports half its oil. Or maybe they worry that global energy use may set off catastrophic climate change.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, more than 1,200 students responded to the invitation of the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority by coming up with energy-saving technology on the cutting edge.</p>
        <p>There was, for example, the "Generadoor," a revolving door of the kind used in office buildings and department stores, modified to make electricity from the force of people pushing it around. That idea, which came from three students at Great Neck South High School on Long Island, won an award. Plan for 'Smart' Window</p>
        <p>So did a project of the three students from Ward Melville High School, in Setauket, L.I., who took an ordinary refrigerator and immersed its cooling coil in water. Water draws off heat better than air, so the refrigerator did the same work using less electricity, and when the water was reused, it gave the water heater a free headstart in its own work.</p>
        <p>There were other plans for making energy from waves, sunlight and wind, for using mutant strains of yeast to produce ethanol fuel, for using bacteria to take the sulfur out of coal, and for improving the energy efficiency of everything from light bulbs to windows to toasters.</p>
        <p>There was a working model of a machine that raises window shades on sunny days in winter, and lowers them on sunny days in summer, and a plan for a "smart" window that would change color with the time of day and season for more efficient heating and cooling.</p>
        <p>"These are offshoots of existing knowledge, ventures into little-known areas," said Murray D. Perl, a biology and research teacher at John F. Kennedy High School in the Bronx, and, as an adviser to student competitors, a veteran of the annual contest since 1985. Feuding Between Regions</p>
        <p>That is in some ways similar to what the authority pays adult researchers to do, said Mary Jean Frank, a spokeswoman for the authority.</p>
        <p>Budget constraints are another parallel between the contest and real life, although they are stricter for the high school students, who received grants of $500 at most.</p>
        <p>And, in an Albany tradition, the contest carries on an upstate-downstate feud. To the upstate science teachers, the contest seems to be in large part an intramural battle among three New York City schools: Bronx Science, John F. Kennedy and Stuyvesant. The state energy research authority, in an effort to broaden the competition, recently changed the rules to establish five slots for high schools that have not previously taken part: a gift to the smallest schools upstate.</p>
        <p>Students feel the tension, but it is their teachers who suffer the most. They are not allowed in the convention hall while the projects are judged, and the judges are forbidden to ask the students which school they attend. While the teachers pace outside the hall like expectant fathers in the maternity ward, the authority tries to break the tension by sending them on a tour of historic sites in Albany. 'Nasty for a Minute'</p>
        <p>"There is almost animosity," said Mary P. Colvard, a biology teacher from Cobleskill in Schoharie County. "It felt nasty for a minute or two," she said of this year's meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perl, of John F. Kennedy in the Bronx, had some awkward praise for entries from rural schools.</p>
        <p>"The upstate schools are oriented toward industrial arts," he said. "Their projects are beautiful."</p>
        <p>His school's projects, he said, tend more toward scientific explanation. By his count, his school was far in the lead, earning 30 plaquesover the last 10 years. Today, Kennedy won one more for a study of ship-fuel efficiency by Dmitriy Rogozhnikov, for whom Mr. Perl was one of two advisers. Magnetic Levitation</p>
        <p>The schools get plaques for winning entries, the students who submit those entries receive savings bonds, and all contestants receive certificates for taking part.</p>
        <p>The young scientists, like their older counterparts, encountered setbacks as well as triumphs. For example, the magnetic levitation train built by two 14-year-olds, Benjamin Lubin and Ken Fujiuchi, turned into the Hubble Telescope of the competition. The two ninth graders said it worked fine back at Manhasset Junior-Senior High School, before it was loaded on a bus.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Lubin valiantly tried to explain the system's operation to a judge, Mr. Fujiuchi tried frantically to fix the train -- a piece of polystyrene with magnets attached that was supposed to move along a sensor system on the seven-foot-long display.</p>
        <p>"It does go, it just crashes after a little while," the judge said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
