<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Orders End to Manufacture Of Ozone-Harming Agents by '96</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="507425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHYL CHLOROFORM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON TETRACHLORIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1130F930A25751C0A964958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Orders End to Manufacture Of Ozone-Harming Agents by '96</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In response to new evidence that the earth's atmospheric ozone shield may be weakening over parts of the United States, President Bush today ordered American manufacturers to end by Dec. 31, 1995, virtually all production of chemicals that destroy ozone.</p>
        <p>The policy, authorized under a provision of the 1990 Clean Air Act, takes effect immediately. Last Friday the Bush Administration reversed its opposition to such a plan and backed a Senate proposal to phase out the production of the chemicals as soon as possible, rather than by 2000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In response to new evidence that the earth's atmospheric ozone shield may be weakening over parts of the United States, President Bush today ordered American manufacturers to end by Dec. 31, 1995, virtually all production of chemicals that destroy ozone.</p>
        <p>The policy, authorized under a provision of the 1990 Clean Air Act, takes effect immediately. Last Friday the Bush Administration reversed its opposition to such a plan and backed a Senate proposal to phase out the production of the chemicals as soon as possible, rather than by 2000.</p>
        <p>The action today not only affects a dozen chemical companies and thousands of manufacturing workers across the country, but also puts enormous pressure on makers of automobile air conditioners, computer equipment, fire prevention systems and refrigerators and other industrial users of the chemicals to redesign their equipment. The chemicals are chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, halons, methyl chloroform and carbon tetrachloride.</p>
        <p>"It's a substantial step, one that we believed was warranted by the scientific evidence, but nevertheless still a big job for us," said Kevin Fay, the executive director of the Alliance for Responsible CFC Policy, a coalition of users and producers of the chemicals.</p>
        <p>The new policy was formulated by a committee of top Administration officials including William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency; Michael R. Deland, the chairman of the President's Council on Environmental Quality, and Samuel K. Skinner, the White House chief of staff.</p>
        <p>"There is a scientific consensus that these chemicals are destructive to ozone in the atmosphere," Mr. Reilly said today in an interview, "and this Administration has a record of responding quickly to that threat."</p>
        <p>Experts with several of the nation's prominent environmental groups praised the action but said more aggressive steps were necessary to halt the deterioration of the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>"This is a modest step in the right direction but not all that is required to protect the ozone layer," said David Doniger, a lawyer at the Natural Resources Defense Council in Washington. "What we've asked the Environmental Protection Agency to do under the Clean Air Act is to phase out halons immediately. We asked that methyl chloroform be eliminated by beginning of next year. And we want CFC production to be eliminated by the end of 1994. That is what Germans have already announced, and we should at least match them."</p>
        <p>The effects of the loss of ozone are to increase ultraviolet radiation that reaches the earth's surface and may result in rates of skin cancer and cataracts. Other scientists have hypothesized that rates of growth of plants and other organisms may also be affected.</p>
        <p>The President's order affects a family of chlorine- and bromine-based chemicals, widely used as solvents, refrigerants and fire retardants and as feedstocks for other chemicals. Developed in 1931 by the General Motors Corporation, they were considered among the most useful compounds ever invented.</p>
        <p>But as early as 1974, chemists at the University of Michigan and the University of California at Irvine recognized that hundreds of millions of pounds of the compounds were escaping and accumulating in the atmosphere every year. The chemists found that sunlight broke up the CFC molecules and that the freed chlorine atoms were capable of destroying ozone in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Last week the National Aeronautics and Space Administration made public preliminary data gathered by high-altitude aircraft and satellites that showed the highest levels ever found in the upper atmosphere of chlorine monoxide, the active compound that destroys ozone. That finding followed a succession of announcements in the last year showing that the man-made chlorine was responsible for ozone losses in the upper atmosphere outside of the polar regions in the middle latitudes, including the United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
