<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What About Oil?; The Gulf War Put the Focus on Supplies, But a New Energy Bill Skips That Issue</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD8163DF93AA15756C0A964958260" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What About Oil?; The Gulf War Put the Focus on Supplies, But a New Energy Bill Skips That Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sixteen months after the nation went to war over oil in the Persian Gulf, an energy bill is taking final shape in Washington, yet the focus is everywhere but on oil.</p>
        <p>Two similar versions, one passed by the House Wednesday and the other by the Senate in February, do, however, include a variety of significant measures, most importantly affecting electric utilities. Those changes would increase efficiency in lights, appliances and motors, improve the natural gas supply for utilities and other customers, and, possibly, remove one of many stumbling blocks to building nuclear plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sixteen months after the nation went to war over oil in the Persian Gulf, an energy bill is taking final shape in Washington, yet the focus is everywhere but on oil.</p>
        <p>Two similar versions, one passed by the House Wednesday and the other by the Senate in February, do, however, include a variety of significant measures, most importantly affecting electric utilities. Those changes would increase efficiency in lights, appliances and motors, improve the natural gas supply for utilities and other customers, and, possibly, remove one of many stumbling blocks to building nuclear plants.</p>
        <p>"I would call it a positive first step on the way to something we don't ever seem to achieve, which is a comprehensive national energy policy," said Wilfrid L. Kohl, director of the international energy program at the Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies. That, he said, would require a stiff gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>Such a tax was not seriously discussed in Washington, but with the United States now importing about half its crude oil and destined to import more in the future, and with the economy resonating with every big oil-price movement, there was no shortage of proposals to cut the nation's consumption or increase its supply.</p>
        <p>Congress seriously considered drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge, requiring more fuel efficiency in cars and rapidly filling the Strategic Petroleum Reserve. But in the end, the House or Senate rejected all three.</p>
        <p>This was probably essential to the energy bill's survival, because opponents of either Arctic drilling or stricter gas-mileage requirements could probably have sunk the package; certainly they could have done so together.  A Lack of Will</p>
        <p>"The most potentially valuable provisions were the most controversial, and there wasn't the will to tackle them," said Eli Bergman, director of Americans for Energy Independence, a Washington-based interest group.</p>
        <p>"Senators and Congressmen will whisper that the thing that would do the most would be a $1 hike in the gasoline tax," he said. "They'll whisper it, but they won't do anything about it." In fact, last fall Congress choked on adding a nickel.</p>
        <p>The result is an energy bill pushed into the public eye by the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait, but which, paradoxically, is hardly relevant to the oil-related aspects of the war. The notable exception -- extending for 10 years some bans on offshore drilling -- is a negative for the industry.</p>
        <p>"At least," mused Lawrence J. Goldstein, the president of the Petroleum Industry Research Foundation, "they were smart enough to realize they've done nothing to deal with U.S. security." A Two-Year History</p>
        <p>The bill, now the National Energy Strategy, began life two years ago as the National Energy Security Act, intended to reduce the impact of oil shocks, Mr. Goldstein pointed out. But reaching political consensus on oil in a nation so divided between the interests of producers and consumers will evidently require a bigger oil crisis or a bloodier war.</p>
        <p>The bill's most important provision is, for the public, obscure and barely comprehensible: revising a 50-year-old law on electric company monopolies. The change might cut electricity bills in the future, but the case is far from clear-cut. It will probably create a bigger cast of characters in the business of building generating stations, but much will depend on the outcome of the House-Senate conference on the bill, because the two houses set different terms for those generators to have access to utility-owned transmission lines.</p>
        <p>The House bill's second-most important provision will aid in raising the efficiency of electric lights, motors and appliances. But in this role the Federal Government is merely helping along what the states and utilities are doing already.</p>
        <p>The bill may not really deserve the title "strategy," but there are a wide variety of provisions. One would provide $927 million between now and 1996 for conservation and development of renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>But more than half of that "expenditure" is a Federal agreement not to jeopardize existing state conservation programs. At the urging of the states, utilities are making cash grants to electricity consumers to buy more efficient equipment, and Washington has been threatening to tax those grants, in effect putting a brake on the states' conservation programs. The House bill makes utility grants to residential customers tax-free, along with two-thirds of the grants to industries and businesses.  Billions for Renewables</p>
        <p>The rest of the money would be used to encourage production of electricity from the sun, the wind, crop wastes and the heat of the earth's core. In contrast, more than $800 million was given to independent oil producers, in the form of tax exemptions from the Alternative Minimum Tax provisions of the Federal tax code.</p>
        <p>The bill authorizes billions of dollars for research and development, into coal, nuclear power and renewable fuels. The slice for renewables is larger than approved in recent years, but environmentalists say they are waiting to see how much is appropriated.</p>
        <p>"It's O.K. as far as it goes," Mr. Bergman said. "It's almost incredible that we even get an energy bill this year, when the price of gasoline is at historic lows and the country has a hell of a lot of other problems."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bergman's group was perhaps the only one to favor both drilling in the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge and an increase in automobile fuel efficiency, alternatives that were initially put forward as tacitly balanced, with at least a third of the Congress vehemently opposed to one or the other.</p>
        <p>At the Sierra Club, which feels good about the outcome in the Arctic and bereft over the failure to require higher-mileage cars, Daniel F. Becker, a lobbyist, said, "We're calling it half a good energy package."</p>
        <p>"It's marginally better than nothing," said Mr. Goldstein of the Petroleum Industry Research Foundation.</p>
        <p>Representative Ron Wyden, an Oregon Democrat on the Energy and Commerce Committee, said that while oil companies should have been forced to pay for the expansion of the Strategic Petroleum Reserve, he supported the bill for its many other provisions.</p>
        <p>"Any way you slice it, this bill helps our nation reduce its dependence on foreign oil," he said, pointing specifically to the sections on conservation and electric utilities.</p>
        <p>But the United States is not without an energy policy. The leading Federal component, according to oil experts and environmentalists, is disguised as the Clean Air Act of 1990, which encourages the use of methanol, natural gas and electricity to run cars. Influence of California</p>
        <p>Perhaps more significant is the California Air Resources Board, whose regulations on cars appear likely to be adopted in several large Northeastern states, perhaps almost all of them. Those regulations appear to require huge numbers of electric vehicles, along with others running on methanol and natural gas.</p>
        <p>There are other components of the energy bill that appear likely to have a long-term impact, although not on oil. Almost no one is happy with the present system for deciding whether natural gas pipelines should be built, and the energy bill would make it easier to win approval. The electric efficiency provisions will also probably increase the average efficiency of refrigerators, lights and similar devices in years to come.</p>
        <p>There is also a wild card: a change in the rules for licensing nuclear power plants. The change has no immediate importance, but reduces one of the many obstacles to a revival of that industry.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
