<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>UTILITY IS SELLING RIGHT TO POLLUTE</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="527904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1990</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TENNESSEE VALLEY AUTHORITY AND PROJECT (TVA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WISCONSIN POWER &amp; LIGHT CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD71E3BF931A25756C0A964958260" item-length="1651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>UTILITY IS SELLING RIGHT TO POLLUTE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two utilities hundreds of miles apart will announce today that they have signed a contract that calls for one to buy from the other the right to emit a chemical that causes acid rain, freeing the dirtier one from having to clean up its own plants as stringently.</p>
        <p>It is the first such deal to be publicly disclosed, say those involved and other experts, and could break the ice for dozens of similar deals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two utilities hundreds of miles apart will announce today that they have signed a contract that calls for one to buy from the other the right to emit a chemical that causes acid rain, freeing the dirtier one from having to clean up its own plants as stringently.</p>
        <p>It is the first such deal to be publicly disclosed, say those involved and other experts, and could break the ice for dozens of similar deals.</p>
        <p>The Tennessee Valley Authority will buy the right to emit 10,000 tons of sulfur dioxide, the main cause of acid rain, from Wisconsin Power and Light. The Wisconsin company will reduce its emissions to a level 10,000 tons below what Federal law requires, and the T.V.A. will get additional time to install smokestack scrubbers or replace high-sulfur coal with cleaner fuels. Deal Over $2.5 Million</p>
        <p>The price was not disclosed but is believed to be around $2.5 million to $3 million.</p>
        <p>The deal was made under a system established in the Clean Air Act of 1990 and will be regulated by the Environmental Protection Agency. Acid rain, which is believed to be responsible for severe damage to lakes and forests, is one of two main targets of the Clean Air Act. The other target is smog and toxic chemical emissions.</p>
        <p>Economists and some environmentalists have long called for a "market-based" system that encourages deals like the one to be announced today. They say such a system reduces the cost to the economy of cutting sulfur emissions, compared with a "command and control" system of ordering each utility to comply. The goal of the Clean Air Act is to reduce such emissions by 10 million tons a year. The T.V.A. is buying "emission allowances" because it believes that at least in the short run the purchase price is less than what it would cost to clean up its own plants enough. For its part, Wisconsin Power can turn a profit by "overcomplying" with the Federal law and selling the allowances.</p>
        <p>The idea of trading emission allowances has generally won praise as creating a "win-win" deal, in which costs are minimized and everyone benefits. Some authorities estimate a savings of 20 percent compared with making each utility comply.</p>
        <p>Such deals create the possibility that sulfur dioxide emissions will fall more in some locations than in others. In most cases, a local group that opposed plans by a utility to buy emission allowances rather than cut emissions could presumably contest the decision before state regulators, but in this case opponents, if they emerge, would appear to have few options because the T.V.A. is not subject to such state regulation.</p>
        <p>But the 10,000 tons represents only a small fraction of the reduction required at the T.V.A., and the authority anticipates meeting the rest of it internally. In fact, experts say that most utilities that buy allowances will meet only a portion of their needs that way.</p>
        <p>Utilities have thus far been slow to strike such deals. Since the first phase of the law takes effect in 1995 and scrubbers usually take 36 months to build, some appear to have decided to forgo the market.</p>
        <p>But this deal could lead the way for others, said John S. Palmisano, president of Aer*x, a subsidiary of Electronic Data Systems, which is seeking to broker similar arrangements. "It's like going to a church dance, with the boys on one side and the girls on another," he said. "Sooner or later, somebody's going to walk into the middle."</p>
        <p>This deal will form a benchmark, he said, with other potential buyers and sellers wanting to peg their prices against this one.</p>
        <p>John B. Henry 2d, the president of Clean Air Capital Markets, a small Washington-based investment banking firm that arranged the contract, said the contract was important because it was the first and because the price was low. "It sends a clear signal to the industry that allowances can be purchased below the cost of most scrubbers," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Henry said scrubbers would become financially attractive on a wide basis if the cost of allowances rose to $300 to $350 a ton.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Henry said, buying allowances could be easier for utilities than relying on cleaner fuels that would have to be shipped from far away. A utility that bought allowances, he said, would often, in effect, be buying the benefit of the seller's having switched to cleaner fuels available locally.</p>
        <p>But for the moment, the terms of this contract, which was signed on May 1, are not clear. Mr. Henry refused to discuss its terms, and neither would top officials of the two utilities. But William F. Malec, the senior vice president and chief financial officer of the T.V.A., said that a report in The Wall Street Journal yesterday that first disclosed the deal and said the price would be $250 to $300 a ton was "in the ballpark."</p>
        <p>Such a price would be on the low end of what experts had expected. But Mr. Malec and Erroll B. Davis Jr., the chief executive of Wisconsin Power, pointedly refused to say when the money would be paid -- now, in 1995 or later. If it is not paid now, the cost of money would have to be figured in, and the value could be less.</p>
        <p>When the Clean Air Act was signed by President Bush, some had estimated that a single allowance, or the right to emit one ton of sulfur dioxide, would be worth about $1,000 on the open market, but with improving technology for lowering such emissions, along with other factors, recent estimates have been lower.</p>
        <p>If the cost of removing a ton of sulfur dioxide from the air is in fact lower than expected, that is good news for electricity users because it means the total cost of compliance with the Clean Air Act will be lower. But it may be bad news for companies that invested heavily in expensive pollution-control hardware, expecting to recoup the cost through sales of allowances.</p>
        <p>The limits are set in terms of pounds of sulfur dioxide per unit of heat produced in utility boilers, keying them, in effect, to electricity production. The limit is set at one level from 1995 to 1999, and a stricter level beginning in 2000. In addition, new plants will have a limit of zero, meaning that for each ton of sulfur dioxide they produce, they must buy an allowance from the owner of an older plant who is willing, for a price, to clean up.</p>
        <p>In the case of the deal to be announced today, Mr. Davis said, "these prices are going to come out eventually, as we go into regulatory proceedings." But his company does not want to divulge the number now, he said, because "we're hoping that the market is a bit more robust" and prices of allowances will rise.</p>
        <p>Establishing the market price is important, according to another expert, Robert D. Conley, the president of Pure Air Inc. of Allentown, Pa., because utilities that are considering buying pollution allowances are weighing that option against installing pollution-control hardware or switching to lower-sulfur fuel, or both. Likewise, a company that is considering making the investment to "overcomply" wants to know what the allowances would sell for. If this deal and others that will presumably follow in coming weeks do not establish a price, then the industry will probably have to wait for an auction of extra allowances that the Environmental Protection Agency is planning to hold in early 1993.</p>
        <p>Mr. Conley said that the T.V.A.-Wisconsin deal was probably small by the standards of those that will follow. Utilities typically need tens of thousands of tons of allowances, or more than 100,000, each year, he said. A Geographic Shift</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act is meant to cut acid emissions roughly in half, but the trading system also has the potential to shift the emissions geographically, if buyers are concentrated in one region and sellers in another. Mr. Henry, the investment banker, described the establishment of the trading system as "like a magic legal wand was waved, and all utilities in the country became one utility for purposes of acid rain control."</p>
        <p>Most environmentalists consider acid rain a national problem, not a regional one, unlike, for example, smog, which is more local in nature. The emissions trading system was passed largely at the impetus of the Environmental Defense Fund, a nonprofit environmental group.</p>
        <p>Acid created in power plants can be deposited hundreds of miles from the source, with rain or snow. Some state regulators, however, have proposed limiting allowance trading to within their borders, instead of allowing utilities in their jurisdictions to clean up their stacks and sell the allowances to utilities upwind, with the resulting pollution coming back to the original state. But experts yesterday said no state had yet instituted such restrictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Malec and others involved in the deal said it should not be construed as the sale of the right to pollute. He stressed that the sum of emissions by the T.V.A. and by Wisconsin Power and Light would be equal to the total permitted by the new law. The 10,000 allowances, a small fraction of the reduction the T.V.A. will need, will give the authority some breathing room in case modifications to boilers or fuel switching arrangements are delayed, he said.</p>
        <p>It is also a small fraction of the allowances that Wisconsin has available to sell. Under a state law, it has been held to stricter standards than those set by Washington, and passage of the act turned that "overcompliance" into a salable asset.</p>
        <p>Generally, however, sellers have been held back in part because state regulators have not ruled on the question of who benefits from the proceeds, the stockholders or the electric customers. Thus, utilities have been reluctant to take the risk of investing in scrubbers or other equipment to create "overcompliance" because their shareholders might not benefit, and if the sale of the allowances does not recoup the costs, their shareholders might actually suffer.</p>
        <p>Wisconsin regulators have not decided how the sale proceeds will be treated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
