<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE TRANSITION: Energy Policy; CLINTON TO REVAMP ENERGY DEPT. ROLE</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="572308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSITION BETWEEN ADMINISTRATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REAGAN, RONALD WILSON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA1238F930A15752C1A964958260" item-length="1759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE TRANSITION: Energy Policy; CLINTON TO REVAMP ENERGY DEPT. ROLE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President-elect Bill Clinton is prepared to give the Department of Energy a dominant role in his efforts to marry the goals of creating jobs, making industry more efficient and reducing environmental damage, transition advisers say.</p>
        <p>Those working on the plans say they reflect Mr. Clinton's desire to transform a bureaucracy largely ignored for most of the Reagan-Bush years into an aggressive player in integrating environmental goals into economic policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President-elect Bill Clinton is prepared to give the Department of Energy a dominant role in his efforts to marry the goals of creating jobs, making industry more efficient and reducing environmental damage, transition advisers say.</p>
        <p>Those working on the plans say they reflect Mr. Clinton's desire to transform a bureaucracy largely ignored for most of the Reagan-Bush years into an aggressive player in integrating environmental goals into economic policy.</p>
        <p>The blueprint being put together by industry executives as well as staff members close to Mr. Clinton and Vice President-elect Al Gore conforms with the promises Mr. Clinton made during the campaign. He said he wanted to wean the nation from its reliance on coal and oil by converting to cleaner, less costly alternatives like natural gas, using tax incentives and research money to encourage development of renewable resources and expanding the American role in the global market for pollution control equipment and services.</p>
        <p>The longer-term goal is to revitalize industry and make the United States more competitive with Japanese and German manufacturers, whose energy efficiency gives them far lower production costs.</p>
        <p>Staff members close to Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore said that to signal the new direction they had identified several actions the President-elect could take immediately by executive order or policy change. Among the proposed actions are these:</p>
        <p>*Converting hundreds of thousands of Federal vehicles to compressed natural gas, which burns more cleanly than gasoline and is less expensive. President Bush issued such an order, but it covers only a fraction of the vehicles in the fleets operated by the Postal Service, the military and other Federal agencies.</p>
        <p>*Accelerating a long-delayed program requiring more efficient energy use in buildings and appliances. Besides encouraging the development of new technology, this would save money as well as fuel, especially for the Federal Government, the advisers say. They added that it would showcase new techniques and provide a market for them.</p>
        <p>*Shifting the Government's research priorities to conservation technologies and renewable resources like wind, sun and water. The department's research program now favors development of nuclear energy and coal.</p>
        <p>* Making available to private industry the new technologies the department is developing in its $5.5-billion-a-year program to clean up the environmental damage from nuclear weapons plants across the country.</p>
        <p>The planning underscores the potential influence of Mr. Gore, one of whose main interests is the environment, as a guiding force behind the new approach. One important figure on the environment-economy transition team is Kathleen McGinty, a 29-year-old lawyer from Philadelphia who became Mr. Gore's chief environmental specialist when she joined his Senate staff in 1989.</p>
        <p>"There is no question that Governor Clinton is prepared to make the Department of Energy an integral component of our long-term economic strategy," said George Stephanopoulos, the director of communications for the transition. "He has not made any final decision on personnel or specific policies. These are options prepared by his staff, and he is reviewing them."</p>
        <p>The advisers on the transition team said Senator Timothy E. Wirth of Colorado, the chairman of the Senate Energy subcommittee on conservation, who did not seek re-election, and Thomas F. McLarty 3d, chairman and chief executive of Arkla Inc., a natural gas utility in Little Rock and one of four board members of Mr. Clinton's transition, head the short list of candidates under consideration by Mr. Clinton for Energy Secretary. Mr. Wirth is also under consideration to be as Secretary of the Interior, the advisers said.</p>
        <p>Both agencies have been lumped together with several others in the transition planning in an effort to integrate the economic, environmental and natural-resource issues they encompass. Others in the group are the Environmental Protection Agency, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the Department of Agriculture, and the Department of Commerce.</p>
        <p>Mr. McLarty went to kindergarten with the President-elect in Hope, Ark., and has been a close friend ever since. He is well regarded in the industry, and Mr. Clinton touted him as a possible energy secretary during campaign swings through Texas when he discussed energy policy with oil and gas industry executives. Mr. McLarty did not respond to messages left with the transition staff and his company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wirth is also well versed on the considerable environmental problems that plague the Energy Department's nuclear weapons industry, which includes the Rocky Flats plutonium plant near Denver. Mr. Wirth was in Europe last week on vacation and could not be reached. Friends in Congress and in Colorado said he was reluctant to talk about his plans but might be interested in becoming Energy Secretary given Mr. Clinton's desire to make the Energy Department central to his economic and environmental policy.</p>
        <p>"From Day 1, you'll see an Energy Department moving very aggressively, and the reason is that a new direction makes sense for jobs, for the economy, for our balance of trade and for a cleaner environment," said Bill Burton, a lawyer in Austin, Tex., who coordinated the Clinton-Gore campaign's strategy on energy issues. "An energy policy based on cheap foreign oil is shameful, and it will change."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton himself signaled the change in a news conference 10 days ago. "I have read, at least in my history books, that some Cabinet appointments are considered major and others are considered minor," he said. "I don't know how you would consider the Departments of Commerce and Energy in that regard, but from the kind of economic policy I have laid out, and the things that I think we have to do to change this country economically, those are very major appointments."</p>
        <p>Among other candidates on the list for Energy Secretary, the advisers said, are Gov. David Walters of Oklahoma, a national co-chairman of the Clinton-Gore campaign; Garry Mauro, the Texas Land Commissioner and chairman of the Clinton-Gore campaign in Texas; Michael L. Beatty, executive vice president and general counsel of the Coastal Corporation in Houston who was an important fund-raiser for Mr. Clinton, and Daniel H. Yergin, president of Cambridge Energy Research Associates in Massachusetts and a research associate at Harvard University who won a Pulitzer Prize this year for his history of the oil industry, titled "The Prize: The Epic Quest for Oil, Money and Power."</p>
        <p>The Department of Energy was established in 1977 to help solve the problem of America's dependence on imported oil, but it has been a largely forgotten bureaucracy.</p>
        <p>In the late 1980's, for reasons that neither President Reagan nor President Bush anticipated, the department became the focus of attention for its mismanagement of the Government's nuclear production plants, laboratories and testing grounds. The end of cold war has produced new opportunities for reordering the department's mission while at the same time advancing Mr. Clinton's agenda for jobs, new technologies, and environmental protection.</p>
        <p>Ms. McGinty is helping to select teams to interview officials in the Department of Energy, the Department of the Interior and the other domestic environmental agencies beginning early next month. That research is intended to help the incoming Cabinet members and their deputies understand which policy decisions made by the Bush and Reagan Administrations should be kept or rejected.</p>
        <p>Requiring Federal vehicles to convert to natural gas is one of an array of measures that Mr. Clinton is preparing as an attempt to strengthen energy production and exploration in this country. The American industry lost 500,000 jobs during the 1980's, more than the auto and steel industries combined, the Department of Commerce has reported.</p>
        <p>Industry executives said roughly 20 trillion cubic feet of natural gas, all of it domestically produced, is used each year in the United States, and each increase of a trillion cubic feet in production could result in 50,000 to 70,000 additional jobs. It is not known how many jobs might be lost in the coal and oil refining industries, which would suffer declines in sales as use of natural gas increased.</p>
        <p>The acceleration of the long-delayed program to raise the energy efficiency standards for buildings and appliances would both conserve fuel and save money, especially for the Federal Government, which spends $4 billion annually to heat and cool its buildings, said James Wolf, executive director of the Alliance to Save Energy, a research group in Washington.</p>
        <p>"The highest priority for new technology is to develop a market," said Mr. Wolf, who helped to write a blueprint for energy policy that was requested by Mr. Clinton's energy advisers. "The new Administration has the opportunity to make Government buildings showcases for new energy technology."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's advisers also said the President-elect wanted an aggressive Energy Secretary who would use the office to change energy research priorities. Of the $3 billion that the Department plans to spend this fiscal year on civilian research and development programs, $1.3 billion is set aside for the development of coal and nuclear energy. Just $212 million is devoted to inventing new machines to take advantage of wind, sun, water, and other renewable energy sources, while $310 million is to be spent of energy conservation measures.</p>
        <p>"A different philosophy will be exercised in the Clinton Administration," said Christopher Flavin, vice president for research at the Worldwatch Institute in Washington. "It will look more like the European industrial strategy where governments work with different industries and accelerate the commercialization of technologies."</p>
        <p>The department's research budget, particularly the program for developing new methods of restoring land contaminated by toxic materials, is spurring the American industrial sector for new pollution control equipment and services. Michael Silverstein, an environmental economist from Philadelphia, said the American share of the $50 billion international market for such equipment and services is $6 billion a year and growing.</p>
        <p>"The salient point, one that is just as important as the technology, is how much political capital Clinton and Gore are willing to invest to make America one of the dominant players in the international environmental cleanup market," Mr. Silverstein said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
