<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From the Platform: A 'New Covenant' With Americans</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Convention" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="542937"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE DEMOCRATIC PLATFORM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS, NATIONAL (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D61E30F936A25754C0A964958260" item-length="2761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From the Platform: A 'New Covenant' With Americans</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the platform adopted by the Democratic National Convention last night. PREAMBLE</p>
        <p>The last 12 years have been a nightmare of Republican irresponsibility and neglect. America's leadership is indifferent at home and uncertain in the world. Republican mismanagement has disarmed government as an instrument to make our economy work and support the people's most basic values, needs and hopes. The Republicans brought America a false and fragile prosperity based on borrowing, not income, and so will leave behind a mountain of public debt and a backbreaking annual burden in interest. It is wrong to borrow to spend on ourselves, leaving our children to pay our debts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the platform adopted by the Democratic National Convention last night. PREAMBLE</p>
        <p>The last 12 years have been a nightmare of Republican irresponsibility and neglect. America's leadership is indifferent at home and uncertain in the world. Republican mismanagement has disarmed government as an instrument to make our economy work and support the people's most basic values, needs and hopes. The Republicans brought America a false and fragile prosperity based on borrowing, not income, and so will leave behind a mountain of public debt and a backbreaking annual burden in interest. It is wrong to borrow to spend on ourselves, leaving our children to pay our debts.</p>
        <p>We hear the anguish and the anger of the American people. We know it is directed not just at the Republican administrations that have had power but at Government itself.</p>
        <p>Their anger is justified. We can no longer afford business as usual -- neither the policies of the last 12 years of tax breaks for the rich, mismanagement, lack of leadership and cuts in services for the middle class and the poor, nor the adoption of new programs and new spending without new thinking.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Therefore we call for A REVOLUTION IN GOVERNMENT -- to take power away from entrenched bureaucracies and narrow interests in Washington and put it back in the hands of ordinary people.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>To make this revolution, we seek a NEW COVENANT to repair the damaged bond between the American people and their government, that will expand OPPORTUNITY, insist upon greater individual RESPONSIBILITY in return, restore COMMUNITY and insure NATIONAL SECURITY in a profoundly new era.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>I. OPPORTUNITY</p>
        <p>Our party's first priority is opportunity -- broad-based, non inflationary economic growth and the opportunity that flows from it. Democrats in 1992 hold nothing more important for America than an economy that offers growth and jobs for all.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>We reject both the do-nothing government of the last 12 years and the big government theory that says we can hamstring business and tax and spend our way to prosperity. Instead we offer a third way. Just as we have always viewed working men and women as the bedrock of our economy, we honor business as a noble endeavor and vow to create a far better climate for firms and independent contractors of all sizes that empower their workers, revolutionize their work places, respect the environment and serve their communities well.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>INVESTING IN AMERICA The only way to lay the foundation for renewed American prosperity is to spur both public and private investment. . . .</p>
        <p>To begin making our economy grow, the President and Congress should agree that savings from defense must be reinvested productively at home, including research, education and training, and other productive investments. We will create a "future budget" for investments that make us richer, to be kept separate from those parts of the budget that pay for the past and present. For the private sector, instead of a sweeping capital gains windfall to the wealthy and those who speculate, we will create an investment tax credit and a capital gains reduction for patient investors in emerging technologies and new business.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>THE DEFICIT Addressing the deficit requires fair and shared sacrifice of all Americans for the common good. . . . We must also tackle spending by putting everything on the table, eliminate nonproductive programs, achieve defense savings, reform entitlement programs to control soaring health-care costs, cut Federal administrative costs by 3 percent annually for four years, limit increases in the "present budget" to the rate of growth in the average American's paycheck, apply a strict "pay as you go" rule to new noninvestment spending and make the rich pay their fair share in taxes. These choices will be made while protecting senior citizens and without further victimizing the poor. . . .</p>
        <p>THE CITIES . . . A national public works investment and infrastructure program will provide jobs and strengthen our cities. . . . We will encourage the flow of investment to inner-city development and housing through targeted enterprise zones and incentives for private and public pension funds to invest in urban and rural projects.</p>
        <p>AGRICULTURE AND THE RURAL COMMUNITY All Americans, producers and consumers alike, benefit when our food and fiber are produced by hundreds of thousands of family farmers receiving a fair price for their products.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>WORKERS' RIGHTS . . . We will act against sexual harassment in the workplace. We will honor the work ethic -- by expanding the earned-income tax credit. . . .</p>
        <p>LIFELONG LEARNING . . . We oppose the Bush Administration's efforts to bankrupt the public school system . . . through private school vouchers. . . . We will expand child health and nutrition programs and extend Head Start to all eligible children, and guarantee all children access to quality, affordable child care. . . . We will adopt a national apprenticeship-style program to ease the transition from school to work for noncollege-bound students, so they can acquire skills that lead to high-wage jobs. . . .</p>
        <p>A DOMESTIC G.I. BILL . . . A Domestic G.I. Bill will enable all Americans to borrow money for college, so long as they are willing to pay it back as a percentage of their income over time or through national service addressing unmet community needs.</p>
        <p>AFFORDABLE HEALTH CARE All Americans should have universal access to quality, affordable health care -- not as a privilege but as a right. . . . We must be united in declaring war on AIDS and H.I.V. disease. . . .</p>
        <p>FAIRNESS . . . We will relieve the tax burden on middle-class Americans by forcing the rich to pay their fair share. We will provide long-overdue tax relief to families with children. . . .</p>
        <p>ENERGY EFFICIENCY AND SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT . . . We will . . . push for revenue-neutral incentives that reward conservation, prevent pollution and encourage recycling.</p>
        <p>CIVIL AND EQUAL RIGHTS . . . Democrats will continue to lead the fight to insure that no Americans suffer discrimination or deprivation of rights on the basis of race, gender, language, national origin, religion, age, disability, sexual orientation or other characteristics irrelevant to ability. We support ratification of the Equal Rights Amendment, . . . civil rights protection for gay men and lesbians and an end to Defense Department discrimination.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>II. RESPONSIBILITY</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>We offer a new social contract based neither on callous, do-nothing Republican neglect nor on an outdated faith in programs as the solution to every problem. We favor a third way beyond the old approaches -- to put government back on the side of citizens who play by the rules. . . .</p>
        <p>STRENGTHENING THE FAMILY . . . Children should not have children. We need a national crackdown on deadbeat parents. . . .Family and medical leave will insure that workers don't have to choose between family and work. . . . We favor insuring quality and affordable child-care opportunities for working parents. . . .</p>
        <p>WELFARE REFORM Welfare should be a second chance, not a way of life. We want to break the cycle of welfare by adhering to two simple principles: no one who is able to work can stay on welfare forever, and no one who works should live in poverty. . . . We'll invest in education and job training, and provide the child care and health care they need to go to work and achieve long-term self-sufficiency. We will give them the help they need to make the transition from welfare to work, and require people who can work to go to work within two years in available jobs either in the private sector or in community service to meet unmet needs. . . .</p>
        <p>CHOICE Democrats stand behind the right of every woman to choose, consistent with Roe v. Wade, regardless of ability to pay, and support a national law to protect that right.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>LABOR-MANAGEMENT RESPONSIBILITIES . . . If a company wants to overpay its executives and underinvest in the future or transfer jobs overseas, it shouldn't get special treatment and tax breaks. . . . Workers must also accept added responsibilities in the new economy. In return for an increased voice and a greater stake in the success of their enterprises, workers should be prepared to join in cooperative efforts to increase productivity, flexibility and quality. . . .</p>
        <p>RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE ENVIRONMENT . . . We will protect our old-growth forests, preserve critical habitats, provide a genuine "no net loss" policy on wetlands, conserve the critical resources of soil, water and air, oppose new offshore oil drilling and mineral exploration and production in our nation's many environmentally critical areas and address ocean pollution by reducing oil and toxic waste spills at sea. We believe America's youth can serve their country well through a civilian conservation corps. . . .</p>
        <p>RESPONSIBLE GOVERNMENT . . . Rather than throwing money at obsolete programs, we will eliminate unnecessary layers of management, cut administrative costs, give people more choices in the service they get and empower them to make those choices. . . .</p>
        <p>RESPONSIBLE OFFICIALS . . . We must limit overall campaign spending and limit the disproportionate and excessive role of PAC's. We need new voter registration laws that expand the electorate, such as universal same-day registration. . . . III. RESTORING COMMUNITY</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Republican leaders have urged Americans to turn inward, to pursue private interests without regard to public responsibilities. By playing racial, ethnic and gender-based politics, they have divided us against each other.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>We take special pride in our country's emergence as the world's largest and most successful multiethnic, multiracial republic. We condemn anti-Semitism, racism, homophobia, bigotry and negative stereotyping of all kinds.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>COMBATING CRIME AND DRUGS Crime is a relentless danger in our communities.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>The simplest and most direct way to restore order in our cities is to put more police on the streets. . . . We will create a Police Corps, in which participants will receive college aid in return for several years of service after graduation in a state or local police department. . . . We will expand drug counseling and treatment for those who need it.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>FIREARMS . . . We support a reasonable waiting period to permit background checks for purchases of handguns, as well as assault weapons controls to ban the possession, sale, importation and manufacture of the most deadly assault weapons. We do not support efforts to restrict weapons used for legitimate hunting and sporting purposes. . . .</p>
        <p>PURSUING ALL CRIME AGGRESSIVELY . . . Democrats will redouble efforts to ferret out and punish those who betray the public trust, rig financial markets, misuse their depositors' money or swindle their customers.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>EMPOWERING THE POOR AND EXPANDING THE MIDDLE CLASS . . . We advocate slower phasing out of Medicaid and other benefits to encourage work, special savings accounts to help low-income families build assets, fair lending, an indexed minimum wage, an expanded Job Corps and an end to welfare rules that encourage family breakup and penalize individual initiative.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>HOUSING . . . We must also confront homelessness by renovating, preserving and expanding the stock of affordable low-income housing.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>THE ARTS We believe in . . . a National Endowment for the Arts that is free from political manipulation. . . .  IV. PRESERVING OUR NATIONAL SECURITY</p>
        <p>. . . Under President Bush, crises have been managed rather than prevented; dictators like Saddam Hussein have been wooed rather than deterred; aggression by the Serbian regime against its neighbors in what was Yugoslavia has been met by American timidity rather than toughness; human rights abusers have been rewarded, not challenged; the environment has been neglected, not protected, and America's competitive edge in the global economy has been dulled, not honed. . . .</p>
        <p>Once again, we must define a compelling vision for global leadership at the dawn of a new era.  Restructuring Our Military Forces</p>
        <p>. . . What the United States needs is . . . a comprehensive restructuring of the American military enterprise to meet the threats that remain.</p>
        <p>MILITARY STRENGTH America is the world's strongest military power, and we must remain so. A post-cold war restructuring of American forces will produce substantial savings beyond those promised by the Bush Administration, but that restructuring must be achieved without undermining our ability to meet future threats to our security. . . .</p>
        <p>USE OF FORCE The United States must be prepared to use military force decisively when necessary to defend our vital interests. The burdens of collective security in a new era must be shared fairly.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Restoring America's Economic Leadership</p>
        <p>. . . Restoring America's global economic leadership must become a central element of our national security policies. . . .</p>
        <p>We cannot be strong at home unless we are part of a vibrant and expanding global economy. . . .</p>
        <p>TRADE Our Government must work to expand trade while insisting that the conduct of world trade is fair. . . . This should include renewed authority to use America's trading leverage against the most serious problems. . . .</p>
        <p>TRADE AGREEMENTS . . . Our Government must assure that our legitimate concerns about environmental, health and safety, and labor standards are included. Those American workers whose jobs are affected must have the benefit of effective adjustment assistance.  Promoting Democracy</p>
        <p>. . . An American foreign policy of engagement for democracy must effectively address:</p>
        <p>EMERGING DEMOCRACIES Helping to lead an international effort to assist the emerging . . . democracies in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA Maintenance of state and local sanctions against South Africa . . . until there is an irreversible, full and fair accommodation with the black majority to create a democratic government with full rights for all its citizens.</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST PEACE Support for the peace process now under way in the Middle East. . . . Jerusalem is the capital of the state of Israel and should remain an undivided city accessible to people of all faiths.  Preserving The Global Environment</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>ADDRESSING GLOBAL WARMING The United States must become a leader, not an impediment, in the fight against global warming.  We should join our European allies in agreeing to limit carbon dioxide emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>OZONE DEPLETION The United States must be a world leader in finding replacements for CFC's and other ozone-depleting substances.</p>
        <p>BIODIVERSITY We must work actively to protect the planet's biodiversity and preserve its forests.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>POPULATION GROWTHExplosive population growth must be controlled by working closely with other industrialized and developing nations and private organizations to fund greater family-planning efforts.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>We believe in the American people. We will challenge all Americans to give something back to their country. And they will be enriched in return, for when individuals assume responsibility, they acquire dignity. When people go to work, they rediscover a pride that was lost. When absent parents pay child support, they restore a connection they and their children need. When students work harder, they discover they can learn as well as any on earth. When corporate managers put their workers and long-term success ahead of short-term gain, their companies do well and so do they. When the leaders we elect assume responsibility for America's problems, we will do what is right to move America forward together.</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATIC PLATFORM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
