<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Campaign Journal; Democrats' Last New Hampshire Debate Becomes a Poise and Pose Contest</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEBATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D71138F934A25751C0A964958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Campaign Journal; Democrats' Last New Hampshire Debate Becomes a Poise and Pose Contest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN TIERNEY,</byline>
      <dateline>MANCHESTER, N.H., Feb. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tonight's debate among the Democrats was confusing and frustrating, but also revealing. It did not give viewers much sense of what policies the candidates stood for, but it provided a nice glimpse of how they reacted to adversity, of how they answered strange questions in the midst of chaos.</p>
        <p>It began with a series of unnecessary videotaped pieces about the candidates and proceeded into a section that resembled two-against-one tennis: two questioners sending question after unrelated question against one candidate. Then the candidates took turns rambling on about whatever was on their minds, after which they delivered one-minute closing statements in the pious, rehearsed tones of schoolchildren in an American Legion essay contest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tonight's debate among the Democrats was confusing and frustrating, but also revealing. It did not give viewers much sense of what policies the candidates stood for, but it provided a nice glimpse of how they reacted to adversity, of how they answered strange questions in the midst of chaos.</p>
        <p>It began with a series of unnecessary videotaped pieces about the candidates and proceeded into a section that resembled two-against-one tennis: two questioners sending question after unrelated question against one candidate. Then the candidates took turns rambling on about whatever was on their minds, after which they delivered one-minute closing statements in the pious, rehearsed tones of schoolchildren in an American Legion essay contest.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most surprising performance of the night was that of the moderator, Bernard Shaw, who had made his mark in a 1988 debate by asking Michael S. Dukakis if he would support the death penalty for a man who raped and murdered his wife. Mr. Dukakis' unemotional answer was noteworthy, and Mr. Shaw's pointed question was called the most revealing of the campaign.</p>
        <p>Tonight Mr. Shaw asked a series of questions that tended to be either unanswerable (What percentage of the gross national product should be spent on the environment?) or unfocused. His first question -- "What qualities should this nation's leader have?" -- might just as well have been, "Give us a little of your standard speech."</p>
        <p>All five candidates eagerly complied and used the opportunity to come out strongly in favor of the environment, jobs and building for the future. They were against global warming, wasting energy and President Bush.</p>
        <p>What was interesting was not what they said but how they did it. Senator Bob Kerrey of Nebraska turned in his best debate performance so far, looking more relaxed and sounding more coherent than in previous debates. When a questioner, Ken Bode of CNN, credited him with a line about other countries having won the cold war, Mr. Kerrey smiled and demurred.</p>
        <p>"I'm afraid it was actually Paul Tsongas who said that the cold war's over and Japan and Germany won it," he said. "I wish I'd thought of that line. It's a great line." Later he had the grace to joke about the man no one wanted to think about: Gov. Mario M. Cuomo of New York. Harkin Digresses</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Harkin of Iowa got the first question of the debate, and he tried to start with a thank-you speech to New Hampshire instead of a direct answer. He was interrupted by Mr. Shaw. Then, asked to specifically name issues where he disagreed with organized labor, which has supported his campaign, he digressed again and began attacking his opponents for accepting money from corporate executives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Harkin was interrupted again, and it added to a very bad first impression. He had better moments later in the debate, but it must have been difficult for some viewers to forget that opening evasiveness.</p>
        <p>Former Senator Paul E. Tsongas of Massachusetts spent much of the debate with pursed lips. He did not seem to be enjoying his status as the leader in polls in New Hampshire, and his dour expression was often matched by vague answers. He maintained some of his reputation for giving the painful truth by standing up against his rivals and supporting nuclear power, but at times he looked defensive.</p>
        <p>Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas took advantage of the chaotic discussion to step in several times and try to play the great unifier or moderator, an effective ploy for looking Presidential. He suggested, for instance, that everyone explain how they planned to reduce the deficit, and that everyone come out in favor of America joining the rest of the world in an agreement to halt global warming.</p>
        <p>Former Gov. Edmund G. Brown Jr. of California started off the evening with a crisp discussion of tax rates, and seemed to be dispelling his image as the outsider railing at the establishment. But then he quickly went back to his old style.</p>
        <p>"Look at the tax code," he complained, "all the loopholes, the ripoffs, the whole sort of what's going on in that Congress. They're spending half their time raising money, and the impact is we have millions of people out of work." He called for a "family bill of rights" that would guarantee "a living wage to every American, education, health care, food and shelter, and to be free of insecurity in their old age."</p>
        <p>No one opposed these notions. Nor, when Senator Harkin called for a moratorium on foreclosing homes of people who had lost their jobs, did anyone raise the question of what such a policy would do to the willingness of banks to lend mortgage money. It was not that kind of a debate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
