<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Opens Environment Talks; Europe Spurs U.S. to Act Urgently</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="511147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF1739F930A35750C0A964958260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Opens Environment Talks; Europe Spurs U.S. to Act Urgently</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, March 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>European nations said today that they were prepared to offer more money to help developing countries comply with proposed new treaties on the environment, and they urged the United States to do the same.</p>
        <p>The Europeans called attention to another major difference between the United States and others in the industrial world by reaffirming their commitment to hold emissions of gases that warm the atmosphere in the year 2000 to 1990 levels -- a pledge that the Bush Administration has so far refused to make.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>European nations said today that they were prepared to offer more money to help developing countries comply with proposed new treaties on the environment, and they urged the United States to do the same.</p>
        <p>The Europeans called attention to another major difference between the United States and others in the industrial world by reaffirming their commitment to hold emissions of gases that warm the atmosphere in the year 2000 to 1990 levels -- a pledge that the Bush Administration has so far refused to make.</p>
        <p>The Europeans' positions were outlined on the opening day of a five-week conference here to prepare for a world environmental summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro in June. The purpose of the June meeting is to forge a consensus on making world economic growth ecologically safe and sustainable.</p>
        <p>Such an agreement would be codified the form of conventions curbing greenhouse gas emissions and protecting plants and animals. At the June meeting, participants also hope to agree on a general statement of environmental principles, to be called the Earth Charter, and a detailed plan of action for the 21st century. It Won't Be Cheap</p>
        <p>The extraordinarily high cost of meeting such goals was re-emphasized today by Maurice F. Strong, a Canadian who has been named secretary general of the Rio de Janeiro meeting. At a news conference, he said the total bill could be as high as $600 billion a year, with developing countries requiring $70 billion more a year in aid.</p>
        <p>Mr. Strong said that for natural resources to have the chance to be protected, poverty would have to be alleviated. World population would also have to be stabilized, easing stress on the environment, he said.</p>
        <p>As European countries pressed the United States to change its positions for the Rio meeting, third-world countries made their case to the relatively well-off nations of the Northern Hemisphere. These poorer countries are seeking a global compact under which rich nations would provide them with money and technology to protect resources and develop their economies in environmentally sustainable ways.</p>
        <p>Senegal's Minister of Tourism and Environmental Protection, Jacques Baudin, said third-world countries had "a right and a duty to develop." He argued that they could do so either by using environmentally friendly technology or by taking the damaging routes to riches that many of the northern countries had used. Altruism and 'Planet Earth'</p>
        <p>"Africa is looking to the developed countries to curb their national egoism to save planet earth," Mr. Baudin said.</p>
        <p>Speaking on behalf of the European Community, Portugal's Environmental Minister, Carlos Borrego, agreed that new financial resources would be needed to help developing countries meet the Rio de Janeiro goals, and he urged "other industrialized countries" -- an allusion to the United States -- to adopt a similar position.</p>
        <p>While European and other industrial nations have committed $1.5 billion to a fund to help developing countries meet their obligations under these conventions and are prepared to give more, the United States at first refused to contribute anything. Last week, though, it offered $75 million. Briton Subtly Prods U.S.</p>
        <p>Britain's Environment Secretary, Michael Heseltine, implicitly criticized American reluctance to accept clear-cut goals for reducing greenhouse emissions, saying "clear and ambitious targets" offer the best way to promote sustainable world economic development.</p>
        <p>He said that the recent findings of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change leave governments little choice but to establish a process for stabilizing the climate and fighting global warming.</p>
        <p>He said the climate negotiations were "at a critical moment," with the majority of the richer countries ready to cooperate with the third world in drawing up the needed convention. Unspoken but implicit in his remarks was an appeal to the United States to get into step with other industrial nations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
