<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan Readied for a Smaller Trump City</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RIVERSIDE SOUTH PROJECT (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUMP CITY PROJECT (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MANHATTAN (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UPPER WEST SIDE (MANHATTAN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUMP, DONALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNLAP, DAVID W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB1030F935A25751C0A964958260" item-length="2493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan Readied for a Smaller Trump City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNLAP, DAVID W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOT as monumental as Donald J. Trump hoped it would be, nor as modest as many Upper West Siders believe it should be, a new plan for the Penn Yards site along the Hudson River is taking definitive form and may begin formal public review next month.</p>
        <p>Much debate is likely to focus on the sheer size of the project that is to rise over a relocated West Side Highway, from 59th to 72d Street: 16 apartment complexes (four of them 40 stories or higher), with up to 5,700 units, and a commercial structure two blocks wide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOT as monumental as Donald J. Trump hoped it would be, nor as modest as many Upper West Siders believe it should be, a new plan for the Penn Yards site along the Hudson River is taking definitive form and may begin formal public review next month.</p>
        <p>Much debate is likely to focus on the sheer size of the project that is to rise over a relocated West Side Highway, from 59th to 72d Street: 16 apartment complexes (four of them 40 stories or higher), with up to 5,700 units, and a commercial structure two blocks wide.</p>
        <p>"We decided that our criterion would not be the politically smartest design but the most publicly responsible design," said Richard A. Kahan, chairman of the Riverside South Planning Corporation. This private entity, financed by Mr. Trump, includes six civic groups with whom the developer agreed to cooperate last year after he abandoned his grandiose Trump City proposal.</p>
        <p>"The political design would have been to keep everything under 40 stories, because 40 is a flash point for some people," Mr. Kahan said, "and to locate the buildings where there were the least number of neighbors to lose views."</p>
        <p>But the private planners did not want to mass buildings at the mid-section of the site, because that is where the proposed riverfront park would be widest. And they could not concentrate residential density at the south end, because that is near a Con Edison plant. So they proposed several of the tallest buildings immediately west of the 3,800-unit Lincoln Towers co-op complex, which would block panoramic vistas of the Hudson River and afternoon sunlight for many residents.</p>
        <p>The private planners operated under an even greater constraint. Under the terms of their entente with Mr. Trump, Mr. Kahan and his colleagues had to figure out a way to accommodate 8.3 million square feet on the site -- roughly the equivalent of three Empire State Buildings.</p>
        <p>Now, that is considerably less than Trump City's 14.5 million square feet.</p>
        <p>Yet "it is still 1 million square feet larger than what we opposed the last time," said Madeleine Polayes, president of the Coaltion for a Livable West Side. She referred to the 7.3 million-square-foot Lincoln West proposal for the site, which was approved by the Board of Estimate in 1982 over community objections and a single nay vote by Andrew J. Stein, then Borough President of Manhattan, who said "this project is simply too big."</p>
        <p>Advocates and opponents of the new project probably will not even agree on how to measure its density.</p>
        <p>If the entire 74.6-acre property owned by Mr. Trump, on land and under water, is taken into account, Riverside South would have a floor-area ratio of 2.55, according to calculations by the architectural firm of Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill, which is working on the project.</p>
        <p>(The floor-area ratio expresses the relation between the square footage of a building and the size of the lot on which it sits. A ratio of 4 typifies five-story, mid-block row houses. Modern apartment towers on major avenues have ratios as high as 12. Some prewar apartment buildings -- such as the Majestic on Central Park West -- have floor-area ratios close to 15.)</p>
        <p>If only the 56.2 acres of dry land in the Trump property are counted, the floor-area ratio rises to 3.39. If the calculation is limited to the area east of the relocated highway, the ratio becomes 5.99. If only the zoning lots are counted -- that is, the building sites and public easements, minus the streets -- the ratio rises to 9.43.</p>
        <p>Finally, to take an extreme example, if the structures between 70th and 71st Streets were measured on the building site alone, they would have an extraordinary ratio of 16.45. The smallest buildings in the project would have only half that density.</p>
        <p>No matter how it is measured, the Riverside South now on the drafting boards is considerably larger than the one shown in a drawing circulated two years ago by the Municipal Art Society, Parks Council and Regional Plan Association. At the time, they were trying to thwart Trump City. Now, they are affiliated with Mr. Trump in the planning process, as are Paul Willen and Daniel Gutman, the architect and engineer who helped them prepare their vision of an alternative to Trump City.</p>
        <p>THE other partners in the Riverside South Planning Corporation are the Natural Resources Defense Council, Riverside Park Fund and Westpride, a neighborhood group whose former executive director, Catharine Cary, is vice president of the corporation and whose former co-chairman, Steven Robinson, is a consulting architect.</p>
        <p>Although the civic groups' alternative proposal of 1990 was never meant as an exact architectural rendering, it helped set new priorities for developing the site. It showed a broad waterfront park minus the elevated West Side Highway, which was well inland and depressed. Paralleling it was a southern extension of Riverside Drive, lined largely by 16- or 18-story apartment houses, in keeping with the scale of older buildings to the north.</p>
        <p>Some blocks even had buildings on the drive that were the scale of town houses. In the current plan, by contrast, the median size of the buildings on the drive would be 33 stories.</p>
        <p>The participation of civic groups in an undertaking with Mr. Trump certainly broadens support for the project. But numerous local leaders insist that this not be mistaken for community approval or acquiescence. Indeed, the Coalition for a Livable West Side has charged that Westpride "betrayed our community."</p>
        <p>A chief concern in the neighborhood is that Riverside South is not happening in a development vacuum. Two other large-scale projects are planned on land between the Trump property and West End Avenue.</p>
        <p>From 61st to 64th Street, the developer Daniel Brodsky has proposed a housing complex called Manhattan West, with 1,000 units in towers up to 38 stories tall and a privately owned and maintained green -- known as a "park-like open space" in planning documents -- at the north end. This was approved in 1990 by the Board of Estimate.</p>
        <p>Between 64th Street and a viaduct at 65th Street, Capital Cities/ABC is considering a mixed-use project with 280,000 square feet of television studios adjoining its workshops, studios and offices to the north, and three 39-story apartment towers with a total of up to 939 units, overlooking the Brodsky green.</p>
        <p>The relation of Riverside South to the Brodsky and ABC sites will be one of the questions raised in the seven-month land-use review procedure, during which the project will be considered by Community Board 7, Borough President Ruth W. Messinger, the City Planning Commission, the City Council's Land Use Committee and the full Council.</p>
        <p>Some questions are beyond the scope of designers to answer: Will Mr. Trump bring in other developers? Who would finance construction? Where would tenants come from? Is there enough money and political will to relocate Route 9A, the West Side Highway, from its shoreline viaduct to a semi-enclosed route curving 550 feet inland?</p>
        <p>Congress has authorized $18.4 million for the relocation project. Mr. Kahan views this is as a "major Federal endorsement," but the money must be supplemented by $3.68 million from local sources. And even that total may account for only 10 or 15 percent of the ultimate cost.</p>
        <p>Other questions have to be answered: How would Riverside South and the riverfront park work if the highway remained? How and where would sewage be treated? What will be done to help the already overburdened 72d Street subway station? How many parking spaces should be created?</p>
        <p>Is there room for affordable housing or, as Ms. Messinger has suggested, dormitories for colleges, medical schools and hospitals? Mr. Kahan said, "It is certainly a desire of all the board members to maximize the amount of housing that is below market and to have as broad a range of incomes as possible."</p>
        <p>What will the park look like? Will everyone be able to use it -- picnickers and ballplayers and roller-bladers and bird-watchers? How will its construction be phased and coordinated? Who will maintain it in the end? How large will it be? Twenty-three acres, as proposed a year ago? Twenty-two acres, as is currently foreseen? Or less?</p>
        <p>Specific answers about the park are not yet forthcoming, as it is still taking shape. "We are going to do a conceptual design," Mr. Kahan said, "in order to give people a good idea of what this place is going to be."</p>
        <p>Ethel Sheffer, former co-chairwoman of the Penn Yards committee of Community Board 7, believes that now is the time to get into details. "For Riverside South," she said, "the whole rationale was the park. That was what captured the imagination. Better answers to questions have to be contained in</p>
        <p>this</p>
        <p>phase. The public has a right to reasonable expectations as to what has been approved and what will get built here."</p>
        <p>If the current plan is short on some answers, however, it is long on others.</p>
        <p>It shows how much space would go where, in what form and for what reasons. This indicates which neighbors might be more or less affected. Also, if approved, the plan would provide a framework for construction, which may proceed as discrete undertakings by different builders rather than as a single mega-development by Mr. Trump.</p>
        <p>"It is being designed so it can be developed on a parcel-by-parcel basis, in a variety of permutations, by a developer or series of developers," Mr. Kahan said. "Depending on the perception of the market, it could proceed with 200 units or 3,000 units."</p>
        <p>Piecemeal development would more closely resemble the evolution of a real neighborhood. And it is a stated goal of the private planners that Riverside South relate to the existing city. "When we're all done," said Marilyn Jordan Taylor, a partner in Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill, "if no one knows where the property lines were, that's the best thing that could have happened."</p>
        <p>That is not to imply a laissez-faire approach. Beyond the usual zoning restrictions, the planning corporation is preparing design guidelines that would specify what materials could be used on the facades, a range of window sizes, what kinds of balconies would be allowed (no "tongue-depressor" slabs, for instance), even what the exterior grilles of air-conditioners should look like.</p>
        <p>"This thing is going to take so long to achieve," said David M. Childs, chairman of Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill. "You don't want to be stifling. But you</p>
        <p>do</p>
        <p>want to mandate quality and interest."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kahan is of two minds about design guidelines. "In an ideal world, we would have none," he said. "There are always good architects. But there aren't always good patrons. I don't feel personally that we have half a handful or less of patrons of good architecture in New York. I can only think of two. And one is Donald Trump, which I wouldn't have predicted prior to entering this project with him. Since we have no choice over who will do the development, we have to go with detailed guidelines."</p>
        <p>Because the northernmost block in the project occupies the critical intersection of Riverside Park, Riverside Drive and 72d Street, it would seem to be the likeliest site for the first building. Its north facade would rise only as high as the adjacent Chatsworth apartment house, which is a landmark. It would rise to a 32-story tower on 71st Street.</p>
        <p>"Some people thought the right thing, from a development point of view, was to put the tallest building at the north end," Ms. Cary said. "But we realized that the best thing was to maintain the character of the neighborhood and protect the feeling of 72d Street and the Chatsworth."</p>
        <p>The west end of 71st Street would be a public-access easement, resembling a city street but privately owned and closed to through traffic, intended primarily for pedestrians and for delivery and emergency vehicles. Other easements would be at 60th, 62d, 65th, 67th and 69th Streets. Traffic would run through 59th, 61st, 63d, 64th, 66th, 68th and 70th Streets.</p>
        <p>ON the south side of 71st Street would be a building of 18 stories that steps down to four to seven stories toward the mid-block, deferring somewhat to the scale of the nearby row houses.</p>
        <p>On the north side of 70th Street, however, would be the tallest building in Riverside South, a 49-story structure. And on the south side of the street would be a 46-story tower.</p>
        <p>"We felt this was a street that had a lot of breadth, sky and air," Mr. Childs said, referring to the fact that 70th Street is 20 feet wider than the average crosstown street.</p>
        <p>In contrast to these skyscrapers is the enclave planned for Freedom Place, which borders Lincoln Towers, from 66th to 70th Street. It would contain four- to seven-story buildings, perhaps with courtyards.</p>
        <p>At the base of these buildings would be neighborhood shops like a supermarket and video store, as well as offices, rehearsal space or theaters for nonprofit cultural groups.</p>
        <p>BETWEEN 68th and 69th Streets would be a 40-story building with broad set-back "shoulders" framing a central tower. These setbacks are meant to increase air and light for Freedom Place. To create a sense of symmetry in the overall skyline, a structure of similar size, with similar massing, would rise between 62d and 63d Streets.</p>
        <p>Twin-towered buildings, reminiscent of Central Park West structures, would be built between 67th and 68th Streets and between 63d and 64th Streets. They, too, are meant as symmetrical counterpoints, although the southern tower is noticeably larger.</p>
        <p>At 41 stories, the twin-towered structure between 63d and 64th Streets would have the highest peaks in Riverside South's southern neighborhood. "It frames the 'park-like open space,' as do the Brodsky and ABC buildings, in a similar manner," Ms. Cary said.</p>
        <p>At the widest portion of the park, between 65th and 66th Streets, would be one of the shortest buildings. "We felt very strongly that the development should defer to the park," Ms. Taylor said.</p>
        <p>At 62d Street, the Riverside South proposal calls for an oval-shaped park, in an effort to mesh with Mr. Brodsky's project. There would be three 28-story apartment buildings around the park.</p>
        <p>Moving south along the drive from 62d Street, building heights would drop from 33 stories to 23 stories to 18 stories, as they approach the Con Ed steam plant, between 58th and 59th Streets, 11th and 12th Avenues, which emits carbon dioxide, water vapor, sulfur dioxide, oxides of nitrogen, carbon monoxide and particulates.</p>
        <p>Dominating the southeast corner of the project would be a vast commercial structure with 1.8 million square feet of television studio space. It would be two blocks wide, cutting off 60th Street, perhaps rising to twin 30-story office towers on West End Avenue.</p>
        <p>"This has to be a very efficient technological block," Ms. Taylor said. "The ground floor defines the location of long-span, high-volume studios."</p>
        <p>Mr. Childs added, "It's one of the few places in the city where that kind of space can happen."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
