<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Global Warming?</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="578193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GLOBAL CLIMATE COALITION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHLAES, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DF133BF931A15751C1A964958260" item-length="373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Global Warming?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Cheapest Protection of Nature May Lie In Taxes, Not Laws" (Science Times, Nov. 24) echoes the theme that bad taxes become good taxes (alias "green fees") when they tax "bad" things. According to the article, these include fossil fuels, traffic and household garbage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Cheapest Protection of Nature May Lie In Taxes, Not Laws" (Science Times, Nov. 24) echoes the theme that bad taxes become good taxes (alias "green fees") when they tax "bad" things. According to the article, these include fossil fuels, traffic and household garbage.</p>
        <p>While tax policy can affect behavior, misguided tax policy can dampen economic prosperity in attempting to solve problems that might not exist or that could be solved in less onerous ways. The World Resources Institute study you cite asks Americans to pay higher energy prices to prevent catastrophic global warming.</p>
        <p>But there is considerable debate on whether or not man-made greenhouse gases (produced primarily by burning fossil fuels) are triggering a dangerous "global warming" trend. At an international meeting of climate experts in 1990, an intergovernmental panel on climate change concluded that "it is impossible to prove a cause and effect relationship" between man-made emissions and global warming. In the 1992 supplement to that report, the scientists stated, "It is still not possible to attribute with high confidence all, or even part of, the observed global warming to the enhanced greenhouse effect."</p>
        <p>We know that climate change over the last 100 years is well within the planet's natural variation (the global climate has never been "stable"). If scientists don't agree that man-made global warming is a problem, does the United States want to pay the costs incurred from an energy tax, including a diminished competitive position with our trading partners? A major Japanese Government agency has backed away from a carbon tax because of its impact on industry. You cite a $5 trillion price tag in the study.</p>
        <p>The American business community has made significant improvements in energy efficiency and now spends approximately $100 billion a year complying with environmental regulations. These improvements have resulted in a substantial reduction in greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>A green fee is a carbon tax, and a carbon tax is an energy tax. That translates into higher prices, lost jobs, reduced paychecks and slower growth. JOHN SHLAES  Executive Director Global Climate Coalition Washington, Dec. 4, 1992</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
