<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="565959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1739F934A15753C1A964958260" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-13  'NO' TO UNION IN CANADA  Voters in Canada rejected a constitutional package intended to strengthen union and, in particular, to end Quebec's drive for succession. The confederation is not likely to dissolve soon, but Quebec may gain some sovereignty.  A1  HINTS OF BRITISH ROLE IN IRAQ . . .  Britain, in exchange for intelligence, helped Iraq build up its military before Kuwait was invaded.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-13  'NO' TO UNION IN CANADA  Voters in Canada rejected a constitutional package intended to strengthen union and, in particular, to end Quebec's drive for succession. The confederation is not likely to dissolve soon, but Quebec may gain some sovereignty.  A1  HINTS OF BRITISH ROLE IN IRAQ . . .  Britain, in exchange for intelligence, helped Iraq build up its military before Kuwait was invaded.  A1</p>
        <p>. . . AND U.S. TRANSACTIONS  The Bush Administration in 1989 approved the export to Iraq of two computers with potential military applications.  A13  TALES FROM THE DYNASTIC BOUDOIR  The Japanese Emperor asked some public questions about China's intimate history on his visit to the Forbidden City.  A3  ISRAEL RETALIATES WITH BOMBS  Israeli artillery, aircraft and gunboats pounded Lebanon in retaliation for a bomb ambush by Islamic fundamentalists that killed five.  A8  CZECHS AND SLOVAKS IN ACCORD  In preparation for their eventual separation, the Czech and Slovak republics agreed on a blueprint for customs, agriculture and foreign currencies.  A6  NEW POWER FOR OLD LEADERS  After years of fighting for autonomy from the Soviet Union, Lithuanians handed power back to the former Communists in country's first elections since independence.  A10  TENSION SPLITS BOSNIAN FORCES  Fissures are spreading through the Government of Bosnia as it becomes clear that an alliance of Muslims and Croats is not in the offing.  A10  SALVADOR REBELS AGREE TO PLAN  Leaders of Salvadoran rebels said they would accede to U.N. deadlines for demobilizing their forces -- under one condition.  A9  NEW TAXES IN BONN'S CRYSTAL BALL  Chancellor Helmut Kohl of Germany said tax increases by 1995 were inevitable because of the high costs of rebuilding East Germany.  A11  WHOEVER IS IN THE WHITE HOUSE . . .  European leaders say they have no qualms about the possibility of a Clinton Administration in Washington and in fact seem more concerned about their own survival.  A12  IRAQI KURDS CLAIM A VICTORY  Iraqi Kurds said they took the main base of separatist Turkish Kurds in northern Iraq.  A12  A bitter taste in the mouths of "alimentari" owners.  A11  Ireland debates wording of abortion referndum.  A8  Santo Domingo Journal: Divergent earthly paths to heaven.  A4  National A14-21  PEROT CONTINUES ACCUSATIONS  Perot continued suggesting there had been a Republican plot to smear his daughter, and a spokesman for the President called the independent candidate "paranoid." A1  F.B.I. LOOKED INTO PEROT CHARGE  Administration officials said the F.B.I. sent an agent to the office of the Bush campaign chairman in Texas in an effort to check out Perot's accusation that Republicans were spying on him.  A1  BUSH CALLS HIMSELF 'ACTIVIST'  Bush took a break from his attacks on Clinton to address voter discontent, painting himself as a "conservative activist" who has the best attributes of Perot and Clinton.  A1  CHRISTIAN CANDIDATES GAIN  Across the country, conservative Christian candidates are building on several years of organizing to mount strong challenges for elected positions minor and major.  A1  CLINTON TALKS CONSERVATIVE  Trying to reach independent, essentially conservative voters, Clinton sounded a theme heavy with values associated with conservatism.  A20  KEY CAMPAIGN ISSUES AVOIDED  Through the many months of speeches and campaign appearances, the candidates have left many crucial issues unexplored.  A21  Perot has again thrown the Presidential race into disarray.  A18  The candidates are engaged in the costliest ad blitz ever.A19  Perot's well-watched TV ads seem to defy political experience.  A19  Stan Greenberg, Clinton's poll taker, has come a long way.  A20  G.M. CHAIRMAN RESIGNS  Robert Stempel resigned as chairman and chief executive of General Motors, amid speculation that his dismissal was imminent and continuing losses at the company.  A1  ADS ON ABORTION BECOME CRUCIAL  Television commercials on abortion are becoming more and more important to candidates running for the House and Senate.  A14  REFERENDUM PUSHES RECYCLING  Environmentalists in Massachusetts are campaigning for the most sweeping recycling measure in the country.  A15  Researchers in Mississippi are trying to lure back bald eagles.  A14  The E.P.A. moved to curb chemicals that cause acid rain.  A16  Two unusual candidates are running for Congress in Madison, Wis.  A14  Science Times C1-10  What makes a perception? Scientists think seriously about it.  C1  The space station has so far stayed mostly on the drawing board.  C1  A comet may hit, but not until 2126.  C7  Metro Digest B1  DINKINS AIDE STEPS ASIDE  Randy Daniels withdrew as a deputy mayor of New York City, indicating that his effectiveness as an adviser to Mayor Dinkins had been destroyed by allegations that he sexually harassed a woman who worked for him five years ago.  A1  Business Digest D1  Fashion Page B9  Arts/Entertainment C13-18  The Talk of Hollywood.  C13  A photographic movement.  C13  Sports B10-16  Baseball: Mets obtain Tony Fernandez.  B11  Hockey: Rangers beat Flyers.  B11  Obituaries B7-8  Roger Miller, country singer.  B8  Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23  Editorials  Getting dizzy with Ross Perot.  The children left behind.  Sex harassment, men in power.  For Congress from New Jersey.  Letters  A. M. Rosenthal: Perot's little helpers.  Russell Baker: The future foretold.  Greil Marcus: The Elvis strategy.  Hiroyuki Kishino: No fear. The plutonium's safe.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
