<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB1439F932A35755C0A964958260" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>A light bulb will be introduced today that uses a high-frequency radio signal instead of a filament to produce light. The new bulb is more cost effective than existing bulbs and will last 14 years if lighted 4 hours a day, electrical engineers say.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Wall Street has been intensively lobbying the members of Congress who are shaping new controls on the Government securities market in the wake of the Salomon Brothers bidding scandal. A bill that would impose new regulations is expected to gain the approval of the House Energy and Commerce Committee this week. Credit Markets.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>A light bulb will be introduced today that uses a high-frequency radio signal instead of a filament to produce light. The new bulb is more cost effective than existing bulbs and will last 14 years if lighted 4 hours a day, electrical engineers say.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Wall Street has been intensively lobbying the members of Congress who are shaping new controls on the Government securities market in the wake of the Salomon Brothers bidding scandal. A bill that would impose new regulations is expected to gain the approval of the House Energy and Commerce Committee this week. Credit Markets.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Ads in medical journals are often misleading about the safety and effectiveness of new drugs, a study found. The journals' editors have an elaborate system of evaluating scientific articles, but they usually screen drug ads only for taste, not for content.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Despite an agreement between Mayor Dinkins and the City Council on the shape of a $29.5 billion budget, City Hall faces a final fiscal hurdle: reaching an agreement with the municipal labor unions on pay raises.  [ B3. ] The Media Business</p>
        <p>Hollywood journalists are in an uproar over a publicist's demand that those attending a press junket for the film "Far and Away" sign a "consent agreement" placing restrictions on them before interviewing the actor Tom Cruise. Press.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>When BET Holdings went public last fall, the stock took off like a rocket. But since that October offering, the black-run cable television company and its new investors have found themselves riding more of a roller coaster than a rocket.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Television stations affiliated with CBS said the network's plan to charge fees for some programs could cause them to drop some programming and, in extreme cases, to consider abandoning the network altogether.  [ D9. ]</p>
        <p>The "CBS Evening News" has been gaining steadily for most of this year, though network executives have not been bold enough to predict that it will stage a comeback comparable to that of CBS's prime-time shows.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Tulsa is the most typical town in America, according to an analysis of 1990 census data. As one of the country's most middle-of-the-road cities, it is is considered an ideal test market.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>One of advertising's most-talked-about topics is the state of relationships between agencies and clients. An annual survey on the subject found surprising disparities in attitudes between parties that are ostensibly partners. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D10. ] International</p>
        <p>A blockade of a private port by Greenpeace seems to foreshadow bitter relations between environmentalists and business people at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>As Europe's environmental debate moves from science to economics, the richest governments are turning to the marketplace as they grapple with the difficult question: what price the environment? The most ambitious attempt yet at an answer came when the European Community proposed a plan to fight pollution and global warming by imposing a tax on oil, coal, natural gas and other non-renewable forms of energy harmful to the environment.  [ A6. ] Companies</p>
        <p>The judge presiding over Olympia &amp; York's restructuring in Canada has struck middle ground in a dispute between the company and its creditors over the use of rental income from court-protected real estate.  [ D2. ] Today's Column</p>
        <p>One of the first companies to offer test-tube babies to Americans now feels confident enough to go public. But some investors are not sure whether IVF America can deliver on its ambitious growth plans and become the McDonald's of the baby-making business. Market Place.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
