<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>or Arctic Data, Ask a Polar Bear</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="572572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLAR BEARS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD1E3CF937A15752C1A964958260" item-length="1480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>or Arctic Data, Ask a Polar Bear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>CHURCHILL, Manitoba</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE helicopter bucks and sways. Dr. Malcolm A. Ramsay is riding behind the pilot over the wind-whipped taiga of northern Manitoba. He anchors his left arm in the open window and aims a rifle at the lumbering yellowish-white shape below.</p>
        <p>The rifle gives a faint pop and a four-inch long Telazol tranquilizer dart jabs the shoulder of the big, hungry polar bear. Within four minutes it is temporarily immobilized.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE helicopter bucks and sways. Dr. Malcolm A. Ramsay is riding behind the pilot over the wind-whipped taiga of northern Manitoba. He anchors his left arm in the open window and aims a rifle at the lumbering yellowish-white shape below.</p>
        <p>The rifle gives a faint pop and a four-inch long Telazol tranquilizer dart jabs the shoulder of the big, hungry polar bear. Within four minutes it is temporarily immobilized.</p>
        <p>The pilot, Steve Miller, drops Dr. Ramsay off in a clearing near the fallen animal, and returns to the Churchill Northern Studies Center, about 75 miles to the north.</p>
        <p>He will return in a few hours to pick up Dr. Ramsay and whatever he has learned about the ecology of the taiga, a coniferous forest in northern climes, from a brief visit with one of its most prominent citizens.</p>
        <p>Because of its peculiar biology, the polar bear acts as a blotter for the stresses on the Arctic environment, and scientists are studying it to learn about chemical pollution, global warming and other potential threats to the survival of this species as well as humans.</p>
        <p>Wrapped in layers of liners, a cavernous parka, thermal boots, thermal socks and thermal gloves, Dr. Ramsay, an associate professor of vertebrate ecology at the University of Saskatchewan and one Canada's leading experts on polar bears, gives the sedated beast sprawled on the snow a physical as thorough as any a company doctor gives a corporate executive. With a winch, tripod, net and electronic scale, he weighs the bear. Other instruments measure its electrical resistance to determine its lean body mass, as opposed to adipose tissue, or fat.</p>
        <p>With pliers he extracts a vestigial premolar tooth that the bear does not use to determine the animal's age. The tooth builds up rings like the trunk of a tree.</p>
        <p>From the femoral vein, he draws blood samples for biochemical tests. He takes a sample of fat tissue for later analysis of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCB's), industrial pollutants that make their way into the polar bear's niche and become concentrated in its fatty tissue. Researchers already know that the levels of PCB's in the bears are dangerous and could start having effects on reproduction. Search for Danger Levels</p>
        <p>Biologists are now trying to ascertain the danger level for PCB concentration in polar bears. For seals, Dr. Ramsay says, deleterious reproductive effects are evident in the PCB levels of 70 parts per million that have been recorded in the blubber of Baltic Sea seals. These animals have been practically wiped out over the last two decades.</p>
        <p>The Baltic is a known dumping ground for materials containing PCB's. Probably reflecting this, adipose tissue of polar bears in the Svalbard islands north of Norway has recently been found to have a concentration of 32 parts per million. Hudson Bay is not yet such a dumping ground, and the mean level of PCB concentration in the Churchill area bears was most recently recorded at eight parts per million.</p>
        <p>Every year between August and the end of November, Dr. Ramsay comes to Churchill to study the species, Ursus maritimus. Over the last dozen years he has similarly examined more than 1,000 of the species.</p>
        <p>Churchill is a popular place for the study because it is easily accessible, by rail or plane, and because the bears congregate in the area just before Hudson Bay freezes. Then they move out on the ice for the ringed seals that are their basic diet. Until the ice forms, they do not eat or drink for periods often exceeding four months.</p>
        <p>"Why do I like to work with polar bears?" the professor asked. "I guess it's because they live in a very simple ecosystem. They feed on a single species, live in a simple environment. It's easier to understand the ecological principles at work in a simple ecosystem than it is in the tropics, or the timber region, where interactions are more complex."</p>
        <p>The knowledge he is accumulating about this "simple" system could prove important not only for an aloof and remote species roaming the roof of the world but for humans. Ability to Retain Mass</p>
        <p>During their long fast, even longer than that of other bears, polar bears meet their energy requirements from fat reserves. These are extensively depleted. Every day of fast they burn up one to one and one-half kilograms of fat.</p>
        <p>But while the fat is burned off, the protein mass of the bear remains constant, or declines only gradually, because polar bears are able to recycle proteins internally. Humans and most other mammals show a continuous loss of these compounds while fasting.</p>
        <p>Proteins make up the structural parts of the body, like muscle, bone, connective tissue, hair, skin, fingernails and are the enzymes that cause reactions, like digestion.</p>
        <p>In all mammals including humans, old protein gets broken down into urea. Kidneys filter urea out of the blood and into the urinary bladder from which it is excreted from the body in urine. The old protein is replaced by protein taken in through food.</p>
        <p>Should kidneys malfunction, the buildup of urea creates a life-threatening danger. In such conditions, humans usually have to go through dialysis, having their blood filtered in effect by an artificial kidney.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Ramsay's examinations have shown that polar bears are blessed with some kind of biochemical pathways that avoid use of kidneys. Instead the urea of the bears is converted back into amino acids, the building blocks of proteins.</p>
        <p>Just how they do this is a mystery that Dr. Ramsay thinks may be solved in the near future. He is working on finding the answer in a joint project with Dr. Ramsay and Dr. Ralph A. Nelson, chairman of the medical school of the University of Illinois.</p>
        <p>If they find a special enzyme in the bear that facilitates the conversion of urea wastes back into amino acids, bypassing the kidneys, and if it can be reproduced pharmacologically, it might help humans with kidney failure to avoid dialysis. Signals to Track Bears</p>
        <p>Some of Dr. Ramsay's bears get collars emitting radio signals that bounce off satellites and can be picked up by telemetry receivers in the helicopter. This permits him to follow reactions in the same animal over a span of weeks or months. In selected bears next season, he will inject urea molecules labeled with a special nitrogen isotope. He will then try to find the same bears again to track those molecules through the biochemical pathways.</p>
        <p>But ecology looms large in his research. He is studying the buildup of contaminants like PCB's, which are now found in the Arctic food chain. PCB's, banned in North America and most of Western Europe but still produced in Eastern Europe, Asia and other less developed areas, are apparently borne by winds to the northern seas and absorbed by marine life.</p>
        <p>Polar bears at the top of the food chain eat the seals that eat the cod that eat the larger plankton that eat the smaller plankton that eat the algae that absorb the PCB's. At each rung of the food chain, the concentration of PCB's increases.</p>
        <p>Once ingested, the PCB's become concentrated in the fatty tissue of the bears. "We don't yet know what happens to the PCB's when the bears fast and burn up their fat reserves," Dr. Ramsay said. "Are they broken down by the liver and excreted from the body? Are they broken down somewhere else? Are they concentrated in the remaining fat? Are they transferred to the cubs through the mother's milk?"</p>
        <p>He and graduate students who join him on some of his northern expeditions, like Susan Polischuk, a 25-year-old masters candidate, and Stephen Atkinson, 24, a Ph.D. candidate, are trying to find answers, joined by Dr. Ross J. Norstrom of Environment Canada, a leading expert on PCB's in food chains, who works closely with Dr. Ramsay.</p>
        <p>Polar bears are not technically an endangered species. They are protected by law in all Arctic countries. In Canada, Indians and Eskimos are permitted to kill a certain number of the bears each year. Others may kill them only in self-defense. Fears of Catastrophe</p>
        <p>Still, Dr. Ramsay worries about their susceptibility to "catastrophic events" in the future. The PCB's are only one danger. Global warming is another.</p>
        <p>Any rise in the mean annual temperature changing the dynamics of sea ice could further shorten the time of their feed with disastrous consequences.</p>
        <p>Another possible source of trouble is that their food supply might die off, as occurred recently in the North Sea when masses of gray and harbor seals perished from an epidemic of a morbillivirus, similar to the distemper that strikes dogs. In the Mediterranean thousands of seals as well as dolphins recently succumbed to a similar epidemic.</p>
        <p>Still another threat is polar bears' limited genetic variability. This has been determined in studies of their genetic blueprint, DNA. Thus with any sudden change in their environment, they might not have the flexibility to cope.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
