<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONFERENCE IN RIO/The Rich Vs. the Poor; Cooling the Globe Would be Nice, But Saving Lives Now May Cost Less</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASAR, SYLVIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DE1F39F932A05756C0A964958260" item-length="1196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONFERENCE IN RIO/The Rich Vs. the Poor; Cooling the Globe Would be Nice, But Saving Lives Now May Cost Less</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIA NASAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASAR, SYLVIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the frustrations for planners of the Earth Summit in Rio has been the inability of the world's nations to reach agreement on an idea that seems relatively obvious: that something must be done to keep the earth from slowly getting hotter.</p>
        <p>Despite the possibility of floods, famines and droughts within the next 50 or 100 years -- though not all scientists are convinced that global warming is a real threat -- the pre-conference talks have already badly split on the issue. Rich nations want poor ones, with their rapid birth rates, to stop scrambling to get more factories and more cars, even if that means they will stay poorer for a while. Poor nations, by contrast, furious that the rich ones have produced far more pollution per person for the last 200 years, want the industrialized countries to be the ones to drive less, plug in less and put expensive scrubbers on their smokestacks -- and they want them to admit that it's more important for poor nations to get out of poverty than to be ecologically pristine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the frustrations for planners of the Earth Summit in Rio has been the inability of the world's nations to reach agreement on an idea that seems relatively obvious: that something must be done to keep the earth from slowly getting hotter.</p>
        <p>Despite the possibility of floods, famines and droughts within the next 50 or 100 years -- though not all scientists are convinced that global warming is a real threat -- the pre-conference talks have already badly split on the issue. Rich nations want poor ones, with their rapid birth rates, to stop scrambling to get more factories and more cars, even if that means they will stay poorer for a while. Poor nations, by contrast, furious that the rich ones have produced far more pollution per person for the last 200 years, want the industrialized countries to be the ones to drive less, plug in less and put expensive scrubbers on their smokestacks -- and they want them to admit that it's more important for poor nations to get out of poverty than to be ecologically pristine.</p>
        <p>Interestingly enough, many economists, including some outspoken liberals, think the poor nations are right.</p>
        <p>The World Bank's 1992 "Development and the Environment" report argues strongly that eliminating poverty should remain the world's top goal. It recognizes that countries will use more energy and pollute more, but argues that growth is a powerful antidote for the kinds of pollution that are killing people right now.</p>
        <p>Nearly 2 billion people live without clean water or sewers, and cholera, typhus and other diseases kill two million children a year. One billion live in cities with unsafe sulfur dioxide levels; coal-fired factories spread lung disease and acidify cropland. Leaded gasoline fumes leave many children retarded. Topsoil depletion costs the third world up to 1.5 percent of its annual gross domestic product, and farmers starve.</p>
        <p>Sacrificing more people by slowing progress in order to forestall deaths in 50 or 100 years makes no sense, the report concludes.</p>
        <p>"Poverty is already a worse killer than any foreseeable environmental distress," said Lawrence H. Summers, chief economist at the World Bank, who calculates that 34 million people a year -- more than live in California -- die of poverty-related causes. "Nobody should kid themselves that they are doing Bangladesh a favor when they worry about global warming."</p>
        <p>These economists insist that it is cheaper and fairer for rich countries to shoulder the anti-warming effort. Any funds they spend in the third world should go for things like safe drinking water, sewers, cleaner smokestacks and engines and soil conservation. Education for girls should be another priority, some say, since studies have shown that girls in developing countries with high school educations have an average of three children, while those without average seven.</p>
        <p>Economic growth increases pollution, economists admit, but they say that the pendulum eventually begins to swing back. By some estimates, once a nation's per capita income rises to about $4,000, it produces less of some pollutants per capita because it can afford technology like catalytic converters and sewage treatment. Solid waste and carbon dioxide emissions keep increasing, though. Some countries, like Mexico and Russia, are at that $4,000 threshold now.</p>
        <p>Poor countries can still fight global warming, the economists say. But the most sensible steps for them to take first are relatively low-cost ones that will also help their economies. For example, eliminating government subsidies on coal and oil will force factories and utilities to become more efficient. Enforcing property rights can slow deforestation. Educating girls can slow population growth. Small Results With High Prices</p>
        <p>"Scientists say there are all these neat things to do for free," said Robert Hahn, an economist at the American Enterprise Institute, an economics research group. "If it would do so much good now, why haven't we done them? The reasons are political."</p>
        <p>In the industrialized world, he points out, even rudimentary steps like adopting taxes on pollution have often been stymied. In the United States, measures like the gas-guzzler tax on big cars and the creation of saleable air-pollution rights have had some effect, but gasoline is still cheap, so there is little incentive to conserve.</p>
        <p>On another front, the economists argue that the high price of curbing global warming will yield only small gains.</p>
        <p>The World Bank cites estimates that keeping American emissions of greenhouse gases at present levels would cost between 3 and 7 percent of the G.D.P. Three percent equals Federal health spending; 7 percent equals military spending.</p>
        <p>The key question is: how much sacrifice is it worth? "You could get rid of highway fatalities if you reduced the speed limit to five miles per hour," said Mr. Hahn. "How much economic growth do you want to give up to buy insurance against global warming?" Like a Recession</p>
        <p>In developing countries, the price might be twice as high, largely because they lack capital, rely heavily on cheap but dirty fuels like wood and charcoal, and have less flexibility since more energy goes for uses like cooking than for air-conditioning.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the economists argue, the costs of global warming, while large, are hardly infinite. William Cline of the Institute for International Economics and others estimate that if the United States's weather became 2 or 3 degrees hotter 50 years from now, the extra costs of adapting -- such as building seawalls and shifting crops -- would equal only 1 to 2 percent of G.D.P., the impact of a mild recession.</p>
        <p>In developing countries, putting money into job-creating industries might make more sense, they argue. If every dollar invested today grows to $100 in 50 years, the higher incomes would make climate changes less painful, since people could afford safer housing, more farm irrigation and the like. "The evidence implies that investments with real rate of return as low as 5 percent do more for future generations than investments in large reductions of greenhouse gas emissions," the report said.</p>
        <p>The scariest prospects involve the damage to agriculture. But as many economists have pointed out, most famines in recent centuries have been caused not by food shortages but by poverty. As a whole, the world grows more food than it can eat. With higher incomes, poor countries could buy more.</p>
        <p>Economists with environmental groups say these estimates are too conservative, and, more important, that they miss the point.</p>
        <p>"The approach that 'We'll be 1 to 6 percent less rich' leaves out the risk of catastrophe," said Mr. Cline. And models that rely on the American economy do not take into account the devastation of, for instance, hurricanes in Bangladesh after ocean levels rise.</p>
        <p>"It's very difficult for economists to conceive of cataclysm," said David Batker, an economist for the environmental organization Greenpeace.</p>
        <p>The debate is apt to continue long after the Rio meeting adjourns. "If science were more certain that we were going to hell in a handbasket," said Mr. Hahn, "you'd get more consensus."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
