<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Benefits</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="527555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB1230F933A25756C0A964958260" item-length="1776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To Aid the Blind</p>
        <p>May 10 -- The 17th annual Iris Ball for the Manhattan League of the Helen Keller Services for the Blind will be held at the Metropolitan Club, 1 East 60th Street. Cocktails at 7 P.M. will be followed by dinner and dancing. Black tie. Tickets, $300, from (212) 285-7029.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To Aid the Blind</p>
        <p>May 10 -- The 17th annual Iris Ball for the Manhattan League of the Helen Keller Services for the Blind will be held at the Metropolitan Club, 1 East 60th Street. Cocktails at 7 P.M. will be followed by dinner and dancing. Black tie. Tickets, $300, from (212) 285-7029.</p>
        <p>Art to Wear</p>
        <p>May 11 -- A reception and fashion show of clothing and accessories made by 65 contemporary artisans will begin at 6 P.M. at the American Craft Museum, 40 West 53d Street. The sale, a benefit for the museum, will continue through May 17. Tickets, $75, from (212) 956-3535.  Musicale on a Barge</p>
        <p>May 11 -- A benefit for the six-member Chelsea Chamber Ensemble will be held at the Barge at the Fulton Street Landing in Brooklyn. The ensemble will perform "Facade," poems of Dame Edith Sitwell set to music by Sir William Walton. A reception and buffet from 6:30 to 7:30 P.M. will precede the performance. Buses will leave Manhattan at 6 P.M. from the Seventh Regiment Armory, Park Avenue at 67th Street, and will return after the performance. Tickets, $100, from (212) 734-3977.  Columbia Nurses' Centennial</p>
        <p>May 11 -- The Columbia University School of Nursing will celebrate its centennial with a black-tie benefit. The Princess of Wales will be honored for her work on behalf of AIDS patients, Princess Yasmin Aga Khan for her fund-raising efforts for Alzheimer's disease, Evelyn H. Lauder for her support of breast cancer research and Dr. Keville Frederickson for her contributions to nursing. Cocktails at 6:15 P.M. at the Pierre will be followed by dinner and dancing. Tickets, $350, from (212) 305-3254.  For Young Performers</p>
        <p>May 11 -- The annual spring dinner and dance to benefit the Professional Children's School will be held at the Marriott Marquis, starting with cocktails at 7 P.M. Alumni and current students at the school for children in the performing arts will present a show. Tickets, $300, from (212) 685-1095.  Live Radio Drama</p>
        <p>May 11 -- The Atlantic Theater Company, which produces radio dramas, will broadcast the premieres of 10 short dramas at its annual spring benefit to be held at Laura Belle, 120 West 43d Street. Roy Scheider and Felicity Huffman will introduce the new dramas by David Mamet and others, and performers will include Elizabeth McGovern. The performances will be broadcast at 9 P.M. on WBAI-FM (99.5). Tickets, $125 for dinner, show and dancing starting at 7 P.M. or $75 for open bar and show starting at 8 P.M., from (212) 645-8015.  Children's Book Night</p>
        <p>May 11 -- The New York Public Library will hold a black-tie dinner-dance at the library. Cocktails and a special exhibition of classic children's books, the evening's theme, will begin at 7 P.M., followed by dinner and dancing. Tickets, $500, from (212) 930-0730.  Fledgling Musicians</p>
        <p>May 12 -- Young Concert Artists, founded in 1961 to advance the careers of young musicians, will hold a black-tie all-Chopin concert at the Equitable Center auditorium, Seventh Avenue at 51st Street. A reception will follow the 8:30 P.M. concert. Tickets, $250, from (212) 307-6655.  'Swan Lake' and Dinner</p>
        <p>May 12 -- The Metropolitan Repertory Ballet will perform one act of "Swan Lake," followed by a reception and dinner to benefit the company. The 7:30 P.M. performance at the Birch Wathen Lenox Theater, 170 East 70th Street, will be followed by the party at Mortimer's, Lexington Avenue at 75th Street. Tickets, $225 or $125 for guests under the age of 35, from (212) 737-9010.  Family Gathering</p>
        <p>MAY 12 -- Cy Coleman, Richard Kiley, Carol Channing, Linda Lavin, Geoffrey Holder and Tony Randall are some of the show-business personalities who will entertain at a benefit at the Waldorf-Astoria for Planned Parenthood of New York City. Cocktails at 6 P.M. will be followed by dinner, an auction of vacations and other events. Tickets are $350, or $175 for dessert and auction only, which starts about 7:45 P.M., from (212) 274-7200.  Shakespeare Revised</p>
        <p>MAY 13 -- The Roots and Branches Theater, which explores intergenerational issues, has set "Romeo and Juliet" on a cruise ship for a benefit at the Jewish Association for Services for the Aged, 40 West 68th Street. A 6 P.M. cocktail reception precedes the performance. Tickets, $30, or $50 for two, from (212) 929-8381.  Pier Party</p>
        <p>MAY 13 -- The Children's Storefront, a private, tuition-free school in Harlem, will hold its annual spring benefit at the Pier 92 Passenger Terminal, West 52d Street and the Hudson River. Cocktails at 6:30 P.M. will be followed by a soul-food dinner and dancing. Tickets, $350, from (212) 838-2660.  Victorian Tea Dance</p>
        <p>MAY 13 -- The annual tea dance of the Victorian Society Scholarship Fund will raise money for graduate and post-graduate students in 19th-century British and American architecture and social and cultural history. It will be held at the Fletcher-Sinclair Mansion, 2 East 79th Street. Period dress is suggested. From 5:30 to 8 P.M. Tickets, $150, from (212) 206-5549.  Funds for a Legacy</p>
        <p>MAY 13 -- The late Joe Papp will be honored, and funds raised for his legacy, the New York Shakespeare Festival, at a benefit under a tent at Tavern on the Green. Alumni of the festival, including Meryl Streep, Kevin Kline, Linda Ronstadt, Cleo Laine and Betty Buckley, will perform at the event, which starts with cocktails at 7 P.M. Dinner and the show follow. Tickets, $500, from (212) 245-6570.  Women in Human Services</p>
        <p>MAY 13 -- A 5:30 P.M. cocktail party and cabaret will benefit Executive Women in Human Services, a group of officials in the public and private sectors working with issues affecting troubled women and girls in New York City. It will be held at the Greenwich House Music School, 27 Barrow Street (near Bedford Street). Tickets, $35, from (212) 254-9283.  About Suicide</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- The American Suicide Foundation, which promotes the study and prevention of suicide, will hold its fourth annual Lifesavers Dinner at the Waldorf-Astoria, starting with cocktails at 6:30 P.M. Matilda Cuomo, wife of Gov. Mario Cuomo, will be one of the award presenters. Tickets, $350, from (212) 410-1111.  Cerebral Palsy Inaugural</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- United Cerebral Palsy of New York has formed an offshoot called the New York Contemporary League, for young professionals who will plan fund-raising events on behalf of the parent organization. A party for the new group will be held at Wunderbar, 27 West 20th Street, with an open bar and buffet from 7 to 10 P.M. Tickets, $30, from (212) 683-6700, or $35 at the door.  Citiwomen Fund-raiser</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- New York Citiwomen, the professional women's group of Women's American O.R.T., which seeks to improve Jewish life worldwide through education, is holding a cocktail party and auction starting at 6:30 P.M. at the Country Club, 209 East 85th Street. Tickets, $55, from (212) 505-7700, Ext. 240, or $65 at the door.  Aiding African Students</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- A dinner-dance with African entertainment will be held in the Delegates' Dining Room of the United Nations to benefit the African student programs of the Phelps-Stokes Fund. Cocktails at 7 P.M. Black tie or national dress. Tickets, $175, from (212) 427-8100.  Global Warming</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- The American Museum of Natural History will celebrate the opening of its exhibition "Global Warming: Understading the Forecast" with a black-tie dinner, with entertainment, in the Hall of Ocean Life. Speakers will include Senators Albert Gore and Tim Wirth and there will be a reading by Charlton Heston. Cocktails at 6:30 P.M. Tickets, $500, from (212) 921-9070.  Jewish Culture Awards</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- Elie Wiesel, Itzhak Perlman and Pearl Lang will be among those honored at the annual Jewish Cultural Achievement Award Ceremonies sponsored by the National Foundation for Jewish Culture. A reception from 7 to 8 P.M. at the 92d Street Y will precede the awards ceremony. Tickets, $250, from (212) 629-0500.  Hispanic Arts Awards</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- The Intar Hispanic Arts Center will honor the writer Mario Vargas Llosa, the painter Fernando de Szyszlo and Luis Cancel, New York City Cultural Affairs Commissioner at a dinner-dance at the Pierre that will include entertainment. Cocktails at 7:30 P.M. Tickets, $225, from (212) 695-6135.  Benefit Billiards</p>
        <p>MAY 14 -- Westside Billiards, at 601 West 50th Street, will be the scene of an evening of billiards and pool, with instruction and demonstrations by professionals along with food, dancing and drinks. From 6:30 to 10:30 P.M. The evening will benefit the Children's Lung Center of Babies Hospital at the Columbia-Presbyterian Medical Center. Tickets, $200, from (212) 305-3155.  Party for De La Salle</p>
        <p>MAY 15 -- An evening of dining and dancing at the Puck Building, Lafayette and Houston Streets, will benefit De La Salle Academy, a Manhattan private school whose students are academically talented and from low-income families. Cocktails, 7:30 P.M. Tickets, $125, from (212) 316-5840.  Day at the Races</p>
        <p>MAY 15 -- An afternoon of racing at Belmont Park Race Track may be watched from the Turf and Field Club while enjoying a champagne brunch to benefit the New York City chapter of the National Multiple Sclerosis Society. Brunch starts at noon. Tickets, $125, from (212) 463-7787.  Dancing in the Park</p>
        <p>MAY 15 -- The Central Park Conservancy, a private group that helps to maintain and improve the park, will have a dance party at the Bethesda Fountain and Terrace at 72d Street in Central Park, from 5:30 to 8:30 P.M. Cocktails and hors d'oeuvres will be served. Tickets, $65, from (212) 315-0385.  Dancing Bulls</p>
        <p>MAY 16 -- The New York Stock Exchange is 200 years old, and there will be dancing on Wall Street to celebrate the anniversary, and to toast the formation of the New York Stock Exchange Bicentennial Foundation. The new foundation will establish programs in New York City public schools on the hows and whys of the world of finance. The black-tie party will be held under a tent outside the entrance of the Stock Exchange, at Wall and Broad streets. Cocktails at 7 P.M. Tickets, $1,000, from (212) 685-0113.  Bronx Literary Brunch</p>
        <p>MAY 16 -- The setting will be the historic 1840 Snuff Mill, the food a varied brunch, and the intellectual fare will be supplied by Frank Gilroy, Avery Corman and Jules Feiffer and other authors at a benefit at the New York Botantical Garden, in the Bedford Park section of the Bronx. The literary brunch, from noon to 2 P.M., will benefit the horticultural programs of the garden. Tickets, $35, (212) 220-8724.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
