<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71F3CF936A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-9  U.S. DISSENSION AT RIO</p>
        <p>The chief American negotiator at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro asked the White House to make it possible for the United States to sign a treaty on protecting animals and plants. He was firmly rebuffed.  A1  WORLD BANK SEEKS 'EARTH' FUND</p>
        <p>The World Bank has proposed that the United States and other donor nations contribute $5 billion to a fund that would provide virtually free grants to help the world's poorest countries protect their ecological systems, officials said.  A6  12 SIGN TREATY TO CURB GASES</p>
        <p>A dozen nations signed a climate treaty to curb gas emissions, and Austria, Switzerland and the Netherlands talked of stronger action.  A6  RUSSIAN AID STALLED IN U.S.</p>
        <p>As election-year politics sap much of the enthusiasm for foreign aid bills, the Bush Administration's multibillion-dollar package for Russia is stalled in Congress. Leaders say they don't know when -- or if -- it will be approved.  A1  NATO SEEKS NEW PEACE ROLE</p>
        <p>Seeking a new role after the cold war, NATO agreed in principle to support peacekeeping operations in Eastern Europe or the former Soviet Union if asked to do so by the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe.  A1  CHILL FOR EAST GERMAN HEARTHS</p>
        <p>People in eastern German towns like Zepernick are near despair as houses are claimed by former owners or their descendants who now live in western Germany.  A3  12 ARRESTED IN SPYING CASE</p>
        <p>Twelve people were arrested, including three officers of the former East German secret police, on suspicion of operating a ring in West Germany that killed hundreds of foes of the former Communist regime.  A7  OUTRAGED POLES OUST PREMIER</p>
        <p>The Polish Parliament voted to dismiss the Prime Minister and his Cabinet after the Interior Ministry released a list of people it said had collaborated with the Communists. The list included many lawmakers and some ministers.  A7  ANTICLIMAX IN YUGOSLAVIA</p>
        <p>The Government of what remains of Yugoslavia said the ruling party had won the biggest bloc of the votes in parliamentary elections. Drivers shrugged in mile-long gas lines.  A8  The European Community will keep pursuing its treaty on union.  A9  The Pope arrives in Angola to celebrate its break with Marxism.  A9  Beijing Journal: Fury has faded since the 1989 crackdown.  A4  National A10-18  BUSH AND PEROT</p>
        <p>The President held a prime-time news conference in which he refused to be drawn into direct criticism of Ross Perot, declining to say even whether he would debate Mr. Perot this fall.  A1</p>
        <p>A transcript of the President's remarks.  A16</p>
        <p>Perot counterattacked against the buy-the-election charge.  A18</p>
        <p>A Senate panel on missing servicemen called Perot to testify.  A18</p>
        <p>Nixon said he "wouldn't bet against" Perot.  A17</p>
        <p>On the Trail: Debates would likely include Perot.  A17</p>
        <p>Cuomo said he did not expect to run with Clinton.  A18</p>
        <p>In a year of unconventional politics, unconventional forums too.  A18</p>
        <p>Congressional Memo: The Constitution and electoral fear.  A14  BIG INSIDER-TRADING CASE</p>
        <p>After a four-year inquiry, the S.E.C. filed insider-trading charges against six prominent corporate executives and investors, including Edward R. Downe Jr., a former director of Bear, Stearns, and Martin E. Revson, co-founder of Revlon.  A1  LOVE ME SLENDER</p>
        <p>The people have spoken. They prefer the younger, trimmer Elvis as the image on a new stamp, and the Postal Service will comply.  A10  SUSPENDED FATES</p>
        <p>Tens of thousands of frozen human embryos, leftovers from high-tech fertility treatment, lie stored in tanks of liquid nitrogen throughout the country. Their number is growing, and in many cases what will happen to them is uncertain.  A10  HAITIAN DETAINEES CHARGE ABUSE</p>
        <p>Refugee advocacy groups say many of the 250 or so Haitians who are interned at a detention center in Miami are being abused and intimidated by guards there.  A10  A FOCUS OF THE POSTAL INQUIRY</p>
        <p>An obscure patronage employee at the House post office has emerged as a pivotal figure in a criminal investigation that has already embarrassed House leaders and now appears to threaten other powerful Democrats, like Representative Rostenkowski.  A12  THE FALLOUT FROM FRIENDLY FIRE</p>
        <p>Although the smoke from the Persian Gulf war has long since cleared, accidental allied casualties from American fire are still sending shock waves through the military.  A14  Sununu intervened in census deliberations, an official said.  A14  Law Page B8  Hocus-pocus? Fraternal argot? Why do lawyers write that way?</p>
        <p>A black woman once barred by a law school claims her place as a regent.</p>
        <p>At the Bar  Metropolitan Digest, B1 CONGRESSIONAL SNAKE</p>
        <p>Slithering from upper Manhattan to Manhattan Beach in Brooklyn, the proposed new Eighth Congressional District would fuse the districts of two longtime Representatives into one new battleground.  A1  ASBESTOS AND TAXES</p>
        <p>The cost of modernizing an obsolete building filled with asbestos can be used to reduce the building's property tax bill, under a ruling upheld yesterday by New York State's top court.  A1  Business Digest, D1  Weekend C1-30  The manners of moviegoing.C1  The sequel in literature.  C1  Fear and loathing in search of evil.  C1  Warning on global warming.  C26  Sports B9-15  Baseball: Yankees fall to Tigers.  B9  Pirates beats Mets, 7-2.  B9  Era ends in Miami.  B1o  Basketball: Teammate chides Jordan.  B12  Column: Vecsey on Jordan.  B9  Tennis: Seles and Graf rally.  B9  Obituaries B7  Patrick Peyton, Roman Catholic priest.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A28-29  Editorials A28  Bad boy of biodiversity? Denmark and Europe. A Mad world. Doing politicians' work. Letters A28  A. M. Rosenthal: Reality in Israel.  A29  Leslie H. Gelb: Silver lining for Eurodoom.  A29  James Squires: When you see Perot, you see Perot.  A29  Louis J. Freeh: The mob claims a martyr.  A29</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-9  U.S. DISSENSION AT RIO</p>
        <p>The chief American negotiator at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro asked the White House to make it possible for the United States to sign a treaty on protecting animals and plants. He was firmly rebuffed.  A1  WORLD BANK SEEKS 'EARTH' FUND</p>
        <p>The World Bank has proposed that the United States and other donor nations contribute $5 billion to a fund that would provide virtually free grants to help the world's poorest countries protect their ecological systems, officials said.  A6  12 SIGN TREATY TO CURB GASES</p>
        <p>A dozen nations signed a climate treaty to curb gas emissions, and Austria, Switzerland and the Netherlands talked of stronger action.  A6  RUSSIAN AID STALLED IN U.S.</p>
        <p>As election-year politics sap much of the enthusiasm for foreign aid bills, the Bush Administration's multibillion-dollar package for Russia is stalled in Congress. Leaders say they don't know when -- or if -- it will be approved.  A1  NATO SEEKS NEW PEACE ROLE</p>
        <p>Seeking a new role after the cold war, NATO agreed in principle to support peacekeeping operations in Eastern Europe or the former Soviet Union if asked to do so by the Conference on Security and Cooperation in Europe.  A1  CHILL FOR EAST GERMAN HEARTHS</p>
        <p>People in eastern German towns like Zepernick are near despair as houses are claimed by former owners or their descendants who now live in western Germany.  A3  12 ARRESTED IN SPYING CASE</p>
        <p>Twelve people were arrested, including three officers of the former East German secret police, on suspicion of operating a ring in West Germany that killed hundreds of foes of the former Communist regime.  A7  OUTRAGED POLES OUST PREMIER</p>
        <p>The Polish Parliament voted to dismiss the Prime Minister and his Cabinet after the Interior Ministry released a list of people it said had collaborated with the Communists. The list included many lawmakers and some ministers.  A7  ANTICLIMAX IN YUGOSLAVIA</p>
        <p>The Government of what remains of Yugoslavia said the ruling party had won the biggest bloc of the votes in parliamentary elections. Drivers shrugged in mile-long gas lines.  A8  The European Community will keep pursuing its treaty on union.  A9  The Pope arrives in Angola to celebrate its break with Marxism.  A9  Beijing Journal: Fury has faded since the 1989 crackdown.  A4  National A10-18  BUSH AND PEROT</p>
        <p>The President held a prime-time news conference in which he refused to be drawn into direct criticism of Ross Perot, declining to say even whether he would debate Mr. Perot this fall.  A1</p>
        <p>A transcript of the President's remarks.  A16</p>
        <p>Perot counterattacked against the buy-the-election charge.  A18</p>
        <p>A Senate panel on missing servicemen called Perot to testify.  A18</p>
        <p>Nixon said he "wouldn't bet against" Perot.  A17</p>
        <p>On the Trail: Debates would likely include Perot.  A17</p>
        <p>Cuomo said he did not expect to run with Clinton.  A18</p>
        <p>In a year of unconventional politics, unconventional forums too.  A18</p>
        <p>Congressional Memo: The Constitution and electoral fear.  A14  BIG INSIDER-TRADING CASE</p>
        <p>After a four-year inquiry, the S.E.C. filed insider-trading charges against six prominent corporate executives and investors, including Edward R. Downe Jr., a former director of Bear, Stearns, and Martin E. Revson, co-founder of Revlon.  A1  LOVE ME SLENDER</p>
        <p>The people have spoken. They prefer the younger, trimmer Elvis as the image on a new stamp, and the Postal Service will comply.  A10  SUSPENDED FATES</p>
        <p>Tens of thousands of frozen human embryos, leftovers from high-tech fertility treatment, lie stored in tanks of liquid nitrogen throughout the country. Their number is growing, and in many cases what will happen to them is uncertain.  A10  HAITIAN DETAINEES CHARGE ABUSE</p>
        <p>Refugee advocacy groups say many of the 250 or so Haitians who are interned at a detention center in Miami are being abused and intimidated by guards there.  A10  A FOCUS OF THE POSTAL INQUIRY</p>
        <p>An obscure patronage employee at the House post office has emerged as a pivotal figure in a criminal investigation that has already embarrassed House leaders and now appears to threaten other powerful Democrats, like Representative Rostenkowski.  A12  THE FALLOUT FROM FRIENDLY FIRE</p>
        <p>Although the smoke from the Persian Gulf war has long since cleared, accidental allied casualties from American fire are still sending shock waves through the military.  A14  Sununu intervened in census deliberations, an official said.  A14  Law Page B8  Hocus-pocus? Fraternal argot? Why do lawyers write that way?</p>
        <p>A black woman once barred by a law school claims her place as a regent.</p>
        <p>At the Bar  Metropolitan Digest, B1 CONGRESSIONAL SNAKE</p>
        <p>Slithering from upper Manhattan to Manhattan Beach in Brooklyn, the proposed new Eighth Congressional District would fuse the districts of two longtime Representatives into one new battleground.  A1  ASBESTOS AND TAXES</p>
        <p>The cost of modernizing an obsolete building filled with asbestos can be used to reduce the building's property tax bill, under a ruling upheld yesterday by New York State's top court.  A1  Business Digest, D1  Weekend C1-30  The manners of moviegoing.C1  The sequel in literature.  C1  Fear and loathing in search of evil.  C1  Warning on global warming.  C26  Sports B9-15  Baseball: Yankees fall to Tigers.  B9  Pirates beats Mets, 7-2.  B9  Era ends in Miami.  B1o  Basketball: Teammate chides Jordan.  B12  Column: Vecsey on Jordan.  B9  Tennis: Seles and Graf rally.  B9  Obituaries B7  Patrick Peyton, Roman Catholic priest.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A28-29  Editorials A28  Bad boy of biodiversity? Denmark and Europe. A Mad world. Doing politicians' work. Letters A28  A. M. Rosenthal: Reality in Israel.  A29  Leslie H. Gelb: Silver lining for Eurodoom.  A29  James Squires: When you see Perot, you see Perot.  A29  Louis J. Freeh: The mob claims a martyr.  A29</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
