<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. FOLLOWING UP ACCORDS FROM RIO</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT COMMISSION (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB1E3CF932A35751C1A964958260" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. FOLLOWING UP ACCORDS FROM RIO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Nov. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After difficult negotiations between industrialized and developing countries, the two sides have agreed on the make-up and the powers of an agency to monitor how governments live up to the promises they made in June in Rio de Janeiro at the first Earth Summit.</p>
        <p>Under an informal agreement reached by assembly delegates last Wednesday, a new 53-member group, the Sustainable Development Commission, will regularly scrutinize the environmental records of all nations, hearing evidence from both governments and private groups like Greenpeace and Friends of the Earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After difficult negotiations between industrialized and developing countries, the two sides have agreed on the make-up and the powers of an agency to monitor how governments live up to the promises they made in June in Rio de Janeiro at the first Earth Summit.</p>
        <p>Under an informal agreement reached by assembly delegates last Wednesday, a new 53-member group, the Sustainable Development Commission, will regularly scrutinize the environmental records of all nations, hearing evidence from both governments and private groups like Greenpeace and Friends of the Earth.</p>
        <p>Though the commission is viewed as a linchpin of the accords reached at the Earth Summit, it will lack the power to make governments respect their pledges to insure that future economic development is environmentally sound. Like the Human Rights Commission in Geneva, on which it is modeled, the Sustainable Development Commission will rely on publicity and international pressure to make countries keep their promises.</p>
        <p>The industrial nations will nominate 19 of the 53 members, Africa and Asia 12 each and Latin America 10. Winners and Losers</p>
        <p>The agreement brings the two sides very different benefits and disadvantages.</p>
        <p>More-advanced developing countries, including India, Malaysia and Brazil, initially opposed outside scrutiny of their industrial policies. But in the end they agreed because the commission will eventually their financial advantage, diplomats here said.</p>
        <p>And a commission that enjoys the confidence of industrial nations could exert political pressure on them to provide the extra aid they promised in Rio to pay for maintaining higher environmental standards in developing lands.</p>
        <p>That aid would include cleaner technologies and an expansion of a special World Bank fund called the Global Environmental Facility. There was also a general pledge, from which the United States disassociated itself, to double the annual share of aid, to seven-tenths of 1 percent of the industrial world's economic output. The Main Tasks</p>
        <p>The resolution setting up the commission is to be adopted by the General Assembly next month. It says the commission's main task is to monitor how countries carry out Agenda 21, which is a blueprint for cleaning up the environment and encouraging development in an environmentally sound manner, and a global consensus on forest management. The latter document recommends that countries assess the impact of economic development on their forests and take steps, individually and jointly, to minimize the damage.</p>
        <p>Separate Rio conventions to protect plant and animal species and curb global warming have their own procedures for compliance.</p>
        <p>The Sustainable Development Commission is to meet twice a year, in New York and in Geneva. Its secretariat will probably be located in Geneva and directed by Nittin Desai of India, who served as deputy to Maurice Strong of Canada, the secretary general of the Earth Summit.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
