<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ACCORD ON LIMITS ON GAS EMISSIONS IS SAID TO BE NEAR</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD133EF93BA35756C0A964958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ACCORD ON LIMITS ON GAS EMISSIONS IS SAID TO BE NEAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, May 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hoping to break a longstanding deadlock between the United States and Europe, negotiators were closing in today on a compromise that would limit industrialized countries' emissions of gases tied to global warming, according to officials involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>The proposal, circulating among delegates in draft form, would be a centerpiece of the Earth Summit meeting next month in Rio de Janeiro. Failure to come to an agreement in the preliminary talks here would seriously undermine the success of the conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hoping to break a longstanding deadlock between the United States and Europe, negotiators were closing in today on a compromise that would limit industrialized countries' emissions of gases tied to global warming, according to officials involved in the talks.</p>
        <p>The proposal, circulating among delegates in draft form, would be a centerpiece of the Earth Summit meeting next month in Rio de Janeiro. Failure to come to an agreement in the preliminary talks here would seriously undermine the success of the conference.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, industrialized countries would limit emissions of greenhouse gases, with the aim of capping them at 1990 levels, a point the Administration has long resisted. But, yielding to Washington's position, the draft does not set a deadline or timetable for reaching the goal. Shifts by Both Sides</p>
        <p>Instead, it calls for industrialized countries merely to recognize that returning to "earlier levels" of emissions by the end of the decade would contribute to the long-term objective of stabilizing the amounts of heat-trapping gases in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Both sides are thus prepared to modify their positions, with the Europeans seeming to yield more in practical terms.</p>
        <p>The draft treaty would also call for a framework, governing body and long-term process for continually assessing and responding to climate change as its nature becomes clearer in coming decades. Catastrophic Warming</p>
        <p>The tentative deal was seen as unlikely to satisfy any parties fully. Environmentalists denounced it as unacceptably weak, even as a first step. Spokesmen for the coal and electric utility industries, which have opposed any restrictions on emissions, said yesterday they would not comment on the draft compromise.</p>
        <p>The treaty would be signed by heads of government at Rio.</p>
        <p>Scientists who are advising the talks here say that if the heat-trapping greenhouse gases continue to build up in the atmosphere at present rates, the earth's climate will warm by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit by the end of the next century, with possibly catastrophic effects on the world's climate.  Carbon dioxide, the most important of the gases, is emitted by the burning of fossil fuels like coal, oil and natural gas, the energy underpinnings of the industrial economy. The United States emits more than 20 percent of the world's carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The text of the draft circulating today said the compromise on emissions would "demonstrate" that the industrialized countries are taking the lead in working toward the long-term objective of stabilizing atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations at safe levels.</p>
        <p>The prospective compromise on emission of the gases bridges the long-held positions of the European Community and the United States.</p>
        <p>The community had argued for action to firmly halt carbon dioxide emissions at 1990 levels by the year 2000. The Bush Administration insisted that for the United States to enact limits on emissions were unnecessary because energy-efficiency measures already being taken by the United States would nearly achieve the desired level in practice. The United States had resisted being forced to adopt targets and timetables it was not sure it could meet without causing economic harm.</p>
        <p>In the compromise under discussion today, the Europeans would also accede to an American preference that all heat-trapping greenhouse gases, not just carbon dioxide, be included in the emissions agreement. The United States believes that its performance is improved when all heat trapping gases are taken into consideration.</p>
        <p>Though the compromise aims for a return to 1990 levels of greenhouse gas emissions, something the United Staes had opposed, it would not actually set a deadline for doing so. According to the text, it calls for the industrialized countries to report periodically on their actions and results in limiting emissions, "with the aim" of returning to 1990 levels.  Treaty 'Is Now a Shell'</p>
        <p>The parties, according to a separate paragraph of the text, would "recognize" that returning to "earlier levels" of emissions by the end of this decade would contribute to the treaty's long-term objective of stabilizing atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations.  The years 2000 and 1990 are not directly linked.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists attacked the compromise on the ground that it appeared to allow governments too much latitude and room to wiggle out.</p>
        <p>"It contains no meaningful commitment to reduce greenhouse gases," said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund. "At best, it provides a procedure which could lead to real commitments in the future."</p>
        <p>Others were stronger in their critcism.</p>
        <p>"The climate treaty is now a shell that will allow continued degradation of the global atmosphere," said Richard Mott, treaties officer of the World Wildlife Fund. "Faced with an ultimatum from the U.S., the Europeans have abandoned their promise to include binding commitments in the treaty." Aid to the Third World</p>
        <p>The compromise was reportedly emerging from intensive negotiations by a steering commmittee, representing 25 key nations and a representative of small island states. They are part of the larger, 130-member Intergovernmental Negotiating Committee on Climate Change, a body that reports to the United Nations General Assembly. The emerging compromise must still be approved by the full committee before the concluding round of treaty talks ends tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Moreover, still to be resolved was the equally critical issue of the way in which industrialized countries will provide financial and technological aid to third-world countries in attacking the problem of climate change. The third-world countries' greenhouse-gas emissions are much lower than those of the industrialized world. But they are expected to grow rapidly in the decades ahead, and the draft treaty requires developing countries to undertake national programs for limiting the gases.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
