<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talking: Solar Energy; New Ways To Get Off The Grid</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544084"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOLAR ENERGY INDUSTRIES ASSN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, ANDREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71630F93AA25754C0A964958260" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talking: Solar Energy; New Ways To Get Off The Grid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREE BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, ANDREE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SALES of solar energy devices for the home are rising after a decade in the doldrums despite the recession and even though the cost may not always make economic sense -- an indication, perhaps, of a desire by more homeowners to help preserve the planet.</p>
        <p>In 1990, solar hot water system sales rose 15 percent over 1989, according to the Solar Energy Industries Association, a trade group based in Washington, which predicted another 15 percent rise this year. And 1991 sales of solar-powered devices for the home, like attic fans and outdoor lighting, rose 27 percent over 1990, with a further 25 percent gain expected this year, the association said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SALES of solar energy devices for the home are rising after a decade in the doldrums despite the recession and even though the cost may not always make economic sense -- an indication, perhaps, of a desire by more homeowners to help preserve the planet.</p>
        <p>In 1990, solar hot water system sales rose 15 percent over 1989, according to the Solar Energy Industries Association, a trade group based in Washington, which predicted another 15 percent rise this year. And 1991 sales of solar-powered devices for the home, like attic fans and outdoor lighting, rose 27 percent over 1990, with a further 25 percent gain expected this year, the association said.</p>
        <p>For some, the potential saving was the catalyst.</p>
        <p>"When you feel pinched, you look for ways to reduce your overhead," said Scott Sklar, president of the association.</p>
        <p>The group discovered that as some homeowners started to refinance to benefit from lower interest rates, it made financial sense to borrow an extra $4,000 or so to install a typical two-panel solar hot-water system. This was particularly true if, despite the added debt service, the system could save the buyer as much as -- or more than -- he had been paying each month to heat water.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mark Novotny, an internist who lives with his wife and two children in Manchester, Vt., installed a $3,200 solar hot-water system in May He estimated that the $38 a month he pays on a 10-year loan would be hardly more than the $30 he had been paying to heat water electrically.</p>
        <p>Paul Hood, a peace activist in Charlotte, Vt., said he chose solar as the primary energy source for his new home because "we had a continuing concern about the disposal of nuclear wastes and the using of nonrenewable energy sources."</p>
        <p>One home solar hot-water system can cut the discharge of carbon dioxide into the atmosphere -- the principal cause of global warming -- by 20 tons over two decades compared to electric water heating, according to the National Renewable Energy Laboratories, a federally financed research group in Golden, Colo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hood's 1,500-square-foot saltbox has eight roof-mounted photovoltaic panels, with a backup generator. Installed last year by Solar Works of Montpelier, Vt., the system cost $8,000, including the inverter that converts solar-generated DC to 110 volt AC for normal appliances. Mr. Hood said the system cost about a third more than hooking up to power lines, which would have had to be extended a half mile to reach the house.</p>
        <p>A glass-covered black metal water tank on the roof provides a simple type of solar-heated hot water during the summer, a cheaper alternative to the traditional solar hot water system, said Mr. Hood. There is a backup propane heater.</p>
        <p>One place homeowners can begin searching for solar solutions is with information on the updated products being marketed -- plus the names and phone numbers of local suppliers and installers.</p>
        <p>Comprehensive background reading can be found in the Consumer Guide to Solar Energy, a 181-page book published in 1991 by Bonus Books of Chicago. For a copy, send $11 to American Solar Energy Society, 2400 Central Avenue, Boulder, Colo., 80301. The book includes a guide to suppliers and local solar trade associations.</p>
        <p>Some 200 solar contractors from around the country are listed in the 1992 edition of the Solar Source Book, a directory compiled by the Solar Energy Industries Association. The book also lists local utility companies that have financial incentive programs or state agencies that can supply information about other financial incentives. Send $12.50 to SEIA, 777 North Capitol Street, Washington, D.C. 20002.</p>
        <p>UTILITY incentive programs are also reviving after being discontinued in the mid 80's "because of pressure from their state utility commissions to reduce demand," said Mr. Sklar. "It's cheaper than building new plants."</p>
        <p>In New York, utility companies are starting to file plans with state officials and more specific information may not available until later this year, said Gary Brown, a policy analyst for the New York State Energy Office. Elsewhere, homeowners should check with their local utility business office.</p>
        <p>New York State has also revived its property tax abatement program for improvements with a solar component. Called the Solar Real Property Tax Exemption, it was reinstated by state legislators on Jan. 1, 1991, after having been discontinued for two years.</p>
        <p>One way to enhance solar efficiency on a limited budget might be to consider improvements to an existing system or the use of second-hand hardware.</p>
        <p>Everett Barber Jr., president of Sunsearch, a solar contractor in Guilford, Conn., is offering about 50 used collectors at about 40 percent below the cost of similar models bought new. They are most useful, he said, for enhancing an existing system.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barber, who is also an associate professor of environmental technologies at Yale School of Architecture, said there are many other ways to put new zest into an older system. He has found, for example, that collectors with a plastic film or fiberglass covering tend to lose about 60 percent of their efficiency after about eight years because the surface gradually clouds over. Replacing the covering costs about $250 a panel, far less than installing new panels.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes we find that the problem is as simple as controls that were wired incorrectly," said Mr. Barber, "or backup sources of heat that were never properly installed."</p>
        <p>Before choosing a solar contractor, Mr. Barber recommends determining how many years of experience the installer has had with the products being installed; the names of area homeowners who are using the same system; the anticipated life of the solar hot-water tank based on the installer's experience rather than the manufacturer's claims; what procedures might be needed to safeguard the system from overheating during a prolonged absence and anticipated maintenance costs.</p>
        <p>Among the many smaller solar-powered items useful for the homeowner on a small budget are attic fans, which sell for around $300. One source is Applied Energy Technology of Swisher, Iowa. (For details, call (319) 857-412.) Much information about solar energy, plus a wide variety of devices -- from toys to complete power systems -- is in the "Real Goods" mail-order catalog. For a free copy, call the company in Ukiah, Calif., toll-free, at (800) 762-7325.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
