<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All About/Insect Repellents; Companies Grapple With the Bugs in Repellents</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="550647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSECTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DANIELS, CORA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D8113CF935A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="1602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All About/Insect Repellents; Companies Grapple With the Bugs in Repellents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORA DANIELS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DANIELS, CORA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For biting insects, this season offers a two-month feast of exposed arms and legs around most of the nation. To ward off the bugs' unwelcome advances, people douse themselves and their children with more than $50 million worth of insect repellents a year.</p>
        <p>Sales have spurted as much as 30 percent in recent years in areas affected by outbreaks of Lyme disease, primarily the Northeast, and encephalitis, mainly in the Southwest. Those illnesses have turned the feeding habits of some mosquitoes, gnats, ticks and flies into more than the usual annoyance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For biting insects, this season offers a two-month feast of exposed arms and legs around most of the nation. To ward off the bugs' unwelcome advances, people douse themselves and their children with more than $50 million worth of insect repellents a year.</p>
        <p>Sales have spurted as much as 30 percent in recent years in areas affected by outbreaks of Lyme disease, primarily the Northeast, and encephalitis, mainly in the Southwest. Those illnesses have turned the feeding habits of some mosquitoes, gnats, ticks and flies into more than the usual annoyance.</p>
        <p>The repellents most used in the fight are Off, the leading brand, from S. C. Johnson Wax, followed by Cutter, from Miles Inc. of Elkhart, Ind.</p>
        <p>The widespread press attention given to the outbreak of the tick-borne Lyme disease a few years ago prompted the companies to promote their maximum-strength formulas. Many also changed their labels to tout their effectiveness against ticks.</p>
        <p>But this aggressive marketing caught the eye last year of New York State health officials, who questioned the safety of DEET, the most common active chemical in repellents. In reaction to the move by New York, which often sets the tone for national changes, the industry turned around to promote its lowest-strength products. Also, several small companies have started selling "natural" insect repellents without DEET.</p>
        <p>Even though the stronger products remain on the market, the marketing shift dismayed some health experts who say the strongerDEET products are safe when used properly. They say lower concentrations of the chemical could lead to increased cases of Lyme disease, because the product might not be strong enough to repel deer ticks.</p>
        <p>Overall, sales of repellents have risen for 40 years, said Ralph Engel, president of the Chemical Specialties Manufacturers Association, a trade group in Washington. "It is a seasonal product which has not grown in leaps and bounds but has steady growth."</p>
        <p>S. C. Johnson, based in Racine, Wis., remains the undisputed leader in the repellent business, with perhaps as much as 80 percent of the industry's sales of DEET-based products. Miles is a far second, with the 3M Corporation and others holding small market shares. Johnson and Miles, as well as most other repellent companies, are privately owned and do not disclose sales or earnings figures.</p>
        <p>Then there's the wild card, Skin-So-Soft bath oil by Avon Products of New York, which by word of mouth has gained a reputation among campers and anglers as an excellent insect repellent. That fact pains Avon executives, who would just as soon not associate bugs with beauty and who decline to capitalize on the bath oil's benign side effect.</p>
        <p>Still, Mediamark Research Inc., a Chicago-based marketing research group, found that 26 percent of shoppers who said they had used insect repellents between March 1991 and February 1992 named Skin-So-Soft as the brand. Off products accounted for 47.5 percent and Cutter was 11.8 percent. Safety Concerns  More DEET, More Trouble?</p>
        <p>Though there are 16 different brands of insect repellents on the market, most are similar in that they contain DEET, the most effective repellent chemical available. The concentrations range from 7 percent in a product for backyard use to 100 percent for people going into the deep woods for a while.</p>
        <p>DEET -- or N,N-diethyl-meta-toluamide -- was developed for the Army in 1951. The safety concerns about DEET stem from reports of minor skin irritations in adults to, in extreme cases, neurological harm to children when overused and misused.</p>
        <p>The New York State Health Department tried last summer to ban repellents sold in the state that contained more than about 30 percent DEET. The Chemical Specialties Manufacturers Association obtained a restraining order blocking the restriction.</p>
        <p>Though New York's health department recognizes that the number of cases involving negative reactions to DEET are rare officials are not convinced that higher percentages of DEET guarantee increased protection.</p>
        <p>"We looked through the literature and there was increased adverse reactions as the percentage of DEET increased," said Vicki Zeldin a spokeswoman for the New York State Health Department. "We are not convinced that 100 percent DEET is necessarily better than 30 percent due to the potential reactions."</p>
        <p>The health department said it acted last year out of concern that misuse would increase because of the public fear of Lyme disease and from what had been the industry's aggressive marketing of repellents with high levels of DEET. Higher levels work longer, but are also more likely to cause an allergic reaction.</p>
        <p>New York had the largest number of incidents of Lyme disease in the nation last year, with more than 3,200 reported cases. The Regulators  New York Against the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>While no other states have followed New York's attempt to restrict the percentage of DEET, in 1989 the Environmental Protection Agency required a caution about the chemical on all repellent labels.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has since conducted extensive testing of DEET and maintains that when used properly it is the safest and most effective repellent chemical.</p>
        <p>As for the New York restrictions, "Our data shows no indication that such actions need to be enforced," said Joe Tavano, assistant product manager in the office of pesticide projects for the E.P.A. "We are talking about a few cases in which the product was obviously misused."</p>
        <p>Besides drinking the repellent, the misuse often involved repeated and heavy coatings of the products beyond the manufacturer's recommendations, especially on infants or young children.</p>
        <p>Repellents in general work by masking the odor from carbon dioxide given off by the body that attracts mosquitoes and some other biting insects.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. recommends that DEET repellents be lightly sprayed onto the skin and clothing and washed off once indoors. Sprayed skin should not be covered up, and care should be taken to avoid spraying the face and mouth area. DEET is not recommended for use on infants or young children. A Natural Approach  Attracting The Consumer</p>
        <p>With questions still remaining about DEET, a few companies are trying to find ways to exploit the uncertainty.</p>
        <p>Some have introduced natural alternative repellents using citronella oil from citrosa grass, which is primarily grown in Florida.  Citrosa plants and citronella candles have been used for more then a decade to repel mosquitoes. But these are effective for shorter amounts of time than DEET and do not protect against ticks.</p>
        <p>One such company is the Tender Corporation, in Littleton, N.H., which has a citronella-based repellent called Natrapal.</p>
        <p>The Tender Corporation also makes a line of DEET repellents called Ben's. But last year, Natrapal generated 29 percent of the company's sales, compared with 16 percent for the Ben's line .</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has relatively little data on citronella, but it says it will be conducting studies in the next few years as part of the oil's re-registration process.</p>
        <p>"Just because something is natural does not mean that it is less toxic," said Dick Mountfort, an E.P.A. manager who is looking into citronella.</p>
        <p>The Littlepoint Corporation in Cambridge, Mass., is countering the DEET scare with a repellent developed specifically for children. The repellent, Skedaddle!, which was introduced last fall, has a system that prevents DEET from seeping directly into the child's skin. This method of reducing absorption rates while limiting the extent of evaporation, enables the 10 percent of DEET in Skedaddle! to last up to four hours, twice as long as usual.</p>
        <p>"Repellents are pretty much the same as underarm deodorants or mouthwashes," explained Joe Knowls, the president of Littlepoint. "All the ones that work use the same ingredient."  A REPELLENT INCOGNITO</p>
        <p>While the major insect-repellent companies work hard to find just the right marketing approach for their products, most acknowledge that Avon's sweet-smelling, DEET-less bath oil has effortlessly become one of their biggest competitors.</p>
        <p>In fact, while the other companies are quick to criticize Skin-So-Soft (though not for attribution) as having no justification as a repellent, a few are trying to imitate its success with their own products.</p>
        <p>S. C. Johnson Wax, for instance, now has Skintastic, which contains 7.5 percent DEET. The company markets the repellent as a "pleasant smelling" lotion that also moisturizes the skin.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency reports an increase in similar low-level DEET repellents that moonlight as skin softeners or sunscreens. But some researchers are concerned that consumers might be misled about the amount of protection the newer products provide.</p>
        <p>"Most of these products haven't been tested," said Durland Fish, director of the Lyme Disease Center at New York Medical College in Armonk. "So people run the risk of getting a serious illness because they think they are being protected."</p>
        <p>As for Skin-So-Soft, researchers say it contains no known repellent. They speculate that it may work for some people because of something in their skin chemistry that combines with the bath oil to prevent bites.</p>
        <p>Avon, a bit embarrassed by the decidedly unglamorous use of its bath oil to fend off pests, denies that Skin-So-Soft is an effective repellent.</p>
        <p>"It does not please us tremendously to hear that our customers are using our products in ways that they are not meant to be used," said Kathleen Walas, Avon's manager of product relations. "We are not in the repellent business, but the beauty business."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
