<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CRATER SUPPORTS EXTINCTION THEORY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="550077"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALEONTOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DINOSAURS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALVAREZ, WALTER (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DC113CF937A2575BC0A964958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CRATER SUPPORTS EXTINCTION THEORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A theory about the mass extinction of the dinosaurs that has been debated by scientists for a dozen years is getting a major boost today as researchers report pinning down the precise date when a huge object from outer space slammed into Earth.</p>
        <p>Its arrival 64.98 million years ago, forming a crater about 110 miles wide on the northern edge of the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico, strengthens its status as the leading candidate for a cataclysmic impact thought to have contributed to the mass extinction of life at the end of the age of dinosaurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A theory about the mass extinction of the dinosaurs that has been debated by scientists for a dozen years is getting a major boost today as researchers report pinning down the precise date when a huge object from outer space slammed into Earth.</p>
        <p>Its arrival 64.98 million years ago, forming a crater about 110 miles wide on the northern edge of the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico, strengthens its status as the leading candidate for a cataclysmic impact thought to have contributed to the mass extinction of life at the end of the age of dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>The idea of cosmic extinction was first proposed in 1980 by Dr. Walter Alvarez, a geologist at the University of California at Berkeley. He and his colleagues had found unusually large amounts of the rare metal iridium in sediments laid down about the time the dinosaurs died out, at the end of the Cretaceous period some 65 million years ago. They proposed that the iridium came from a cosmic catastrophe. Crater Was Rediscovered</p>
        <p>A weak link in the theory was the lack of a candidate crater formed at the right time and big enough to trigger mass extinctions by blotting out the sun with a global pall of dust.</p>
        <p>Scientists recently rediscovered the huge Yucatan crater, long buried by sediment and tentatively identified in 1981 by oil geologists, and put it forward as probable ground zero. It was definitely big enough, but its age was uncertain. Rock samples taken above the crater were quite old, leading some experts to rule it out as an agent of dinosaur destruction.</p>
        <p>Now, the Yucatan crater has been dated accurately. Dr. Alvarez and 11 colleagues at seven institutions report today in the journal Science that melted rock from the crater itself is 64.98 million years old, plus or minus 0.05 million years, and that older rocks above the crater were probably thrown there by the catastrophic upheaval. 'Thinking We'd Never Find It'</p>
        <p>Dr. Alvarez said that since the theory was first proposed, he had often been disappointed, "if not embarrassed," by the failure of experts to locate an appropriate crater. "Many of us were thinking we'd never find it," he said in an interview. "So it's a very exciting and rewarding time."</p>
        <p>The Yucatan crater, named Chicxulub (pronounced cheek-soo-LOOB) after a nearby Mexican town, is one of the largest impact craters, if not the largest, of the 140 or so that have been found on Earth.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alvarez and his colleagues, led by Dr. Carl C. Swisher 3d at the Institute of Human Origins in Berkeley, identified its age with an advanced method, argon-argon dating, which reads a radioactive clock that ticks away in rocks as bits of potassium-40 decay into argon-40.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alvarez and his colleagues found not only that the crater's age was exactly right for the candidate killer, but that its melted rock was of an age "virtually indistinguishable" from that of glassy debris known as tektites that have been found in Haiti and northeastern Mexico.</p>
        <p>The findings, they said, suggest that the tektites were created by the fiery impact.</p>
        <p>From the outset, the Alvarez theory has had backers and detractors in many fields of science, with skeptics arguing that volcanoes and other terrestrial processes could more plausibly explain the demise of the dinosaurs. Some Remain Skeptical</p>
        <p>Dr. William A. Clemens, a prominent paleontologist at the University of California at Berkeley, said yesterday that he remained skeptical despite the new study that a strike from space extinguished much life on Earth 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>"Impacts are more frequent that we used to think," he conceded. "But many of these appear to occur at times when there wasn't profound change in the Earth's flora and fauna, so the correlation of impact to environmental change and extinction is far from substantiated."</p>
        <p>But Dr. Alvarez noted the tremendous size of the Chicxulub crater and the fact that it was dug out of limestone. Vaporized limestone would have been particularly noxious because it would have released vast amounts of carbon dioxide, producing an immediate drop in temperatures followed by greenhouse warming. The knowledge of its geology, he said, would now help scientists do detailed analyses to better understand the end of the Cretaceous period.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
