<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviews/Film; Engaging in Conversation on the Normandy Coast</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAPRA, BERNT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MINDWALK (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D81639F93BA35757C0A964958260" item-length="627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviews/Film; Engaging in Conversation on the Normandy Coast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT CANBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANBY, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Bernt Capra's "Mindwalk," opening today at the Film Forum, an alienated scientist (Liv Ullmann), a losing candidate for the United States Presidency (Sam Waterston), and an American poet (John Heard) who lives in self-imposed exile in France meet by chance at Mont-St.-Michel and spend the day walking and talking.</p>
        <p>Though not exactly spontaneous and seldom witty, it is good serious talk, a sort of feature-length op-ed piece. The source material is "The Turning Point" by the director's brother, Fritjof Capra, a physicist and the author of the best seller "The Tao of Physics," which finds links between science and religious mysticism. (The Austrian-born Capra brothers are no relation to Frank Capra.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Bernt Capra's "Mindwalk," opening today at the Film Forum, an alienated scientist (Liv Ullmann), a losing candidate for the United States Presidency (Sam Waterston), and an American poet (John Heard) who lives in self-imposed exile in France meet by chance at Mont-St.-Michel and spend the day walking and talking.</p>
        <p>Though not exactly spontaneous and seldom witty, it is good serious talk, a sort of feature-length op-ed piece. The source material is "The Turning Point" by the director's brother, Fritjof Capra, a physicist and the author of the best seller "The Tao of Physics," which finds links between science and religious mysticism. (The Austrian-born Capra brothers are no relation to Frank Capra.)</p>
        <p>It is Fritjof Capra's point that the Earth can be saved only by a radical rethinking of priorities. Because the universe and everything within it function according to a single system of interdependencies, he believes, a holistic approach is needed to solve all problems, from famine, overpopulation and global warming to the tired businessman's heart attack.</p>
        <p>Mont-St.-Michel, a mile off the Normandy coast, is as apt a locale for the Capra brothers today as it was for Henry Adams in 1904. That was when Adams privately published his first edition of "Mont-St.-Michel and Chartres," a meditation upon the 13th century, when, as he saw it, the worship of the Virgin Mary briefly gave a transcendent unity and coherence to French life.</p>
        <p>The ancient Benedictine abbey, founded in the eighth century, is a spectacular setting, though "Mindwalk" is less interested in scenery than in delivering ideas as efficiently and conversationally as possible.  Miss Ullmann's scientist must do most of the talking while she leads the two men around the island, gently lecturing them on Descartes, Newton and the outmodedness of the mechanistic approach to science.</p>
        <p>"Well, let's take the population problem, for example," she says by way of one preamble, or "Take Brazil. As you know they are destroying the Amazon rain forest at the rate of one football field a second."</p>
        <p>A specialist in laser physics, she describes herself as being on "a semi-permanent sabbatical" from her post at an American university.  She lost interest, she tells them, when she found her work was being "fed to the U.S. Defense Department."</p>
        <p>She is intense, sincere and so very knowing that the politician and the poet haven't much to do except make little interjections, which allow her to catch her breath and the audience to digest her last speech. "Is that what's known as scientific thinking?" one man might say. Or more bluntly, "What does that mean?"</p>
        <p>In the course of the day, the poet has a chance to quote Pablo Neruda. The politician, who seems less introspective than empty, invites the scientist to join his staff.</p>
        <p>Miss Ullmann goes on dropping large thoughts. To make her point about the relative sizes of things, she says that if an orange were blown up to the size of the Earth, the atoms in it would be the size of cherries. "Wow," the poet says, "that's an image!"</p>
        <p>Though "Mindwalk" is better read than said, it will have done its job if it stirs people whose list of unopened books reaches from here to Philadelphia. Mindwalk  Directed by Bernt Capra; screenplay by Floyd Byars and Fritjof Capra, based on Mr. Capra's book "The Turning Point"; director of photography, Karl Kases; edited by Jean Claude Piroue; music by Philip Glass; produced by Adrianna A. J. Cohen; released by Triton Pictures. At the Film Forum, 209 West Houston St. Running time: 111 minutes. This film is rated PG. Sonia Hoffman . . . Liv Ullmann Jack Edwards . . . Sam Waterston Thomas Harriman . . . John Heard Kit Hoffman . . . Ione Skye Romain . . . Emmanuel Montes</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
