<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Issues -- The Environment; Clinton and Bush Show Contradictions in Balancing Jobs and Conservation</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUAYLE, DAN (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D9133FF930A25753C1A964958260" item-length="1627" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: Issues -- The Environment; Clinton and Bush Show Contradictions in Balancing Jobs and Conservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Both President Bush and Gov. Bill Clinton say promoting economic growth is just as important as protecting the environment. But the two candidates clearly differ on how the Government should be used to set priorities and promote these goals.</p>
        <p>Though the candidates have taken pains to prepare position papers and deliver speeches to make their differences apparent, both men have histories that are filled with contradiction on the issue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Both President Bush and Gov. Bill Clinton say promoting economic growth is just as important as protecting the environment. But the two candidates clearly differ on how the Government should be used to set priorities and promote these goals.</p>
        <p>Though the candidates have taken pains to prepare position papers and deliver speeches to make their differences apparent, both men have histories that are filled with contradiction on the issue.</p>
        <p>That is part of the reason that Mr. Bush and Mr. Clinton have given their running mates, Vice President Dan Quayle and Senator Al Gore of Tennessee, the bulk of the responsibility for talking about the environment and jobs. During the Vice-Presidential debate in Atlanta on Tuesday night, the environment is likely to be a principal focus.</p>
        <p>In his last two years in office, Mr. Bush has come down clearly on the side of saving jobs in the short term, and that has been his emphasis as he runs for re-election. With the encouragement of Mr. Quayle, who heads a Federal panel aimed at reducing Government regulations, Mr. Bush has spent most of the last 16 months trying to roll back environmental safeguards, some of which he promoted when he was running for office four years ago. Reversal on Wetlands</p>
        <p>He called for opening half the nation's wetlands to development, a clear reversal of a 1988 campaign promise, and proposed drilling for oil in the untouched Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska.</p>
        <p>He urged changes in the law to allow strip mining for coal in national forests, and he dulled the effectiveness of the 1990 Clean Air Act by delaying a host of new rules and changing others.</p>
        <p>Just three weeks ago, Mr. Bush's stance reached its height in a campaign stop in Colville, Wash. First, Mr. Bush promised to do everything in his power to remove legal restrictions on cutting the virgin forests of the Pacific Northwest. "This will not stand," he said, waving his fist and grimacing. "I mean it."  Conservation Law Attacked</p>
        <p>Then, Mr. Bush delivered the strongest attack a President has ever issued against the Endangered Species Act, calling the nation's toughest conservation law "a sword aimed at the jobs, families and communities of entire regions like the Northwest."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's Democratic challenger, Mr. Clinton, calls any effort to sacrifice the environment for jobs a "false choice." He has promised to make Government an active presence on environmental and energy issues. And with his choice of Mr. Gore, of Tennessee, a leading environmental authority in Congress who is the author of a best-selling book on global resource problems, he appears ready to act on that pledge.</p>
        <p>If he is elected, existing environmental rules will be strictly followed, Mr. Clinton has said. He said he supported raising mileage standards for automobiles 45 miles a gallon from 27.5 miles a gallon now.</p>
        <p>Agreeing with the economists who say modernized plants are less likely to pollute, Mr. Clinton has also proposed new tax incentives and other measures to encourage such modernization. Clinton Swayed by Gore</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Clinton cautiously endorsed the North American Free Trade Agreement, even though he said he was concerned that it endangered both his environmental and job creation goals. Mr. Bush's Administration negotiated the agreement in an effort to eliminate trade barriers between Mexico, Canada and the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's aides said he made the decision to endorse it conditionally, in part because of his running mate's argument that it could be used to help the environment and business in all three countries. Mr. Gore argues that "the biggest new market in the history of world business is the market for new products and processes that will foster economic growth without environmental destruction." Mexico recently announced, for instance, that it was spending $4 billion in the next year just for equipment to control air pollution.</p>
        <p>Between these competing views is the environmental program advanced by Ross Perot. Though his record is thin, and Mr. Perot has said almost nothing in public about the environment, his book that details his economic platform, "United We Stand; How We Can Take Back Our Country," includes a few proposals, although they are sketchy.  Little Record for Perot</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot calls for greater use of coal and nuclear power, coupled with conservation measures to lower America's dependency on foreign oil and avoid future oil wars in the Persian Gulf. As part of his economic plan, he urges an increase of 50 cents a gallon in gasoline taxes over five years, and this would have the effect of reducing oil consumption and air pollution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot has no clear record on environmental issues. But both Mr. Clinton and Mr. Bush do. And the records of both indicate that the public has reason to be suspicious.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's election-year attack on environmentalism is an almost complete about-face from the position he took in 1988. Next to his "no new taxes" pledge, some of the most familiar phrases from the 1988 campaign were Mr. Bush's promises to protect the environment. Mr. Bush attacked his 1988 opponent, Michael S. Dukakis, for allowing Boston Harbor to become the "dirtiest in America" and a "harbor of shame."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he wanted to be "the environmental President," and promised a new era in which the Government would exert its authority to clear the skies, clean the beaches and use the "White House effect" in international negotiations to battle the "greenhouse effect" of global warming caused by atmospheric pollutants.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Bush almost always refers to conservationists as "environmental extremists" whom he "will not allow to shut down the United States."</p>
        <p>In 1988, Mr. Bush promised a new no net-loss policy to preserve the nation's marshes, bottomlands and other wetlands. But in 1991, Mr. Bush proposed a new national rule that would open half the wetlands to development.</p>
        <p>In 1989, Mr. Bush broke a 13-year political deadlock in Congress and pushed through a new Clean Air Act, a law intended to control every important source of air pollution. But in 1992, Mr. Bush allowed Mr. Quayle and the Council on Competitiveness, the panel that he heads with a goal of reducing Federal regulation, to delay more than 50 rules and rewrite several others to limit the law's reach.</p>
        <p>In 1989, Mr. Bush told a group of conservationists that his Administration "would provide leadership in finding cooperative international solutions" to the world's environmental problems. But in 1992, Mr. Bush was the last of the world's leaders to announce that he would attend the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development in Rio de Janeiro, and once there gave a perfunctory speech and refused to sign a treaty to halt the decline of endangered species that had been endorsed by almost every other nation in attendance.  Recent White House Shift</p>
        <p>Environmental historians have said that no President has shifted his position one the environment so sharply. Polls in the Northwest, California, the upper Middle West and New England, regions where environmental issues are an important part of the public debate, indicate that the President's shift has not helped him gain an advantage over Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>But now the tough talk is being perceived in the White House as a political liability, and efforts are under way to soften Mr. Bush's positions. Late last month, James A. Baker 3d, the chief of staff, dropped a proposal championed by Mr. Quayle to allow manufacturers to dispose of hazardous chemical wastes in town dumps. Killing the proposal was a signal that Mr. Baker was seizing control of environmental policy from Mr. Quayle.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Clinton, he acknowledged in a speech on Earth Day in April that too often as Governor of Arkansas he had chosen job creation over environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>The most notorious corner of contamination in Arkansas is the region around Fayetteville where the state's enormous poultry and livestock industry is polluting the White River and its tributaries with fecal bacteria. During his terms in office 1978 to 1980, and 1982 to today, Mr. Clinton encouraged the development of the nation's eighth largest animal agriculture industry. But it took Mr. Clinton a decade to respond to the contamination of the White River, an oversight that has made the river's condition a prime target for attack by Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>In the Earth Day speech, and several others since, Mr. Clinton has said he has learned that such trade-offs are counterproductive because they bring greater environmental cleanup costs without producing any more jobs. He has promised that as President he would ban new offshore oil and gas drilling, support an international treaty to control emissions of carbon dioxide that add to global warming and convene a meeting to settle differences between environmentalists and loggers in the Pacific Northwest, though he says he would leave the Endangered Species Act unaltered.</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club has endorsed Mr. Clinton, largely because of his choice of Mr. Gore as his running mate. A Clinton Administration, the candidate promises, will be active in protecting the environment, though his own record is spotty.</p>
        <p>"I would implement many energy conservation measures, including raising corporate average fuel efficiency standards for vehicles, improving energy efficiency for buildings and expanding Federal and state technical assistance for reforestation programs," he told the League of Conservation Voters earlier this year. "Global warming poses a dire threat to human survival around the world. The potential harm to the world's food basket would be severely damaging to the United States and devastating to the developing world."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
