<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviews/Television; Geraldo Rivera as a Murder Victim on 'Perry Mason'</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL BROADCASTING CO (NBC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERRY MASON (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CASE OF THE RECKLESS ROMEO, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DC1E3AF936A35756C0A964958260" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviews/Television; Geraldo Rivera as a Murder Victim on 'Perry Mason'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The tired but durable "Perry Mason" formula hits on an unusually tantalizing gimmick this evening: Geraldo Rivera as murder victim. Before thousands weep or cheer, let it be noted quickly that Mr. Rivera is not really the victim. He is merely playing the title role in "The Case of the Reckless Romeo," tonight at 8 on NBC. But the character's resemblance to Mr. Rivera in several respects stretches coincidence very near to the breaking point.</p>
        <p>Ted, as he's called, is the host of "Revelations," a cable-television show specializing in tabloid sensationalism. "Watch yourself, because someone may be watching you," is Ted's warning to viewers. A familiar story: The show is sleaze, the ratings are climbing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The tired but durable "Perry Mason" formula hits on an unusually tantalizing gimmick this evening: Geraldo Rivera as murder victim. Before thousands weep or cheer, let it be noted quickly that Mr. Rivera is not really the victim. He is merely playing the title role in "The Case of the Reckless Romeo," tonight at 8 on NBC. But the character's resemblance to Mr. Rivera in several respects stretches coincidence very near to the breaking point.</p>
        <p>Ted, as he's called, is the host of "Revelations," a cable-television show specializing in tabloid sensationalism. "Watch yourself, because someone may be watching you," is Ted's warning to viewers. A familiar story: The show is sleaze, the ratings are climbing.</p>
        <p>But Ted doesn't just expose the pecadillos of others. Now he's publishing a book about himself, complete with detailed descriptions and photos of a string of former lovers. As it happens, Mr. Rivera himself published just such a book not too long ago, and subsequently conceded that it was probably a mistake.</p>
        <p>Most of Ted's kiss-and-tell victims are furious. "That S.O.B!" cries the producer, one of the betrayed. "Yes, but he's</p>
        <p>our</p>
        <p>S.O.B," counters the sponsor, who also happens to be Ted's current fiancee. An actress says her agent is always saying she should do something environmental. "Killing Ted," she decides, "would be right up there with saving the ozone layer." Offering a copy of the book to a female colleague, Ted is told: "Thanks, but I haven't finished reading 'Mein Kampf.' "</p>
        <p>Ted wonders why people don't have a sense of humor. Everyone else suggests he get a bodyguard. Sure enough, Ted is found with a knife through his heart, reportedly killed by a woman in a red dress. Each of the many suspects, of course, owns a red dress, providing the properly colored herrings. The case proceeds to the courtroom, where Mr. Mason, as embalmed in the authoritative voice of Raymond Burr, gets down to business as usual.</p>
        <p>But it's not quite the same without Mr. Rivera's unflaggingly cocky presence. He has been a natural before the camera from his very beginning on television, more than 20 years ago. He just has to be himself. As someone says of Ted's ability to insinuate himself, "Guess he was a very good actor." As for Mr. Rivera's motive in playing this reckless Romeo, you have a choice: Sense of humor, or no sense of shame. Perry Mason The Case of the Reckless Romeo  Written by Brian Clemens. Christian I. Nyby, director; Barry Steinberg and Billy Ray Smith, producers; Dean Hargrove, Fred Silverman and Joel Steiger, executive producers. A production of Dean Hargrove Productions and the Fred Silverman Company in association with Viacom Productions. Tonight at 8 on NBC. Perry Mason . . . Raymond Burr Della Street . . . Barbara Hale Ken Malansky . . . William R. Moses Ted Mayne . . . Geraldo Rivera Charley Adams . . . Tracy Nelson Brenda Kingsley . . . Priscilla Barnes Roxanne Shields . . . Amy Steel Laura Rand . . . Mary-Margaret Humes Nora Turner . . . Anjanette Comer Annie . . . Vonetta McGee</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
