<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ecology Fuels Energy Studies</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION (PRIMARY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DD1E31F936A35757C0A964958260" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ecology Fuels Energy Studies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Matthew L. Wald</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN THE 1950's, when oil was cheap, the United States was an exporter and families still outnumbered cars, energy was not part of the standard elementary school curriculum, unless civil defense drills -- putting a duffel coat over one's head and crouching under the desk while waiting for nuclear attack -- can be considered a lesson in high-energy physics. By 1980, though, the United States had weathered two oil shortages and children were sometimes drafted as energy wardens, telling parents to turn down the thermostat, turn off lights and drive slower.  What's School Role?</p>
        <p>Today, the threat of both nuclear war and oil shortages are fading into the past. What role is left for energy in the schools?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN THE 1950's, when oil was cheap, the United States was an exporter and families still outnumbered cars, energy was not part of the standard elementary school curriculum, unless civil defense drills -- putting a duffel coat over one's head and crouching under the desk while waiting for nuclear attack -- can be considered a lesson in high-energy physics. By 1980, though, the United States had weathered two oil shortages and children were sometimes drafted as energy wardens, telling parents to turn down the thermostat, turn off lights and drive slower.  What's School Role?</p>
        <p>Today, the threat of both nuclear war and oil shortages are fading into the past. What role is left for energy in the schools?</p>
        <p>A strong one, according to educators -- as a tool to save the environment.</p>
        <p>"We don't talk about an oil shortage, we talk about conservation and the environment," said Roy M. Seitsinger, principal of the Stony Lane School, an elementary school in North Kingstown, R.I. "We say, 'If you turn off this light, you'll save 14 barrels of oil and help save the environment.' " Children, Mr. Seitsinger added, will do almost anything to improve the environment.</p>
        <p>"Energy is not the hot issue itself," agreed Merrillee Harrigan, the program manager at the Alliance to Save Energy, a nonprofit Washington-based group. "But kids are very concerned about the environment, and they are receptive to the notion that if you save energy it helps the environment."</p>
        <p>To adults whose ideas about energy were formed on the gasoline lines of the 70's that may be a new notion. But the relationship between energy and environment is clear in Washington, where Congress is debating the National Energy Strategy that President Bush introduced during the Persian Gulf war. A large part of the oil savings envisioned by the program come from requirements of the Clean Air Act, which will substitute cleaner fuels.</p>
        <p>The National Energy Strategy also emphasizes the need for math and science education at all levels, to produce the engineers and scientists to solve energy problems, and to create informed voters.  No Global Scarcity</p>
        <p>Global fuel scarcity is not an issue; between the Arab oil embargo of 1973 and today reserves of oil are up 50 percent.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, fuel use is the major source of air pollution and carbon dioxide, the gas that some scientists fear will lead to a catastrophic warming trend -- reason, many educators argue, to make energy a school concern. That concern sometimes makes it out of the classroom and into the adult community.</p>
        <p>At the Stony Lane School, for example, students counted all the light bulbs and calculated how many hours a year they were in use, how much electricity they consumed and how much less electricity a newer-model bulb would use. Then, flip charts in hand, they briefed the local School Committee, the equivalent of a board of education. It was not only a lesson in energy, said Mr. Seitsinger, but in "public speaking, collecting data and organizing data in a cohesive way."</p>
        <p>It worked; the School Committee approved re-lamping the building.</p>
        <p>But the era is over when schools taught children to turn out the lights and nag their parents to do the same. "That's something that tends to be effective only in a crisis, and even then, people don't like it," said Ms. Harrigan of the Alliance to Save Energy.  Several Lessons</p>
        <p>Neither schools nor anyone else try much to have people change their energy behavior, unless "behavior" means choosing a refrigerator that may cost more initially but is energy-efficient. That requires a deeper understanding of mathematics than many adults, let alone children, bring to purchasing decisions. But teachers say that the subject can teach several lessons.</p>
        <p>For example, the New England Electric System, which serves parts of Massachusetts, New Hampshire and Rhode Island, published a book with the Conservation Law Foundation, a Boston-based nonprofit group, called "How Many Light Bulbs Does It Take to Change a People?" that is an exercise in arithmetic, mathematical reasoning and energy efficiency. It shows how to calculate whether a $20 compact fluorescent is less expensive in the long run than a $1 incandescent bulb (it is) and describes how to build a device to compare the brightness of the two.</p>
        <p>"Kids are fascinated by energy projects and fascinated by the environment," said Peggy Dufour, special assistant to the Secretary of Energy. "The nice thing is that that interest can be captured and used to show them the skills they'll need, instead of saying, 'You'll have to learn these fractions.' We're seeing a lot of that tie-in."</p>
        <p>It does not always work. In Cleveland, Natural Power, a nonprofit advocacy and education group dedicated to alternative energy sources, created an exercise to help children understand the value of solar hot-water heaters. The object was to calculate how big a collector would be needed if the student knew the volume of water to be delivered and the temperature of the water going in.</p>
        <p>"In most cases, we guessed accurately as to whether they could grasp concepts," said Irwin Friedman, an engineer and the organization's chairman. But "we overestimated the ability of the kids to do math."</p>
        <p>But the light bulb book also teaches that in life nothing is simple. It includes a skit for fifth-graders featuring characters like Ellie Electricity and King Coal to acquaint pupils with the sources of electricity, and the consequences of drawing on each source, from oil spills to the destruction of river habitats by hydroelectric power.</p>
        <p>The light bulb book and other energy education materials stress hands-on efforts. William R. Einsig, who helps develop curriculum at the West Shore School District in suburban Harrisburg, Pa., gives teachers chocolate chip cookies and toothpicks. He tells them to pretend the chips are coal, and after they have "mined" the chips, he asks them to repair the cookies, an impossibility. In teaching children about energy and the environment, he said, "The first step is awareness." Energy Sources</p>
        <p>TEACHING materials are available from several sources.</p>
        <p>* The United States Department of Energy has a Public Inquiry Office, 202-586-5575.</p>
        <p>* The department's Energy Information Administration also publishes a listing of organizations, industry associations and companies that provide energy materials. Write to the National Energy Information Center, United States Department of Energy, Washington, D.C. 20585.</p>
        <p>* The National Science Teachers Association publishes a free catalogue of books and educational products. Write to 1742 Connecticut Avenue N.W., Washington, D.C. 20009, or call 202-328-5800.</p>
        <p>* The American Solar Energy Society publishes "Science Projects in Renewable Energy and Energy Efficiency." Contact the National Energy Foundation, 5160 Wiley Post Way, Suite 200, Salt Lake City, Utah 84116, 801-539-1406.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
