<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Research Lags, Report Finds</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="515554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DD1F30F933A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Research Lags, Report Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Research conducted by the Environmental Protection Agency suffers from uneven quality, inadequate funds, poor direction and a lack of first-rate scientists and equipment, a report made public today says.</p>
        <p>The report, discussed at a hearing of the House Committee on Science, Space and Technology, said the environmental agency neither conducts environmental research as well as it could nor uses science effectively in considering and writing regulations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Research conducted by the Environmental Protection Agency suffers from uneven quality, inadequate funds, poor direction and a lack of first-rate scientists and equipment, a report made public today says.</p>
        <p>The report, discussed at a hearing of the House Committee on Science, Space and Technology, said the environmental agency neither conducts environmental research as well as it could nor uses science effectively in considering and writing regulations.</p>
        <p>Critics charge that many of the agency's policies are driven by response to a crisis rather than by research. William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the E.P.A., says that is not the way it should be.</p>
        <p>Concerned about the poor reputation of its science, Mr. Reilly appointed a special advisory committee of prominent scientists last year to assess the work of the E.P.A.'s Office of Research and Development and the agency's overall use of technical information. 'Uneven Quality' Found</p>
        <p>"The panel affirms that the E.P.A. needs its own strong science base to provide the background required for effective environmental protection programs," the committee said. "Currently, E.P.A. science is of uneven quality, and the agency's policies and regulations are frequently perceived as lacking a strong scientific foundation."</p>
        <p>The committee recommended that the agency take steps to improve matters, including bringing in promiment scientists and appointing a high-ranking science adviser for the agency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly, testifying at the hearing, praised the report and said he would begin immediately to carry out many of its suggestions. He promised to appoint science advisers at different levels in the agency, have himself regularly briefed on technical issues, and create and publish an annual research agenda that establishes priorities.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes our decisions are based on partial information, and we need to be clearer about our sources of data and the quality of the data," Mr. Reilly said in an interview. "The time has come when science should be what we do and what we are seen to do. We are not eco-cowboys and we don't want to be seen that way."</p>
        <p>Representative George E. Brown Jr., who is chairman of the Science, Space and Technology Committee, noted that the E.P.A. conducted little basic research on fundamental environmental processes and health effects. The agency has to do more than short-term applied research if it wants to reduce scientific uncertainties that hamper efforts to create thoughtful, cost-effective regulations, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, a California Democrat, praised Mr. Reilly's quick response to the science study and said he would try to get more money for environmental research. An analysis by the committee found that even though the environmental agency's research and development budget had been rising modestly in recent years, it still had not recovered from deep cuts that were made under the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>The research budget increased from $358.1 million in the fiscal year 1991 to $525.9 proposed for the fiscal year 1993. But the analysis found that, after adjusting for inflation, the budget was 3 percent less than it was in 1981.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bernard D. Goldstein of Rutgers University, a member of the four-member panel of scientists that studied the E.P.A.'s research, said the panel held three public meetings, interviewed 30 scientists and other experts on environmental issues and received additional comments from 25 others. Science Counseling Urged</p>
        <p>"There is a perception that the quality of science at the E.P.A. is uneven and that the agency's policies and guidelines lack a strong scientific foundation," Dr. Goldstein said at the hearing. The agency needs to recognize the importance of quality science, he said, and include scientific advice "early and often in its deliberations."</p>
        <p>When it considers regulations, Dr. Goldstein said, the environmental agency "always has someone from the general counsel's office to assure that what it is doing is in compliance with the law." He added, "We suggest the same role for science in these deliberations."</p>
        <p>Responding to the report's recommendations, Mr. Reilly said he wanted agency policies to be driven by rational priorities based on dealing with the greatest environmental risk, and not on the popular crises of the day.</p>
        <p>Science and research play a major role in determining both risks and priorities, he said, and have been improving at the agency in recent years. 'Pro-Science' Culture Sought</p>
        <p>Saying he wanted to "alter the culture at the agency to be more pro-science," Mr. Reilly said the E.P.A. would try to attract prominent enviromental scientists and engineers to the agency for permanent positions by establishing the equivalent of six endowed chairs at the agency, at $1 million for each.</p>
        <p>Other parts of the plan are these:</p>
        <p>*Reorganizing the staff into areas by issue, so that work can be conducted long in advance of crises. Some of the areas would include drinking water pollution, climate change, species loss and indoor air pollution.</p>
        <p>*Increasing the involvement of academic scientists with the agency by reducing contract research at E.P.A. offices and laboratories, and offering more competitive grants for university researchers.</p>
        <p>*Establishing a new standard for research done by the agency, making all of it of publishable quality and assuring taht all of it gets reviewed by a panel of peers, which Mr. Reilly said is often not the case now.</p>
        <p>*Creating a board of scientific counselors, made up of the best scientists in academia, government and industry, to advise the E.P.A.'s research division.</p>
        <p>*Starting programs to encourage young scientists to choose the E.P.A. as a career to supplement the agency's aging cadre of scientists, and seeking more money to update aging equipment at its laboratories.</p>
        <p>"I believe that the steps we are proposing to take will fundamentally alter the way in which scientific information is developed and used in the E.P.A.," Mr. Reilly said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
