<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Bringing Environmental Policy to Fore</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="576604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE TRANSITION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D7163BF936A25751C1A964958260" item-length="692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Bringing Environmental Policy to Fore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a month to go before the Clinton Administration takes office, Vice President-elect Al Gore has already had unusual influence on a broad range of appointments and is supervising the development of new policies on the environment, natural resources, technology and the economy, transition aides say.</p>
        <p>The most immediate example of Mr. Gore's influence with Mr. Clinton occurred last Friday when a former senior Senate aide was chosen by Mr. Clinton to be Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a month to go before the Clinton Administration takes office, Vice President-elect Al Gore has already had unusual influence on a broad range of appointments and is supervising the development of new policies on the environment, natural resources, technology and the economy, transition aides say.</p>
        <p>The most immediate example of Mr. Gore's influence with Mr. Clinton occurred last Friday when a former senior Senate aide was chosen by Mr. Clinton to be Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Another example will come Tuesday, the second day of the economic conference in Little Rock, Ark., when Mr. Gore is to lead a panel he organized on the connection between economic growth, environmental safeguards and new technology.</p>
        <p>But such visible signs of Mr. Gore's authority are viewed by transition aides as merely the prelude to a much larger vision that Mr. Gore and Mr. Clinton have for the Government: how to make environmental and economic goals equal in virtually every decision the new Administration makes. Counterweight to Quayle</p>
        <p>"A heavy majority of the American people understand that our future depends on maintaining a sustainable environment, on conserving our resources, on solving our problems and that in doing that we can create economic opportunity," Mr. Clinton said at a news conference on Friday.</p>
        <p>Indeed, scholars of the American Presidency say that Mr. Gore's influence will apparently exceed the considerable power wielded by Vice President Walter F. Mondale early in President Jimmy Carter's Administration.</p>
        <p>Some said the only comparable example is the commanding role that Vice President Dan Quayle has played on environmental and economic issues in the last two years of President Bush's Administration. Mr. Quayle and a group of aides, through his Council on Competitiveness, developed the White House program for stalling regulations deemed unfriendly to business and speeding those considered helpful.</p>
        <p>Aides to the Clinton transition said the process of gaining economic benefits from environmental safeguards begins by dismantling the barriers that have long existed between the agencies that regulate the environment, natural resources, research and economy. Traditional Bureau Battles</p>
        <p>For example, the head of the United States Forest Service historically battled the Environmental Protection Agency over decisions on barring defoliants. Nor was the Department of the Interior often in contact with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration on offshore drilling.</p>
        <p>Transition aides said the new Administration goal is to have concern for environmental protection permeate the entire range of public policy, an idea Mr. Gore has long advocated.</p>
        <p>In one indication of such goals, Mr. Clinton named his boyhood friend, Thomas F. McLarty 3d to be chief of staff. Mr. McLarty is a member of the Business Council for a Sustainable Energy Future, which has called for creating thousands of jobs and reducing environmental damage by sharply increasing the use of natural gas and renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore declined to be interviewed.  But on Sunday on the CBS News program "Face the Nation," Mr. Gore said he did not have any "line responsibilities for the environment." He added, though, that Mr. Clinton had "been very generous in asking for my advice on the decisions that he faces."</p>
        <p>Some evidence for Mr. Gore's clout has been highly public. On Friday, Carol M. Browner, the Secretary of Environmental Regulation in Florida and a former senior aide to Senator Gore, was chosen to be Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>A week ago, Mr. Gore announced he would block the opening of the nation's newest hazardous-waste incinerator in Ohio pending the outcome of a Congressional investigation into its safety and how its permits had been issued.</p>
        <p>Other examples of Mr. Gore's authority have been less public. Mr. Gore helped scuttle the nomination of Lawrence H. Summers, the chief economist at the World Bank, as chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers after environmentalists criticized his views on protecting natural resources.</p>
        <p>THE TRANSITION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
