<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; More Advisers, Less Council?</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="577117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COUNCIL OF ECONOMIC ADVISERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYSON, LAURA D'ANDREA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD103DF934A25751C1A964958260" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; More Advisers, Less Council?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JAWS dropped last week on word of the appointment of Laura D'Andrea Tyson to head Bill Clinton's Council of Economic Advisers. To win this most coveted job in the economics profession, Ms. Tyson had to beat out a half-dozen high-profile heavyweights, some of whom had been tirelessly lobbying the Clinton transition team. And until a few months ago, Ms. Tyson was known simply as a competent scholar who had thrown in her lot with the trendy minority of economists and political scientists intent on waging techno-warfare with Europe and Japan.</p>
        <p>Her surprised colleagues concede the 45-year-old University of California professor made her own luck -- that in her encounters with Mr. Clinton she was exceptionally persuasive and well organized. On reflection, that should not have been surprising: Ms. Tyson is a very successful teacher, as well as a polemicist with a flair for winning arguments without making enemies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JAWS dropped last week on word of the appointment of Laura D'Andrea Tyson to head Bill Clinton's Council of Economic Advisers. To win this most coveted job in the economics profession, Ms. Tyson had to beat out a half-dozen high-profile heavyweights, some of whom had been tirelessly lobbying the Clinton transition team. And until a few months ago, Ms. Tyson was known simply as a competent scholar who had thrown in her lot with the trendy minority of economists and political scientists intent on waging techno-warfare with Europe and Japan.</p>
        <p>Her surprised colleagues concede the 45-year-old University of California professor made her own luck -- that in her encounters with Mr. Clinton she was exceptionally persuasive and well organized. On reflection, that should not have been surprising: Ms. Tyson is a very successful teacher, as well as a polemicist with a flair for winning arguments without making enemies.</p>
        <p>But they still insist that the dark-horse appointment marks a radical departure, one suggesting that Bill Clinton already has well-formed views on economic policy. "This is proof that the President will be his own chief economic adviser," said Robert Z. Lawrence of Harvard's Kennedy School of Government.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tyson is certainly a card-carrying member of the economics establishment. She earned a Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, arguably America's most selective graduate school in economics. She wrote a doctoral thesis on Yugoslav-style socialism under Martin Weitzman, perhaps America's most distinguished theoretician of planned economies. She bagged a first job in Princeton's elite economics department. And when she left Princeton to move west with her family, she managed an appointment to the almost-as-prestigious Berkeley faculty.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tyson's scholarship has not set the academy afire. But, then, much of it concerned Eastern European economies before the fall of Communism -- a subject that generated little interest in the West. And in any case, academic research is not necessarily the best proving ground for policy makers. Walter Heller, President John F. Kennedy's chief economist, was not a particularly distinguished scholar. But he certainly knew enough economics to pioneer the use of fiscal fine-tuning in an era when Keynesianism was often equated with Bolshevism.</p>
        <p>What, then, is the beef with the Tyson appointment? One objection is that she aced out some of the most innovative and seasoned policy economists around -- most notably, Lawrence H. Summers, the chief economist for the World Bank.</p>
        <p>Another is that she is closely identified with Silicon Valley, the high-technology producers who will be lobbying hard for subsidies and for government-negotiated shares of world markets. "You've never had a situation where the Council of Economics Advisers was captured by an interest group," said Gary Saxonhouse of the University of Michigan. And while others doubt that Ms. Tyson will be anybody's tool, many do worry that her lack of ideological commitment to free trade will open the gates to protectionists.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, the Council of Economic Advisers has served as a counterweight to the Commerce Department and Congress, which generally represent domestic producers' interests at the expense of consumers'. But with Ms. Tyson in charge, "there's a risk a voice will be absent at the table," said William Cline of the Institute for International Economics.</p>
        <p>A broader concern is that the role of the Council of Economic Advisers is being downgraded, and with it the role of economic analysis in White House policy making. No one -- perhaps not even Mr. Clinton -- knows how the Council of Economic Advisers and its staff will divide responsibilities with the National Economic Council, newly created by the President-elect. What is known, though, is that the new body will be headed by an investment banker, Robert E. Rubin, who has close ties to Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Most striking, perhaps, is that the President-elect has not chosen a single economist with broad knowledge of policy issues to join his inner circle. Alice M. Rivlin, the new deputy budget director who was recruited from the Brookings Institution, might be considered the exception.</p>
        <p>But her days -- and probably her nights -- will be consumed with the technical aspects of managing a trillion-dollar-plus budget. And in any case, Ms. Rivlin is not known to have the sharp elbows needed to push her responsibilities beyond the formal job description.</p>
        <p>A plausible explanation is that Mr. Clinton already has an economic policy and simply wants a staff to fiddle with the nuts and bolts. His remarkable performance at this week's economic teach-in in Little Rock certainly suggests that he has a better command of the subject than any previous President.</p>
        <p>But the line between justified self-confidence and hubris is a thin one. With thorny issues ranging from fiscal policy to defense conversion to global warming facing the President-elect, he may yet regret his decision to pass by the wisest economic heads of his generation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
