<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Where Have New York's Fans Gone?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DC1F3EF93BA15756C0A964958260" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Where Have New York's Fans Gone?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOUND my longies and went to the ball park the other day. No traffic backing onto the highway. No lines at the parking lot. The attendants all asked, "How are you today, sir?" They seemed lonely. Inside Shea Stadium, a cold, damp wind reminded me of how Richard Todd's passes often fluttered on dank December afternoons. The Jet fans, such as they were, huddled together for warmth.</p>
        <p>It is all well and good to lay blame for the bad weather on Saddam Hussein for setting the oil wells on fire in Kuwait, on the Brazilians for burning their forests, on modern technology for producing acid rain. But is weather the main culprit for the Mets' attendance being down from last year by an average of 8,921 and the Yankees' attendance being down by 1,142?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOUND my longies and went to the ball park the other day. No traffic backing onto the highway. No lines at the parking lot. The attendants all asked, "How are you today, sir?" They seemed lonely. Inside Shea Stadium, a cold, damp wind reminded me of how Richard Todd's passes often fluttered on dank December afternoons. The Jet fans, such as they were, huddled together for warmth.</p>
        <p>It is all well and good to lay blame for the bad weather on Saddam Hussein for setting the oil wells on fire in Kuwait, on the Brazilians for burning their forests, on modern technology for producing acid rain. But is weather the main culprit for the Mets' attendance being down from last year by an average of 8,921 and the Yankees' attendance being down by 1,142?</p>
        <p>Around the country, major league attendance is up by 0.7 percent, mainly because of the new stadium in Baltimore and the enthusiasm in Atlanta -- "the tyranny of statistics," said Commissioner Fay Vincent, noting that attendance for 15 of 26 teams is down, and that tickets unsold in April and May can never be recovered.</p>
        <p>The fans will cite the poor national economy, and many will say they are turned off by high salaries and rising ticket prices, but I'm not sure they are making any overt statement by their absence. In the meantime, is something unattractive happening with New York baseball?</p>
        <p>"I think it's a whole group of things," said Al Harazin, the general manager of the Mets, observing the turnstile average drop from 30,652 a year ago to 21,731 going into last night.</p>
        <p>"First, it's the general economy of the New York area," Harazin said. "Normally, when you bring in superstars like Bobby Bonilla, Bret Saberhagen and Eddie Murray, you think ticket sales will jump. But despite all that, our season sales were off a little."</p>
        <p>Harazin said that longtime customers were "consolidating" their plans from eight tickets to four, or dropping out because of financial problems. Don't cry for the Mets just yet. Harazin said the average tickets sold in the glory years was 3.3-3.5 million, and he fully expects to sell 3 million this year.</p>
        <p>National League policy is to announce only the fans in attendance. From a Mets record of 3,047,724 in 1988, attendance dropped to 2,284,484 last year. Since the Mets make approximately $3 per person on concessions, they do prefer the paying fans to actually attend the games.</p>
        <p>Why haven't the fans been coming out this year? Harazin said: "This has been the lousiest spring I remember. We haven't had one warm night yet, although we had a few warm days. Plus, our games are on television, and the Knicks and Rangers advanced and it was easy for the fans to say: 'Hey, it's a crummy night. Let's stay home and watch the Knicks.' "</p>
        <p>Harazin is convinced the fans are not staging any kind of protest over prices, which now reach $15 for a box seat and $12 for most decent seats. Some other force is at work in Flushing, and it may be as simple as a generation-long period of mourning. "It may be that in the mid-80's we had a unique set of personalities," Harazin said. "We had somebody like Keith Hernandez. We had a young Doc Gooden. We had Strawberry, Carter, Mookie Wilson, Lenny Dykstra. As good as we might be, we may not be entitled to that kind of team again."</p>
        <p>The same may be true in the Bronx, where the monuments behind the outfield fence and the retired numbers in the scorecard produce a maudlin sense of nostalgia. The Yankees' attendance dropped to 1,863,731 last year, the lowest since 1984, and their dip is more moderate than the Mets' because American League policy is to announce actual tickets sold, and because the Yankees had less far to fall.</p>
        <p>Some people believe fans shy away from the south Bronx, but Vincent said that "is more of a perception problem than a reality problem."</p>
        <p>"Yankee Stadium," he added, "is still a magical atmosphere, and the Yankees do a pretty good job there."</p>
        <p>My own guess is that the fans have not been drawn back by the discreet charms of Andy Stankiewicz, Melido Perez and Buck Showalter.</p>
        <p>Attendance is one thing, but the real economic crunch is going to come after next season when the networks start lopping off zeros from the current $1.46 billion, four-year contract with CBS and ESPN, and the owners realize how foolish they were with long-term player contracts. As somebody lucky enough to have a good job, I would not minimize the economic problems in the nation, but there is money kicking around for witless third-sequel $7 movies, expensive sneakers, designer haircuts, nail salons. My own guess is that if the Mets and Yankees were fashionable, the fans might be wearing long johns or they might be wearing short shorts, but they would be surging to the ball parks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
