<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Soviet Central Asia's Politics Aren't Simple; Siberian Timber Rush</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="510140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORESTS AND FORESTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SIBERIA (RUSSIA)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia/Siberia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8143DF934A15751C0A964958260" item-length="598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Soviet Central Asia's Politics Aren't Simple; Siberian Timber Rush</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Experts Say Logging of Vast Siberian Forest Could Foster Warming" (Science Times, Jan. 28) quotes Roger Sedjo, an expert in world forests, as saying that Siberian logging operations would be among the costliest in the world. Because wages in Russia are extremely low compared with United States standards -- $100 month is a substantial salary -- the costs Dr. Sedjo speaks of are presumably from transportation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>"Experts Say Logging of Vast Siberian Forest Could Foster Warming" (Science Times, Jan. 28) quotes Roger Sedjo, an expert in world forests, as saying that Siberian logging operations would be among the costliest in the world. Because wages in Russia are extremely low compared with United States standards -- $100 month is a substantial salary -- the costs Dr. Sedjo speaks of are presumably from transportation.</p>
        <p>Six months ago I would have agreed that transportation costs would hinder development of this resource. However, the dizzying pace of political and economic change in the former Soviet Union have accelerated the threat to the forests.</p>
        <p>Siberians are now desperate for cash. They do not have a meaningful level of agriculture, and must trade natural resources for food. But the devolution of control over resources has resulted in chaos.</p>
        <p>Forests are being sold in timber commodities exchanges in Irkutsk and Ulan-Ude; they are being sold by the Russian Forest Ministry; they are being sold by cooperatives and local authorities. Timber at the harvest level is going for less than one-twentieth its price on the world market. Our environmentalist colleagues in Siberia believe, with such bargains, foreign timber companies will put in their own roads to get the timber.</p>
        <p>Terms are being accepted now that a year ago would have been unthinkable. For example, a joint venture that Louisiana Pacific tried to forge in 1990 was never completed, because the regional forest ministry believed that the terms were too lopsided. A virtually identical contract is being pursued by Aurima-Woods, and the Prime Minister in Buriatia is leaning toward acceptance.</p>
        <p>The threat of large-scale cutting is no longer remote. Despite the insistence by Scott Marshall, Weyerhaeuser Corporation spokesman, that "We're not doing anything yet" in Siberia, another Weyerhaeuser representative, Harthon Bill, has informed me and Armin Rosencranz, my colleague, that the company hopes to be cutting by midyear.</p>
        <p>Weyerhaeuser's efforts have been confirmed by our colleagues in Khabarovsk, who have observed a public relations campaign by the company to convince locals that it is a "green" company.</p>
        <p>The threat that Siberian deforestation presents to global carbon warming is not so straightforward as deforestation of tropical rain forests. There is a tremendous difference between the rate of carbon release when a forest is burned and when the timber is converted to pulp and lumber. But two points need to be made. All cut timber eventually releases its carbon. More important, bad harvesting techniques often make free regeneration impossible.</p>
        <p>While Dr. Sedjo maintains that unoccupied timberlands regenerate, Buriatia's forest minister has said that 50 percent of the Siberian permafrost forest becomes swampland in the wake of a large-scale clear cutting. Replanting efforts on lands that do not become swamp are almost completely ineffective. And in non-permafrost areas in Buriatia replanting in the wake of large-scale clear cuts is only 10 percent to 15 percent successful because of low rainfall and thin, sandy soils.</p>
        <p>If destructive harvesting practices prevent effective regeneration, we won't see a net reduction of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Comprehensive land-use strategies have to be developed, and cutting practices must be carefully chosen so as to guarantee the long-term health of both the forests and economies of Siberia. ANTONY SCOTT  Director of Research, Pacific Energy and Resources Center Sausalito, Calif., Feb. 17, 1992</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
