<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Gains Seen in Environmental Talks, but Big Divisions Remain</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D7113AF93AA15750C0A964958260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Gains Seen in Environmental Talks, but Big Divisions Remain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, March 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Delegates from the 160 countries planning to attend the Rio de Janeiro environmental conference in June are edging toward agreement on a sweeping plan for making economic progress ecologically sustainable, but remain deeply divided over how to pay for a global cleanup.</p>
        <p>As a five-week preparatory meeting for the Rio conference enters its final week here on Monday, rich and poor countries disagree not only over how to pay for higher environmental standards but who should accept moral responsibility for problems like global warming and pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Delegates from the 160 countries planning to attend the Rio de Janeiro environmental conference in June are edging toward agreement on a sweeping plan for making economic progress ecologically sustainable, but remain deeply divided over how to pay for a global cleanup.</p>
        <p>As a five-week preparatory meeting for the Rio conference enters its final week here on Monday, rich and poor countries disagree not only over how to pay for higher environmental standards but who should accept moral responsibility for problems like global warming and pollution.</p>
        <p>As the talks on the economic plan continued, the Bush Administration made a small concession to the developing world last week on aid. But the United States remains isolated over the single most important agreement that leaders attending the Rio conference hope to announce: a binding international convention to stabilize the global climate by freezing production of gases that warm the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>This convention is being negotiated outside the preparatory meeting, and the next round of talks is to be held in Paris next month. Last week President Bush, who still has not agreed to to attend the meeting in Rio de Janeiro, called again for an agreement without gas emission targets that could force the United States to cut gasoline consumption. Statement of Principles</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the European Community's environmental commissioner, Carlo Ripa di Meana, denounced the American stand, calling it "an attack on the very heart of the Rio conference." He accused the Bush Administration of staking out a position to win political support from industry.</p>
        <p>But delegates say they are within sight of agreement on an 800-page set of guidelines aimed at allowing economic growth without long-term destruction to the environment.</p>
        <p>The economic document, known as Agenda 21, sets nonbinding principles for promoting development while covering issues from toxic waste disposal to the protection of nature.</p>
        <p>"We are close to agreement on a detailed package for international cooperation in the field of environment and development through Agenda 21," the spokesman for the conference, Jean-Claude Faby, said on Thursday. A senior American official agreed on Friday, saying the United States expects agreement on most of Agenda 21 by the end of next week and full accord at the Rio meeting.</p>
        <p>But on the core issue of how the developing world is to pay for these higher environmental standards, North and South remain far apart.</p>
        <p>Putting Agenda 21 into effect will cost developing countries $125 billion a year, or $70 billion more than the $55 billion they now receive in aid.</p>
        <p>Most of the extra money could be found if industrialized countries met the target they have set of devoting 0.7 percent of economic output to aid, which would provide an additional $50 billion a year.</p>
        <p>But it appears unlikely that the industrialized countries will achieve that goal. European delegates predict that the North will have a maximum of $3 billion to $5 billion to offer in new aid at the Rio summit meeting.</p>
        <p>The developing south wants this "new and additional" aid paid into a new Green Fund that it would control and is seeking free access to environmentally safe technology. Industrialized countries insist that all new cash be funneled through existing aid institutions, where they exercise more control than the recipients. 'Earth Charter' in Peril</p>
        <p>Hopes that rich and poor countries could draw up an "Earth Charter" setting out the broad environmental principals underlying Agenda 21 are meanwhile on the point of collapse.</p>
        <p>Southern countries still insist on a document that would attribute the world's environmental difficulties to the North's pursuit of self-interest and would call on industrialized countries to reduce consumption.</p>
        <p>Since this approach is unacceptable to the north, some delegates are now suggesting abandoning or at least postponing the Earth Charter negotiations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
