<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Halon Ban Nears, Researchers Seek a New Miracle Firefighter</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="576737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HALONS (CHEMICAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF STANDARDS AND TECHNOLOGY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GROSSHANDLER, WILLIAM (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1431F936A25751C1A964958260" item-length="1118" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Halon Ban Nears, Researchers Seek a New Miracle Firefighter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A RECENT agreement by 87 countries to halt the manufacture of halon fire extinguishers one year from now will eventually eliminate a potent threat to the earth's protective ozone layer. But experts believe that the ban will make some fires harder to put out and could cost lives.</p>
        <p>Halons are up to 10 times more effective in putting out fires than other chemicals, and chemists doubt that halons can ever be replaced by equally effective extinguishers. Halons, unlike other fire extinguishers, not only extinguish fires swiftly but are chemically inert, nontoxic, and harmless to delicate equipment, including computer circuits. No other extinguishers combine all these features.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A RECENT agreement by 87 countries to halt the manufacture of halon fire extinguishers one year from now will eventually eliminate a potent threat to the earth's protective ozone layer. But experts believe that the ban will make some fires harder to put out and could cost lives.</p>
        <p>Halons are up to 10 times more effective in putting out fires than other chemicals, and chemists doubt that halons can ever be replaced by equally effective extinguishers. Halons, unlike other fire extinguishers, not only extinguish fires swiftly but are chemically inert, nontoxic, and harmless to delicate equipment, including computer circuits. No other extinguishers combine all these features.</p>
        <p>Like the chlorofluorocarbon (CFC) chemicals widely used as refrigerants, insulators and solvents, the halon chemicals used as fire extinguishers are so resistant to decomposition that once released, they can remain in the atmosphere for many years without breaking down. Halon molecules therefore have ample time to drift into the upper atmosphere, where intense ultraviolet radiation from the sun breaks them apart into molecular fragments that interact with ozone and destroy it.</p>
        <p>Ozone, a molecule consisting of three oxygen atoms, is poisonous to animals and human beings, but in the stratosphere it strongly blocks ultraviolet radiation that would otherwise reach the ground, causing cataracts and skin cancer, and damaging crops and habitats.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the ozone "layer" has been drastically depleted or punctured, and most scientists believe the culprits are man-made CFC's and halons. Damage to Ozone Layer</p>
        <p>In 1987 an international agreement known as the Montreal Protocol set a timetable for phasing out the production and use of CFC's and a few other ozone-destroying chemicals. The manufacture of halons is also to be ended, although their use can continue until supplies are exhausted. But because the destruction of the ozone layer has proved to be faster and more severe than originally believed, the schedule has been advanced several times since 1987, most recently on Nov. 25 in Copenhagen. The ban on CFC's in industrialized countries is now to take effect in 1996 instead of 2000, and the manufacture of halons is to cease on Jan. 1, 1994. (Developing nations have been given a 10-year grace period to phase out CFC's and halons.)</p>
        <p>At the Gaithersburg, Md., laboratories of the National Institute of Standards and Technology, scientists and firefighting experts are screening 12 chemicals on behalf of the United States Air Force in hopes of identifying one with at least some of the desirable properties of Halon-1301.</p>
        <p>Halon-1301, a molecule in which a single carbon atom is linked to three fluorine atoms and one bromine atom, is the most widely used of the halon fire extinguishers. It is nontoxic and extremely effective and fast. Used in Army tanks, in which engine and munition fires can spread like lightning, halon fire extinguishers operate automatically when sensors detect flame. A blast of halon gas can snuff out a raging gasoline fire in thousandths of a second. Since halons quickly disperse, leaving no corrosive residues, they are also used in computer rooms and other places where delicate machinery would be damaged by dry-chemical or foam fire extinguishers.</p>
        <p>Experts do not entirely understand why halons are so effective.</p>
        <p>Dr. William Grosshandler, director of the standards institute's Building and Fire Research Laboratory, said that halons are such good extinguishers that there has been little need to investigate their chemical properties since they came into use in the 1960's. Now that halons are to be banned, however, scientists are rushing to gain insights into their chemical properties, with a view to mimicking them in substitutes.</p>
        <p>"The theory is that the bromine in Halon-1301 combines with the hydrogen released in fires by burning oil, gasoline, wood, paper or any other hydrocarbon," Dr. Grosshandler said. "By removing the free hydrogen liberated in a hydrocarbon fire, hydrogen is no longer available to combine with oxygen in the air. The burning of hydrogen with oxygen is one of the main producers of heat in a hydrocarbon fire, and when this is stopped, the reaction is cooled, helping to put out the fire."</p>
        <p>All the possible substitutes for halons have disadvantages, Dr. Grosshandler said. One candidate, perfluorobutane, consists of 4 carbon atoms linked to 10 fluorine atoms, and is quite effective as an extinguisher. But although it is not expected to harm the ozone layer, perfluorobutane is a strong "greenhouse" gas; its presence in the atmosphere would trap the heat of sunlight and could contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>The prohibition against manufacturing halons will not immediately block their use. The volume of halons actually used to put out fires is small, and the halons already mixed into the upper atmosphere were released mostly by tests conducted by military forces. The United States Department of Defense, one of the main users of halons in the past, has virtually halted all firefighting tests and training exercises that release halons into the atmosphere, however, thereby reducing global halon releases to a small fraction of their previous rate.</p>
        <p>"This has helped in two ways," said Thomas Cortina, executive director of the Halon Alternatives Research Corporation, a Washington-based information network of halon users, fire departments, chemical manufacturers and government agencies. "First, it sharply reduces the rate at which halons escape into the atmosphere. Second, it conserves halon reserves, so that even though halons are no longer to be manufactured, some will be available for many years for the special uses in which they are deemed to be indispensable."</p>
        <p>Another common halon, Halon-1211, is packaged in hand-held fire extinguishers of the kind used on airport flight lines, and is stored aboard aircraft for putting out engine fires. Known as a "streaming" extinguisher, it is a liquid rather than a gas.</p>
        <p>"In the case of jet engine fire extinguishers used in flight," Dr. Grosshandler said, "we don't have to worry about toxicity in a halon substitute, because human beings would never be exposed. But any substitutes developed for Halon-1301, which is used in confined, inhabited spaces like computer centers, must be nontoxic, and that requirement greatly complicates the problem.</p>
        <p>"I foresee a need for several substitutes for each halon -- perhaps many substitutes, each one designed to meet some special fire-extinguishing requirement. None will be as effective or versatile as the halons, but we simply have to learn to live without halons, for the sake of the global environment."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
