<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cades Cove Journal; No Final Tears Shed for Paradise Lost</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="552413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT SMOKY MOUNTAINS NATIONAL PARK</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PIGEON FORGE (TENN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">OZARK MOUNTAINS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">APPALACHIAN MOUNTAINS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CADES COVE (TENN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">APPLEBOME, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAUGHRON, RUTH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAUGHRON, KERMIT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Great Smoky Mountains National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D91E31F937A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cades Cove Journal; No Final Tears Shed for Paradise Lost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER APPLEBOME,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">APPLEBOME, PETER</byline>
      <dateline>CADES COVE, Tenn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The distance seems to be measured in centuries, not miles, from this breathtaking American Eden, population 2, to the menagerie of Elvis museums, water slides and bumper car emporiums just over the mountains in Pigeon Forge.</p>
        <p>But, then again, who knows?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The distance seems to be measured in centuries, not miles, from this breathtaking American Eden, population 2, to the menagerie of Elvis museums, water slides and bumper car emporiums just over the mountains in Pigeon Forge.</p>
        <p>But, then again, who knows?</p>
        <p>A visit to the last two residents of what was once an idyllic mountain hamlet and is now part of the Great Smoky Mountains National Park can be a bittersweet reminder that the line between God's Country and Man's Revenge can be more elusive than it seems.</p>
        <p>You can buy prints of "Echoes of Cades Cove" by the mountain artist Lee Roberson, but the last authentic echoes of Cades Cove are Kermit and Ruth Caughron. The two are the last residents of this shimmering valley of hardwood forest, wild turkeys and black bears that became part of the national park in 1934.</p>
        <p>Nearly all the 120 families living there at the time took an offer of money and nearby farmland and moved away to more virgin soil and less isolated surroundings. But a handful stayed on, raising cattle and living in their homes under a lease agreement with the Government meant to expire when they do. For more than two decades the Caughrons have been the last ones left, living in what used to be the town's schoolhouse, without electricity or telephone service.</p>
        <p>The Caughrons have done well, dabbling in real estate and tending their beehives while their two sons have taken over their Cades Cove cattle-grazing operation, which helps keep the forest from swallowing up the open spaces that provide the park with its breathtaking vistas.</p>
        <p>The vistas are a lot less spectacular in Pigeon Forge, 25 miles away, a place far more typical of the tourism boom that is transforming much of the Appalchians and Ozarks from North Carolina to Arkansas.</p>
        <p>Incorporated 31 years ago, Pigeon Forge began to take off about the time of the 1982 World's Fair in Knoxville. Now it is a place where the mountain views give way to a madcap world of Dolly Parton's Dollywood amusement park and the Elvis Museum and where shoppers flock to 200 factory outlet stores.  There are now 700 businesses in all, and their annual receipts have increased to $379 million from $114 million in 1985. The permanent population now exceeds 3,000.</p>
        <p>Some longtime area residents, like Mr. Caughron's cousin, A. Randolph Shields, a local historian who grew up in Cades Cove, view the six-lane hubub of Pigeon Forge with dismay, but Mr. Caughron is not among them.</p>
        <p>"If you were the one making the money off of it, you'd probably think it's fine," he said.</p>
        <p>In fact, his only bad memory of Pigeon Forge has to do with problems far from the Smokys.</p>
        <p>"I was at Dollywood on the 17th of October 1987, when the stock market fell 500 points," he said. "I couldn't enjoy anything. I just wanted to go to Paine Webber in Maryville and see how my stocks were doing."</p>
        <p>Mr. Shields, who at 79 years of age is one year younger than his cousin, says plans to develop Cades Cove began as early as 1910, when a timber baron named Morton Butler started buying up land hoping to build dams, flood much of the Cove and develop it as lake-front property. Mr. Shields figures the park has saved Cades Cove from becoming much like Pigeon Forge.</p>
        <p>Though no one could ever confuse the two places, Cades Cove and Pigeon Forge have some common problems. With the Smoky Mountain Park the most-visited national park -- it had 8.6 million tourists last year -- the traffic through the loop road around Cades Cove can match the bumper-to-bumper traffic in Pigeon Forge. It takes from two to three hours for campers and vans to cover the 11-mile route.</p>
        <p>"If a groundhog is in the middle of the road, they have to stop and gawk at it," Mr. Caughron grouses.</p>
        <p>And, despite its pristine appearance, the park is being ravaged by pollution, ranging from acid rain to ozone that has reduced visibility by 30 percent over the last 30 years, damaged trees and plants and imperiled many species at the highest elevations of the park.</p>
        <p>The park is not Pigeon Forge, but maybe it's not quite Cades Cove either. But then the unsentimental last residents of a place that's often cited as one of the most spectacular spots east of the Rockies seem to think that's just as well.</p>
        <p>"Oh, you have people saying how much they'd like to live this way, but they might do fine for a week," Mrs. Caughron said. "If you had all the modern conveniences here, you could tolerate it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
