<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Faces Pressure To Allow Use of Gasohol</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHANOL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOBBYING AND LOBBYISTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRUM, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINER, SCOTT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D9153AF936A15756C0A964958260" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Faces Pressure To Allow Use of Gasohol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES STRUM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STRUM, CHARLES</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, May 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prodded by the grain-alcohol lobby, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency is considering whether to force New Jersey to permit the sale of an ethanol fuel mixture commonly called gasohol.</p>
        <p>While the lobbyists say ethanol can reduce emissions of carbon monoxide from motor vehicles, New Jersey says it can increase other pollutants, including ground-level ozone, or smog. And that's just about the last thing New Jersey wants to do. The whole state is out of compliance with Federal standards for ozone, and 18 of the state's 21 counties have severe problems. Only Los Angeles is worse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prodded by the grain-alcohol lobby, the Federal Environmental Protection Agency is considering whether to force New Jersey to permit the sale of an ethanol fuel mixture commonly called gasohol.</p>
        <p>While the lobbyists say ethanol can reduce emissions of carbon monoxide from motor vehicles, New Jersey says it can increase other pollutants, including ground-level ozone, or smog. And that's just about the last thing New Jersey wants to do. The whole state is out of compliance with Federal standards for ozone, and 18 of the state's 21 counties have severe problems. Only Los Angeles is worse.</p>
        <p>"The economic interests of the ethanol industry should not take precedence over the health and environmental interests of New Jersey citizens," said the state's environmental commissioner, Scott A. Weiner.</p>
        <p>He said he was particularly concerned that the introduction of ethanol could negate the effects of a state program to promote car pooling. This program, which affects businesses with 100 or more employees, is among the steps mandated by the Environmental Protection Agency to help New Jersey reduce its ozone levels 42 percent by the year 2005 to comply with the Clean Air Act. 'Promote Its Own Interests'</p>
        <p>"The ethanol industry has sought to promote its own interests by keeping steady pressure on the E.P.A.," Mr. Weiner said. "Now they seek to undermine clean air" by rule making, he added.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, interest in gasohol has grown with national concerns about air pollution from oil and other fossil fuels. Gasohol's proponents say the ethanol-gasoline mixture would help reduce dependence on foreign oil because ethanol is made from a renewable source: corn. Political leaders like Senator Bob Dole, Republican of Kansas, have thrown their weight behind the farmers, lobbying for an industry that accounts for about 5 percent of the 115 billion gallons of motor fuel sold annually.</p>
        <p>Ethanol in gasoline produces more complete combustion and thereby reduces noxious emissions. But because ethanol is so volatile, it can increase vapors, particularly nitrogen oxide, emitted from gas tanks or from under car hoods. These unburned hydrocarbons react with sunlight, particularly in the summer, to create ozone, a major source of respiratory problems.</p>
        <p>Ethanol may be used in the winter under New Jersey's air standards, because the sun's rays are not as strong and ozone formation is not as serious a problem, but it is barred in summer. As a result, the ethanol industry says it cannot make a dent in New Jersey or the rest of the Northeast because petroleum companies, many with large refineries or storage plants here, cannot accommodate seasonal sales of gasohol. Lobby Seeks U.S. Pressure</p>
        <p>"When you talk to companies like Amerada Hess or Getty or Sun you find these companies will tell you, 'We have to plan our supply storage, terminaling and contracts on an annual basis, not four months in, four months out,' " said Eric Vaughn, president of the Renewable Fuels Association in Washington, the main industry lobby for ethanol.</p>
        <p>At a hearing in Manhattan on May 5, the fuels association asked the E.P.A. to require New Jersey to change its summer standards for gasohol evaporation. A few years ago the E.P.A. said it would permit such changes largely as an accommodation to the ethanol industry, said Richard D. Wilson, director of the agency's Office of Mobile Sources, which conducted the hearing. "We were stuck with either giving them a break or putting them out of business," Mr. Wilson said.</p>
        <p>He said he expected the E.P.A. to rule by midsummer on whether to force New Jersey to grant a waiver for ethanol.</p>
        <p>New Jersey's allowable vapor pressure is 9 pounds per square inch; the grain-alcohol lobby wants a waiver to 10, the Federal standard.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
