<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Few Tears for a Blocked Plastics Ban</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="511886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LANDFILL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAPER AND PULP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTAINERS AND PACKAGING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SUFFOLK COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARBANEL, JOSH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Containers and Packaging</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DB1331F936A35750C0A964958260" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Few Tears for a Blocked Plastics Ban</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSH BARBANEL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARBANEL, JOSH</byline>
      <dateline>MINEOLA, L.I., March 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the Suffolk County Legislature voted this week to block most of a landmark law banning a host of plastic products, from supermarket shopping bags to foam takeout cups, few tears were shed by environmentalists.</p>
        <p>In 1988, when the law, the first of its kind in the nation, was passed, it had been a rallying point for environmentalists in something of a holy war against an eternal and evil substance called plastic, piling up in landfills across the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the Suffolk County Legislature voted this week to block most of a landmark law banning a host of plastic products, from supermarket shopping bags to foam takeout cups, few tears were shed by environmentalists.</p>
        <p>In 1988, when the law, the first of its kind in the nation, was passed, it had been a rallying point for environmentalists in something of a holy war against an eternal and evil substance called plastic, piling up in landfills across the country.</p>
        <p>But four years later, after the law was held up by litigation filed by the plastics industry, environmentalists now view it as something of an anachronism and an embarrassment: plastics, they realized, when tightly compacted in a landfill, are not much worse than paper packaging.</p>
        <p>Instead, the focus of environmentalists has shifted to a state-by-state drive for laws that would pressure the packaging industry to produce lighter packaging, promote recycling and create markets for recycled products.  'A Long Way'</p>
        <p>What has changed in the interim, environmentalists say, is the understanding of modern landfills, the plastics industry's effort to promote recycling, and increased cooperation between some business groups and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>"We've come a long way since the Suffolk County ban came into place," said Lisa Collaton, a planner with the Environmental Action Council, who has been working on solid-waste issues.</p>
        <p>At a news conference at the courthouse here today, environmentalists filled a large table with "waste-maker award" products, from small juice boxes to disposable training pants, to promote a New York State bill to require "environmentally sound packaging."</p>
        <p>And while they expressed some regret about the decision by the Suffolk County Legislature, a few miles away to the east, they said their focus was now on statewide efforts to promote the use of recyclable packaging.</p>
        <p>The Suffolk County law would have banned plastic bags, utensils and plastic-foam cups in food stores and takeout restaurants. When it was passed, it was hailed as the answer to the excesses of a throwaway society, where fast-food containers were filling up the rapidly depleting space in landfills.</p>
        <p>Nowhere was this message more potent than on Long Island, where landfills were being forced to close, disposal fees were skyrocketing and a barge loaded with local garbage wandered the seas for four months in 1987 searching for a place willing to take the garbage. Second Thoughts</p>
        <p>But then there were second thoughts.</p>
        <p>One of the main reasons for targeting polystyrene foam was that the manufacturer of the foam used chemicals that were known to deplete the protective ozone layer of the atmosphere. But then, under pressure, the industry agreed to try a new manufacturing process that was less harmful.</p>
        <p>In a breakthrough for environmentalists, McDonald's agreed to switch from foam to packaging made from recycled paper, and the Punch and Judy show between environmentalists and big business became somewhat more complicated.</p>
        <p>And the plastics industry, in what some environmentalists viewed as a public-relations effort, began to promote recycling, and in particular offered technical assistance to schools and businesses to recycle plastic products.</p>
        <p>Suddenly the problem became not banning plastics but finding markets for the plastics that were piling up in recycling bins across the country. Many environmentalists began to accept that plastics were unavoidable and they started focusing on making recycling permanent.</p>
        <p>Late last year, after legal challenges were settled, the County Legislature narrowed the law, exempting hospitals and company cafeterias that recycle plastics. Then on Wednesday, it voted 12 to 5 to delay putting much of the law into effect -- it will still apply to businesses with more than 100 employees -- and legislators predicted that the entire law would eventually be repealed. 'Played to the Masses'</p>
        <p>"We passed this under pressure from so-called environmental groups," said one county legislator, Michael O'Donohoe, a Conservative from East Northport who led the opposition. "We played to the masses and we end up with bad legislation on the books."</p>
        <p>Now the focus has shifted to legislation under consideration in a dozen states to bar packaging of all kinds -- not just for food -- that is not reusable, is made of recycled materials or cannot be recycled in most places.</p>
        <p>The goal, environmentalists say, is to force packaging manufacturers to take the lead in developing recycling programs for their products, and by using recycled materials to improve the market for materials collected by local governments for recycling. Support in State Assembly</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say that with many legislators concerned over the high cost of garbage disposal, their bill has wide support in the State Assembly in Albany. Gov. Mario M. Cuomo has said he will introduce his own packaging legislation as well.</p>
        <p>Roger Bernstein, director of state government affairs for the Society of the Plastics Industry, said the industry would resist specific goals and timetables and penalties sought by environmentalists but would continue to support recycling.</p>
        <p>"I don't believe the product-ban approach is one that is very popular today," he said. "There has been a common focus that we can work in a partnership with environmental organizations and government together to advance recycling goals."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
