<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying a Market Approach to Smog</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="516633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFINERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC103FF936A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying a Market Approach to Smog</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, March 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After laboring for decades under the nation's toughest air-quality rules, companies in Southern California now face a daunting new challenge: proving that they can figure out on their own how best to clean up the nation's worst smog.</p>
        <p>Under a plan that regional air-quality regulators approved earlier this month, Southern California will scrap most of its cumbersome rules for oil refineries and other large industrial polluters. Instead, the regulators are introducing a radical new free-market approach. Companies will still face strict quotas for reducing emissions. But they will be free to satisfy these limits in almost any way they see fit -- even by buying the right to pollute from another company that has surpassed its cleanup quota.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After laboring for decades under the nation's toughest air-quality rules, companies in Southern California now face a daunting new challenge: proving that they can figure out on their own how best to clean up the nation's worst smog.</p>
        <p>Under a plan that regional air-quality regulators approved earlier this month, Southern California will scrap most of its cumbersome rules for oil refineries and other large industrial polluters. Instead, the regulators are introducing a radical new free-market approach. Companies will still face strict quotas for reducing emissions. But they will be free to satisfy these limits in almost any way they see fit -- even by buying the right to pollute from another company that has surpassed its cleanup quota.</p>
        <p>The plan will not take effect for a year and many important details remain to be worked out by the South Coast Air Quality Management District. But companies are already gauging the effects on their operations and laying plans to cut emissions or buy pollution rights.</p>
        <p>Southern California Edison envisions savings and is stepping up efforts to help customers develop less-polluting technologies. ARCO, the big oil company, anticipates such great costs that it is lobbying for changes.</p>
        <p>The plan's goal is to reduce the costs to industry -- and the region's economy -- of eradicating the choking brown haze that covers the Los Angeles basin. It is the most ambitious effort in the nation to use free-market forces to reduce pollution. The results are certain to have a profound influence on national policy, which is already moving in the same direction.</p>
        <p>Several companies large and small, ranging from Terra Furniture of City of Industry to ARCO of Los Angeles, say the plan demands too much additional emissions reduction and will ultimately prove unworkable.</p>
        <p>George H. Babikian, the president of ARCO's gasoline refining and marketing division, said the plan "would impose an additional burden on industry that is technologically unrealistic and financially unreasonable." Big Savings Expected</p>
        <p>But most companies say the new approach will save them hundreds of thousands or even millions of dollars as the region pushes to meet Federal clean-air standards by early in the next century.</p>
        <p>The Coatings Resources Corporation, a small company in Huntington Beach that makes paints and coatings for products like Mattel toys, plans to use new technologies and less polluting paint ingredients, reducing emissions enough to become a seller of pollution credits. In contrast, Southern California Edison says it can meet its emissions requirements more cheaply by buying credits than by investing in additional pollution-control technologies itself.</p>
        <p>"The market will assign the cheapest way to get the necessary emissions reduction," said Michael Hertel, Edison's manager of environmental affairs.</p>
        <p>The plan frees companies to reduce pollution in the most cost-effective ways they can find and provides incentives for research into new pollution-control techniques. Creating a Market</p>
        <p>Companies that exceed their emission-reduction quotas can sell pollution credits on an open market. The trading will be monitored by the regional air-quality agency, which will most likely vouch for the validity of the credits and provide up-to-date price information.</p>
        <p>The buyers would be companies that could not meet their quotas or that decided it would be less expensive to buy credits than to invest in new technology. The Federal Environmental Protection Agency is developing a similar program on a national scale to promote reductions in the pollutants that cause acid rain.</p>
        <p>"What the business community has been saying is, 'We can clean up the air cheaper if you let us do it our way,' " said Joel Schwartz, a staff scientist at the Coalition for Clean Air, an environmental group. "If the program goes forward, they're going to have to prove to us that they can give us real, quantifiable reductions in emissions and progress towards clean air. Otherwise we have to go back to the old system, which may be more onerous, but also easier to enforce."</p>
        <p>Many business groups, eager to increase the potential supply of emissions credits and therefore hold down their price, want the plan to include not just the 2,700 largest polluters, as the air-quality agency has proposed, but almost all companies in the sprawling Los Angeles basin. Some environmental and health groups want to exclude certain large polluters, including utilities, on the ground that they are just coming under tough new regional regulations and should not be allowed to escape them. Trying to Save Jobs</p>
        <p>But the overall plan has apparently gained unstoppable political momentum. At a time when many companies are fleeing from California, in part because of high regulatory costs, officials are eager to save jobs by granting industry more flexibility.</p>
        <p>Some critics of the system say it will actually encourage the flight of businesses because if they close they can sell credits equal to their total emissions -- money they could then use to relocate to another state with looser rules. They could also move to Mexico, though Mexico City's mayor just issued a warning to companies to cut their emissions.</p>
        <p>But a study by the air-quality district found that the program would reduce 1994 industrial-compliance costs by $427 million, a reduction of 65 percent based on projected costs under current regulations. In 1997, the savings would be $270 million, or 29 percent. By 1997, the study said, the region would be losing nearly 2,000 fewer jobs a year than under the current approach.</p>
        <p>Southern California Edison, for example, has seven large plants in the region, all of which emit nitrogen oxides in burning fuel to create electricity. Nitrogen oxides are one of the two basic classes of smog-forming pollutants covered by the plan; the other is reactive organic gases, which are released primarily in the use of paints, coatings and solvents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hertel said that Southern California Edison has reduced its nitrogen oxide emissions by more than 70 percent since 1979. The company's estimated cost for each further ton of annual reductions is $30,000, he said. Because many other companies can reduce their emissions more easily, the cost of buying a credit for one ton of annual nitrogen oxide emissions is projected at $6,800 or less, he said, making it highly attractive for Southern California Edison to be a "smog credit" buyer.  Working With Customers</p>
        <p>At the same time, the utility is helping some of its customers reduce their emissions through imaginative uses of electricity. Fender Guitars was having trouble meeting air-quality standards because its wood coatings emit gases as they dry. But Southern California Edison developed a process to cure the coatings using ultraviolet and infrared light, reducing the quantity of solvents needed and therefore reducing the pollution.</p>
        <p>Under a broad-based program of trading pollution credits, Mr. Hertel said, more companies would be willing to invest in similar innovations, since they could pay for the investment by selling the resulting emissions credits.</p>
        <p>"By unleashing the innovation that comes from people looking to make a dollar from reducing emissions," Mr. Hertel said, "I think we're going to see much more rapid progress towards the clean-air goal than we would under the old command-and-control system."</p>
        <p>The owner of the Coatings Resource Corporation, Ed Laird, said the company was well on its way to eliminating completely its use of paint and coatings ingredients that contain a type of gas known as volatile organic compounds. Suppliers of the resins that go into his paints and coatings are already developing products that do not have the compounds, he said.</p>
        <p>But what to many companies is the plan's virtue -- allowing industry to meet emission-reduction quotas any way it wants -- is a curse to others. Mr. Babikian of ARCO said the program would benefit the company for several years because it knows how to squeeze a certain additional amount of pollution out of its operations. After that, Mr. Babikian said, there is no assurance that the oil industry will be able to develop the technology needed to reduce its emissions of nitrogen oxides by 8 percent annually through the year 2010, as the plan requires.</p>
        <p>"We'd be relying on technological innovations that may or may not take place," he said. If ARCO were forced to bid for pollution credits to meet its quota, Mr. Babikian said, it would only encourage more small companies to cash in their credits and move out of the region.</p>
        <p>At Terra Furniture, Gary Stafford, the chief financial officer, said the company, which has 50 employees, probably could not afford to meet its emission-reduction quota by purchasing credits at an estimated cost of $40,000 per annual ton.</p>
        <p>Yet the cost of meeting the quota by installing new technology to reduce emissions is also prohibitive, probably $1 million plus operating costs. Even being able to sell the resulting emissions credits would not make a $1 million investment economical, Mr. Stafford said.</p>
        <p>It is unclear whether furniture makers will be included in the new plan. The air-quality agency wants to start only with companies that emit more than four tons of pollutants a year, and about half the furniture companies in the region fall below that threshold. But despite his reservations, Mr. Stafford is lobbying for the industry to be included because the new approach would delay until after the year 2000 emission-reduction goals that furniture makers and some other companies would otherwise have to meet by 1997.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
