<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poor vs. Rich in Rio; If Development in Southern Hemisphere Is to Be 'Green,' North May Have to Pay</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="533375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD91438F930A35755C0A964958260" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poor vs. Rich in Rio; If Development in Southern Hemisphere Is to Be 'Green,' North May Have to Pay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Earth Summit, a vast environmental jamboree bringing together thousands of delegates from more than 170 countries, countless ecological watchdogs and the world press, gets under way tomorrow in Rio de Janeiro and it has already become mired in discord and suspicion between rich and poor nations.</p>
        <p>The central issues are: Who will pay the bill for the first comprehensive attempt to repair the environmental damage caused by industrialization? And who will insure that the poor nations of the southern hemisphere industrialize at a lower cost to the environment than the richer nations of the North did?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Earth Summit, a vast environmental jamboree bringing together thousands of delegates from more than 170 countries, countless ecological watchdogs and the world press, gets under way tomorrow in Rio de Janeiro and it has already become mired in discord and suspicion between rich and poor nations.</p>
        <p>The central issues are: Who will pay the bill for the first comprehensive attempt to repair the environmental damage caused by industrialization? And who will insure that the poor nations of the southern hemisphere industrialize at a lower cost to the environment than the richer nations of the North did?</p>
        <p>The largely northern-inspired drive to make the South's development environmentally sustainable has opened a new chapter in a battle between the have and the have-not nations that dates from the 1960's and 70's. The Goals of the South</p>
        <p>If nothing else, the arguments prove that the end of the cold war has not ended recriminations by the developing world directed at the major industrial democracies.</p>
        <p>At a news conference today, Maurice Strong, the Earth Summit's normally ebullient Secretary General, put the best face he could on the difficulties confronting him, saying: "Success will not come easily. I predict this conference will look as though it is going to collapse before it is over."</p>
        <p>The atmosphere is one of poor and rich countries playing on each other's anxieties.</p>
        <p>Poor countries want to exploit northern worries about climate change, the destruction of forests and polluted seas to extract more aid. They say that the rich countries must pay the extra cost of "clean" development, just as 20 years ago they demanded a new world economic order to shift the North's riches southward.</p>
        <p>Richer northern countries want to hold the poor to their pledge to pursue sustainable economic development by setting up a commission to monitor the South's strategies. But the developing world is resisting any obligation to abide by outsiders' recommendations.</p>
        <p>The Earth Summit's success is also being jeopardized by the Bush Administration's refusal to sign a convention protecting the diversity of nature because of disagreements over patent rights and the way they are paid for.</p>
        <p>Britain, Japan and France may withhold support too. But if so powerful a quartet of industrialized countries refuses to sign a convention widely perceived as favorable to the developing world, southern countries warn, they may not sign a convention backed by the North on stabilizing the climate.</p>
        <p>Such a deadlock could deal a crippling blow to the meeting here, for the two conventions have been billed as its greatest triumph and their signature is a major reason why nearly 100 heads of state and government will be here for the finale on June 14.</p>
        <p>Another looming difficulty is Israel's expected bid on Wednesday to remove references to the environmental rights of "people under occupation" that Arab nations have inserted into several documents even though this threatens to unravel existing agreements.</p>
        <p>Austria, the Netherlands and Switzerland are also planning to isolate the United States further by inviting countries that favor stricter control of gas emissions than President Bush will accept to sign a "like-minded countries declaration," pledging to do more to combat global warming. Smaller Nations Weigh In</p>
        <p>The Earth Summit is officially the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development, and as that name suggests, its overarching goal is to find a way for rich and poor to raise living standards while insuring that growth is tailored to what the Earth can stand.</p>
        <p>But after two years of preparatory talks, poor southern countries are fearful the North wants to keep them that way. The poor countries say they will only match their development to environmental goals if the rich pay the bill.</p>
        <p>The industrialized world is afraid of new financial commitments at a time of slow growth and widespread recession. The electoral paralysis that seems to be seeping through the United States only adds to the indecision.</p>
        <p>Conference officials are still given to extravagant statements about the meeting's significance. "We have a clear mandate to take new steps towards a new order in the interests of mankind," Brazil's Foreign Minister Celso Lafer said today.</p>
        <p>But most delegates' expectations range from low to modest.</p>
        <p>"The real test is whether governments carry out their commitments," said Mr. Strong, the Canadian who is leading the conference. "We have to hold them to account."</p>
        <p>The last time the developing South sought access to the coffers of the rich on such a scale came 20 years ago when -- encouraged by the oil exporters' success in raising prices tenfold -- they tried to jack up the price of other raw materials. Some Convergence</p>
        <p>That attempt failed. But this time the developing world senses that the North may be more vulnerable.</p>
        <p>Already industrialized countries have agreed that nothing less than the "eradication of poverty" must be the cornerstone of ecological survival. And they also know that if China and India industrialize, as Britain did in the 19th century, by burning their coal reserves, all the North's efforts to curb pollution will come to nothing.</p>
        <p>In preparatory negotiations stretching back over two years, the North and the South have already reached a measure of agreement on some steps.</p>
        <p>They include conventions to curb the emission of gases that may warm the atmosphere and to preserve flora and fauna, as well as an ambitiously detailed plan, called Agenda 21, to clean up virtually every aspect of the environment during the next century.</p>
        <p>These will be complemented by a declaration setting out the basic principles that should guide this quest.</p>
        <p>Final negotiations begin in earnest after the ceremonial opening on Wednesday by President Fernando Collor de Mello of Brazil and Secretary General Boutros Boutros-Ghali of the United Nations at the immense, shabby concrete-and-steel conference center almost an hour's drive from the center of town.</p>
        <p>The estimated cost of cleaning up the globe are astronomical: some $125 billion a year just for the goals in Agenda 21. But the North so far has only pledged to provide "new and additional resources," without saying how much.</p>
        <p>The developing world receives about $55 billion in aid each year; if all this were used for environmentally sound projects, it would take another $70 billion to meet the bill for Agenda 21.</p>
        <p>Most of the new money could be found if the industrial world increased aid to the target they have already set: seven-tenths of 1 percent of total economic output.</p>
        <p>Developing countries have asked for a commitment to reach this level by 2000. But Britain, Germany and Belgium oppose setting a binding date, and the United States has never accepted the higher target.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
