<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Informally Offers to Cut Rise in Climate-Warming Gases</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19920430T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="524661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROUS OXIDE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DD113AF93AA15757C0A964958260" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Informally Offers to Cut Rise in Climate-Warming Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, April 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Bush Administration has for the first time offered to curb the increase in climate-warming gases released into the atmosphere by American factories, trucks and automobiles as part of a proposed agreement being prepared for a top-level international environmental conference to be held in Rio de Janeiro in June.</p>
        <p>This American negotiating position was stated in Paris earlier this month during informal talks on the planned treaty between the industrial nations and some developing countries, officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Bush Administration has for the first time offered to curb the increase in climate-warming gases released into the atmosphere by American factories, trucks and automobiles as part of a proposed agreement being prepared for a top-level international environmental conference to be held in Rio de Janeiro in June.</p>
        <p>This American negotiating position was stated in Paris earlier this month during informal talks on the planned treaty between the industrial nations and some developing countries, officials said.</p>
        <p>But the United States is still refusing to join the rest of the industrial world in accepting a treaty commitment to stabilize the emission of these "greenhouse gases" at 1990 levels by the year 2000. Already Succeeding, Bush Says</p>
        <p>In a document released last week, the Bush Administration suggested that there was no need for it to join in this pledge, contending that environmental programs the United States has already put into effect would reduce its emissions of greenhouse gases by 7 percent to 11 percent below what they would have been by 2000.</p>
        <p>But officials acknowledged that the levels of such gases released into the atmosphere through American industrial production and use would still be 1.5 percent to 6 percent higher in 2000 than they are today.</p>
        <p>At the Paris preparatory talks, the United States, in convoluted language, pledged only "to contribute to the global effort" on climate stabilization by "recognizing that the reduction of growth of net anthropogenic emissions of the total of all greenhouse gases not covered by the Montreal Convention would be an appropriate signal that longer-term emission trends have been modified consistent with that objective."</p>
        <p>The Montreal Convention bans the release of gases that damage the ozone layer, meaning man-made emissions of carbon dioxide, methane and nitrous oxide. In the view of many experts, these gases threaten environmental havoc by trapping heat in the atmosphere and melting portions of the polar ice caps, raising ocean levels.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration's stand at the Paris talks, which ended on April 16, is being seen by many diplomats and officials here as an indication that the United States is becoming slightly more flexible on global warming, which until recently it refused to recognize as being a problem at all.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, its position remains far from that taken by leaders of other industrial nations, in refusing to set legally binding targets for curbing greenhouse gas releases.</p>
        <p>And in a presidential election year, the Administration appears reluctant to make commitments that might hamper economic growth. The President has not yet said whether he plans to attend the Rio meeting, which is known as the Earth Summit.</p>
        <p>For officials in Washington, there are also considerations of life style. Americans, per person, consume more energy and other resources than Europeans or Japanese, and much more than citizens of third world countries. And many of those Americans who benefit from energy-intensive industries, or who enjoy well-heated houses and big cars, will vote in November. Their preferences are not likely to be overlooked as the Administration considers its positions in Rio de Janeiro and in the preparatory talks.</p>
        <p>Negotiators from rich and poor countries are to meet here on Thursday to try once more to draft a climate-change treaty in time for the Rio meeting.</p>
        <p>Such a treaty would likely be the most important achievement in Rio, and many heads of state and government are likely to make their attendance conditional on its being ready for signature then.</p>
        <p>The United Nations officials organizing the meeting also hope to agree on another convention aimed at preserving the world's animal and plant life, as well as a general declaration on the need to insure that economic growth is environmentally sustainable. And they will seek a vast plan of action for cleaning up the global environment over the 21st century. Help From Tokyo</p>
        <p>Officials said that in Paris earlier this month, Japan dropped its insistence that it be allowed a 6 percent increase in greenhouse gas emissions by 2000 to compensate for its expected population increase. This enabled industrial nations except the United States to agree on a single target.</p>
        <p>America's negotiating offer to reduce the degree of increase in the levels of these gases leaves it the option of compensating for increased emissions through a large-scale reforestation program. Forests and oceans naturally absorb many warming gases.</p>
        <p>The use of this Washington standard -- a reduction in increase, rather than a stabilization or reduction in existing levels -- might encourage countries like Brazil or Malaysia to preserve and expand their forests because it would give them room for industrialization while creating less danger to world climate.</p>
        <p>But there is as yet no agreed method for calculating the quantity of greenhouse gases absorbed by oceans, forests and grasslands. And some experts express fear that the United States might use this lack of scientific agreement as a pretext to delay reducing emissions.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 30, 1992, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about the Bush Administration's policy on controlling the emission of gases believed to contribute to global warming misstated the focus of the international accord called the Montreal Protocol. It sets a timetable for phasing out chlorofluorocarbons and other chemicals associated with destruction of the earth's ozone layer; it does not cover "greenhouse gases" linked to global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 30, 1992, Thursday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article yesterday about the Bush Administration's policy on controlling the emission of gases believed to contribute to global warming misstated the focus of the international accord called the Montreal Protocol. It sets a timetable for phasing out chlorofluorocarbons and other chemicals associated with destruction of the earth's ozone layer; it does not cover "greenhouse gases" linked to global warming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
