<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Damage Report; The World's Oceans Are Sending an S.O.S.</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RED TIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPECTER, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE153AF930A35756C0A964958260" item-length="1974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Damage Report; The World's Oceans Are Sending an S.O.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL SPECTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SPECTER, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the world prepares for an international conference on the environment in June, signs are emerging that the suffering of the oceans is speeding up. Red tides are increasing. Salmon runs are fading and bluefin tuna are threatened. From the Baltic to Long Island, seals are washing up dead, and PCBs are a major suspect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the world prepares for an international conference on the environment in June, signs are emerging that the suffering of the oceans is speeding up. Red tides are increasing. Salmon runs are fading and bluefin tuna are threatened. From the Baltic to Long Island, seals are washing up dead, and PCBs are a major suspect.</p>
        <p>The last decade has not been easy on the world's oceans, the largest and seemingly least vulnerable resource on Earth. With an immensity so humbling and grand, few people can comprehend the kind of human assault required to do serious damage to the world's seas.</p>
        <p>And the sea does seem to surge forever. But most humans and fish live within the 200 miles where coastal waters brush up against the sand, exactly where many of the world's richest fishing grounds have been transformed into its most extensive sewers.</p>
        <p>Every day, for example, more than 40 million gallons of partially untreated sewage are sent gushing into New York's Hudson and East Rivers. Rivers of waste flow into the Mediterranean, and over the last decade typhoid has been at least 100 times more common near it than in Northern Europe.</p>
        <p>Many of the most discouraging trends in the sea -- giant tumors on turtles, PCBs in the flesh of fish, amnesic shellfish poisoning of humans by algae blooms -- were unknown 30 years ago. And while there is no scientifically certain way to prove a pattern, or to assert that humans are always to blame, the deterioration has escalated notably in the last decade. Autopsies on beluga whales -- sometimes called the most polluted animal on earth -- regularly find ulcers, cancers, immune deficiencies and lung infections that may be caused by the mercury, lead, PCBs and other toxins that quietly accumulate in their blubber every time they swallow a fish from the rivers of Europe or America.</p>
        <p>Little of this appears to have made an impression on most Americans, partly no doubt because along with their deeply held love of the sea has come an understandable belief in its intangible abundance. There may be a hole in the ozone and acid rain falling on the forests, but surely the oceans -- the ineffably endless oceans -- will always be there to wash away the accumulated grime of lives tethered to the land.</p>
        <p>The sea enchants us and we don't like to hear bad news about our reveries. "Go visit the prairies in June, when for scores and scores of miles you wade knee-deep among tiger lilies," Herman Melville, America's greatest ocean-worshipping novelist, wrote in Moby Dick. "What is the one charm wanting?"</p>
        <p>Yes, it's the sea, in which Melville and many others like him have divined the "image of the ungraspable phantom of life." To a degree almost inconceivable to people who rely more visibly on the oceans for sustenance and their livelihoods, Americans have become accustomed to their eternal, unchanging presence.</p>
        <p>Yet, signs of a crisis are hard to miss:</p>
        <p>Nearly half of Europe's harbour seals were destroyed by viral infections in the 1980's. Ulcerative mycosis -- classified only in 1978 -- has wiped out fleets of food fish like the Atlantic menhaden. The sea's most delicate and commanding coral reefs, from the Florida Keys to Australia's Great Barrier Reef, have begun to die; some slowly as logging silt chokes off sunlight; others suddenly as divers squirt in cyanide to stun fish for aquariums.</p>
        <p>And that's not the worst of it. An epidemic of tumors the size of baseballs has assaulted sea turtles, already an endangered species, from the Gulf of Mexico to the coastal waters of Indonesia. Slicks of plastic trash hug the coasts, and birds wash out of them, their graceful necks wrapped in six-pack holders.</p>
        <p>Even the essential chemical balance at many river mouths has changed as nitrogen-rich fertilizers and acid rain have increased while fresh water is siphoned off by dams and development. As the water's composition changes, so does the sea's intricate food chain -- starting with plankton, and ending with people.</p>
        <p>Still, it's hard to work up much concern for the largest and most physically obvious fact of life on Earth. Covering 70 percent of the planet and accounting for up to 45 percent of the total heat transported in the Northern Hemisphere, the ocean isn't about to dry up or turn to sludge tomorrow.</p>
        <p>But it is being depleted of life at astonishing rates. Canada's once plentiful coastal fishing stocks are being "vacuumed out of the seas" by European and Asian trawlers that can snare millions of pounds with ease, officials say. In 1954, the world's annual fish catch was 21.6 million tons. In 1983 the amount had more than trebled, and the figure by last year was well over 100 million tons. There is a limit to the fish in the sea.</p>
        <p>Good news does break through from time to time. Japan and Taiwan have agreed to stop using drift nets by the end of the year. And the free flow of mercury and many other poisons has been greatly reduced.</p>
        <p>But if Ahab sought the White Whale today, he would almost certainly find a frail Leviathan, defiant still, but riddled with ailments. Mammal Die-offs</p>
        <p>During the last five years there has been a rash of fatal epidemics among sea mammals in the world. In 1987-88, about 2,500 bottlenose dolphins died of bacterial infections along the U.S. East Coast. In 1988-89, about 18,000 European harbor seals -- half the population -- died on Scandinavian and English coasts of a virus resembling the distemper that kills dogs. In 1990, a similar virus killed 6,000 striped dolphins in the Mediterranean near Spain and has since spread to Greece. Since November, about 75 seals have washed up on Long Island -- about double the usual number, with some dead of distemper. In 1990, 300 dolphins died in the Gulf of Mexico of unknown causes.</p>
        <p>Between 1957 and 1987, said Bruce McKay, a toxicologist at Greenpeace, there were only two large die-offs of mammals, both of seals in cold northern waters. Scientists cannot say why the deaths have increased, nor why so many whales have grounded themselves or swum into urban harbors sick and disoriented. But many of these fish-eating mammals have very high levels of PCB's in their blubber -- now-banned chemicals still making their way from landfills downriver into oceans. PCB's suppress immune systems, letting other infections spread. They also suppress birthrates, hurting a herd's chances of recovering.</p>
        <p>Drift Nets</p>
        <p>Drift nets can be as much as 40 miles long -- the size of one in comparison to Manhattan Island is shown below. On that scale, the Empire State Building would be the size of the letter i in this sentence. Environmentalists estimate that an area of ocean the size of Ohio is swept by high seas fleets each night, and the nets catch virtually everything down to a depth of 30 feet. The Center for Marine Conservation estimates that 200,000 mammals die in nets each year.</p>
        <p>Opponents of drift nets won a resounding victory this year when Japan and Taiwan reluctantly agreed to stop using them by 1993. South Korea may follow suit.</p>
        <p>But drift nets are by no means the only danger. All nets can entangle mammals and birds, and their thin plastic threads often slice off fins and beaks. Studies of gill nets set for shark and halibut in California reported by the Center for Environmental Education estimated that in 1983 alone they killed 1,000 sea lions -- like the one above -- 300 porpoises, 100 harbor seals, 100 sea otters, 30 pilot whales and many gray, humpback and finback whales. Another 1983 study estimated that 25,000 sea birds died in nets off central California; one inspection of 133 halibut nets found an average of 6.3 halibut in each net -- and 7.2 sea birds.</p>
        <p>Dams, which block fish spawning runs, and logging, which fills spawning streams with mud, have so reduced Pacific salmon that limits on the California-Oregon-Washington coast were cut to minimal levels this year.</p>
        <p>Drift-netting contributed to the problem. Foreign fleets are not supposed to catch fish that spawn in another nation's waters, but the National Marine Fisheries Service estimated that Japanese fleets took 174,000 North American salmon in 1990.</p>
        <p>Even shifts in restaurant menus threaten species. The Marine Fisheries Service says the popularity of "blackened redfish" nearly wiped out red drum in the 1980's. And the bluefin tuna that once filled so many sandwiches that it was the "chicken of the sea" is now threatened. All species of shrimp are overfished in American waters, and shrimp nurseries are being wiped out as marshes are filled for housing.</p>
        <p>Trash</p>
        <p>Plastic trash, which floats indefinitely and resists degradation by salt water and sunlight, is found on the most remote islands and emptiest seas in the world. Turtles mistake sandwich bags for jellyfish and die of blocked intestines. Diving birds swallow bits of styrofoam or tangle in six-pack holders, as the pelican at right did. Two humpback whales washed up on Long Island this year, one enmeshed in discarded fishing gear, another dead of a stomach infection researchers said was worsened by a plastic bag.</p>
        <p>In 1991, the Center for Marine Conservation rounded up 118,200 volunteers to clean up 3,800 miles of U.S. coastline. In one day, they picked up 2.5 million pounds of trash.</p>
        <p>Red Tides</p>
        <p>These sudden blooms of microscopic algae have been recorded for centuries. But scientists say they are now increasing rapidly, rising in step with human populations around harbors. Many "red tides" -- which can be brown, yellow or green -- are slimy and unpleasant, but harmless. However, if the algae are thick enough, they form mats and block sunlight, killing shellfish beds. The mats die and rot, consuming all the oxygen in the water. Red tides have wiped out fish farms in many harbors.</p>
        <p>Even more dangerous: some planktons produce toxins, and those species are spreading. Paralytic shellfish poisoning, for example, was discovered in California in the 1920's, and many mussel beds there are closed. But amnesic poisoning was unknown before 1987, when it struck 185 Canadians near an unpolluted bay, killing three. About 1,000 have died since of shellfish poisoning in the Philippines, Thailand, Guatemala and Japan.</p>
        <p>Coral Bleaching</p>
        <p>As many as 3,000 species of plants and animals may live in one reef, and reefs grow slowly, over decades. Bleaching -- death of the whole ecosystem -- is increasing everywhere. The wider causes include river mouths full of sea-darkening sewage or silt from logged hillsides and the periodic warm El Nino currents that stretch across the southern Pacific. But reefs are also killed by people who fish with dynamite or cyanide, gather armloads to polish for tourist jewelry and let dragging anchors snap off coral heads.</p>
        <p>Diseases</p>
        <p>An epidemic of fibropapillomas -- tumors on necks and flippers that grow until swimming or eating is impossible -- has struck sea turtles around the world. The turtles were already endangered by shrimp fishing and beach development: for example, nests of the Kemp's ridley turtle declined from an estimated 40,000 in 1947 to 800 by 1988.</p>
        <p>Fungus infections in which red dots grow into holes that rot fins or expose organs and bones have attacked many food fish, like the Atlantic menhaden at right. The infections are most common on polluted American and European coasts.</p>
        <p>Polluted Fish</p>
        <p>Even "farm-raised" fish spend weeks in ocean pens. Sea-spawning predators like tuna and swordfish eat fish from polluted rivers and poisons build up in their fat. A 1991 Consumer Reports survey of supermarket fish found that 43 percent of the salmon and 25 percent of the swordfish tested contained PCBs; 90 percent of the swordfish contained mercury too. Some clams had high lead levels. Others contained arsenic. The most pollutant-free species were flounder and sole.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
