<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush on the Environment: A Record of Contradictions</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Bush Record -- Seventh article of a series." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540450"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECESSION AND DEPRESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK TIMES/CBS NEWS POLL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED9173EF937A35754C0A964958260" item-length="2083" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush on the Environment: A Record of Contradictions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>KENOVA, W. Va.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The people who live here in the hazy valleys cut by the Ohio and Big Sandy Rivers, where the air has been among the most polluted in the country, are benefiting from cleaner air these days, thanks to changes in weather patterns as well as to a law passed two years ago.</p>
        <p>President Bush saluted that law, the Clean Air Act, and said it would "make the 1990's the era for clean air."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The people who live here in the hazy valleys cut by the Ohio and Big Sandy Rivers, where the air has been among the most polluted in the country, are benefiting from cleaner air these days, thanks to changes in weather patterns as well as to a law passed two years ago.</p>
        <p>President Bush saluted that law, the Clean Air Act, and said it would "make the 1990's the era for clean air."</p>
        <p>But now, with a Presidential campaign in progress and the economy stubbornly sluggish, the law, the most comprehensive and expensive environmental statute ever enacted, is under attack within the Administration, where business interests often seem to outweigh environmental concerns. And that is leaving many people here worried that the Clean Air Act's initial gains will not be followed by the more sweeping improvements the law was supposed to provide. Views of Record Differ</p>
        <p>During the 1988 campaign Mr. Bush often said he wanted to be known as "the environmental President." But critics say that while he took strong stands on environmental matters for the first two years of his administration, his approach changed in the midst of the recession.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush now seems to place a much higher priority on reducing the costs of complying with environmental regulation than on cleaning the nation's air.</p>
        <p>In every public accounting the President has offered of his domestic accomplishments, he ranks the Clean Air Act at or near the top of the list. "I invite comparison of the record that we as a country and an Administration have built," Mr. Bush said in a speech last month. "It is aggressive. It is comprehensive. And it is ambitious, but carefully balanced."</p>
        <p>But leaders of environmental groups have a different view.</p>
        <p>"In his commitments during the 1988 campaign, he was good on some issues, mediocre on others, and very weak on a few," said Carl Pope, associate executive director of the Sierra Club in San Francisco. "But what we did get in the first two years was environmental moderation. He did not treat the environment as an issue he would throw away to the right wing of the Republican party and the least responsible sectors of American business.</p>
        <p>"But what we have seen in the last six months," he added, "is an almost compete reversion to the policies pursued by the Reagan Administration."</p>
        <p>The available evidence lends support to that view. Reversed Direction</p>
        <p>In his first two years as President, Mr. Bush approved sharp increases in the Environmental Protection Agency's budget, blocked a new dam in Colorado that would have flooded a scenic canyon, and added more than $100 million to the Federal budget for buying land for parks and refuges.</p>
        <p>But in the last year, Mr. Bush approved a proposal that would make it much harder to halt a dam like the one in Colorado. And he backed two proposals approved by the Departments of Agriculture and Interior that would limit or eliminate the public's ability to block timber cutting in national forests and mining or oil exploration on public lands.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Mr. Bush put the coast of New England, southern Florida and most of California off limits to oil exploration and drilling for a decade. But a year ago, Mr. Bush tried to open the untouched Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska for oil exploration. Congress killed that plan.</p>
        <p>In 1988 and 1989 Mr. Bush repeatedly promised to fashion a land-use policy that would produce "no net loss" of the nation's swamps, marshes and other wetlands. But last summer, he approved a plan that would allow development on 50 million acres of wetlands, half the nation's total, including parts of the Florida Everglades.</p>
        <p>In his first two years, Mr. Bush signed international agreements to ban ivory trading, to eliminate large-scale drift-net fishing and to protect Antarctica. But Mr. Bush was the last leader of an industrialized nation to announce he would attend the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro last month. Once there, he drew international criticism for weakening a treaty to combat global warming and for refusing to sign another to protect endangered species. Job Losses Cited</p>
        <p>The President and his aides say they are trying to protect jobs. But environmentalists maintain that jobs would be created by tighter regulations that would spur development of new equipment and techniques to make American factories more efficient.</p>
        <p>Since the passage of the Clean Air Act in 1990, the Administration has failed to complete more than 30 regulations needed to put much of the law into effect, including most of the important ones. The few rules the White House has issued seem intended primarily to reduce the costs of regulation to business. Before the Administration began weakening the provisions last year, the oil industry had estimated that full compliance at the 200 refineries across the country would cost $40 billion over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>In the view of environmentalists, the most effective rules so far were those written by Congress when the law was drafted. Those provisions dealt with acid rain and cleaner fuels and amounted to about 30 percent of the law. The remaining rules are supposed to be written by the Administration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides, including Robert E. Grady, the acting Deputy Director of the Office of Management and Budget, said Mr. Bush's commitment to environmental goals has not changed.</p>
        <p>"The President has been the greatest defender of land and water since Teddy Roosevelt," Mr. Grady said. The Stated Goals Push for Clean Air Ends Up as Retreat</p>
        <p>With ambitious goals and high costs, the Clean Air Act was seen from the beginning as a test of the President's strategy of balancing environmental concerns with economic needs.</p>
        <p>And in few other environmental efforts has the President's about-face seemed clearer. With prodding from the President's Council on Competitiveness, a cabinet group headed by Vice President Dan Quayle whose goal is to reduce the cost of regulations, Mr. Bush has responded to complaints from manufacturers and utilities by curtailing the law's reach.</p>
        <p>In June the Administration issued a new rule that allows each of about 35,000 chemical, pharmaceutical and other plants to increase emissions of hazardous air pollutants by up to 245 tons a year, just by asking states' permission to do so. No public hearings or notification are required.</p>
        <p>In March, four days before the Michigan primary, Mr. Bush told a group of Detroit businessmen that he was waiving a Clean Air rule requiring auto makers to install canisters in new cars to capture fumes during refueling.</p>
        <p>"The manipulation of regulations is a direct result of industry lobbying at the White House," said Norm Steenstra, environmental coordinator for West Virginia Citizen Action Group, an environmental group in Charleston. "We're learning very quickly that one can pass legislation and then get murdered in the regulatory phase." Awaiting Regulations</p>
        <p>In this region, where Kentucky, Ohio and West Virginia come together in a lumpy landscape of narrow valleys and low hills, it's easy to measure any changes in the White House view of the Clean Air Act. An accident of man and nature often makes the air here dirtier than anyplace in the East, according to the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>On windless winter and hot summer days, the valleys trap air carrying tons of dust and chemicals churned out by steel, coke and chemical plants along the Ohio and Big Sandy Rivers. During the dry summer of 1988, residents said, the air was so bad that doctors warned families to keep children indoors.</p>
        <p>By every measure, according to air pollution authorities in the three states, the air in the Ohio River Valley is cleaner this year, especially around this town of 4,000 people. One reason is that temperatures have been much cooler. Another is that sulfur dioxide has been reduced by the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Across the Big Sandy River in Catlettsburg, Ky., the nation's 13th largest oil refinery, owned by Ashland Oil Inc., turns crude oil into gasoline, diesel fuel and Valvoline motor oil. The refinery is one of the region's principal sources of sulfur dioxide pollutants, which can cause respiratory illnesses and which combine with moisture in the atmosphere to form acid rain.</p>
        <p>Over the last several years, Kentucky air-pollution authorities have repeatedly levied fines against Ashland totaling several hundred thousand dollars. A report by the West Virginia Air Pollution Control Commission showed that in 1987, one of the refinery's units released caustic ash into the air that fell as thick as snow, peeling paint from cars and causing other damage. Multimillion-Dollar Investment</p>
        <p>A provision in the Clean Air Act requires refiners to reduce the amount of sulfur in diesel fuel from 0.22 percent to 0.02 percent. Ashland responded by spending $68 million in the last year on new equipment to strip sulfur from the fuel and keep it from escaping into the air. That brought the sharply lower sulfur dioxide levels.</p>
        <p>"We are complying with the law, and we supported the Clean Air law from the beginning," John R. Hall, Ashland's chairman, said in an interview at the company's hilltop headquarters. "We believe the new requirements for diesel fuel are right."</p>
        <p>But Sue Holland, a mother of five and a leader of Tri State Environmental Impact, a local environmental group, complains that the cleanup of other pollutants in the Ohio Valley's air can't even begin until the Administration issues the necessary regulations. Words and Actions Regulatory Delays Slow Enforcement</p>
        <p>Representative Henry A. Waxman, the California Democrat who was a principal author of the Clean Air Act, filed a lawsuit on June 5 asserting that the Administration was deliberately trying to thwart the intent of the law by delaying regulations to help businesses. Mr. Waxman said the Administration had missed 30 deadlines for writing regulations and had failed to follow 29 other requirements of the law.</p>
        <p>"The record is clear," Mr. Waxman said in a statement accompanying the lawsuit. "After publicly pledging support for this law, President Bush worked closely with big polluters to undermine it, in many cases holding up vitally important regulations at the White House. This is very different than flip-flopping on a campaign promise. The new Clean Air program was enacted into law. Having signed the law, the President is legally bound to carry it out."</p>
        <p>In interviews, the President's aides said the Administration's work on the Clean Air Act had been fair; their goal, they said, was to achieve cleaner air without bankrupting companies. The many delays in writing the law's more important rules resulted from the sheer volume of the work, they said.</p>
        <p>"Deadlines are frequently missed," acknowledged C. Boyden Gray, the President's counsel. "The E.P.A. is being called on to issue more rules under this statute than any other act, in a concentrated period of time. It's all unfolding pretty much as Congress intended. There is a delay here and a delay there, but that is par for the course. It's very rare that anybody comes in on time under any statute."</p>
        <p>Mr. Waxman and other critics assert that election-year politics have allowed the nation's largest corporations to influence the President's decisions on the Clean Air Act and virtually every other facet of environmental policy. In-Fighting E.P.A. on One Side, Quayle on the Other</p>
        <p>One reason for the delays is an angry battle within the Administration between William K. Reilly, the E.P.A. Administrator, and Vice President Quayle and cabinet members over how rigorous the Clean Air rules should be.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air program for reducing emissions of 189 toxic substances was to take 10 years. Under the law, the Administration was supposed to begin the process last November by listing every source of toxic contamination that would need to be reduced or eliminated. But oil, chemical and other industrial lobbyists have asked Mr. Quayle's Council on Competitiveness to reduce the costs of the new rules. Mr. Reilly opposes that, and because of this disagreement the Administration has not issued the rules needed to start the program.</p>
        <p>"This law makes the states more responsible than ever to control air pollution, but we are not in control of writing the rules," said G. Dale Farley, director of the West Virginia Air Pollution Control Commission. "Until they are finished, we can't begin to plan our work. The effect of all this is unfortunate. It means the air doesn't get cleaner."  THE 1992 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
