<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comet Alert Canceled, Thanks to New Data</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="579723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SWIFT-TUTTLE (COMET)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL ASTRONOMICAL UNION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARVARD-SMITHSONIAN CENTER FOR ASTROPHYSICS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARSDEN, BRIAN G (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DE1F3CF93AA15751C1A964958260" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comet Alert Canceled, Thanks to New Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DOOMSDAY has been postponed a thousand years or so, at least as far as Comet Swift-Tuttle is concerned.</p>
        <p>New evidence suggests that the six-mile-wide mountain of ice and dirt, zipping through space at 37 miles a second, has virtually no chance of colliding with the Earth on its next pass through the inner solar system. In October, astronomers warned that the comet might hit Earth during that pass 134 years from now, in 2126.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DOOMSDAY has been postponed a thousand years or so, at least as far as Comet Swift-Tuttle is concerned.</p>
        <p>New evidence suggests that the six-mile-wide mountain of ice and dirt, zipping through space at 37 miles a second, has virtually no chance of colliding with the Earth on its next pass through the inner solar system. In October, astronomers warned that the comet might hit Earth during that pass 134 years from now, in 2126.</p>
        <p>The impact could have created a global pall of dust capable of blocking sunlight, disrupting the climate and ending civilization. A collision between the Earth and an object from outer space 65 million years ago is widely believed to have contributed to the extinction of the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>Swift-Tuttle's orbit, poorly understood at the time of the doomsday alert, has now been calculated with greater precision thanks to a series of new observations and the discovery of previous sightings of the comet.</p>
        <p>"We're safe for the next millennium," said Dr. Brian G. Marsden of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics in Cambridge, Mass., who issued the original alert for the International Astronomical Union, the world astronomy authority.</p>
        <p>Its Central Bureau for Astronomical Telegrams, which Dr. Marsden heads, informs astronomers of rapidly changing phenomena so they can focus their observations on events that are often fleeting and enigmatic. Updated Information Streams In</p>
        <p>In a different reprieve from doomsday, scientists at Pennsylvania State University concluded in the current issue of the journal Nature that a precipitous decline in atmospheric carbon dioxide that would starve plants of their main chemical building blocks would come in a billion or so years, not the 100 million years predicted earlier.</p>
        <p>The comet alert Dr. Marsden sounded in October prompted scores of astronomers around the globe to train their telescopes on the sky and provide him with updated data on the comet's position. It also prompted a review of historical documents, which showed that on its periodic visits to the inner solar system, Swift-Tuttle probably zipped past the Earth in A.D. 188 and apparently in 69 B.C. as well, when it was sighted by observers in China.</p>
        <p>The two sets of information combined to improve calculations of Swift-Tuttle's future orbit. Thus, the previous suggestion that the comet had a 1-in-10,000 chance of hitting the Earth on Aug. 14, 2126, was ruled invalid.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marsden, writing in bureau circular No. 5671 this month, laid out the new information and concluded: "There is very little possibility of the comet's collision with the Earth during the next millennium."</p>
        <p>The new calculations also explain why there were no apparent sightings of Swift-Tuttle between A.D. 188 and an appearance in 1747, despite its passage every 130 years or so through the inner solar system. It was in fact too far from Earth to be readily visible.</p>
        <p>Swift-Tuttle is thought to cause the annual Perseid meteor shower, which usually peaks in August. The comet's repeated passes through the solar system over the ages, all the while shedding bits of dust and debris, have formed a river of particles along its path. Crossing a River of Debris</p>
        <p>Each year as Earth passes through this river, the sky comes alive with flashes of light. The Perseids are the best known and most reliable of the many meteor showers throughout the year.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Marsden noted that during its journey through the solar system, the comet could eventually come back to threaten the Earth.</p>
        <p>"In the year 3044, we have the possibility of a very close approach," he said, noting that a direct hit could not be ruled out because of inaccuracies in trying to make such a long-term forecast.</p>
        <p>"This date is so far in future that I hope people will not get unduly worried," Dr. Marsden said. "But some day there's a chance of a hit."</p>
        <p>Contemplating such disasters, and eager for a new job after the cold war, weapon scientists have eagerly talked in recent years of building fleets of rocket interceptors that would travel thought space to deflect a speeding intruder with giant nuclear explosions. But the demise of Swift-Tuttle as a threat has presumably sapped some of the energy from their campaign.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
