<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warmest Winter Slips (on Ice) Into History</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="515462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEASONS AND MONTHS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL WEATHER SERVICE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DB1F3FF933A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warmest Winter Slips (on Ice) Into History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Winter, or what there was of it, ended this morning at 3:48 A.M. Eastern time. The National Weather Service is counting this winter as the warmest in the 97 years records have been kept.</p>
        <p>Nationwide the average temperature from December through February (the Weather Service's "winter," for record-keeping purposes) was about 4 degrees Fahrenheit above normal, but that hid large variations. Eastern Montana was 11 degrees above normal; Chicago was 6 degrees above normal. Major Northeast cities recorded temperatures 2 degrees above normal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Winter, or what there was of it, ended this morning at 3:48 A.M. Eastern time. The National Weather Service is counting this winter as the warmest in the 97 years records have been kept.</p>
        <p>Nationwide the average temperature from December through February (the Weather Service's "winter," for record-keeping purposes) was about 4 degrees Fahrenheit above normal, but that hid large variations. Eastern Montana was 11 degrees above normal; Chicago was 6 degrees above normal. Major Northeast cities recorded temperatures 2 degrees above normal.</p>
        <p>But the weather statisticians could tell without looking at the numbers. "I didn't put on my long underwear this year," said Dr. David R. Rodenhuis, director of the National Weather Service's climate analysis center in Camp Springs, Md., near Washington.</p>
        <p>Some public officials and people worried about the environment fear that rather than just talking about the weather, people are doing something to it, releasing pollutants that are changing the global climate. But scientists remain skeptical that a single North American winter, or even the string of warm years since the late 1980's, is evidence of a long-term global trend.</p>
        <p>Still, said Dr. John W. Firor, a specialist in the greenhouse effect at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., "their resolution to be skeptical" had been weakened."</p>
        <p>As if to demonstrate the variability of nature, the last full day of winter produced snow across a broad band of the Northeast, in some cases the only major snowfall of the season. In fact, the last few days of winter came with a blast of cold air, a phenomenon that Natural Gas Intelligence, a weekly newsletter, called "Indian Winter." It said the weather arrived "as if to tease producers about what might have been." Gas is the largest winter heating fuel, and this was the second year in a row of low gas use.</p>
        <p>"We had a normal winter about three years ago," C. J. Silas, president of Phillips Petroleum, said with a nostalgic glow, referring to an extended cold stretch in December 1989. "It was cold for three weeks. We used to have a month or two of that."</p>
        <p>Mr. Silas, who is chairman of the oil and gas industry's main trade association, the American Petroleum Institute, said his industry did not know what was going on. "We haven't found a consultant to explain it," he said. "We could go to church, maybe, and talk to them."</p>
        <p>In Glasgow, Mont., where it was 11 degrees warmer than normal, there were few regrets. "It's been a beautiful winter," said Nancy Runningen, the office manager in the city water department. "Right now there is no snow, my tulips are up and sticking their noses out, and I've seen a few robins." Need for Rain</p>
        <p>She recalled one winter when the temperature stayed below zero for 78 straight days; this year, the temperature climbed above zero almost every day, she said. But the temperature was not the most important oddity of this year, she said. Local farmers and ranchers will miss the moisture if it does not rain soon, she said. Along with Montana, Idaho, Oregon and Wyoming experienced one of the five driest winters in the last 97 years.</p>
        <p>Around the United States, the only areas where temperatures were not above normal were parts of western Maine, the central Rockies and northern and western Alaska, according to the climate analysis center.</p>
        <p>The Government figures, for the sake of simplicity, count winter as running from Dec. 1 until the end of February, although astronomically winter runs from late December through late March, when the sun crosses the Equator in the vernal equinox.</p>
        <p>While North America was warm again, the North Atlantic was colder, and so was North Africa. Jerusalem had more than a foot of snow, and Cyprus had its first snow in 40 years. Athens, Beirut and Shanghai, where it rarely snows, all had snow this winter.</p>
        <p>Siberia and Eastern Europe were also warmer than normal, according to meteorologists.</p>
        <p>A short-term explanation of the weather may be the existence this year of El Nino, a current in the Pacific Ocean that flows toward South America, and is generally correlated with warmer weather in the midwestern United States.</p>
        <p>Drawing a global picture is difficult, said Dr. Firor, and generalizing from the experience here is risky. "The U.S. is in the neighborhood of 6 percent of the globe," he said. "We don't amount to a hill of beans in the grand average." Another problem is that while temperature in this country is recorded on 10,000 thermometers, the South Atlantic, which is an area almost as large, has 2. "We've got a real problem with the data set," he said.</p>
        <p>"I am a firm believer that the world is in deep trouble," he said. "We are going to have a climate change that is too rapid for easy adaptation." But the data are not adequate to support that, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rodenhuis said that the calendar year 1991 was the second-warmest year on record, considering air temperature over land around the world. The warmest was 1990. Globally, he said, 7 of the past 10 calendar years were warmer than average, which he said was not proof of global warming, "but part of the growing evidence."</p>
        <p>Daniel H. Graf, a meteorologist at the Weather Communications Group at Penn State University, said: "The major climate events are cast in terms of tens of thousands of years. We have a record of 97 years that we work with here in the U.S. "You would figure that every 100 years you would have an unusual group of years. It's hard to say if that's really something bizarre. If you were to have 1,000 years of records, you'd see a lot of strange things."</p>
        <p>Is it global climate change? "We don't have proof," he said. "We have some concerns."</p>
        <p>Though the causes of the recent warm winters in this country may be in doubt, there is little doubt about the effects on energy suppliers. Warm winters meant lower heating bills for almost everyone. Nationally, the demand for heat was down about 10 percent this heating season compared with normal demand, according to Weather Service statistics. On the West Coast, it was nearly 14 percent lower than normal. The south Atlantic area was 11.5 percent warmer than usual and the mid-Atlantic region was 10 percent warmer.</p>
        <p>This is of most importance to gas producers, because gas heats more than half the nation's homes. Electricity has the second-largest share, followed by oil, but oil companies say that because most oil is used in transportation, mild winters do not have a major effect on oil prices. But gas prices are at their lowest in 10 years.</p>
        <p>The gas industry has numerous problems, said Theodore Eck, an economist at Amoco, which holds extensive gas properties, and warm weather is simply adding to the problems. But, he vowed, "We will have winter, one of these years."</p>
        <p>Another gas expert, Robert A. Hefner 3d of the GHK Company, of Oklahoma City, a gas producer, said: "Nature is fickle. You'll have some good ones and some bad ones." But the experience of the last few years, he said, was that "we can't live for the next cold winter." Gas companies will have to cut overhead to survive, he said, and to seek regulatory changes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
