<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spy Data Now Open For Studies Of Climate</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ESPIONAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D91638F930A15755C0A964958260" item-length="1746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spy Data Now Open For Studies Of Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCIENTISTS in search of clues to environmental change are beginning to examine the reconnaissance treasures of the cold war, gathered by spy satellites, jets, ships and submarines at a cost of hundreds of billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The main focus is archives of secret reconnaissance data compiled during the cold war that promise to shed light on such environmental trends as global warming. But the way has also been cleared, at least in principle, for scientists to redirect some of the nation's reconnaissance gear to collect new data of purely ecological interest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCIENTISTS in search of clues to environmental change are beginning to examine the reconnaissance treasures of the cold war, gathered by spy satellites, jets, ships and submarines at a cost of hundreds of billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>The main focus is archives of secret reconnaissance data compiled during the cold war that promise to shed light on such environmental trends as global warming. But the way has also been cleared, at least in principle, for scientists to redirect some of the nation's reconnaissance gear to collect new data of purely ecological interest.</p>
        <p>The push for scientific access to this secretive realm began some two years ago in Congress, with Senator Al Gore gaining a preliminary release of data. Momentum built slowly in private groups like the Council on Foreign Relations and recently gathered speed in the Bush Administration as criticism of its environmental record mounted.</p>
        <p>On May 28, President Bush, a former Director of Central Intelligence with a special interest in spy satellites, signed a directive that cleared the way for environmentalists to use the nation's spy gear and records. Already, three teams of scientists and intelligence officials are being formed to explore this new frontier.</p>
        <p>Civilian scientists over the years have lofted a few specialized satellites for monitoring the environment and are planning to launch more. But the nation's flotilla of spy satellites is already quite large and its archives relatively old, promising nuggets of historical data unavailable by other means.</p>
        <p>Critics say the nation's spies, in cooperating with ecologists, are simply trying to perpetuate cold war budgets at a time when espionage should be in decline. But many scientists see the new partnership as potentially rewarding.</p>
        <p>Dr. Allen M. Solomon, an ecologist at Michigan Technological University who helped stir interest in the exploration, said: "There's a possibility we'll come up with something really fantastic; for example, a photographic record of North Atlantic ice formation over 50 years." But he cautioned that little of major importance might be discovered, adding that the only way to find out was to search.</p>
        <p>Dr. Daniel Hillel, an ecologist at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, said the hunt had great potential.</p>
        <p>"The science community doesn't have these kinds of resources," he said. "I think there's considerable potential for substantial information that would help in monitoring the global environment." Experts say information from these kinds of intelligence "platforms," as they are known in military parlance, could aid the study of environmental change:</p>
        <p>Satellites.  Orbiting craft like the KH-11 have powerful telescopes and cameras that, among other things, have photographed missile silos in the former Soviet Union season after season. It may be possible to extract measurements of snowfall from these data for clues to changes in planetary temperatures. A different class of spy satellites uses radar to peer through clouds, darkness and foliage, possibly helping ecologists gain new insights into the fate of the world's forests.</p>
        <p>Aircraft.  Spy planes not only take photographs but also air measurements to track various types of military activity around the world. These records might tell about levels of methane and carbon dioxide, which have been implicated in global warming, and about levels of chlorofluorocarbons, which damage the earth's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Ships.  An armada of Navy vessels sails the world's oceans to track changes in currents, temperatures, salinity and chemistry, in part to aid the hide-and-seek game of submarine warfare. These records might yield insights about ocean pollution and global climate change.</p>
        <p>Submarines.  These have measured, among other things, the thickness of the Arctic ice cap to find areas for safe submarine passage and to determine whether and where missiles could be fired in time of war. These measurements, taken over decades, could reveal changes in ice thickness caused by temperature shifts.</p>
        <p>The United States has always tried to keep its spy operations, particularly the power of cameras and sensors, secret so military rivals are ignorant of American surveillance abilities. The availability of such information might enable a knowledgeable opponent to evade attempts at espionage. Difficult Balancing Act</p>
        <p>Experts agree that a major challenge will be to balance this need for secrecy with the scientific requirement for data that are reliable and specific. Dr. Hillel warned that it might take years to work out a reliable bureaucratic mechanism to meet both goals. But other experts noted that positive steps in this direction had already taken place.</p>
        <p>Beginning in early 1990, Mr. Gore, a Tennessee Democrat who heads the Senate space subcommittee, pioneered a release of secret data from the Navy. He had read that environmental scientists were unable to tap Navy data on polar ice thickness and sought to bring the two sides together.</p>
        <p>In March 1990, at a meeting on Capitol Hill, civilian scientists and Navy officials discussed ice findings by the nation's fleet of nuclear submarines. Later the Navy released reams of formerly secret data.</p>
        <p>"It was very worthwhile," said Dr. Kenneth Hunkins, an Arctic scientist at the Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory of Columbia University who was a member of the civilian team. He said the researchers were now seeking financing so they could analyze and publish the ice data.</p>
        <p>Inspired by that success, Senator Sam Nunn, chairman of the Senate Armed Services Committee, in June 1990 proposed using the nation's spy technology to address ecological problems, which he called "a growing national security threat." He was joined in the plan by Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>The two men and their colleagues succeeded in having more than $200 million in the Defense Department budget earmarked for what they named the Strategic Environmental Research and Development Program. The Pentagon, despite some study of the issue, has spent little money and released no environmental data so far.</p>
        <p>Eager for action, Mr. Gore wrote to Robert M. Gates, Director of Central Intelligence, early this year to propose that ecologists be given access to reconnaissance archives. Mr. Gates agreed. Panel to Study Issue</p>
        <p>A special group of outside scientists and officials of the Central Intelligence Agency is now being set up to determine what secret information is most relevant to ecological research and how it can be made available.</p>
        <p>"The objective is to cooperate with the environmental community and at the same time to protect intelligence sources and methods," said a spokesman for the Central Intelligence Agency, who insisted on anonymity.</p>
        <p>The push on Capitol Hill led to parallel efforts by private groups, most notably the Council on Foreign Relations. Last year it sponsored a private discussion by spies and scientists on ecological reconnaissance that was led by Bobby R. Inman, a former C.I.A. deputy director. This April an expanded session was headed by William H. Webster, who last year resigned as Director of Central Intelligence.</p>
        <p>"There was mutual interest -- even excitement -- about using classified data to broaden scientific analysis," Alton Frye, vice president of the council, wrote of the meetings in an article on May 3 on the op-ed page of The Washington Post.</p>
        <p>The payoff for years of lobbying came last month when Mr. Bush signed a directive ordering all the Government's space-based gear, both military and civilian, to be evaluated with the aim of improving "our ability to detect and document changes in the global climate system."</p>
        <p>The unclassified directive, made public June 5, says the Defense Department and the Central Intelligence Agency will "seek to make appropriate technology and data from those programs available." A White House official, speaking on the condition of anonymity, said the directive was mainly aimed at spy satellites and their records.</p>
        <p>In explaining the directive's origin, the official said the Administration's teams had concluded that "heretofore classified assets" might aid ecological research, "the winds of change being what they are." The existence of the directive was first reported in Space News, a trade publication. View Through 'Soda Straw'</p>
        <p>For more than a year, select scientists have quietly debated how reconnaissance could aid ecological research. One clear limit of spy satellites is their narrow field of view, which has often been likened to seeing the world through a soda straw. In contrast, satellites built to monitor the environment tend to have broader horizons.</p>
        <p>One solution, said a former C.I.A. analyst, would be to sample a wide region periodically. "It's like having thermometers scattered throughout the forest," he said.</p>
        <p>On the plus side, orbiting spy craft have unusual power. Radar satellites can see through clouds and all kinds of obstructions, in theory giving ecologists a rich harvest of new data. In 1981 an experimental radar aboard a space shuttle unexpectedly penetrated up to 16 feet into the dry sands of the Sahara, revealing traces of ancient sub-Saharan rivers that had carved out valleys as broad as those of the present Nile.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ferris Webster, an oceanographer at the University of Delaware who is chairman of the National Academy of Sciences' committee on geophysical and environmental data, said a major problem in predicting the usefulness of reconnaissance information was that scientists have been in the dark about what was available. Skepticism on Achieving Goal</p>
        <p>"Even the catalogues are classified," he noted. And while applauding the recent openings, Dr. Webster said the spy data might prove to be more fool's gold than a treasure.</p>
        <p>"It can't help but be in our interest to open up whatever data sets are available," he said. "But I'm skeptical we'll find anything revolutionary. Civilian files tend to be very good."</p>
        <p>John E. Pike, head of space policy for the Federation of American Scientists, a private group in Washington, estimated that over the decades the nation had spent $125 billion on its spy satellite operations and said that it made sense to examine the data closely.</p>
        <p>"If you've invested $125 billion, and can get a billion dollars worth of environmental data for a small additional investment, then it's certainly worth doing," Mr. Pike said. "There's so much stuff there that you're bound to find something useful."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
