<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Staying Cool and Saving the Ozone</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="537987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ICC TECHNOLOGIES INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DE1031F931A15755C0A964958260" item-length="1373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Staying Cool and Saving the Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Using a new device that sucks nearly all water vapor out of the air, a small air-conditioning company here has built a cooling system that uses ordinary water in place of ozone-destroying chemicals -- and provides cooling for a small fraction of the energy of conventional systems.</p>
        <p>The system is at an early stage of development. But its potential is enormous. If it succeeds, a radically different approach to cooling could emerge that would reduce the demand for electricity. That, in turn, would reduce the use of fuels by utilities that supply electricity. Burning less fuel would reduce the emission of the pollutants that form acid rain and smog, and of carbon dioxide, which is believed to cause global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Using a new device that sucks nearly all water vapor out of the air, a small air-conditioning company here has built a cooling system that uses ordinary water in place of ozone-destroying chemicals -- and provides cooling for a small fraction of the energy of conventional systems.</p>
        <p>The system is at an early stage of development. But its potential is enormous. If it succeeds, a radically different approach to cooling could emerge that would reduce the demand for electricity. That, in turn, would reduce the use of fuels by utilities that supply electricity. Burning less fuel would reduce the emission of the pollutants that form acid rain and smog, and of carbon dioxide, which is believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>Saving the energy used in air-conditioning is also economically important to many utilities, because summer is the season of peak demand for electricity. By lowering that peak, utilities would need fewer generating stations.</p>
        <p>The technology is based on the same principle that the human body uses to keep cool: evaporation. As water turns from a liquid into a vapor -- evaporating, in other words -- it absorbs energy, in effect cooling everything around it. The system uses a new type of desiccant, or drying agent, which makes air so arid that large amounts of water can be put back at the chilling stage without making the air uncomfortably humid.</p>
        <p>The company, ICC Technologies, which is based here, has been selling devices using an older type of desiccant for the last three years. These systems, intended as supplements to conventional air-conditioners, deliver very dry air at moderate temperatures.</p>
        <p>Now, using a new desiccant recently developed by the Englehard Corporation of Iselin, N.J., ICC has built a working model of an air-conditioner that could cool anything from a house to a hotel or small office building. The model has no compressor, the part in a conventional air-conditioner that consumes most of the electricity. Nor does the working model use ozone-destroying chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's.</p>
        <p>Desiccants are familiar to consumers as small white packets that come in cartons with new cameras and TV sets, usually labeled "do not eat." The new desiccant, described as a crystalline material with tiny holes that absorb gaseous water molecules, is like those packets, only far more effective, ounce for ounce. It is made of silica and alumina, Englehard said.</p>
        <p>ICC's efforts are not the first attempt at a cooling system centered on the ability to dry out air. "The patents are 30 years old," said P. Richard Heimann, a researcher at ICC. "People have tried, but they have been limited by the underlying materials."</p>
        <p>Englehard's new desiccant represents the long-awaited breakthrough, he said. The compound has a special crystalline structure that acts as a molecular sieve, straining water molecules out of the air.</p>
        <p>The system relies in part on the scientific truth of the old saw: It's not the heat, it's the humidity.</p>
        <p>"The primary purpose of cooling air is humidity control," said Dean E. Lewis, senior director of education and program development at the Refrigeration Service Engineers Society in Des Plaines, Ill. Taking moisture out of air means taking energy out of it, he said, making it feel cooler and more comfortable; drier air feels cooler than moist air at the same thermometer reading.</p>
        <p>Conventional air-conditioners tend to deliver clammy air, because as they lower the temperature, the relative humidity rises to near 100 percent. In addition, experts say, moist air in air-conditioning ducts is a breeding ground for bacteria. How It Works</p>
        <p>Desiccant cooling works like this: First, air is passed through a chemical that absorbs 90 percent of the moisture in it. That leaves the air very dry. But it also makes the air hotter, because as the desiccant removes the water vapor from the air and converts it to liquid, the process gives off heat -- precisely the opposite of evaporation, which absorbs heat as water goes from liquid to vapor.</p>
        <p>The hot, dry air is run over a rotating metal wheel, which has been cooled by damp air. Next, the air, still dry but now reasonably cool, is put in another chamber where a small amount of water is added. As that water evaporates at a subsequent stage, it lowers the temperature further.</p>
        <p>A working model of the system took air with a temperature of 80 degrees and about 50 percent relative humidity, and cooled it to 60 degrees with about 50 percent relative humidity. Energy Requirements</p>
        <p>Some energy is consumed by the fans that move the air, and by small motors that turn the metal heat-exchanger wheel and the wheel holding the desiccant.</p>
        <p>In addition, one side of the desiccant wheel, the side away from the air being cooled, is heated to about 180 degrees, which makes the water drip back out of the desiccant. That heat can be produced by burning natural gas, or can be drawn from the waste heat of a refrigerator or freezer, or even a conventional air-conditioner. If a conventional air conditioner is kept on the job, of course, then the system is not free of CFC's.</p>
        <p>The ICC machine spits a spray of hotter, wetter air out the back, just as a conventional air-conditioner dumps heated air outside the room or building being cooled. Looking for Alternatives</p>
        <p>At a time when the use of CFC's is being phased out in anticipation of a ban in the United States by the end of the decade, ICC's work may be of wide interest.</p>
        <p>"The whole air-conditioning industry is looking at alternatives to CFC's," said Barry M. Cohen, director of the space conditioning department at Tecogen, a Waltham, Mass., company that sells a variety of heating, cooling and electricity-producing products.</p>
        <p>Desiccant cooling is not a new idea, Mr. Cohen said, but it is not yet commercially viable as a stand-alone sytem in most parts of the country. Earlier Supermarket Versions</p>
        <p>ICC, whose stock is traded overthe counter, had sales of less than $3 million last year.</p>
        <p>It has been selling desiccant systems for three years, mostly to supermarkets, which find that no matter how hard they run their conventional air-conditioners, too much moisture remains in the air. That moisture eventually forms ice crystals in the freezer cases, which, unchecked, can make a frozen chicken look like a pterodactyl in a glacier.</p>
        <p>Many of the supermarket installations have been subsidized by electric utilities, because the systems enable grocers to air-condition stores with far less use of electricity. The dessicant systems also provide a summer market for natural gas, helping balance demand around the year.</p>
        <p>But that technology has always had its limits, and on hot days must be supplemented by an old-fashioned air-conditioner with a type of CFC known by the trade name Freon. 'We're Very Optimistic'</p>
        <p>One utility that has already subsidized the installation of an ICC system is the Consolidated Edison Company of New York. Ronald P. Guilbeault, administrator of a subsidy program at Con Ed, said the system, installed in a supermarket in Ossining, N.Y., had helped cut the workload of the conventional system.</p>
        <p>"We're very optimistic about supporting desiccant technology," he said. A desiccant air-conditioner that operated without a conventional backup "would be a great idea," he said, because it could run on natural gas, saving electricity when electricity is most in demand. That would save money for the customer who installed it, and reduce the need to build new electric generating stations. "Everybody would be winning in that case," he said.</p>
        <p>At the Philadelphia Electric Company, Joseph F. Martorano 3d, an engineer who is head of the business- development division, said a desiccant-based cooling system would be "a great solution for residential and medium-sized commercial cooling." The company is interested in any technology that would cut the energy required for cooling, he said.</p>
        <p>Neither utility has seen the new desiccant work, however.</p>
        <p>But the United Technologies Corporation, the world's largest producer of heating, ventilation and air-conditioning systems, has seen technical reports, a company spokesman said, and the company's chairman, Karl J. Krapek, wants to see how it works.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
