<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Leaves Rio With Shots At Foreign and U.S. Critics</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536018"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE EARTH SUMMIT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB123EF937A25755C0A964958260" item-length="668" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Leaves Rio With Shots At Foreign and U.S. Critics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush left the Earth Summit today firing parting shots at his many critics, saying Americans are "the leaders, not the followers," on environmental issues and will be "pre-eminent" in carrying out accords signed here.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news conference at his seafront hotel, Mr. Bush dismissed suggestions that his appearance here had not gone well and reserved some of his criticism for domestic rather than global issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush left the Earth Summit today firing parting shots at his many critics, saying Americans are "the leaders, not the followers," on environmental issues and will be "pre-eminent" in carrying out accords signed here.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news conference at his seafront hotel, Mr. Bush dismissed suggestions that his appearance here had not gone well and reserved some of his criticism for domestic rather than global issues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, who agreed to sign only a watered-down version of the summit treaty to reduce the threat of global warming, proposed on Friday that the nations gather on Jan. 1 to report specific plans to reduce emissions of pollutants that trap heat in the Earth's atmosphere. The treaty sets a deadline of the end of the century for meeting emission control goals.</p>
        <p>At the news conference, Mr. Bush rejected the notion that his call for an early start on the global warming issue was not welcomed by world leaders.</p>
        <p>"The developed nations want to meet the commitments they've signed up for, so I've not found that it wasn't well received at all," Mr. Bush said. "In fact, Bill Reilly told me it was well received, and we will be there with specific plans." Support for Meeting Seen</p>
        <p>Administration officials said today that some other leaders had told Mr. Bush and William K. Reilly, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, that the President's plans for the meeting had merit.</p>
        <p>But they said they knew of no specific commitments by any nations to attend such a meeting. Nor could they report any assurances yet that other developed nations will support the other major initiative Mr. Bush brought to Rio, a proposal to double spending to conserve and restore the world's dwindling forests.</p>
        <p>The President ended the 45-minute news conference with an unusually bristling denunciation of House Democrats. Several House committees are separately investigating Mr. Bush's conduct of American policy toward Iraq and rumors, never proved, that Mr. Bush and Ronald Reagan worked secretly during their 1980 Presidential campaign to delay the release of Americans held hostage in Iran.</p>
        <p>The President characterized the inquiries into allegations that his Administration helped build Saddam Hussein into a global menace as "purely political" and "recklessly" conducted. Iran Inquiry Criticized</p>
        <p>He was even more vehement about the Iran inquiry, which was touched off by a book that says he secretly flew to Paris in 1980 in an effort to keep American hostages from being released before the Presidential election.</p>
        <p>"You're spending millions of the taxpayers' dollars trying to prove on the basis of a stupid book that I was there," he said. "Would you please certify to the American people whether this now-President and then-candidate was in Paris?"</p>
        <p>"Why the Congress keeps spending the taxpayers' monies on these witchhunts, I do not know." he continued. "And I'm a little sick of it, but there's not a heck of a lot I can do about it except to express a continual and somewhat mounting frustration as I see now another attack."</p>
        <p>At another point, Mr. Bush allowed that observers "may be right" when they say they detect some anxiety on his part over the course of his re-election effort.</p>
        <p>"I mean, this has been a tough, weird political year at home," he said. Distance From Quayle</p>
        <p>In that vein, the President also sought today to distance himself from widely publicized remarks about the election made on Friday by Vice President Dan Quayle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle sharply attacked Mr. Bush's popular but undeclared rival for the Presidency, Ross Perot. The Vice President called Mr. Perot "a temperamental tycoon who has contempt for the Constitution," and said voters would be wiser to elect a Democrat as President than to support Mr. Perot's independent candidacy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said he was "very unenthusiastic" about Mr. Quayle's proposal.</p>
        <p>"I feel they ought to elect a Republican President and a Republican Congress," the President said.  THE EARTH SUMMIT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
