<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>143 Lands Adopt Treaty To Cut Emission of Gases</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="527424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920510T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D6173EF933A25756C0A964958260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>143 Lands Adopt Treaty To Cut Emission of Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, May 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representatives of 143 countries adopted a treaty today that commits the nations of the world to limit emissions of carbon dioxide, methane and other heat-trapping gases that scientists fear could cause a catastrophic global warming in the next century.</p>
        <p>The treaty, its key provisions hammered out in intensive talks over the last few days, is to be signed early next month at the Earth Summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representatives of 143 countries adopted a treaty today that commits the nations of the world to limit emissions of carbon dioxide, methane and other heat-trapping gases that scientists fear could cause a catastrophic global warming in the next century.</p>
        <p>The treaty, its key provisions hammered out in intensive talks over the last few days, is to be signed early next month at the Earth Summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
        <p>Its long-term objective is to stabilize atmospheric concentrations of the greenhouse gases soon enough to prevent dangerous disruption of the earth's climate and enable ecosystems to adapt naturally to any climate change. This stabilization could be achieved only by substantially reducing present emission levels.</p>
        <p>The treaty calls for industrial nations, until now the biggest polluters, to aim at capping emissions at 1990 levels. But no timetable for achieving this has been set. Instead, the industrial nations would simply recognize that returning to "earlier levels" of emissions by the end of this decade would advance the treaty's overall objective. Not a One-Shot Deal</p>
        <p>But it does require that these countries report periodically to all the treaty signers on their efforts to limit emissions. And in what many said would be the true significance of the pact, machinery would be set up to constantly assess the danger of climate change and to take further action, if necessary.</p>
        <p>This approach has been successfully used in the case of chemicals that weaken the earth's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>"It all adds up to a significant achievement," said Richard E. Benedick, a former United States diplomat who negotiated the ozone treaty and an amendment to it. "It is a very important first step in a process that is going to take us out of fossil fuels," said Mr. Benedick, who is now a senior fellow at the World Wildlife Fund.</p>
        <p>The burning of fossil fuels like coal, oil and natural gas produces carbon dioxide, the most significant of the greenhouse gases. Scientific advisers for these talks say the average global temperature will rise 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit by some time in the next century if the greenhouse gases continue to build at current rates.</p>
        <p>The proposed treaty is a compromise, and few negotiators said they were fully satisfied. Many environmentalists characterized it as disappointing and assailed its failure to establish clear targets and timetables on emissions, as the European Community advocated and the United States resisted.</p>
        <p>Still, said David Doniger of the Natural Resources Defense Council, "if you cut through to the heart of the text, it does in effect establish an international benchmark against which U.S. action will be judged."</p>
        <p>The proposed treaty also requires third world countries to develop plans to control their emissions, which are expected to grow substantially. And it commits the industrial nations to give them financial help to do this.</p>
        <p>The United States, which produces more than 20 percent of carbon-dioxide emissions, has argued that energy-efficiency actions to which it is already committed will bring it close to limiting emissions in the year 2000 at 1990 levels. But it said strict adherence to timetables might harm its economy.</p>
        <p>The treaty's provisions on emissions were described as "a measured approach" and a "reasonable response to the current state of scientific knowledge" by William K. Reilly, administrator of the United States Environmental Protection Agency, who fought within the Bush Administration for a strong treaty.</p>
        <p>The one that emerged, according to Mr. Reilly, "says, 'Do what you prudently can to restrain greenhouse gas emissions while pursuing other social and economic goals.'(TM)"</p>
        <p>The treaty does not specify how much aid the industrial nations would give to the less-developed ones. The aid would be channeled, as an interim measure, through the Global Environmental Facility recently established by the United Nations Development Program, the United Nations Environment Program and the World Bank.</p>
        <p>Many developing countries have resisted the idea of using the fund as the financial mechanism for the treaty for fear that industrialized countries would dominate the administration of the fund. The treaty calls for changes in the administration of the fund to reflect these concerns.</p>
        <p>The negotiators were supposed to have completed their work sooner, but an attempt by Saudi Arabia to introduce a series of amendments derailed the effort temporarily. Because the Saudi economy is based on the sale of oil, many delegates interpreted the Saudis' actions as an attempt to scuttle the treaty.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
