<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teflon-Like Material Could Prevent Graffiti</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAFFITI</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLUORINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAINTS AND PAINTING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DOW CHEMICAL CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graffiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB163FF934A35757C0A964958260" item-length="446" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teflon-Like Material Could Prevent Graffiti</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chemists reported today that there was new hope for winning the battle against graffiti that have proliferated on walls around the world since the invention of spray paints and marking pens.</p>
        <p>Though not ready for marketing, its developers say, the new anti-graffiti agent promises to do to spray-can marks what antibiotics did to streptococci.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chemists reported today that there was new hope for winning the battle against graffiti that have proliferated on walls around the world since the invention of spray paints and marking pens.</p>
        <p>Though not ready for marketing, its developers say, the new anti-graffiti agent promises to do to spray-can marks what antibiotics did to streptococci.</p>
        <p>The scientist chiefly responsible for the invention, Dr. Donald L. Schmidt of the Dow Chemical Company, reported at the annual meeting of the American Chemical Society that nothing sticks to the new material.</p>
        <p>Unnamed as yet, the protective coating consists of very large molecules built up from fluoroalkyl molecular components based mainly on carbon and fluorine atoms. The material is a distant cousin of Teflon but has very different properties.</p>
        <p>The licensing manager of the Dow Company, George D. Mignin, said his company did not plan to manufacture products based on the invention but expected to license other companies to do so.</p>
        <p>Dr. Schmidt said that some details of formulating the compound for use in marketable products remained to be worked out, but that the water-based material was easy to spray or brush on most surfaces. Once the coating dries, he said, the molecules of which it is made form chemical bonds with each other and with the surface they coat to form a transparent, colorless, unwettable coating. Nothing Gets It Wet</p>
        <p>"Water won't wet it, or acetone, or methyl ethyl ketone, or anything else we've tried," Dr. Schmidt said. Used to coat cars, the anti-stick compound prevents grime, dead insects and everything else from adhering to the surface.</p>
        <p>A major advantage the new material has over Teflon, he said, is its ease of application. Teflon must be applied using special solvents, and it has to be cured at relatively high temperatures.</p>
        <p>Teflon has special lubricating and heat-resistant qualities, however, that the new anti-stick coating does not share. Teflon partly owes its non-sticking slipperiness, Dr. Schmidt explained, to its ability to shed its outer layers of molecules. When a charred egg is brushed loose from a Teflon-coated frying pan, it pulls along the loose upper layer of molecules from the Teflon itself. By contrast, the new coating resists sticking by preventing any liquid from wetting it.</p>
        <p>Tests have proved the new coating impervious to all kinds of dirt, acid rain, bird droppings and solvents, Dr. Schmidt said. In a lecture, he demonstrated that "permanent" marking pens leave no marks at all on wallpaper coated with the new substance.</p>
        <p>"The day may come when you could coat New York City with the stuff," Dr. Schmidt said. "Wouldn't that be something?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
