<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vatican Seeks a Voice in Earth Summit Resolutions on Population</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="531921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POPULATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMIT CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COWELL, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Population</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D71739F93BA15756C0A964958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vatican Seeks a Voice in Earth Summit Resolutions on Population</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COWELL, ALAN</byline>
      <dateline>ROME, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In preparation for next month's Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro, Vatican diplomats have begun a campaign to try to insure that the gathering's conclusions on the issue of runaway population growth are not in conflict with Roman Catholic teaching on birth control.</p>
        <p>To pursue its cause, the Vatican has insisted on changes in the wording of some documents on demographic issues to be put before the summit, which is to be attended by the leaders of nearly 100 countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In preparation for next month's Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro, Vatican diplomats have begun a campaign to try to insure that the gathering's conclusions on the issue of runaway population growth are not in conflict with Roman Catholic teaching on birth control.</p>
        <p>To pursue its cause, the Vatican has insisted on changes in the wording of some documents on demographic issues to be put before the summit, which is to be attended by the leaders of nearly 100 countries.</p>
        <p>It has circulated a confidential document to embassies here, setting out positions that challenge the United States and other Western countries on such issues as technology transfer between industrial and developing nations and excluding war from a list of hazards to the environment, Vatican officials said.</p>
        <p>While the summit's resolutions will not be binding on participants, the Vatican's position draws on a moral authority among the world's estimated 980 million baptized Roman Catholics and thus carries a particular weight in the discussions.  'Family Planning' Controversy</p>
        <p>The issue that has caused most controversy relates to changes in a summit document on demographic trends. At preparatory negotiations in New York last month, officials said, Vatican diplomats insisted on changing the wording in references to "family planning" to the formulation: "the responsible planning of family size in keeping with fundamental dignity and personally held values and taking into account ethical and cultural considerations."</p>
        <p>The more cumbersome wording reflects the Roman Catholic Church's prohibition on all forms of artificial birth control. Vatican officials, speaking on condition that they not be identified, said the changes also reflected a broader concern within the church for individual human and religious rights in the face of governmental population control programs that either place limits on family size, as in China, or offer incentives for sterilization, as in Brazil.</p>
        <p>Some development experts argue that expanding third-world populations are the principal cause for the growing poverty of those regions.</p>
        <p>But Msgr. Diarmuid Martin, who is part of the Vatican's 10-member delegation to the Earth Summit, said in a separate interview that the Vatican felt that "attributing the responsibility for poverty exlcusively to population growth is a little bit naive."  Diplomats Given a Memo</p>
        <p>Diplomats accredited to the Holy See said they had received a memorandum from the Vatican that said in part: "The relationship of development and the environment to population growth is complex and often tenuous. Population growth of and by itself is seldom the primary cause of environmental problems.</p>
        <p>"The Holy See is especially concerned about strategies that make population decline the primary factor in overcoming ecological problems. Programs for reducing population directed and financed by the developed nations of the North easily become a substitute for justice and development in the developing nations of the South," the memo was quoted as saying.</p>
        <p>When word of the changes in the summit documents first leaked out, the revisions prompted accusations from some feminists and members of Protestant Christian churches that the Vatican was trying to remove the entire issue of population control from the summit's agenda.  A Papal Response</p>
        <p>But that provoked an angry response from Joaquin Navarro Valls, Pope John Paul II's spokesman.</p>
        <p>"The Holy See has never tried to place obstacles to the negotiating process on any point," he said. "If instead of 'family planning' the documents say 'responsible planning of family size,' who can honestly object to the choice of couples being responsible?</p>
        <p>"If it is proposed that demographic choices be based on respect for social, cultural and religious traditions, who can oppose that except those who wish to impose alien politics?" the papal spokesman asked. "Would that not be neocolonialism?"</p>
        <p>In its broader approach to the summit, the Vatican is staking out positions that are at odds with those of Western governments. For example, diplomats here said, the European Community has registered reservations about the notion of transferring technology from the industrialized to the developing worlds while, in one conference discussion, the United States sought to drop the word "war" from a list of ecological disasters that includes deforestation and desertification.  Ecology and Morality</p>
        <p>In the memorandum circulated to diplomats in recent days, however, the Roman Catholic Church depicts the world's ecological crisis as a "moral crisis," diplomats said.</p>
        <p>"The goods of the earth -- including those produced by human activity -- are for the benefit of all," the diplomats quoted the Vatican document as saying. "All peoples and countries have a right to fundamental access to those goods -- natural, spiritual, intellectual and technological -- which are necessary for their internal development."</p>
        <p>The diplomats said the document spoke of "an obligation to insure a just and equitable transfer of appropriate technology" to promote development. It also said that "the damage to the human and natural environment caused by war is an increasingly serious problem."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>European to Boycott Summit</p>
        <p>BRUSSELS, May 27 (AP) -- The European Community's Environment Minister said today that he would boycott the Earth Summit, charging that it will fail to adequately deal with global warming.</p>
        <p>"I have decided not to go to a conference where everything, or virtually everything, has been arranged," said the official, Carlo Ripa de Meana.</p>
        <p>He said the conference would not set sufficiently strict goals to curb carbon dioxide emissions that scientists say could lead to global warming. But all 12 nations of the European Community will send their own national representatives to the Brazilian meeting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ripa de Meana's comments were the latest charges that accords to be signed at the Earth Summit were too weak. On Monday, France said it would not sign a treaty to protect the diversity of animal and plant species, insisting that it should contain a list of species and ecosystems to be guarded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
