<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. at the Earth Summit: Isolated and Challenged</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="535003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SCANDINAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D91338F933A25755C0A964958260" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. at the Earth Summit: Isolated and Challenged</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>RIO DE JANEIRO, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Earth Summit enters its final phase, Europe and Japan are showing increasing independence from the United States on environmental issues, worsening American isolation and creating a diplomatic challenge for Washington.</p>
        <p>President Bush strained relations with industrialized countries and the third world when he rejected detailed targets in a treaty to curb global warming and refused to join a pact to preserve plant and animal life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Earth Summit enters its final phase, Europe and Japan are showing increasing independence from the United States on environmental issues, worsening American isolation and creating a diplomatic challenge for Washington.</p>
        <p>President Bush strained relations with industrialized countries and the third world when he rejected detailed targets in a treaty to curb global warming and refused to join a pact to preserve plant and animal life.</p>
        <p>The traditional northern allies are still trying to build bridges to the increasingly beleaguered American delegation because they realize that without Washington's participation, no agreements made here can be effective. But they are constrained by the fact that they see the problem differently.</p>
        <p>They do not agree with President Bush that the measures should be rejected or modified because they could threaten jobs. Unlike the Administration, they see safeguarding the environment as an unavoidable challenge that will strengthen their industry in the long run, not as a new and sinister threat to their way of life. Forfeited U.S. Leadership</p>
        <p>"What we see emerging in the United States is something like 'ecologism' -- fear of a new Communism hidden behind ecology," Environment Minister Klaus Topfer of Germany told reporters here recently.</p>
        <p>That view may be extreme. But America's lonely position at the Earth Summit does appear to represent a departure from the recent course of post-cold-war diplomacy.</p>
        <p>While the United States has had little difficulty getting its way in other multilateral organizations, like the United Nations Security Council, since the Soviet Union broke up, it has forfeited its leadership role here, and neither Europe nor Japan are able to step in.</p>
        <p>A powerful reason why some of America's closest allies do not share the Administration's apprehension about the economic costs of cleaning up the world is that they expect to benefit from such a commitment. Japan's Reluctant Stance</p>
        <p>Japanese and German industries in particular have led the development of "clean" technologies, and they hope the Earth Summit plan to endorse Agenda 21, a global cleanup proposal, and to give third-world countries money to pay for it will translate into fat orders for their companies.</p>
        <p>"Of course there are short-term costs," said the European Community spokesman, Laurens Jan Brinkhorst, this morning. "But in the end energy efficiency is good for industry, not bad."</p>
        <p>Dr. A. S. Kasenally, Environment Minister of the Indian Ocean island of Mauritius, said, "It's difficult to see how America is protecting jobs by not signing a biodiversity convention that would allow its drug companies to experiment with our natural genetic resources."</p>
        <p>Japan certainly appears to take the meeting more seriously than the United States, fielding a delegation of more than 100 officials compared with 45 American officials. But diplomats say it remains reluctant to give a clear lead that cuts across American interests.</p>
        <p>As the world's largest market, the European Community clearly has potential clout, but it often lacks unity of purpose. Despite economic difficulties caused by unification, Germany is often closer to the neutral Scandinavian countries in its enthusiasm for green causes than Britain, Spain, and Portugal, who shy away from new financial burdens.</p>
        <p>Western diplomats generally see the roots of the present Administration's grudging approach in the political pressure of a Presidential election campaign, an economic recession and a high budget deficit.</p>
        <p>"The United Nations must learn never to hold an international conference during an American election year," says Thomas K. Koh, the respected Singapore diplomat who heads the main negotiating committee.</p>
        <p>The major United States initiative, an offer of $150 million in bilateral aid to save third-world forests, backfired because most countries saw it as an attempt to distract attention from Mr. Bush's unpopular decisions.</p>
        <p>In an effort to change that impression, Britain and Germany want the American offer accepted as a first contribution toward a new world agreement they eventually hope to negotiate on preserving forests.</p>
        <p>The European Community and the Nordic countries also rejected as unnecessarily anti-American a plan suggested by the Netherlands, Switzerland and Austria for a joint statement criticizing the global-warming convention that President Bush weakened and pledging to strengthen it.</p>
        <p>Instead, the European Community adopted a uniform statement setting targets and timetables for reduction of carbon-dioxide emissions to 1990 levels by the end of the century -- a position at odds with that of the United States.</p>
        <p>But the 12 also offered the Bush Administration a face-saving way of signing the convention on biodiversity by agreeing to make a statement setting out their own interpretation of contentious clauses. The White House has shown no interest in going along with it.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Europeans are increasing America's isolation by trying to persuade small island states as well as India, which all face severe flooding if the climate warms, to back their call for tougher commitments on cutting warming gas emissions.</p>
        <p>That sense of isolation may increase further when heads of state and government start addressing the meeting at the end of the week. For President Bush is unlikely to be able to pledge the third world as much help with making its future development environmentally sustainable as his counterparts from Europe and Japan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
