<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: In Dispute; Quayle and Gore Battle Devolves Into a Hand-to-Hand Fight About 4 Issues</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="562946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VICE PRESIDENTS AND VICE PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEBATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABORTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LATIN AMERICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUAYLE, DAN (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D81730F937A25753C1A964958260" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: In Dispute; Quayle and Gore Battle Devolves Into a Hand-to-Hand Fight About 4 Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Vice President Dan Quayle and Senator Al Gore argued across a broad spectrum of issues in the Vice-Presidential debate this evening, they conducted the verbal equivalent of hand-to-hand combat over four specific points.</p>
        <p>The most intense confrontations came on the issues of the environment, arms control, Government programs aiding Central American development and abortion</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Vice President Dan Quayle and Senator Al Gore argued across a broad spectrum of issues in the Vice-Presidential debate this evening, they conducted the verbal equivalent of hand-to-hand combat over four specific points.</p>
        <p>The most intense confrontations came on the issues of the environment, arms control, Government programs aiding Central American development and abortion</p>
        <p>On the environment, The two men clashed over whether the Tennessee Senator had proposed raising $100 billion a year from American taxpayers to help solve global problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle said the proposal was contained in "Earth in the Balance," Mr. Gore's best-selling book on the environment, and asserted it would put an impossible burden on Americans in difficult economic times.</p>
        <p>"It's on page 304 in the book," Mr. Quayle said. "Is he going to disavow what's in his book?" Truth on Both Sides</p>
        <p>"You've got it wrong," Mr. Gore responded. "There is no such proposal. What I have called upon is a cooperative venture with Europe and Asia."</p>
        <p>There are elements of truth in the statements by both men.</p>
        <p>In his book Mr. Gore calls for public works and research projects to deal with environmental problems around the world. Mr. Gore calls the initiative a global Marshall Plan, and says that with its financial resources, the United States should be responsible for organizing the project and paying a large share of its cost.</p>
        <p>On page 304 of "Earth in the Balance" Mr. Gore does not specify how much the United States should contribute, but notes that an effort comparable to the Marshall Plan to rebuild Europe after World War II would mean the expenditure of $100 billion a year. Dispute With Stockdale</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore notes in the book that such levels of spending would be impossible given the country's current economic distress and calls on the other industrialized countries to contribute.</p>
        <p>The scientific validity of Mr. Gore's book also came under attack by James B. Stockdale, Ross Perot's running mate, who said that the Democratic Vice-Presidential candidate had exaggerated the threat from global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stockdale suggested that the danger of global warming was minimized by Dr. Roger Revelle, one of the first scientists to identify the greenhouse effect and Mr. Gore's professor at Harvard in the 1960's. Mr. Gore has said he drew heavily on Dr. Revelle's research in preparing his book.</p>
        <p>Before his death in July 1991 Dr. Revelle said in a paper, "the scientific baseis for a greenhouse warming is too uncertain to justify drastic action at this time."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore said that Dr. Revelle's daughter, Carolyn Revelle Hufbauer, had written an article published in The Washington Post last month that reported her father had not "renounced his belief in global warming" and did not advocate inaction on the issue.</p>
        <p>On arms control, Mr. Gore seemed to take Mr. Quayle by surprise when he contended that the nuclear arms reduction agreement reached in principle by President Bush and President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia in June had collapsed because the Russians were reneging on destroying their most dangerous intercontinental missiles, the 10-warhead SS-18's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that he thought that "President Bush made a very serious misstatement of fact in response to Ross Perot" in Sunday's debate among the candidates for President.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle responded, "The President does have a commitment from Boris Yeltsin to eliminate the SS-18s."</p>
        <p>American officials said this evening that the Russians did not want to renege on getting rid of the SS-18's, but did want to retain some SS-18 silos, which were also supposed to be destroyed. If the Russians were allowed to do that the silos would be used for missiles the Russians are allowed to retain, saving their country money, the American officials said. Jobs and Foreign Aid</p>
        <p>On another issue, Mr. Gore asserted that the Bush Administration had a program subsidizing the export of jobs from the United States by giving financial assistance to companies in Latin America.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that workers at a textile plant in his state were among those who had lost jobs because of the program to promote development in countries paying lower wages. "You have used our tax dollars to subsidize the recruitment of U.S. companies to move overseas and throw Americans out of work," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Quayle denied that there was any such program, saying, "Never have we ever, nor would we, support the idea of someone closing down a factory here and moving overseas."</p>
        <p>The program, as described this evening by Congressional aides and State Department officials, is operated by the United States Agency for International Development. Companies in EL Salvador, Honduras and Guatemala have received money in the program, which is intended to stimulate economic development in Latin America and increase its imports from the United States.</p>
        <p>But critics of the program, including labor union officials and Democrats in Congress have said it encourages companies to shift manufacturing operations from the United States.</p>
        <p>A.I.D. officials defended the program, saying it increased Central American imports from the United States. A spokesman for the agency said, "It is not the policy of A.I.D. to shut down U.S. manufacturing operations and shift them to Central America."</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Gore and Mr. Quayle clashed over abortion and especially over whether Mr. Gore had shifted his position on the issue.</p>
        <p>"Talk about waffling around," Mr. Quayle said, adding that at one time, Mr. Gore, "had a pro-life position."</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said, "That is simply not true."</p>
        <p>An examination of Mr. Gore's record shows that while he may not have been strongly opposed to abortion, his views on the issue have changed markedly. Like Mr. Clinton, he once accepted restrictions on abortion. Now he prefers to emphasize that abortion is a decision that should largely be left to a woman and her doctor.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Clinton, he once accepted restrictions on abortion. Now he prefers to emphasize that abortion is a decision that should largely be left to a woman and her doctor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton aides have acknowledged his "evolution" on the issue, but Mr. Gore has resisted suggestions that he once held different views.</p>
        <p>President Bush, strongly opposed to abortion and endorsed by the leading anti-abortion groups, was years ago a supporter of abortion rights. Mr. Quayle has long been an opponent of abortion rights who in 1983 proposed a constitutional amendment to overturn the 1973 Supreme Court decision legalizing abortion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
