<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For the Environmentalists, Hurdles on the Road to Rio</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="517028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RIO DE JANEIRO (BRAZIL)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil/Rio de Janeiro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF1E3FF934A15750C0A964958260" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For the Environmentalists, Hurdles on the Road to Rio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>BRASILIA, March 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ten weeks before a giant environmental summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro, the conference is clouded by giant woes: a corruption scandal, the replacement of Brazil's environmental leadership, the slow approach of a cholera epidemic, and doubts over whether President Bush will attend.</p>
        <p>Calling Mr. Bush's attendance "decisive," President Fernando Collor de Mello told reporters here today that he telephoned the American leader on Wednesday to urge him "to strongly consider" traveling to Rio for the June conference. So far, 60 heads of state, including leaders of almost all industrialized nations, have confirmed their participation in the summit meeting, officially called the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ten weeks before a giant environmental summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro, the conference is clouded by giant woes: a corruption scandal, the replacement of Brazil's environmental leadership, the slow approach of a cholera epidemic, and doubts over whether President Bush will attend.</p>
        <p>Calling Mr. Bush's attendance "decisive," President Fernando Collor de Mello told reporters here today that he telephoned the American leader on Wednesday to urge him "to strongly consider" traveling to Rio for the June conference. So far, 60 heads of state, including leaders of almost all industrialized nations, have confirmed their participation in the summit meeting, officially called the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development.</p>
        <p>The Brazilian President said he had also asked Mr. Bush to break the impasse in talks in New York over setting goals for the reduction of carbon dioxide gases and for providing pollution-control technology to developing nations. On Wednesday, the European Community's environmental commissioner, Carlo Ripa de Meana, said in Brussels that American intransigence over the two accords threatened to reduce the Rio meeting to an exercise in rhetoric.</p>
        <p>In Rio, more obstacles appeared today on the road toward a smooth preparation of a conference that is expected to draw at least 30,000 people from around the world. 'A Corruption Problem'</p>
        <p>The coordinator of a Government task force organizing the conference resigned on Wednesday in the face of accusations that he violated bidding rules in awarding a multimillion-dollar contract for the renovation of the meeting hall. The official, Luiz Octavio Themudo, denied the accusations, saying he resigned only to avoid compromising the conference's image.</p>
        <p>"The infrastructure preparations are running late, and now we have a corruption problem," said Joao Paulo Capobiancao, superintendent of SOS Mata Atlantica, a private environmental group here.</p>
        <p>Defending the conference organization, Warren H. Lindner, an American environmentalist who is coordinating a parallel fair of private groups in Rio, said today: "The momentum toward Rio is much too great for it to go fundamentally off track. I'm confident that come June, it will all come together."</p>
        <p>Last week, Muslim nations complained that the June 1-12 conference dates coincided with an Islamic festival. Brazilian organizers now say the conference will run from June 3 to 14, but the United Nations has yet to confirm the new dates.</p>
        <p>Today's newspapers also carried a new worry: Rio de Janeiro State's fourth cholera case. The epidemic, which was largely restricted to the Andean nations last year, is slowly moving down Brazil's Atlantic coast and is expected to hit Rio fully by May. There have been 2,751 cases reported this year in Brazil, but doctors have kept the mortality rate low, to fewer than 2 percent of hospitalized cases.</p>
        <p>In a move that apparently disconcerted foreigners more than Brazilians, President Collor on Saturday removed the Secretary for the Environment, Jose Antonio Lutzenberger, and Eduardo Martins, the president of Brazil's environmental agency, Brazil's top two environmental officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lutzenberger had won a large following overseas for impassioned pleas to save the Amazon rain forest and for a world without pollution, but at home the press ridiculed him as "Lutzenboeing," criticizing his frequent travel to the detriment of working on solving environmental problems at home.</p>
        <p>Today, President Collor faulted Mr. Lutzenberger for displaying "managerial inexperience" and a "radicalized vision" of the world. He said that Brazil's host at the conference would be Jose Goldemberg, Brazil's Education Minister and Acting Environmental Secretary. A Plan for the Amazon</p>
        <p>Seeking to regain momentum in environmental affairs here, Maria Teresa Jorge Padua, the new president of the environmental protection agency, announced in an interview today an ambitious Amazon protection plan: expanding the national park system to cover 30 percent of Brazil's Amazon. Ms. Padua, who was sworn in on Tuesday, said national parks, forests and reserves currently cover 6 percent of Brazil's Amazon rain forest.</p>
        <p>Often called the "Mother of Brazil's National Parks," Ms. Padua helped create 15 million acres of park land when she managed the environmental agency's parks department in the 1970's and early 1980's. Widely respected for her managerial skills, Ms. Padua has served for the last six years as president of Brazil's largest conservation group, Funatura.</p>
        <p>An experienced fund raiser, the new agency president said today that she had identified $500 million in foreign financing available for environmental projects in Brazil. The largest amounts are $120 million from the World Bank and $30 million from the Inter-American Development Bank.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
