<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; Clinton's Promise</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="519608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GELB, LESLIE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, JERRY (EDMUND G BROWN JR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D81031F935A35757C0A964958260" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; Clinton's Promise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE H. GELB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GELB, LESLIE H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Yorkers have the power to destroy one of the most promising Presidential candidates in decades. Or they can give Bill Clinton a chance to be heard fully and clearly for the remainder of this campaign.</p>
        <p>More than anyone now on the national scene, the Governor from Arkansas could be what we most need: a Great Experimenter in foreign and domestic policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Yorkers have the power to destroy one of the most promising Presidential candidates in decades. Or they can give Bill Clinton a chance to be heard fully and clearly for the remainder of this campaign.</p>
        <p>More than anyone now on the national scene, the Governor from Arkansas could be what we most need: a Great Experimenter in foreign and domestic policy.</p>
        <p>No one has good answers for the kind of world descending on us, nor for the complexities of health and education in post-industrial societies.</p>
        <p>A leader through this haze and maze must be committed to solutions, as are Democrats, and possessed of a practical skepticism about means, as are Republicans. Such a leader has to be a bleeding-heart conservative, a bold experimenter like Franklin Roosevelt, Harry Truman and John Kennedy.</p>
        <p>To get a sense of these qualities in Mr. Clinton, just compare the world he talked about in his foreign policy speech last week with the worlds of Jerry Brown and George Bush.</p>
        <p>The world sketched, stingily, by Mr. Brown seems to be a very simple place inhabited by destructive environmental Martians -- and little else.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's world seems still peopled by dictators like the Chinese whom he wants to protect and tyrants like President Assad of Syria whom he seeks to befriend. It is an old, crumbling chessboard where kings play with each other and are indifferent to their subjects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton does not pretend to understand or describe the world of the 21st century. Instead, he concentrates on what he does know and on what really matters -- on people, their problems and aspirations.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Bush, he is committed to doing something dramatic to combat global warming. But he is not bound to particular actions regardless of cost and before clearer remedies are at hand, unlike Mr. Brown.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Bush, Mr. Clinton still worries about U.S. energy security and dependence on Persian Gulf oil. But he is still searching for politically palatable solutions like increased gas taxes, unlike Mr. Brown, who never seems troubled by political realities.</p>
        <p>Unlike Mr. Bush, who would keep U.S. military spending near current levels and have Americans police the world alone, Mr. Clinton would make significant cuts in the Pentagon budget and stress the need for collective military action against aggression. Unlike Mr. Brown, he would do so with a scalpel, not with a meat cleaver.</p>
        <p>Above all, Mr. Clinton's pronouncements center on the new and profound connections between foreign and domestic affairs. This connection is at the heart of modern diplomacy, and Mr. Clinton understands this. No nation, even one as mighty as the U.S., will be able to exercise sustained influence abroad unless it is economically strong at home, and Mr. Clinton understands this, too.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Clinton speaks of America first, but never of America only.</p>
        <p>In his treatment of domestic issues, he also brings commitment to ends and flexibility about means.</p>
        <p>He accepts the necessity of a new national health care plan. But given the massive disagreements about means and costs, he talks about trying different approaches, about experimenting. He presses for reform in education. And while he highlights the idea of giving parents a choice of schools as a way to generate quality, he is open to other ideas as well.</p>
        <p>Jerry Brown talks as if he really had all the answers -- and they are all simple. But mostly it seems that he has returned from his latest deep space probe as Jack D. Ripper, full of anger and nastiness. Mr. Bush, by contrast, seems to have no ideas and offers gimmicky slogans like "family values" and "Congressional reform." His new "change thing" is every bit as convincing as his "vision thing."</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton may not have vision either. We do not yet know. But he does have energy, drive, ideas and an incredible fund of knowledge about domestic policy issues, second only to Senator Pat Moynihan of New York.</p>
        <p>Yes, we all have questions and doubts about somebody labeled Slick Willie. And we should have lots of questions and doubts about Turnstile Jerry, No New Taxes Bush and a Paul Tsongas who so abruptly quit the campaign.</p>
        <p>But Bill Clinton could be special, a bold experimenter in a world searching for answers. New Yorkers could defeat him or they could work through the tabloid garbage to glimpse that promise -- and put it to a further test.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
