<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pelicans Are Coming! To the South Shore!</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="544709"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIRDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PELICANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DD163EF931A15754C0A964958260" item-length="672" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pelicans Are Coming! To the South Shore!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>SOUTHAMPTON, L.I.,</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It happened to Russell S. Stein, an environmental lawyer, who saw 15 birds skimming the waves early Sunday morning near his Montauk home. "I looked at them and took a few more steps, and then it was like someone hit me with a sledgehammer," Mr. Stein said.</p>
        <p>It happened to Dorothy Friedman in Wainscott as she and some friends were walking on the beach. "It's one of those things where you know what you saw, but logic tells you it's impossible," she said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It happened to Russell S. Stein, an environmental lawyer, who saw 15 birds skimming the waves early Sunday morning near his Montauk home. "I looked at them and took a few more steps, and then it was like someone hit me with a sledgehammer," Mr. Stein said.</p>
        <p>It happened to Dorothy Friedman in Wainscott as she and some friends were walking on the beach. "It's one of those things where you know what you saw, but logic tells you it's impossible," she said.</p>
        <p>What is happening along the South Shore of Long Island is that people are seeing brown pelicans far north of their normal range.</p>
        <p>"It's like U.F.O. sightings," Mr. Stein said. "It's all over the place."</p>
        <p>The appearance of the pelicans, once an endangered species along the Atlantic Coast, has set off speculation that they may be following the example of the cardinal, the mocking bird and other birds that have ranged north in the last half century. Is It Global Warming?</p>
        <p>"I think what we are seeing is a range extension, perhaps in response to global warming," said Larry Penny, the director of natural resources for the Town of East Hampton, who has been gathering brown pelican reports. "This is the way it begins."</p>
        <p>Brown pelicans, with breeding grounds in this country ranging from Florida to North Carolina, have been seen along the Island's South Shore for years, often after tropical storms in the South. But Mr. Penny said they had never been seen in the numbers appearing in recent days.</p>
        <p>He said he had reports of 92 pelicans flying in formation east past Fire Island Inlet last Wednesday, the same day he said 87 pelicans were counted at Jones Beach and 17 more in Moriches Bay.</p>
        <p>In another sighting Sunday, Sandra and Herbert Rosenblum, standing watch over a piping plover habitat, videotaped 27 birds flying west over Georgica Beach in Wainscott. "We are 98 percent sure they were pelicans, but I wouldn't want to say for sure until somebody sees the videotape," Mrs. Rosenblum said. Mr. Penny saw the tape, and he was sure: Pelicans.  Brown Turning White</p>
        <p>The birds, agile flyers with elastic pouches beneath their bills for filtering out fish from water, weigh an average of seven pounds and are brown in color when young, growing whiter with age.</p>
        <p>Pelicans are also found on the Pacific Coast, with sightings as far north as Vancouver Island. They also range from the Gulf Coast to the northern coast of South America.</p>
        <p>Experts offer a variety of theories about why the pelicans are showing up now in Long Island and thriving in other parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Jesse Grantham, a brown pelican expert in the National Audubon Society's western regional office in Sacramento, said that since a ban was imposed on the use of the pesticide DDT in the early 1970's, brown pelican populations had increased remarkably. He said that in 1964 fewer than 40 pelicans remained in Texas, and now, he estimated, there are up to 6,000 brown pelicans nesting along the Texas Gulf Coast.</p>
        <p>And he said the sightings in Long Island might reflect a resurgence of breeding grounds in states like North Carolina, where, for instance, 4,000 pairs of brown pelicans were counted in 1991. "If each pair produces two young on the average, that's about 8,000 young last year, and that's a pretty significant number," he said.</p>
        <p>"It might be we've got birds from the Carolinas starting to move north after the breeding season," Mr. Grantham said. "We haven't seen brown pelicans that far north in many years in these numbers, so obviously the birds are dispersing northward. Maybe we are seeing some kind of return to historical patterns."</p>
        <p>Alexander Sprunt IV, the vice president for special projects for the Audubon Society in the Florida Keys and an observer of the brown pelican for 30 years, said that a surge in sightings occurred in 1983 from Delaware to Long Island, but that since then counts had been far lower.</p>
        <p>"It is true that pelicans have been moving north somewhat," he said. "Whether it's because of global warming, nobody really knows."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
