<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Labor Raises Its Voice On L.I. Sound</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="503198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDING (CONSTRUCTION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEWERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND SOUND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELVIN, TESSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD81638F935A15752C0A964958260" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Labor Raises Its Voice On L.I. Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TESSA MELVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MELVIN, TESSA</byline>
      <dateline>WHITE PLAINS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE environmentalists inside the Stouffer Westchester Hotel last weekend called their gathering a citizens summit to clean up Long Island Sound. The construction workers marching outside called it a conference to ban all building projects along the Sound.</p>
        <p>Carrying signs like "Labor Votes. Crabs Don't," about 1,500 steamfitters, carpenters, plumbers and electricians demonstrated for two hours in cold winds. A balloon floating 40 feet overhead capsulized their message: "A Sound Economy Needs Jobs, Not Sewer Bans."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE environmentalists inside the Stouffer Westchester Hotel last weekend called their gathering a citizens summit to clean up Long Island Sound. The construction workers marching outside called it a conference to ban all building projects along the Sound.</p>
        <p>Carrying signs like "Labor Votes. Crabs Don't," about 1,500 steamfitters, carpenters, plumbers and electricians demonstrated for two hours in cold winds. A balloon floating 40 feet overhead capsulized their message: "A Sound Economy Needs Jobs, Not Sewer Bans."</p>
        <p>The building industry in Westchester, where the unemployment rate is estimated to be as high as 50 percent, is fearful that efforts being considered for protecting the Sound's water quality will destroy what little opportunity still exists for construction work in the shore communities. But there are also suggestions that the need to build new and upgraded sewage plants could form the basis of an alliance between labor and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month the State Department of Environmental Conservation banned expansion of the four sewer districts in Westchester that empty into the Sound and also stopped plans by the county to expand a sewer district in North Castle. But that moratorium halting new development was lifted on Jan. 17 when county officials submitted an alternative plan to limit pollution in the Sound. The county's plan will limit fertilizers used on golf courses, construct new wetlands and curtail boat discharges. It comes in response to a call by Federal and state agencies sponsoring the Long Island Sound Study, a six-year partnership of Federal, state and local agencies to identify the most pressing environmental threats to the Sound and to produce a Comprehensive Conservation and Management Plan to guide solutions.</p>
        <p>Excess amounts of nitrogen, one of the elements released in the treatment of human waste, in agricultural and lawn-fertilizer runoff and by natural causes, including plant decay and acid rain, is believed to be responsible for reduced oxygen levels in the Sound. That, in turn, has caused large numbers of fish and shellfish to suffocate. Back to 1990 Levels</p>
        <p>Last fall, sponsors of the Long Island Sound Study, whose final report is to be released this November, became so concerned about pollution that they ordered a no-net nitrogen-increase as an interim solution. Officials in Connecticut and New York are developing legal mechanisms to enforce that order to limit the flow to 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>"No one wants a building moratorium, including us," said Cesare J. Manfredi, the water-pollution control engineer for the state's Department of Environmental Conservation and the official who had imposed the temporary ban. "We do want to insure there is no net increase in nitrogen flow."</p>
        <p>To accomplish this goal, tradeoffs are necessary, he said.</p>
        <p>"It's fine to allow new construction, which will increase sewage," he said, "but you have to decide where the reductions will come from."</p>
        <p>Although in December Westchester County had authorized the expansion of the Blind Brook Sewer District to North Castle, Mr. Manfredi said, "You can't just build a new district or expand old ones without a plan to reduce nitrogen flows elsewhere."</p>
        <p>It was because of pressure from his department, he said, that the county's interim plan was quickly put into place. A committee of municipal officials has been looking into ideas for controlling pollution in the Sound. A Meeting This Week</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Mr. Manfredi said, his agency will meet with representatives of the county's Department of Environmental Facilities to discuss an impending $150,000 to $250,000 Federal grant that will enable the monitoring of major tributaries that feed into Long Island Sound from the county. Data from this survey will help the state agency conduct periodic followup surveys of nitrogen levels.</p>
        <p>Although restricting nitrogen flows to the Sound through tradeoffs could allow development to continue, the relationships are complex. At least one county sewer district, the one centered in Blind Brook, is seeking Federal aid to help it modernize and reduce the amount of nitrogen the plant releases into the Sound. Reduced volumes from this plant could provide a "bank" of permitted nitrogen flow and allow new construction in areas served by plants discharging into the Sound from Mamaroneck, New Rochelle and Port Chester.</p>
        <p>Rye city officials who supervise the use of the Blind Brook plant are reluctant to discuss sharing the benefits of reduced nitrogen flow with their neighbors until the financial implications are cleared up. "We have no assurances that we will get Federal money to upgrade the plant," said Warren R. Ross, the Mayor of Rye.  "Without that money, our sewer district taxpayers must pay the cost, and if so, they should be the ones to benefit."</p>
        <p>There are critics who charge that the environmentalists' support of nitrogen restrictions is a smokescreen to prevent development on lands bordering the waterway. 'There's a Conflict Here'</p>
        <p>"There's a conflict here," said Gerald Lloyd, one of a handful of construction-industry supporters who attended the Jan. 18 environmental conference here, which was sponsored by the Long Island Sound Watershed Alliance, a 150-member coalition of environmental and civic groups.</p>
        <p>"That's why those guys are out there," Mr. Lloyd, who represented the Westchester Chamber of Commerce, told the 150 conference participants. "They don't trust you any more."</p>
        <p>Calling the Sound "an economic as well as an environmental resource," Robert Bendick, deputy commissioner of the State Department of Environmental Conservation and a conference speaker, defended his department's limit on nitrogen increases "as a way to get everybody to the table."</p>
        <p>Resolving the issue, he said, will require a partnership with the Federal Government. Helping sewage-treatment plants upgrade their operations and reduce nitrogen flow into the Sound will require as much as $6 billion for the region, including Long Island and Connecticut, Commissioner Bendick said.</p>
        <p>"That's lots of money and lots of construction work," he said, explaining why he believes "a very strong coalition between environmentalists and industry can be developed here."</p>
        <p>David J. Miller, chairman of the Watershed Alliance, agreed. "Labor and environmentalists are not on opposite sides of the spectrum of Long Island Sound issues," he said, adding that the workers' demonstration provided "a great window of opportunity" for the two groups to begin working together. A Link to Labor Perceived</p>
        <p>The alliance was formed a year ago after the National Audubon Society's Listen to the Sound Citizens Hearings Campaign, a series of 15 public forums that offered people living in the Sound area an opportunity to discuss their concerns and make recommendations for the future of the Sound.</p>
        <p>Pointing to "the link between labor's call for jobs and development and our call for sewage-treatment plant upgrading and growth management," Mr. Miller, who is also regional vice president of the National Audubon Society, said both groups support Federal financing to upgrade sewage-treatment plants.</p>
        <p>Without Federal aid "both jobs and the Sound will be losers," Mr. Miller said.</p>
        <p>He will meet with construction industry leaders for the first time on Wednesday to discuss mutual goals. "There has been a barrier of communication that has to be crossed," Mr. Miller said. "Now, if we both go to Washington seeking Federal money to upgrade sewage-treatment plants, we'd both be winners. This is the beginning of a marriage of ideas."</p>
        <p>While the leaders of both groups planned discussions, those talks appeared to be a long way from the men on the line last weekend. Running a Gantlet</p>
        <p>Nick Colombo, agent for Local 38 of the Sheet Metal Workers union, was among those making up the thick gantlet of workers on West Red Oak Lane, through which Harrison police officers guided cars carrying conference guests up to the hotel. Mr. Colombo said he had had no trouble getting many of his 480 members to attend the rally.</p>
        <p>"Half of them are out of work, many so long they have run out of unemployment," he said. "We have a food bank and a work-sharing program to help these guys, but it's not enough." Union members, he said, are being evicted from their apartments in increasing numbers, losing their homes and finding that they can no longer meet their car payments.</p>
        <p>Another knot of men representing Carpenters' Local 149 stood nearby. Several identified themselves as "the lucky ones," the ones still working. Almost half the members in their 450-member local do not have jobs.</p>
        <p>Steve Sullivan, for example, was recently notified by the Department of Labor that his unemployment benefits had expired.</p>
        <p>"So many in the media view us as a bunch of labor goons," said Mr. Sullivan, who has four children. "What you see here is a group of fathers, Scout leaders and Little League coaches. We care about the environment. The only difference is that when we run out of work, we panic."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
