<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="528502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA133DF937A25756C0A964958260" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-15  U.N. PESSIMISTIC ON BALKANS</p>
        <p>Citing continued warfare, Secretary General Boutros-Ghali ruled out peacekeeping forces for Bosnia and Herzegovina. And he even raised the possibility of canceling plans to send 14,000 peacekeepers to Croatia.  A1</p>
        <p>Violence subsided in Sarajevo as a cease-fire went into effect.  A12  TURMOIL IN NIGERIA</p>
        <p>The worst street violence in years erupted as anti-Government protesters battled the police in Lagos. A gasoline drought in the oil-producing nation set off the protests, which some believe could upset plans for the military to transfer power to civilians by next year.  A3  TYING AID TO REFORMS</p>
        <p>Another African nation experiencing unrest, Malawi, was told by the World Bank and Western donor nations to show evidence of democratic reforms. Development aid was frozen for this year and next.  A15  THE COST OF POLLUTION</p>
        <p>In an effort to limit pollution and global warming, the European Community proposed that a stiff tax be imposed on all forms of fuel. The plan sharpened the community's differences with the United States on environmental polices.  A5</p>
        <p>Rio Journal: Trying to clean up in time for the Earth Summit.  A4  NEW PRIME MINISTER IN LEBANON</p>
        <p>A week after riots forced the Cabinet to resign, President Hrawi named Rashid Solh as Prime Minister. Mr. Solh said he would work to bring about Israel's evacuation of its buffer zone in the south.  A11  TWO KINGS AT ODDS</p>
        <p>King Fahd of Saudi Arabia and King Hussein of Jordan are in a bitter dispute over the repair and maintenance of Muslim shrines in Jerusalem. Their relations have been tense since they took opposite sides in the Persian Gulf crisis.  A7  A COAL REGION'S PAIN</p>
        <p>The funerals began in tiny villages in Pictou County, Nova Scotia, where 26 miners were trapped in an explosion. Fifteen bodies have been recovered as hopes for a miracle fade.  A3  THE LAOTIAN MASK</p>
        <p>The small, poor Southeast Asian country has done away with the trappings of Communism and opened its economy to investment and trade. But officials defend the one-party state, and a former official says that "socialism is still the goal." A6  An ex-Defense Minister and a lawyer lead the Philippine vote count.  A10  A controversial Roman Catholic group prepares for its big day.  A12  North Korea returned what it says are the remains of U.S. soldiers.  A8  Britain seeks to continue border checks of European travelers.  A14  National A16-23, B12-13  SURGE IN GUN OWNERSHIP</p>
        <p>The riots in Los Angeles, and the resulting fear that the police may not be able to protect lives or property during an outbreak of civil unrest, have led Californians to buy firearms at the highest rate in at least two decades. Other states, too, are reporting a quick rise in gun purchases.  A1</p>
        <p>Prosecutors will seek to retry one officer in the King beating.  A20</p>
        <p>Washington's new unity on urban policy is already fraying.  A20  THE VALUE OF A COLLEGE DEGREE</p>
        <p>Two labor economists reported that since 1989, the pay of most college-educated Americans had failed to keep pace with inflation. The finding suggests that as many high-paying jobs vanish from the workplace, a bachelor's degree is becoming less of a ticket to a rising income.  A1  A HUNT FOR HOMOSEXUALS</p>
        <p>A gay employee of the Federal Emergency Management Agency was pressured to provide a list of other homosexual workers to the agency's managers and security personnel, who contended that they needed the information to help identify security risks.  A1  NICE CATCH IN OUTER SPACE</p>
        <p>Three astronauts from the shuttle Endeavour ventured into the void of space, reached out with gloved hands and snared a wayward satellite.  A1  PEROT'S 50-STATE QUEST</p>
        <p>When Ross Perot began his foray into Presidential politics by declaring that he would run if his name were placed on the ballot in every state, his backers were drawn into a labyrinth of rules that are mind-numbing in their complexity, vary from state to state and, according to Mr. Perot's aides and some scholars, are designed by Republicans and Democrats to thwart third-party candidacies like his.  A18</p>
        <p>Bush's veto of a campaign finance bill was sustained.  A18  INCREASE IN DRUG USE</p>
        <p>A new Federal report on hospital emergencies attributed to cocaine and heroin abuse shows a continuing rise that officials say emphasizes the need for greater treatment and prevention efforts. And drug experts say the Administration's proposals for increasing treatment programs fall far short of meeting the needs of heavy drug users.  A16  STARTING OVER</p>
        <p>The sole adult survivor of the Philadelphia police's firebombing of the radical group MOVE left prison after serving a seven-year term for riot and conspiracy.  A16  THE DEAFENING OF AMERICA</p>
        <p>At a gathering of the American Acoustical Society, experts from a number of fields agreed that the nation was being deafened by noise and that the din seemed to be getting louder.  B13  Boston Journal: Fighting drugs and guns with music.  A16  Metropolitan Digest, B1 NEEDLE-EXCHANGE PROJECT</p>
        <p>The Dinkins administration will permit drug addicts to receive clean hypodermic needles in a research effort to measure whether the move will slow the spread of AIDS. Approval of the program represents a shift on the part of Mayor Dinkins, who had opposed needle-exchange programs in the past.  A1  DISTRICTING BATTLE, PART 2</p>
        <p>As the New York State Legislature has struggled in vain to negotiate a Congressional redistricting plan, its ability to strike a deal has been stymied by a series of thorny political decisions. And as the district lines have remained undrawn, the process has ended up in the hands of two different courts.  A1  Business Digest, D1  The Home Section C1-12  Less or more, style rules.  C1  What's so funny? Ask the young.  C1  Sand, cookies and a hearty taste of life.  C1  Arts/Entertainment C14-22  Theater man in a movie town.  C17  Spring art auctions.  C17  Sports B15-21  Basketball: Knicks need big game from Ewing.  B15  Column: Anderson on the Rangers. Dead Again.  B15  Hockey: Penguins eliminate the Rangers.  B15  Obituaries B14  Robert Reed, an actor.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A24-25  Editorials A24  The Los Angeles law: use it. Deep doubts about a death. Spare the horses in N.Y.C. Topics: Meddle, medal. Letters A24  William Safire: V.P. morning line.  A25  Anthony Lewis: Public keep out.  A25  Linda DiVall: Women of the year.  A25  Joseph A. Califano Jr.: Don't blame L.B.J.  A25</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-15  U.N. PESSIMISTIC ON BALKANS</p>
        <p>Citing continued warfare, Secretary General Boutros-Ghali ruled out peacekeeping forces for Bosnia and Herzegovina. And he even raised the possibility of canceling plans to send 14,000 peacekeepers to Croatia.  A1</p>
        <p>Violence subsided in Sarajevo as a cease-fire went into effect.  A12  TURMOIL IN NIGERIA</p>
        <p>The worst street violence in years erupted as anti-Government protesters battled the police in Lagos. A gasoline drought in the oil-producing nation set off the protests, which some believe could upset plans for the military to transfer power to civilians by next year.  A3  TYING AID TO REFORMS</p>
        <p>Another African nation experiencing unrest, Malawi, was told by the World Bank and Western donor nations to show evidence of democratic reforms. Development aid was frozen for this year and next.  A15  THE COST OF POLLUTION</p>
        <p>In an effort to limit pollution and global warming, the European Community proposed that a stiff tax be imposed on all forms of fuel. The plan sharpened the community's differences with the United States on environmental polices.  A5</p>
        <p>Rio Journal: Trying to clean up in time for the Earth Summit.  A4  NEW PRIME MINISTER IN LEBANON</p>
        <p>A week after riots forced the Cabinet to resign, President Hrawi named Rashid Solh as Prime Minister. Mr. Solh said he would work to bring about Israel's evacuation of its buffer zone in the south.  A11  TWO KINGS AT ODDS</p>
        <p>King Fahd of Saudi Arabia and King Hussein of Jordan are in a bitter dispute over the repair and maintenance of Muslim shrines in Jerusalem. Their relations have been tense since they took opposite sides in the Persian Gulf crisis.  A7  A COAL REGION'S PAIN</p>
        <p>The funerals began in tiny villages in Pictou County, Nova Scotia, where 26 miners were trapped in an explosion. Fifteen bodies have been recovered as hopes for a miracle fade.  A3  THE LAOTIAN MASK</p>
        <p>The small, poor Southeast Asian country has done away with the trappings of Communism and opened its economy to investment and trade. But officials defend the one-party state, and a former official says that "socialism is still the goal." A6  An ex-Defense Minister and a lawyer lead the Philippine vote count.  A10  A controversial Roman Catholic group prepares for its big day.  A12  North Korea returned what it says are the remains of U.S. soldiers.  A8  Britain seeks to continue border checks of European travelers.  A14  National A16-23, B12-13  SURGE IN GUN OWNERSHIP</p>
        <p>The riots in Los Angeles, and the resulting fear that the police may not be able to protect lives or property during an outbreak of civil unrest, have led Californians to buy firearms at the highest rate in at least two decades. Other states, too, are reporting a quick rise in gun purchases.  A1</p>
        <p>Prosecutors will seek to retry one officer in the King beating.  A20</p>
        <p>Washington's new unity on urban policy is already fraying.  A20  THE VALUE OF A COLLEGE DEGREE</p>
        <p>Two labor economists reported that since 1989, the pay of most college-educated Americans had failed to keep pace with inflation. The finding suggests that as many high-paying jobs vanish from the workplace, a bachelor's degree is becoming less of a ticket to a rising income.  A1  A HUNT FOR HOMOSEXUALS</p>
        <p>A gay employee of the Federal Emergency Management Agency was pressured to provide a list of other homosexual workers to the agency's managers and security personnel, who contended that they needed the information to help identify security risks.  A1  NICE CATCH IN OUTER SPACE</p>
        <p>Three astronauts from the shuttle Endeavour ventured into the void of space, reached out with gloved hands and snared a wayward satellite.  A1  PEROT'S 50-STATE QUEST</p>
        <p>When Ross Perot began his foray into Presidential politics by declaring that he would run if his name were placed on the ballot in every state, his backers were drawn into a labyrinth of rules that are mind-numbing in their complexity, vary from state to state and, according to Mr. Perot's aides and some scholars, are designed by Republicans and Democrats to thwart third-party candidacies like his.  A18</p>
        <p>Bush's veto of a campaign finance bill was sustained.  A18  INCREASE IN DRUG USE</p>
        <p>A new Federal report on hospital emergencies attributed to cocaine and heroin abuse shows a continuing rise that officials say emphasizes the need for greater treatment and prevention efforts. And drug experts say the Administration's proposals for increasing treatment programs fall far short of meeting the needs of heavy drug users.  A16  STARTING OVER</p>
        <p>The sole adult survivor of the Philadelphia police's firebombing of the radical group MOVE left prison after serving a seven-year term for riot and conspiracy.  A16  THE DEAFENING OF AMERICA</p>
        <p>At a gathering of the American Acoustical Society, experts from a number of fields agreed that the nation was being deafened by noise and that the din seemed to be getting louder.  B13  Boston Journal: Fighting drugs and guns with music.  A16  Metropolitan Digest, B1 NEEDLE-EXCHANGE PROJECT</p>
        <p>The Dinkins administration will permit drug addicts to receive clean hypodermic needles in a research effort to measure whether the move will slow the spread of AIDS. Approval of the program represents a shift on the part of Mayor Dinkins, who had opposed needle-exchange programs in the past.  A1  DISTRICTING BATTLE, PART 2</p>
        <p>As the New York State Legislature has struggled in vain to negotiate a Congressional redistricting plan, its ability to strike a deal has been stymied by a series of thorny political decisions. And as the district lines have remained undrawn, the process has ended up in the hands of two different courts.  A1  Business Digest, D1  The Home Section C1-12  Less or more, style rules.  C1  What's so funny? Ask the young.  C1  Sand, cookies and a hearty taste of life.  C1  Arts/Entertainment C14-22  Theater man in a movie town.  C17  Spring art auctions.  C17  Sports B15-21  Basketball: Knicks need big game from Ewing.  B15  Column: Anderson on the Rangers. Dead Again.  B15  Hockey: Penguins eliminate the Rangers.  B15  Obituaries B14  Robert Reed, an actor.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A24-25  Editorials A24  The Los Angeles law: use it. Deep doubts about a death. Spare the horses in N.Y.C. Topics: Meddle, medal. Letters A24  William Safire: V.P. morning line.  A25  Anthony Lewis: Public keep out.  A25  Linda DiVall: Women of the year.  A25  Joseph A. Califano Jr.: Don't blame L.B.J.  A25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
