<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Silence of the Frogs</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="576290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FROGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOADS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOFFE, EMILY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DF133CF930A25751C1A964958260" item-length="6257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Silence of the Frogs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Emily Yoffe;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YOFFE, EMILY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the early 70's, a bizarre, inexplicable illness was sabotaging the academic career of Cynthia Carey. Then a young biologist, she was writing a dissertation on the physiology of coldblooded animals. Her creature of choice was Bufo boreas, named for the ancient Greek god of the north wind, an extravagant tag for a warty, blotchy, four-inch toad. It is more commonly and appropriately known as the western toad, its range encompassing the mountains of western North America. Twice a week, Carey went into the vast, pristine wilderness of Colorado to do her research. At times the toads were so plentiful she had to be careful when driving away not to crush them under her wheels.</p>
        <p>In 1973, two years into her work, the illness struck. When she went into the field, Carey started coming upon an alarming sight: dozens of dying toads, toads barely able to move because their legs were puffy and red. She took one back to a veterinarian, who told her the toads were dying from an opportunistic infection because their immune systems had collapsed. But why?</p>
        <p>Carey was in no position to unravel the mystery -- she had a dissertation to do. But by 1979, there were no western toads, healthy or sick, to be found at any of the previous sites, or anywhere else in Colorado she looked. "These are wilderness areas," she says today from her laboratory at the University of Colorado at Boulder, where she is an associate professor of biology. "There was no development, no housing, no habitat destruction. I was sad and mystified."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the early 70's, a bizarre, inexplicable illness was sabotaging the academic career of Cynthia Carey. Then a young biologist, she was writing a dissertation on the physiology of coldblooded animals. Her creature of choice was Bufo boreas, named for the ancient Greek god of the north wind, an extravagant tag for a warty, blotchy, four-inch toad. It is more commonly and appropriately known as the western toad, its range encompassing the mountains of western North America. Twice a week, Carey went into the vast, pristine wilderness of Colorado to do her research. At times the toads were so plentiful she had to be careful when driving away not to crush them under her wheels.</p>
        <p>In 1973, two years into her work, the illness struck. When she went into the field, Carey started coming upon an alarming sight: dozens of dying toads, toads barely able to move because their legs were puffy and red. She took one back to a veterinarian, who told her the toads were dying from an opportunistic infection because their immune systems had collapsed. But why?</p>
        <p>Carey was in no position to unravel the mystery -- she had a dissertation to do. But by 1979, there were no western toads, healthy or sick, to be found at any of the previous sites, or anywhere else in Colorado she looked. "These are wilderness areas," she says today from her laboratory at the University of Colorado at Boulder, where she is an associate professor of biology. "There was no development, no housing, no habitat destruction. I was sad and mystified."</p>
        <p>She was also in trouble. "I had to change my research. You can't tell your tenure committee, 'I haven't done my research because all my animals went extinct.' " Instead she switched to bird eggs, became an expert on them and for the next nine years thought little about where all the toads had gone.</p>
        <p>Then in 1988, she read a scientific paper on how environmental disturbances suppress the immune systems of fish. "That's when all the lights went on," Carey says. She has since set out to discover what happened to Bufo boreas, now missing from at least 80 percent of its historic range.</p>
        <p>Around that time the same light bulb was clicking on for herpetologists (scientists who study amphibians and reptiles) all over the world. And by 1989, the light was blinding. That year in Canterbury, England, the first World Congress of Herpetology was taking place. On the agenda were esoteric and, to the non-herpetologist, faintly ridiculous-sounding presentations like "Belly Pattern of Triturus Carnifex and Triturus Vulgaris in Two Ponds of Ligurian Apennines, Northern Italy." But to many of the 1,300 participants from around the world, it was as if there were another conference taking place in the hallways and over meals, during breaks and at talks late into the night. The subject of this impromptu conference could be summed up in one ominous question: Where have all the frogs gone?</p>
        <p>"A bunch of us got together and started comparing notes," recalls Jay M. Savage, a professor of biology at the University of Miami. "People were struck by the fact it seemed to be occurring on a worldwide basis."</p>
        <p>Savage has spent much of the last 40 years studying the evolution and ecology of amphibians, mostly in Central America. In 1964, he and a colleague discovered a species of toad native to Costa Rica, in what is now called the Monteverde Cloud Forest Reserve. The toad's Latin name is Bufo periglenes, but it is better known as the golden toad -- the male a Day-Glo orange. The golden toad lives underground, and emerges for an annual, explosive, breeding season. Since 1964, scientists have watched as thousands of these tiny, vivid animals gathered for their yearly ritual. That was until 1988. That year, at the primary breeding site, only one adult male was found. Two years later, there were none -- and none have been seen since.</p>
        <p>The apparent disaster is being repeated among other Cloud Forest species. The exquisite glass frogs, small lime-green animals with see-through undersides and large quizzical eyes, were abundant until the late 80's; now they can hardly be found. "Jewels in the night we called them," Savage recalls. "You used to see hundreds."</p>
        <p>The black, yellow and red patterned harlequin frog, an amorous creature that can spend days clamped in a breeding embrace, also virtually disappeared in the late 80's. "Human beings are great at rationalization," Savage says. "We said, it must be local damage; if we just went over the hill, we'd find them. Most herpetologists were trying to explain things that way. What was striking was we found it was happening on such a broad basis."</p>
        <p>At the meeting, Michael J. Tyler, an associate professor of zoology at University of Adelaide in Australia who has an enviable record for identifying remarkable species, told of the disappearance of the gastric brooding frog named Rheobatrachus silus. In 1974, Tyler identified the reproductive strategy of this inhabitant of the rain forest in the Connondale Ranges in Australia. The strategy was so implausible that when Tyler wrote a paper describing it, the editors of Nature rejected it. (Science magazine, however, did publish the findings.) The Rheobatrachus female swallows her fertilized eggs, which then gestate in her stomach and are regurgitated as tiny froglets six weeks later. It was hoped the frog, who somehow turns off her gastric activity, could provide a breakthrough in treating human stomach ailments.</p>
        <p>"We were looking at the frontiers of biological science," says Tyler. "We were rewriting concepts of how bloody magnificent some animals are." In 1980, the gastric-brooding frog disappeared, as usual, in the rocks for the winter. But then not one emerged that spring, nor has one been seen since. The species is now presumed extinct. To add to the puzzle, a number of the area's other frog species vanished as well, and remain missing.</p>
        <p>In the United States, Bufo boreas is not the only amphibian disappearing from the West. Also in decline are the Yosemite toad, the mountain yellow-legged frog and the red-legged frog, which was likely the protagonist in Mark Twain's famous story "The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County." These frogs are missing from sites where they have been abundant in naturalists' accounts going back 75 years.</p>
        <p>In all, almost one-third of North America's 86 species of frogs and toads appear to be in trouble. (In general, frogs have a smoother, more moist skin and live more closely to water than toads, which are squatter and often covered with warty bumps.) Gary Fellers, a research biologist with the National Park Service, visited Lassen Volcanic National Park in Northern California last year looking for the once-common Cascades frog. He used as his guide historic research papers describing the frog as being present every few feet. "We visited 50 sites with decent habitats," he says. "We found two frogs at one site." This year there were none.</p>
        <p>Until recently, one of the most common sounds in western Canada's national parks was the low, throaty grunt of the northern leopard frog, Rana pipiens, the green-spotted creature almost everyone dissected in high school. Then, in the 1980's, the frogs started dying and populations plunged. The government of Alberta has even put out a "wanted" poster. Above a photo of Rana pipiens are the words, "Have You Seen This Frog?"</p>
        <p>PERHAPS THE NEED TO FIND overarching explanations is encoded in our genes. From the search for a unified field theory of physics, to deconstructing the big bang, to proving that it was a straying asteroid that wiped out the dinosaurs, we like definitive theories to explain the phenomena that create and govern life.</p>
        <p>What is killing the frogs? In many instances, the answer, as with much of the world's disappearing flora and fauna, is no mystery. Humans are destroying habitats with unprecedented frenzy. Researchers estimate that one-quarter to one-half of the earth's species could be extinct in the next 30 years. Cut down a forest, drain a wetland, build a shopping center, and the local frog species die. No one puzzles as to why Southern California is virtually barren of most of its native frogs.</p>
        <p>There are other obvious human causes. For one thing, pesticides and herbicides that have been found safe for humans may be devastating to other animals at vulnerable points in their life cycles. For another, in national parks, the Government's fire-suppression policies have greatly accelerated the slow process of marshes becoming woods, thus robbing amphibians of habitat. Then there is the human impulse to rectify nature's oversights. The effect of this is seen in the Sierras. After the last Ice Age, fish did not colonize the high-elevation lakes; frogs did. These lakes have been stocked with nonnative game fish, which feed on tadpoles. This has left many frog populations isolated at higher headwaters, where they have become vulnerable to disease or harsh weather. And when the frogs are wiped out at a site, they can't recolonize it. Frogs themselves can also be the problem: when foreign species are introduced, they can overrun native populations.</p>
        <p>But nothing explains it all. "I wish there were a death star to explain it," says David B. Wake, from his office at Berkeley, where he is the director of the Museum of Vertebrate Zoology at the University of California. "I don't see a single toxin, a single virus. My theory is that it's general environmental degradation. That's the worst thing. Frogs are telling us about the environment's overall health. They are the medium and the message."</p>
        <p>Most herpetologists recognize that the world will never rally around their cosmetically challenged creatures. Their only hope is to portray frogs as four-legged, bug-eating Cassandras, and pray the prophecy is heard. "Frogs are in essence a messenger," Wake says. "This is about biodiversity and disintegration, the destruction of our total environment."</p>
        <p>They aren't the only messenger. Visit any well-stocked zoo that identifies endangered animals, and you begin to feel you are walking the corridors of a hospice. Most of these endangered species, from migratory songbirds to rhinoceroses, are dying because of human actions -- from habitat destruction to outright slaughter. Some signals are more mysterious; coral is bleaching out in some of the world's oceans for yet-unknown reasons. But one of the most disturbing things about what's happening to amphibians is that species are disappearing from some of the most remote, pristine places left on the earth -- as if following some synchronized command.</p>
        <p>Herpetologists, with perhaps not the greatest objectivity, say frogs are the ideal creature to reflect the health of the environment. In their view, frogs are living environmental assayers, moving over their life cycles from water to land, from plant-eater to insect-eater, covered only by a permeable skin that offers little shield from the outside world. Over and over, these scientists say amphibians represent the global equivalent of the proverbial canary in the coal mine. "They're very fragile organisms," says William Duellman, director of the Center for Neotropical Biological Diversity at the University of Kansas.</p>
        <p>There is a paradox in portraying frogs as delicate creatures experiencing a collective case of the evolutionary vapors. After all, in the 200 million years since frogs first surfaced on the earth, they have survived whatever killed the dinosaurs, whatever did in the woolly mammoths and other huge animals that wandered this continent. They have withstood glaciers coming and glaciers going. They have been found everywhere from the Himalayas to the Sonoran desert. It is precisely because frog species have been so historically hardy that scientists now find themselves so baffled -- and alarmed. "Something is out of balance," says James Vial, professor of Wildlife Ecology at Oregon State University. "The changes in the environment may be more drastic than they appear."</p>
        <p>Since Canterbury, David Wake has been a leader of a save-the-frogs movement among his colleagues. That conference three years ago was the first time, he says, "that a number of us herpetologists expressed our concerns openly to each other." And when the herpetologists started talking, they began to realize how much they had in common: for years many of them had been losing the subjects of their lifework. Before Canterbury, the scientists were reluctant to share their bad news with the rest of the world. "No one wanted to publish on it," Wake says. "It was sort of like a macho thing. 'I can't find frogs. I can't do the job anymore.' "</p>
        <p>In 1990, Wake helped organize a symposium on the topic in Irvine, Calif., out of which came the Declining Amphibian Populations Task Force. The group, with headquarters in Corvallis, Ore., was conceived as a three-year project to determine the extent and possible causes of amphibian decline. Operating as a unit of the World Conservation Union in Switzerland, which provides part of the $250,000 budget, the task force now has more than a thousand researchers in 40 countries.  The task force is set to expire at the end of next year, but already members are discussing making it a permanent organization. The Frog's Leap Winery in Napa Valley has donated the money for its bulletin: Froglog.</p>
        <p>Like the species they study, herpetologists are solitary, even quirky creatures. Getting the task force organized, deciding how to accomplish its goals -- long-term monitoring or short-term assessment, field research or lab experiments -- took about a year. In the end, the members decided on all of the above.</p>
        <p>One member of the task force's board, John Wright, the curator of herpetology at the Los Angeles Museum of Natural History, has been a vocal critic of the delays. But even if herpetologists were suddenly to adopt the cooperative social model of, say, ants, Wright would be pessimistic about the future. "In the real world and the scientific world, someone throws a dollar in the corner and everyone runs to it," he says. "Dollars are being thrown at other corners than biodiversity. If we can't do it with the warm fuzzies -- mammals and beautiful birds, we aren't going to do it with frogs." The answer to finding out what's going on with frogs, many herpetologists believe, would be a project documenting the world's species that is akin to the Human Genome Project.</p>
        <p>An equally challenging problem is the need for herpetologists to move beyond alarming anecdote to absolute proof. Since almost no carefully controlled, long-term studies have been done on frog-population dynamics, can scientists even be sure they are seeing the disaster they think they're seeing?</p>
        <p>"There is a lot of data on a number of populations taking nose dives over the last 20 years," says David Bradford, a wildlife ecologist with the Environmental Protection Agency. "It's a good record, but it's anecdotal."</p>
        <p>Using frogs as their study species, scientists have focused on exotic subjects like the physiology of living at high altitudes or the genetics of skin coloration. Then their research yielded something unexpected: there were no more frogs to study. Like Cynthia Carey, Bradford watched in the 70's as his study population -- mountain yellow-legged frogs in Sequoia and Kings Canyon National Parks in California -- sickened and died. Ten years later, in 1989, he returned to census 26 of his study sites. He found frogs at one.</p>
        <p>But a few herpetologists -- a decided minority -- are deeply troubled about the lack of long-term data. After the Canterbury conference, a Rutgers University biologist, Peter J. Morin, recalls: "I and a number of other people were a little alarmed that the data weren't there to support the conclusions. We need more real data on populations to find out if they are increasing, decreasing or just fluctuating." To be conclusive, such studies take 10 to 20 years.</p>
        <p>Some skeptics say the problem isn't too few frogs, but too many frog researchers. It could be called the baby-boom theory of frog decline. The idea is that about 20 years ago graduate schools were filling up with young scientists studying the new biological discipline of population dynamics. "When people go out to do research projects, they usually pick common organisms," says Stephen G. Tilley, professor of biological sciences at Smith College. "If populations fluctuate, there's a good chance when you go back to look they might not be as common as they were when you first studied them." He points out that many animals, like some rodents or insects, have large population swings.</p>
        <p>Tilley does believe that some species of frogs, like those in the Sierra Nevada, are in trouble. But he has seen nothing to convince him disappearances around the globe are linked. "I'm concerned about the species that are documented to have undergone a radical decline," he says. "But I am not convinced they tie together."</p>
        <p>Many of the most alarming population crashes, he points out, like those in Costa Rica or Australia, are among species that have been discovered only recently. "The problem is a lot of the species people are concerned with right now haven't been studied long-term. For all we know, they fluctuate. There's a paper in Science, and the bottom line is when people do long-term studies of amphibian populations, they find they fluctuate a lot."</p>
        <p>At first glance, the Science article does look like a T.K.O. to those crying extinction. From 1978 to 1990, census information was collected for species of three salamanders and one frog at a well-protected two-and-a-half acre pond near the center of the 300-square-mile Savannah River Ecology Laboratory in South Carolina. At the end of those years, breeding populations increased in one species and showed no declines in the others. Nevertheless, during the 12 years themselves, population size fluctuated widely -- one salamander was virtually absent for the first two years of the study, but by 1990, almost 600 females of the species bred.</p>
        <p>But to the worried herpetologists, the article is equivalent to proving there is no homelessness in Los Angeles by going on a tour of Beverly Hills. They claim to be seeing not fluctuations, but dead drops. David Wake, who wrote a commentary in Science to accompany the article, praises its research and agrees that more long-term data are needed. But he takes no comfort from it, because the Savannah River site is located in an area that is vast and wet and green. "It's an excellent breeding site," Wake says. "They could have total extinction of a local pond, and it would be recolonized the next year. There's no risk to those animals moving back and forth."</p>
        <p>Joseph H. K. Pechmann, an author of the Science article on the Savannah River project, agrees with Wake that, in many ways, his site is unique. "We would be the first to say the results from one study should not be generalized to the next pond down the road, let alone to a pond halfway around the world," says Pechmann.</p>
        <p>But he adds his own warning: conclusions about a global frog crisis should not be generalized from existing evidence. "It remains an open question whether declines and disappearances of some frog species in isolated, pristine environments represent a natural fluctuation or some subtle effect of human activities that we don't understand," Pechmann says. "My money is on the natural fluctuations, but I can't prove that. Only further research will say for sure."</p>
        <p>NO herpetologist disputes the value of long-term studies. But many insist that to wait for the data to come in would be foolhardy. "These declines, in many cases, are so catastrophic and are occurring simultaneously in so many parts of the world that we cannot wait for monitoring studies before we express our concern," says James Vial of Oregon State University, who is the task force's international coordinator. "Because if we wait for a prolonged period, there may not be anything left to study."</p>
        <p>Many researchers refuse to wait, and are now exploring the possible causes of the mysterious declines -- those not clearly linked to habitat destruction. At the top of the list is an increase in ultraviolet radiation. Among the hardest-hit amphibians are those that live at high altitudes, or near-the-ozone-hole southerly latitudes, from the Rockies and Sierras to the Andes to Australia. High-altitude frogs have already developed strategies to protect themselves from harmful radiation, while absorbing the heat so necessary to their survival. Many highland species lay black eggs and have a black peritoneum and, in the male, black testes. "This suggests they already live at the edge," says Wake. "How much more does it take to push them over?"</p>
        <p>While there may be indications that those who wear sunblock will inherit the earth, right now it's difficult to prove that increased ultraviolet radiation is a major cause of the decline. The simple reason is that studies have yet to be done to show if UV radiation really is increasing, and there is little historical information. More than a century's worth of temperature and rainfall statistics leaves the very false impression that similar data exist on all other atmospheric phenomena. "I can't believe how little we know," says Wake. "One reason global climate change is a touchy field is we don't have the right records."</p>
        <p>There is, of course, another species not protected by fur or shell or feathers that seems to be suffering from exposure to the sun's rays. Human skin-cancer rates are rising dramatically around the world. And Wake says we need to heed such warnings. "I say use biological indicators," he says. "The instruments won't do it. We need to measure effects."</p>
        <p>Andrew R. Blaustein, professor of zoology at Oregon State, is using instruments</p>
        <p>and</p>
        <p>measuring effects. The National Science Foundation and the National Geographic Society are helping to pay for his three-year, $272,000 study of ultraviolet radiation on amphibians. Blaustein has discovered that in the past four years, there has been a large dying off of western-toad eggs. What is unusual about this is that while very few toads and frogs make it to adulthood, mortality does not normally occur until after the eggs have hatched. "This year there were about two-and-a-half million eggs," Blaustein says. "Ninety-five percent of them died." There have been experiments that show exposure to UV radiation will destroy the development of eggs, but these have been in the laboratory. Blaustein wants to find out what effect current UV radiation levels are having in the field.</p>
        <p>As for other possible causes, acidification also has its partisans. But for every study that shows acid rain is damaging frogs, another one refutes it. "I have dismissed it as a factor in the Rocky Mountains," says Stephen Corn, a zoologist with the United States Fish and Wildlife Service in Fort Collins, Colo., who has just completed an extensive survey of acid rain's effect on western amphibians. And Blaustein, too, can find no evidence of acid in the Cascade Mountain lakes he is studying. "The acid stuff doesn't fit at all," he says. "We've taken pH measurements for two years. It's totally normal. And in the three lakes we've studied these animals, there are no pollutants."</p>
        <p>The mystery of the frog decline challenges the distinction between what is local and what is global. Because we as a species are so successful, so pervasive, the consequences of our local actions now ripple across the globe. No pristine place can protect a species from hazardous levels of, say, UV radiation. What is happening to frogs calls into question our belief that we can preserve the natural world in small, unsullied pockets. "You cannot lock up nature," Wake says. "There's no Noah's ark big enough."</p>
        <p>"THEY HAVE BEAUTIFUL eyes. You can really fall in love with them."</p>
        <p>Cynthia Carey is talking about the large, amber, if rather unexpressive, eyes of the specimen of marine toad now bloating up in the hands of her research assistant, Judy Bissonnette. The bloating, which makes this six-inch toad start to resemble a tiny dirigible, is a natural response to danger. In this case, the danger is being one of a dozen research animals in this small lab room at the University of Colorado at Boulder.</p>
        <p>Almost 20 years after she first wondered why all the western toads she saw were dying, Carey, who wears a small, silver frog pendant around her neck, is trying to decipher the immune system of frogs. The sick toad she had autopsied many years ago died of a massive infection from the bacteria Aeromonas hydrophila, which is ubiquitous in fresh water. In the final stages of infection, the circulation of a toad or frog will break down, causing hemorrhaging that brings blood to the skin -- thus the common name, red-leg disease. Red-leg, like AIDS, is a condition caused by the collapse of the immune system. A healthy frog should not succumb to massive Aeromonas hydrophila infection, just as a healthy human should be able to fight off the staph and strep infections that can be so devastating to AIDS patients. But unlike AIDS, no one knows what is triggering the toads' immune system breakdown; if it is a pathogen, it remains unidentified.</p>
        <p>Departing from several of her colleagues who are looking to prove that a specific environmental factor kills frogs outright, Carey says she believes the problem is more complex. Her hypothesis is that a combination of several factors -- be it ultraviolet radiation, acid snow or something yet unknown -- creates a degree of sublethal stress sufficient to cause the cascading breakdown of the immune system.</p>
        <p>With a $20,000 grant from the National Science Foundation, Carey is figuring out what a healthy toad's immune system looks like. Once she has this basic information, the next step will be to expose toads to acidified water, pesticides, ultraviolet light and rapid temperature change. The object is to try to find out which of these conditions, if any, will induce the collapse of toad immune systems. It's a large undertaking. "We don't really understand why when you and I get under a lot of stress, and then the stress is over, we immediately get sick. We don't understand that for us, let alone amphibians." She can't risk using the remaining western toads for her preliminary experiments -- their population is too fragile. Instead, she buys marine toads, natives of the Gulf Coast, from an animal supply house.</p>
        <p>In a way, Carey's research is as metaphorical as molecular. What if she does find that what's killing frogs is some mix of global environmental changes? Aren't they really, then, a disturbing sign about the health of the</p>
        <p>planet's</p>
        <p>immune system? "Frogs aren't the only thing disappearing," she says. "The more biological diversity we destroy, the less flexibility we have to create new food sources that can tolerate the environment we are creating."</p>
        <p>THERE WAS THAT unprecedented moment in amphibian history when a frog was America's sweetheart. But Kermit aside, frogs have never been much loved by people. Carolus Linnaeus, the 18th-century Swedish naturalist who developed the classification system of living things, once wrote, "These foul and loathsome animals are . . . abhorrent because of their cold bodies, pale color, cartilaginous skeletons, filthy skin, fierce aspect, calculating eye, offensive smell, harsh voice, squalid habitation and terrible venom."</p>
        <p>Frogs lack the qualities that seem to arouse human passion toward other species -- the wild variety and soaring ability of birds; the cuddliness or majesty of mammals. They are not the subject of riveting nature specials or glossy coffee-table volumes. They are of little economic value. For most urbanites and suburbanites, they are creatures long ago encountered at summer camp, dismembered in high-school lab -- and little thought of again. This distant relationship with humans has made quantifying their disappearance more difficult. Amateur bird watchers, for example, keep records, so there is abundant long-term data showing the decline of migratory songbirds.</p>
        <p>The first amphibians emerged around 350 million years ago. Depending on what you consider a frog, the first frogs appeared about 200 million years ago during the Triassic period or 180 million years ago during the Jurassic. Amphibians -- the word comes from the Greek "amphi" and "bios" (living a double life) -- are a bridge between the aquatic and the terrestrial, the link between fish and reptile. They include salamanders as well as frogs and toads.</p>
        <p>Herpetologists have not done a very good public relations job for their creatures; Linnaeus's attitude toward frogs has been passed down through the centuries. "This popular concept that they are imperfectly adapted, lowly vertebrates is garbage rooted in an archaic vision of evolution," says Stephen Tilley of Smith College. "They are a highly adapted group in their own right. They have extremely complicated behaviors, anatomies, physiologies and reproductive patterns."</p>
        <p>There are about 3,800 known species of frogs and toads that occur on every continent except Antarctica. As with much of life, frogs are more colorful, more diverse and more plentiful in the tropics. For example, the forests of Borneo are host to probably 200 species. Texas, which is of equivalent size, has only about 35. Paradoxically, during the 80's, when the great disappearances were first noticed, there was an explosion in species identification. Twenty percent of South America's frog species were named in that decade. "I'm just sitting here, looking at material I just brought back from Peru," says William Duellman, from his office at the University of Kansas. "They have apparently two new species of tree frogs that no one has ever collected before."</p>
        <p>For the past 30 years, Duellman has concentrated his research on South and Central America. He has a particular fondness for documenting frogs' astounding breeding strategies -- from marsupial frogs, which carry fertilized eggs in a pouch on their back that develop into tadpoles or froglets, to Darwin's frog, whose males incubate newly hatched tadpoles in their vocal sacs until they emerge as frogs, to a type of dart-poison frog, which deposits her tadpoles in water pooled in bromeliad leaves and then feeds them during their development with her unfertilized eggs.</p>
        <p>While Duellman says the frog situation in the environs of the Midwest seems "copacetic," he, too, has been perplexed as South American species he has studied for years appear to be dropping off the face of the earth. "About 1984 was when I started getting an inkling of declines in frog population in the Andes of Ecuador," he recalls. "You'd have frogs crawling all over one year, then the next year, none. That's pretty dramatic. What we're facing now are indications of a crisis. This is the first time in my tenure as a herpetologist we've seen anything of this type."</p>
        <p>TREADING carefully in the muck, Stephen Corn of the Fish and Wildlife Service reaches down and picks up a small, mottled, olive-green and brown creature found nowhere else on earth. This unprepossessing animal is one of the last surviving members of its species, the Wyoming toad. Corn looks at its front foot. "It's a male," he says. In the males of many species the "thumb" is dark and calloused-looking, an "all the better to squeeze you with my dear" adaptation. During mating, called "amplexus," the male grabs the female and mounts her; from similar-looking orifices, they simultaneously spew either sperm or eggs, which are fertilized outside the female.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for the future of the Wyoming toad, there have been no breeding females to grab for the past year. Adding to the problem has been an outbreak the past two years of red-leg disease.</p>
        <p>The toad's Latin name is Bufo hemiophyrs baxteri, after George Baxter, a retired professor of zoology at the University of Wyoming who first discovered the species -- actually a subspecies of the Dakota toad -- in 1946. Over the years, Baxter would take his classes to the dozens of sites of the animal's small range, 100 square miles around Laramie. Then, as the familiar story goes, in the mid-70's Baxter realized he was having a hard time finding his toads. By 1983, no one could find any; they were placed on the endangered species list, and presumed to be extinct.</p>
        <p>But in 1987, a sharp-eyed fisherman spotted some at a small, stocked fishing lake about 10 miles west of Laramie -- a last, holdout population of about 100 toads. Introduced fish do not seem to be the cause of this toad's demise. These amphibians produce fairly toxic tadpoles, unlike many species whose yet-to-metamorphosize young are prime fish morsels. This year, the Fish and Wildlife Service bought the fishing lake, as well as three nearby lakes and 1,800 acres around them, for about $300,000 -- one of the few Government refuges established for amphibians.</p>
        <p>The burly, bearded Corn is running an annual census of the toads. Three times last summer, he and a group of biologists came to the lake to capture every toad they could, photograph them and try to match their unique markings with previous toad mug shots. The population is considered too unstable for the more common identifying procedure of toe-clipping, or the new high-tech version being used on a population of western toads in which a transponder the size of a grain of rice is inserted below the skin.</p>
        <p>Corn is pessimistic about the future of Bufo hemiophyrs baxteri. This fall's population was 162, but then his research team found that an estimated one-quarter of the total had been hit by red-leg disease. And in 1989, an unusually cold winter probably killed off many of that year's young. Researchers believe that the female of the species breeds only in the third year of its life, so the 1989 die-off has left a female population that is too young to breed. As Corn holds the toad, a male he estimates was born in 1990, it emits a small, alarmed cheep. "They cheep when a predator or another male grabs them," he explains. "The breeding call is a low-grade whine." The male has had plenty to whine about the last few years. "This is one that tried to breed this year," Corn says, "but he couldn't find any girls."</p>
        <p>Such population fluctuations, as the Savannah River study shows, may have less serious consequences when there is a larger population of the species available to recolonize a site, but the Wyoming toad has no such backup. "I think realistically it's a matter of time," Corn says.</p>
        <p>Adding to the mystery of the Wyoming toad is the thriving population of chorus frogs that are hopping along in the same muck. This frog, bright green and skinny with dark green stripes, has an intense chirp of a breeding call; in fact, some herpetologists joke that these creatures have caused them some loss of hearing. What is the secret of their success? One irony-rich theory is that chorus frogs have shorter individual life spans than Wyoming toads. That is, they reach maturity and reproduce so quickly that they don't live long enough to succumb to whatever is doing in the toads. But dying young isn't a foolproof method of survival: The chorus frogs of eastern Canada now appear imperiled.</p>
        <p>WHAT WOULD HAPPEN if frogs died out? Understandably, that's a world few herpetologists care to imagine. One consequence, they say, may be a field day for insects; amphibians provide a far safer method for keeping insect populations in check than any chemical insecticide. Bangladesh, where native frogs have been nearly wiped out to appease the French appetite for their legs, appears to be reaping the consequences. "They now have increased numbers of mosquitoes and malaria," William Duellman says. And the indisputable importance of frogs to the food chain is not just a matter of what they eat, but who eats them; they are a major food source for many birds, fish, reptiles and mammals.</p>
        <p>But herpetologists say that simply saving frogs is not the point. "We don't know how many species can be lost before the system ceases to function," says Richard L. Wyman, adjunct associate professor of biology at the State University of New York at Albany. "But eliminate enough species and sooner or later it will cease to function. In the past, life responded to change through evolution, and that process depends on genetic diversity. If everything's the same, evolution stops. It's as if we are killing evolution itself."</p>
        <p>In his book on the history of earth's extinctions, "The Miner's Canary," the paleontologist Niles Eldredge writes, "Extinction resets the evolutionary clock." So far, six mass extinctions have reset the earth's evolutionary clock -- like the one that happened at the end of the Cretaceous period that took the dinosaurs with it. And some scientists, including Eldredge and celebrated biologist Edward O. Wilson of Harvard, insist we are in the midst of another cataclysm -- the first to be caused by man.</p>
        <p>Life has never stopped completely, however. A few species have always managed to cross the valley of death, and those that made it to the other side were able to begin the evolutionary process again. In light of that, David Wake is more sanguine about the frogs' future than ours.</p>
        <p>"They have been here hundreds of millions of years, humans less than five," Wake says. "I have no doubt there are survivors among them. I think they will do better than we will. I am totally convinced that frogs will be here when we are long gone."  Emily Yoffe, a former senior editor at Texas Monthly, is a writer who lives in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Emily Yoffe, a former senior editor at Texas Monthly, is a writer who lives in Los Angeles.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
