<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush-Kohl Talks Stalled on Farm Trade</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="516218"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROTECTIONISM (TRADE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOHL, HELMUT (CHANCELLOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protectionism (Trade)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920323T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DE1738F930A15750C0A964958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush-Kohl Talks Stalled on Farm Trade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A weekend of talks between President Bush and Chancellor Helmut Kohl of Germany, leaders of the two biggest exporting nations, ended today with no suggestion of progress on a dispute over farm goods that is blocking a global agreement to lower trade barriers.</p>
        <p>At a news conference at the White House, the two leaders expressed optimism that the proposed trade accord among 108 nations can be completed in mid-April, as negotiators have pledged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A weekend of talks between President Bush and Chancellor Helmut Kohl of Germany, leaders of the two biggest exporting nations, ended today with no suggestion of progress on a dispute over farm goods that is blocking a global agreement to lower trade barriers.</p>
        <p>At a news conference at the White House, the two leaders expressed optimism that the proposed trade accord among 108 nations can be completed in mid-April, as negotiators have pledged.</p>
        <p>But Administration officials have long said that the agreement hangs in part on the ability of Germany, the dominant force in the European Community, to persuade France and its other neighbors to break down a network of subsidies and trade barriers that protect farmers. 'Both Sides Have to Move'</p>
        <p>Mr. Kohl indicated today that his talks with Mr. Bush had produced no breakthrough. He also appeared to call for the United States to drop its demands for a more open European market, something Mr. Bush can ill afford in an election year in which he will depend on the farm vote. Canada and Australia have supported the United States in making these demands on Europe.</p>
        <p>After two days of talks with Mr. Bush at Camp David, Md., Mr. Kohl said, "We still have some questions to solve before we can reach agreement. When we talk about compromise, it means that both sides have to move."</p>
        <p>The talks also covered aid to the former Soviet republics and emerging democracies in eastern Europe, world environmental problems and preparations for a summit meeting of the seven largest industrial nations, scheduled for July 6 in Munich.</p>
        <p>Both leaders consider the trade agreement crucial both to promoting growth in developing nations and to preventing the world from breaking into warring economic camps now that the United States-Soviet rivalry no longer dominates international affairs.</p>
        <p>But Europe, led by France, has resisted demands by the United States, Canada and Australia that it open its borders more to farm imports and that it stop subsidizing exports like wheat. Eyes on Europe and U.S.</p>
        <p>Other nations are refusing to negotiate lower trade barriers in other areas, like manufactured goods, until the United States and Europe solve their differences.</p>
        <p>Administration officials expressed frustration with Mr. Kohl last week, saying that he had promised two years ago to press the French for concessions on trade but had failed to deliver.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kohl said today that he "will give a full report of these two days of talks" to other European leaders, "and we will once again try to find out where there is further room for negotiations."</p>
        <p>The two leaders also agreed to work with other Western nations at the Munich summit talks toward what Mr. Kohl called a "help for self-help" for Russia and the other former Soviet republics: technical assistance on problems ranging from unproductive farms to antiquated transportation networks to nuclear-reactor safety.</p>
        <p>That advice would supplement the international financial aid now being assembled to stabilize Russia's currency and finance new development, he said. And both aid packages would replace the hastily organized relief missions and injections of money that have kept the former Soviet states from collapsing further this winter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kohl also said that he and Mr. Bush agree on the importance of the summit meeting on environmental problems scheduled for June in Rio de Janiero. At the meeting, developing nations are expected to resist requests by the West to curb industrial pollution and to take other costly steps to combat global warming and depletion of the Earth's protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The Administration had sought until recently to discount the need for the session. Mr. Bush's first chief of staff, John Sununu, was openly skeptical of claims that some environmental problems were reaching a crisis, and the White House had reduced Mr. Bush's public involvement in foreign affairs after charges that he was paying too little attention to domestic issues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
