<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH LIKELY TO GO TO ECOLOGY TALKS</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WINES, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D9163CF934A35756C0A964958260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH LIKELY TO GO TO ECOLOGY TALKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WINES, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ending one of the more fractious debates within his Administration in recent months, President Bush is expected to announce soon that he will fly to Brazil for a United Nations environmental conference that his conservative advisers call a trap and his economic experts see as a fiscal debacle.</p>
        <p>The prospect of that announcement is likely to cheer a worldwide alliance of environmental advocates and political figures involved in environmental issues, who have long feared that Mr. Bush might single-handedly wreck the meeting simply by staying home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ending one of the more fractious debates within his Administration in recent months, President Bush is expected to announce soon that he will fly to Brazil for a United Nations environmental conference that his conservative advisers call a trap and his economic experts see as a fiscal debacle.</p>
        <p>The prospect of that announcement is likely to cheer a worldwide alliance of environmental advocates and political figures involved in environmental issues, who have long feared that Mr. Bush might single-handedly wreck the meeting simply by staying home.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have resorted to advertising on national television to press Mr. Bush to attend, and the issue loomed as an important factor in the presidential campaign. World's Biggest Polluter</p>
        <p>As the world's largest industrial economy and its largest energy user, the United States is both the Earth's most prolific polluter and far and away its prime source of clean-up technology and money, and thus is regarded as indispensable to the meeting, which convenes in Rio de Janeiro next month.</p>
        <p>Some of the same environmentalists pressing the President to attend, however, now complain that Mr. Bush's own hardball negotiating tactics may make the conference more a symbolic triumph than a substantive success. The President has dangled the threat of a boycott while seeking major concessions on environmental agreements to be signed in Rio.</p>
        <p>"It would be hard to imagine a more important event for the future of the global environment than this one," James Gustave Speth, president of the Washington-based World Resources Institute, said in an interview. "And so it's been one of the most discouraging experiences of my 10 years of working on international environmental issues to see my Government fail to give the kind of leadership that it gave 20 years ago."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has yet to declare his intention to attend the Brazilian meeting, although White House officials have said for some weeks now that a decision was close. But several Administration officials, who refused to be named, said in interviews this week that Mr. Bush almost certainly will attend the meeting, although his stay may be brief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's aides insist that the United States has been a leader in negotiations leading up to the meeting by resisting treaties that would dictate rigid goals and methods for reducing global pollution; at the same time, it has advocated the sorts of free-market environmental strategies that the Administration has tried to push at home.</p>
        <p>"My sense is that he will attend," said one Administration official at the center of the debate. "The President has nothing to be ashamed of -- we've got a good environmental record -- and we've told him he ought to make the case for the good methods of achieving these goals rather than the command-and-control methods they've been talking about."</p>
        <p>The meeting, formally called the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development, will be attended by at least 100 world leaders, including most Western leaders, and 6,000 experts on the global environment. Its centerpieces, now being negotiated, are a worldwide agreement to slow the production of chemicals that have accelerated the warming of the Earth's atmosphere and a second agreement on means to preserve plants and animal species.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has repeatedly voiced great skepticism about the conference. For most of this year, while his aides haggled over the fine points of treaties and declarations, he has publicly fretted that the conference would become a soapbox for poor nations to demand billions in environmental technology and cash that the White House neither has nor intends to pledge.</p>
        <p>Some aides also expressed alarm that the conference would commit the United States to actions intended to avert global warming, like reductions in emissions of carbon dioxide, that would cripple major industries at a time of fragile economic growth.</p>
        <p>"I am not going to go to the Rio conference and make a bad deal or be a party to a bad deal. I'm not going to sign an agreement that does not protect the environment, and the economy of this country," the President told business executives last month.</p>
        <p>But he is apparently going anyway, in no small part because a curious alliance of political advisers and policy experts has convinced him that he cannot afford to stay home.</p>
        <p>That alliance includes his campaign manager, Robert M. Teeter; his national security adviser, Brent Scowcroft; senior officials at the State Department and the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>It also features a rising young official at the Office of Management and Budget, Robert Grady, who was the architect of not only Mr. Bush's environmental policy but his use of pollution in Boston harbor as a campaign issue in the 1988 presidential election.</p>
        <p>That group is bound by an array of interests. State Department diplomats and Mr. Scowcroft are said to believe that Mr. Bush's absence would be an abdication of global leadership, since most major leaders will be at the conference and strongly support its goals.  The meeting also bears potentially huge political implications for Mr.  Bush. Aides believe that his failure to attend would blot his environmental record at a time when the issue has become a major factor in the votes of young people and in some large states, like California and Florida. His absence would weaken his ability to attack his likely opponent, Gov. Bill Clinton of Arkansas, whose environmental record has also been criticized.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
