<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Theory on a Plateau And the Climate Gains</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="567442"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TIBETAN PLATEAU</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TIBET</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURE (JOURNAL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUDDIMAN, WILLIAM (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAYMO, MAUREEN (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Tibet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1239F930A35752C1A964958260" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Theory on a Plateau And the Climate Gains</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DID the rise of the Tibetan Plateau over the last 40 million years cause the climatic changes and cooler temperatures that shape weather patterns prevailing today?</p>
        <p>The idea has found a growing acceptance since 1989, when Dr. William Ruddiman and Dr. Maureen Raymo first proposed it. The two researchers published a review article last month in Nature magazine that brought together findings from several scientific fields lending support to the Tibetan Plateau theory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DID the rise of the Tibetan Plateau over the last 40 million years cause the climatic changes and cooler temperatures that shape weather patterns prevailing today?</p>
        <p>The idea has found a growing acceptance since 1989, when Dr. William Ruddiman and Dr. Maureen Raymo first proposed it. The two researchers published a review article last month in Nature magazine that brought together findings from several scientific fields lending support to the Tibetan Plateau theory.</p>
        <p>The theory is born of a marriage of two disparate fields. Dr. Ruddiman, a professor in the Department of Environmental Sciences at the University of Virginia, has studied changes in weather caused by the rise of the plateau. Dr. Raymo, an assistant professor in the Department of Earth, Atmospheric and Planetary Sciences at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, has examined whether global cooling resulted from a decrease in carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"Our model shows physically caused changes of atmosphere, and Maureen comes in on the chemical side of the argument," Dr. Ruddiman said.</p>
        <p>Using a computer simulation model at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., Dr. Ruddiman and Dr. John Kutzbach of the University of Wisconsin studied the rise of the Tibetan Plateau and the plateau in the western United States. Removing Carbon Dioxide</p>
        <p>Before the rise of these plateaus, which began 40 million to 55 million years ago, the earth's climate was equable, warmer and more temperate throughout. As the plateaus rose, Dr. Ruddiman said, they changed the circulation and wind patterns, giving rise to the disparate vegetation patterns that characterize the Northern Hemisphere today.</p>
        <p>In addition, the rise of the Tibetan Plateau, which is one-third the size of the United States, created the monsoon in that region. The hot air that gathers at the top of the plateau rises, and is displaced by moist, cooler air from the Indian Ocean, which causes the annual rains.</p>
        <p>It is this heavy rain, in turn, which has helped to remove large amounts of carbon dioxide from the atmosphere, Dr. Raymo said.</p>
        <p>The carbon dioxide in the rain reacts with silicate rock that is exposed as the plateau continues to rise. The rain weathers the rock, and the minerals wash down river into the ocean, where sea animals use them to form their shells. The minerals are eventually deposited as limestone on the ocean floor. This process is called chemical weathering.</p>
        <p>"There is an incredible amount of rainfall in a region that is tectonically active," Dr. Raymo said of the Tibetan monsoon. "The tectonic forces are breaking up the rock, and this unique weather system is working on rocks that are being broken up."</p>
        <p>Dr. Raymo said the Tibetan Plateau and the Himalayas produce a large percentage -- up to a quarter -- of the rock sediment released into the world's oceans, though they make up only 5 percent of the earth's land mass.</p>
        <p>The removal of so much carbon dioxide from the atmosphere would help cool the earth's temperatures. Carbon dioxide traps heat in the earth's atmosphere, as glass does in a greenhouse. Temperatures today are 12 to 15 degrees Celsius cooler than they were 50 million years ago.</p>
        <p>As scientists have focused on a possible current warming trend, the "greenhouse effect," they have also turned back to the global cooling of the last 50 million years and questioned whether that was caused by a decrease in carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In the Nature article, Dr. Raymo pits her theory for decreasing atmospheric carbon dioxide against some models put forward in the early 1980's, which suggest that weathering is controlled by temperature changes, rather than vice versa. Dr. Raymo also argues that weathering increases as temperatures drop, while the other models suggest that weathering increases at higher temperatures.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Robert A. Berner of Yale University, one of the first researchers to offer a temperature-driven model, questioned Dr. Raymo's ideas.</p>
        <p>"They have created a false dichotomy," he said of Dr. Raymo and Dr. Ruddiman. "The idea of increased weathering due to mountain uplift is not antithetical to weathering controlled by changes in global temperature."</p>
        <p>He said he had already added uplift to his carbon cycle models in response to Dr. Raymo and Dr. Ruddiman's theory.</p>
        <p>In order to prove the theory, researchers will need to develop more reliable means of determining temperature change over time and the effects of weathering.</p>
        <p>"It's the type of thing that's very easy to say and very hard to test," said Dr. Peter Molnar, a senior research associate at M.I.T. who has studied climate and mountain uplift.</p>
        <p>Dr. Molnar said one of the key elements to explore in the coming years would be the timing of the rise of the Tibetan Plateau, since there is wide disagreement about whether uplift has been steady or much faster over the last 20 million years. Unfortunately, that aspect of the problem will continue to elude researchers until the Chinese or Tibetan Government allow them to work at the plateau.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
