<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outsider Steals Bush's Rose Garden Scene</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="524895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRUPP, FRED</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DE163EF933A05757C0A964958260" item-length="445" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outsider Steals Bush's Rose Garden Scene</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW ROSENTHAL,</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In its drive to convey the image of a President offering an agenda for the future, the White House sent President Bush into the Rose Garden today for a much-advertised announcement on what he called "one of my top priorities" -- Government deregulation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spoke at a sparsely attended ceremony, railing against the hazards of step stools as an example of over-regulation as he raced through his speech in a virtual monotone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In its drive to convey the image of a President offering an agenda for the future, the White House sent President Bush into the Rose Garden today for a much-advertised announcement on what he called "one of my top priorities" -- Government deregulation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush spoke at a sparsely attended ceremony, railing against the hazards of step stools as an example of over-regulation as he raced through his speech in a virtual monotone.</p>
        <p>And two of his top aides were left fuming in the White House driveway afterward while one of the guests denounced the President at microphones that were set up for businessmen who were supposed to heap praise on Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>The announcement was to be the apex of a week devoted to deregulation. Instead, it was a reminder of the trouble the White House is having with the nuts and bolts of the Presidency as Mr. Bush searches for a broader vision for his re-election campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush announced a 120-day extension of a 90-day moratorium on burdensome regulations that expired today. He then explained why that was necessary, using one of the oldest anti-regulation anecdotes in Washington, dating to the creation of the Occupational Safety and Health Administration in the mid-1970's.</p>
        <p>"If Government mandates make ladders more and more costly to consumers, just for example, more people will turn to cheaper substitutes," he said. "And they'll climb up on chairs or step stools, which are far less safe."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush offered other examples, including environmental regulations that he said hurt businesses.</p>
        <p>But that only provided ammunition for Fred Krupp, executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund. Mr. Krupp helped the Bush Administration draft its position on acid rain during negotiations on the 1990 Clean Air Act, but today he stepped to the microphones before anyone else could get there and said that the regulations' freeze was a "wholesale handout to the American business community" at the expense of clean air and water.</p>
        <p>C. Boyden Gray, the White House counsel, and Michael J. Boskin, Mr. Bush's chief economist, had rushed outside, expecting to find Drew Lewis, who heads the Business Roundtable, and Dirk Van Dongen, head of the National Association of Wholesaler-Distributors, telling reporters how much the moratorium would help the economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gray and Mr. Boskin retreated indoors as White House aides tried to figure out how Mr. Krupp got in. It turned out that he had been invited.</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. Boskin said that the White House "welcomes discussion of all views" but that Mr. Krupp represents the past. Just the kind of "old thinking," he said, that led to the collapse of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
