<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GROWING</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="551494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LILA WALLACE-READER'S DIGEST FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DA1E31F933A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GROWING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was hot in the forest, which can so often look just like a mess of plants. And the work itself looked hot and messy as two dozen high school students from the Bronx hacked away at porcelainberry vine and amur honeysuckle with weed wackers and hand clippers.</p>
        <p>"But we sing and we make jokes and the time flies by," said Angel Colon, 18, a senior at Morris High School. "Sometimes I feel kind of sad because I'm so into it and then it's time to go home."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was hot in the forest, which can so often look just like a mess of plants. And the work itself looked hot and messy as two dozen high school students from the Bronx hacked away at porcelainberry vine and amur honeysuckle with weed wackers and hand clippers.</p>
        <p>"But we sing and we make jokes and the time flies by," said Angel Colon, 18, a senior at Morris High School. "Sometimes I feel kind of sad because I'm so into it and then it's time to go home."</p>
        <p>As he talked, Angel didn't stop clipping the porcelainberry that climbed over his head into the trees. This invasive "exotic" -- it comes from Japan -- has no natural enemies like fungus or insects to check its growth, and it is choking out the native plants, like viburnum and mountain laurel, young pines and serviceberry.</p>
        <p>So all summer, Angel and his companions have been clearing the 60 acres of forest that wraps around the western edge of Wave Hill and down the eastern bank of the Hudson into Riverdale Park. They have been rebuilding paths, too, to stop erosion, and constructing rugged sluices along the ravines to guide the washouts that come from sudden rainstorms.</p>
        <p>It is the second summer of a five-year forest restoration program at Wave Hill and Riverdale Park, financed by the Lila Wallace-Reader's Digest Fund, though volunteers and staff members at the public garden have been working for more than 11 years to control the invasive species and to plant natives in their place.</p>
        <p>Angel has had a lot of jobs. "Supermarket, pizzeria, security guard, delivery man," he said. "You name it, I've been there. But this is the hardest job I've ever had. You feel like you keep cutting and there's always more."</p>
        <p>In the pizzeria, Angel worked in the steaming hot kitchen washing dishes all by himself. In the supermarket, he unpacked cans and boxes in the basement. It was kind of lonely and the time dragged. But here he works on a team and has a feeling of accomplishment.</p>
        <p>And being out in the woods, even with the bugs and the humidity, he is a part of something that he cannot quite put his finger on.</p>
        <p>"I like to use my hands," he said. "I used to help my father in Puerto Rico."</p>
        <p>Angel was born there, but his parents were separated when he was 2 months old, and his mother moved to this country. He did not see his father until he revisited the island when he was 13.</p>
        <p>"By then he had another son, so he wasn't very interested in me," Angel said. Still, the lush country, the woods and rivers crept into his mind. And in some way, being in the woods is a kind of homecoming.</p>
        <p>Down the bank, a tall young man named Winston Sealey pulled wild grapevines from a young serviceberry that was as bent over as an old woman from the weight of the wild vines. "You feel kind of sorry for the trees; they need our help," said Winston, who graduated this year from Grace Dodge Vocational High School. "But we need these trees to breathe."</p>
        <p>He could not identify more than a handful of trees at the beginning of the summer, but when you help plant more than 600 natives -- viburnums and witch hazel and yellow root and hickory -- you get to recognize bark and leaves, almost like the features of a friend's face.</p>
        <p>That is a Norway maple, said Edward</p>
        <p>Quainoo, who just graduated from Theodore Roosevelt High, taking a breather from rebuilding a path that leads down the bank from Wave Hill.</p>
        <p>"No, it's a sugar maple," said Alexander Reyes, a senior at DeWitt Clinton High. "You can tell by the undersides of the leaves. They're soft instead of shiny." And the points of the leaves look different.</p>
        <p>They talk like environmentalists -- about erosion control, diversity of species and global warming. But the forest is the teacher (with the help, of course, of college-age crew leaders and the project manager, Wendy Mukendi, a naturalist at Wave Hill). The young workers are learning respect for the natural world -- and for themselves.</p>
        <p>"The nice thing is, they tell you what to do, but they don't make you feel like you have to be watched over all the time," said Winston, brushing bark off his Malcolm X T-shirt. "They know we're good workers."</p>
        <p>Winston was almost ousted from the project this summer. "I like to make jokes," he said. "I don't like to be sad all the time. But one day, I kept fooling around when Wendy was talking, and she said I wasn't serious."</p>
        <p>Ms. Mukendi, who at 28 has worked with young people and conservation since she was a teen-ager herself in California, told him to take a look at himself. "Winston is the type of person who has a presence," she said. "People look up to him and he could be a leader."</p>
        <p>So she told him straight: "If he wanted to play around and be a kid, I didn't want him on the project. Because he was being less than his best."</p>
        <p>Winston went home and thought about it. And when he came back, he still made people laugh, but in a way that helped get the work done.</p>
        <p>"I've already asked Wendy if I could come back as a crew leader, but you have to be 21," said Winston, who is only 19. "The worst thing about this job is you can't come back once you've graduated."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
