<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Energy Prophet Who Guessed Right</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="559021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, S DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DC1E39F934A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Energy Prophet Who Guessed Right</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a way, S. David Freeman is a prophet coming into his own. As head of the Ford Foundation's energy project in the early 1970's, he correctly predicted that improved energy efficiency would be cheaper than continued expansion of power plants, and he predicted that American energy use, then galloping ahead, would reach a plateau by the late 1980's. At the time, oil companies and utilities said his idea was radical and wrong, but in fact it was not radical enough. When the plateau was reached, it was 15 percent lower than what Mr. Freeman had predicted.</p>
        <p>For the last two years Mr. Freeman has been general manager of the Sacramento Municipal Utility District (SMUD), which is scrambling to replace the power from the Rancho Seco nuclear plant, which the voters closed three years ago. But Mr. Freeman is still a radical prophet. And in an interview earlier this month, he backs new technologies for electricity production to replace nuclear power.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a way, S. David Freeman is a prophet coming into his own. As head of the Ford Foundation's energy project in the early 1970's, he correctly predicted that improved energy efficiency would be cheaper than continued expansion of power plants, and he predicted that American energy use, then galloping ahead, would reach a plateau by the late 1980's. At the time, oil companies and utilities said his idea was radical and wrong, but in fact it was not radical enough. When the plateau was reached, it was 15 percent lower than what Mr. Freeman had predicted.</p>
        <p>For the last two years Mr. Freeman has been general manager of the Sacramento Municipal Utility District (SMUD), which is scrambling to replace the power from the Rancho Seco nuclear plant, which the voters closed three years ago. But Mr. Freeman is still a radical prophet. And in an interview earlier this month, he backs new technologies for electricity production to replace nuclear power.</p>
        <p>Question: You have a toe in the water in every form of conservation and alternative generation. Why?</p>
        <p>Answer: We're going to end up by the year 2000 not only with a very much cleaner power system, but one where the price of electricity for the people of Sacramento County is going to be very reasonable and stable.</p>
        <p>If over the next 10 years, through our rebates and education and financing, we can displace the energy-consuming devices with much more efficient ones and reduce the per-capita consumption of electricity 10 or 20 percent, even if we raise the rates 5 percent, I've got happy customers.</p>
        <p>We're replacing the nuclear plant with cogeneration, using natural gas, plus a large chunk of advanced and renewable technologies that we're working to improve, so that when we have to commit to them, they can be fairly cost effective, especially if you pay any dues at all to the environmental costs.</p>
        <p>Q: Is this as if you set out to sea and lost sight of land and are going to innovate your way to the other shore?</p>
        <p>A: On the contrary. It's the people who feel that we're going to produce our way out of this problem with nuclear power and carbon-rich coal who are at sea. We have learned the one lesson that needs to be learned from the last 20 years, that nuclear power has proven to be an economic failure in the United States of America, that we can't afford it. The planet cannot afford the continued or increased production of coal or oil.</p>
        <p>Now we start off with the advantage of having some hydropower in our system, and some geothermal. We're taking care of all of our growth with efficiency improvements. And we're adding the windpower and a big block of renewables, and we have some geothermal. Add the whole thing up, we're going to be predominantly a clean utility.</p>
        <p>Q: SMUD wants to plant 50,000 trees a year. Why?</p>
        <p>A: When I came to Sacramento a little over two years ago, I bought a home in Arden Park, and some wise person, 20 or 25 years ago, had planted some Modesto ash trees that form a canopy. It was in June, and I'd just come from Austin, Tex. What I had was not a tree but an air-conditioner. It had the wonderful impact of getting better every year, not rusting.</p>
        <p>I asked the guys to come up with some numbers. The numbers were that in year 10, we had sizable savings. It was worth giving the trees away; they were saving electricity at less than 4 cents a kilowatt-hour, which was our economic screening device. It sounds like we're just a bunch of do-gooders, greenies, but this is a hard-headed, cost-effective part of our efficiency program.</p>
        <p>Q: Is SMUD's experience a guide for anybody else?</p>
        <p>A: I think so. No one that I know of has put down the simple number of what has nuclear power generated in cost per kilowatt-hour. But if you take all of the plants that were abandoned, plus the ones that were built, I would guess that that number is very close to 20 cents per kilowatt hour. Though you have the emotional believers in nuclear power making fun of solar enery and wind energy, their product hasn't cut it in the marketplace even though it's highly subsidized.</p>
        <p>Q: Can renewable energy sources compete economically?</p>
        <p>A: We may very well end up with less renewables and more efficiency. But that's a wonderful contest to have on your hands. I've got my energy-efficiency people now competing with the guys who develop the solar technologies. Whichever one wins, we're going to be a winner.</p>
        <p>We take these issues seriously. We think that's the foundation for our credibility in electrifying our transportation system. The electric system will reduce carbon tremendously because the electric motor is 98 percent efficient, and you don't run the car when it's idling. It not only cuts out local air pollution but it reduces the carbon emissions, not to mention ameliorating the problem of going to war  [ to secure the oil needed ]  to get to work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
