<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Era for Windmill Power</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="555067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRICITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINDMILLS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electricity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D81139F93BA3575AC0A964958260" item-length="1599" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Era for Windmill Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>LIVERMORE, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new generation of windmills that Don Quixote could never tilt at is ready to take its place as an economical and important source of the nation's energy.</p>
        <p>Because of striking improvements in technology, the commercial use of these windmills, or wind turbines as the builders call them, has shown that in addition to being pollution free, they can now compete with fossil fuels in the cost of producing electricity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new generation of windmills that Don Quixote could never tilt at is ready to take its place as an economical and important source of the nation's energy.</p>
        <p>Because of striking improvements in technology, the commercial use of these windmills, or wind turbines as the builders call them, has shown that in addition to being pollution free, they can now compete with fossil fuels in the cost of producing electricity.</p>
        <p>As a result, officials of utility companies from around the world have come, cash in hand, to California to inspect the tops of the ridges here at the Altamont Pass, for example, where new machines that look like sideways helicopters married to computers are harnessing the wind.</p>
        <p>In recent months, utilities serving upstate New York Illinois, Iowa, California and the Netherlands have decided to try to use the wind to produce electricity commercially. Competing With Fossil Fuels</p>
        <p>Kingsley E. Chatton, president of U.S. Windpower, which operates 22 new-generation windmills here, said the economics of wind power was at the point where it "will compete with fossil fuel." Others agree.</p>
        <p>Edgar A. DeMeo, in charge of renewable-energy research at the Electric Power Research Institute, a nationwide research consortium based in Palo Alto, Calif., said the work in California represented a significant advance. Mr. DeMeo's organization, which is supported by dues from utilities, carries out wide-ranging investigations on new technologies and ways to improve existing technologies involving all sorts of power sources.</p>
        <p>"We're beyond Kitty Hawk and into the jet age," he said.</p>
        <p>The turbines are a successor to the thousands of crude, flimsy windmills put up by optimistic pioneers of the early 1980's, machines that generated more tax credits than electricity and by now have largely disappeared. Capturing More Energy</p>
        <p>The new windmills capture far more of the wind's energy -- a surprisingly tricky feat. Wind varies greatly, but electricity must be so uniform that a user can, for example, set a clock by it. Uniformity has been largely achieved with durable, high-technology adjustable fiberglass propeller blades directed by computers.</p>
        <p>Wind turbines cannot replace fuel-burning plants completely because the wind cannot be ordered to blow. But it can be counted on enough over time to produce substantial amounts of energy and thus reduce conventional generation with its emissions of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, and carbon dioxide, the biggest greenhouse gas.</p>
        <p>Wind can also be used to save the water behind hydroelectric dams to last through dry seasons. In some locations, wind is reliable enough to be counted on at certain hours of the day or seasons of the year.</p>
        <p>The newest generation of windmills thus crosses an economic threshold that will allow their use in many areas of the country, although it will take several years before they produce a large fraction of the nation's electricity. Mr. DeMeo said he would not be surprised to see windmills generate 10 percent in 30 years -- about equal to the share now produced by hydroelectricity.</p>
        <p>He predicted that successive generations of windmills, building on the combination of sophisticated blades and computer control, would be bigger and would not need costly items like gearboxes, lowering costs further. A Cold, Noisy Wind</p>
        <p>On a recent morning here atop the Altamont Pass, about 30 miles east of San Francisco, the wind, at 30 miles an hour, was strong enough to whip open a car door as soon as the passenger began to open it. The turbines whined at different pitches, while the cold wind whistled through the 80-foot towers covering the bare hills. None of this seemed to bother the cows or the ground squirrels, but for a visitor it was altogether eerie.</p>
        <p>"Kind of a nice day, isn't it?" Chuck Ferguson, a field engineer, said as he opened the power electronics box at the base of one tower. It was generating enough electricity to run about 80 houses with their central air-conditioners going, meaning the 22 machines here can power thousands of homes and businesses.</p>
        <p>That's a lot of tilting.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chatton of U.S. Windpower said the cost of wind-turbine production, from capital investment to operation and maintenance, was about five cents a kilowatt-hour, roughly half the average retail price for power nationwide. A kilowatt-hour is enough electricity to light 10 100-watt bulbs for an hour. At an oil-fired plant, that much electricity costs about 5 cents in fuel alone, apart from capital investment, operation and maintenance expenses. So a power company that now uses oil could save money by building windmills.  Cheaper to Build Windmills</p>
        <p>At existing plants that run on coal and natural gas, generation costs are lower, and the money to build the plants has already been spent. But in many locations, building new wind turbines may be cheaper than building new fossil-fuel-burning plants.</p>
        <p>Coal-burning utilities with no need for new capacity also have an incentive to turn to wind. The Federal Clean Air Act limits their sulfur dioxide emissions, often requiring them to buy cleaner fuel at a premium, or to buy "emissions allowances" from utilities that are cleaner than the standard required. Windmills do not pollute.</p>
        <p>Not that they are completely benign. Some complain that windmills clutter up the landscape. And in some places, environmentalists have said windmill blades have killed birds.</p>
        <p>Here at Livermore, U.S. Windpower has painted some blades with a striped pattern to see if this will keep birds away. Company officials say they have not found dead birds at any of the machines, striped or not.</p>
        <p>Still, windmill use is spreading. U.S. Windpower, a subsidiary of the Kenetech Corporation, has recently announced these projects:</p>
        <p>*A joint venture with the Iowa-Illinois Gas and Electric Company to develop 250 megawatts worth of windmills, that is, about 600 windmills. A megawatt is a thousand kilowatts.</p>
        <p>*The sale of a 50-megawatt plant to the Sacramento Municipal Utility District, which is seeking to replace the output of a retired nuclear plant.</p>
        <p>*The construction of a 25-megawatt plant in Holland, with the power to be bought by Energiebedrijf voor Groningen en Drenthe, known as E.G.D., and the sale of a 50-megawatt plant to four utilities in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>U.S. Windpower also plans to have two turbines installed by Nov. 1 for the Niagara Mohawk Power Corporation in upstate New York, to see how they work in cold weather.</p>
        <p>The Iowa-Illinois and Pacific Northwest deals are particularly significant because of the role utilities will play, as owners or co-owners, rather than buyers of power. The utilities can also supply money for capital costs at far lower rates than start-up high-technology companies can obtain. The Last Windmill Maker</p>
        <p>U.S. Windpower, the only American company that builds windmills, has outlasted the others and has 138 patents on its equipment. Some smaller concerns, however, do assemble windmills from imported components. U.S. Windpower's parent, Kenetech, is owned in part by its management and in part by the Hillman Company, Allstate Insurance, F. H. Prince &amp; Company and a variety of other, smaller investors. Last year, the company had revenues of about $350 million.</p>
        <p>To produce alternating current at precisely 60 cycles a second, the standard for this country since early in the century, most traditional windmills have been designed to turn at only one speed. If the wind is not strong enough to turn the blades at that speed, no power is produced. If the wind blows more strongly, anything above the minimum amount of energy needed to produce electricity is wasted by the blades. Worse, on a really windy day the machines cannot work at all because they would be damaged.  Combining Two Technologies</p>
        <p>The new generation of machines is a marriage of aerodynamics and microelectronics. U.S. Windpower adapted the idea of variable-pitch blades from airplanes and developed a system to let the blades and the generator turn at whatever speed the wind allows. Computers open and close electronic circuits to smooth out the air flow over the blades and create electric current that alternates at the right cycles.</p>
        <p>The result: while older machines produce no power until the wind reaches 14 miles an hour, the new ones start making electricity at 9 miles an hour. The older ones shut down at 45 miles an hour; new ones work at up to 60.</p>
        <p>Another innovation is size, with new machines having a bladespan of about 100 feet, up from 56 feet in previous designs. That means four times as much power, at a total cost only about two and a half times more. There have also been improvements in the blades, which are now 2,000-pound fiberglass structures derived from sailboat masts.</p>
        <p>The ridges where U.S. Windpower's turbines stand are between California's sunny central valley and the cloud-bound coast. Every day, the sun warms the air in the valley and as the hot air rises, cooler air from the coast rushes in to fill the void. This gives the site more predictable winds than most other places.</p>
        <p>But the "wind resource," as proponents call it, is not peculiar to California. In fact, by national standards, California is not particularly windy: a strip of states from North Dakota to Texas has far more wind. And although electricity is usually generated within a few hundred miles of where it will be consumed, Texas alone could, theoretically, generate 36 percent more kilowatt-hours from wind than are used in the entire continental United States.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
