<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Finding on Sun's Gases May Shed Light on Ozone</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="535011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HATHAWAY, DAVID H (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DD1E38F933A25755C0A964958260" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Finding on Sun's Gases May Shed Light on Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBUS, Ohio, June 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The blazing gases of the Sun's surface continuously flow away from the solar equator toward the poles, a scientist for the space agency has discovered.</p>
        <p>The scientist, Dr. David H. Hathaway, detected the circulation pattern of solar gases by a subtle analysis of measurements made at the National Solar Observatory in Tucson, Ariz., by a special telescope and filter system that observes solar oscillations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The blazing gases of the Sun's surface continuously flow away from the solar equator toward the poles, a scientist for the space agency has discovered.</p>
        <p>The scientist, Dr. David H. Hathaway, detected the circulation pattern of solar gases by a subtle analysis of measurements made at the National Solar Observatory in Tucson, Ariz., by a special telescope and filter system that observes solar oscillations.</p>
        <p>The discovery is expected to shed light not only on the behavior of the Sun but also on its effects on Earth, including the ozone layer that protects living things from dangerous solar ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>At a meeting of the American Astronomical Society here Monday, Dr. Hathaway, of the National Aeronautic and Space Administration's Marshall Space Flight Center in Huntsville, Ala., showed that gases in the outer part of the Sun's convection layer move steadily away from the equator to the north and south poles, where they loop downward into the depths of the layer and reverse direction.</p>
        <p>Some of gases then move directly to the Sun's equator, where they climb to the surface and head poleward again, Dr. Hathaway said. But another part of the deep flow apparently emerges at the surface near a latitude of 30 degrees in both the northern and southern hemispheres, he said.  Circulation and Sunspots</p>
        <p>This upward-welling gas converges with gas flowing poleward from the equator, Dr. Hathaway said. It is in these mid-latitude regions of both the northern and southern hemispheres that sunspots form, Dr. Hathaway notes. He infers that there is a relationship between the sunspots and this circulation pattern.</p>
        <p>"This slow but steady flow should carry with it the magnetic fields that produce sunspots and solar flares," he said.</p>
        <p>Astronomers had previously discovered that the surface gases of the Sun are somewhat cooler than average in this mid-latitude zone. They had long suspected the existence of a poleward flow in the Sun's convection zone, but it proved extremely difficult to detect because this flow is masked by other activity on the Sun's surface. New Data Provides Evidence</p>
        <p>Dr. Hathaway worked with data recently produced by the first of six large instruments that together will make up the Global Oscillations Network Group.  This network measures what the astronomers call the "ringing" of the Sun as it oscillates in a variety of modes.</p>
        <p>The instruments can detect whether a given patch of gas on the Sun's surface is moving toward the Earth or away from it by measuring the shifting of spectral lines of light coming from the patch, known as the "Doppler shift." Like sound, light is shifted to a higher frequency when it comes from an approaching object, and to a lower frequency from a receding object.</p>
        <p>But the movement of any given patch of gas on the Sun is extremely complex. Part of this movement comes from the Sun's rotation, which carries along gas at the equator at a speed of about 4,500 miles an hour. Another component results from the upward-boiling motion of columns of gas, known as convection "cells," which create a granular appearance on the Sun's surface.</p>
        <p>The apparent movement of a patch of gas is also affected by the movement of the observer on Earth. The direction of tilt of the Sun's axis of rotation and the many modes in which the Sun vibrates further complicate the measurement of movement.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hathaway's project takes the effects of all these movements into account by calculating the contribution each one makes to the Doppler shifting of light from the Sun. The result is a computer-generated picture of the subtle poleward flow of gas, a mechanism that NASA expects will shed light on the complex dynamics of the Sun's outer layer. This, in turn, is believed to affect the Earth's atmosphere in a variety of ways, including the rate at which ozone is produced in the upper atmosphere. Overlap of Sun Cycles</p>
        <p>This ozone, formed under the influence of solar radiation, helps to shield the surface of the Earth from dangerous ultraviolet radiation. Scientists have demonstrated that chlorofluorocarbon chemicals released by human activity are breaking down the ozone layer faster than solar radiation can replenish the ozone.</p>
        <p>In another report based on data from the National Solar Observatory, Dr. Richard Altrock of the United States Air Force Phillips Laboratory described evidence of a cycle of solar activity that lasts much longer than the familiar 11-year variation between maximum and minimum.</p>
        <p>The Sun may undergo cycles of as long as 20 years, and this implies that one kind of cycle must overlap with another and that the cycles are not synchronized, Dr. Altrock said. During the last 19 years of observations, he said, sunspots associated with the 11-year cycle form at 30 degrees latitude, but other kind of magnetic activity may start at much higher latitudes as the result of other mechanisms in the solar engine.</p>
        <p>The difficulty in measuring activity at solar latitudes relatively close to the Sun's poles is that these regions are foreshortened for an observer on the Earth, and details are difficult or impossible to discern directly.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Altrock adopted the strategy of observing the faint solar corona, a shell of luminous gas visible only when the bright disk of the Sun is blocked out by a special instrument. The solar corona near the poles revealed a pattern of solar activity at latitudes of 70 or 80 degrees, suggesting a cycle of about 19 years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
