<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Artistic Visions Make a Case For a Troubled Environment</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="535773"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1538F937A25755C0A964958260" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Artistic Visions Make a Case For a Troubled Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIEN RAYNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAYNOR, VIVIEN</byline>
      <dateline>PELHAM</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WESTCHESTER artists are again coming to the aid of the environment. This time, there are 11 of them, mustered by Candace Taubner and Agnes Carbrey at the Art Center here, under the title "Against the Tide: Artists and the Water Cycle."</p>
        <p>Christy Rupp leads the way as the best-known of the group by opening the show with works she has displayed elsewhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WESTCHESTER artists are again coming to the aid of the environment. This time, there are 11 of them, mustered by Candace Taubner and Agnes Carbrey at the Art Center here, under the title "Against the Tide: Artists and the Water Cycle."</p>
        <p>Christy Rupp leads the way as the best-known of the group by opening the show with works she has displayed elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Two are large shells seemingly of a nautilus and a whelk and are "drawn" with welded steel rods and packed with plastic bottles. Beside them on the wall are fish painted on cardboard and cut out. All these are titled "Acid Rain Brook Trout," but the one extruding an unidentifiable but ominous form is subtitled "1987 Savan Chemical Spill Commemorative."</p>
        <p>Also by Ms. Rupp is the painted steel sculpture that is called "Flip Flop" and consists of an oversize sandal and syringe entangled with seaweed. Few of the artists leave anything to chance.</p>
        <p>Noting in her statement that water flows through "all living things," Jean Blackburn piles up glass boxes, the sides of which are covered with transparencies of the substance and the clouds it falls from.</p>
        <p>Sandy Gellis observes that water occupies 70 percent of the earth's surface and 65 percent of the human body and she presents a sheet divided into 124 five-inch squares imprinted by etching plates, some of them blank, others mottled black and gray. The artist says that a year of rain, snow, sleet and assorted pollutants left these impressions, thus implying that the acid falling from the heavens is concentrated enough to bite through the wax coating on the plates.</p>
        <p>Mary Ting takes the plight of the earth more personally than most by suspending a tangle of wires and tarry objects suggesting oil-soaked corpses of birds and explaining that they "bespeak despair" at the destruction of the biosphere.</p>
        <p>Connie Jost joins Ms. Ting by observing that many of the fish species that she has cast in latex are on the endangered list, which makes her a zoological record keeper. For this show, however, her findings serve as fashion accessories stuffed into the pockets of latex vests and, in the case of "Investment No. 3 Persian Gulf," accompanied by shells, seaweed and a rubber glove.</p>
        <p>Most people who contemplate the end of the world see it as the extinction of life. But for Gayil Nalls it would be the "death of birth." Though the stage at which this would occur is unclear, the artist expresses it by casting larger-than-life (or -death) spermatozoa in iron and arranging the results in a circle.</p>
        <p>Easier on the intellect (and eye) is Pamela Hollinde's "Migration Song," which is multiple woodblock images of birds and fish printed on handmade paper. These shapes, black silhouettes on grounds of streaky pink, lavender and green, are arranged in circles within circles to make a disk about five feet in diameter. With an eye to the decorative, Ms. Hollinde celebrates the cycles of life still to be found in the biosphere and its waters.</p>
        <p>To some extent, Noah Baen does the same thing in his Expressionist landscape, a cheerful image even though it includes belching smokestacks, a nuclear silo and a lot of suspiciously white water. Mr. Baen's point is that the scenery that once soothed now arouses fear -- about toxins visible and invisible.</p>
        <p>This is art in which you must search for the trouble, but where the works of Judith Belzer and Janet Culbertson are concerned, art and trouble exist in symbiosis.</p>
        <p>Ms. Belzer states that she depicts nature as neither ideal nor remote. Yet her closeups of marshland painted in browns, olive and yellow are far from dispassionate. In fact, the view of sunlight hitting reeds that curve in unison is both forlorn and menacing.</p>
        <p>Still, the most successful sermon in paint comes from Ms. Culbertson, both of whose canvases feature illuminated billboards.</p>
        <p>In one, the "advertisement" is for a creek lush and green in bright sunlight, but the surrounding landscape is dark with trash all the way to the horizon. In the other, the billboard depicts the trash-filled vista but itself stands in living landscape under a setting sun.</p>
        <p>In his middle to late years, Kandinsky produced abstractions that could serve as analogies to cellular formations -- and have done so in The Sciences, a magazine in which reproductions of high art accompany scientific texts as a pianist accompanies a singer. Michael Sandstrom takes the opposite tack by starting with photographs of diatoms and ending with -- if not Kandinskys -- handsome, rather celestial-looking arrangements of these organisms painted in bright colors against solid blue -- or purple -- backgrounds.</p>
        <p>Although not enough to inspire a "save the diatom" movement, Mr. Sandstrom's images afford relief to the more-environmental-than-thou atmosphere that seems inevitable in all such exhibitions.</p>
        <p>I left the show thinking about the close-to-insoluble problems facing the Environmental Summit in Rio de Janeiro, especially that which could be summed up as the nations who have gorged themselves on the world's goods telling those who have not to cool it. It would be hard enough preaching the environmental gospel on, say, Fordham Road, in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Some of the artists in "Against the Tide" seem as intent on saving their own souls as on saving the world. Nevertheless, a display like this at least encourages thought about the global crisis, whereas on television disaster becomes yet more entertainment.</p>
        <p>"Against the Tide" is on view through June 27. The number for more information is 738-2525.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
