<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skull Fragment Identified as Earliest Human Fossil</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KENYA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">YALE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILL, ANDREW (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1530F933A15751C0A964958260" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skull Fragment Identified as Earliest Human Fossil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists have identified what they think is the earliest known fossil of a member of the Homo line of human ancestors. They are dating it as 2.4 million years old, and so extending by half a million years the age of the genus that would lead to and include modern humans.</p>
        <p>The fossil, a fragment of a skull, has provided the first evidence that human ancestors in East Africa made the crucial transition to the larger brain genus Homo at a time coinciding with the earliest known examples of stone tools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists have identified what they think is the earliest known fossil of a member of the Homo line of human ancestors. They are dating it as 2.4 million years old, and so extending by half a million years the age of the genus that would lead to and include modern humans.</p>
        <p>The fossil, a fragment of a skull, has provided the first evidence that human ancestors in East Africa made the crucial transition to the larger brain genus Homo at a time coinciding with the earliest known examples of stone tools.</p>
        <p>The fossil also appeared to lend chronological support to a theory that the first species on the evolutionary path leading directly to modern humans appeared about 2.5 million years ago in a period of dramatic climate change.</p>
        <p>The discovery, reported in today's issue of the journal Nature, was made by scientists who took a new look at a three-inch-long skull fragment found near Lake Baringo in Kenya more than 25 years ago. On first inspection, scientists had been unable to date or classify the fossil, known only by its laboratory code, KNM-BC1. Wide-Based Cranium</p>
        <p>Taking advantage of advances in dating technology and fossil analysis, the scientists, led by Dr. Andrew Hill of Yale University, were able to determine that the specimen was embedded in volcanic ash 2.4 million years old and that its cranium had a relatively wide base and a few other characteristics typical only in the genus Homo.</p>
        <p>The bone fragment came from the right side of the cranium and includes the mastoid, earhole and the connecting point to the jaw. Dr. Steven Hill, an anatomist at Northeastern Ohio Universities College of Medicine in Rootstown, near Akron, said ridges and grooves on the inner side of the bone suggested some of the structure of the brain and helped place the fossil in the human evolutionary spectrum.</p>
        <p>The scientists concluded in the journal report that the specimen is "the earliest securely known fossil of our own genus found so far."</p>
        <p>As the path of human evolution is now delineated, the family that would lead to humans diverged from the apes 5 million to 9 million years ago. By 3.7 million years ago, these increasingly humanlike creatures walked on two legs but still had small skulls and brains similar to those of modern chimpanzees. These creatures are the earliest known species in the genus Australopithecus.</p>
        <p>Then the genus Homo diverged from Australopithecus from 2 million to 3 million years ago. The Australopithecine line became extinct about a million years ago. The earliest known Homo fossil, before the latest discovery, was 1.9 million years old. The earliest recognized species in the genus, Homo habilis, meaning "handy" man, emerged about 1.8 million years ago, judging from fossils found in Tanzania. Homo erectus, with an even larger brain, emerged 1.6 million years ago, and Homo sapiens, modern humans, evolved about 300,000 years ago. Uncertainty Over Species</p>
        <p>Dr. Hill said he could not yet determine the species to which the 2.4-million-year-old specimen belonged. "There's not enough to the fossil for us to be giving it a new species name, if it merited one, or assigning it to an existing species," he said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>In a commentary on the report published in the same issue, Dr. Bernard Wood, a paleontologist at the University of Liverpool in England, noted that scientists have for years considered the greater antiquity of the Homo line, possibly going back as early as 2.9 million years ago. But there has been no agreement on whether the earlier Homo was of the habilis species or a different, transitional species.</p>
        <p>"What is sorely needed," Dr. Wood wrote, "is more paleontological evidence from the interval between 2 and 3 million years ago."</p>
        <p>Both Dr. Wood and Dr. Hill's group of scientists noted the possible significance of the discovery in view of the theory, proposed in 1984 by Dr. Elisabeth S. Vrba , a Yale geologist, that the Homo line arose about 2.5 million years ago because of a sudden global cooling. That period of apparent environmental stress was marked by many extinctions and the first appearances of new species in the fossil record.</p>
        <p>Although they cautioned against jumping to any conclusions, Dr. Hill's group wrote, "It is intriguing to correlate the origin of our genus with global climatic shifts, possibly extraterrestrially triggered."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
