<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Optimism (Relentless) on Humanity</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="521819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, LEWIS (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FRAGILE SPECIES, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDE123CF935A25757C0A964958260" item-length="913" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Optimism (Relentless) on Humanity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Fragile Species  By Lewis Thomas 193 pages. A Robert Stewart Book/Charles Scribner's Sons. $20.</p>
        <p>Several of his books ago -- in "The Medusa and the Snail: More Notes of a Biology Watcher," to be precise -- Lewis Thomas revealed what was news to this reader at least (and evidently to "Bartlett's Familiar Quotations"): that the source of a lovely passage in T. S. Eliot's "Little Gidding" was the words of a 14th-century nun named Julian of Norwich: "But all shall be well and all shall be well and all manner of thing shall be well."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Fragile Species  By Lewis Thomas 193 pages. A Robert Stewart Book/Charles Scribner's Sons. $20.</p>
        <p>Several of his books ago -- in "The Medusa and the Snail: More Notes of a Biology Watcher," to be precise -- Lewis Thomas revealed what was news to this reader at least (and evidently to "Bartlett's Familiar Quotations"): that the source of a lovely passage in T. S. Eliot's "Little Gidding" was the words of a 14th-century nun named Julian of Norwich: "But all shall be well and all shall be well and all manner of thing shall be well."</p>
        <p>This might as well be Dr. Thomas's motto, particularly appropriate to his sixth and latest collection of essays, "The Fragile Species." For in the 14 pieces collected here he writes of the most dreadful prospects now facing human beings: AIDS and overpopulation, senile dementia and global warming, cancer and thermonuclear war, to name but the most obvious.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he doesn't always shine the brightest light on seeming human triumphs. We may think of medical science as progressive. But as he reveals in "Becoming a Doctor" and "In Time of Plague," it wasn't until the 19th century that doctors realized they had been mistaken in accepting Galen's second-century theory that disease was caused by misdistribution of "humors" in the body.</p>
        <p>And even now, he writes, there is less science in medicine than we might think. For instance: "My own theory is that the 20 percent drop in American coronary disease was the result of commercial television, which appeared in the early 1950's and has made a substantial part of its living ever since through the incessant advertising, all day and all night, of household remedies for headache and back pain, all containing aspirin."</p>
        <p>Yet despite all the downbeat news in "The Fragile Species," Dr. Thomas keeps smiling. There's cause for hope, he says repeatedly. The work on AIDS is "going beautifully," especially considering how short a time its virus has been recognized and how complex and baffling an organism it is. What's more: "I do not agree with this century's fashion of running down the human species as a failed try, a doomed sport," he reassures us. "At our worst, we may be going through the early stages of a species' adolescence, and everyone remembers what that is like."</p>
        <p>Does such optimism ever grate? Here and there it does a little, as when Dr. Lewis writes: "Looked at as larvae, even as juveniles, for all our folly, we are a splendid, promising form of life and I am on our side." But one forgives such fulsome cheeriness, even as one forgives the author for not achieving here the range of subjects of his earlier books and for repeating himself in these essays several times on such matters as the origin of life in bacteria 3.7 billion years ago and on how spirochetes may have specialized themselves.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lewis is so charmingly full of wonder at the good news he reads in the details of nature. He learns that moths can produce random flight patterns when closely threatened by attacking bats, and he proposes that what we have here is a rudimentary form of thought. He notices how adept young children are at speaking, and he concocts a persuasive fantasy of prehistoric youngsters gathering together and evolving the first human language.</p>
        <p>He reports on James Olds's experiments with the pleasure centers in rats' brains, and he concludes that the purpose of those centers is to record the pleasure of being alive. "Never mind the rules in this single case, make an exception here, allow for the pure fun that ravens have swooping down in the winds along the sides of mountain cliffs, allow for what cats do when not busy with serious cat business, make a provision for humans, especially young children playing, put in a mechanism that can handle the inside of the messages conveyed both by the 14th Quartet and the fourth movement of the Missa Solemnis, where the violin and the human voice suddenly turn into a single voice, and install the receptor for that word in that line of that poem, that jolt of that image."</p>
        <p>No wonder that for Dr. Thomas the bad news is the good news. So there was a time in recent natural history when the Crown of Thorns starfish was "spreading like a contagion and on the verge of eliminating all coral reefs in the Pacific." Creatures that run out of control like that run the risk of "crashing," the ecological jargon term for the catastrophic events that follow inevitably when species overextend themselves. "Human beings would do well to look very closely at this situation," Dr. Thomas writes, "and at others like it, and to mobilize the resources of marine science to examine the matter."</p>
        <p>Some mysterious force intervened and the starfish got out of its fix and settled back into its niche. People can learn from that, too, and no doubt will, the author concludes. Repeatedly, with such unusual leaps of perspective, he reassures us that while "we are only tentatively set in place, error prone, at risk of fumbling, in real danger at the moment of leaving behind only a thin layer of our fossils, radioactive at that," nevertheless all shall be well.</p>
        <p>The repetitions in "The Fragile Species" create a static quality not present in the best of Dr. Thomas's earlier collections, like "The Lives of a Cell" and "The Medusa and the Snail." Still, the curiosity and wonder present in these pieces convince you that the mysteries of nature are too deep for easy despair. All after all may indeed be well.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
