<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Does Your Garden Grow?; Stand Up For Hybrids</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BURPEE, W ATLEE, &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BALL, GEORGE JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DA153EF932A15750C0A965958260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Does Your Garden Grow?; Stand Up For Hybrids</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By George Ball Jr.;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BALL, GEORGE JR</byline>
      <dateline>WARMINSTER, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The controversy over hybrid versus nonhybrid vegetables and flowers for the home gardener has grown vigorously, a result of heavy fertilization by politically correct but scientifically uninformed garden pundits. At stake is not only the success and satisfaction of millions of home gardeners across the country but also the value that society has placed on scientific truth.</p>
        <p>Many gardening and environmental writers and editors tell fashion-conscious gardeners to grow nonhybrid plants and to avoid contemporary hybrids. They argue that hybrids threaten the planet's biodiversity by shrinking the gene pool of vegetables and flowers -- an argument that attempts to play as heavily on our emotions as the threat of global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The controversy over hybrid versus nonhybrid vegetables and flowers for the home gardener has grown vigorously, a result of heavy fertilization by politically correct but scientifically uninformed garden pundits. At stake is not only the success and satisfaction of millions of home gardeners across the country but also the value that society has placed on scientific truth.</p>
        <p>Many gardening and environmental writers and editors tell fashion-conscious gardeners to grow nonhybrid plants and to avoid contemporary hybrids. They argue that hybrids threaten the planet's biodiversity by shrinking the gene pool of vegetables and flowers -- an argument that attempts to play as heavily on our emotions as the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>However, the facts show the opposite to be true. Hybrids may represent a dramatic increase in genetic diversity. Plant breeders create and maintain enormous genetic variation, much of it valuable even if it is not released to the average gardener. These genes are preserved and studied by the Government, universities, seed companies and private and public gene banks.</p>
        <p>There is no question that old-fashioned, heirloom flowers and vegetables have an appealing quaintness that is in sync with the back-to-basics zeitgeist: "Save the 100-year-old eggplant!" However, any astute gardener will tell you that the benefits of a modern hybrid over an older variety are like those of a new car over a 1918 Model T. It might look nice in your garden but you wouldn't want to drive it across the country.</p>
        <p>Since hybrids are more resistant to garden diseases borne by insects and microorganisms than old-time nonhybrids, they require less, if any, pesticide. They produce more nutrients, sugars, acids and oils as well as a greater overall yield than heirloom varieties because of their robust, long lives. They are also more adaptable over a variety of environments.</p>
        <p>An antique or heirloom may have value as a novelty, such as an unusual shape, color or fragrance, but those qualities are often offset by inferior performance in the areas most important to many home gardeners: yield, resistance to disease and size of fruit or flower.</p>
        <p>Arguing in favor of horticultural science and technology is hard for two reasons. First, the believers are often blinded by their philosophical orientation. For the heirloom converts, there's no such thing as a good hybrid. Any vegetable or flower that has somehow interacted with technology is bad.</p>
        <p>Second, the average American is at least several generations removed from a farm or farming community and is thus more susceptible to anti-hybrid propaganda. By contrast, Europeans, who if they don't spend time on a farm are at least likely to live in a village or town that still depends on a farmer's market, generally can't wait to get their hands and trowels on the latest hybrid plants, flowers and vegetables.</p>
        <p>The creation of a new hybrid variety is a complex but traditional process. Plant breeders simply move the hybridization of nature along at a more rapid pace and in new directions. Plant breeders and seed producers serve their home gardeners by developing new products as well as maintaining old ones. For example, one of the most popular hybrid tomatoes on the market was created in 1948.</p>
        <p>To believe that the earth's genetic diversity is threatened by hybrids is much easier and thus more gratifying than learning the scientific facts involved in this complex issue. There is no good reason not to grow hybrids. If a gardener gets satisfaction from rearing the same carrot or rose his ancestors grew in the 1800's, so be it. But stop the hybrid-bashing.</p>
        <p>George Ball Jr. is chairman of W. Atlee Burpee &amp; Company, which breeds, produces and sells mostly hybrid and some nonhybrid seeds.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">George Ball Jr. is chairman of W. Atlee Burpee &amp; Company, which breeds, produces and sells mostly hybrid and some nonhybrid seeds.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
