<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary/April 18-23</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D71F38F936A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary/April 18-23</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hubert B. Herring</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ECONOMY Isn't That Bob Dole, With Democratic Feathers in His Mouth?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ECONOMY Isn't That Bob Dole, With Democratic Feathers in His Mouth?</p>
        <p>This round goes to Bob Dole. The Senate minority leader held his troops firmly in line last week to kill off President Clinton's economic stimulus bill, rejecting all compromises aimed at ending a Republican filibuster. But Mr. Dole, far from gloating, even seemed a bit embarrassed that he'd won -- making light of it as "just a bump in the road" for the President. That's a far cry from his recent colorful snipings. But the Democrats, furious at this Republican ambush, unleashed a harsh volley, with Senator Robert Byrd saying Republicans would accept "billions for unemployment, not one cent for jobs" and calling them "guardians of gridlock." And George Stephanopoulos, voice of the White House, said that for Mr. Dole, "playing politics is a lot more important than putting people to work." As the dust cleared, though, maybe there was a lesson for Mr. Clinton on how to deal with those folks on Capitol Hill. Greenspan Sees Low Inflation  If Alan Greenspan has anything to say about it -- and he has a lot to say about it -- there'll be no burst of inflation any time soon. In a speech to the Economic Club of New York, the Federal Reserve chairman said inflationary pressures were "difficult to imagine" with bank lending subdued and labor costs under control. And he vowed not to repeat the mistakes that led to high inflation in the late 70's. He clearly sees low inflation as crucial to a strong economy, saying that it has helped businesses focus on productivity, not raising prices -- and that the resulting jump in productivity could signal a lasting trend. Maybe in another year you'll be refinancing that mortgage yet again. In the meantime, the economy took another stumble. Durable-goods orders -- a key barometer of industrial health -- fell a surprisingly large 3.7 percent in March, the biggest decline in 15 months. John W. Kluge knows what minority youths sorely need: a good education. And he's putting a good chunk of his fortune where his heart is. Last week Mr. Kluge, chairman of Metromedia and one of the nation's richest people, gave Columbia University $60 million for minority scholarships. That will work out to yearly grants of $10,000 for 300 students. But what Mr. Kluge does</p>
        <p>not</p>
        <p>need is a campus building with his name on it. Columbia and other colleges have offered it, repeatedly, "but I'm not interested," he said. What he's interested in is minority scholarships, because, he said simply, "the need is there."  A Greener President  When the hard choices come, how much will Clinton stick up for the environment? Early signs weren't good, as the President backed away from a shift in Federal land policy and allowed a toxic waste incinerator in Ohio. But maybe a bit of Earth Day spirit got into him last week. Reversing two key Bush policy positions, Mr. Clinton said the United States would sign an international treaty protecting endangered species and would act to reduce global warming. Environmentalists, including Vice President Gore, cheered. "President Clinton has brought America back into step with the rest of the world on environmental protection," said Fred Krupp, executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund. Law Firm Pays Its Keating Dues  In 1989, the Government paid $2.5 billion to mop up after Charles Keating and his pals at Lincoln Savings. Uncle Sam was not happy. The Government got Mr. Keating behind bars, and keeps trying to get some money back. Last week, Jones, Day, Reavis &amp; Pogue, the giant law firm, agreed to chip in $51 million just before a trial was to begin to decide whether it should pay a lot more. Back in 1986, Jones, Day did some work for Lincoln -- and, a Government lawyer said, was told in "graphic and detailed terms" about Lincoln's shenanigans. It was a prime opportunity "to stop Mr. Keating in his tracks," he said.  INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Fiat Says Yes, There's a Problem  Maybe a healing process is beginning in Italy. For the first time, Gianni Agnelli, Fiat's chairman, publicly acknowledged corporate corruption and urged investigators to get on with it. For over a year, the scandal has mushroomed, with more and more tales of bribes to politicians for contracts, and Fiat, the giant of Italian business, was at the heart of it. Mr. Agnelli's admission was seen as an attempt to head off further damage. Eurotunnel's Coming, Someday  Some cynics, surely, think there will never really be a tunnel linking England and France -- believing England is destined to remain that sceptred isle, standing aloof from the rest of Europe. Cynics, take heart. Last week the planned opening of the delay-plagued Eurotunnel was delayed yet again. It was supposed to be Christmas, but now -- amid a dispute over $1 billion in costs -- it looks more like next year. So for a bit longer, that fortress built by nature is unscaled by engineers. A Trade Issue of Clinton's Own  Bill Clinton has talked tough on trade, but until now there's been no true taste of Clinton action. There have been disputes on autos and computer chips, but those were holdovers from the Bush days. Last week, the first trade issue taken up by this Administration came to the fore, and the result was mixed. There was an accord with Europe on contracts for work on electric utilities, but Europeans will be barred from bidding on other contracts. COMPANIES</p>
        <p>I.B.M.'s Been Down So Long . . .  Investors have gotten so used to large-scale grim news from I.B.M. that they looked at last week's $285 million quarterly loss and said, well, it could have been worse -- and bid the stock up by $1.375, to $50.625. But the news</p>
        <p>was</p>
        <p>bad -- as the market soon realized, with the stock slipping to $47.75 by week's end -- because the fine print showed that I.B.M.'s mainframe business had serious, lasting problems. These big machines have always paid I.B.M.'s bills, and though companies still buy them, competitive pressure has pushed prices down 30 percent in a year -- and there's no end in sight. On the plus side, I.B.M. cut operating costs by a sharp 9 percent in the quarter, but Louis V. Gerstner Jr., the new chief executive, still has a huge task ahead. Goodbye House, Goodbye Garden  Maybe home decorating, like housecleaning, is an endangered art as hassled multicareer families have less time to fuss about the nest. Maybe magazine advertising is not bouncing back all that quickly. Or maybe it's just that Conde Nast did not want to compete against itself. But whatever the reason, HG (born in 1901 as House &amp; Garden) is no more. Conde Nast, which just bought HG's healthier rival, Architectural Digest, said last week that HG's July issue would be its last. The publisher's financial reasons were certainly sound, but many found it hard to see an institution die. "It's the end of an era," one designer said. And one shocked journalist added, "It was like the death of a friend." Trade Center Tenant, at a Price  BankAmerica may have qualms about moving into the World Trade Center, but it wasn't admitting them last week when it signed a 15-year lease for eight floors. With improvements made since the February bombing, it is "the safest building in New York, and perhaps even in the country," the bank said. Pretty strong words. But then again, it was given some pretty strong incentives to sign that lease -- two years free rent, among other things. Fearing that other tenants might flee when their leases end, local officials badly wanted this new tenant -- and were willing to pay the price. "BankAmerica is sending an important message," Gov. Mario Cuomo said, seizing on the symbolism. "The World Trade Center is back." McDonnell Clings to the C-17  This much is clear: McDonnell Douglas badly wants to keep making the C-17 cargo plane, and the Air Force badly wants the plane, to replace an outdated model. But then it gets murky. At a hearing last week, House members accused John F. McDonnell, the chairman, of conspiring with the Government to bail out his company. But Mr. McDonnell strongly denied any wrongdoing. Even the company's earnings were questioned. On the eve of the hearing, McDonnell had reported a strong comeback, but some on the House panel expressed doubt about its recovery. A Five-and-Dime It's Not  What, exactly, is a store? A place to buy what you need and then quickly get on with your life? Get real. These days, "people are looking for fantasy and entertainment from retailing," a market researcher says. True, there are still those driven souls who dart into a department store for lipstick or a tie, but Takashimaya turns up its nose at them. "Jewelry and cosmetics on the main floor are tired concepts," said a merchandise manager for the Japanese retailer. So, out with tired concepts! Last week, Takashimaya opened a Fifth Avenue store whose first two floors are devoted to an art gallery and a soaring atrium. Will hurried New Yorkers make time for this? We'll see.  Look Who's Back: Sears  Six months ago, Sears, Roebuck posted its first loss since the Depression. It was smarting from an auto-repair scandal, its Allstate Insurance unit had taken a hurricane beating and its merchandising business was floundering. But last week those clouds vanished: Aided by a new vigor at Allstate and strength in retailing, Sears reported the highest first-quarter profit in its 106-year history. The stock, in the low 40's in October, closed the week at $53.50.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
