<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Head-On Look at the Ethics of Hunting Animals</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="627622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERASOTE, TED</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BLOODTIES: NATURE, CULTURE AND THE HUNT (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED91531F93AA3575BC0A965958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Head-On Look at the Ethics of Hunting Animals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bloodties Nature, Culture and the Hunt By Ted Kerasote Map. 277 pages. Random House. $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bloodties Nature, Culture and the Hunt By Ted Kerasote Map. 277 pages. Random House. $22.</p>
        <p>It is easy enough to dismiss as crackpot some of the thinking that opposes the killing of animals. Ted Kerasote, a nature writer, cites examples in his sensitive report "Bloodties: Nature, Culture and the Hunt," a book that ends up cautiously on the side of hunting. There are, for instance, his nonhunting neighbors where he lives in western Wyoming who take the lead of the civil rights and feminist movements and argue that killing animals -- whether for food or sport -- is, as the author paraphrases the case, "an expression of a long-standing patriarchal culture's enslavement of a minority group that must be ended." As this argument concludes, "Animals, like others who have been disenfranchised, must be given rights."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerasote makes a powerful case against such fanaticism. He once tried avoiding meat but found that there was no escape from killing animals. To embrace what he calls supermarket vegetarianism was to condone a system that does its own form of killing, by clearing land for farming, by creating "ecological traps" that attract and kill a variety of small creatures, by using pesticides, by carrying produce to market and by developing the fossil fuels needed for that transportation.</p>
        <p>"In short," he writes, "being a supermarket vegetarian didn't take me out of the web in which animals are constantly dying to feed humans, it merely put their deaths over the horizon, making them, in the bloodless jargon of cost-accounting, externalities." Planting an organic garden wasn't the answer either, since like so much of the world, his part of the country wasn't suitable for such farming, and to drive somewhere to buy organic produce would only increase its fossil fuel cost.</p>
        <p>No, Mr. Kerasote found that to kill a 150-pound elk would expend 79,000 kilocalories of fossil fuel energy according to an analysis done at Cornell University; whereas to consume the caloric equivalent in Idaho potatoes would use up 151,000 kilocalories of fossil fuel energy. Better to kill the elk, so long as he was honorable about it and looked the dying elk in the eye.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Kerasote makes the case against hunting too, against the wanton harvesting of specimens just for the sake of cutting another notch in your sense of dominion. In a section that drips with subtle disdain, he introduces us to several trophy hunters hell-bent on shooting one of every creature that boarded Noah's Ark, and the biggest possible one at that. He even accompanies a few of them on a trip to Siberia to shoot Marco Polo sheep, and reports how one intrepid hunter killed an animal after it had been herded into shooting range by helicopters, no less.</p>
        <p>So where is one to turn for an answer to the question, Is it wrong to kill animals? The power of "Bloodties" lies in the way it forces the reader to feel the inescapable tragedy of being both part of nature and outside of it, of having to participate in the violence of sustaining life and yet having to be conscious of the pain inevitably inflicted. The narrative begins with the author's visit to an Eskimo village in Greenland, among people whose only food source is the narwhals, seals and polar bears they can kill.</p>
        <p>These people were slow to accept the author because they feared he was with Greenpeace, an environmental organization that, he says, brought economic hardship to the Eskimos by opposing the clubbing of juvenile harp seals in Newfoundland and thereby inadvertently affecting the killing of ringed seals in Greenland. But gradually they came to trust him, and took him along on some of their dogsled hunts.</p>
        <p>Next he turns to the trophy hunters, one of whose number, an Alaskan billionaire, says of hunting: "To me it's the same as business. . . . It's goal seeking, it's thrilling, and it gives an extreme sense of self-reliance, self-accomplishment, overcoming almost any difficulty, because the hunter has to go across the river and up the mountain."</p>
        <p>Finally, Mr. Kerasote embraces a synthesis, which unfortunately turns out to be none other than himself. This is not as pompously self-serving as it may sound. By looking inward, he can better describe the respectful form of hunting he advocates than if he had interviewed some like-minded person. But his prose in this final section suffers a little.</p>
        <p>As a nature writer, he takes as one of his models Henry Beston's classic work, "The Outermost House" (1928), an account of a year spent living in a shack on a beach in Cape Cod. Mr. Kerasote's acute awareness of his surroundings goes well with the excitement of the Greenland hunt: "Over the ice cap the full moon had risen and, to the northwest, the sun skidded along the horizon, tinting the frozen sea the color of wild roses. When it set, the sky above it turned lilac, then lavender, then a clear and profound celestial blue containing one bright star."</p>
        <p>But when he is back home in Wyoming, going through the daily rounds of a freelance writer, his sensitivity to nature can teeter toward tedious self-indulgence: "Spring! Spring at last! Spring at home, after so many months away. It's good to lie in bed in the morning, underneath the warm elk hide, as the first pale light takes away the darkness, and listen to the deer chewing the rose hip bushes just beneath the bedroom window, while the caw of ravens floats faintly in the air."</p>
        <p>Still, it never takes long for Mr. Kerasote to turn up some new and curious aspect of the hunting debate. And when he has finished summing it all up, it's hard to argue with his final objective. This is to remove the gratuitous forms of pain from the world, and learn to inflict only "the instrumental pain caused by the honest biological clamor of our guts' wanting to be fed . . . which seems irreducible."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
