<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Large Role For Russia Expected On Station</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL SPACE COOPERATION AND VENTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE STATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD71539F930A25757C0A965958260" item-length="1704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Large Role For Russia Expected On Station</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STRIKING new details have emerged about the plan announced last week to invite Russia's collaboration in designing a sharply smaller outpost for American astronauts. It now appears that Russian aid will amount to far more than mere ideas, as a pivotal ground rule of NASA's proposed redesign makes clear.</p>
        <p>If at all possible, the redesigned space station is to fly in an orbit where the angle of inclination to the equator is 51.6 degrees, according to NASA experts and internal agency documents. That seemingly obscure figure speaks volumes, for it is a path through space that has been used exclusively by Moscow for virtually all its manned voyages.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STRIKING new details have emerged about the plan announced last week to invite Russia's collaboration in designing a sharply smaller outpost for American astronauts. It now appears that Russian aid will amount to far more than mere ideas, as a pivotal ground rule of NASA's proposed redesign makes clear.</p>
        <p>If at all possible, the redesigned space station is to fly in an orbit where the angle of inclination to the equator is 51.6 degrees, according to NASA experts and internal agency documents. That seemingly obscure figure speaks volumes, for it is a path through space that has been used exclusively by Moscow for virtually all its manned voyages.</p>
        <p>For reasons of orbital geometry, the United States would have to adopt such an unusual orbit if it were to rely on the Russians for substantive help in launching a joint space venture. America used that orbit only once before, in 1975, when Apollo and Soyuz capsules joined briefly some 140 miles above the Earth to mark a thaw in the cold war.  Daniel S. Goldin, Administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, said yesterday in an interview that teamwork with Russia and use of the 51.6-degree inclination were requirements stemming from the need to boost the space station's capabilities while cutting its construction costs by up to two-thirds. The highly inclined orbit, he said, would give the revamped outpost greater powers of Earth observation and pave the way for wide Russian participation.</p>
        <p>"It's not absolutely necessary but it opens up all the new vistas," he said of the 51.6-degree orbit, adding that its utilization was a general goal of the redesign process. "We said, 'Shoot for 51.6. If you can't get it, tell us the best you can do.' "</p>
        <p>The space agency's 50-member redesign team was informed of Moscow's entry into the turbulent nine-year history of the space station by Dr. John H. Gibbons, the White House science adviser, on April 3 as President Clinton and President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia discussed the issue at the Vancouver summit meeting.</p>
        <p>"The overall goal of the redesign effort is to develop options for reducing station costs," Dr. Gibbons told the team, an agency statement made public last week showed. "Careful integration of Russian assets could be a key factor in achieving that goal."</p>
        <p>In recent years Moscow and Washington have increasingly teamed up on relatively minor space projects. But experts say that designing and building a space outpost together, if it comes to that, would be a watershed in East-West relations. Competition to Cooperation</p>
        <p>"We have implemented a process that a few years ago would have been inconceivable," said a White House official, who spoke on condition of anonymity. "It's ironic," the official added, "but cooperation with the Russians may help us save a program that conflict with the Russians begat," referring to the space program's cold war roots.</p>
        <p>The space station effort was begun in 1984 by President Ronald Reagan and was to be a high-technology triumph over Moscow, which had a long history of success with outposts for astronauts. Although design work has so far consumed more than $8 billion, the planned outpost has long been mired in technical and political problems. Most recently it was envisioned as a 350-foot-long structure costing some $31 billion, its price seeming to rise almost daily.</p>
        <p>The United States is turning to the Russians for help mainly in an effort to cut costs and only secondarily to advance a post-cold-war agenda, the White House official said. Moscow itself has independently and vigorously promoted such an East-West realignment.</p>
        <p>On March 16, two top Russian officials, Yuri Koptev, head of the Russian space agency, and Yuri Semenov, head of Russia's main rocket builder, NPO Energia, wrote Mr. Goldin to propose a celestial union. 'They Want You to Buy'</p>
        <p>"Billions of dollars" could be saved, the Russians wrote, by the "unification of efforts" of the two nations to realize a "joint advanced orbital station." They made no mention of the beneficial effects that Western currency could have on idle Russian production lines.</p>
        <p>"When the Russians say they want to cooperate," noted the White House official, "they mean they want you to buy their hardware."</p>
        <p>The two Russian officials called for a physical merger in space of an upgraded version of Moscow's station currently in orbit, Mir, with elements of the Western plan, including an American laboratory, the European laboratory "Columbus" and a Japanese experimental module. The outpost could house three astronauts by 1997 and, with further expansions, nine astronauts by the year 2000. Offering Better View</p>
        <p>The Russians proposed an orbital inclination of more than "50 degrees, providing essential capabilities for Earth surface observation." This is considered a strong selling point given the push for global data on climate change and habitat destruction.</p>
        <p>A law of orbital geometry says the area of Earth surveillance increases with rising inclination. This is because the angle at which an orbiting spacecraft crosses the equator is just another way of stating extremes of latitude it hits as the Earth turns beneath it. For instance, an outpost orbiting at 50 degrees inclination to the equator would travel across the Earth's face as high as 50 degrees north latitude in Canada and as low as 50 degrees south latitude near the tip of South America. A smaller angle of inclination means less of the Earth's surface is visible.</p>
        <p>Although the American space shuttles are usually launched due east from Cape Canaveral over the Atlantic, at an inclination of 28.5 degrees, they can go as high as 57 degrees and still avoid land. The shuttles have done so occasionally for Earth-observation missions and other reasons.</p>
        <p>In theory the Russians have less flexibility. They fly their manned missions from the Baikonur Cosmodrome in Central Asia, which is located at 45.9 degrees north latitude. If spacecraft flew due east from there, getting the greatest possible boost into space from the Earth's own rotation, they would have an orbital inclination of 45.9 degrees. But they never do since this path would take them over neighboring countries. Avoiding China and Mongolia</p>
        <p>Instead, the Russians fly slightly higher at an inclination of 51.6 degrees, staying over their own territory during the fiery ascent and avoiding the risk of dropping astronauts or spent rocket stages on Mongolia or northern China.</p>
        <p>Just as the Russians lose some rotational boost by flying a more northerly course, so will the Americans if they link up with the Russians in Moscow's traditional space orbit. In fact, NASA experts say shuttles launched from Cape Canaveral would loose about one-third of their payload-lifting power. This is clearly a drawback of the cooperative plan, since the shuttle's powers are already overtaxed for the planned lifting of big outpost modules.</p>
        <p>One aid would be the debut of more powerful shuttle booster rockets, which were once envisioned as starting work around 1996 but now have been delayed to the year 2000.</p>
        <p>James E. Oberg, an American specialist on the Russian space program and author of "Red Star in Orbit," said a different kind of aid would be for the Russians to move toward the preferred American orbit by bringing their own inclination down to 45.9 degrees, the best one for Russian rockets energetically. 'Cold War Fossil'</p>
        <p>"Operationally, dynamically and politically," he said, "51.6 degrees is a cold war fossil."</p>
        <p>But experts at two NASA centers said an inclination of 51.6 degrees was now a ground rule in station redesign. And late last month agency headquarters in Washington issued an internal document stating that the new outpost should have an "orbital inclination to provide dual access by multinational launch systems."</p>
        <p>Such an orbit is a necessary but not sufficient condition for close East-West teamwork, so exactly what will become of Moscow's participation in the effort remains an open question.</p>
        <p>Experts say a 51.6-degree orbit could allow the Russians to do as little as making symbolic visits to an American station, or as much as becoming major partners in constructing and putting it into orbit. Mr. Goldin noted in the interview that the orbit would also allow stranded American astronauts to be rescued by Moscow. Not weighing such merits, he said, "would be irresponsible."</p>
        <p>An intermediate possibility for cooperation was sketched out in the October 1992 issue of Aerospace America by Dr. Jerry Grey, director of science and technology policy for the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics, a professional group based in Washington.</p>
        <p>He posited that American shuttles from Cape Canaveral would ferry astronauts to an orbit of 51.6 degrees but carry no cargo, and that the 20-story Russian rocket known as Energia, the world's most powerful, would blast off concurrently loaded with American station gear.</p>
        <p>Only four such pairs of launchings would be needed to produce a full station, he wrote, in contrast to more than 30 shuttle flights if the United States did the job alone. Shuttle flights are estimated by private experts to cost about $1 billion a piece, and Energia flights about half that, so the savings on transportation alone could in theory amount to about $25 billion.</p>
        <p>Dr. Grey noted, however, that the Energia is a new vehicle whose reliability is unproven.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he said in an interview, "a whole bunch of questions exist about whether we can rely on the Russians with their economy the way it is," adding, "And integrating the space programs would not be easy. You run into severe engineering problems."</p>
        <p>But if these and other questions can be addressed with open-eyed realism, he said, "the benefits of a truly international space program far exceed the costs."</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin, in his prepared statement on April 4 at the end of the Vancouver meeting, said the foundations had been laid for a peaceful new era of space exploration.</p>
        <p>"We decided to cooperate in this area and decided to join forces," he told reporters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton echoed those remarks, saying he saw "real opportunity for joint activity."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
