<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Moon May Save Earth From Chaotic Tilting of Other Planets</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARS (PLANET)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DD163CF931A35750C0A965958260" item-length="1598" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Moon May Save Earth From Chaotic Tilting of Other Planets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF there is a kind of music of the spheres, as Kepler suggested centuries ago, it could be thought of as the accompaniment to the solar system's stately cotillion of planets gliding around the Sun, spinning and sometimes nodding, most with partners, each responding in subtle ways to all the others.</p>
        <p>Orderly and predictably harmonic this may seem, and in the short term it is, but scientists analyzing the motions of planets with powerful computers are realizing that there is a certain cacophony, as it were, to the music of the spheres. In the new scientific lexicon, the solar system is chaotic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF there is a kind of music of the spheres, as Kepler suggested centuries ago, it could be thought of as the accompaniment to the solar system's stately cotillion of planets gliding around the Sun, spinning and sometimes nodding, most with partners, each responding in subtle ways to all the others.</p>
        <p>Orderly and predictably harmonic this may seem, and in the short term it is, but scientists analyzing the motions of planets with powerful computers are realizing that there is a certain cacophony, as it were, to the music of the spheres. In the new scientific lexicon, the solar system is chaotic.</p>
        <p>This means that over great spans of time an accumulation of small gravitational disturbances from neighboring planets, combined with their own slightly wobbly rotations, can cause significant fluctuations in the orbits and orientations of the planets. The changes are exponential, and this compounding effect leads to striking consequences over time scales of four million years. Scientists conclude that such behavior is essentially unpredictable.</p>
        <p>It also means that the orientations of the spin axes of the inner planets, including Earth, have changed chaotically at some time in their history. Mars is still undergoing wild variations, which could explain its apparent history of extreme climate swings. Earth may be spared a similar fate because of the stabilizing influence of the Moon, the only large satellite in the inner solar system.</p>
        <p>These implications of chaos in the solar system were described by a team of French scientists led by Dr. Jacques Laskar of the Bureau des Longitudes in Paris, reporting research results two weeks ago in the journal Nature, and by Dr. Jack Wisdom, an astronomer at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, writing in the current issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>The relatively new science of chaos explores the connections between different kinds of irregularities. Motions in nature, like flowing water, jagged lightning strokes and cloud formations, may appear random and disorderly, but on closer examination, can be seen to be quite deterministic, since their motions are fully determined by preceding events in accordance with physical laws. Only recently have high-speed computers enabled scientists to conduct the lengthy, complex calculations that revealed the chaotic motions of planets.</p>
        <p>"Ten years ago, no one in planetary science knew about chaos," Dr. Wisdom said in an interview. "Everyone thought of the solar system as evolving very regularly."</p>
        <p>Dr. Stanton J. Peale, an astrophysicist at the University of California at Santa Barbara, credited Dr. Wisdom's research in the early 1980's with "opening the door to our understanding of the chaotic nature of planetary motions."</p>
        <p>Of all the inner planets, Mars is experiencing the most volatile effects. Because of its place and the timing of its orbit, complex gravitational perturbations combined with the mechanics of the planet's own wobbling rotation produce a phenomenon called resonance. Dr. Wisdom likened this to someone on a swing pumping his legs back and forth. If done at certain frequencies, the pumping will change the swinger's trajectory. In the case of Mars, the gravitational tug of other planets, coupled with its own speed of rotation, set up resonances which, over time, change the shape of the planet's orbit and the tilt of its spin axis.</p>
        <p>The computer simulations by Dr. Wisdom and his graduate student, Jihad Touma, show that under the influence of perturbations over the last 100 million years the tilt of the Martian spin axis has probably fluctuated from 10 degrees to 50 degrees away from a line perpendicular to the plane of the planet's orbit.</p>
        <p>Such extreme variations in the obliquity, as this tilt angle is called, should give planetary scientists new insights into the history of Martian climate, particularly what appear to have been the periodic appearance and disappearance of the polar ice caps. The most profound questions about Mars are how water could have flowed over the planet in the past, as spacecraft photography of the terrain indicates, and thus if life could have evolved there at some time.</p>
        <p>Dr. Carl D. Murray, an astronomer at the University of London, wrote in Nature that new research of the obliquities of planets "is of fundamental importance to any study of climatic change."</p>
        <p>A planet's obliquity is responsible for the seasons. If a planet spun exactly perpendicular to its orbit, the maximum amount of sunlight would always fall on the Equator instead of alternating between northern and southern hemispheres.</p>
        <p>But if the obliquity is large, the poles would get much more sunlight, which on Mars could evaporate the ice caps, releasing water over the otherwise arid surface and more carbon dioxide into the air to produce a denser atmosphere. Signs of Unstable Climate</p>
        <p>Photography by Mariner 9 and the two Viking spacecraft in the 1970's showed the deposits of ice and soil at the Martian polar caps to be layered like uneven stacks of pancakes. This suggested to scientists that the ice sheet has expanded and retreated many times as a result of periodic climate shifts.</p>
        <p>Currently, the Martian obliquity is about 25 degrees, an angle not much greater than Earth's, which is 23.5. Earth's obliquity never varies by more than plus or minus 1.3 degrees.</p>
        <p>Early this century, the Yugoslav astronomer Milutin Milankovitch demonstrated mathematically that these and other variations, however slight, could have dire climatic consequences, presumably accounting for a succession of ice ages in the recent geological past.</p>
        <p>It could be worse. In their computer studies, Dr. Laskar and his colleagues found that without the Moon, the obliquity of Earth might have undergone chaotic variations of up to 85 degrees. This might have occurred in the early solar system before Earth captured the Moon.</p>
        <p>Being so large and close, the Moon exerts enough gravitational pull not only to move the oceans in tides but also to provide a restraining torque on the planet's propensity to tilt. "In this sense," the French researchers concluded, "one might consider the Moon to act as a potential climate regulator for the Earth."</p>
        <p>Although the scientists did not say that a moonless Earth would necessarily have been lifeless, it would certainly have been a bleaker place -- and not just for lovers and song writers. This may yet come to pass. As Dr. Murray noted in an article commenting on the findings, the Moon is moving away from Earth at the rate of an inch a year and consequently, one theory predicts an obliquity near 60 degrees some two billion years in the future. Sharp Tilt of Venus</p>
        <p>Dr. Laskar said the Moon's influence on Earth's climate would need to be "taken into consideration when estimating the probability of finding a planet with climate stability comparable to the Earth's around a nearby star."</p>
        <p>Among the other planets, the obliquities of Mercury and Venus may have varied in the beginning but are now stabilized mainly because of their proximity to the Sun. The axial tilt of Venus, though, is an extreme 178 degrees, perhaps the result of a collision long ago with a large body or else some early chaotic processes, scientists said.</p>
        <p>In this as in many other respects, distant Pluto is poorly understood. But in an earlier study by Dr. Wisdom and Dr. Gerald Jay Sussman, a computer scientist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, the motion of Pluto was found to be "robustly chaotic." Why and how is not known.</p>
        <p>The four giant gaseous planets -- Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune -- seem to be massive enough to withstand many of the chaotic tendencies. Their obliquities are essentially stable, Dr. Laskar's group determined, and can be considered to be virtually the same as when these planets formed, though something must have dealt Uranus a smashing blow that knocked it on its side. But the motions of the Jovian satellites exhibit some apparently chaotic behavior.</p>
        <p>Although current studies of the planetary dynamics depend on computers crunching numbers for months on end, observations of one oddly shaped satellite of Saturn could give scientists a glimpse of the real thing, chaos in accelerated action. The satellite, Hyperion, is so rotund at its equator and flattened at its poles that it looks like a squat hamburger. It has an eccentric orbit and is influenced strongly by resonances produced by the gravity of Titan, Saturn's largest moon.</p>
        <p>"All this causes Hyperion to tumble chaotically and its spin axis to change to a wide range of positions," Dr. Peale of Santa Barbara said in an interview. "It's something we can watch on a short time scale and see changes resulting from chaotic motions." Prediction Is Confirmed</p>
        <p>Dr. Peale has reason to appreciate that planetary dynamics can be curiouser than any music of the spheres imagined by Kepler. In 1979, Dr. Peale recognized that Io, the large moon closest to Jupiter, is being pulled to and fro by the gravitational effects of Jupiter and its other large moons. This, he concluded, should produce powerful tidal forces on Io's interior, generating heat that could fuel volcanoes.</p>
        <p>Confirmation came a few days after Dr. Peale's prediction was published. A Voyager spacecraft photographed volcanic eruptions on the surface of Io.</p>
        <p>Current research may not foreshadow similar discoveries. "It's just fun, a very interesting mathematical problem," Dr. Peale said. "It's also a new way to know more about the evolution of the solar system and perhaps learn how to infer planetary systems elsewhere."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
