<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Violent World of Corals Is Facing New Dangers</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="590680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CORAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REEFS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HURRICANES AND TROPICAL STORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D71638F935A25751C0A965958260" item-length="1719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Violent World of Corals Is Facing New Dangers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DENSELY abloom with a wealth of life unsurpassed for bizarre beauty, coral reefs seem to exist in a state of dreamy tranquillity. Not so.</p>
        <p>The reef is in truth a realm of violent struggle and constant disruption. Coral colonies wage unrelenting chemical warfare on each other, their polyps stinging, dissolving and poisoning each other. Bigger reef creatures savage large chunks of colonies and fill the water with toxins. Sooner or later, an irresistible force like a hurricane or a change in sea level lays waste the whole teeming ecosystem and the corals must rebuild.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DENSELY abloom with a wealth of life unsurpassed for bizarre beauty, coral reefs seem to exist in a state of dreamy tranquillity. Not so.</p>
        <p>The reef is in truth a realm of violent struggle and constant disruption. Coral colonies wage unrelenting chemical warfare on each other, their polyps stinging, dissolving and poisoning each other. Bigger reef creatures savage large chunks of colonies and fill the water with toxins. Sooner or later, an irresistible force like a hurricane or a change in sea level lays waste the whole teeming ecosystem and the corals must rebuild.</p>
        <p>But rebuild they do, and this resilience is at the heart of a dispute among marine biologists over the contribution of human activity to the stresses on coral ecosystems.</p>
        <p>One school of thought holds that corals worldwide are now in serious peril because of human assaults like global warming, overfishing, pollution and physical destruction of reefs by fishermen and tourists.</p>
        <p>An opposing school holds that while some reefs are indeed in big trouble, many others remain pristine and even the damaged ones have adapted in the past to natural forces at least as destructive as human activity.</p>
        <p>Any serious threat to corals would be an ecological tragedy. The biological diversity of coral reefs compares with that of tropical forests. Reefs themselves, built from the calcified skeletons of polyps, are the largest structures created by life. The many strange toxins evolved by reef denizens for their biological warfare hold considerable promise as treatments for various human diseases.</p>
        <p>For all these reasons, there has been a heightening of scientific interest in corals of late, including an outpouring of research on coral ecology and chemistry.</p>
        <p>Coral colonies, each composed of innumerable tiny, tentacled polyps, take the forms of trees, shrubs, fans, plates and huge boulders. The phantasmagoria of shapes creates a habitat for other marine creatures like fish, lobsters, sponges, mollusks, octopuses and sea anemones.</p>
        <p>Competition with no quarter given is the rule in this interdependent but mutually hostile world. When polyps in one colony come face to face with another in a constant competition for scarce space, they expand their bodies to engulf their rivals and exude digestive juices that turn the competitors to jelly.</p>
        <p>As a countermeasure, polyps in the second colony grow "sweeper tentacles" studded with special stinging organelles that "zap the neighbors," says Dr. Judith Lang, a reef ecologist at the Texas Memorial Museum at the University of Texas.</p>
        <p>Still other polyps enshroud their enemies in a sticky mucus that dissolves the tissues.  Combat with toxins is also thought to be a common mode of warfare, though the toxins have proved hard to pin down in actual use.</p>
        <p>Coral reefs may be one of the most naturally poisonous environments on earth. One study found that 73 percent of 429 species of exposed invertebrates commonly occurring on Australia's Great Barrier Reef were toxic to fish.</p>
        <p>Although much remains unknown about how the toxins are used, they have "tremendous potential" as pharmaceuticals, said Dr. Drew Harvell, a coral reef ecologist at Cornell University. For example, Dr. Harvell said, some toxins produced by soft corals "are anti-inflammatory agents, some have potential as being effective against AIDS and some as anticancer drugs, and that's just one class of organisms."</p>
        <p>Because of this great potential, the reefs have recently become prime prospecting grounds. Many potentially useful compounds have been discovered and are now undergoing further testing, said Dr. David J. Newman, a chemist in the National Cancer Institute's Natural Products Branch. The center has been collecting about 1,000 samples of coral-reef organisms a year for the last five years. The prospecting effort is still young; the journey to market for any drug derived from natural sources typically takes 5 to 15 years.</p>
        <p>In nature, the coral toxins may play an indirect but key role in the reef ecosystems' resilience in the face of disturbance. Dr. Robert Endean and Dr. Ann Cameron of the University of Queensland in Australia, who have long studied the Great Barrier Reef, postulate that extensive boulder-like coral colonies have been able to exist continuously for hundreds and even thousands of years because they are so successful in using toxins to ward off predators.</p>
        <p>Because the shape and mass of these long-lived "persister" colonies protect them from the storms that devastate more fragile corals, Dr. Endean theorizes, they form the staunch backbone of the reef ecosystem. They must be protected from destruction by humans at all costs, he warns. Harmful Human Activity</p>
        <p>Scientists generally agree that humans are putting serious stress on at least some coral reefs. Sediment from dredging and agricultural runoff, sewage, chemical pollution, dynamiting of reefs by fishermen, damage from boat anchors and scuba divers, shell-collecting, mining of reefs for calcium deposits and overfishing that shatters ecological checks and balances all play a role.</p>
        <p>"I don't know how to state it in strong enough terms," Dr. Harvell said of the destruction. There has been especially widespread degradation in the Philippines and other Southeast Asian waters. "It's not just that there aren't any fish on these reefs," Dr. Harvell said. "That's bad enough, but there aren't any corals on many. You don't want to panic everybody that the world is falling apart, but some places are."</p>
        <p>But there is disagreement about the extent of the degradation, about the ability of the reefs to withstand human-induced stress and about whether some of the damage is caused by humans at all.</p>
        <p>Some scientists contend that the threat is global. But "very few people have looked at reefs all over the world and have the big picture," said Dr. Richard Grigg of the University of Hawaii, who edits The Journal of Coral Reefs. While it is true that the human impact has been heavy in Southeast Asian and Caribbean waters, he said, reefs in wide areas of the Pacific remain pristine. "There is no one answer," he said. "You have to look at it case by case."</p>
        <p>Some threats seem more general, but there is doubt as to whether humans are responsible. In recent years, corals in several parts of the world have turned white and died.  Coral polyps are largely nourished by carbon compounds produced by algae in their cells. The algae also give the polyps their brilliant colors.</p>
        <p>Some scientists testified before Congress that because the algae die when the water gets too warm, human-induced global warming was a likely cause of the bleaching. But many other scientists say that while warmer water does cause coral bleaching, it is too soon to tell whether the oceans are warming as a result of waste industrial gases that trap heat in the atmosphere. The warmer water, they say, could be a natural phenomenon.</p>
        <p>Some scientists also say human activity is to blame for widespread damage to corals by a population explosion of the highly predatory crown-of-thorns starfish. The starfish's own natural predators were decimated by overfishing, it is contended. Other scientists, noting that the starfish population is just as out of control on pristine Pacific reefs, argue that natural fluctuations in animal populations are at work.</p>
        <p>But since some human-induced damage is indisputable, does it portend disaster?</p>
        <p>One body of thought, with which Dr. Endean has been associated, sees reef ecosystems as being so delicately adjusted to natural conditions that disturbance by humans could impoverish them indefinitely. An opposing body says that far from being in fine balance, reefs are always recovering from some natural disturbance or other, and that there is little effective difference between natural disruptions and those caused by humans.  "Nature can be and often is more perverse than man," Dr. Grigg said. Destruction From Nature</p>
        <p>For example, in 1980 Hurricane Allen smashed vast stretches of tree-like staghorn corals in the Caribbean, causing a total collapse of this formerly dominant ecosystem element along the north coast of Jamaica. And at the end of the last ice age, most of the world's corals died when rapidly rising sea waters shut out the sunlight on which their life-giving algae depend. Most of today's reef ecosystems developed after that. The oldest are about 8,000 years old.</p>
        <p>The question of coral reefs' hardiness depends on what time scale is considered, said Dr. Jeremy B. C. Jackson, a senior scientist and coral reef ecologist at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute in Panama. Corals are among the most ancient of animals. On the longest scale, they have also been among the most fragile; living reefs have disappeared from the planet entirely as part of more general extinctions of life in the remote past. But for the last million years, despite temporary setbacks like the one at the end of the last ice age, they have generally been remarkably stable.</p>
        <p>On the scale of a human lifetime, Dr. Jackson said, it may look as if "the sky is falling, and in some cases with good reason." That is, he said, if a hotel owner in Grand Cayman or Jamaica suddenly finds that the coral reefs that attract tourists have become trash, things look pretty bad and unstable.</p>
        <p>From this viewpoint and that of other people who have much to lose from reef destruction, say scientists on all sides of the question, what humans are doing to the reefs is serious. The longer the stress continues, the longer natural recovery is delayed. Assessing the Threat</p>
        <p>But Dr. Grigg, no adherent of doomsday thinking, posed this question: "How many corals are extinct from either natural or human-induced changes in the last couple of hundred years?" And then he answered: zero.</p>
        <p>Even so, he said, a new coral-reef doomsday is not unthinkable. Although corals over the last several million years have survived "all manner of catastrophes," including meteor and comet impacts and some 20 ice ages, he recently wrote, this proof of robustness "may hold little consolation" in the face of a vast and rapid expansion of human population.  Unless the expansion is reined in, both corals and people themselves could be threatened; and that, he wrote, may be the real truth spoken by the reefs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
