<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Beat Swords Into Other Swords</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="616674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="IDEAS &amp; TRENDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY EQUIPMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">USSR (FORMER SOVIET UNION)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DA113EF933A15755C0A965958260" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Beat Swords Into Other Swords</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the Soviet threat gone, American military commanders are scrambling to find new missions for some of their fiercest and most costly cold war weapons.</p>
        <p>The Navy is deploying marines aboard aircraft carriers. Submarines built to hunt Soviet subs now practice disgorging commandos near beaches. And the Air Force wants to spend $3 billion to retool the B-1B bomber, which was designed to drop nuclear bombs on Moscow, to drop laser-guided bombs in local battles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the Soviet threat gone, American military commanders are scrambling to find new missions for some of their fiercest and most costly cold war weapons.</p>
        <p>The Navy is deploying marines aboard aircraft carriers. Submarines built to hunt Soviet subs now practice disgorging commandos near beaches. And the Air Force wants to spend $3 billion to retool the B-1B bomber, which was designed to drop nuclear bombs on Moscow, to drop laser-guided bombs in local battles.</p>
        <p>Shrinking military budgets drive these changes as commanders try to adapt what they have to new threats instead of junking what it took billions to build.</p>
        <p>But it has not been an easy transition. Congress, having already spent $27 billion on nearly 100 B-1B's that have never flown in combat, is balking at sinking any more money into the troubled aircraft.</p>
        <p>Navy officials grumble that bumping one squadron of F-14's to make room for 600 marines turns the mammoth carrier Theodore Roosevelt into the Navy's largest transport ship. The marines could help evacuate an embassy or rescue downed pilots, but not much else. Even Gen. Carl E. Mundy Jr., the Marine Corps commandant, expresses concern that the carrier's most potent strike force -- attack aircraft -- is being halved to accommodate a small number of marines.</p>
        <p>And some officers fear that landing fighters on the same deck with large troop-carrying helicopters -- which normally operate off helicopter carriers -- is inviting disaster. "They're running risks on the operational side to protect themselves on the political side," said Loren B. Thompson, deputy director of Georgetown University's National Security Studies Program.</p>
        <p>When weapons cannot be adapted, new missions are found for them.</p>
        <p>The new C-17 cargo plane was originally conceived to fly troops and gear to the front lines in Europe. Now the Air Force and Army point to conflicts in Bosnia and Somalia as examples of places where the C-17 can land on primitive airfields with more cargo than a C-130.</p>
        <p>By 1999, the Defense Department plans to slash the number of Navy attack submarines to 55 from 88 now.  Before 1991, the submarines spent less than 1 percent of their time practicing launching cruise missiles, clearing mines and inserting troops; the rest they spent mostly on their primary mission: hunting Soviet subs. Now they spend about 25 percent on other missions. The Monster Doesn't Exist</p>
        <p>Some Pentagon critics think the conversions are wasteful desperation moves.</p>
        <p>"We have an awfully lot of weapons that were designed to confront a Soviet monster that doesn't exist anymore," said John Isaacs, president of the Council for a Livable World, an arms control organization. "What use are these things in Serbia or Somalia? A major focus of the Pentagon should be retiring weapons."</p>
        <p>The military has often tried to save money by upgrading weapons -- like the B-52 bomber, which has been in use since the 1950's -- but it has stepped up the practice as budgets shrink. The Army puts new software in its Patriot missiles about once a year. The new Apache/Long Bow helicopter has been fitted with new radar and targeting devices. The Air Force has ordered the Lockheed Corporation to give its new air-to-air fighter, the F-22, the ability to strike ground targets too.</p>
        <p>In other cases, the military is making its highest-tech weaponry more useful in small conflicts by giving battlefield commanders access to information previously available only to intelligence agencies. For example, satellites that were built largely to keep an eye on Soviet nuclear missiles were used to detect the launches of much smaller Scuds in the Persian Gulf war, and the information was channeled not just to command centers in Omaha, but to Patriot batteries in Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>In Bosnia, Air Force pilots are using satellite-generated maps to pick drop zones for relief supplies. Soldiers in Somalia rely on satellite telephones to communicate from remote villages. "What you have is a radical reorientation of space to help the war fighter," said Gen. Charles A. Horner of the Air Force, the head of the United States Space Command in Colorado Springs.</p>
        <p>Now environmental scientists and other researchers are getting their hands on some of the data generated by spy planes and reconnaissance satellites. Planes that take photographs also take air samples of methane and carbon dioxide, implicated in global warming.</p>
        <p>Cloud-piercing radar can spot fires and logging in tropical forests. Other satellites can measure snowfall and follow climate changes.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department also has 21 navigational satellites, called the Global Positioning System, that allow pilots and ships to locate themselves within a matter of yards. The commercial applications for the navigational aids may ultimately surpass any military use. Surveyors, archeologists and recreational boaters are snapping them up.</p>
        <p>IDEAS &amp; TRENDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
