<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television; In 90 Minutes, 500 Years' Worth of Destruction</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY (CIA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOME BOX OFFICE (HBO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC BROADCASTING SERVICE (PBS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EARTH AND THE AMERICAN DREAM (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADAM SMITH (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDD103EF931A15757C0A965958260" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television; In 90 Minutes, 500 Years' Worth of Destruction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Earth Day message from HBO is that America was a much pleasanter land when it was inhabited by more bison than human beings, and when none of the latter were white Europeans.</p>
        <p>If pretentiousness were an ecological threat, "Earth and the American Dream" would face a heavy fine for fallout. Moving through 500 years of assaults on the environment in 90 minutes, Bill Couturie (who won an Academy Award for his 1989 documentary, "Common Threads: Stories From the Quilt," a work about AIDS) exploits visual effects the way American industry has exploited natural resources.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Earth Day message from HBO is that America was a much pleasanter land when it was inhabited by more bison than human beings, and when none of the latter were white Europeans.</p>
        <p>If pretentiousness were an ecological threat, "Earth and the American Dream" would face a heavy fine for fallout. Moving through 500 years of assaults on the environment in 90 minutes, Bill Couturie (who won an Academy Award for his 1989 documentary, "Common Threads: Stories From the Quilt," a work about AIDS) exploits visual effects the way American industry has exploited natural resources.</p>
        <p>The program begins with highly unnatural-looking nature scenes that are meant to evoke the idyll that was supposedly North America before the invasion by the European horde. These are accompanied by portentous quotes from famous figures (Washington, Toqueville, Thoreau, Audubon) read in a somewhat hard-breathing way by even more famous actors (Edward Asner, Alec Baldwin, Ellen Burstyn, Gene Hackman, Anthony Hopkins, Dustin Hoffman, Jeremy Irons, you name them).</p>
        <p>The westward movement is pictured as an invasion, every ground clearing an attack on the environment. A few old photographs, particularly one of a man, presumably a buffalo hunter, standing like a conqueror on a small mountain of buffalo heads, make the point better than all the fancy shots of sparkling streams and splashing fish. One real picture is worth a thousand imitations.</p>
        <p>The program picks up as the 20th century comes in, when by a striking use of newsreels and, later, television commercials, set to peppy tunes, Mr. Couturie catches America's unstoppable drive to produce and its insatiable capacity to consume, with small regard for the long-range cost. One generation's progress becomes another's problem. A picture of a pile of junked automobiles echoes that pile of slaughtered buffalo.</p>
        <p>In the final minutes, the documentary goes global, hopscotching the world for catastrophe. It is a phantasmagoria of oil spills in Alaska, famine in Ethiopia, disasters in Chernobyl, Bhopal and elsewhere, to a litany of sound bites about global warming, toxic dumping and acid rain. (Pictures of the homeless are dropped in, although the connection between their troubles and global warming remains smoggy.) The prolonged conclusion offers prophetic preachments from friends of the earth like Rachel Carson and Jacques Cousteau, and ends, as it began, with an appreciation of nature by an American Indian.</p>
        <p>Presenting American history from the perspective of the land itself, although no longer novel, can still be enlightening, but "Earth and the American Dream" suffers from videoitis, a tendency to lay on visual stunts to disguise the conventionality of the ideas. Still, what reviewer wants to come across as a fan of strip mining, clear cutting, ocean dumping, leaded gasoline and holes in the ozone? So, happy Earth Day. 'Adam Smith'  PBS, tonight at 8 P.M. (Channel 13 in New York)</p>
        <p>"Now that the cold war is over, do we need a Central Intelligence Agency?" The question is posed by tonight's timely edition of this lively PBS staple. The most definite answer comes from Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan. The ever-eloquent New York Democrat says that since the agency has been "getting everything wrong for 30 years," this is a good time to hand out medals and send the snoopers into early retirement.</p>
        <p>But others, like Adm. Stansfield Turner, a former Director of Central Intelligence, supports turning the agency's attention to economic intelligence, which he grants means spying on friends and allies, like Japan and Germany, who, no one doubts, are spying on American business. Senator Dennis DeConcini, the Arizona Democrat who heads the Senate Intelligence Committee, also seems to be inclined toward some such effort.</p>
        <p>The half-hour, dotted with pictures of lock picking and a shady-looking photographer at work, ends with the reminder that the Soviet K.G.B., by whatever name, is still busy. The hope is expressed by a Russian critic that for a change, it is spying on the United States economy instead of on its own people. Earth and the American Dream  HBO, tonight at 8</p>
        <p>Produced by Bill Couturie and Janet Mercer; written by Mr. Couturie and Ken Richards; directed by Mr. Couturie; edited by Gary Weimberg; music by Todd Boekelheide; Cis Wilson, executive producer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
