<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Pretty Plants Become Too Pushy</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637078"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="GARDENING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DC1F31F935A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Pretty Plants Become Too Pushy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOAN LEE FAUST</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE asters are blooming. The goldenrods are glowing by highways. Chrysanthemums are filling in flower borders with gold, yellow, bronze, maroon, even white blossoms. One would think that the growing season is winding down and the end for herbaceous plants is near.</p>
        <p>But not for all of them. Some plants seem to thrive in spite of all these signals. In fact, they spread far and wide until they make plant nuisances of themselves. Some gardeners call them weeds. Some call them plant pests. Others call them invasive exotics.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE asters are blooming. The goldenrods are glowing by highways. Chrysanthemums are filling in flower borders with gold, yellow, bronze, maroon, even white blossoms. One would think that the growing season is winding down and the end for herbaceous plants is near.</p>
        <p>But not for all of them. Some plants seem to thrive in spite of all these signals. In fact, they spread far and wide until they make plant nuisances of themselves. Some gardeners call them weeds. Some call them plant pests. Others call them invasive exotics.</p>
        <p>Everyone has a few troublemaking plants on a list. These plants become especially significant when they are on your property, block your view, or interfere with your favorite activity.</p>
        <p>One of the worst, in fact it might even be termed a plant outlaw, is the all-too pretty, when in bloom, purple loosestrife (lythrum). Once it gets a root hold, this plant spreads and spreads. Its rose-pink spires do make a beautiful statement, but when hundreds of these plants choke wetland areas, they are nothing but trouble.</p>
        <p>Some nursery operators once claimed that in a garden border setting, lythrum could be kept under control. Two especially showy cultivars, Morden's Gleam and Dropmore Purple, were propagated and sold to an innocent public.</p>
        <p>It was believed that these cultivars were sterile and would cause no problems. But tests showed that though the cultivars, when self-pollinated, did not set seed, they were indeed fertile with pollen from the wild species. So much trouble is caused by lythrum, some states such as Illinois have prohibited its sale under an Exotic Weed Act.</p>
        <p>Right along with lythrum is another denizen of wetlands: phragmites, a reed grass. Although it is a natural soil binder and part of the ecology of wetlands, the plant can become an aggressive nuisance if it is growing in a property's pond or wetland. Nothing seems to stop it. Since the root of this plant's name is from the Greek, phragma, for screen, this derivation provides a strong clue to the over-all impression. It is almost impossible to stop, once it gets going.</p>
        <p>Many regions struggle with these invasive exotics. Residents of Florida, for example, battle with the Australian tree melaleuca, which in spite of its handsome evergreen beauty is taking over the region and choking out desirable species. It thrives aggressively because it is salt tolerant and resistant to grass fires.</p>
        <p>Then there is the Asian vine, kudzu, which is taking over the South. Studies have shown that the vine thrives in carbon dioxide enriched areas and it can grow as much as a foot a day. Anyone who has driven through the Southern states is well aware of the aggressiveness of this vine, which covers tall trees, telephone wires, plowed fields and sometimes abandoned houses.</p>
        <p>Closer to home, there are many species that gardeners should be on guard against. Although a plant may appear delicate and pretty at first sight, it is most practical to find out something about it before it is introduced to the property. A plant or two is set out innocently. The 1 or 2 plants soon become 5 or 10 and in a few years, the species is off and running. Then the problem is, "How do I get rid of it?"</p>
        <p>Sometimes runaway plants are a delight and gardeners do not care if they take over. This often happens with groundcovers where they are set out to hold the ground. But these plants, too, can lose their innocence and take over. Even ivy, pachysandra and myrtle, the big three, can become pests. Another groundcover that is often selected because its leaves are so delightful is goutweed (Aegopoium). The name alone should be clue enough.</p>
        <p>Then there is the sweet and delicate corydalis, which is a cousin of bleeding heart. It is a delightful plant with soft green foliage. The yellow-flowered species is a longtime flowering plant, but it also has a bad habit of popping up everywhere. The seed dispersal mechanism is most efficient.</p>
        <p>The same is true for an aggressive, yet pretty campanula. The species C. rapunculoides has pretty blue flowers, typical of the bellflower clan, but it has a nasty way of spreading by its roots and is banned from most gardens as a weed. In fact this particular campanula can be rampant and choke out other delightful plantings. Be warned!</p>
        <p>Another plant that appears sweet enough, but deserves fair warning is the perky Star of Bethlehem, an ornithogalum. This little lily is delightful to see when it blooms in the spring. Its delicate appeal belies its aggressiveness. Many of the better behaved species are listed for sale in fall bulb catalogues, but be warned about planting Ornithogalum nutans, the Star of Bethlehem.</p>
        <p>Everyone can think of other plants that have been planted innocently, and then become pests. The important thing is to know the nature of any plant before it is introduced. The adage, "Look it up," couldn't be made more emphatic.</p>
        <p>GARDENING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
