<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABOUT BOOKS</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="638518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY LITERARY HALL OF FAME</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LIBERTY SCIENCE CENTER (JERSEY CITY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONMOUTH COLLEGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HORNER, SHIRLEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUMFORD, LEWIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DD1031F930A35753C1A965958260" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABOUT BOOKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Shirley Horner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HORNER, SHIRLEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE New Jersey Literary Hall of Fame is holding its fifth induction ceremony tonight at the Liberty Science Center at Liberty State Park in Jersey City. The organization is calling the event "Literary Stargazing," so it seems only appropriate that one of the four authors to be honored is Carl Sagan, the Cornell University astronomer and Pulitzer Prize-winning author, who is a native of Rahway.</p>
        <p>The other inductees are Patricia Lee Gauch of Basking Ridge, who has written more than 30 children's books; Robert Lipsyte of Closter, a sports columnist for The New York Times and the author of "The Contender," a young-adult novel published by Harper in 1967 and still in print, and Sister Margherita Marchione of Morristown, author of some 30 books in English and Italian and professor emeritus of Italian language and literature at the Florham Park-Madison campus of Fairleigh Dickinson University. Each honoree will attend the event.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE New Jersey Literary Hall of Fame is holding its fifth induction ceremony tonight at the Liberty Science Center at Liberty State Park in Jersey City. The organization is calling the event "Literary Stargazing," so it seems only appropriate that one of the four authors to be honored is Carl Sagan, the Cornell University astronomer and Pulitzer Prize-winning author, who is a native of Rahway.</p>
        <p>The other inductees are Patricia Lee Gauch of Basking Ridge, who has written more than 30 children's books; Robert Lipsyte of Closter, a sports columnist for The New York Times and the author of "The Contender," a young-adult novel published by Harper in 1967 and still in print, and Sister Margherita Marchione of Morristown, author of some 30 books in English and Italian and professor emeritus of Italian language and literature at the Florham Park-Madison campus of Fairleigh Dickinson University. Each honoree will attend the event.</p>
        <p>Dr. Herman Estrin of Scotch Plains, the founder of the Hall of Fame and professor emeritus of English at the New Jersey Institute of Technology in Newark, said, "This event, where we recognize authors of major literary talent with a strong New Jersey tie, informs the world of our state's significant contribution to contemporary American literature."</p>
        <p>The inductees were either born in New Jersey or have lived here at one point in their lives.</p>
        <p>Each inductee receives a plaque designed by Michael Graves of Princeton, the architect noted, among other things, for his reworkings of the Whitney Museum in New York and the Newark Museum.</p>
        <p>Previous recipients of the award, which has come to be known as the Michael, include Mary Higgins Clark of Saddle River, Belva Plain of Short Hills, Wende and Harry Devlin of Mountainside, the Nobel laureate Dr.  Arno Penzias of Highland Park and Gay Talese of Ocean City. Another past recipient, John T. Cunningham of Florham Park, is the master of ceremonies. The Jersey Shore As a 'State of Mind'</p>
        <p>Part memorabilia, part travel book, part love story, "Down the Jersey Shore," by Russell Roberts and Rich Youmans (Rutgers University Press; $27.95; $12.95 paper), is much more than the sum of its parts. In their introduction, Mr. Roberts of Trenton and Mr. Youmans of Rocky Hill contend that in addition to being "one of the cultural storehouses" of New Jersey, the Jersey Shore "is truly a state of mind."</p>
        <p>Readers can learn about the founding of Ocean City and its link to the socialist ideas of Francois Marie Charles Fourier of France; about the flourishing Lakewood of 1893, where President-elect Grover Cleveland chose his Cabinet; about Island Heights, where the financier John Wanamaker arrived in 1899 to set up a "quasi-military operation," and about Asbury Park at the turn of the century, when its founder, James A. Bradley, insisted that women on the beach wear "Bradley bags," which were flannel swimming suits, "high in the neck, with puckered sleeves."</p>
        <p>The procession of personalities through these 275 pages adds facts to the lives of the famous and introduces readers to the unheralded. Eugene O'Neill -- his "greatness still in the future" -- moved to Point Pleasant (then West Point Pleasant) in 1918 and is said to have antagonized the residents. Timothy Thomas Fortune, a pioneering black journalist, who went on to start The New York Age, once the nation's leading black newspaper, moved to Red Bank in 1901.  His Red Bank home, Maple Hill, is a National Historic Landmark.</p>
        <p>There's a caveat in the last chapter: "What the rising sea will do to the Jersey Shore is currently a matter of speculation." Mumford Collection At Monmouth College</p>
        <p>The connection between Lewis Mumford, the visionary social critic, and Monmouth College in West Long Branch emerged even stronger recently with the news that the college has dedicated and named a special site, the Lewis Mumford Room, to house the author's personal library of more than 4,000 books, photographs and memorabilia.</p>
        <p>As many a curator is unwilling to divulge, such largesse doesn't just fall into an institution's lap. Back in 1984, Kenneth R. Stunkel of Neptune, a professor of history at the college and dean of its School of Arts and Sciences, along with Vincent DiMattio of Atlantic Highlands, chairman of the college's art department, first made a visit to Mumford's home in Amenia in upstate New York, Dr. Stunkel recalls, to bring "this great thinker's previously unknown drawings and watercolors -- they numbered over 300 -- to exhibit here."</p>
        <p>In the next seven years, until Mumford died in 1991 at the age of 94, Dr. Stunkel would make about 14 more visits to the author, becoming, he said, "a friend of the family."</p>
        <p>Dr. Stunkel said that Mumford, as one of the most distinguished humanists of the 20th century, "stimulated the careers of three generations of urban planners, social philosophers, architects and students of art." One of their topics of conversation was the experimental community of Radburn in Fair Lawn in Bergen County, which Mumford -- always much opposed to a machine-dominated civilization -- helped plan in the 1920's. In Radburn, pedestrian and vehicular traffic are separated by overpasses and underpasses. Humanities Committee Marking Anniversary</p>
        <p>On Oct. 29, the New Jersey Committee for the Humanities will present a daylong event, "The Culture of Community: The Importance of Community in American Life and 20th Anniversary Dinner," at the New Jersey Law Center in New Brunswick. For more than 20 years, the nonprofit organization has served as a state council of the National Endowment for the Humanities.</p>
        <p>The conference, from 9 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., features a keynote address by Charles Long, director of the Research Center for African-American Studies at the University of California at Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>The dinner will celebrate the committee's 20th anniversary and will also honor Miriam Murphy, the executive director of the committee since 1975, who will retire next month. Jane M. Kenny, the committee chairwoman, said the fete would acknowledge Mrs. Murphy's "18 years of professional and personal commitment, her leadership and guidance of the committee from its earliest days."</p>
        <p>David McCullough, the author of "Truman" (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1992) and the recipient of the Pulitzer Prize in 1992, will speak at the dinner.</p>
        <p>Cynthia Koch, the director of the Old Barracks Museum in Trenton, will succeed Mrs. Murphy as executive director.</p>
        <p>The conference costs $25, or $20 for students and the elderly. The dinner begins at 6 P.M. and costs $35. The telephone number for information is (908) 932-7726.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
