<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lilco's Emissions Sale Spurs Acid Rain Concerns</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="596570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND LIGHTING CO (LILCO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMAX ENERGY INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DB173BF93BA25750C0A965958260" item-length="933" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lilco's Emissions Sale Spurs Acid Rain Concerns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Long Island Lighting Company wants to sell the right to emit pollution to a fuel supplier that would resell the pollution rights to any of a dozen utilities scattered around the Midwest, South and West, according to documents made public yesterday and people involved in the deal.</p>
        <p>Disclosure of the name of the buyer, Amax Energy Inc., opens a new chapter in a mystery that has concerned environmentalists for weeks. Many people upstate worry that if the ultimate buyer is a company upwind of New York, a result could be an increase in the acid rain that blows into sensitive areas, especially the Adirondacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Long Island Lighting Company wants to sell the right to emit pollution to a fuel supplier that would resell the pollution rights to any of a dozen utilities scattered around the Midwest, South and West, according to documents made public yesterday and people involved in the deal.</p>
        <p>Disclosure of the name of the buyer, Amax Energy Inc., opens a new chapter in a mystery that has concerned environmentalists for weeks. Many people upstate worry that if the ultimate buyer is a company upwind of New York, a result could be an increase in the acid rain that blows into sensitive areas, especially the Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>Several trades of emission allowances, essentially purchases of a right to pollute, have been announced in the last few months, but this is apparently the first in which the buyer plans to resell them.</p>
        <p>Such a complex trade is just the kind of transaction that economists envisioned when they helped convince Congress that an open market in emissions would find the cheapest ways to reduce pollution.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists say this situation also illustrates their fear that a ton of pollution can cause more damage in one location than another.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Amax Energy, Kevin A. Feeney, said the company planned to sell the allowances in a package with its coal or natural gas, essentially offering them as incentives to encourage the sale of energy products that create comparatively high levels of pollution, particularly coal, which has a high sulfur content.</p>
        <p>"It gives us another marketing tool to use in marketing our products," he said. In practice, with the Clean Air Act of 1990 making it harder to burn high-sulfur coal, offering the fuel with the allowances will simplify compliance for utilities.</p>
        <p>All Lilco has sold is an option to buy the allowances, not the allowances themselves. The New York State Public Service Commission could still step in and stop the deal.</p>
        <p>Sale of the allowances is permitted under the Clean Air Act, but environmentalists are concerned that such deals could allow utilities in the Midwest to burn dirtier coal, resulting in more acid rain blowing back into New York.</p>
        <p>The news yesterday would greatly increase the difficulty of predicting the effects of the sale.</p>
        <p>"This is exactly the worst-case scenario from the point of view of protecting New York State," said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Democrat from Westchester County who is the chairman of the committee on environmental conservation.</p>
        <p>Lilco previously said it had concluded a deal to sell options on the emission allowances, but had sought to keep the details secret. The Public Service Commission, in a ruling that took effect yesterday, said that Lilco did not have to disclose how many allowances the option covered, or at what price, but that the buyer's name must be made public. The buyer, Amax Energy of Greenwich, Conn., is a subsidiary of Amax Corporation, a conglomerate based in Manhattan. Amax Energy's Indianapolis-based coal company says it is the nation's third-largest producer of coal; another subsidiary, in Houston, produces oil and natural gas.</p>
        <p>Amax produced 41 million tons of coal last year, much of it high-sulfur coal from Tennessee, Indiana and Illinois. It also produces low-sulfur coal from West Virginia and Wyoming. Mr. Feeney said the company's coal customers include Ohio Edison, Kansas City Power &amp; Light, the Public Service Company of Indiana, the Central Indiana Public Service, the Tennessee Valley Authority and the Public Service Company of Colorado. Way of Meeting Standards</p>
        <p>The Midwestern utilities are the ones likeliest to need allowances to meet the Clean Air Act limits on sulfur dioxide, which take effect in 1995. Some will build "scrubbers" -- devices that filter sulfur dioxide and other pollutants out of smokestacks -- on their plants, others will switch to lower-sulfur fuel and still others are expected to buy allowances.</p>
        <p>The allowance trading system was approved by Congress at the urging of economists and some environmentalists, who said it would improve efficiency in pollution reduction. The intent is to encourage that reductions be made in the cheapest way possible while not affecting the amount of emission reduction nationwide.</p>
        <p>The act gave Lilco a windfall because a New York State law forced it to reduce emissions in the 1980's to levels below what the Federal law will require. As a result, Lilco has 40,000 to 50,000 allowances a year to sell, each representing one ton of sulfur dioxide, beginning in 1995. Publicly announced trades have pegged the price of an allowance at $250 to $400.  Potential for Damage Seen</p>
        <p>Lilco said it would use the income to lower its rates, which are now the highest in the mainland United States.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists said a result would be to hurt the vulnerable Adirondacks. "There is the potential for extreme damage from a sale like this," said John Sheehan, a spokesman for the Adirondack Council. "Part of our problem with this process is there is an inherent lack of accountability as far as what will result from the trading of allowances," he said.</p>
        <p>The solution, he said, was for the Environmental Protection Agency to set limits on the amount of acid rain that could be deposited, and review each trade to see whether it would push any area over the limit.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Brodsky is the author of a bill that would permit the Public Service Commission to block such trades if it found them harmful to New York State. The Public Service Commission has jurisdiction already but the standards it can use are "hazy," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
