<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ozone-Depleting Chemicals Building Up at Slower Pace</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC &amp; ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELKINS, JAMES W (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF123DF935A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="1010" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ozone-Depleting Chemicals Building Up at Slower Pace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The buildup of the industrial chemicals most responsible for depleting the earth's protective ozone layer has slowed substantially, Government scientists are reporting today.</p>
        <p>If the trend continues, they say, the buildup should stop before the end of the decade. As a result, the worst of the ozone destruction should come around the turn of the century, when the peak load of chemicals, now slowly wafting upward, finally reaches the stratosphere, where ozone depletion occurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The buildup of the industrial chemicals most responsible for depleting the earth's protective ozone layer has slowed substantially, Government scientists are reporting today.</p>
        <p>If the trend continues, they say, the buildup should stop before the end of the decade. As a result, the worst of the ozone destruction should come around the turn of the century, when the peak load of chemicals, now slowly wafting upward, finally reaches the stratosphere, where ozone depletion occurs.</p>
        <p>Then, as the chemicals are gradually destroyed by natural processes, the ozone layer should begin a recovery lasting 50 to 100 years, they say.</p>
        <p>The ozone layer keeps the sun's harmful ultraviolet rays from reaching the earth. Unimpeded, those rays can cause skin cancer and cataracts and disrupt ecological processes. Rapid Cut in Production</p>
        <p>The global slowing of the buildup of ozone-destroying chemicals in the atmosphere had not been detected before. It is being attributed to industry's unexpectedly rapid cut in the production of the chemicals even before international agreements to phase them out took full effect.</p>
        <p>The effort to rein in the ozone destroyers is widely seen as at least one instance in which government and industry have responded effectively to an environmental threat, once persuaded by scientists of its seriousness.</p>
        <p>"Here is a beautiful case study of science and public policy working well," said Dr. James W. Elkins of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's climate diagnostics laboratory at Boulder, Colo. He was the leader of the team that detected the slowing rate of the chemicals' increase. 'The 2 Big Guys'</p>
        <p>The chemicals, chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, have been used as cooling agents in air-conditioners and refrigerators, cleaning solvents for electronic circuits and employed in the production of foam packaging materials and insulation. Now they are being replaced in all those uses, producers say.</p>
        <p>"We were all caught off guard" by the slowing of the buildup, said Dr. Elkins. "We didn't expect it to occur so soon."</p>
        <p>As reported today in the British journal Nature, the scientists measured atmospheric concentrations of the two most important ozone destroyers, CFC-11 and CFC-12, at a number of locations in the Northern and Southern Hemispheres. CFC-11 and CFC-12 "are really the two big guys" most responsible for ozone depletion, said Dr. Elkins, an atmospheric physicist.</p>
        <p>He and his colleagues found that the growth rate for concentrations of CFC-11 dropped from an annual average of 11 parts per trillion from 1985 to 1988 to 3 parts per trillion in 1993. For CFC-12, the growth rate dropped from 20 parts per trillion in 1985-88 to 11 parts per trillion in 1993.</p>
        <p>"That's good news," said Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund, a public-interest group. But while the findings are encouraging, he pointed out, stratospheric ozone "will not return to normal levels for several generations." The reason for the slow recovery is that once the chemicals are in the atmosphere, concentrations decline only over decades -- at least 40 years for CFC-11 and as much as 140 years for CFC-12.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Oppenheimer said, several other ozone-destroying chemicals, including especially the pesticide methyl bromide, are not yet fully regulated by international treaty. Greater Depletion Found</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Dr. Elkins said, solving the CFC problem would solve the bulk of the ozone-depletion problem, especially since another class of ozone destroyers, the halons, have also been accumulating at lower rates. Halons, which are used in fire extinguishers, are actually more potent ozone-eaters, molecule for molecule, than CFC's. But there is less of them in the atmosphere, and they consequently destroy far less ozone.</p>
        <p>Under an agreement signed by 87 countries last November in Copenhagen, the manufacture of CFC's is to be phased out by the end of 1995, while halon manufacture is to stop by the end of this year. Controls were first placed on CFC production by the Montreal Protocol of 1987.</p>
        <p>The deadlines were moved up in 1990 and again last November after scientists found that ozone depletion was more extensive than had been believed.  In October 1991, for instance, scientists working under United Nations auspices reported for the first time that the ozone layer in the latitudes of the United States had depleted in the previous summer.</p>
        <p>In response to these findings, E. I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company, the world's largest manufacturer of CFC's and halons, announced that it was speeding up its phase-out by three to five years after surprising the world three years earlier by pledging to eliminate them by 2000. Other manufacturers around the world have followed suit.</p>
        <p>An analysis by Du Pont scientists included in today's report found a decline in emissions of CFC-11 and CFC-12 because of shrinking production over the last few years. The decline of emissions matched the slowing of the growth of atmospheric concentrations, leading researchers to conclude that one caused the other.</p>
        <p>CFC's have been largely eliminated as spray propellants, as cleaning solvents and as ingredients in plastic-foam products like drinking cups and packing materials. That accounts for roughly half the original market, said Tony Vogelsberg, the environmental manager of Du Pont's fluorochemicals division. Replacing CFC's as coolants in air-conditioners and refrigerators, the main use of CFC-12, has proved more difficult.</p>
        <p>Automobile air-conditioners are the largest single group emitting CFC-12, Mr. Vogelsberg said. New cars are rapidly being equipped with air-conditioners using substitutes. "About 85 percent of the new cars in the 1994 model year will be CFC-free, starting this month," he said. But the industry still sells CFC's to service older automotive air-conditioners. In two years, when CFC's are no longer produced, owners of those cars will have to use recycled CFC's or replace their air-conditioners with CFC-free ones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
