<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Capturing Methane From the Coal Mines</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930117T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINES AND MINING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D7153EF933A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Capturing Methane From the Coal Mines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>PHILIPPI, W. Va.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Douglas C. Alexander stood slightly stooped and completely intent before his battered, hissing hydraulic drilling machine, which was wedged between the floor and the low ceiling of a coal mine 500 feet beneath the surface. The machine had forced a slender steel pipe 1,480 feet into the wall of unexplored coal before him, but suddenly its progress had slowed, and two pressure dials, one measuring the fluid that pushed the pipe forward and the other the water that turned the drill bit at the tip, had shot higher. He had missed his target.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander, a veteran of 14 years of coal mining, now turned driller, is at the literal cutting edge of a new technology intended to slow the greenhouse effect. In an environmental experiment sponsored by the New England Electric System, Mr. Alexander was drilling a well to capture the methane gas found here. The methane, better known as natural gas, which is found in most deep coal mines, is 21 times more potent than carbon dioxide, ton for ton, entrapping heat when it is released into the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Douglas C. Alexander stood slightly stooped and completely intent before his battered, hissing hydraulic drilling machine, which was wedged between the floor and the low ceiling of a coal mine 500 feet beneath the surface. The machine had forced a slender steel pipe 1,480 feet into the wall of unexplored coal before him, but suddenly its progress had slowed, and two pressure dials, one measuring the fluid that pushed the pipe forward and the other the water that turned the drill bit at the tip, had shot higher. He had missed his target.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander, a veteran of 14 years of coal mining, now turned driller, is at the literal cutting edge of a new technology intended to slow the greenhouse effect. In an environmental experiment sponsored by the New England Electric System, Mr. Alexander was drilling a well to capture the methane gas found here. The methane, better known as natural gas, which is found in most deep coal mines, is 21 times more potent than carbon dioxide, ton for ton, entrapping heat when it is released into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The United States Environmental Protection Agency and the Bureau of Mines both say that capturing this methane should be feasible and even profitable; revenues from gas sales would more than offset the cost. At present, mines like this one, the 1.3-million-ton-a-year Sentinel Mine of Philippi Development Inc., spend hundreds of thousands of dollars a year to vent methane as a waste, because the gas, which miners once carried canaries to detect, intermittently blows up mines and kills unwary miners. So, say the experts, capturing and selling this gas would be better than a free lunch. In this case the restaurant pays the diner.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Alexander was finding the going rough, because the coal seam he was working in, the Lower Kittanning, is only about five feet thick, and it undulates beneath the hills of northern West Virginia, rather like a blanket thrown over a rumpled sheet.</p>
        <p>He was practicing a relatively new technique: directional horizontal drilling, which means sinking a well sideways, and controlling its path in an unseen area. When he blundered out of the seam, he could either twist his diamond-tipped bit in a different direction, hoping to catch the seam again, or laboriously partially withdraw it and try branching off in a different direction.</p>
        <p>He twisted the bit's course and pressed ahead. About three feet later, the pressure gauges dropped, as the bit left the hard rock and re-entered the soft coal, and proceeded toward its target length of 2,000 feet.</p>
        <p>"Doug made the right decision," he said with a slight smile on his coal-grimed face. Another 500 feet or so, and the utility and his company, Resource Enterprises, of Salt Lake City, would begin to determine if they had a commercial success, which would require a minimum flow of some 500,000 cubic feet a day, worth about $1,000.</p>
        <p>NEW ENGLAND ELECTRIC, of Westborough, Mass., laid out $150,000 for the initial study. If commercial production is feasible, the two companies will split the required investment of $500,000 to $750,000. A compressor will be installed so the gas can be sold to a pipeline company. Philippi will get a royalty of one-eighth of any profit, and will save on use of its 1,600-horsepower ventilation fan, which sends a steady breeze through the mine's tunnels.</p>
        <p>The utility's goal is not the profit, however; it is voluntarily looking for "offsets," or partial remedies, for the greenhouse gases emitted by its power plants. It has already paid to plant trees and subsidized an Indonesian forestry company to operate more carefully and spare commercially worthless trees when it cuts the more valuable species.</p>
        <p>Those are efforts to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide, which scientists say represents nearly half the greenhouse emissions. Methane with emissions of 400 to 640 million metric tons a year is the second-largest cause, accounting for 18 percent of greenhouse emissions. Gas from coal mining is only 30 to 50 million tons, but experts believe it may be the easiest part to address -- certainly easier than the 300 million tons from natural sources.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency, in a draft report issued in November, estimated that by 2000, tapping coalbed methane could reduce emissions by 5 billion cubic feet to 40 billion cubic feet annually, offsetting the greenhouse impact of 500,000 to 3.9 million cars; by 2010, the E.P.A. estimated, the impact could equal that of 6.3 million cars.</p>
        <p>A private group, the Center for Clean Air Policy, estimated that American Electric Power, a seven-state Midwestern utility that is one of the nation's largest coal-burners, could reduce its greenhouse impact nearly 5 percent by capturing coalbed methane.</p>
        <p>R. Peter Calvert, the principal fuel planner at New England Electric, called such estimates optimistic, "as one would expect for reports generated within the Washington D.C. beltway."</p>
        <p>Indeed, there are several obstacles to such work. The drilling machine, for example, must operate on hydraulic pressure instead of electricity to avoid bringing an ignition source near the fresh-cut coal, which can emit methane with a noise that sounds like bees. A dozen yards behind the machine, an electric compressor provides the pressure. The drillers would like to use a small computer to plot their progress, but in the absence of a hydraulic model, they make do with pencil and coal-gritty paper.</p>
        <p>And there are other frustrations. A few minutes after Mr. Alexander wrestled the unseen bit back into the coal, he decided to test its position, by slipping a tube-shaped camera with a compass in its nose down the pipe. The camera, controlled by a timer, takes a photo of the compass and is then retrieved. The film is developed on the spot, and by reading the negative, the drillers can plot the location and orientation of the bit.</p>
        <p>ON this occasion, the tricky operation was particularly cumbersome; the $10,000 device reached the end of the well before the timer went off, but it snagged on the way back and had to be pried loose.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, the Sentinel mine is unusual in that the operator also owns the methane rights. Often these rights are separately owned. The well will take months or years to drain the coal formation of gas, but most mine operators, who suffer from very tight margins, do not look favorably on anything that interferes with operations.</p>
        <p>One key question is whether the methane will flow naturally to the well, or whether drillers will have to fracture the surrounding rock to facilitate the flow of hydrocarbons, as they do at many oil and gas wells. Norris E. Brooks, the president of Philippi Development and a proponent of coal mine methane development, said breaking up the rock could create future problems for the coal miners. "We don't want the roof collapsing on us," he said.</p>
        <p>Another problem is that much of the methane escapes in ventilation air, at a concentration of under 1 percent, far too low to be useful to a pipeline. In other cases, the purity is higher but still far short of the 95 percent that pipelines require, and purification is expensive. And many mines are miles from the nearest pipeline.</p>
        <p>One idea is to use the low-concentration gas as fuel for a small power plant. But Jeffrey J. Schwoebel, vice president of Resource Enterprises, noted that a coal company's largest customer is often the local utility, and "coal companies don't like to compete with their largest customer."</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 17, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on the Technology page last Sunday, about ways to offset the greenhouse effect, misstated the nationality of a forestry company being subsidized to spare commercially worthless trees when it cuts the more valuable species. The company is Malaysian, not Indonesian.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 17, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on the Technology page last Sunday, about ways to offset the greenhouse effect, misstated the nationality of a forestry company being subsidized to spare commercially worthless trees when it cuts the more valuable species. The company is Malaysian, not Indonesian.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
