<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swords to Plowshares: The Bureaucratic Snags</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="590762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUPERCOMPUTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SANDIA NATIONAL LABORATORIES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">OAK RIDGE NATIONAL LABORATORY (TENN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEFENSE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDREWS, EDMUND L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D6103FF935A25751C0A965958260" item-length="1487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swords to Plowshares: The Bureaucratic Snags</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDREWS, EDMUND L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At first glance, it seemed like the perfect collaboration between Government and industry -- just what President Clinton championed, in fact, during his campaign.</p>
        <p>With great fanfare, James D. Watkins, then the Secretary of Energy, announced plans in October for a $70 million venture among two major national weapons laboratories and Cray Research Inc. to develop a new generation of supercomputers. The project would advance technology, improve American competitiveness and benefit the environment with programs to map climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At first glance, it seemed like the perfect collaboration between Government and industry -- just what President Clinton championed, in fact, during his campaign.</p>
        <p>With great fanfare, James D. Watkins, then the Secretary of Energy, announced plans in October for a $70 million venture among two major national weapons laboratories and Cray Research Inc. to develop a new generation of supercomputers. The project would advance technology, improve American competitiveness and benefit the environment with programs to map climate change.</p>
        <p>But the project has drawn criticism from rival companies, which attack it as a sweetheart deal giving unfair advantage to one player in the supercomputer field. And now, the Energy Department says it is merely in "initial discussions" with Cray.  The Problems of Conversion</p>
        <p>The dispute highlights the difficulties that confront the new President in reaching his goal of redirecting Government research away from weapons development. Mr. Clinton has said that with the cold war over, and the economy in need of a competitive lift, the laboratories should designate as much as 20 percent of their combined budget of $25 billion for research ventures with private industry into new technologies.</p>
        <p>Problems are presenting themselves, though, and not only with choosing one company over another or with picking the right project. Bureaucratic infighting at the Energy and Defense Departments, which share control of the nation's research laboratories; budget battles, and patent-rights disputes have created obstacles that even lab officials say make it hard to work with industry.</p>
        <p>Representative Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon and chairman of a House Small Business Committee panel that held hearings on the issue in December, says that much of the nation's economic health depends on overcoming these hurdles. "Taxpayers pay a fortune for all these labs, but unless we can excavate the fruits of all those dollars we're not going to be tapping our potential," he said.</p>
        <p>Despite years of earnest prodding by both Congress and the Bush Administration, there are few demonstrable results from technology transferred out of the nation's biggest energy and military laboratories.</p>
        <p>"There has always been a civil war between the labs and D.O.E. on technology transfer," one White House official involved in technology policy said. "The labs have been straining at the bit to be involved with industry, because they saw their old mission dying. But the central bureaucracy at D.O.E. didn't want that to happen."</p>
        <p>Federally sponsored research and development goes on in hundreds of labs. The Energy Department oversees 21 huge labs, with a combined budget of roughly $6 billion and a work force of more than 70,000 people. These range from the Los Alamos and Sandia national laboratories in New Mexico, which have been primarily devoted to weapons research, to the Oakridge National Laboratory in Tennessee that works primarily on energy projects.</p>
        <p>The Defense Department also operates a vast network of laboratories with a combined budget of about $7 billion and more than 60,000 employees. In addition, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration runs 10 labs, and the National Institutes of Health finances more than $9 billion in medical research, mostly through universities and other outside organizations.</p>
        <p>The biggest debate focuses on the Energy Department, because its labs are huge and their expertise has potentially wide industrial applications.</p>
        <p>In December, officials at three weapons labs -- Los Alamos, Sandia and Lawrence Livermore Laboratory in California -- urged the new Administration to formulate a series of "grand challenges," modeled after the Apollo moon program. Among the suggested projects were creation of a high-speed national communications "superhighway," development of an automobile that burns far less fuel and an effort to understand global climate changes.</p>
        <p>"We feel the national labs have a significant amount to contribute," said Kay Adams, director of the Industrial Partnership Center at Los Alamos. Sandia, in Albuquerque, has formed 71 cooperative research and development agreements, or cradas, as they are known, covering $191 million in work, of which industry partners will finance at least 50 percent.</p>
        <p>One prominent example, involving a number of laboratories, is research on battery technology for electric cars. There, the Energy Department is contributing $130 million over four years to the Advanced Battery Consortium of businesses, car companies and equipment manufacturers, and much of that money will pay for research at the Federal labs.  Lack of a Corporate Culture</p>
        <p>But experts in technology policy say the labs often suffer from a cultural gap that makes it hard for them to address business concerns. The biggest complaint is that the labs focus heavily on fundamental research while industry is market driven and has needs that are much more short term. Worse still, these experts say, the labs do not have enough authority over their operations so that even when they try to forge ahead, the agencies overseeing them often hold them back.</p>
        <p>For example, officials of Motorola Inc. reported to Representative Wyden's Subcommittee on Regulation, Business Opportunities and Energy that they had often spent more than a year negotiating agreements with Federal laboratories -- and then simply gave up on many proposed agreements because of legal disputes.</p>
        <p>Lab officials say they can accept only a small fraction of the industry proposals they receive, because they lack the authority to redirect money from other work. "I have in front of me 70 proposals for about $250 million in work over the next three years, but I have an available pool of $30 million," Daniel Arvizu, head of Sandia's technology transfer office, said.</p>
        <p>A report last fall by the Council on Competitiveness, a nonprofit organization in Washington formed by corporate executives, academics and labor leaders, called for major changes in how Federal labs are controlled. The council urged that Congress require labs run by the Energy Department and NASA to assign at least 10 percent of their budgets to technology transfer programs. It also urged that lab directors be given the authority to negotiate and carry out joint research agreements on their own.</p>
        <p>But lab officials say there is a strong reluctance in the Energy Department to shifting gears. "We haven't been real successful in re-allocating money," Ms. Adams of Los Alamos said. "It's sort of like changing the direction of a battleship."</p>
        <p>Roger A. Lewis, director of technology utilization at the Energy Department, said the Government had improved its deal-making. Working with the computer industry, the Government drafted a model contract for collaborations that has speeded up the process of negotiation and approval. "A lot of the complaints are based on data that is a year or two old," he said. "A lot has changed."</p>
        <p>In addition, Energy Department officials contend that they now think about technology transfer to industry much more broadly than before. Mr. Lewis noted that fully $1.5 billion of research money, in fields like clean coal technology and renewable energy, involve industry partners and the labs can often tap into this money even though it is not part of their official technology transfer budget.  Industry Rivalries</p>
        <p>Finally, there are the issues of fairness posed by the Cray controversy. When the Energy Department announced the "preliminary agreement" for a $70 million jointly financed program on Oct. 29, it said that Lawrence Livermore and Los Alamos labs would work with Cray on supercomputer programs for a range of environmental, industrial and military tasks.</p>
        <p>What outraged rivals was that the Government also indicated that it would work on operating systems, the basic instructions that would run programs on Cray's new computers. Some of the rivals took that to mean that the Government would be underwriting Cray's next computer and giving Cray valuable business.</p>
        <p>Those objecting included the Intel Corporation of Santa Clara, Calif., Convex Computer of Richardson, Tex., and Ncube of Foster City, Calif. "We are incensed," Michael Mierer, president of Ncube, said. "They are effectively getting a $35 million Government contribution, and that gives us a competitive disadvantage."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lewis of the Energy Department acknowledged the controversy but defended the plan. "When you are dealing with the private sector, you are going to have some folks object to having relationships with their competitors," he said, adding that other companies are still free to propose their own deals.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Energy Department officials have retreated from the fanfare of the original announcement. They now say they are only in initial discussions and have made no decision about what form the collaboration with Cray would take.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
