<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="651451"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KETCHAM, DIANE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DD1631F932A15752C1A965958260" item-length="1270" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE KETCHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KETCHAM, DIANE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Keeping Gray Cells Alive</p>
        <p>DOROTHY MURPHY GLASSER returned to her alma mater dressed in a navy blue blazer and a dapper pea cap. She must have selected the cap especially for the college trip. "No," Mrs. Glasser said. "I woke up this morning with a stiff neck."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Keeping Gray Cells Alive</p>
        <p>DOROTHY MURPHY GLASSER returned to her alma mater dressed in a navy blue blazer and a dapper pea cap. She must have selected the cap especially for the college trip. "No," Mrs. Glasser said. "I woke up this morning with a stiff neck."</p>
        <p>At 86, Mrs. Glasser was not as concerned about how she dressed for college as the fact that she was going there. She and 10 others from the Consolation Residence in West Islip journeyed to St. Joseph's College in Patchogue for a day of classes.</p>
        <p>It was part of a roving-scholar program. Only this time the scholars roving were the residents, rather than a professor visiting them. "It's a change of atmosphere for our residents," Diane Cameron of the home said. "We like to encourage intellectual growth."</p>
        <p>And new horizons. This was not the home's first field trip. "We've been to the South Shore Mall," the recreation-therapy director, Sister Noeline Roberts, said, "and to Shea Stadium. They love the Mets."</p>
        <p>As the caravan of wheelchairs and walkers slowly made its way into the main building of the college, students in tights stopped and stared. A few shyly smiled. Why, those elderly scholars could be their grandparents. One was. "My granddaughter Jennifer Rooney goes here," said Betty Donohue as she was wheeled into a classroom.</p>
        <p>"The college likes to offer its expertise to a different population," the roving-scholar coordinator, Ann Powers, said. "It's a way for us to stretch into the community."</p>
        <p>For Mrs. Glasser, it was a way to visit the school that she attended 65 years ago, although she went to its campus in Brooklyn. She was president of the class of '29 but was so zealous that she graduated with the class of '28. She went on to receive her master's at Columbia. Her desire was to become a mathematics teacher. But it was the Depression. "There were no teaching jobs," she said. Eventually she became a secretary.</p>
        <p>The other day she seemed comfortable being a scholar. She attended English 115, a class on the short story. "I know we had scheduled an X-rated story today," the teacher, Sister Loretta McGrann, told the class. "But we're going to discuss something else. It has nothing to do with censorship. I just want our guests to know the story."</p>
        <p>After reading it, nursing-home residents joined in a discussion with students like Brian Callaghan of Plainview. In Mrs. Glasser's college days there were no male students. That wasn't all that had changed. "I learned there's a different attitude in the classroom today," she said. "When I was in college we had to have such respect for the teacher." At St. Joseph's she saw students' bantering with their professor about sex and feminism.</p>
        <p>In an art class across the hall a black-and-white Christmas card created by Athena Carris, 20, of Fort Salonga, was being examined by Genevieve Whitelaw, 87. "I would make it red and green," Ms. Whitelaw suggested. "It would be more colorful."</p>
        <p>From her purse she took out red-and-green needlepoint, a tea-bag holder and a magnet for the refrigerator door. "Next time I come maybe I could bring some more things I made," she said.</p>
        <p>She smiled at the students. They smiled back. "What have you learned today?" the instructor, Sister Patricia Manning, asked her college students. Shari Daniello of West Islip raised her hand. "Add a little color in your life," she said. The nursing-home residents already had.  Madhouse Courthouse</p>
        <p>Forget Joey and Amy. (Please let us, you are saying.) Ah, but one cannot allow the largest media event on Long Island to go unchronicled. Especially when the event wasn't as much Mr. Buttafuoco's sentencing as the coverage of it.</p>
        <p>"Hurry, get the camera!" Billy Kimball shouted to his crew on the steps of the Nassau County Courthouse. Mr. Buttafuoco must be arriving. "No," Mr. Kimball said. "We're missing a hair-spray shot." Steve Dunleavy of "A Current Affair" had taken out a giant can of hair spray and amid hundreds of reporters, court officers and lawyers was spraying his hair.</p>
        <p>That scene set the tone of the day. At least for Mr. Kimball, an executive producer with Comedy Central. Why was a comedy channel covering a sentencing? "We cover news events," Mr. Kimball said, "like the Nafta debate." Not particularly funny. "It had its moments," he said.</p>
        <p>The moments surrounding Mr. Buttafuoco's arrival in a chauffeur-driven Rolls-Royce and his courtroom meeting with Miss Fisher were observed by a mind-boggling number of journalists and news organizations that included the comedy channel, MTV and Geraldo Rivera.</p>
        <p>Fox-TV had six crews there. Newsday sent five reporters, seven photographers and the deputy photo editor. The first reporter on line was Shirley Perlman of Newsday. She arrived for the 11 A.M. sentencing at 7:15. "We had someone here at 6 A.M.," she said. But the doors did not open until 8. "We had to be first," Ms. Perlman said. "This is our turf."</p>
        <p>Producers from News 12 obviously thought otherwise. They parked their remote truck in front of the courthouse the night before the sentencing. But the prize for first reporter on the scene went to a young college graduate, Jeffrey Crabtree. He left New Jersey four days earlier.  "I'm writing for The Courier News of Bridgewater," he said. "I'm staying in the Freeport Motor Inn." In the room where Mr. Buttafuoco and Miss Fisher made tabloid history? "No I couldn't get room 256," he said. "That was occupied," (by Amy Pagnozzi of The New York Post). "So I had to settle for 257."</p>
        <p>In front of the courthouse were 16 satellite and microwave television trucks. With them all beaming up at once, one wonders whether Mr. Buttafuoco's sentencing blew some hole in the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>"This is the biggest media turnout on Long Island ever," said Drew Scott of WPIX-TV News.</p>
        <p>"Even more than the plane crash?" asked Kent Jarrell, whom CBS-TV News had taken off the White House beat to cover the sentencing.</p>
        <p>"Yes and I'm thoroughly embarrassed,"Mr. Scott said.</p>
        <p>As one out-of-work journalist sold T-shirts for $15 each -- "Butta-bing, Butta-bang, Butta-fuoco," they read -- Comedy Central interviewed Chico the cat, who is owned by Ron Decristoforo of Massapequa. "We came to see justice done," Mr. Decristoforo said.</p>
        <p>Paul Phillips, a student at Hofstra, was recording reporters who were interviewing other reporters. "This is a project for my advanced-broadcasting class," he said. "My angle is the media coverage."</p>
        <p>Amid all the cameras was one being held rather shakily by Bob DeHaven. "I'm shooting this for the Nassau County D.A.'s office," Mr. DeHaven said. "I'm not so good with a camera, but we wanted a record of this." Not the sentencing. Mr. DeHaven was taking pictures of the press. "I've already shot about two hours worth of stuff," he said. "I even got Geraldo." Post or Southampton?</p>
        <p>In its quest for a national championship the C. W. Post soccer team is scheduled to play the defending champions from Southern Connecticut College this weekend. But before reaching the national finals, Post had to play for the conference title. Its opponent was Southampton, another campus of Long Island University.</p>
        <p>That raised an interesting question for Dr. David Steinberg, president of L.I.U. What team to root for? "He stood right in the middle of the sidelines and rooted for both teams," a spokesman for L.I.U., Chris Hendriks, said. "And under his pinstriped suit he wore an L.I.U. sweatshirt that had the logo of all the L.I.U. campuses on it."</p>
        <p>Post won the match-up, 2-0. "Dr. Steinberg was very happy for Post," Mrs. Hendriks said. But very sad for Southampton, she was quick to add.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
