<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Frost-Free in Manhattan: A Couple's Odyssey; Keeping Up With 1980's Refrigerator Technology Isn't That Easy, Despite the Benefits</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="605402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PETER COOPER VILLAGE (MANHATTAN)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN LIFE INSURANCE CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, MILTON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, MILDRED</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDD113AF93AA15757C0A965958260" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Frost-Free in Manhattan: A Couple's Odyssey; Keeping Up With 1980's Refrigerator Technology Isn't That Easy, Despite the Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1988 Milton and Mildred Lewis bought a two-door, frost-free refrigerator for $800.</p>
        <p>Almost anywhere else that would be an unremarkable action. In a perfect world -- or maybe just a rational one -- what followed would have been impossible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1988 Milton and Mildred Lewis bought a two-door, frost-free refrigerator for $800.</p>
        <p>Almost anywhere else that would be an unremarkable action. In a perfect world -- or maybe just a rational one -- what followed would have been impossible.</p>
        <p>But the Lewises live in New York City.</p>
        <p>So ever since 1988, they have been fighting their landlord, the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, which has insisted that they pay extra for using their new refrigerator, or take one that Met Life supplies, like the old one, a noisy 1962 model with a freezer big enough for only two ice trays and a package or two of frozen peas. If they take back the old one, the energy they need for refrigeration would double, according to Con Edison, an expense that would fall, believe it or not, on Met Life. Defending Age-Old Appliances</p>
        <p>Virtually everyone who thinks about it wants the Lewises and everyone else to use less electricity. Consolidated Edison, City Hall and the state Public Service Commission think using electricity more efficiently will lower costs by reducing the need for new power plants. And last week President Clinton promised that the United States would reduce fuel use so this country can meet the goals laid out in last year's "Earth Summit" in Rio de Janeiro to reduce the gases that cause global warming.</p>
        <p>"There are probably more instances than anyone could count where existing laws don't make sense, or match national policy goals," said Marla Romash, a White House spokeswoman, who said that Vice President Gore will soon begin a review of such rules. In most cases, she added, improving efficiency not only helps the environment but also enhances corporate profits.</p>
        <p>In the refrigerator case, however, Met Life may have avoided all three.</p>
        <p>The Lewises have lived for 18 years in Peter Cooper Village, which, with the adjacent Stuyvesant Town, forms a well-kept complex of 11,000 apartments east of First Avenue. A 1962 Frigidaire, noisy and requiring frequent defrosting, was there when they moved in. Eventually they tired of it and bought a frost-free Amana.  Frost Free, at a Cost</p>
        <p>As is often the case in New York, electricity is included in the rent, which in the Lewises' case is just under $700 for a two-bedroom apartment. The price, far below market levels, is held down by rent stabilization, a system that lays out in excruciating detail the landlord's obligations.</p>
        <p>Met Life has regulations too. The walls of the apartments are an official standard of off-white; if the tenant wants another color, there is an extra charge.</p>
        <p>In this case, the company insisted that the refrigerator specified in the rules meant a manual-defrost refrigerator and that the Lewises had to pay $15 a month more for the privilege of having a frost-free model, even if they bought it themselves.</p>
        <p>The Lewises contended that their landlord should be glad they had a new refrigerator because they said it would use less energy than a 30-year-old model. But in September 1989, the assistant resident manager told them to pay up, saying "our renting committee does not wish to enter into a debate with our tenants concerning charges." The Lewises paid, but went to the state's Division of Housing and Community Renewal to complain.</p>
        <p>In the ensuing legal battle, Met Life gave a fuller explanation. "Consultation with knowledgeable energy managers together with the owner's many years of experience in property management dictate quite simply that a frost-free refrigerator uses more electricity than a standard manual-defrost refrigerator," said the company's lawyers.</p>
        <p>It is not clear who the "knowledgeable energy managers" could have been. Precise comparisons are impossible because the 1962 Frigidaire pre-dates energy standards by a decade, but it probably uses about double the electricity of the Amana, according to Harold M. McShane, manager of Consolidated Edison's Energy Conservation Center. The difference would be more than $100 a year in electricity, he said.</p>
        <p>Depending on how many of the old refrigerators were still running, a monthly charge that discouraged tenants from replacing their 1960's model refrigerators could raise the landlord's energy costs by hundreds of thousands of dollars a year.</p>
        <p>John F. Stephenson, the operating supervisor for Peter Cooper Village and Stuyvesant Town, said in a telephone interview that he is very energy conscious. The company has given away thousands of screw-in fluorescent bulbs, he said, which produce the same light for one-quarter the electricity of a standard incandescent bulb. Met Life has also given away brushes that tenants can use to clean dust from the refrigerator's coils, another cause of energy waste. And when it must install a new refrigerator, Met Life picks an efficient model "for the price," he said.  Charge Barred by State</p>
        <p>The easiest kind of conservation, experts outside New York say, is the kind that generates more savings than it costs, like a refrigerator that saves enough electricity to pay for itself in four or five years.</p>
        <p>The state did not consider these issues, but after about three and a half years the Division of Housing and Community Renewal rendered a final decision. The rent stabilization law simply did not allow for the charges, the state said on April 10, and Met Life would have to refund the extra charges. With interest, it came to $825.89.</p>
        <p>The state did say Met Life could tell the Lewises what refrigerator to use, and charge them more if it provided a frost-free model.</p>
        <p>So Met Life paid and told the Lewises that they could not use the refrigerator they had purchased. "Because it would be administratively impossible to investigate the energy efficiency of every refrigerator already purchased by tenants, Met Life feels that fairness is best served by requiring all tenants to accept refrigerators provided by management," the company said in a statement. A spokeswoman, Nancy Peskin, said "it's a matter of administrative control."</p>
        <p>The Lewises say they were told they could have a frost-free model chosen by Met Life, which would mean a rent increase of $10.01 a month. The company also offered "the refrigerator which was furnished to you by us prior to the installation of your refrigerator," or a comparable one.  And Manual Defrost It Is</p>
        <p>In an interview, however, a Met Life official said that it did not have any working 1962 models left and would supply a newer model, of the manual-defrost type.</p>
        <p>In a statement, Met Life said that "after consulting with representatives from Con Edison, General Electric and our own electrical engineers, we are convinced that frost-free refrigerators consume more electricity than manual-defrost models."</p>
        <p>Mr. McShane of Con Edison did not concur. After hunting to find figures on a manual-defrost refrigerator, of which few are made, he reported that in theory it would save 67 cents a month. But if it has to be defrosted, he said, it has to be allowed to warm to room temperature, and then it has to work hard to re-chill itself, probably using just as much power as the model that defrosts itself.</p>
        <p>The Lewises have not given up their refrigerator. They said they were considering going back to the rent regulation agency and charging harassment by Met Life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
