<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turkey's Monument to a Goddess</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="588582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREEK CIVILIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">APHRODISIAS (TURKEY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JACOBS, DEBORAH L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DD143FF934A35751C0A965958260" item-length="3196" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turkey's Monument to a Goddess</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH L. JACOBS;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JACOBS, DEBORAH L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a young archeologist visited the Turkish village of Geyre in 1959, he found modern houses supported by Corinthian columns. For years villagers plowing this fertile spot overlooking the Menderes River Valley in southwestern Turkey had been turning up rubble from an earlier civilization and putting it to modern uses. Elaborately carved marble sarcophagi served as handsome watering troughs for sheep and as vats for pressing grapes into homemade wine.</p>
        <p>Modern inhabitants, who rode their donkeys beside the majestic columns that were still standing, passed along a legacy of the ancient city of Aphrodisias. According to legend, the Greeks and Romans built this ornate marble metropolis to honor Aphrodite, the goddess of love, life and fertility. But it took more than 30 years of excavations to provide a portrait of the extensive cultural center, complete with a stadium that could hold 30,000 spectators, centrally heated Roman baths and workshops where sculptors elevated marble-carving to a high art.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a young archeologist visited the Turkish village of Geyre in 1959, he found modern houses supported by Corinthian columns. For years villagers plowing this fertile spot overlooking the Menderes River Valley in southwestern Turkey had been turning up rubble from an earlier civilization and putting it to modern uses. Elaborately carved marble sarcophagi served as handsome watering troughs for sheep and as vats for pressing grapes into homemade wine.</p>
        <p>Modern inhabitants, who rode their donkeys beside the majestic columns that were still standing, passed along a legacy of the ancient city of Aphrodisias. According to legend, the Greeks and Romans built this ornate marble metropolis to honor Aphrodite, the goddess of love, life and fertility. But it took more than 30 years of excavations to provide a portrait of the extensive cultural center, complete with a stadium that could hold 30,000 spectators, centrally heated Roman baths and workshops where sculptors elevated marble-carving to a high art.</p>
        <p>To facilitate the excavations, the Turkish Government relocated the village of Geyre, which once covered parts of the old city, to a site about a mile and a half away. Aphrodisias is now a Government-operated archeological park, with an extensive museum displaying sculptures found at the site.</p>
        <p>While reachable by car and by public transportation, this remote spot in Turkey's interior is less visited by tourists than more accessible archeological sites like Ephesus and Pergamum along Turkey's western coast. Most of the visitors to Aphrodisias come on tour buses and spend just a few hours. But the opening last year of the 27-room Hotel Aphrodisias one mile from the site has made it possible for independent travelers to linger comfortably for longer.</p>
        <p>To get to Aphrodisias, my husband, Ken Stern, and I rented a car in the port city of Izmir, and drove 135 miles southeast along a two-lane rough-hewn asphalt road. That route took us toward Anatolia, the central region of Turkey known as the country's breadbasket. After crossing the winding Menderes River (origin of the English word meander) the land turned from arid to lush, with grapes and corn ready for harvesting, and children selling ripe green figs along the side of the road. Just past the turnoff for the village of Geyre, the 14 columns of the Temple of Aphrodite appeared in the distance.</p>
        <p>Built in the first century B.C., and believed to have been the focus of the city during antiquity, the temple was largely destroyed during the sixth century A.D., when Byzantines converted it into a Christian church. Lost in the transition was a cult statue of Aphrodite believed to have stood along one of the temple walls. A similar structure, with a battered face, was found during excavations in two four-foot sections -- it had been used as filling in the wall of a Byzantine building.</p>
        <p>Although known to European explorers, and excavated briefly during the first 50 years of this century, Aphrodisias was not extensively explored until the 1960's. Shortly before that, Kenan T. Erim, the son of a Turkish diplomat who was educated as an archeologist in the United States and Europe, went to Aphrodisias on a scouting trip for potential excavation sites. He found the columns of the 2,000-year-old Temple of Aphrodite still there. "They stood like the last wounded sentinels of a vanquished army," Mr. Erim wrote, describing his first glimpse of the temple columns. Thus entranced, Mr. Erim, a professor of classics at New York University until his death in 1990, devoted most of his career to directing excavations at Aphrodisias. His legacy includes prolific scholarly writing about the site, and a guide to Aphrodisias and its museum that visitors can use to navigate the ancient city.</p>
        <p>Approaching the Temple of Aphrodite along the path leading from the Aphrodisias Museum, one comes first to the Tetrapylon, a colossal gate consisting of four rows of fluted Corinthian columns. Its elaborately carved roof depicts Eros, the god of love and the son of Aphrodite, frolicking with Nike, the goddess of victory. Originally part of a wall that formed an entrance to the temple, the Tetrapylon provides a ceremonial approach for the contemporary visitor.</p>
        <p>In its heyday Aphrodisias is believed to have had a population of as many as 30,000, all of whom could have been accommodated in the stadium at the northern end of the city.  Believed to be one of the best-preserved examples of its kind in the Mediterranean, the stadium is roughly the size of two football fields and elliptically shaped so spectators would not block each others' views.</p>
        <p>One of the triumphs of the Aphrodisias dig is the restoration of a 7,000-seat theater, believed to have been built in the second half of the first century B.C. Before the excavations by Mr. Erim and his team, the site of the theater was covered with stone cottages erected by 20th-century inhabitants. Mr. Erim postulated that the theater had been heavily damaged by earthquake during the seventh century A.D., and that subsequent occupants of the area had used rubble from the damaged theater -- fallen columns and smashed benches -- in building their homes.</p>
        <p>The excavations turned up elaborately carved marble statues, presumed to have decorated the theater, and some of which are now on display in the Aphrodisias Museum. Among them is a relief bust of Aphrodite, recognizable by her crown, headdress of laurel leaves and scallop-trimmed clothing.</p>
        <p>In keeping with current trends in archeology, the finds of Aphrodisias are displayed chiefly at the site museum, making it easy for visitors to see the buildings where the pieces were found, and to imagine what they looked like in their original settings.</p>
        <p>The collection conveys the importance of Aphrodisias as a sculpturing center. For raw material, artists relied on a plentiful supply of marble in white and blue-gray tones quarried from Baba Dag (Father Mountain), a 7,572-foot mountain a mile and a half from Aphrodisias. Unlike other sculptors in antiquity, who copied earlier techniques, the artisans of Aphrodisias derived a style of their own, making the city a training ground for sculptors from other parts of the Roman Empire. Signatures of marble carvers schooled in Aphrodisias have been found on sculptures in Italy.</p>
        <p>Characteristic of the Aphrodisian style is an emphasis on realism and attention to detail. A headless statue of a Roman emperor in military dress accentuates the muscles in the warrior's legs. A relief of Polis, the graceful female with an angelic face who symbolizes the city, depicts the wind blowing through folds of clothing, causing the fabric to cling to the legs. Interspersed with the masterpieces are some less successful efforts. One example, presumed to have been a reject, is an unfinished statue of a Constantinian official whose head is disproportionately large in relation to his body.</p>
        <p>The finds of Aphrodisias also suggest that the area did a brisk business in marble sarcophagi. One well-preserved example, in the museum courtyard, depicts the cherubic Eros embracing Psyche above a wreath of grape leaves and a hanging bunch of grapes. It was the inclusion of grapes as a common motif on such sarcophagi that led modern inhabitants of the town of Geyre to presume that they should be used for producing wine. However, archeologists believe that grapes were nothing more than a popular decoration of the time. Mr. Erim theorized that the sarcophagi were mass produced, and delivered not quite finished to some far-flung destinations. When the time came, local craftsmen could personalize a sarcophagus by adding a relief of the deceased.</p>
        <p>While the excavation is extensive, so little of the original city has apparently been uncovered that a visitor can still experience the sense of discovery that must have excited Mr. Erim when he came to Aphrodisias in 1959. A fallen marble column along the approach to the Odeon, a concert hall, is still partly embedded in the earth. Pieces of columns and capitals throughout the site convey a feeling that there is much more to explore.</p>
        <p>Many precious finds, including elaborate mosaics, remain in storage since there is no place to display them. The two summers since Mr. Erim's death have largely been spent just documenting his work, says R. R. R. Smith, the current director of excavations and a professor at N.Y.U. Digging will resume this summer, he says.</p>
        <p>In addition to occupying a team of archeologists, work at the site has provided manual labor and income for inhabitants of Geyre. The village, its red-roofed houses visible from the theater at Aphrodisias, offers little of touristic interest, however. A dirt road runs through the main street, where old men linger over afternoon tea. Restaurants and lodgings are outside the village, on the road leading to the archeological site.</p>
        <p>We stayed at the Hotel Aphrodisias, and our room there, though simple, was pleasantly furnished with a double bed, a cupboard, rugs and ample reading light. Breakfast, served in the front arden each morning, included home-grown tomatoes and cucumbers, goat cheese and hard-boiled eggs.</p>
        <p>From Aphrodisias we traveled the 70 miles to Pamukkale, a popular tourist spot where calcium-rich thermal springs have formed huge limestone cascades and ancient Romans relied on the reputed healing powers of the mineral waters. Our southeastern route there took us through small farming towns, each with its own mosque. Along the way we passed sunflowers, their faces turned east toward the light, and tobacco leaves strung out on poles to dry in the sun. We shared the road with an occasional tractor, turtles and villagers on donkeys.</p>
        <p>As we climbed the hill toward Pamukkale we saw the massive white stalactites that have earned the place its name, Turkish for "cotton castle." From a distance it looks as if someone has coated the hills with sugar glaze. In fact these travertines have been formed by deposits from the calcium-rich water flowing over the hills and carving out a series of steppes, where water collects in shallow pools. Even in ancient times, the water was considered a therapy for coronary ailments, high blood pressure and various skin diseases.</p>
        <p>Wet or dry, the travertines fool the senses. While the dry limestone appears rough in texture, it is soft on the soles, enabling visitors to walk the length of the town barefooted for a mile or more along the travertines.  When wet, the travertines look like a glacial landscape, so much so that we observed it used as the backdrop for a fashion shoot, with models wearing skiwear in the blazing August sun.</p>
        <p>The road that bisects Pamukkale separates the travertines from the ancient city of Hieropolis. Built in the second century B.C., the city was repeatedly destroyed by earthquakes, but rebuilt by the Romans in the first and second centuries A.D., and in the third century under the Byzantines. Battered by war between the Byzantines and the Turks in the 12th century, it was further devastated by earthquakes, and ultimately abandoned a century later.</p>
        <p>Modern excavations, begun in 1887 by a German team and still in progress under the aegis of the Italian Archeological Institute, have resurrected the ancient Roman city, built according to a grid plan. Reconstructed in the excavations are the extensive defense walls, a well-preserved amphitheater and some of the bathhouses where the ancients came for the healing waters. An extensive necropolis or graveyard, among the largest in Anatolia, includes many varieties of sarcophagi, going back as far as the second century B.C. and arranged according to the status of the deceased.</p>
        <p>While the excavation is impressive, the waters of Pamukkale, which collect in ankle-deep pools along the travertines, seem the bigger attraction for most tourists. Some 200,000 visitors come to Pamukkale each year, according to the local government tourist office. The town, which thrives on the traffic, is a profusion of hotels and souvenir shops.</p>
        <p>Economically dependent on tourism, Pamukkale now struggles to balance the competing interests of ecology and commerce. To maintain their whiteness, the travertines require a steady stream of water. But the limited supply of this resource, now controlled by the town, cannot keep up with the pedestrian flow. The travertines have turned muddy gray in many spots -- a sign of insufficient moisture, and damage from visitors who have ignored the posted notices to remove their footwear. Motels built on the travertines compete for the rights to siphon water from the natural pools to fill their man-made swimming pools. One such establishment is the Pamukkale Motel, which has a giant swimming pool in its courtyard in which visitors can swim over submerged marble columns and capitals. The water in the pool is bathtub temperature, tastes like warm seltzer, and is so effervescent that swimmers feel more buoyant than usual. Our guidebook indicated that the swimming pool, complete with its contents, was actually the flooded main street of ancient Hierapolis. We found this a poetic notion, as we donned swimming goggles and dog-paddled about, being careful not to scratch our legs on the rough marble surfaces underwater. But since we were unable to confirm the information with other sources, we suspected that the story, like the pool, was a modern contrivance.</p>
        <p>As for the reputed healing powers of the water, that too required a leap of faith. A sign posted beside the pool listed the contents, including sulfate, nitrophosphate and carbon dioxide. And it didn't take a chemist to realize that the choking sensation we felt after 10 minutes of swimming meant it was time to retreat.</p>
        <p>Whether the promised cures of the waters are medical or folkloric (or whether they are healthful at all), a soak in the pool or walk on the travertines is a soothing interlude for weary travelers. And the sheer wonder of the giant white stalactites instills a sense of awe, even when the travertines are crowded.</p>
        <p>Against this backdrop, the local people stroll at sundown. Women in floral dirndls and blouses, their heads wrapped in dark scarves, amble beside the scantily clad French tourists in bikinis gamboling in the thermal pools. Weaving their way through the crowds, barefooted peddlers hawk pizzas, postcards and Polaroids. A better time to visit might have been spring or fall, when the crowds would be thinner, the air temperature cooler and the thermal waters still uplifting.</p>
        <p>We found none of the solitude in Pamukkale that we enjoyed in Aphrodisias. But while the sculptors of Aphrodisias worked their art in marble, centuries of nature's handiwork have crafted the natural masterpieces of Pamukkale. Both give modern visitors ample reason to trace the footsteps of the ancients. FOLLOW THE YELLOW-SIGN ROAD Getting There</p>
        <p>The trip by road to Aphrodisias from Izmir takes about four hours, and the route along E24, a two-lane highway, is amply marked. Follow the blue signs to Aydin, Denizli and Nazilli. About a mile and a half outside Kuyucak, turn right at the yellow sign marked Aphrodisias. The rest of the route, about 32 miles, is also marked with yellow signs, the designation for archeological sites. Pamukkale, about two hours south of Aphrodisias, is reached by passing through Tavis and Denizli and following the yellow signs from Denizli to Hierapolis.</p>
        <p>The trip by public transportation takes longer: a direct bus (about $4) from Yeni Garag bus station in Izmir leaves twice a day and takes about five hours. The bus goes to the archeological site, but along the way passes hotels and motels from which the site can be reached by foot or by minibuses known as dolmushes, which run at frequent if irregular intervals. Ask the driver to drop you off at one of the hotels.</p>
        <p>The simplest route by public transportation from Aphrodisias to Pamukkale is by minibus. The bus, which does not have a guide, travels from Pamukkale to Aphrodisias every morning, returning to Pamukkale in the evening. The fare is about $5 each way. Pamukkale can also be reached from Aphrodisias by taking a dolmush from Geyre to Denizli, and then by shuttle bus to Pamukkale. The shuttle runs every half hour. Hours and Admission</p>
        <p>The site and museum are open every day from 9 to 6:30. Admission is $1.25 to each. What to Read</p>
        <p>"Aphrodisias," by Kenan T. Erim, published in Istanbul by NET, costs $9 at bookshops in Izmir and Istanbul, as well as at the site. Places to Stay</p>
        <p>Aphrodisias Hotel, Aphrodisias, Karacasu, Aydin, Turkey; telephone (6379) 8132 (the country code for Turkey is 90); no fax. A double room with private bath at this 27-room hotel, the most comfortable accommodation in the area, is $20 a night.</p>
        <p>Chez Mestan, Aphrodisias, Karacasu, Aydin, Turkey; (6379) 8046; no fax. A 15-minute walk from the archeological site, but significantly less private than the Aphrodisias: its 12 rooms are on a corridor off the restaurant. Rooms are simply furnished with cots and Turkish handicrafts. All have a sink and hand-held shower, but some share the toilet down the hall. Doubles are $6 a night.</p>
        <p>Pamukkale Motel, Pamukkale, Denizli, Turkey; (6218) 1024; fax (6218) 1026. Rooms here are small and musty. A double with private bath is $50 a night with breakfast.</p>
        <p>Tusan Hotel, Pamukkale, Denizli, Pamukkale, Turkey; (6218) 1010; fax (6218) 1011. This hotel with a pool is on the travertines. The rooms have newer furniture than those at the Motel Pamukkale, and there is less traffic from tour groups. A double with private bath costs $50 a night with breakfast.</p>
        <p>Motel Koru, Denizli, Pamukkale, Turkey; (6218) 1429; fax (6218) 1023. The best hotel value we found in Pamukkale, Motel Koru is on the travertines and somewhat removed from the hubbub of the town. The rooms are air-conditioned. The motel has three large outdoor pools and one indoor pool. A double with private bath is $50 with breakfast. Places to Eat</p>
        <p>Anatolia Restaurant, (6379) 8138, opposite the Aphrodisias Hotel, serves an assortment of Turkish appetizers, including whipped yogurt with chili peppers and garlic, and sigara borek, a flaky pastry in the shape of a cigar with goat cheese and parsley in its center.  Cooked foods include a zesty kefte, a lamb meatball, shish kebab and grilled trout. Dinner for two, with soft drinks or homemade wine, is about $18.</p>
        <p>The Chez Mestan restaurant offers the same selection of foods as the Anatolia. It has a large assortment on a steam table of precooked hot offerings (many variations on tomatoes, potatoes and eggplant). A single-course dinner for two, with beverages, is about $10.</p>
        <p>The Pamukkale Motel restaurant, overlooking the swimming pool, has a selection of Turkish and international dishes. Lamb and chicken kebabs were finely marinated, although the portions were small. Dinner for two, with beverages, is about $15.</p>
        <p>The Hotel Koru dinner buffet is an exceptional value at $10 per person for all you can eat. Choices include 15 varieties of appetizers and main courses that include traditionally cooked lamb or chicken as well as pilaf, french fries and pasta.</p>
        <p>DEBORAH L. JACOBS, a business and law writer, visited Turkey last summer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">DEBORAH L. JACOBS, a business and law writer, visited Turkey last summer.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
