<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="633022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DE113BF934A3575AC0A965958260" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-13 ARAFAT IS GAINING SUPPORT</p>
        <p>With six Persian Gulf nations supporting the Israeli-P.L.O. plan, Yasir Arafat went to Cairo to work out remaining differences on a draft accord for limited Palestinian self-rule in the occupied territories.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-13 ARAFAT IS GAINING SUPPORT</p>
        <p>With six Persian Gulf nations supporting the Israeli-P.L.O. plan, Yasir Arafat went to Cairo to work out remaining differences on a draft accord for limited Palestinian self-rule in the occupied territories.  A1</p>
        <p>News analysis: An Israeli-Syrian accord appears to be essential.  A12 Jewish settlers in the Gaza Strip are worrying about their future.  A12 The mundane details of a Palestinian future are being planned.  A13 THE TWO FACES OF CHINA</p>
        <p>While the Communist Party of China has often been brutally repressive, it has also been able raise living standards to stunning levels. Both exist side by side, the yin and yang of the China of the 1990's.  A1 NIGERIANS SUSPEND OIL STRIKE</p>
        <p>The oil workers' union in Nigeria suspended their 10-day strike, but the Government did not give in to demand that it publish the results of the June presidential election.  A3 DEADLY ETHNIC STRIFE IN KENYA</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 people have been killed in Kenya in the last year, the worst ethnic violence since independence from Britain in 1963.  A3 NICARAGUA TALKS ARE STALLED</p>
        <p>Plans for internationally supervised talks on Nicaragua's political crisis have stalled because some leaders refused to meet with the Government and the Sandinistas. A5 POPE AND THE ORTHODOX CHURCH</p>
        <p>Visiting Lithuania for the first time since its independence, Pope John Paul II struck conciliatory tones toward the Eastern Orthodox Church in pursuing a desire to visit Moscow and crown his cold war crusade against Communism.A6 DESPITE WAR, SCHOOL IN BOSNIA</p>
        <p>In the 10 percent of Bosnia that is Government control, about 200,000 primary school and 60,000 high school students began a new year of classes in homes, cafes, garages and basement shelters.  A8 Muslims tell of abuse at Bosnian Croat prison camps.  A8 Boa Vista Journal: White gold-miners vs. Indians of the Amazon.  A4 Ferdinand Marcos's body was returned to the Philippines.  A11 National A14-17, D10 THE SURGE IN MUTUAL FUNDS</p>
        <p>Americans are pouring money into mutual funds at a rate of nearly $1 billion a day, putting their savings at risk and contributing to the instability of the financial markets. "Not enough people are aware of the risks," said John Bogle, chief executive of the Vanguard Group.  A1 CONGRESS FACES FULL PLATE</p>
        <p>Besides the huge and complicated issues of health care and trade, Congress faces a raft of other topics, from immigration to crime to campaign finance, when it returns.  A1 ASYLUM FOR IRAQIS STIRS CRITICISM</p>
        <p>Former Iraqi soldiers are being resettled in the United States under a refugee law that allows them to seek asylum. But the benefits they receive are prompting criticism A1 NOVEL PLAN FOR GARBAGE</p>
        <p>While most cities are still struggling to recycle trash, officials in Lancaster, Pa., have taken a novel approach, mining garbage and burning it to create electricity.  A14 POINT MAN FOR TRADE PACT</p>
        <p>Washington at work: William Daley, the Special Counselor to the President on the North American Free Trade Agreement, is trying to calm criticism.  A16 JURY GETS CASE OF BURNED MAN</p>
        <p>After nine days of testimony, jurors began deliberating the case of two white men charged with burning a black Brooklyn tourist.  A14 SEEKING RELIGIOUS HARMONY</p>
        <p>News analysis: Organizers of the Parliament of the World's Religions found that the road to harmony was filled with pitfalls.  A15 CLINTON CAMPAIGNS IN FLORIDA</p>
        <p>In Miami, the President opened a public relations campaign to portray his many projects for this month as parts of a single plan.  A17 The head of the National Gay and Lesbian Task Force resigned.  A17 Metro Digest B1 A NEW STYLE FOR GIULIANI</p>
        <p>In his 1989 campaign for Mayor, Rudolph W. Giuliani was a political rookie who struck many New Yorkers as both stiff and unpredictable. Now a veteran, he has changed his campaign style sharply. He is more relaxed, less defensive and, so far, more effective.  A1 INDEPENDENCE VIA COMPUTER</p>
        <p>Until he started using computer equipment, Eric, a severely retarded boy, could not communicate. Now he can move his head and convey a message. Advocates for the retarded say such "adaptive" technology has the potential to revolutionize their care and education.  A1 Business Digest D1 Arts/Entertainment C13-18 Artifacts of Napoleon's life.  C13 Wider horizons for church concerts.  C13 A time of change for John Malkovich.  C13 Let the chess wars begin.  C18 Books: "Smoked," by Leon Bing.  C18 Television: "Reader's Digest" of the air.  C18 Fashion B7 For a resort look, mix well.  Science C1-12 The latest wrinkle in parachutes: learning how they work.  C1 A new timetable for the Cambrian-era explosion of species.  C1 Is this poll reliable? Depends on how you ask the question.  C1 A possible organ for a probable sixth sense in humans.  C3 Encouraging data on acid rain, amid some doubts.  C4 Sports B8-15 Baseball: Yanks fall to Rangers.  B9 Green has had it with Schourek.  B11 Columns: Vecsey on U.S. Open.  B9 On Baseball B11 TV Sports B11 Football: Simms still needs help.  B9 Jets not going to no-huddle.  B14 Montana finds new receiver.  B14 Hockey: Camps open.  B13 Horse Racing: Fight among 3-year-olds tightens.  B15 Sports People B13 Tennis: Navratilova ousted.  B9 Open notebook.  B12 Obituaries D11 Stanley L. Kaufman, a lawyer who focused on stockholder lawsuits. Leonard Bocour, an artist and paint manufacturer. Admiral Louis Archibald Gillies, a militia commander in New York. Editorials/Op-Ed A18-19 Editorials Alan Hevesi for Comptroller. Housecleaning time. James Greenfield: East Europe. Letters A. M. Rosenthal: Crime of the Hasidim. Russell Baker: The big sizing down. Louis Winnick: Al Gore's misguided mission. Flora Lewis: The war on Arab intellectuals. Chronicle B6 Bridge B6 Crossword C14</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
