<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Q&amp;A: Capt. John H. Wadsworth; Exploring Changes in the Environment</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="638420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADSWORTH, JOHN H (CAPT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOMMER, MIMI G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D6173EF930A35753C1A965958260" item-length="1535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Q&amp;A: Capt. John H. Wadsworth; Exploring Changes in the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIMI G. SOMMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SOMMER, MIMI G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CAPT. JOHN H. WADSWORTH, simply Captain John to all who meet him, commands a fleet of four sport fishing and nature cruising vessels that are moored in the Niantic River close to his base of operations in Waterford at the river's edge.</p>
        <p>His explorations of the Connecticut River, of the Sound and of the Atlantic's waters beyond Connecticut shores create a tale of the modern day explorer who returns to port with revelations of Connecticut's natural environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CAPT. JOHN H. WADSWORTH, simply Captain John to all who meet him, commands a fleet of four sport fishing and nature cruising vessels that are moored in the Niantic River close to his base of operations in Waterford at the river's edge.</p>
        <p>His explorations of the Connecticut River, of the Sound and of the Atlantic's waters beyond Connecticut shores create a tale of the modern day explorer who returns to port with revelations of Connecticut's natural environment.</p>
        <p>Captain Wadsworth, who was born in Willimantic and spent his earliest years on a farm in Lebanon, as a child moved with his family to Waterford. He grew up on the waterfront, and made the nearby waters his professional domain.</p>
        <p>He has been a licensed master of vessels up to 100 tons since 1954, and he is an instructor for safe boating courses for the state's Department of Environmental Protection as well as serving on the department's boating advisory committee.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview at his office on the Niantic River at his Sport Fishing Center, Captain Wadsworth described changes in the natural environment that he has witnessed over time and spoke of the varied water wildlife in the near inland and offshore waters of Connecticut. Here are some excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. Is your background maritime?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, my father started this right after the war, and I grew up in it. I learned everything right here. I started when I was still in knee pants working around the dock here, renting boats, bailing them out for my father and selling lobsters and fish, working on the charter boats.</p>
        <p>Q. What is one of your most memorable seafaring experiences?</p>
        <p>A. Your biggest concern, of course, is always safety. I'd been in a position a couple of times to help other people -- something that really sticks in my mind -- helping people off a sinking vessel in the early 60's out in the ocean. We were the only two boats in the area. May Day had to be sent out. The Coast Guard was on its way, but had not arrived. I was in a 38-foot wooden sport fishing boat. We got the captain and crew off safely, and got them aboard. Shortly thereafter, their vessel sank.</p>
        <p>Q. When did you add nature cruises to your sport fishing program? And how did you discover that seals and eagles were in the area?</p>
        <p>A. Pretty close to 10 years. I do a lot of work with the American Museum of Natural History. They have an ongoing project for over 30 years now, out here on Great Gull Island -- nine miles south of here on the eastern end of Long Island Sound -- and I had been carrying their people back and forth for over 20 years, taking them and supplies out there to do their studies on the birds, on the terns. That led to meeting different people in the bird field.</p>
        <p>The osprey, which was almost extinct, as well as the bald eagle -- both fish-eating birds, and the DDT was bothering their reproduction, because it was causing egg shells to be very thin and break in the nest. This was all discovered by people I knew at the American Museum.</p>
        <p>Until about 15 years ago, when the Audubon Society asked me to help them make a promotional film on bald eagles, I was not aware that we had a wintering eagle population here in Connecticut. The population was very small at that time.</p>
        <p>It's amazing how people today are more conscious of the ecology than they used to be when I was growing up. Everybody was very much interested that we had bald eagles. When I started telling the general public, they wanted to watch it also. So, I started.</p>
        <p>Q. Though whale watching is a popular adventure, your eagle watch along the Connecticut River must have a special draw. Would you describe the eagle watch?</p>
        <p>A. The first thing we do is welcome everybody aboard, tell them where our life jackets are, and call it our safety speech. We tell them not to pollute. Plastic pollution accounts for over 30,000 deaths a year in sea birds and animals in the sea. A simple thing like a six-pack ring is the worst thing out there.</p>
        <p>First of all, we leave from Saybrook Point to spare our passengers the inconvenience of having to get here earlier at my own place on the Niantic River and to avoid the discomfort of traveling between here and Saybrook on the Sound on a windy day, when the Sound might be choppy. The trip, itself, leaves on Sunday at 9 A.M. and returns back to the dock about 12:30. We go up past Essex, Hamburg Cove, try to get up around Gillette's Castle and up as far as the Haddam bridge. Where we go depends on how much ice is in the river. We start in January and continue through mid-March.</p>
        <p>Bald eagles like to be alone. They don't like to be around other animals and people. Movements on the boat, loud voices, things can disturb them.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, individual birds sometimes will fly down directly over the boat from behind. I've had them land on ice floes up ahead of me. I had to stop the boat one time. Two birds were coming down on a piece of ice. They weren't even feeding. They were just riding on the ice. I couldn't get out of the channel to get around them, so I had to stop the boat. They got very close. When they decided they had enough of that they flew off to a dead tree on the river bank.</p>
        <p>The one we go in search of mostly is the North American bald eagle. We also have at least one or two golden eagles that we see most frequently right around the Gillette Castle area.</p>
        <p>Q. Why is the Connecticut River the eagles' winter habitat? Is it the fish?</p>
        <p>A. That's why they are there! They breed up in the tundra of Canada. When they leave there, in the fall when it starts to freeze up, it's a natural thing for them to come down to the Connecticut River. They can feed on fish all the way down. They winter here, arriving about mid-December until mid-March. As it starts to thaw out up north, they start working their way back up to Canada for the spring.</p>
        <p>There is a breeding pair here in Connecticut and we hope that we can get native stock back again. We lost our native stock. The Department of Environmental Protection is keeping watch.</p>
        <p>Q. If a native population develops, can Connecticut's climate accommodate the eagle year round?</p>
        <p>A. Yes.</p>
        <p>Q. Are your nature cruises unique in Connecticut?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, I think we're the only ones that do it by boat. One of the reasons for that is a lot of people that would like to enjoy this don't have the heavy down coats and the big long telescopes to be able to observe long distances or the desire to stand out in the freezing cold for long periods of time to watch. By doing it on our boat, we have a heated cabin, if the weather gets inclement. Best viewing is outside.</p>
        <p>Q. What gear do you recommend?</p>
        <p>A. A light pair of binoculars, long underwear. Dress warmly in layers.</p>
        <p>Q. What is a typical seal watch itinerary?</p>
        <p>A. On our harbor seal cruises, we leave from my facility here in Waterford. It's about a three-hour morning cruise. The seals travel all up and down the New England coast, and come down here in the winter time. We start seal watching from about mid-March through mid-May. We find them in their natural habitat. When you're watching in the wild, you can't get as close to them as you could in an aquarium. They're a little bit skittish. We leave the Niantic River through a highway bridge and a railway bridge and enter into Niantic Bay, which is a little indentation in Long Island Sound. From there we travel down Long Island Sound to Fishers Island Sound between Fishers Island the Mystic River. We're in protected waters.</p>
        <p>It's really a pleasure and a privilege to be able to go out and see these things and just be there to observe them. We get to see 50 to 120 on a given seal watch. The estimated area population is between 200 and 250. I've found that every animal is an individual. I don't care if it's a whale, eagle or seal, you can talk in generalities, but you can't always predict what they'll do.</p>
        <p>Q. What are your plans for the nature cruises?</p>
        <p>A. This coming season we'll expand our nature cruise operations, because I am finding today more and more people are aware of the ecology and of pollution and its causes. I know that they are teaching more of it in the schools. We're hoping to combine that with a nature cruise whereby they can come out in the field and see it first hand. We're going to expand this into more days per week to accommodate more of the school groups and nature groups. We'll have that all set up by October.</p>
        <p>When they study about recycling, about holes in the ozone layer, a lot of that is distanced, until they can actually take a trip on the river or out here on the Sound, and see that there's no trash floating around, see that the bird population is coming back and they're flourishing, and know why. It's actually because of their efforts that this is happening.</p>
        <p>Q. Have you seen the change from highly polluted waters to less polluted waters?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, there's been a drastic change on Long Island Sound and the oceans have cleaned up tremendously in the last few years, and still plastic pollution still accounts for an estimated 30,000 deaths of animals and seabirds here in the ocean. This is as good as it's been for some time. Earlier, the numbers would have been greater.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
