<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unusual Joint Effort Is Seeking to Reduce Sulfur in Diesel Fuel</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="636723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR AND SULFUR COMPOUNDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRUCKS AND TRUCKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DIESEL POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1990</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D81E39F935A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unusual Joint Effort Is Seeking to Reduce Sulfur in Diesel Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beginning Friday, pedestrians in New York and other congested cities may begin to breathe easier, as may motorists sandwiched between trucks in the Lincoln Tunnel, on the Long Island Expressway and on the nation's interstate highways.</p>
        <p>The black soot pouring out of the exhaust pipes of the 2.5 million trucks, buses and many other diesel-fueled vehicles in the United States should begin to be substantially reduced. Within 60 days, diesel-fueled vehicles that use the roads and highways must begin to use fuel that contains 90 percent less sulfur -- no more than 0.05 percent sulfur, compared with the current standard of 0.5 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beginning Friday, pedestrians in New York and other congested cities may begin to breathe easier, as may motorists sandwiched between trucks in the Lincoln Tunnel, on the Long Island Expressway and on the nation's interstate highways.</p>
        <p>The black soot pouring out of the exhaust pipes of the 2.5 million trucks, buses and many other diesel-fueled vehicles in the United States should begin to be substantially reduced. Within 60 days, diesel-fueled vehicles that use the roads and highways must begin to use fuel that contains 90 percent less sulfur -- no more than 0.05 percent sulfur, compared with the current standard of 0.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The change is a result of an unusual five-year effort involving the Environmental Protection Agency and the oil and trucking industries, one of the most ambitious collaborations yet between industry and the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>The effort began in 1988, when the oil industry and the manufacturers of diesel engines, under the threat of stiffer regulations, submitted a joint proposal for meeting new environmental standards with low-sulfur fuel and modifications to diesel engines.</p>
        <p>In 1990 the Clean Air Act was amended accordingly, and the oil industry -- with the support of the trucking industry -- began a multibillion-dollar effort to gear up to produce the lower-sulfur fuel.</p>
        <p>"It makes sense to do our part," said Thomas Donohue, the president of the American Trucking Association, a trade group in Washington.</p>
        <p>He said truckers would pay about 3 cents to 4 cents a gallon more for the cleaner fuel. But he said they would pay less for the new engines, which will require less complicated technology to reduce pollution than those now in use. The manufacturers of diesel engines must meet the lower emission standards in 1994.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has estimated that the savings from the new engines will be $60 to $325 per vehicle.</p>
        <p>Although the new fuel is supposed to be available on Friday at gas stations, truck stops and fueling centers, some trucking companies have not been able to get enough of it.</p>
        <p>After the trucking association demonstrated that shortages existed, the E.P.A. granted a 60-day grace period for the industry to phase in the cleaner diesel at fuel stops. Inspections are Planned</p>
        <p>E.P.A. inspectors will soon begin testing to make sure the fuel distribution centers are using the new fuel, but during the grace period trucking companies can continue to use the older fuel if they can show that they made a good-faith effort to get supplies.</p>
        <p>Richard Ackerman, a station chief for the E.P.A. in Washington, said the grace period was not a blanket moratorium; rather, each company would have to prove it could not get the fuel. Companies that fail to do so could be fined $25,000 a day plus any economic benefit they might get from using the cheaper high-sulfur fuel.</p>
        <p>Responding to the concern of the truckers that their rigs would be stopped for spot checks of fuel tanks, Mr. Ackerman said that would not happen unless the agency got a tip that a particular trucking company was using high-sulfur fuel. "We're not going to stop trucks on the road," he said. "That's not in our plan." Reduced Emissions</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has estimated that under the new regulations, by 1995, the emissions of particulates, or soot, will be reduced by up to 38 percent, and sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain and is formed when sulfur is released into the air, will decrease by up to 80 percent.</p>
        <p>Particulates are small carbon particles that are not broken down in the air and can lodge in the lungs. The particulates have been considered a possible cause of cancer, and high levels can cause respiratory infections and attacks of asthma and bronchitis.</p>
        <p>Because of those dangers, some environmentalists contend that not enough is being done in congested urban areas to cut emissions from buses. Yet they are encouraged by the effort to reduce sulfur in diesel fuel. Eric Goldstein, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council, a national environmental group based in New York, said the oil and trucking industries had a financial motive for cooperating to help reduce pollution in urban areas.</p>
        <p>"There are many people who believe that the way to address the urban diesel problem is to switch to cleaner fuels like natural gas," Mr. Goldstein said.</p>
        <p>High-sulfur varieties will still be available for about half the users of diesel fuel -- railroads, ships and vehicles used primarily on farms.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has estimated that it will cost the oil industry from $380 million to $910 million by 1995, and up to $1.3 billion by 2010, to make the upgrades to meet the demand for the new low-sulfur fuel.</p>
        <p>The National Petroleum Council, a Federal advisory committee to the United States Secretary of Energy, who appoints its members, said in a recent study that the oil industry would have to invest about $37 billion over the next decade to upgrade its refineries to meet Federal and state environmental requirements.</p>
        <p>Charles Walz, the vice president of refining for Texaco, estimated that the company had spent about $175 million to upgrade its four refineries to produce the new fuel.</p>
        <p>"We're in a painstaking transition process," he said, "You have to flush out the old material at refineries, distribution centers and finally at service stations."  Falling Prices</p>
        <p>The prices of diesel fuel and gasoline have been falling, as has the price of crude oil, in the face of plentiful supplies and weak demand.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the spot market for the new diesel fuel has been weak, leading some industry executives to predict that eventually it will command a premium of only a cent or two a gallon over high-sulfur fuel.</p>
        <p>Such predictions come as a relief to trucking firms and hundreds of thousands of independent truckers, because on Oct. 1, they will be hit not only with higher-priced fuel, but also with an added tax of 4.3 cents a gallon passed by Congress as part of the deficit-reduction package.</p>
        <p>The National Petroleum Council study has estimated that gasoline, jet fuel, home heating oil and diesel fuel could cost an average of 6 cents more a gallon by 1995 as a result of the various Government standards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
