<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Without Acid Rain Is Dealt Another Problem</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597499"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH CAROLINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DE1531F931A15750C0A965958260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Without Acid Rain Is Dealt Another Problem</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>COLUMBIA, S. C.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Congress established strict rules in 1990 to control acid rain by ordering coal-burning power plants to reduce emissions of sulfur dioxide, the managers of the South Carolina Electric and Gas Company estimated they would have to spend up to $300 million over five years to comply.</p>
        <p>To say they were angry understates their reaction. The reason: There is no acid rain in South Carolina because the state has no problem with sulfur dioxide. Winds generally blow anything in South Carolina's air out to sea, not to nearby states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Congress established strict rules in 1990 to control acid rain by ordering coal-burning power plants to reduce emissions of sulfur dioxide, the managers of the South Carolina Electric and Gas Company estimated they would have to spend up to $300 million over five years to comply.</p>
        <p>To say they were angry understates their reaction. The reason: There is no acid rain in South Carolina because the state has no problem with sulfur dioxide. Winds generally blow anything in South Carolina's air out to sea, not to nearby states.</p>
        <p>The problem, the utility's executives say, is not just the expense of the rules but their usefulness as well. And South Carolina's concerns come amid growing questions about how serious a problem acid rain really is nationwide.</p>
        <p>After years of rising concern about acid rain, Congress enacted the strict limits on sulfur emissions. The idea was to protect thousands of lakes, miles of forests and hundreds of streams in the East, and many other lakes in Canada, that were believed to be heavily damaged by acid falling from the sky. Ignored Its Own Study</p>
        <p>Since then, utilities have spent $5 billion a year to comply. But when Congress approved the law, it ignored the results of its own $540 million study, commissioned a decade earlier and completed in 1990.</p>
        <p>In one of the most thorough analyses of an enviromental problem ever conducted, researchers checked acidity levels in more than 4,000 lakes and thousands of miles of streams. Their tests showed that acid rain, while a problem, was certainly not a crisis for this country. While a few hundred lakes and streams were shown to have high levels of acids, the study also said that thousands of others had not been affected.</p>
        <p>Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the New York Democrat who voted for the clean-air law, said the Congressional study was ignored because it would have upset the delicate regional political alliances that had been formed to push through the acid-rain protections.</p>
        <p>"That's the way it happened," Mr. Moynihan said in an interview. "It was not a pretty way to make policy." Creating New Problems?</p>
        <p>In South Carolina, state officials say they have never detected high acidity levels in any lakes or streams, most of which teem with fish. And utility officials say complying with the acid-rain requirements may actually cause more environmental problems. They argue that the scrubbing equipment most utilities use also produces thousands of tons of powdery wastes that must be buried somewhere.</p>
        <p>But the state's chief air-quality manager says he is bound to enforce the law as it is written.</p>
        <p>"How this came out was decided by Congress, and it must be changed by Congress," said James A. Joy 3d, the director of air quality in the state Department of Health and the Environmental Control. "What would make more sense is to look at the actual causes of pollution and determine what are the true sources."</p>
        <p>Mr. Joy declined to discuss the utility's specific problem. But he did say: "What's happening is that we are not looking very carefully at where we should be spending our money to make the environment safer. The concept of protecting the environment makes sense. How we are doing it now may not make sense in some instances."</p>
        <p>The managers at South Carolina Electric and Gas are not nearly as reticent.</p>
        <p>"Industry is not against paying for measures that protect the environment," said John W. Preston, the utility's senior engineer for environmental services. "The big concern we have is for every dollar you spend, are you getting at least a dollar in benefits? No matter which way you look at this acid-rain rule, it's hard to see any measurable benefits for us or our customers." What the Study Found</p>
        <p>The 1990 Government study on acid rain found high acidity in 4.2 percent of 1,181 lakes that were assessed and in about 3 percent of the nearly 4,000 miles of streams. Most of the problem, it said, was confined to Upper Michigan, the Adirondack region of New York, the Green Mountains in Vermont, the Monongahela National Forest in West Virginia and parts of Florida. The study also found that in those lakes that were affected, even those in Canada, acidity levels were already dropping as a result of requirements of the 1970 Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>In short, the study undermined the conventional wisdom that acid rain affected thousands of lakes and tens of thousands of miles of streams in every region east of the Mississippi River.</p>
        <p>According to several Congressional staff members, Congress ignored this data because the members were intent on establishing an acid-rain rule that could be uniformly applied. They wanted to be sure that states with clean air could not gain a competitive edge over others, where expensive controls would have to be installed, and thus attract industry by offering less expensive power.</p>
        <p>Here in South Carolina, the result is that by the end of the decade homeowners will pay $60 more each year for their electricity.</p>
        <p>Since the state began measuring air quality more than two decades ago, even the highest annual concentration of sulfur dioxide was less than Federal standards. That was in Columbia in 1980, when the level reached 22 millionths of a gram per cubic meter, as against the Federal standard of 80 millionths of a gram. Surrounding states are not affected by the low levels here, since prevailing winds blow the sulfur dioxide out to sea.</p>
        <p>"If I had $300 million to spend to improve air quality in South Carolina, I wouldn't spend it on acid rain," Mr. Joy said. "Most of our problem is smog caused by cars and trucks, and that's where I'd look for improvements -- not in controlling sulfur dioxide from power plants."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
