<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Dance; The Paris Opera Ballet in Nureyev's 'Bayadere'</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="598044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARIS OPERA BALLET</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NUREYEV, RUDOLF</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DE1239F935A15750C0A965958260" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Dance; The Paris Opera Ballet in Nureyev's 'Bayadere'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Rudolf Nureyev's sumptuous three-act staging of Marius Petipa's 1877 ballet "La Bayadere" for the Paris Opera Ballet, the warrior-hero abandons his hunting in the forests of India to arrive at his engagement party atop a huge prop elephant on wheels.</p>
        <p>The symbolism is apt. "La Bayadere" remains a white elephant of a ballet. Its 19th-century melodrama and confused Orientalisms are tolerable only because they frame the set pieces of classical dancing that lead up to Petipa's masterpiece of pure classicism: the scene known as "Kingdom of the Shades."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Rudolf Nureyev's sumptuous three-act staging of Marius Petipa's 1877 ballet "La Bayadere" for the Paris Opera Ballet, the warrior-hero abandons his hunting in the forests of India to arrive at his engagement party atop a huge prop elephant on wheels.</p>
        <p>The symbolism is apt. "La Bayadere" remains a white elephant of a ballet. Its 19th-century melodrama and confused Orientalisms are tolerable only because they frame the set pieces of classical dancing that lead up to Petipa's masterpiece of pure classicism: the scene known as "Kingdom of the Shades."</p>
        <p>Even Nureyev, who filled this production with a mix of Hollywoodish and Parisian glamour, could not save "La Bayadere" from itself. Nonetheless, the United States premiere of the staging he completed three months before his death in January triumphed on Wednesday night through the outstanding dancing of its principals: Isabelle Guerin, Laurent Hilaire and Elisabeth Platel.</p>
        <p>Appearing before a packed opera house as part of the France Danse festival at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts here, these three stars offered a performance to remember. Brilliantly, profoundly, confidently, they searched and found the emotional core of a ballet that threatens to be drowned in the contrasting glitter and heaviness proffered by its two Italian designers, Ezio Frigerio (sets) and Franca Squarciapino (costumes).</p>
        <p>The overall atmosphere recalls a Midwestern movie palace with fake temple sculptures in its lobby. Even the jungle foliage, quite unexpected, that fills the backdrop of the "Shades" act looks like enlarged wallpaper design. After Solor, the hero, has betrayed Nikiya -- the temple dancing girl or bayadere -- by his betrothal to Gamzatti, the rajah's daughter, he lies down to drown his sorrows in an opium dream. But he does so in front of a painted solarium: a greenhouse effect that is largely irrelevant.</p>
        <p>There are other colorful touches. The tiger killed by Solor has a bloody red spot on the cloth that covers him. The extras include body builders, standing with muscles flexed. Unlike Natalia Makarova, who staged a full-length version of "La Bayadere" in 1980 for American Ballet Theater, Nureyev has kept more of the character dances and folk-inspired pieces that remain in the three-act version performed by the Kirov Ballet.</p>
        <p>Like the Kirov production, seen in New York last summer, the Paris version ends with the "Shades" scene and omits the original fourth act, which Miss Makarova re-choreographed. The vengeful gods thus do not destroy the rajah's entourage with the collapse of a temple. Solor here is reunited with Nikiya at the close of the "Shades" act. It makes for an abrupt ending and gives an unfinished look to the production, although it has been marvelously rehearsed by the company's ballet master, Patrice Bart.</p>
        <p>Many of the dances were staged by the former Kirov ballerina who assisted Nureyev, Ninel Kurgapkina. Her first name is Lenin spelled backwards, a curiosity that identifies her with an era in Soviet history when such names were common. The Soviet era is also felt in this version through the post-Petipa interpolations running through the choreography.</p>
        <p>Nureyev kept the Kirov's crude 1950's pas de deux for Nikiya and a male slave (Laurent Novis), which serves as a floor show inside the rajah's palace in the second part of Act I. The even cruder duet that ends the tribal dance at the betrothal celebrations in Act II is also in the Kirov version. But it is danced now with exciting elasticity by Virginie Rousseliere and Ludovic Heiden, both loose-hipped high kickers.</p>
        <p>Such fine individual performances build gradually to compensate for the slow-moving mime of the first act, in which Francis Malovik's high priest, more monotone than volatile, is rejected by Nikiya. Miss Guerin's Nikiya made the Soviet-style duet with Mr. Hilaire's Solor in this scene a study in ecstasy. The voluptuousness of her initial solo before the temple and her dramatic despair explained the desperation she expressed so strongly later.</p>
        <p>Nureyev's new choreography is kept to a minimum and includes chiefly a finicky number for the masked tribal group and a difficult variation for Solor in the prologue to the "Shades." The young corps in that act was on the wobbly side, obviously a case of nerves. But the soloists -- Nathalie Aubin, Fanny Gaida and the boldly hyperextended Nathalie Rique -- made a fine showing.</p>
        <p>Vello Pahn, an Estonian, conducted Ludwig Minkus's score, which has been opened to include the dances from a 1941 Kirov staging that Miss Makarova omitted from Act II. Nureyev has restored the tribal dance, a group with parrots on their wrists and two little girls who tease a woman with a jar on her head.</p>
        <p>The "Golden Idol," danced with sparkling bravura by Lionel Delanoe, is now surrounded by little girls in blackface, a 19th-century convention that American companies would discard.</p>
        <p>Amid the gold and glitter of the palaces and saris onstage, the Paris principals stand out amid the otherwise standard choreography. The generation of French dancers that Americans first saw in 1986 has found a new maturity in both projection and technique.</p>
        <p>Miss Guerin is certainly the best Nikiya around, sensual to the extreme in her harem-pants solo, stretching and arching to the utmost before she dies of a snakebite. But the same arched back and fluency imbue her classical dancing with the profundity of perfection that she offers in the "Shades" act. Mr. Hilaire always matches her, and when he triumphed in his last variation, he grinned deservedly.</p>
        <p>Miss Platel made for a beauteous Gamzatti, fiercely dramatic in her vengeful gestures (her stylized confrontation with Nikiya was anything but the usual soap opera). Her dancing glitters more than it flows, and she radiated brilliance in the classical showpiece of Act II. Fans are already asking the name of the difficult reverse turn that she performed with such panache: it is called "attitude enveloppee en dedans." Amid all the fairy-tale fantasy on view, the dancers delivered the real thing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
