<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nafta and the Environment</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="637216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930927T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DA143CF934A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nafta and the Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Environmentalists, accustomed to unified struggles against common enemies like air pollution and Ronald Reagan, have fallen to fighting among themselves over the North American Free Trade Agreement. Grass-roots organizations like Friends of the Earth say it will create a polluters' paradise in Mexico and degrade America. Mainstream groups like the National Wildlife Federation say it all but guarantees a cleaner hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Nafta's critics are even more jittery now that a Federal appeals court has ruled that the White House can forward the agreement to Congress without an environmental impact statement. A careful reading of Nafta should ease their worries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Environmentalists, accustomed to unified struggles against common enemies like air pollution and Ronald Reagan, have fallen to fighting among themselves over the North American Free Trade Agreement. Grass-roots organizations like Friends of the Earth say it will create a polluters' paradise in Mexico and degrade America. Mainstream groups like the National Wildlife Federation say it all but guarantees a cleaner hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Nafta's critics are even more jittery now that a Federal appeals court has ruled that the White House can forward the agreement to Congress without an environmental impact statement. A careful reading of Nafta should ease their worries.</p>
        <p>No previous trade agreement tackles as many pollution issues as Nafta does. The General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade -- the basic document governing international commerce -- doesn't even mention the word "environment." Nafta, by contrast, includes numerous environmental protections; a side agreement makes them even stronger. Mexico is more likely to become a cleaner nation with Nafta than without.</p>
        <p>Critics raise three complaints, all overstated.</p>
        <p>Nafta Undermines Laws. Critics say the agreement threatens global environmental treaties as well as stiff U.S. laws that, they fear, could be challenged by either Canada or Mexico as unfair barriers to free trade. But Nafta explicitly protects the international pact prohibiting illegal trade in wildlife, the Basel Convention against shipment of hazardous waste, and the Montreal Protocol phasing out production of ozone-destroying chemicals.</p>
        <p>Nafta also protects the right of each country to set any standards it wants as long as they seek a "legitimate" environmental objective, are based on scientific data and apply to foreign and domestic products alike. Given this language, it seems highly unlikely that Mexico could, for example, successfully challenge a U.S. decision to prevent the import of fruits sprayed with pesticides banned by U.S. law.</p>
        <p>Nafta Won't Clean the Border. The boundary between Mexico and the U.S. is undeniably a cesspool. "Dirty" U.S. industries like petrochemicals have flocked to the border zone because, under Mexican law, the goods they manufacture can be shipped back to the U.S. duty-free.</p>
        <p>Nafta addresses the border problem in two ways. First, the side agreement promises $8 billion for water and sewage treatment, although the money has yet to be appropriated. More important, all of Mexico will become a duty-free zone under Nafta, thus removing any incentive to concentrate industry on the border.</p>
        <p>Nafta Will Ruin Mexico. Although Mexico has strong environmental laws, it rarely enforces them. Thus, critics say, America's dirtiest industries -- tempted not only by Mexico's lower wages but by its regulatory indifference -- will now infest every nook and cranny of Mexico, adding greatly to Mexico's existing pollution overload.</p>
        <p>However, Nafta explicitly bars all three parties to the agreement from creating "pollution havens" by waiving or ignoring environmental laws for the purpose of seeking investment. The trick is to insure that this pledge is honored. To that end, the side agreement sets up a three-nation mechanism, the Commission on Environmental Cooperation. Any country (or private group like the Sierra Club), believing that a nation is not enforcing its laws, can complain. If the commission finds a pattern of violations, it can impose fines of up to $20 million on the offending country and, if that doesn't work, invoke trade sanctions.</p>
        <p>The procedure is cumbersome and it is hardly foolproof. But at least it would bring to bear international pressures that do not now exist and would give Mexico an incentive to obey laws that it routinely ignores.</p>
        <p>Nafta will not turn Mexico, Canada or the U.S. into a preindustrial paradise. It simply seeks to protect the environment against the economic explosion that Nafta is supposed to let loose. Those who claim otherwise haven't done their reading.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
