<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AT DINNER WITH: Leslie Nielsen; For His Hamlet, A Whoopee Cushion, Not a Skull</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Home and Garden; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="630889"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIELSEN, LESLIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DA1231F936A1575BC0A965958260" item-length="1313" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AT DINNER WITH: Leslie Nielsen; For His Hamlet, A Whoopee Cushion, Not a Skull</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COULD this be the once-elegant Leslie Nielsen? Inside the restaurant, waiters didn't know whether to eject the actor or to dissolve in embarrassed laughter. Nearby diners were caught between astonishment and shame. A movie actor making such undignified noises! Mickey Rourke might do this, but here was the cinematic captain of the S.S. Poseidon with the ennobling white hair attacking the high-ceilinged back room with the breezy reports of a hand-held whoopee cushion, a device he has toted globally for 18 years.</p>
        <p>"I've done it on almost every network, at the White House, in Japan, Denmark, Holland, Australia," he said. He was unrepentant.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COULD this be the once-elegant Leslie Nielsen? Inside the restaurant, waiters didn't know whether to eject the actor or to dissolve in embarrassed laughter. Nearby diners were caught between astonishment and shame. A movie actor making such undignified noises! Mickey Rourke might do this, but here was the cinematic captain of the S.S. Poseidon with the ennobling white hair attacking the high-ceilinged back room with the breezy reports of a hand-held whoopee cushion, a device he has toted globally for 18 years.</p>
        <p>"I've done it on almost every network, at the White House, in Japan, Denmark, Holland, Australia," he said. He was unrepentant.</p>
        <p>The resonant rubber toy was tucked in his large left hand, under the table or in his jacket pocket. He operated deftly, out of sight, to punctuate the tales he told over dinner.</p>
        <p>"I've never found anything that gets people down to earth faster," he said. "People approach me as an authority figure, which isn't in my makeup. Two cranks of this and people talk to me the way I want."</p>
        <p>Mr. Nielsen's girlfriend, Barbaree Earl, first experienced his sonic onslaught when he emptied a Hawaiian art gallery 13 years ago. "He lives for elevators," she said dryly.</p>
        <p>Here was the true Leslie Nielsen. Once, he played a thousand dramatic, debonair, villainous, romantic, sophisticated, yukless roles in films and television. He was an injured pilot opposite Debbie Reynolds in "Tammy and the Bachelor" (1957), a spaceship commander playing opposite a robot in "Forbidden Planet" (1956). For more than three decades, the prankster chortling inside him -- a Joe E. Brown! a Larry Fine! a Guy Kibbee! -- hoped for a chance to emerge on screen as a joker, yearned to escape the Hollywood pigeonhole his princely looks had stuffed him into.</p>
        <p>"I've always been a closet comedian," he said, over a languid dinner of mussels, red snapper, martinis and sound effects at Brasserie Pascal, an elegant new restaurant near Lincoln Center, on a recent stormy Sunday.</p>
        <p>The career of this gleefully immature 67-year-old melded at last with his silly inner child via the character of Lieut. Frank Drebin -- Mr. Nielsen's Hamlet. Drebin is the oblivious detective first glimpsed on television in the sitcom "Police Squad" (1982) but more famous from the films "The Naked Gun" (1988) and "The Naked Gun 2 1/2" (1991). Drebin meanders deadpan through his crime-solving while flinging a Barbara Bush lookalike off a White House porch and making love to Priscilla Presley while they wear full-body condoms.</p>
        <p>Much of the humor is verbal, as in this exchange between Drebin and his ex-girlfriend, Jane Spencer, played by Ms. Presley:</p>
        <p>JANE: Oh, Frank, we're no good together. All you ever lived for was your police work.</p>
        <p>DREBIN: And you were always busy trying to save the end zone layer.</p>
        <p>JANE: Ozone layer. You never tried to understand.</p>
        <p>FRANK: How can you say that? When I sank every penny I had into buying that 1,000 acres of Brazilian rain forest. Then I had it slashed and burned so we could build our dream house.</p>
        <p>"I used to think when I was doing Frank Drebin, it was an acting role and when I came home, I came home to me, not Frank Drebin," he said. "A few years have passed now and I realize that I'm really as dumb and stupid as Frank Drebin. "</p>
        <p>Now, he has expanded his lunatic fringe. With David Fisher, he has written a show-biz memoir, "The Naked Truth" (Pocket Books), that is anything but. It is a clearly preposterously imaginary account of Mr. Nielsen's life that features, among other episodes, the winning of two Academy Awards, an affair with Elizabeth Taylor, a key role in the breakup of Martin and Lewis and a lengthy stint at a clinic to overcome an addiction to dopey jokes.</p>
        <p>"Oprah Winfrey postponed publication of her book because she said there were many things she still wanted to say," Mr. Nielsen sort of explained. "We published because there were a lot of things I didn't want to say."</p>
        <p>In the typical Hollywood memoir, the star pours out a version of his or her life to a collaborator. It is then sifted into a very subjective truth.  "I'd suspect that what we've done would be more truthful than the average memoir," he said.</p>
        <p>Why? he was asked.</p>
        <p>"Why not?" he said, blue eyes ablaze. "You got a problem with that?"</p>
        <p>In "The Naked Truth," Mr. Fisher and Mr. Nielsen created a more fabulous life for the book's subject, although the facts glint through from time to time: boyhood near the Arctic Circle (true), where young Leslie was the son of a Mountie (true), the owner of legs so bowed that he said they made him look like a walking eggbeater (possibly true), the brother of a future Deputy Prime Minister of Canada (true), a ballroom dance pupil of Martha Graham (who knows?) and the portrayer of Richard III in the back of a kosher deli (false).</p>
        <p>"David helped me refresh my memory about things that did not happen," Mr. Nielsen said of his co-author. "He gave me new memories, which was like giving my life back to me. It's like being born again."</p>
        <p>Is he religious? "Not at all," he said, then paused. "I might have been at one time, but it slipped my mind."</p>
        <p>Mr. Nielsen has familiarized himself with every line of his bogus resume; after all, whose fabricated life is it, anyway? He deftly follows every nuance of the ruse as if he actually had romped naked with Brigitte Bardot or been wed to Michelle Pfeiffer.</p>
        <p>He actually has been married three times, but never to an actress, and has two adult daughters, Thea, a horse trainer, and Maura, a real estate developer. He's been living with Ms. Earl, whom he met back then in Hawaii, for several years.</p>
        <p>It was the film-making Zucker brothers (David and Jerry) and their partner Jim Abrahams who liberated Mr. Nielsen. They cast him in "Airplane!" (1980) as a loopy doctor, with a bevy of other stone-faced actors -- Robert Stack, Peter Graves, Lloyd Bridges -- playing it straight while the farce passed before and behind them. The trio then created Frank Drebin for the short-lived "Police Squad" and brought the character to stardom in the movies.</p>
        <p>"It's like they said to me, 'Leslie, come out and play,' " Mr. Nielsen said. "Thank God for them."</p>
        <p>Jerry Zucker grew up wishing he could see his favorite dramatic actors play in comedies where "they don't let on they are in comedies."</p>
        <p>"When we have ideas for satires," he continued, "we come to Leslie pretty quickly. He has the ability to do whatever a script requires because of all his dramatic work." Last month, the team reunited to start filming "The Naked Gun 33 1/3."</p>
        <p>Mr. Nielsen has parlayed his newly goofy persona into a cottage industry. He has appeared in commercials for Coca-Cola, Coors beer and Dollar Rent-a-Car. This summer brought the film "Surf Ninjas," in which he plays Colonel Chi, a campy villain with a face like a cross between the Phantom of the Opera's and a Klingon's; an instructional video, "Bad Golf Made Easier," is due out in the fall.</p>
        <p>He doesn't expect to return easily to dramatic roles, and he doesn't really care. "It won't come easy, but that's not important," he said.</p>
        <p>Leaving the restaurant, Mr. Nielsen autographed menus for the waiters and napkins for the diners. Outside, a thunderstorm blossomed. As Mr. Nielsen stepped onto 64th Street, a taxicab smashed into the right side of his silver limousine.</p>
        <p>He shrugged to the driver, who was uninjured, did not demand another car, and waited impassively for the police to arrive and the rain to end. He was being sprayed with rain, standing on the edge of the restaurant canopy. He seemed oblivious to any discomfort or inconvenience.</p>
        <p>The next day, Mr. Nielsen was taken to Kennedy International Airport by the same limo driver, in a different limo, for a flight to Washington. On the way, a car collided with the limosine. Mr. Nielsen was not injured. No one is ever really hurt in a comedy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
