<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suit Attacks Swap Plan On Pollution</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="595743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB133BF937A25750C0A965958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suit Attacks Swap Plan On Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the New York State Legislature are moving to block a Federal law that allows one utility to sell its right to pollute to another. If they succeed, environmentalists around the country could follow suit and a system that economists have hailed as a cheap way to clean the environment could be stopped before it gets started.</p>
        <p>The Cuomo administration filed suit on Friday to stop the Long Island Lighting Company from selling a Midwestern company the right to emit pollutants that might be blown into upstate New York. The Assembly may act as early as tomorrow on a law that would do the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Mario M. Cuomo and the New York State Legislature are moving to block a Federal law that allows one utility to sell its right to pollute to another. If they succeed, environmentalists around the country could follow suit and a system that economists have hailed as a cheap way to clean the environment could be stopped before it gets started.</p>
        <p>The Cuomo administration filed suit on Friday to stop the Long Island Lighting Company from selling a Midwestern company the right to emit pollutants that might be blown into upstate New York. The Assembly may act as early as tomorrow on a law that would do the same.</p>
        <p>The question of selling pollution allowances divides environmentalists and also appears to pit the interests of electricity customers on Long Island against the health of lakes and forests in the Adirondack Mountains. It also sets the stage for an argument between Albany and Washington over which will rule on national environmental issues. Trying to Reduce Acid Rain</p>
        <p>The basis for the conflict is a provision of the Clean Air Act of 1990, which orders utilities nationwide to reduce their emissions of sulfur dioxide, a byproduct of fuel burning that forms acid rain. Trying to reduce the cost of complying with the law, the electric companies and some environmentalists persuaded Congress to adopt an "emissions trading" provision. It is supposed to work like this:</p>
        <p>Two utilities each have to reduce their emissions by 100,000 tons. One finds a cheap source of low-sulfur coal to substitute for its current high-sulfur coal and finds it can cut emissions at a cost of $200 a ton, but the other decides it must install a scrubber, at a cost of $400 a ton.</p>
        <p>Instead, the first company cuts out 200,000 tons, twice what it has to, and sells allowances to emit 100,000 to the second company for $300 a ton. The first company makes a profit of $100 a ton, the second saves $100 a ton, and the cost to the national economy is reduced.</p>
        <p>Lilco finds itself in the position of the first company. Because of rules adopted by New York State in 1984, it already exceeds the new Federal standards and is generating allowances of 40,000 to 50,000 tons a year. Deals announced so far have put the price between $250 and $400 a ton, so the allowances are worth $10 million to $20 million annually. The company says it would use the money to cut electric rates, which are the highest in the mainland United States.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Lilco announced it had sold a Midwestern company an option to buy allowances. It has not yet said who the buyer was, or disclose the volume or price of the deal. But environmentalists fear the buyer is in the Ohio Valley, upwind of the Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>So on Friday, Attorney General Robert Abrams and Environmental Conservation Commissioner Thomas C. Jorling filed suit against the Environmental Protection Administration in the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia.</p>
        <p>Joan Leary Matthews, the assistant attorney general in charge of the suit, said, "The Clean Air Act is an environmental statute, recognizing the problem of acid rain and the devastation it has wrought in sensitive receptor areas. What's the purpose of having this environmental statute if the problem isn't going to be abated?" Rules Unintended by Congress</p>
        <p>She added that the Bush Administration had drafted rules that added a provision not intended by Congress, allowing utilities to generate allowances by cleaning up before the new requirements took effect.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Defense Fund has filed a similar suit.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Lilco, Suzanne Halpin, said that even with the trading provision, the Clean Air Act would sharply cut overall sulfur dioxide emissions. "It's a new approach to cost-effective energy regulation and it should be given a chance to work," she said. She would not comment directly on the suit.</p>
        <p>In another attack on the deal, Assemblyman Richard Brodsky, a Democrat from Westchester County who is the chairman of the committee on environmental conservation, has introduced a bill that could be voted on Monday that would require utilities in Lilco's position to file an environmental impact statement. If the statement shows damage, the trade could be blocked by the Public Service Commission.</p>
        <p>"That there is a national scheme is terrific," he said. "That New York should pay the price is terrible."</p>
        <p>But the Environmental Defense Fund, a national group based in Manhattan, does not like the New York State bill. If a market can develop in emissions trading, the group reasons, it will encourage Midwestern utilities, the nation's most polluting, to clean up in excess of the Federal standards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
