<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Promoting Home-Grown Ideas for Cleaner Air</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D91038F937A15753C1A965958260" item-length="976" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Promoting Home-Grown Ideas for Cleaner Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BURTON TRIBBLE came from Kansas to the nation's capital last week to volunteer the services of his 3,000 swine for the Clinton Administration's war against the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>At the White House, Vice President Al Gore cited the hog farmer as an example of what business can do to cut the emissions of gases that trap the sun's heat within the atmosphere, possibly raising the earth's temperature enough to do serious environmental damage in years to come.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BURTON TRIBBLE came from Kansas to the nation's capital last week to volunteer the services of his 3,000 swine for the Clinton Administration's war against the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>At the White House, Vice President Al Gore cited the hog farmer as an example of what business can do to cut the emissions of gases that trap the sun's heat within the atmosphere, possibly raising the earth's temperature enough to do serious environmental damage in years to come.</p>
        <p>The United States signed a treaty last year pledging to reduce greenhouse gas emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000, and the Administration last week produced a plan that calls for achieving the goal primarily through voluntary efforts and profit incentives rather than strict new regulations.</p>
        <p>So what can a hog farmer do about it?</p>
        <p>At the Tribble spread near Nortonville, Kan., the pollution takes the form of methane rising from a 20-foot-high tank where a slurry of pig manure ripens until it is used as fertilizer. Mr. Tribble wants to spend more than $100,000 installing a lid on the tank and other equipment to capture the methane and burn it for heat and electricity. He estimates that he will halve his energy bills and pay for the investment in less than five years.</p>
        <p>It is not a terribly novel concept, but neither is it widely practiced on American farms, and Mr. Tribble said he has been having problems with the idea when he takes it to the bank.</p>
        <p>"I am finding a major problem finding financing," he said. "Hogs have a stigma."</p>
        <p>The Administration hopes to help with an inexpensive program of technology assistance, education and publicity, pushing projects like Mr. Tribble's into operation at about half the 3,000 or so swine and dairy operations where it makes economic sense, and capturing an estimated 1.5 million metric tons of methane without costly regulations or subsidies.</p>
        <p>That would be one step among dozens -- involving utilities, forestry, home appliances, landfills and manufacturing plants -- that are expected to reduce net emissions of greenhouse gases, principally carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxides, and hydrofluorocarbons, by 109 million metric tons in the next seven years.</p>
        <p>Much of that reduction might happen with or without a national plan, since, like Mr. Tribble's methane plant, they are expected to pay for themselves. The Administration estimates that the private sector will invest $60 billion between 1994 and 2000, recovering every penny in reduced energy costs in that period, and saving $200 billion in the following decade.</p>
        <p>Already, 50 utilities have signed letters of intent promising the Energy Department that they would cut greenhouse gas emissions, mostly in the form of carbon dioxide, even though no Federal law requires them to do so.</p>
        <p>But increasingly, state utility commissions are requiring power companies to take pollution into account when making investment decisions, and are rewarding companies for investing in conservation.</p>
        <p>Conservationists have applauded this thinking, which is what allows utilities to subsidize consumers who buy low-energy light bulbs, or to lend money to homeowners for efficient furnaces or insulation. The plan also relies heavily on encouraging efficient lighting in commercial buildings and efficient machines in factories. It's Cheaper Overseas</p>
        <p>But environmental groups find some parts of the plan disturbing, especially those that encourage polluters to scour the world seeking cheap ways to reduce emissions, instead of taking more costly measures closer to home.</p>
        <p>The concept is called "joint implementation," an approach that rests on the fact that greenhouse gases do their damage globally no matter where the emissions come from.</p>
        <p>As an example, several American utilities are examining an investment in the town of Decin in the Czech Republic, where apartment houses are heated by plants burning environmentally dirty brown coal. The town cannot afford to tap into nearby natural gas pipelines, but if an American utility foots part of the bill, the reduction in emissions could be much cheaper for the utility than similar results in Wisconsin or New York.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists also worry about the plan's reliance on forests as storehouses for carbon absorbed by trees from the atmosphere. About 9 percent of the so-called "reduction" in emissions in the plan comes from expanding forests, as utilities and other producers of carbon dioxide are encouraged to plant trees.</p>
        <p>Of course, the environmental movement favors forest preservation, but not necessarily trading trees for coal and oil. Unused fossil fuels like oil will store carbon for millions of years; trees die relatively soon, and then return their carbon to the air. "The best way to store carbon is in a dead dinosaur," said Dan Becker of the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>All the numbers being bandied about, and the Administration's optimistic talk about fighting the war with an all-volunteer army, mask considerable uncertainty over whether the goal will in fact be achieved.</p>
        <p>If the economy grows 0.5 percent a year less than the Administration assumes, carbon emissions, mostly in the form of carbon dioxide, could be 29 million metric tons less than the plan predicts, the Administration estimated. If oil prices stay flat until the year 2000, carbon emissions could rise 16 million metric tons more than predicted.</p>
        <p>On Monday, the Energy Department will publish its first comprehensive inventory of greenhouse gas emissions, up to 1990. It will show that carbon dioxide emissions grew at an annual rate of 1.4 percent between 1985 and 1990, well below the rate of growth in the economy. Calvin Kilgore, a department official, said the economy was becoming more energy efficient on its own. And that, of course, was happening before global warming rose to the top of the national environmental agenda.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
