<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dutch Do the Unthinkable: Sea Is Let In</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECLAMATION OF LAND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WETLANDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CROP CONTROLS AND SUBSIDIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DAIRY PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NETHERLANDS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMONS, MARLISE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reclamation of Land</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crop Controls and Subsidies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D91138F934A35750C0A965958260" item-length="1671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dutch Do the Unthinkable: Sea Is Let In</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMONS, MARLISE</byline>
      <dateline>MIJDRECHT, the Netherlands</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the soggy lowlands south of Amsterdam, 18 feet below sea level, the Netherlands is rolling back history: a large expanse of farmland reclaimed a century ago is to be flooded again to revert to marshland and lakes.</p>
        <p>In the uplands farther east, an arm of the Rhine, tightly hemmed in by walls and jetties, will be set free to meander. In some places the unthinkable is already happening: bulldozers are punching holes in several dikes to let a river spill into its flood plains and recreate alluvial forest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the soggy lowlands south of Amsterdam, 18 feet below sea level, the Netherlands is rolling back history: a large expanse of farmland reclaimed a century ago is to be flooded again to revert to marshland and lakes.</p>
        <p>In the uplands farther east, an arm of the Rhine, tightly hemmed in by walls and jetties, will be set free to meander. In some places the unthinkable is already happening: bulldozers are punching holes in several dikes to let a river spill into its flood plains and recreate alluvial forest.</p>
        <p>For more than a thousand years, the Dutch have wrested land from the sea and, in the process, turned this swampy and unstable river delta into today's prosperous nation. But the Dutch have concluded that the intense manipulation of land and water has in many instances become too costly and damaging, playing havoc with water tables, sinking the lowlands further and polluting fields and aquifers. The Daisy Is Dwindling</p>
        <p>Dutch farmers have achieved some of the world's highest yields per acre of flowers, vegetables, meat and produce, but their constant manicuring of the land and use of chemicals have also driven out numerous native plant and animal species. Even the daisy is dwindling, the Government has noted, and larger creatures like the stork, long a national symbol, have disappeared. The last known otter was killed by a car about five years ago.</p>
        <p>"We've become like a big artificial park, where every centimeter is dammed in, sprayed, fertilized, grazed or cultivated or else it's paved and inhabited," said Maarten Peren, an agronomist. "We are being suffocated by our diligence."</p>
        <p>Under an ambitious "master plan for nature," the Government is buying up tens of thousands of acres to stop "the overall deterioration and decline of the Dutch landscape." The plan, approved in 1990, is now in its initial stages and eventually aims to return some 600,000 acres, almost one-tenth of the present farmland, to forest, wetlands and lakes.</p>
        <p>The Dutch nature plan has been made easier, officials say, by recent changes in the European Community's agricultural policy. Farmers must now take 15 percent of their land out of use if they want to benefit from milk quotas and guaranteed prices for other products. These new rules apply to all 12 member nations but so far only the Netherlands -- Europe's most densely populated country -- is rushing to return surplus farmland to nature.</p>
        <p>In a nation where historically nothing could stand in the way of creating more arable land, the Dutch turnabout strikes many experts as remarkable. The plan has wide support in the cities, but stirs concern across the countryside where farming families have worked the land for generations.  Lowlands Sink Lower</p>
        <p>The plan's advocates note that centuries of pumping have lowered water tables in the country's higher regions, sometimes by as much as two feet, which is harming farms and nature. At the same time, in the lowlands, where 60 percent of the population lives, the land is sinking as the soil compresses after being pumped dry. In the past, when pumps were driven by windmills and later by steam engines, the land sank slowly. But modern technology has speeded this up. In some areas, the land has dropped between one and two feet this century.</p>
        <p>While the lowlands sink, the sea level is rising. The Dutch Government fears that warming of the earth due to greenhouse gases will raise the sea level by up to two feet in the next century.</p>
        <p>Regenerating nature could have an effect on the staggering effort needed to keep this country dry. Close to 27 percent of the country lies below sea level and needs sluicing and draining. The Netherlands, a country less than 150 miles long and just over 100 miles wide, spends more than $400 million a year to drain water and repair inland dikes. This bill does not include new projects, like the $2.4 billion sea-barrier completed in 1986.</p>
        <p>The problems are evident around Mijdrecht, 10 miles south of Amsterdam, one of the regions scheduled for flooding. It seems a stable world, dotted with farms and meadows that roll on toward the horizon, crisscrossed by drainage channels and ditches that sparkle in the winter sun. Endless Pumping</p>
        <p>The land here is 20 feet below sea level, one of the country's lowest spots. It poses a major challenge for the local water board. "Other people may pump only when it rains, but we often have to pump and drain for 16 hours a day to stay dry," said Gijs Tijsseling, a farmer and a local Councilman. "Even so, our cows often have their feet in the water. As we pump, the pressure of the groundwater gets stronger and pushes up."</p>
        <p>Once a peat bog that supplied Amsterdam with fuel, the shallow lagoons around Mijdrecht were reclaimed only at the end of the last century. Experts cite them as an example of the excesses of the relentless drive to gain land.</p>
        <p>"Quite a few of the 19th century engineering works would not be done today," said Kees Schipper, an official of the water board in nearby Utrecht. "We have a better understanding of the huge costs not only of reclaiming land but also of maintaining it. And we see the harm it does to the surroundings. Today it makes no economic sense."</p>
        <p>Part of the Government master plan is to create "ecological cores and corridors" across the country. It argues that development has become so pervasive that the few relatively pristine spots that remain are often too disturbed and small for natural ecosystems to survive. In the case of Mijdrecht, for example, the plan calls for flooding some 9,000 acres so that engineers can link up two lakes and thus create one long one. This will mean flooding close to 50 farms. Reversing Tradition</p>
        <p>In some regions, a tradition of centuries will be reversed. In the northeast, near Dollard Bay on the German border, people have been building dikes along the sea since the 14th century. Whenever the land silted up behind the dike, the settlers reached out farther and set up a new dike. The medieval dikes now stand useless, deep inland, relics of an ancient battle.</p>
        <p>Around these dikes, the Government plans a new 6,000-acre lake for water sports and tourism. Nearby, some 15,000 acres of impoverished rapeseed and sugar beet farms will be set aside to revert to wetlands and, biologists hope, become a a breeding ground for storks, geese, cranes and other birds. Since 1950, the country has lost one-third of its bird species. In the hope to bring back the popular stork and otter, the Government has set up several stations where these are bred and then released. Nature Bounds Back</p>
        <p>"It's spectacular to see how quickly nature recovers," said Kees van Scharenburg, an ornithologist working for the local government. He was speaking of land that has now been left fallow for two years.</p>
        <p>"Weeds come back, so you get insects, so you get birds," he said. "We already got more partridges. There are more mice, so we get small buzzards and other predators." After not seeing a Montague's harrier for years, he said, elated, "I have just counted 26."</p>
        <p>One of the more dramatic changes came last June on an arm of the Rhine near Rhenen. Conservation groups have recently bought old bottom land, and last summer, after removing miles of barbed wire and digging creeks, workers broke holes in two outer dikes that had restricted the river channel. There was cheering several weeks ago when the rising river nosed through the holes in the dikes and surged over the flood plain. Biologists expect that an alluvial forest of poplars and willows will soon regenerate, centuries after the old forest was cut down and turned to pasture. Too Much Efficiency</p>
        <p>In the national environmental debate, which has raged for almost a decade, it is not the engineers but the farmers who have acquired a bad image. Both have shaped the Dutch landscape. But the farmers, long seen as the guardians of nature, are now seen as the aggressors. Their problem is their efficiency.</p>
        <p>The prolific flower industry uses tons of insecticides and fertilizer, and Dutch farmers breed some 110 million pigs, calves, chickens and sheep. Much of the produce is for export. These millions of tons of manure, chemical fertilizers and pesticides contaminate drinking water, feed algae blooms, acidify the soil and send ammonia into the air, which contributes to acid rain. Farmers have been ordered to cut use of pesticides by 50 percent and manure spraying by 70 percent by the end of the decade.</p>
        <p>The Government, which pays about $3.5 billion each year in farming subsidies in addition to the hundreds of millions for maintaining dikes and installing ever more expensive water treatment plants, argues that it makes economic sense to reduce farmland and livestock and return less viable lowlands to nature. Caring for the Land</p>
        <p>Along with buying land from farmers, the Netherlands and some other nations including Germany and Britain, are introducing a "stewardship" scheme under which farmers are paid to help manage the land rather than sell it to the government. In the Netherlands, some contracts stipulate that ponds must be cared for and that fields cannot be mowed before June, after the young grassland birds have left their nests. At the last count, 3,250 farmers had signed up.</p>
        <p>Around Waddinxveen, north of Rotterdam, where the Government wants to return almost 100 farms to forest, some families have said they will fight the plans, and if necessary block the roads. Others said that if the change were inevitable, they would rather restart elsewhere as soon as possible. Farmers around the projected nature reserves also complain. A marshland or forest nearby, they argue, will bring insects, birds, animals and other nuisances to their fields.</p>
        <p>Gijs Tysseling has already sold one of his farms near Mijdrecht to the Government, but he is still holding onto the other.</p>
        <p>"My father came here in 1927 when the land was just dry," he said. "He worked hard to level it. He is 93 now. I wouldn't want him to see it flooded."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
