<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Theater; The Angel Of No Hope Visits New York</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930522T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="610374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICH, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIVERA, JOSE (PLAYWRIGHT)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARISOL (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DD123EF932A15756C0A965958260" item-length="869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Theater; The Angel Of No Hope Visits New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK RICH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICH, FRANK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If an angel who descends to New York in Jose Rivera's "Marisol" is to be believed, there's only one hope for the city: "Immediate evacuation followed by fire on a massive scale." This is not a play the Mayor would want to use for a re-election platform. In Mr. Rivera's urban landscape of 1993, citizens who are not bludgeoned to death on the IRT are likely to be sickened by contaminated milk or drenched in acid rain. Coffee and apples are extinct, and even the moon is hiding in shame.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rivera, born in Puerto Rico and of late a resident of Los Angeles, is an adventurous young writer who has been steadily moving toward the phantasmagoria of "Marisol" in his decadelong career. After first gaining attention at Ensemble Studio Theater with "The House of Ramon Iglesia," a smart coming-of-age work later seen on public television on "American Playhouse," he began to smash through convention by tentatively injecting magical realism into his plays' immigrant households. In "Marisol," which opened last night at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, Mr. Rivera breaks through to the other side. Heaven and hell are the only settings that count in this gruesome fantasy, though hell happens to go by such names as Brooklyn and the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If an angel who descends to New York in Jose Rivera's "Marisol" is to be believed, there's only one hope for the city: "Immediate evacuation followed by fire on a massive scale." This is not a play the Mayor would want to use for a re-election platform. In Mr. Rivera's urban landscape of 1993, citizens who are not bludgeoned to death on the IRT are likely to be sickened by contaminated milk or drenched in acid rain. Coffee and apples are extinct, and even the moon is hiding in shame.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rivera, born in Puerto Rico and of late a resident of Los Angeles, is an adventurous young writer who has been steadily moving toward the phantasmagoria of "Marisol" in his decadelong career. After first gaining attention at Ensemble Studio Theater with "The House of Ramon Iglesia," a smart coming-of-age work later seen on public television on "American Playhouse," he began to smash through convention by tentatively injecting magical realism into his plays' immigrant households. In "Marisol," which opened last night at the Joseph Papp Public Theater, Mr. Rivera breaks through to the other side. Heaven and hell are the only settings that count in this gruesome fantasy, though hell happens to go by such names as Brooklyn and the Bronx.</p>
        <p>The title character (Cordelia Gonzalez) is a young publishing copywriter who is tossed into the inferno and refuses to let it defeat her. But the only way out for Marisol, and by extension her civilization, is a "new history," a fresh start. For this, she looks to the skies, where her sometime guardian angel (Danitra Vance), a black woman, is fighting a revolution against a senile old white God who is dying and "taking the rest of us with him." In "Marisol," hope is the thing with wings, if not necessarily feathers.</p>
        <p>Thanks to Mr. Rivera's senses of humor, language and theater, his bleak portrayal of the present and his optimistically multiculturalist vision of the future are not always so formulaic as they sound. His apocalypse is no stock horror show but is flecked with bizarre creations that glint like knife blades in the gloom, from a gun-toting matinee matron in a fur coat (Phyllis Somerville) who can't find her way to "Les Miserables" to a man in a wheelchair (Skipp Sudduth) who has lost his skin. In the eat-or-be-eaten jungle of "Marisol," where neo-Nazi gangs torch the homeless, the skinless man is humanity's grotesque common denominator made memorably and literally flesh.</p>
        <p>Just the same, the evening lacks the drive that might propel the audience excitedly among its often absorbing vignettes. Part of the problem is Mr. Rivera's half-hearted narrative line, which now and then evokes movies like "Taxi Driver," "Death Wish," "Blade Runner" and "Batman," but never delivers a dramatic punch to match that of the surrounding pyrotechnics. It seems a particular mistake to let the angel disappear for most of the second act, especially given that she is played by Ms. Vance, the one magical presence in the cast.</p>
        <p>The rest of the company, dominated by Ms. Gonzalez's heroine and by Mr. Sudduth's turns as a variety of creeps, is forceful without adding many frills in terms of either wit or originality. Michael Greif's staging could also use an added dimension of Boschian inspiration. As he demonstrated in his Public Theater revival of Sophie Treadwell's "Machinal," Mr. Greif has an Expressionist feel for depicting the grinding, deadening horror of the dehumanizing industrial state. While that talent serves "Marisol" up to a point, Mr. Rivera's palette and poetic ambitions seem larger than that. The heavy, graffiti-covered scenic environment, while professionally realized by the designer Debra Booth, lacks the specificity of the writing. This production of "Marisol" could just as easily serve at least two other doom-laden plays seen at the Public this season ("Woyzeck" and "On the Open Road"); when the onstage rock guitarist joins the fray, the staging seems to mimic early Sam Shepard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rivera has his own voice and urgent passions, which are not to be confused with those of other writers, including Tony Kushner, with whom he shares an angel and millennial daydreams but little else. As the audience waits for "Marisol" to start, it stares at a curtain on which is emblazoned the message "Wake up!" The alarm Mr. Rivera sounds in the play to come is very loud, but then what is his war-torn New York if not the future he has already seen in his hometown of L.A.? Marisol  By Jose Rivera; directed by Michael Greif; set by Debra Booth; costumes by Angela Wendt; lighting by Kenneth Posner; violence director, David Leong; sound by David Budries; original music by Jill Jaffe; dramaturge, Morgan Jenness; guitarist, Chris Cunningham; production stage manager, Lori M. Doyle. Produced in association with the Hartford Stage Company. Presented by the New York Shakespeare Festival, Joseph Papp, founder; George C. Wolfe, producer; Jason Steven Cohen, managing director. At the Joseph Papp Public Theater, Martinson Hall, 425 Lafayette Street, East Village.  WITH: Doris Difarnecio, Cordelia Gonzalez, Decater James, Robert Jimenez, Anne O'Sullivan, Phyllis Somerville, Skipp Sudduth and Danitra Vance.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 22, 1993, Saturday</p>
        <p>A movie review in Weekend yesterday about "Sophie" misstated the nationality of its director, Liv Ullmann. She is Norwegian, not Swedish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 22, 1993, Saturday</p>
        <p>A movie review in Weekend yesterday about "Sophie" misstated the nationality of its director, Liv Ullmann. She is Norwegian, not Swedish.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
