<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="600221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DF1E38F936A35757C0A965958260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-9  AID RISES TO $1.6 BILLION  President Clinton pledged $1.6 billion in assistance intended to show "immediate and tangible" support for Boris N. Yeltsin's reforms. The amount was higher than the initial $1 billion because of $700 million in long-term, low-cost credits to enable Russia to start receiving American grain shipments.  A1  A NEW BRAND OF SUMMIT  In the summit meeting of the 1990's, it's partnerships, not handouts; pragmatism not pomp, and trafficking in money, not threats. Image is paramount, and low-key is the operative word.  A9</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-9  AID RISES TO $1.6 BILLION  President Clinton pledged $1.6 billion in assistance intended to show "immediate and tangible" support for Boris N. Yeltsin's reforms. The amount was higher than the initial $1 billion because of $700 million in long-term, low-cost credits to enable Russia to start receiving American grain shipments.  A1  A NEW BRAND OF SUMMIT  In the summit meeting of the 1990's, it's partnerships, not handouts; pragmatism not pomp, and trafficking in money, not threats. Image is paramount, and low-key is the operative word.  A9</p>
        <p>The stars glittering in Vancouver included Hollywood imports.  A8  Russian living rooms a far cry from Vancouver.  A9  EGYPTIAN DISCUSSES BOMBING  If the officials had heeded Egypt's broad warnings about an Islamic fundamentalist network operating in the United States, the bombing of the World Trade Center might have been prevented, President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt said.  A1  TRADE BATTLE OVER BANANAS  Latin America is in revolt against the European Community over quotas and tariffs aimed at sharply cutting Europe's banana imports.  A1  ISRAEL CUTTING ARAB LABOR  Israel began measures to cut the number of Palestinians from the occupied territories who will be allowed to work in Israel after the territories are reopened. A committee is working on ideas for replacing Arab laborers with Jews.  A7  MORE WOES FOR SREBRENICA  A Bosnian commander ordered a United Nations convoy to leave Srebrenica without the Muslim civilians the trucks had come to evacuate. He said that permitting the evacuation threatened to leave the Muslim area to Serbian occupation.  A3  SERBS MARCH BEYOND PEACE PACT  A long tradition as ruthless warriors used to suffering and winning lay beneath the message Bosnia's Serbs sent the world when they voted against a plan to end the fighting in Bosnia and Herzegovina and redistribute the land.  A3  Azerbaijan said Armenia has broadened its offensive.  A7  Johannesburg Journal: The adventures of Madam and Eve.  A4  National A10-18  NAVY TURNAROUND ON WOMEN  The Navy's top admiral wants to allow women to serve in combat eventually and has recommended expanding the number of jobs on ships that are open to them immediately, Pentagon officials said.  A1  GAY SAILOR'S SQUAD SPEAKS  Flight instructors assigned with the sailor who successfully challenged the Navy's ban on homosexuals say their point of view was not being addressed in the public debate on the subject.  A18  MILITARY WORKERS STRANDED  So far, the shift of many bases and weapons factories to reduced or altered missions has left most of the highly trained workers without outlets for their skills.  A1  MARKETING OF THE PRESIDENT  President Clinton has surrounded himself with aides who are steeped in the latest technology, and they are marketing the President in ways never tried before.  A1  U.S. DISPUTED IN CULT SIEGE  Lawyers for the leaders of a cult besieged by Federal agents near Waco, Tex., gave a version of a Feb. 28 gunfight that differed from that of the authorities.  A10  REPUBLICAN POWER STRUGGLE  News Analysis: The stalemate in the Senate over the jobs measure in the budget package concerns not spending but rather Republican power, both collectively and individually, and Presidential ambitions.  A14  FRUSTRATION AT ARTS CENTER  James Wolfensohn, an investment banker, cellist and arts patron who has triumphed at everything he put his hand to, may have met his match in the Kennedy Center.  A15  Most heads of major charities earn six figures, a survey shows.  A15  READING A TEXAS ELECTION  A crowded race to fill the Senate seat vacated by Lloyd Bentsen is likely to evolve into a preview of the 1994 Congressional elections and a kind of early referendum on Bill Clinton's Presidency.  A13  The A.C.L.U. opposed the second trial in the Rodney King case.  A10  The shuttle Discovery was prepared to study the ozone layer.  A10  These days, the C.I.A. director must play host to politicians.  A14  Metro Digest B1  EXPERIMENTAL SCHOOLS  In the most sweeping expansion of New York City's public high school system in decades, school officials are rushing to sign up students and prepare classrooms for the inauguration of 37 experimental schools, each with a curriculum centered on a separate theme.  A1  Business Digest D1  Arts/Entertainment C13-18  Michael Ovitz's reach.  C13  Laurels for "Car Talk." C13  Theater: Cirque du Soleil.  C13  Music: The Philharmonic's European tour.  C13  Dance: "Swan Lake." C14  In Review C15  Word and Image: "Medicine at the Crossroads." C16  Docudrama tackles fat cats.  C16  "For Love," by Sue Miller.  C18  Sports C1-11  Auto Racing: Remembering Alan Kulwicki.  C9  Baseball: Ball drops, season begins.  C1  Confusion and cuts on Yanks' final day.  C2  Mets open against Rockies.  C2  Basketball: Stage is set for title game.  C1  Lynch the key for Carolina.  C6  Texas Tech wins women's title.  C7  Knicks defeat Spurs.  C1  Nets lose to Cavaliers.  C8  Bulls beat Celtics.  C8  Column: Vecsey on Chris Webber C6  Football: Trade rumors surround Montana.  C11  Ismail unable to outrun controversy.  C11  Golf: Love looks for the Masters touch.  C9  Hockey: Rangers defeat Capitals.  C3  Devils fall to Penguins.  C3  Maine savors championship victory.  C2  Horse Racing: Eliza departs from Derby field.  C4  Tennis: Graf beats Sanchez Vicario.  C9  Obituaries B7-8  Andrew Goodman, former owner of Bergdorf Goodman.  B7  Ludwig Jesselson, philanthropist and commodity trading executive.  B8  Frank W. Sharp, financier involved in 1970's stock scandal.B8  Woodrow Swancutt, Air Force General and atomic test pilot.  B7  Editorials/Op-Ed A16-17  Editorials  At last, a team for Justice.  Public space for the public.  Karl E. Meyer: Russia's history.  Letters  Anthony Lewis: The limit of shame.  William Safire: In the cruelest month.  Andrew O'Hehir: Ireland's troubled sleep.  Marie Brenner: Girls of summer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
