<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pondering an Energy Tax That Can't Please All the People</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586934"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXCISE TAXES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENTSEN, LLOYD (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD7173DF932A05752C0A965958260" item-length="2070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pondering an Energy Tax That Can't Please All the People</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE energy tax being considered by the Clinton Administration could reduce the budget deficit, cut oil imports and meet environmental goals. But before the Administration asks Congress to approve one, it will have to decide which problems it wants cured the most, and whom it is willing to offend in the process.</p>
        <p>Last weekend the Treasury Secretary, Lloyd Bentsen, said the Administration was considering a "broad-based energy tax." Experts say that there are three practical ways to levy such a tax. First is the "B.T.U." tax, in which each unit of energy, no matter what the source, would be taxed at the same rate; second is a sales tax on the fuel used by utilities, industries and individuals ; third is a "carbon tax" based on how much carbon dioxide the fuel's use creates. Other possibilities -- not so broad-based -- are taxes on oil imports and on gasoline.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE energy tax being considered by the Clinton Administration could reduce the budget deficit, cut oil imports and meet environmental goals. But before the Administration asks Congress to approve one, it will have to decide which problems it wants cured the most, and whom it is willing to offend in the process.</p>
        <p>Last weekend the Treasury Secretary, Lloyd Bentsen, said the Administration was considering a "broad-based energy tax." Experts say that there are three practical ways to levy such a tax. First is the "B.T.U." tax, in which each unit of energy, no matter what the source, would be taxed at the same rate; second is a sales tax on the fuel used by utilities, industries and individuals ; third is a "carbon tax" based on how much carbon dioxide the fuel's use creates. Other possibilities -- not so broad-based -- are taxes on oil imports and on gasoline.</p>
        <p>Each produces a different set of winners and losers, allies and enemies. The carbon tax, for example, would hit residents of the Midwest very hard, and the oil import tax would hurt the Northeast; both would be felt much more mildly in the Pacific Northwest.</p>
        <p>If any energy tax is enacted, consumers would pay more not just for the energy they buy directly, like gasoline or electricity. Everything has an energy component, from maple syrup, which is produced with prodigious amounts of oil, to a dentist's filling a cavity, which requires electricity for the drill. Indeed, most people pay more for energy through the goods and services they buy than they pay directly in utility or fuel bills. In that sense, a "broad-based energy tax" could resemble a national sales tax or a value-added tax.</p>
        <p>Picking which tax will emerge, if any, is difficult. A spokesman for the Treasury Department, Scott Dykema, said on Friday that "nothing has been ruled in and nothing has been ruled out."</p>
        <p>But Roger Altman, deputy Treasury Secretary, said in an interview with John McLaughlin, host of the television program "The McLaughlin Group", on Friday that "there are good arguments for a B.T.U. tax, and there are good arguments for an ad valorem tax." An ad valorem tax is a sales tax on energy.</p>
        <p>"I think those two are the primary options in this area," he said. "I don't think that a gasoline tax is as attractive, I don't think that a carbon tax is as attractive, but whether the President will ultimately decide on an energy tax at all, and how he'll come down as between these two or some of the other options, I don't know."</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, key players have yet to take a position. Dan Rostenkowski, the chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, reiterated last week that he favors a gasoline tax, 25 cents a gallon or more, and has also said he would support other tax increases if the President wants them. But he has not been more detailed on the subject of energy taxes.</p>
        <p>Likewise, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, the New York Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Finance Committee, has supported an energy tax but not expressed any preference thus far.</p>
        <p>Whatever tax is chosen, implementation would probably be complicated. And the tax would create a drag on the economy -- perhaps even a sudden burst of inflation. But such taxes are also extremely attractive as a way to raise money. The national energy bill is about $475 billion a year, nearly 10 percent of the gross domestic product. "There's real money here," said Phillip K. Verleger Jr., an energy and commodity economist. If the Administration holds to its goal of cutting the deficit by $145 billion in four years, that implies major revenue growth even if there are also spending cuts.</p>
        <p>Some people in the energy industry say that energy should not be singled out for taxation. "Good economics tells you you should raise revenue from the broadest source possible," said Bruce G. Humphrey, the chief economist at the Edison Electric Institute, the trade association of investor-owned utilities. "An energy tax literally excludes 90 percent of the rest of the economy." The result, he said, is distortions in the economy.</p>
        <p>But that is the idea, say proponents who want to change the way energy is used. However, such considerations may be secondary, especially in Mr. Bentsen's mind. The trial balloon for this tax was floated by the Treasury Secretary, not the Energy Secretary, Hazel Rollins O'Leary, who told the Senate Energy Committee in her confirmation hearings a few days earlier that she did not favor energy taxes.</p>
        <p>Following is a description of the options: The 'B.T.U.' Tax</p>
        <p>Fuel comes in many forms and when engineers compare them -- to decide, say, whether to run a factory on oil or natural gas -- they refer to the heat content as measured by B.T.U.'s, or British thermal units.  Trivia buffs will recall that a B.T.U. is the quantity of heat needed to raise the temperature of one pound of water by one degree Fahrenheit at or near 39.2 degrees.</p>
        <p>Some people, including Mr. Altman, say that rather than taxing coal by the ton or oil by the barrel, which effectively means different taxes for different kinds of fuels, they should be taxed according to a common standard. Each B.T.U., no matter what fuel it came from, would be taxed at the same rate.</p>
        <p>Under this tax, the hardest hit would be coal, because its price per million B.T.U.'s is the lowest, around $1.50, so on a percentage basis, any fixed tax would add to coal's cost the most. The price of a million B.T.U.'s of natural gas varies by season but is generally around $2. The price of heavy oil, the kind most often in competition with gas and coal, varies sharply but recently has been around $2.50 per million B.T.U.'s.</p>
        <p>By contrast, a B.T.U. tax would fall only lightly on the uranium used in nuclear power plants. Uranium, which is not priced by the B.T.U., in any case costs far less than fossil fuels. (Most of nuclear energy's costs come from capital and labor.)</p>
        <p>A B.T.U. tax could also be applied to energy from windmills and hydroelectric plants. Currently the Energy Department measures the electric output of those plants and calculates how many B.T.U.'s would have been required to make that electricity from the average plant running on fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>"A B.T.U. tax might be viewed as being regionally fairer" than a carbon tax, which would hit some fuels more than others, said Roger Dower, an energy expert at the World Resources Institute, a nonprofit group in Washington that advocates the use of taxes to achieve environmental goals. But Mr. Dower added that such a tax, while more politically palatable, is not aimed at the fuels that cause the most damage.</p>
        <p>Some analysts say the tax would drive some users to oil from coal, therefore increasing reliance on oil imports. Also, a B.T.U. tax would discourage the use of not just fossil fuels but all energy, including environmentally benign "renewable" sources like wind, geothermal energy or wood from tree farms.</p>
        <p>As measured in B.T.U.'s, about 40 percent of the energy consumed in this country comes from oil, 24 percent from natural gas, 23 percent from coal, 8 percent from nuclear power and 4 percent from hydroelectricity. If the tax were levied by energy content, those fuels would bear it in those proportions.</p>
        <p>A variant of a B.T.U. tax would be a fixed tax on the price of all fuels -- say 5 percent. It would be just like a sales tax. This would exempt windmills, hydroelectric dams and geothermal energy, whose operators do not pay for fuel. Nuclear power would benefit, too, because uranium is very cheap, even if reactors are expensive.  The Carbon Tax</p>
        <p>Most environmentalists favor something more targeted: a tax on fuels in proportion to the amount of carbon dioxide their use creates. Carbon dioxide is implicated by scientists as the single most important gas in global warming. Among fossil fuels, natural gas produces the least carbon dioxide, oil is in the middle and coal produces the most. Hydroelectricity and nuclear power produce none; windmills, which are on the threshold of commercial success, and solar electric systems, which are a step behind wind, are also free of carbon dioxide. Vice President Gore, when he was a Senator, expressed support for a carbon tax.</p>
        <p>"I think a carbon tax makes sense," said Dr. Harold M. Hubbard, now a fellow at the Hawaii Natural Energy Institute, who wrote an article in Scientific American two years ago that environmentalists hail as a landmark in explaining why energy should be taxed. "A carbon tax is probably the most politically acceptable and even-handed way," he said, pointing to the goals of reducing dependence on fossil fuels, moving to "sustainable" energy sources, and "spreading the misery over a broader base."</p>
        <p>But some regions would suffer much more than others from a carbon tax. Almost 90 percent of the electricity in Ohio comes from coal. By contrast, about 90 percent of the electricity in Washington state is from hydroelectricity or nuclear power. That means the energy-intensive aluminum mills of the Pacific Northwest could continue almost unaffected by a carbon tax, while the farms and factories of the Midwest would face huge new costs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Humphrey of the Edison Electric Institute said hypothetically that a tax of $100 per ton of carbon emitted by burning fuel would raise the price of a ton of coal by 230 percent, of oil by 65 percent, and of natural gas by 90 percent.</p>
        <p>At most utility power plants a million B.T.U.'s turns into about 105 kilowatt-hours of electricity. This implies an increase of about 2.4 cents per kilowatt-hour from coal-burning plants on a national average price of electricity of about 7.5 cents -- a big blow to customers.</p>
        <p>The tax would favor renewable energy sources and nuclear power over other sources. But John H. Lichtblau, chairman of the Petroleum Industry Research Foundation, said the main effect would be to make coal less competitive against gas. "Most inter-fuels competition is in the electric sector, with coal and gas," he said.</p>
        <p>Proposing a carbon tax would also create an instant nexus of opposition, from the coal industry and coal-state members of Congress. Environmentalists and tax experts refer to Robert C. Byrd, the West Virginia Democrat who is the President Pro Tem of the Senate, as if he were a force of nature when they describe how difficult it would be to enact a tax over his opposition. The Oil-Import Fee</p>
        <p>Both a carbon tax and a B.T.U. tax would dampen demand for oil, but neither would do anything for domestic oil producers, which have lost nearly half a million jobs in 10 years and are now producing less oil than at any time since the early 1960's. The independent producers -- that is, those whose companies only produce oil, as opposed to refining or marketing it -- recently called for a fee of some kind on oil imports. Backed by some oil-patch members of Congress, this would amount to a more narrowly based energy tax.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, J. Bennett Johnston, the Louisiana Democrat who is chairman of the Senate Energy Committee, said he would propose a floor price of $25 a barrel on oil imports. If the world price were lower, the Government would impose a tariff to effectively raise the price to $25.</p>
        <p>But the United States has ratified a free trade agreement with Canada, one of this country's largest sources of oil, and has signed, if not ratified, a similar agreement with Mexico, another major producer. Washington would also like to avoid destabilizing Venezuela, a big source of imports, or offending an ally, Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>An oil-import tax also has problems. For example, of the roughly 94 million housing units in this country, more than half, about 48 million, use natural gas, and only about 13 million use heating oil. Nearly all of those 13 million are in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Alternatively, Washington could propose a tax only on gasoline, said Jeffrey C. Genzer, the lawyer for the National Association of State Energy Officials. That would raise the ire of people in the West, who typically drive longer distances, but it would also upset state officials, who would see that increase as pre-empting future increases in state gasoline taxes.</p>
        <p>In budget maneuvering last year, Congress shied away from a gasoline-tax increase of even 5 cents. Such a tax produces severe differences in impact by region and income. But in its favor, the price of gasoline is low now, which might make it more politically palatable.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
