<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bubbles May Have Speeded Life's Origins on Earth</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="619908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUBBLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOLOGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LERMAN, LOUIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D81231F935A35754C0A965958260" item-length="1733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bubbles May Have Speeded Life's Origins on Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HARDLY anything matches the evanescence of bubbles, those fragile watery spheres filled with air that have but a moment before they dissolve or burst. Time enough, though, to enchant with their iridescence in sunlight, give scented caresses in a warm bath or tickle the nose over a champagne glass. Even time, perhaps, to have set in motion chemical reactions that led to the origin of life.</p>
        <p>The role of bubbles in the creation of life on earth is one of the newest approaches to solving the scientific mystery that is probably second in importance only to the problem of how the universe itself began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HARDLY anything matches the evanescence of bubbles, those fragile watery spheres filled with air that have but a moment before they dissolve or burst. Time enough, though, to enchant with their iridescence in sunlight, give scented caresses in a warm bath or tickle the nose over a champagne glass. Even time, perhaps, to have set in motion chemical reactions that led to the origin of life.</p>
        <p>The role of bubbles in the creation of life on earth is one of the newest approaches to solving the scientific mystery that is probably second in importance only to the problem of how the universe itself began.</p>
        <p>No one is suggesting that bubbles might explain everything. But in a new hypothesis receiving close attention, the multitudes of bubbles forming on the surface of the primordial seas must have collected chemicals and concentrated them for synthesis into complex molecules. Eventually, through multistage reactions constantly repeated by uncounted generations of bubbles, the molecules grew in size and ambition, ready for the transition to living, reproducing cells.</p>
        <p>The bubble hypothesis was described yesterday by Louis Lerman, a geophysicist at Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory in California, at a conference in Barcelona of the International Society for the Study of the Origin of Life. He also explained the concept in an interview last week, calling it the prebiotic origin of organic molecules hypothesis.</p>
        <p>Biologists said the concept seemed sound, was based on well-established physical principles and was certainly worth detailed study. "It's an imaginative hypothesis," said Dr. Harold Morowitz, professor of biology at George Mason University in Fairfax, Va., the author of "Beginnings of Cellular Life" (Yale University Press, 1992).</p>
        <p>Dr. Sherwood Chang, a specialist in the origin of life at the Ames Research Center in Mountain View, Calif., said, "Clearly the ocean-atmosphere interface is a dynamic environment worthy of much future study and simulation as a site for chemical evolution."</p>
        <p>The earth is about 4.5 billion years old, and the earliest unequivocal fossil evidence of living organisms is dated at 3.5 billion years. According to Mr. Lerman's hypothesis, some time before those fossils the earth was already seeded with prebiotic organic compounds, composed mainly of carbon atoms, which would later be synthesized into the building blocks of living organisms. The initial organic material could have been delivered from space by falling meteorites, which are known to contain such molecules, or spewed out by volcanic eruptions -- or it could have come from both sources.</p>
        <p>Once dispersed in the air and the sea, then covering almost the entire earth, the simple organic chemicals were trapped by underwater bubbles and atmospheric aerosols and droplets. When the bubbles rose to the surface and burst, according to the hypothesis, the more concentrated organic material was ejected into the air and carried upward by winds.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric chemistry, triggered by lightning or solar ultraviolet radiation, then altered the material into complex organic molecules that precipitated back down to earth as rain and snow. Raindrops and snowflakes, as well as the wind and waves, created more bubbles on the sea surface, starting the cycle all over again. Mr. Lerman called the cycle "a natural reactor for prebiotic chemistry."</p>
        <p>As he remarked, "It may not have been a global primordial soup which was the key to chemical evolution, but the primordial bubble."</p>
        <p>For several decades, most thinking about the origin of life has centered on the idea that chemical evolution somehow occurred in a primordial soup, a variation of Darwin's speculation that life started in "a warm little pond." In this view, set forth in the 1930's by A. I. Oparin, a Russian scientist, vast stores of compounds containing carbon and hydrogen and other chemicals accumulated in the earth's early waters. Energy from lightning and solar radiation then caused the compounds to evolve spontaneously into living matter.</p>
        <p>An experiment in 1953 by Dr. Stanley L. Miller, then a graduate student working with Dr. Harold Urey at the University of Chicago, provided the first clear laboratory evidence that life could arise out of simple chemical reactions. He did this by sending sparks of electricity, to simulate lightning, into a mixture of atmospheric gases and warm water, which produced amino acids that form proteins essential to life.  Mechanism for Life to Begin</p>
        <p>One attraction of the new hypothesis is that it offers a mechanism for a rapid chemical evolution. "Lerman is suggesting how the primordial soup might have been stirred up," said Dr. James P. Ferris, a chemist at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., and editor of the journal Origins of Life and Evolution of the Biosphere.</p>
        <p>As long as scientists thought life had almost a billion years to get started, the relatively passive primordial soup model served their purposes. Once the early molten earth cooled off and developed a solid crust, rampant volcanism dispersed water vapor and other gases, producing a thick atmosphere and vast oceans. This occurred by 4.4 billion years ago, time enough presumably to cook up the chemically-rich mixture that resulted in the first life for which there is fossil evidence, 3.5 billion years ago.</p>
        <p>But scientists had failed to take into account the heavy bombardment of huge asteroids that blasted the inner solar system until at least 3.8 billion years ago. The earliest geological period of earth is not called Hadean for nothing; it was a nonliving hell.</p>
        <p>The cratered surfaces of the Moon, Mars and Mercury testify to the bombardment's devastating effects. And there is no reason to think that Earth would have been spared. Geologists estimate that the extensive Imbrium Basin on the Moon was produced by the impact of an object at least 160 miles in diameter.</p>
        <p>Since an extraterrestrial object no bigger than six miles wide is thought to have contributed to the mass extinctions on Earth 65 million years ago, dooming the dinosaurs, scientists now recognize that life might not have had a chance to get started on Earth until after the bombardment ended 3.8 billion years ago, after the Imbrium impact. Timing of Process</p>
        <p>Using estimates of impact fluxes, Dr. David J. Stevenson of the California Institute of Technology and Dr. Norman H. Sleep of Stanford University, have calculated that shorter time intervals, from six million to 165 million years, may have been available for prebiotic evolution than previously thought.</p>
        <p>Another complication to previous models is that the atmosphere gases assumed for the Miller-Urey experiment may have been wrong. Scientists suggest that in the absence of the protective ozone layer, ultraviolet radiation would have destroyed ammonia and methane in the atmosphere; the major atmospheric components were probably carbon dioxide and nitrogen from volcanoes. Without ammonia and methane, the supposed synthesis of amino acids would have been more problematic.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lerman first raised the idea of the bubble cycle in 1986 and has been working ever since to develop it as a full hypothesis, especially in view of the relatively short time now thought to have been available.</p>
        <p>Being a geophysicist, not a chemist or biologist, Mr. Lerman emphasized that in the hypothesis he was not replacing the details of prebiotic chemistry that have already been worked out by others. He said he was "providing the engineering scaffolding that will allow the specific chemistry at any given stage to go from one level of complexity to the next."</p>
        <p>For this, Mr. Lerman said, he made only two fundamental assumptions. One is that there was an ocean then and that it interacted with the atmosphere, conditions accepted by all scientists. There is no reason to think the rotating Earth was not generating winds and waves, then as much as now. The other assumption, also not unreasonable, is that there were prebiotic organic materials of some kind.</p>
        <p>Scientists also said that the role of bubbles and aerosols in circulating chemical compounds in the ocean has been known for years. At any given time, bubbles cover 3 percent to 4 percent of the ocean's surface. Disturbances of the water can create concave indentations that eventually fold back on themselves, making a closed cavity, a bubble, containing air. The inner lining of this sphere was formerly the surface of the water, containing the chemicals and metal particles that had been there.</p>
        <p>In other theories, clays and minerals like iron pyrite have been credited with playing central roles in the origin of life, from acting as catalysts to serving as templates for self-replicating organisms. Bubbles, Mr. Lerman noted, are excellent scavengers of minerals and clay particles.</p>
        <p>Although most scientists are skeptical of origin-of-life theories invoking clay and minerals, Mr. Lerman said, "If they did play an important role in prebiotic organic synthesis, the bubble cycle may well have played a crucial role by concentrating clays and organics at a common meeting ground."</p>
        <p>But the main point, Mr. Lerman said, is that the bubbles and their atmospheric counterparts, aerosols and rain drops or snow, provided the organizing matrix in which chemicals could concentrate, stabilize and synthesize into more complex molecules. The bubble cycle serves these functions to this day.</p>
        <p>Other scientists emphasize that much more analysis and experimentation would be required before the validity of the bubble-cycle hypothesis could be established. Mr. Lerman, collaborating with Dr. Chang, has proposed building an experimental device that would be able to test some of these properties of bubbles.  Of Mars and Beyond</p>
        <p>Much of the current research has been focused on later steps in the chain of events leading to life, namely the problem of how organisms, once they arose by some alchemy, could reproduce themselves and so become truly living matter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lerman is also contemplating other steps. He said such a mechanism for the chemical evolution of life over short periods might improve the chances that life could have arisen elsewhere, on Mars perhaps or on planets around other stars. But that is another story, since scientists are having enough trouble just figuring out how it began on the one world where its existence is beyond dispute -- Earth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
