<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Weekend; Travails of a Would-Be Cheerleader's Biggest Fan</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601117"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">POSITIVELY TRUE ADVENTURES OF THE ALLEGED TEXAS CHEERLEADER</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDC1030F93AA35757C0A965958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Weekend; Travails of a Would-Be Cheerleader's Biggest Fan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A couple of years ago, the story of the Texas housewife who set out to advance her eighth-grade daughter's cheerleading ambitions by arranging to kill the mother of a rival classmate quickly snagged the public's fancy. The news media wasted no time in descending on the town of Channelview with opportunities for interviews on national television and contracts for possible movies.</p>
        <p>An earnest, typically solemn ABC "Movie of the Week" has already been broadcast. Now, putting this slice of Americana in far more whacky and astute perspective, there is "The Positively True Adventures of the Alleged Texas Cheerleader-Murdering Mom," directed by Michael Ritchie (who also directed the movie "Smile") and having its premiere on HBO tomorrow night. Holly Hunter and Swoosie Kurtz give the most dazzling performances of their already formidable careers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A couple of years ago, the story of the Texas housewife who set out to advance her eighth-grade daughter's cheerleading ambitions by arranging to kill the mother of a rival classmate quickly snagged the public's fancy. The news media wasted no time in descending on the town of Channelview with opportunities for interviews on national television and contracts for possible movies.</p>
        <p>An earnest, typically solemn ABC "Movie of the Week" has already been broadcast. Now, putting this slice of Americana in far more whacky and astute perspective, there is "The Positively True Adventures of the Alleged Texas Cheerleader-Murdering Mom," directed by Michael Ritchie (who also directed the movie "Smile") and having its premiere on HBO tomorrow night. Holly Hunter and Swoosie Kurtz give the most dazzling performances of their already formidable careers.</p>
        <p>We meet Wanda Holloway (Ms. Hunter) after her trial for attempted murder (at which she was convicted) has been declared a mistrial on a technicality, a ruling still being appealed when the movie opens. Now quite blonde and almost chic, Wanda is being interviewed for a sleazy television magazine program, giving her version of what happened and pointing out that unlike the serial-murderer Jeffrey Dahmer, she never really killed anyone. "It's not even funny, O.K.?" she says in a drawl that could boil grits. Wanda is clearly what you could call a pistol. If she points herself in your direction, run for cover.</p>
        <p>Told in flashback, Wanda's story is a disquieting parable of life in Small Town, U.S.A., where for all those millions watching "Donahue" and "Oprah," chances of success can boil down to the remote possibility of your son's excelling in sports or your daughter's becoming a popular cheerleader. Wanda was never a cheerleader. Her father, she explains, was a Baptist and was very family oriented. Wanda is still the pianist for her local church, where one day she hears the minister request a "prayer for any of our parishioners who are sick, troubled or indicted." Even her eyebrow is raised discreetly.</p>
        <p>Sensing that her daughter, Shanna (Frankie Ingrassia), genuinely sweet but not especially gifted, is not going to win the cheerleading sweepstakes, Wanda goes to her former brother-in-law, Terry Harper (Beau Bridges), slob survivor of four marriages and assorted petty scrapes with the law. She wants Terry to devise some way to get rid of a neighbor, Verna Heath (Elizabeth Ruscio), whose daughter is more talented than Shanna. A giggling Wanda keeps hatching plots in Terry's car ("Send her to Cuba or something"), not knowing that early on he has been wired by the police. Says the very serious Wanda: "The things you do for your kids. God!"</p>
        <p>Terry, meanwhile, lives in a ramshackle mobile home with Marla (Ms. Kurtz), who, when not seeing furry little things on the walls, might suddenly take to removing the hair on her legs with Drano or Easy-Off. Rarely leaving her own private ozone layer, she will try to come to the defense of Wanda at the subsequent trial. She does not make a credible witness.</p>
        <p>The bizarre in this film is periodically spiked with sober insights. An explosion at an oil refinery obviously leaves fragile lives badly shaken. Rattling on about "a lack of sensitivity around here," Wanda says that in Texas the only attitude toward husbands who beat wives or women being bitten by snakes in the supermarket is "Glad it wasn't me." Ms. Hunter's Wanda can, even in the middle of another dizzily ominous diatribe, let intriguing signs of uncertainty flicker across her face. Ms. Kurtz's Marla just won't back down, triumphantly snapping at Terry that "crazy women are made by crazy men." In the background, a radio news report on breaking events in the Persian Gulf is quoting President George Bush on the clear differences between good and evil, right and wrong.</p>
        <p>The final section of this diabolically provocative film focuses on the accompanying publicity circus. Everybody wants a piece of the rights action. Some, like Wanda's first husband, are shrewder than others. The story reaches the pinnacle when it becomes the subject of a joke in Johnny Carson's monologue. Even Verna, the intended victim, keeps a book of press clippings and talks amiably to the movie people (Jane Anderson, who wrote this script, appears as herself). Told that Holly Hunter is going to play Wanda for HBO, Verna says, "No, I think it should be Susan Lucci."</p>
        <p>In the final scene, Verna is sitting in the school stadium, coaching her pompon daughter as dusk falls. In the corner of the picture, an American flag is being lowered, descending ever so slowly.  The Positively True Adventures of the Alleged Texas Cheerleader-Murdering Mom HBO, tomorrow night (At 8 in the New York area) Directed by Michael Ritchie; written by Jane Anderson; original music by Lucy Simon. James Manos Jr., producer; Frederick S. Pierce and Kyle A. Heinrich, executive producers. A Frederick S. Pierce Company and Sudden Entertainment production of a Michael Ritchie film.  Wanda Holloway . . . Holly Hunter Terry Harper . . . Beau Bridges Marla Harper . . . Swoosie Kurtz Shanna . . . Frankie Ingrassia Verna Heath . . . Elizabeth Ruscio Troy McKinney . . . Matt Frewer Shane Holloway . . . Fred Koehler Tony Harper . . . Gregg Henry C. D. Holloway . . . Eddie Jones Mickey . . . Katie Layman</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
