<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Rethinking the Refrigerator</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUNPOWER INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA1638F934A15755C0A965958260" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Rethinking the Refrigerator</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Clinton Administration recently announced a "revolutionary development" in environmentally friendly refrigerator technology, the adjectives flowed like Freon through a cooling coil.</p>
        <p>"This is an exciting, technological breakthrough," Carol M. Browner, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said in the news release. "We believe this invention will do for the refrigerator and air conditioning industry what the microchip did for the computer."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Clinton Administration recently announced a "revolutionary development" in environmentally friendly refrigerator technology, the adjectives flowed like Freon through a cooling coil.</p>
        <p>"This is an exciting, technological breakthrough," Carol M. Browner, the Administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, said in the news release. "We believe this invention will do for the refrigerator and air conditioning industry what the microchip did for the computer."</p>
        <p>But the E.P.A.-financed development, a technique for making energy-saving compressor motors for home refrigerators and room air conditioners, has met a cool reception from the manufacturers in the over $6 billion-a-year market for such devices.</p>
        <p>Despite the agency's calculation that its approach will conserve energy use by up to 15 percent and save consumers $150 in electric bills over the life of the machine, manufacturers say it is too soon to tell if the technology is reliable enough to endure the 20 years or so of useful life that Americans have come to expect from refrigerators.</p>
        <p>"There are still significant design obstacles to overcome," said Len Swatkowski, vice president for technology at the Association of Home Appliance Manufacturers. "What they have now is a prototype."</p>
        <p>That the manufacturers do not share the E.P.A.'s euphoria may be understandable, for these are tough times in the refrigerator business. One set of Government regulations is forcing manufacturers to reduce the amount of energy needed to keep food cold. Meanwhile, other regulations will ban the use of chlorofluorocarbons -- the main ingredient in refrigerating and insulating materials -- because they have been linked to depletion of the earth's ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Substitutes for the chlorofluorocarbon materials that will be banished from manufacturing after 1995 have been developed, but it is not clear that they will be compatible with oil lubricants in the compressors that are the heart of a refrigerator or air conditioner. And lubrication is everything in machines that are supposed to operate reliably for two decades.</p>
        <p>In its recent announcement, the E.P.A. declared the problem solved. Using $200,000 in Federal money, Sunpower Inc., a small research company in Athens, Ohio, has developed a compressor that does not need oil lubricants.</p>
        <p>REPRESENTATIVES of the appliance industry concede that the technology is interesting, but they are quick to point out that it is unproven. "This is truly a development program," said Ken Taulbee, a vice president of Americold, the largest producer of refrigerator compressors in the United States, with about 50 percent of the market. "We are going to have to do at least three years of life testing and field testing before we can decide if it is a commercial product."</p>
        <p>E.P.A. officials said that their role was limited to helping develop the basic technology and that it is up to appliance makers and their suppliers to do the required reliability and other testing.</p>
        <p>And despite the industry naysayers, Jean Lupinacci, an official in the agency's Global Change division, said the technology was one of the few alternatives to conventional compressors to have drawn widespread interest from the appliance industry. "There is often a difference between what they say in public," she said, "and what they say in private about where they want to go."</p>
        <p>Today's refrigerators use reciprocating compressors that are similar to a cylinder in a car engine. Rotary motion from an electric motor turns a crankshaft that is attached to a piston by a connecting rod. As the piston descends, an intake valve opens and refrigerant flows in.</p>
        <p>The valve closes as the piston moves upward, compressing the fluid. Near the top of the stroke, the outlet valve opens and the compressed refrigerant is pushed out, circulating through the cooling tubes where it sheds the heat collected from inside the refrigerator.</p>
        <p>The technology eliminates the crankshaft and connecting rod. Instead the piston is mounted on a spring and is positioned inside an electrically energized coil where it moves up and down in response to changes in the strength of the magnetic field produced by the coil.</p>
        <p>THE E.P.A. says that eliminating the crankshaft and connecting rod reduces friction and other energy losses, saving from 9 to 15 percent of the power consumed by the best conventional designs. The agency calculated that if the compressor went into universal use, the reduction in electrical consumption would cut carbon dioxide emissions from utility power plants by 20 billion pounds a year. Carbon dioxide is one of the gases associated with the so-called greenhouse effect that is said to be causing global warming.</p>
        <p>Conventional compressors also use a lot of electricity because they run at full power for as long as it takes to cool a refrigerator or a room to the desired temperature, then switch off until things start to heat up again.</p>
        <p>The Sunpower design, in contrast, can vary the output of the compressor by adjusting the stroke of the piston. This continuous operation, with the piston bouncing up and down in its spring, saves power, according to John Crawford, a program manager at Sunpower, because it eliminates the surge of electricity needed to start an idle compressor.</p>
        <p>Since there is no crankshaft or other mechanical connection in the Sunpower compressor, there is no need for oil as a lubricant. The refrigerant vapor acts as a lubricant between the piston and the cylinder walls.</p>
        <p>Still, appliance-industry officials caution that this free-piston approach has been tried before and was not successful. Mr. Swatkowski of the manufacturers association said General Electric had a patent on a similar design in the 1960's, but never put it into production. One major problem, he said, was in controlling the movement of the piston. Often, it rode too far upward, slamming into the valves and destroying the unit.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Taulbee of Americold said that electronic controls have improved vastly since that time, so he believes that Sunpower's electronic control box should be able to keep the piston within safe limits.</p>
        <p>Being more efficient, however, may also cost more. "That control box looks like a cost adder," Mr. Taulbee said. "And then you have to look at capital costs. How much new tooling would I have to put in to change over?"</p>
        <p>But appliance makers may have no choice but to opt for a more expensive compressor. New Federal electricity efficiency rules that went into effect at the beginning of this year stipulate that new refrigerators draw no more power on average than a 75-watt light bulb, according to Mr. Swatkowski. And more stringent, though still undefined, regulations are due to be imposed in 1998.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. Taulbee is correct, the savings estimated by the E.P.A. may be offset by higher prices for the refrigerators. "The cost of the other components looks about the same as today," he said, "so if you add in the electronic control, we're pretty sure the cost is more."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
