<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Human Noises in Ocean Held to Threaten Marine Mammals</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="643004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHALES AND WHALING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAMMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIGRATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL MARINE FISHERIES SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W.</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Heard Island and McDonald Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mammals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Migration</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6DF1130F93AA25753C1A965958260" item-length="1885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Human Noises in Ocean Held to Threaten Marine Mammals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W.</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the world's oceans increasingly disturbed with man-made sounds, scientists are facing a vexing dilemma: many of the most important discoveries about sea creatures and their environment are made by the use of sound, but some sounds generated by scientists may be contributing to the destruction of the very mammals they want to protect.</p>
        <p>At a meeting here of the Acoustical Society of America this month, scores of experts presented evidence that the welfare and lives of some marine mammals were increasingly threatened by noise of human origin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the world's oceans increasingly disturbed with man-made sounds, scientists are facing a vexing dilemma: many of the most important discoveries about sea creatures and their environment are made by the use of sound, but some sounds generated by scientists may be contributing to the destruction of the very mammals they want to protect.</p>
        <p>At a meeting here of the Acoustical Society of America this month, scores of experts presented evidence that the welfare and lives of some marine mammals were increasingly threatened by noise of human origin.</p>
        <p>The cacophony bombarding animals in the sea comes mostly from industrial underwater explosions, ocean drilling, oil rig construction, ship engines, icebreakers, submarine sonar devices, supersonic aircraft and countless other human sources of noise, not to mention the natural thunder of cracking polar ice fields, marine earthquakes, storms, underwater volcanoes and sounds made by the animals themselves.</p>
        <p>But a certain amount of ocean noise is generated by scientific research.</p>
        <p>Loud, low-pitched noise can travel immense distances through water, often reaching halfway around the world from its source, and spreading and reverberating in all directions. Oceanic noise pollution has reached such a point that the Federal Government is considering a ban on some loud human noises.</p>
        <p>The National Marine Fisheries Service, which is responsible for enforcement of the Marine Mammal Protection Act of 1972, is considering new regulations that may limit scientists to making no ocean noises louder than 120 decibels. The harassment of marine mammals is forbidden by the Marine Mammal Protection Act, and in April the Government is expected to define excessive noise as a form of harassment.</p>
        <p>Some experts have observed that 120 decibels can frighten whales away from their normal migration routes, contending that noise of this intensity should be designated as an upper limit.</p>
        <p>But the suggested 120-decibel limit has brought a storm of anxious comment from underwater acousticians, oceanographers, geologists, bioacoustic experts, climatologists and other scientists whose research depends on oceanic sound, including the kind made by underwater loudspeakers and explosions.</p>
        <p>At a series of discussions during the acoustics meeting here, scientists voiced their objections to Carol Fairfield, an official of the National Marine Fisheries Service. The agency exercises veto power over experiments deemed harmful to whales and seals. Another agency, the Fish and Wildlife Service, is responsible for enforcing rules to protect sea otters, walruses, manatees and polar bears.</p>
        <p>Among the scientists opposing a noise limit of 120 decibels was Dr. John R. Potter of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at La Jolla, Calif. "In many ocean regions, sound at a level of 120 decibels is the natural background," he said. "Dolphin calls are far louder -- up to 220 decibels. Fin whale calls and commercial ships put out about 180 decibels. The noise from polar ice packs is about 150, and breaking waves produce 130.</p>
        <p>"A legal limit of 120 decibels imposed on the sounds scientists use would effectively close down research in underwater acoustics and marine geology, as well as offshore oil prospecting and drilling and many other activities."</p>
        <p>Well-meaning but ill-informed Government regulation could make matters worse, some scientists argued. Dr. William C. Cummins, an acoustics consultant in San Diego, said that the National Marine Fisheries Service itself recently engaged him to study the effects of underwater explosions on Kemp's ridley turtles in the Gulf of Mexico, only to cancel the experiment when officials discovered it would violate the agency's own regulations.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ann Bowles, the senior research biologist at the Hubbs-Sea World Research Institute in San Diego, noted that decibels measured in water are very different from decibel measurements taken in air, where a noise of 110 to 120 decibels causes pain to human ears. In water, equivalent discomfort to a human diver would be caused by about 195 decibels.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fairfield said that no rigid noise limit had yet been decided for the future regulations, but she told scientists at the meeting that if they wished to comment on or influence future regulations, they should quickly write to members of Congress.</p>
        <p>So far, environmental groups have had little to say about oceanic noise pollution. Low Decibels Affect Some Animals</p>
        <p>"Not many of us have experience in this field," said Dr. Rodney Fujita, a scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund's office in Oakland, Calif. "We're intrigued by this nexus between acoustic experiments to measure global atmospheric warming -- very useful and important research -- and the protection of marine mammals against noise, including the noise created by these experiments. But despite conflicting interests, everyone reached amicable agreement on the Heard Island experiment, and I hope that will be the pattern in the future."</p>
        <p>The Heard Island experiment was begun in 1991 by eight nations under the guidance of Dr. Walter Munk, an acoustic oceanographer of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography. It demonstrated the feasibility of measuring the speed of sound as it passes through enormous stretches of ocean. The speed of sound in water is related to the temperature of the water, and from a noise that travels some 11,000 miles from one side of the world to the other, scientists believe they can calculate the average temperature of the water through which it passes. Long-term changes in this average may reflect long-term temperature changes of the global atmosphere, and could reveal the "greenhouse" warming from carbon dioxide pollution that some scientists believe has begun.</p>
        <p>The sound used for this experiment came from an underwater speaker broadcasting from deep water near Heard Island in the Indian Ocean at an intensity of 209 decibels, roughly equivalent to 270 decibels in air, about as loud as a jetliner taking off.</p>
        <p>The Heard Island experiment produced such promising results that a new and more ambitious experiment based on the same idea, called Acoustic Thermometry of Ocean Climate, began in January. The three-year project, sponsored by the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, will also generate noise that could disturb marine mammals.</p>
        <p>Dr. Arthur B. Baggeroer of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a participant in the new experiment, said that for the earlier Heard Island research, scientists had had to obtain a special United States Government permit to "harass" more than 300,000 marine mammals, "virtually every mammal in the Indian Ocean," by broadcasting a loud sound. The new experiment will need even broader regulatory exemptions to proceed.</p>
        <p>Some of the effects of anthropogenic sound on sea mammals seem to occur at low sound levels, while louder sounds may have no effect. Dr. W. John Richardson, a vice president of the Canadian environmental consulting company LGL Ltd. in King City, Ontario, said he had observed bowhead whales scared off by distant boats emitting sounds of only 90 decibels, while other whales tolerated drilling sounds up to 135 decibels.</p>
        <p>Evidence from other investigators suggested that the hearing of some animals may be temporarily or permanently impaired by noise, and that this could seriously impair their ability to communicate or navigate.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sean Todd, a biologist with the Whales Research Group at Memorial University in St. John's, Newfoundland, and a team of Canadian and American colleagues, found behavioral hints that whales off the coast of Newfoundland were becoming deaf. The humpback whales had been feeding on plankton in Chance Cove near Bull Arm, the site of heavy blasting last year to deepen a channel and remove underwater obstructions for passing tankers.</p>
        <p>Whales often become trapped by fish nets in the area, and scientists free them whenever possible. But last year during the blasting, the number of trapped whales increased sharply, Dr. Todd reported. Moreover, two of the whales, after being cut free, became trapped a second time, the first such instance ever recorded by scientists observing whale behavior in the region. (The group was able to keep track of each whale in the area by the distinctive color pattern of its flukes.)</p>
        <p>"Normally, it's the young whales that blunder into the fish nets," Dr. Todd said, "and after one bad experience, they know enough to stay clear of the nets, which they may be able to detect by acoustic echolocation. But this was different. One possibility is that their hearing was impaired by the explosions, and they could no longer spot the nets by echolocation."</p>
        <p>Two whales were killed during the scientists' sojourn at Chance Cove by the underwater detonation of five tons of explosives. One whale was apparently killed immediately and the other survived for two days before stranding.</p>
        <p>One of the leading scientists in the group, Dr. Darlene R. Ketten, a hearing specialist at Harvard Medical School, flew to Newfoundland to dissect and examine the whale's head, using antique flensing knives borrowed from the descendants of whalers living in the area. Essential parts of the whale's gigantic ears were filled with blood and pus, she reported, and were so badly injured that the animals would have been totally deaf if they had survived. The whale that briefly survived the explosion may have succumbed to meningitis, a fatal infection caused by the ear damage.</p>
        <p>Scientists do not know how much noise of what frequency, type and duration is enough to harm various species of marine mammals, but they suspect that the danger may be greater than hitherto realized.</p>
        <p>It was once assumed, for example, that the atmospheric shock wave generated by transport planes flying faster than the speed of sound could not project sound into the ocean below, but this assumption was dashed by one of the reports given at the acoustics meeting.</p>
        <p>Dr. Victor W. Sparrow of Pennsylvania State University presented a mathematical analysis that showed the shock wave from a plane flying at Mach 2.1, or 2.1 times the speed of sound, would send an acoustic pulse into the ocean below. The sound would be sharp and intense to a depth of about 8 feet, and would be audible to animals at a depth of 300 to 400 feet.</p>
        <p>"Since the United States may soon be building supersonic transports for ocean-crossing flights, we need to start looking at their possible effects on marine animals," he said. "If we ever start flying supersonic transports at speeds of Mach 5, as some have proposed, the effect on ocean life would be much greater."</p>
        <p>Enforcement of oceanic noise pollution bans would be next to impossible, however. Regulations promulgated by the United States Government apply only to American waters and to American citizens throughout the world; other nations cannot be compelled to observe them on the high seas. The imposition of noise regulations on tankers and other noisy ships would be difficult.</p>
        <p>Still, scientists hope that some of the worst abuses of noise at sea can be curbed.</p>
        <p>"It may be that the inconvenience of noise to marine mammals will remain unavoidable," Dr. Potter said, "but we must try to prevent noise that causes substantive damage."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
