<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding an Economic System for a New Century; Never Better</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="580187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PETERSON, PETER G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC123CF932A35752C0A965958260" item-length="436" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding an Economic System for a New Century; Never Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The foundation for most of Peter G. Peterson's "Hard Truths for Better Days" (Op-Ed, Dec. 1) is an almost universally accepted but increasingly flawed view of how the economy works and ought to work. Briefly, the core "truth" is the old saw that rising production will solve the problems of unemployment and poverty just as a rising tide lifts all boats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The foundation for most of Peter G. Peterson's "Hard Truths for Better Days" (Op-Ed, Dec. 1) is an almost universally accepted but increasingly flawed view of how the economy works and ought to work. Briefly, the core "truth" is the old saw that rising production will solve the problems of unemployment and poverty just as a rising tide lifts all boats.</p>
        <p>One reason this view is likely to fail is that the planet can only support full employment of the world's growing labor force at a cost of worldwide environmental degradation.</p>
        <p>Equally important is a related but more subtle truth that will undermine public support for averting environmental catastrophe.</p>
        <p>While Bill Clinton and Mr. Peterson are correct that jobs lost in defense may well be created in industries that protect the environment, America's consumers cannot fill their shopping bags with the production of these industries, and they will perceive a further decline in living standards.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the tangible realities of a car, videocassette recorder or compact-disk player, Mr. and Mrs. Public will be unaware of the cancer they did not suffer because the ozone layer was preserved; the arsenic their family didn't ingest because the ground water wasn't contaminated; the funerals they didn't attend because highway safety improved. The list of unperceived benefits can be extended, but the public will not be persuaded to support policies that force it to give up material rewards for invisible blessings.</p>
        <p>Economists know that there are only two ways to improve living conditions: increase supplies of stuff or decrease demands for stuff. But only supply increase is within the purview of economic science. Hence, the prescription for growth, growth, growth (or jobs, jobs, jobs). Yet despite the worship of growth, no economist can imagine a demonstration that an individual is better off today with more stuff than a few years ago with less stuff. (We should exclude those who were starving or ill and are now filled and healthy. Anyway, these are not constituents usually addressed by commentators and politicians.)</p>
        <p>Put another way: the essence of our admirable economic system is to create wants as fast as, or faster than it satisfies them. Thus the improvement of living conditions, meaning greater consumer satisfaction, is, by definition, impossible!</p>
        <p>Jimmy Carter was unfairly maligned for speaking this harder truth, one that is ignored by Peter G. Peterson. JOHN MAHER Hamden, Conn., Dec. 7, 1992</p>
        <p>The writer retired as professor of economics at Southern Connecticut State University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
