<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What a Little Chicken Breath Can Do</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930314T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POULTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MARTHA'S VINEYARD (MASS)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">EDEY, ANNA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Cape Cod and the Islands/Martha's Vineyard</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB103EF934A35750C0A965958260" item-length="1320" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What a Little Chicken Breath Can Do</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN on a blustery zero-degree day, it's so warm -- 80 degrees -- in Anna Edey's solar greenhouse on Martha's Vineyard in Massachsetts that the vents are open. Let those blizzards with their raging winds pound the four layers of plastic glazing outside. The greenhouse has survived hurricanes. And every week, this 3,000-square-foot space produces 60 pounds of greens -- 25 varieties of leaf lettuce and 20 other greens and herbs, like chicory, arugula, beet greens, sorrel, cilantro, dill and parsley. Nasturtiums and borage bloom. Insects drink their nectar.</p>
        <p>This winter greenhouse, which grosses $100,000 a year, is a Solviva greenhouse -- Ms. Edey's own invention. The name is her tribute to the good life that the sun can bring. The greenhouse runs without oil or gas. Its heat and electricity come from the sun -- and the body heat of 100 chickens.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN on a blustery zero-degree day, it's so warm -- 80 degrees -- in Anna Edey's solar greenhouse on Martha's Vineyard in Massachsetts that the vents are open. Let those blizzards with their raging winds pound the four layers of plastic glazing outside. The greenhouse has survived hurricanes. And every week, this 3,000-square-foot space produces 60 pounds of greens -- 25 varieties of leaf lettuce and 20 other greens and herbs, like chicory, arugula, beet greens, sorrel, cilantro, dill and parsley. Nasturtiums and borage bloom. Insects drink their nectar.</p>
        <p>This winter greenhouse, which grosses $100,000 a year, is a Solviva greenhouse -- Ms. Edey's own invention. The name is her tribute to the good life that the sun can bring. The greenhouse runs without oil or gas. Its heat and electricity come from the sun -- and the body heat of 100 chickens.</p>
        <p>"Each chicken puts out eight B.T.U.'s an hour per pound," Ms. Edey said, as the clucking of hens and the occasional crows of two roosters filtered through the north wall. Each hen, scratching about on the earth floor and laying eggs in coops next to the greenhouse wall (lined with 50-gallon bags of water that collect heat), saves the business about two and a half gallons of fuel oil a year. And don't forget the two roosters. Multiply the savings by 100, and you save about 250 gallons of oil a year.</p>
        <p>Not to mention the gold in chicken breath. Chicken breath?</p>
        <p>"They're producing CO2 , which plants need because carbon is their basic building block," said Ms. Edey, a 53-year-old Swedish-born weaver who raises her own sheep for wool. "So if you add more CO2 , the plants will grow more." The carbon dioxide content in the greenhouse is about three or four times as high as in the air outside, she added.</p>
        <p>"So even with shorter days in winter, the plants grow faster than outside in the summer garden," she said. Considering that many commercial growers use bottled carbon dioxide to bolster production in their greenhouses, chickens might become a hot commodity.</p>
        <p>The chicken breath gets to the plants via a solar-powered fan that draws the air from the chicken coop into a series of perforated pipes that lie beneath the soil of the growing beds. The carbon dioxide then simply rises up through the soil particles and into the air of the greenhouse, where it is absorbed by the leaves.</p>
        <p>On Tuesdays, Ms. Edey and a crew of three harvesters pick enough greens, leaf by leaf, for about 200 one-ounce salads a day. The combinations, complete with edible flowers like nasturtiums, red salvia and borage blossoms, which are electric blue and as sweet as honey (bees love them, too), are rinsed in a big tank in the middle of the greenhouse, dried and bagged, and then sold on the island or shipped to restaurants in Boston. The greens are grown without chemical fertilizers or pesticides. Compost and seaweed beef up the soil, and if the aphids and whiteflies get out of control, Ms. Edey just orders more ladybugs and parasitic wasps.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there is no burning oil to pollute the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Ms. Edey learned about the body heat and carbon dioxide of animals from a newspaper article that her ex-mother-in-law had sent her about 10 years ago, when Ms. Edey was experimenting with growing plants in the solar house that she built in 1980. The article told of a nurseryman in Oregon who had traded his oil furnace for 450 rabbits, which saved him $750 a year. (The annual oil bill was $1,000; rabbit food cost $250.)</p>
        <p>"My mother-in-law wrote me a note asking, 'Do you think Vineyard rabbits would do as well?' " said Ms. Edey, who was so inspired by the idea that she sat up all night designing a greenhouse. A dedicated environmentalist and mother of three daughters, she had spent years reading about alternative energy and waste systems (her house has compost toilets) and visiting experimental stations like the New Alchemy Institute on Cape Cod, which raised fish and vegetables for years in solar greenhouses with no backup heat.</p>
        <p>Her own solar house provided free, nonpolluting energy on all but the coldest days (her Franklin stove, which burns compacted rolled newspaper, supplements heat and hot-water needs), as well as producing a year-round garden of greens, tomatoes and herbs.</p>
        <p>"I had four-year-old tomato plants with vines 25 to 40 feet long, and stems as thick as my wrist, producing wonderfully juicy tomatoes in the middle of the winter," Ms. Edey said. "The experts told me this could not be done because of the low light levels in winter, but I had a feeling it was the temperature that was the most crucial factor."</p>
        <p>Ms. Edey began building her $30,000 solar greenhouse in 1983, insisting on her own design specifications, which struck contractors as rather original, to put it mildly.</p>
        <p>"They'd say: 'It'll get too hot. It'll get too cold. It'll get too humid. The bugs from the plants will fly into the house,' " recalled Ms. Edey, who would rather have a few beneficial bugs in the air than chemical pesticides. "The ultimate warning was that the roof would catch fire if I covered it with solar panels."</p>
        <p>That possibility did strike fear in her heart, so she put panels on only a third of the roof. "Now I wish I'd stuck to my original plan," she said. "Because the ventilation system doesn't let the house overheat."</p>
        <p>But back to the rabbits.</p>
        <p>"I started out with three Angora rabbits because I wanted to combine their fur with the sheep fleece," she said. "And I also had 100 chickens, figuring the eggs and Angora would pay for the animal feed."</p>
        <p>Which was great, in theory. The problem was that the rabbits acted too much like rabbits. She had 30 before she knew it. Then 60. And the male rabbits were too aggressive.  "They'd try to kill each other, so I had to put the females in cages," she said.</p>
        <p>So she decided to stick to chickens. The Rhode Island Reds and Plymouth Rocks proved extremely peaceable and needed little care. The two roosters were perfect gentlemen. The flock produced plenty of carbon dioxide and body heat for the greenhouse, as well as high-nitrogen manure. And their healthy life style -- eating fresh greens from the greenhouse and scratching around daily in their outside pen -- produced that rare object: an organic egg with a hard shell and a yolk as orange as the setting sun.</p>
        <p>It seemed perfect until Ms. Edey noticed spots on the leaves of some of her plants.  "They looked as if someone had splashed boiling water on the leaves," she said.</p>
        <p>After calling a number of universities, she found a professor at the University of Massachusetts who pegged the problem on the chickens. He asked: Did she ever smell ammonia, a byproduct of the bird's waste?</p>
        <p>When Ms. Edey said yes, he told her that ammonia concentrations as low as 14 parts per million can be harmful to plants.</p>
        <p>She almost despaired at this wrinkle.</p>
        <p>"I thought of all the gadgets and filters required to get rid of the ammonia," she said, "and began thinking that the animals justaposed too many problems."</p>
        <p>Then she remembered that the people at New Alchemy Institute had heated their greenhouse with manure and vented the ammonia through perforated pipes in the soil.</p>
        <p>"The moisture, carbon and microbes in the soil help transform ammonia into nitrogen, which fertilizes the plants," Ms. Edey said. That's when she put the perforated pipes under the soil.</p>
        <p>And so it goes on the cutting edge. Meanwhile, back on the solar ranch, imagine having your morning coffee under a blooming hibiscus and looking out at a pond through a wall of double-pane glass. Or taking a bath in the afternoon in a deep old-fashioned bathtub with its clawed feet resting on a carpet of grass-green baby's tears, under a little jungle of banana plants and avocado trees, birds of paradise, giant jade plants and flowering jasmine. Not to mention savoring all those greens and tomatoes.</p>
        <p>The house and the greenhouse ask the question, Why not?</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS  Correction:  March 14, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Cuttings column last Sunday, about a solar house and greenhouse on Martha's Vineyard, referred incorrectly to contractors' design concerns. Their warnings about climate, bugs and the possibility of a fire referred to the original design proposed for the house, not for the greenhouse. A picture caption with the column referred incorrectly to the design of the greenhouse. The greenhouse's solar panels are installed on the ground. It is the house that has solar panels on a third of its roof.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 14, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Cuttings column last Sunday, about a solar house and greenhouse on Martha's Vineyard, referred incorrectly to contractors' design concerns. Their warnings about climate, bugs and the possibility of a fire referred to the original design proposed for the house, not for the greenhouse. A picture caption with the column referred incorrectly to the design of the greenhouse. The greenhouse's solar panels are installed on the ground. It is the house that has solar panels on a third of its roof.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
