<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With a Tour of Damaged Beaches, Officials Call for Aid</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="592810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAST EROSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEACHES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATE AND LOCAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTHAMPTON BEACH (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JONES BEACH STATE PARK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCQUISTON, JOHN T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coast Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DC1F3BF935A15751C0A965958260" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With a Tour of Damaged Beaches, Officials Call for Aid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCQUISTON, JOHN T</byline>
      <dateline>WESTHAMPTON BEACH, L.I., Feb. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Warning that Long Island's fragile ecology and tourist-dependent economy are at risk, political and business leaders called today for a joint Federal and state effort to help repair the coastal damage from this winter's stormy weather.</p>
        <p>Staging a media blitz to draw attention to the devastation, the Nassau and Suffolk County Executives, Thomas S. Gulotta and Robert J. Gaffney, led reporters and photographers on a two-and-a-half-hour helicopter tour of the South Shore from Jones Beach, where sand was being trucked in to rebuild the dunes, to Westhampton Beach, where a new inlet, created by a northeaster in December, is now nearly half a mile wide and growing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Warning that Long Island's fragile ecology and tourist-dependent economy are at risk, political and business leaders called today for a joint Federal and state effort to help repair the coastal damage from this winter's stormy weather.</p>
        <p>Staging a media blitz to draw attention to the devastation, the Nassau and Suffolk County Executives, Thomas S. Gulotta and Robert J. Gaffney, led reporters and photographers on a two-and-a-half-hour helicopter tour of the South Shore from Jones Beach, where sand was being trucked in to rebuild the dunes, to Westhampton Beach, where a new inlet, created by a northeaster in December, is now nearly half a mile wide and growing.</p>
        <p>"We are concerned that what has happened since December has brought the island's ecosystem and economy into genuine crisis," said James L. Larocca, president of the Long Island Association, the region's largest business and civic group. He said Federal and state help were essential to help preserve the entire island's 1,180 miles of coastline.</p>
        <p>"We need all levels of government working together on this," said Mr. Larocca, who arranged the aerial news conference. Some Things Unmentioned</p>
        <p>None of the officials on this morning's tour would hazard a guess as to how much beach repairs would cost or who would pay. They all acknowledged, however, that budgets were tight from the Federal Government all the way down to the village level.</p>
        <p>This cost factor has added to growing pressure from many environmentalists to let nature take its course and swallow beaches and summer homes. And even though it may involve losing some of the most expensive real estate in the world, as is the case in the Hamptons, many argue that the expense of fighting the effects of storms and a rising sea level is far too great. They also argue that it would be unfair to taxpayers to spend so much to benefit so few.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gulotta appeared to take a middle road in the debate. "Mother Nature has blessed us with some of the most precious natural resources in the world," he said. "And it's our responsibility as a society to insure that we preserve her gifts. But we must not fight Mother Nature in doing so, but work with her."</p>
        <p>One thing was indisputable: the damage done by the storms.</p>
        <p>Scores of homes that only three months ago sat safely behind dunes at Westhampton Beach, hundreds of feet from the water's edge, now teeter atop pilings in the surf, slowly breaking apart. Scores of other homes have already been washed into the sea. The top half of one home sat in shallow water just inside Moriches Bay, waves washing though the open windows and out the back door.</p>
        <p>At the widening inlet at Westhampton Beach, more than 30 homes have disappeared along with Dune Road, which linked the rest of the narrow barrier beach with its nearly 300 homes to the mainland. Mr. Gaffney said it may take the Army Corps of Engineers until May to decide whether it will reclose the inlet. Local town officials have already said they can't afford to do it alone.</p>
        <p>The Atlantic now flows heavily through the inlet into Moriches Bay, threatening to change the salinity of the bay and expose its prized shellfish beds to an invasion of starfish from the ocean, Mr. Gaffney said.  Nature, and Dredges, at Work</p>
        <p>While the natural rebuilding of the beaches has begun from Coney Island to Montauk, the gradual effort will take decades to replace what was lost in December. However, dredging equipment was at work today at Gilgo Beach and Jones Beach, where the helicopter was set down.</p>
        <p>Some 400,000 cubic yards of sand deposited on the North Shore of the island during the last ice age has been trucked from a quarry in Broad Hollow and dumped to form dunes at Jones Beach, whose reserves were depleted by the December storm.</p>
        <p>Airborne in a bright morning sun, the helicopter's shadow traced the receding shoreline of Fire Island, where more beach houses have been claimed by the sea.</p>
        <p>Where jetties had been built to slow the natural drift of sand from east to west, the beach extended briefly outward but then receded sharply immediately to the west of the last jetty. Such was the case at Westhampton Beach, where environmentalists argue that a scouring action created by the jetties bore through the barrier beach, helping to create the inlet.</p>
        <p>"If we're going to build jetties -- and I'm not suggesting that's the solution, -- we'll have to start at Coney Island and work east all the way to Montauk," said Mr. Larocca. "You have to think of how each action at any one location effects the entire island, and that includes the North Shore as well."</p>
        <p>The effort to save the island's beaches is to be discussed at the Long Island Coastal Conference June 16 and 17 in Uniondale and at Jones Beach. It is sponsored by the Long Island Association with the support of both Nassau and Suffolk counties and the State Office of Parks, Recreation and Historic Preservation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
