<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>George Herbert Walker Bush: A Premature Historical Verdict</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="583676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BESCHLOSS, MICHAEL R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D8133EF934A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>George Herbert Walker Bush: A Premature Historical Verdict</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael R. Beschloss;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BESCHLOSS, MICHAEL R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From "The Historians' Guide to American History," published 2008. BUSH, GEORGE (HERBERT WALKER) (b. June 12, 1924, Milton, Mass.) 41st President of the United States (1989 to 1993)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From "The Historians' Guide to American History," published 2008. BUSH, GEORGE (HERBERT WALKER) (b. June 12, 1924, Milton, Mass.) 41st President of the United States (1989 to 1993)</p>
        <p>A President's historical reputation usually sinks just after he leaves office, especially when he has been defeated for re-election. George Bush was a victim of this phenomenon for an additional reason. His defeat by Bill Clinton in 1992 ushered in a 16-year cycle of progressive activism. During an era dominated by two energetic Presidents -- Bill Clinton and his successor, Al Gore -- the stature of a right-of-center chief executive like George Bush, who recoiled from using the full powers of the Presidency, was bound to suffer.</p>
        <p>Thus, throughout the decade after he left office, memories of the Bush Administration remained vague. Those Americans who thought of the former President at all tended to blame him for mismanaging the economy. In 1994, during a $50,000 speech to the Electric Toaster Manufacturers Association, a horseshoe was thrown at Bush by a protester who blamed him for the loss of his house during the 1990-92 recession. Otherwise the 41st President was rarely mentioned in the press.</p>
        <p>The former President was also treated badly by his own party. After his term ended, Republican leaders instantly disowned him as an unwanted reminder of their flirtation with ideological moderation. At their 1996 convention in Salt Lake City, when Representative Robert Dornan of California was nominated for President, Mr. Bush was not invited onto the podium. Dornan and his running mate, Representative Newt Gingrich, rushed to the retirement homes of former Presidents Richard Nixon and Ronald Reagan for endorsements but eschewed all invitations to be photographed with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>During the 1990's, Mr. Bush enjoyed approximately the same esteem among historians as former President William Howard Taft did during the New Deal. One scholar described Mr. Bush as "another Taft, but without the personality." There were other obvious similarities: both Mr. Taft and Mr. Bush were Yale Republicans with Ohio forebears who owed their Presidential elections to the popularity of their predecessors, Theodore Roosevelt and Ronald Reagan. Most historians now believe that, like Mr. Taft, had Mr. Bush made a stronger public effort to acknowledge his ideological and political debt to his predecessor, the Republican votes he would have gained might have won him re-election.</p>
        <p>Other developments during the 1990's continued to whittle away at Mr. Bush's historical standing. Memoirs by his aides portrayed him as a weak, indecisive figure who consistently refused the counsel of the more brilliant advisers around him -- notably Richard Darman's "I Told Him So" (1993), John Sununu's "Genius: My White House Years" (1995) and James Baker's "Presidents Who Have Known Me" (1997). In "Conscience of a Conservative: The Sequel" (1998), Mr. Bush's Vice President, Dan Quayle, blamed his former boss directly for the failure of his own 1996 Presidential campaign, from which he was forced to withdraw after finishing second in the Indiana primary.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's military triumphs in Panama in 1989 and the Persian Gulf in 1991 also came under a cloud. Just as many historians now blame John F. Kennedy for mistakes that helped create the Cuban missile crisis while praising his efforts to end that episode, the public learned more of how Mr. Bush privately encouraged the ambitions of the Panamanian dictator Manuel Noriega and the Iraqi dictator Saddam Hussein before changing his mind and striking at each regime with military force.</p>
        <p>After Noriega's release from prison in 1998 and Saddam's ouster by military coup in 1999, the two men held a joint news conference in Asuncion, Paraguay, during which they played tapes of private conversations with Mr. Bush. According to the tapes, then-Vice President Bush told General Noriega in 1985: "We love your commitment to democracy. Keep it up!" During a 1990 telephone call to Mr. Hussein, then-President Bush praised Iraq as "an island of stability in a troubled region."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also remained shadowed by his 1992 pardon of Caspar Weinberger and others involved in the Iran-contra scandal. Historians still differ over whether Mr. Bush used the pardon to keep a Weinberger trial from disclosing information that would contradict his own claims of limited involvement in the affair. With his investigation now in its 22d year, independent counsel Lawrence Walsh has yet to sustain a conviction.</p>
        <p>A DECADE AFTER MR. Bush left the White House, his stock on the historical exchange, depressed for so long, began to rise. One reason: the left-of-center activism embodied by Presidents Clinton and Gore was faltering. In 2002, for the first time in a half-century, Republicans seized control of both houses of Congress and quickly voted to strip the funds from numerous White House-sponsored programs, such as Clinton's National Service Corps and Gore's Global Warming Initiative (G.W.I.). This legislative drive drew the support of perennial Presidential candidate Ross Perot and nearly all of the other 38 billionaires who declared their candidacies for the White House in 2004.</p>
        <p>World events at the start of the 21st century -- like the breakup of the Russian Federation into 284 mutually hostile republics, the purchase of Brazil by the Taiwanese, the Quebec-Ontario border war and acquisition of nuclear weapons by such entities as the Government of Barbados and the talk show host Rush Limbaugh -- made the early 1990's in the United States seem by contrast a heroic period. Scholars now grant Mr. Bush far more credit for his world leadership in that period than did the voters of 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's once-maligned leadership style also attracted unexpected praise. A book called "Another Hidden Hand: Bush as Leader" (2006), made the case that the 41st President should be viewed not as another Taft but another Eisenhower. It used newly released papers to demonstrate that, like Eisenhower, Mr. Bush was far more commanding and articulate in private than his news conferences or the memoirs of his spiteful aides suggested.</p>
        <p>The book also argued that Mr. Bush had deliberately modeled his Presidency on Eisenhower's -- eschewing traditionally divisive domestic issues in order to unify Americans after a period of national controversy -- but kept his decision to emulate the moderate President secret out of fear that it would infuriate conservative Republicans. The book further revealed how guilt-ridden Mr. Bush was when he compared himself during the 1992 campaign to Harry Truman, a one-time political enemy of Eisenhower's. It quoted from Mr. Bush's private diary: "Beloved President Ike, so sorry to be doing this. Have to understand. Just in campaign mode now. Don't mean it. What a way to make a living!"</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush's reputation gathered steam, some scholars even recast what had been thought to be the weakest part of his record, his handling of the economy. "Message -- I Care: Bush's Economic Management" (2007) argued that Mr. Bush's much-vilified 1990 budget compromise with Congress that broke his campaign pledge -- "Read My Lips: No New Taxes" -- actually helped make the so-called Bush recession shorter and shallower than economists at the time understood.</p>
        <p>Now 84, Mr. Bush has proven to be one of America's longest-living ex-Presidents. Like William Howard Taft, who became Chief Justice, and Jimmy Carter, who served as a human rights activist, Mr. Bush enhanced his reputation by engaging in activities that seemed to suit his temperament more than the Presidency had. In Houston, he established the Bush Center for Internationalism, which became his platform for lectures and writings opposing growing isolationist impulses in both parties. President Gore appointed him to undertake special diplomatic missions to post-Communist Cuba, the semi-autonomous republic of Northern Moscow and to Monaco, where peace talks with France inspired by Mr. Bush were entering their 16th year.</p>
        <p>In retirement, Mr. Bush has also been a fierce opponent of the Hispanic-American secessionist movement. In Kearny, N.J., in 2003, he gave a famous address against "suicidal nationalism." (Foes lampooned it as the "Chicken con Kearny speech.") When his Hispanic-American grandson, George P. Bush, was elected to the United States Senate from Florida in 2006 on an anti-secessionist ticket, Mr. Bush was guest of honor at the South Miami victory rally. The Senator-elect turned to his grandfather, thanked him for campaigning on his behalf in Hobe Sound and Palm Beach and then repeated a battle cry he had uttered as a young man at the 1992 Republican Convention: "</p>
        <p>Viva</p>
        <p>Bush!" The 41st President's eyes filled with tears. Additional promary sources on the Bush Presidency -- "Derwinski: Reminiscences of a Secretary of Veterans Affairs" by Edward J. Derwinski (1994), "The Skinner Year" by Samuel K. Skinner (1995), "Stop Lying About My Record: The Autobiography of Willie Horton" (1996) and "Saddam: My Own Story" by Saddam Hussein with William Novak (1999).  Michael R. Beschloss is a historian and author of "The Crisis Years: Kennedy and Khrushchev, 1960-1963." His latest book, written with Strobe Talbott, is "At the Highest Levels: The Inside Story of the End of the Cold War," to be published next month by Little, Brown.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael R. Beschloss is a historian and author of "The Crisis Years: Kennedy and Khrushchev, 1960-1963." His latest book, written with Strobe Talbott, is "At the Highest Levels: The Inside Story of the End of the Cold War," to be published next month by Little, Brown.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
