<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rise in Ultraviolet Rays Seen in North America</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="650350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ULTRAVIOLET LIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TORONTO (ONTARIO)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENT CANADA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERR, J B (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCELROY, C T (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario/Toronto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC143AF935A25752C1A965958260" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rise in Ultraviolet Rays Seen in North America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the first time, researchers have measured long-term increases in harmful ultraviolet rays in North America caused by a weakening of the earth's protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Although the finding comes as no surprise to most experts, it may nevertheless plug a troublesome hole in the conventional analysis of the ozone problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the first time, researchers have measured long-term increases in harmful ultraviolet rays in North America caused by a weakening of the earth's protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>Although the finding comes as no surprise to most experts, it may nevertheless plug a troublesome hole in the conventional analysis of the ozone problem.</p>
        <p>Most scientists who have worked on the problem regard its main scientific aspects as settled. They know that ozone in the stratosphere normally prevents ultraviolet rays from reaching the earth's surface, where they can cause cancer and eye cataracts and disrupt natural ecosystems. Researchers have documented decreases in stratospheric ozone around the globe, most significantly over Antarctica, where accompanying increases in ultraviolet radiation have also been measured. And they have demonstrated to the satisfaction of most experts that the decreases in ozone are caused primarily by chemical reactions that occur when ozone-destroying chemicals like chlorofluorocarbons, produced by industry, are carried up to the stratosphere by atmospheric circulation.</p>
        <p>But although scientists have assumed that ozone depletion is resulting in long-term increases in ultraviolet radiation around the world, they had not shown until now that this was the case outside Antarctica and its environs.</p>
        <p>In the new study, Dr. J. B. Kerr and Dr. C. T. McElroy of Environment Canada, the Canadian environmental agency, measured ultraviolet radiation reaching the ground in Toronto at least once every hour from sunrise to sunset of every day during five summers and four winters from 1989 to 1993. Ozone levels over Toronto decreased about 4 percent a year in winter and about 2 percent a year in summer. Those two seasons were selected because ozone depletion is greatest in winter and ultraviolet radiation is most intense in summer.</p>
        <p>The measurements were made in all kinds of atmospheric conditions so they represented, Dr. Kerr said, "what nature delivers to the earth's surface through pollution, rain, shine and all types of weather -- whatever the atmosphere throws at it." Some critics of the ozone theory have maintained that ultraviolet increases would never be detected through clouds and pollution. "Very Important Measurement"</p>
        <p>Using instruments that recorded ultraviolet radiation across a broad spectrum of wavelengths, Dr. Kerr and Dr. McElroy examined wavelengths between 290 and 325 nanometers, the range in which ultraviolet rays are blocked by ozone and in which they are most harmful to organisms. At a midrange sample wavelength of 300 nanometers, the researchers reported in the current issue of the journal Science, they found that the harmful radiation reaching Toronto increased by 6.7 percent a year in summer and 35 percent a year in winter.</p>
        <p>"It's a very important measurement; it does clearly show that ultraviolet increases when ozone decreases," said Dr. David Hofmann, a senior scientist and ozone expert at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's climate monitoring and diagnostics laboratory in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>But he, Dr. Kerr and Dr. McElroy cautioned against drawing conclusions about trends in ozone depletion, and therefore in ultraviolet radiation, beyond the four-and-a-half-year term of the study. Ozone levels in the study period could have been influenced not only by chlorofluorocarbons but also by natural factors, they said, especially the lingering effects of the volcanic eruption of Mount Pinatubo in the Philippines in 1991.</p>
        <p>Many scientists believe that aerosols from volcanic eruptions deplete ozone. If so, the Mount Pinatubo eruption could have temporarily exaggerated the ozone depletion trend already under way as a result of chlorofluorocarbons. It is unlikely, Dr. Hofmann said, that the rate of ozone depletion measured in winter by Dr. Kerr and Dr. McElroy will continue much longer.</p>
        <p>Government scientists expect the atmospheric buildup of chlorofluorocarbons to continue until almost the end of this decade, though more slowly than in the recent past. The slowdown is attributed to industry's unexpectedly rapid cut in production of the chemicals in the face of international agreements to phase them out.</p>
        <p>If this continues, the Government scientists believe, the worst of the ozone destruction caused by human activity should come around the turn of the century. Then, they say, the ozone layer should begin a recovery to natural levels.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
