<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="592638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DA163CF936A15751C0A965958260" item-length="987" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-13  HINDUS BARRED FROM PROTEST  More than 45,000 Hindus across India have been arrested as they tried to travel toward New Delhi in response to a call from the main Hindu political party to join a demonstration against the Government.  A1  CANADIAN LEADER TO RESIGN  Brian Mulroney, Canada's 18th Prime Minister who solidified free trade with the United States but failed in efforts to reinforce unity between English and French-speaking Canadians, announced that he was retiring after eight-and-a-half years in office.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-13  HINDUS BARRED FROM PROTEST  More than 45,000 Hindus across India have been arrested as they tried to travel toward New Delhi in response to a call from the main Hindu political party to join a demonstration against the Government.  A1  CANADIAN LEADER TO RESIGN  Brian Mulroney, Canada's 18th Prime Minister who solidified free trade with the United States but failed in efforts to reinforce unity between English and French-speaking Canadians, announced that he was retiring after eight-and-a-half years in office.  A1</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE IN SOMALIA CAPITAL  After two months of uneasy calm, the Somali capital exploded in violence as thousands of partisans of a major warlord stormed the streets in Mogadishu, looting, burning tires, hurling rocks and menacing foreigners.  A1  SEOUL'S FIRST CIVILIAN CHIEF  Kim Young Sam took the oath as South Korea's first nonmilitary President in more than three decades. He delivered a fiery inaugural address, accusing the generals who had preceded him of leading the country into a "dark political night" of corruption and economic malaise.  A1  Britain and China are holding talks on the future of Hong Kong.  A5  C.I.A. warned that North Korea may be hiding nuclear production.  A7  RUSSIA'S NEW RETAILERS  The famous State Department Store on Moscow's Red Square, best known by its Russian acronym, GUM, became private more than two years ago. But now any Russian can get a piece of GUM, a covered mall that houses many shops, including branches of some well-known Western ones.  A3  EUROPE WELCOMES U.S. AIRDROP  Even before President Clinton's announcement to airdrop relief supplies in Bosnia and Herzegovina, Western European leaders welcomed it as a sign that the United States was joining in efforts to stop the Balkan fighting.  A8  BRITON BACKS CLINTON PLAN  President Clinton received the backing of Prime Minister John Major of Britain for his proposed airdrop into Bosnia. But the two leaders clashed on another key issue: American complaints that the Europeans were unfairly subsidizing their civilian aircraft industry.  A8  SERBS SHOW DEFIANCE IN BOSNIA  As the Clinton Administration considered the details of its airdrop, Serbian nationalist forces halted another U.N. convoy trying to deliver relief supplies to besieged Muslim towns in eastern Bosnia.  A8  National A14-17, B7, D23  BRIGHTER PROSPECTS FOR RU486  In what may be the first step toward bringing the French abortion pill to the American market, the president of the company that makes it said should be introduced to the United States.  A1  THE RACE TO REFINANCE  All across America, corporate managers, municipal officials and homeowners are trading in their old debt for new long-term loans whose rates have fallen to levels that most have never seen before.  A1  NEW NUCLEAR STRATEGY  An American military command is building computer models that would enable the President to aim nuclear-armed missiles at third-world countries that threaten the nation's interests.  B7  Aspin will reduce his workload and may need a pacemaker.  B7  ADMINISTRATION FILLS OUT SLOWLY  Some Cabinet officers are frustrated by the White House's time-consuming efforts to add diversity and otherwise shape top Administration appointments.  A16  The Clinton economic plan is drawing praise from the states.  A16  Congressional Democrats predicted some haste on the budget.  A16  Pediatric experts backed a universalvaccination program.  B7  RULING ON DRUG FORFEITURES  The Supreme Court rebuffed the Government's assertion of sweeping power to confiscate property tainted in any way by an illegal drug transaction.  A17  The Justices considered a rare kind of church-state issue.  A17  FINDINGS ON A SUPERNOVA  Astronomers have found evidence that a star as bright as the full moon exploded into view 340,000 years ago and that its dazzling radiation could have damaged earth's ozone layer and sunburned man's Stone Age ancestors.  D23  LEGACY OF THE WESTERN DROUGHT  The drought that punished the West for six years is over but has left a fundamentally changed policy landscape across the region.  A14  BEATING TRIAL GOES FORWARD  Last-minute legal hurdles were cleared in the Federal trial of four police officers accused of violating Rodney G. King's civil rights.  A15  For rescued skiers, a hero's welcome and also criticism.  A14  A gain was reported in predicting quake-related ocean waves.  D23  A European satellite can now monitor American weather.  D23  Exercise extends the lives of middle-aged men, a study suggested.  B7  Metro Digest B1  A SIGN OF THE RECESSION  The fund used to pay unemployment benefits in New York State will run out of money this week, and a Cuomo administration official has proposed a significant increase in business taxes to keep the system solvent. New York is the fifth state whose unemployment insurance fund has gone into the red since the start of the national downturn in 1990.  A1  SHOOTING AT BRONX COURTHOUSE  A woman accompanying her husband to the Bronx County Building yesterday was shot and killed by a man in a camouflage jacket and a bulletproof vest. Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly said the department was investigating whether the killing was linked to the killings of six people in a Bronx apartment on Feb. 14.  A1  Business Digest D1  Home Section C1-13  Arts/Entertainment C15-24  Obituaries B8  Editorials/Op-Ed A18-19  Editorials  Indecent disclosure.  Lifeline for Bosnia.  Home alone at Justice?  Mr. Mulroney steps down.  Letters  William Safire: The Bill &amp; Boris show.  Leslie H. Gelb: Balkan strategy, part I.  Elie Wiesel: Shadows in the camps.  Richard Manning: Chainsaw logic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
