<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON DECLARES NEW U.S. POLICIES FOR ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="603960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENTSEN, LLOYD (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'LEARY, HAZEL R (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDB1F38F931A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1438" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON DECLARES NEW U.S. POLICIES FOR ENVIRONMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Repudiating two major Bush Administration environmental policies, President Clinton said today that the United States would sign an international treaty protecting rare and endangered species and follow a specific timetable to reduce the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>In his first major speech on environmental policy, President Clinton declared: "We cannot walk away from challenges like those presented by the biodiversity treaty. We must step up to them."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Repudiating two major Bush Administration environmental policies, President Clinton said today that the United States would sign an international treaty protecting rare and endangered species and follow a specific timetable to reduce the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>In his first major speech on environmental policy, President Clinton declared: "We cannot walk away from challenges like those presented by the biodiversity treaty. We must step up to them."</p>
        <p>Speaking on the eve of Earth Day observances to environmental groups who had gathered at the Botanical Gardens in the shadow of the Capitol, Mr. Clinton said, "We also must take the lead in addressing the challenge of global warming that could make our planet and its climate less hospitable and more hostile to human life." Bush Rejection Based on Cost</p>
        <p>President Bush had rejected both initiatives, saying they might be too expensive and would unfairly penalize some American companies.</p>
        <p>President Clinton committed the United States "to reducing our emissions of greenhouse gases to their 1990 levels by the year 2000." Greenhouse gases, so called because they trap heat in the atmosphere like the glass panes in a greenhouse, include carbon dioxide produced by burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that his Administration would put forward a plan for limiting greenhouse gases by August. Such limits are not expected to impose immediate, significant new costs on private industry or on the Government, although opponents of the restrictions on greenhouse gases say the restrictions will raise costs in the long term and increase Government regulation of business. Many companies and Government agencies have already started taking steps to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases.  A Victory for Gore</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Clinton had pledged the action during the campaign, his announcement on global warming was an important victory for Vice President Al Gore over Treasury Secretary Lloyd Bentsen and Energy Secretary Hazel R. O'Leary, who, among others, had argued that such restrictions would harm American industry.</p>
        <p>The dispute had continued into late Tuesday, with Administration officials still unsure about what to put in the speech on reducing emissions.</p>
        <p>The treaty to protect the diversity of the world's living things, known as the biodiversity treaty, will require the approval of two-thirds of the Senate.  White House officials said they did not expect major legislative opposition.</p>
        <p>The treaty also stipulates that biotechnology companies must share profits and technologies with any countries whose biological resources they use in developing products.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has said he shares some concerns raised by Mr. Bush that this provision would weaken patent protections for biotechnology companies, discouraging research and innovation.</p>
        <p>To get around those misgivings, the White House met with biotechnology and pharmaceutical companies, as well as environmental groups, to draft an "interpretative statement" that Mr. Clinton will attach to the United States signature on the treaty.</p>
        <p>Vice President Gore, who has been overruled on other environmental matters like his pledge to keep a toxic waste incinerator closed in Ohio, sounded elated today over Mr. Clinton's announcement. "There was no fight on global warming with me," he told reporters. "I made a commitment and we're going to keep it."</p>
        <p>In campaigning last year as Mr. Clinton's Vice Presidential running mate, Mr. Gore frequently described Mr. Bush's refusal to support the environmental initiatives as an embarrassment to the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush disregarded the advice of his own chief environmental official in opposing the treaty, angering environmentalists attending the Earth Summit meeting in Rio de Janeiro last June.</p>
        <p>The speech today raised Mr. Clinton's stock with environmentalists, many of whom had attacked his decision last month to back off from a shift in Federal land policy that would have led to increased mining and grazing fees. 'It's a Timely Move'</p>
        <p>"President Clinton has brought America back into step with the rest of the world on environmental protection," said Fred Krupp, executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
        <p>William K. Reilly, the former administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency who had pressed Mr. Bush to sign the biodiversity treaty, said of Mr. Clinton's action: "It's a timely move, a positive new direction for the Administration. It will be very welcomed, particularly in the developing world."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also announced that he would sign five executive orders directing the Federal Government to take steps to reduce pollution in Federal agencies.</p>
        <p>They would instruct the agencies to change their purchasing policies to use fewer substances that are harmful to the ozone layer; commit the Federal Government to buy thousands more American-made vehicles that use fuels like natural gas, ethanol, methanol and electric power; require agencies to do more to buy and use recycled products; require agencies to purchase energy-efficient computers, and require Federal offices that use toxic chemicals to publicly report their wastes and releases.</p>
        <p>The President also announced an energy and environmental audit of the White House, to find ways to reduce waste in the lighting, heating and cooling systems. A Different Course</p>
        <p>"For too long, we have been told that we have to choose between the economy and the environment," Mr. Clinton said, "between our jobs, between our obligations to our own people and our responsibilities to the future, and to the rest of the world, between public action and private economy. I'm here today in the hope that we can together take a different course of action, to offer a new set of challenges to our people."</p>
        <p>White House officials said the interpretative statement to accompany the biodiversity treaty would assure American companies that they would not have to share technology with developing countries that provide resources for products manufactured by those companies.</p>
        <p>"We think we have done the work necessary to protect the intellectual property of American industries and to protect the environment," Mr. Clinton told reporters. "We believe that all the difficulties have been worked out and that this effort will be supported by both the businesses involved and the American environmental community."</p>
        <p>G. Kirk Raab, president of Genentech Inc., which was part of the coalition that developed the interpretative statement, said, "This is a major step forward for both businesses and environmentalists."</p>
        <p>But some environmental organizations, in a letter to Mr. Clinton, accused him of compromising the protection of species to insure profits for biotechnology companies. 'Dangerously Shortsighted'</p>
        <p>"The Clinton-industry proposal, which undercuts international attempts to regulate the creation and release of genetically engineered organisms, is dangerously shortsighted and scientifically naive," said Andrew Kimbrell, policy director of the Greenhouse Crisis Foundation, one of the groups that signed the letter.</p>
        <p>Despite their general praise for Mr. Clinton, several environmental groups said their one concern was that he did not say whether he would move to cap greenhouse gas emissions after the year 2000. White House officials said no decisions had been made on that course of action.</p>
        <p>"Unless the President commits America to capping emissions and leads the world in that direction," said Michael Oppenheimer, senior scientist of the Environmental Defense Fund, "it will be like going on a diet and then gaining all the weight back."</p>
        <p>But John Shlaes, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition, a business group, warned that further targets and timetables for emissions reductions, if carried out in an arbitrary fashion, "could jeopardize the economic health of the nation." 'Greatly Encouraged'</p>
        <p>More typical from environmental groups were the comments from Jim Maddy, executive director of the League of Conservation Voters. "We were holding our breath on global warming," he said, "and we got everything we had hoped for. We were also pleased by what Mr. Clinton said on Federal facility compliance. We felt we were going to struggle with that issue for a long, long time."</p>
        <p>Peter A. A. Berle, president of the National Audubon Society said, "With President Clinton's commitments today, integrating environmental and economic goals, setting an example from the White House and setting out an agenda of Federal actions to conserve energy, to curb or clean up pollution, we are greatly encouraged."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
