<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Not So Fast on the Ozone Layer Celebration</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMAN, JEFFREY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D7113CF937A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Not So Fast on the Ozone Layer Celebration</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re "Good News, for Once, on Ozone" (editorial, Aug. 30): While it is good news that concentrations of ozone-destroying chemicals have been measured at a somewhat lower concentration than previously projected, this should not be the basis for unwarranted euphoria.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re "Good News, for Once, on Ozone" (editorial, Aug. 30): While it is good news that concentrations of ozone-destroying chemicals have been measured at a somewhat lower concentration than previously projected, this should not be the basis for unwarranted euphoria.</p>
        <p>Even before the recent readings there was a presumption that the ozone layer problem would begin to recede in a few years after the production and use of ozone-destroying chemicals had been phased out by the Montreal Protocol and its international successors, and the Clean Air Act in the United States.</p>
        <p>Yet this assumption has been questioned by Dr. Alfred Wong at the University of California, Los Angeles, who notes that such chemicals linger in the atmosphere 40 years or longer. He notes also that the chlorine ions in these chemicals from the molecules broken up by ultraviolet rays in the upper atmosphere will not necessarily disappear as quickly as assumed. Besides that, it is pure speculation how quickly the ozone layer will recuperate without massive remediation efforts after the emissions have largely ceased.</p>
        <p>As Friends of the Earth notes in "The Science of Ozone Depletion": "it is also possible that the rate of ozone depletion will not simply increase in line with chlorine levels."</p>
        <p>And in addition: "No one is able reliably to forecast the extent of ozone depletion, particularly in the Northern Hemisphere."</p>
        <p>The assumption that the ozone layer issue has been largely solved underlies policy inaction. My research was unable to find any proposed or pending legislation in Congress that goes beyond the Clean Air Act. Carol Browner, director of the Environmental Protection Agency, said in response to a question from me on National Public Radio last May 7 that no such new legislation was being drafted at her agency either.</p>
        <p>Given the record of scientific "certainty" on such issues as nuclear energy, and complacency about the ozone problem itself after ozone-depleting aerosols were banned in the 1970's, we should be skeptical about rosy assumptions by leading experts, as distinct from actual readings.</p>
        <p>The dangers in ozone layer destruction are of apocalyptic proportions. Oceanic plankton -- the planet's "lungs," source of more than 70 percent of the world's oxygen -- are killed by ultraviolet light, and die-offs of 15 percent or more have been observed in some areas.</p>
        <p>In addition, rain forests and agriculture could suffer catastrophe, while two-thirds of all Australians are predicted to get skin cancer during their natural lifetimes because of ozone layer depletion.</p>
        <p>These trends, expected to worsen for at least five years, might not improve after that. The planet could be stuck with no technical solution adequate to address a worsening global catastrophe.</p>
        <p>Ozone remediation is thus a necessity -- something a government willing to spend trillions of dollars on a "triad" defense system should recognize as necessary. Ozone remediation refers to efforts to filter or neutralize ozone-destroying chemicals in the atmosphere or possibly to add ozone to certain areas or otherwise "repair" the damaged ozone layer.</p>
        <p>These issues are complex. Rather than swallowing "don't worry, be happy" presumptions, moderates and progressives, as well as activist groups, should get cracking on this crucial issue. JEFFREY HOLMAN  Berkeley, Calif., Sept. 2, 1993</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
