<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON'S ECONOMIC PLAN: The Energy Plan; Fuels Tax: Spreading The Burden</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="591097"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D6153CF93BA25751C0A965958260" item-length="622" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON'S ECONOMIC PLAN: The Energy Plan; Fuels Tax: Spreading The Burden</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton wants to add some new letters to the Government's tax-code alphabet soup: B.T.U.</p>
        <p>His proposed broad-based energy tax would apply to the energy content of nearly all fuels, as measured by the British thermal unit, or B.T.U. -- the quantity of heat needed to raise the temperature of a pound of water by 1 degree Fahrenheit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton wants to add some new letters to the Government's tax-code alphabet soup: B.T.U.</p>
        <p>His proposed broad-based energy tax would apply to the energy content of nearly all fuels, as measured by the British thermal unit, or B.T.U. -- the quantity of heat needed to raise the temperature of a pound of water by 1 degree Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>When the tax is fully in force, the Treasury estimated, it would increase the $2,242 energy bill for a family of four earning $25,000 by $105. Increase for Gasoline</p>
        <p>The new tax would raise the price of gasoline by 2.5 cents a gallon next year; in 1996 the tax would be 7.5 cents a gallon higher than it is now. With the average household using about 1,000 gallons of gasoline a year, that means an increase cost of about $25 the first year and $75 the third year .</p>
        <p>Treasury officials said the energy tax would result in a 75-cent increase in the average home's monthly electricity bill, now $67, in the first year, and in a $2.25 increase in the third year.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they chose the new energy tax because it would encourage conservation, reduce pollution and not hurt any one region much more than others. Mr. Clinton selected it after criticizing a gasoline tax during the Presidential campaign on the ground that it would hit the middle class disproportionately. But many experts say that a broader energy tax would still hit the middle class harder than it hits the wealthy. Sparing Renewable Energy</p>
        <p>The tax would not be imposed directly on consumers but on producers, refiners and transporters. It would then be passed on to consumers in the form of higher prices.</p>
        <p>Administration officials propose to phase in the tax over three years, with the first third taking effect on July 1, 1994. The new tax would increase energy costs for the typical household by about 4.5 percent once it is fully phased in after July 1, 1996.</p>
        <p>The new tax would increase the cost of gasoline, natural gas, home heating oil and electricity coming from coal, hydropower and nuclear power. But the tax would not apply to renewable sources of energy, including wind, solar power and geothermal power.</p>
        <p>A specific amount of fuel would generally be taxed according to the B.T.U.'s it produces: for example, a tax of 25.7 cents for each million B.T.U.'s of coal and natural gas, 59.9 cents for each million B.T.U.'s of oil. The price of a million B.T.U's of natural gas varies by season, but is about $2. The same unit of heavy oil, the kind used in competition with gas and coal, is around $2.50. That unit of coal is around $1.50. A Higher Tax on Oil</p>
        <p>Administration officials said they proposed to tax oil more because it pollutes more than natural gas and imposing a similar levy on both fuels would have raised the price of cleaner-burning natural gas far more proportionally than it would have raised the price of oil. The Administration proposed the same B.T.U. tax for coal and natural gas even though coal pollutes more; coal is far cheaper, so proportionally the tax would be higher.</p>
        <p>The Administration also proposed to extend a 2.5-cent-a-gallon Federal gasoline tax that was scheduled to expire in 1995.</p>
        <p>Industry officials today welcomed the news that the energy tax would not be placed on raw materials that are components of other products, like oil derivatives used to make plastics. But they said they were disappointed that the Administration did not plan to refund the energy taxes paid on exported goods, adding that the tax would make such goods less competitive abroad.</p>
        <p>The Administration plans to collect $1.5 billion from this tax in the fiscal year 1994, $8.9 billion in 1995, $16.4 billion in 1996 and $22.3 billion in 1997.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
