<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Risk-Shy Utilities Avoid Trading Emission Credits</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="585593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1990</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC UTILITIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DE153AF936A15752C0A965958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Risk-Shy Utilities Avoid Trading Emission Credits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Congress amended the Clean Air Act in 1990, backers said the law would cut $1 billion a year from the cost of reducing pollution, introducing free-market efficiencies to a command-and-control system by letting utilities trade "emissions allowances" among themselves.</p>
        <p>So far, though, the market is a nonstarter. With the first deadline looming, only a few trades have been announced, and the terms of those have not been made public. As a result, utilities owning more than 15,000 megawatts of coal-fired power stations, nearly 20 percent of the affected total, have decided to build "scrubbers" without a clear idea of how much it would cost to meet their obligations by buying the allowances instead. Benefits Unclear to Industry</p>
        <p>Utilities are also unsure how much they could have earned by building extra scrubbers and "overcomplying" with the law, for which they would receive credits that they could sell to other companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Congress amended the Clean Air Act in 1990, backers said the law would cut $1 billion a year from the cost of reducing pollution, introducing free-market efficiencies to a command-and-control system by letting utilities trade "emissions allowances" among themselves.</p>
        <p>So far, though, the market is a nonstarter. With the first deadline looming, only a few trades have been announced, and the terms of those have not been made public. As a result, utilities owning more than 15,000 megawatts of coal-fired power stations, nearly 20 percent of the affected total, have decided to build "scrubbers" without a clear idea of how much it would cost to meet their obligations by buying the allowances instead. Benefits Unclear to Industry</p>
        <p>Utilities are also unsure how much they could have earned by building extra scrubbers and "overcomplying" with the law, for which they would receive credits that they could sell to other companies.</p>
        <p>A market could still emerge in time to be useful to help utilities meet the second, stricter round of environmental requirements in 2000, but it would have to happen soon, according to specialists in the field. That is because of the long lead time required to build and test scrubbers. Some experts say the impediments that have blocked the market so far are still present, including the industry's aversion to risk that makes the whole system seem the equivalent of teaching elephants to dance.</p>
        <p>"Utilities have no motive; they're looking at compliance, not profit," said Don Justin Jones, the managing director of a consulting firm that specializes in utilities and environmental issues. Under the rules enforced by state public service commissions, he said, if a trade saves money, electric rates are cut, but if a trade later turns out to have raised costs, shareholders suffer.</p>
        <p>The message to engineers and planners who would have to arrange the trading, Mr. Jones said, is that "if you screw up you get shipped off to count transformers."</p>
        <p>At the Edison Electric Institute, a trade association of investor-owned utilities in Washington, James E. Evans, the director of environmental activities, said the market's development had been inhibited by its hybrid nature. "It certainly is difficult when you try to overlay a market-based approach on a regulated industry like the utility industry," he said. Risk Aversion</p>
        <p>For many of the companies, Mr. Evans said, their antipathy toward risk means generating a few extra emission allowances, but holding onto them in case of future need rather than facing the possibility of running short and being at the mercy of sellers, or of being fined by the Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of the trades have been announced, involving a few thousand tons of sulfur dioxide, the chemical that causes acid rain. Analysts say that there have been some private deals, but that these, too, were small. And there has been no public announcement of the prices involved, other than a general statement of between $250 and $400 a ton.</p>
        <p>The deals will eventually come into the public record through applications to state regulatory agencies for rate increases. But the utilities appear nervous about disclosing the financial arrangements, especially when the deals could be considered trend-setters.</p>
        <p>In addition, the buyer may suffer from image problems. When the Tennessee Valley Authority said that it would buy 10,000 tons of emission allowances from Wisconsin Power and Light, environmentalists in Tennessee complained that the decision would make their region dirtier. Some Benefits Seen</p>
        <p>The trading system has already provided some benefits, however, by allowing utilities to "trade" within their own systems, experts said. Scrubbing big plants is cheaper, ton for ton, than small ones, so the trading system has allowed companies with several dirty plants to overcomply at one, in effect averaging the emissions among the company's plants.</p>
        <p>Some experts said that a market for inter-company trading may yet be jump-started in April, after the E.P.A. auctions a stock of allowances. Proponents of the trading believe that auction should establish a clear price.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Board of Trade is still planning to make a market in "allowance futures," permitting utilities or others to lock in prices of allowances or gamble on future price moves. Richard L. Sandor, a director of the Board of Trade and the official in charge of the allowance market, said it was too early to conclude that a market would not develop.</p>
        <p>"You've got years to go, and interest from all kinds of industrial corporations," he said. In the second phase, in 2000, he noted, companies outside the electric business could "opt in," or clean up their own emissions and generate allowances for sale. Stricter Rules for the 2d Phase</p>
        <p>The requirements for 2000 will be substantially harder to achieve. While the 1995 phase covers 110 of the largest, dirtiest plants in 21 Eastern and Midwestern states, the 2000 phase covers about 800 utility plants nationwide. The 1995 requirement restricts boiler emissions to no more than 2.5 pounds of sulfur dioxide for each million British thermal units they produce, an amount of heat sufficient to make about 10 kilowatt-hours of electricity. In 2000 the standard drops to 1.2 pounds per million B.T.U.'s.</p>
        <p>Even with the current reticence in the industry, some believe the emissions allowance market is about to heat up. John B. Henry 2d, whose company, Clean Air Capital Markets arranged one of the few publicly announced allowance deals, said that 1993 would see "a rash of deals."</p>
        <p>Building and testing major scrubbers takes four years, Mr. Henry said, so that meeting a deadline of 2000 would require starting in 1996. Most companies would want to start their construction two years earlier to persuade regulators that the scrubbers were needed and their costs should be billed to customers. That would move the starting date up to the beginning of next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
