<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Animals That Are Peerless Athletes</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="612524"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXERCISE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LUNGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRONGHORN SHEEP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESPIRATORY SYSTEM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THOROUGHBRED RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHREWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUMMINGBIRDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANGIER, NATALIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Exercise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Respiratory System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D91F3AF932A35755C0A965958260" item-length="1923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Animals That Are Peerless Athletes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATALIE ANGIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANGIER, NATALIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO the recreational joggers of the world, champion runners like Carl Lewis and Olga Markova are the anointed children of Zeus, cardiovascular demigods who seem to ignite the air molecules around them as they race.</p>
        <p>Yet even the most elite human athlete is thoroughly pathetic compared with nature's other aerobic masters. Take the pronghorn antelope of Wyoming, for example, a goat-sized ungulate that may rank as the greatest athlete alive. Its maximum speed of 60 miles per hour is second only to the cheetah's top pace of 70 m.p.h. But while the cheetah can sprint for just a few seconds before practically collapsing, the pronghorn can maintain its freeway stride for an hour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO the recreational joggers of the world, champion runners like Carl Lewis and Olga Markova are the anointed children of Zeus, cardiovascular demigods who seem to ignite the air molecules around them as they race.</p>
        <p>Yet even the most elite human athlete is thoroughly pathetic compared with nature's other aerobic masters. Take the pronghorn antelope of Wyoming, for example, a goat-sized ungulate that may rank as the greatest athlete alive. Its maximum speed of 60 miles per hour is second only to the cheetah's top pace of 70 m.p.h. But while the cheetah can sprint for just a few seconds before practically collapsing, the pronghorn can maintain its freeway stride for an hour.</p>
        <p>When migrating between California and South America, a hummingbird will fly for 24 hours at a stretch, all the while beating its wings thousands of times each minute. In so doing, the tiny creature burns up such huge volumes of oxygen so efficiently that it would take a human athlete working for a week at peak capacity without a moment's break to match the hummingbird's aerobic performance.</p>
        <p>The world's smallest mammal, the Etruscan shrew, is almost as light as a dime, and yet it can run more than half as fast as the fastest human. Were it scaled up to human dimensions, it would dash through a mile in about 40 seconds.</p>
        <p>Such are the conclusions that physiologists reach when they compare the aerobic capabilities of extremely athletic mammals with those of people. Naturalists have long been impressed with the swoops, soars, dives and dashes displayed by the creatures they study, but only lately have researchers begun to understand the physiological basis of the animals' feats.</p>
        <p>They have learned how the hearts, lungs and circulatory systems of aerobic stars like the pronghorn and the blue fox differ from those of such rutabagas of the animal kingdom as the 100-pound capybara, a four-foot-long South American rodent that Dr. James H. Jones, a physiologist at the University of California at Davis, describes as a "big ball of flab."</p>
        <p>Some of the recent results in the field of comparative physiology were presented recently at a meeting of the American Lung Association in San Francisco. Speaking to an audience of clinicians concerned largely with human respiratory ailments, the physiologists emphasized how much could be learned about human anatomy and performance by considering the cardiovascular prowess of other species.</p>
        <p>Many of the latest studies focus on oxygen transport, the journey of a breath of air as it passes down the trachea and into the lungs, through the capillary walls of the lungs and into the blood, and from the blood into the muscles, where the oxygen is transformed into energy. Animal performance depends on many factors beyond oxygen use, including muscle mass, skeletal strength and limb length, but it is the relative efficiency of oxygen metabolism that accounts for the streak of a stallion or the sluggishness of a porcupine.</p>
        <p>"If you're trying to understand how the oxygen transport system really works, and you restrict your studies to humans, you'll see maybe a difference of only 5 or 6 percent between a sedentary person and an athlete," said Dr. Jones, a leading figure in the field. "But when you start comparing systems between animals, you come up against differences of fivefold or tenfold, and those are much easier to measure and to understand."</p>
        <p>Comparative studies have also revealed where the limits to human athletic achievement may lie. Scientists have found, for example, that the lungs may be the biggest bottleneck to improved performance in sports. The heart can grow larger with training and thus can pump more blood around the body. The greater the volume of blood, the more oxygen it can pick up from the lungs and take to the muscles where it is needed. In addition, a rigorous training program will induce the abundant sprouting of new capillaries to more efficiently deliver oxygen-rich blood to the muscles. But the lungs themselves do not grow or improve with exercise, and eventually their fixed structure may be what holds back the swiftest possible transit of oxygen from the airways and into the bloodstream.</p>
        <p>"The lungs of an elite athlete and the lungs of a couch potato are the same," said Dr. Peter D. Wagner, a physiologist at the University of California at San Diego. "The cardiac output of the athlete is higher, but the lungs aren't matched to the higher flow rate.</p>
        <p>"In this sense, and in several others, champion athletes are like race horses. As it flies fly around the track, its snout thrust forward, its eyes practically popping from its skull, the race horse, too, is limited by the unchangeable size of its lungs."</p>
        <p>Yet as relentlessly as elite human athletes may push the envelope of their pulmonary power, they do not show signs like those seen in thoroughbred horses that they have gone over the edge. It turns out that nearly all thoroughbreds bleed into their lungs after a race, a clear sign, physiologists said, of the dangers of breeding animals for one purpose alone. The bleeding results from the great volumes of blood coursing through the lungs, putting unbearable pressure on the lung capillaries and causing them to burst. Some horses are so fragile, they even begin to bleed through the nose during an easy trot.</p>
        <p>"Race horses have been selected so strongly for a single characteristic, speed, that the rest of the animal hasn't had the opportunity to evolve ways to handle it," said Dr. Stan L. Lindstedt, a physiologist at Northern Arizona University in Flagstaff who has studied pronghorn performance. "Pronghorns are much more stable. They'll flat out beat horses, but there's no indication of bleeding into the lungs. They have had millennia to work out their problems."</p>
        <p>But horses, like many other mammals with great aerobic capacity, do have a skill that humans lack. When horses begin running, their spleens contract and spew out large volumes of red blood cells, the cells that carry oxygen. "It's a huge effect," said Dr. Wagner. "Within 75 seconds, the number of circulating red blood cells doubles." The only way humans can increase their red blood cell concentration is to inject more cells, a trick called blood doping, in which a person injects himself with his own or another's blood right before a race. The practice can indeed improve performance, but it is illegal in most sporting events.</p>
        <p>In conducting their comparative experiments, the researchers have inveigled a wide spectrum of animals into galloping themselves windless on treadmills and sticking their snouts in masks, where expired air can be captured for analysis to see how much oxygen is metabolized each second. They have analyzed blood gases and taken muscle biopsies to count the number of capillaries that feed into the tissue, bearing the red blood cells rich with hemoglobin, which encages the needed oxygen.</p>
        <p>The different species have been more or less amenable to study depending on their natural inclination for exercise. Dr. Lindstedt said the pronghorns have happily participated in the workouts. "They liked it so much that you'd open the door to the lab in the morning and they'd run right in and jump on the treadmill," he said.</p>
        <p>Not so the goats or the steer. "They'll only run for you if you give them a ton of grain," said Dr. Jones. "They figure, O.K., O.K., if this is what I have to do to get my treats."</p>
        <p>From comparative experiments, physiologists have learned that the single biggest factor determining how much oxygen a mammal uses is its size: the smaller the animal, the more oxygen it takes in for every ounce of its flesh. "A gram of shrew muscle metabolizes 50 times as much oxygen as a gram of whale muscle," said Dr. David E. Leith, a physiologist at the Veterinary Medical College at Kansas State University in Manhattan. Why smaller animals must rev up at such a high metabolic rate is one of the great mysteries of physiology. "People used to think it was because smaller animals have more surface area relative to their weight than do bigger animals, and so they needed a higher metabolism to keep their body temperature up," said Dr. Kim E. Longworth, a research fellow at the University of California at Davis. "But the relationship between the two measurements hasn't held up, so this is still a big question in the field."</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason for the difference in metabolic rates, scientists have worked out in general how small mammals manage to take in and use so much oxygen. A tiny animal like the shrew breathes about 50 times as often as an elephant. Its windpipes, accordingly, are quite large relative to its body size, to accommodate a high influx of air. The shrew's lungs have greater internal surface area relative to its size, and thus they can trap more oxygen. To remove the oxygen from the lungs as swiftly as possible, the shrew's heart beats 1,200 times a minute, compared with the human heart rate of about 75 beats per minute. The pumped blood is exceptionally rich in hemoglobin, the molecular carrier that shuttles the oxygen through the body. The animal's muscles are dense with capillaries to take in oxygen and expel carbon dioxide waste.</p>
        <p>Of great importance, the muscle cells themselves are designed to put the delivered oxygen to immediate use: up to 50 percent of their volume is taken up with mitochondria, the little powerhouse structures where oxygen, along with sugar, is converted into energy. By contrast, the muscle cells of a cow, an animal whose most vigorous activity is likely to be swatting flies with its tail, are built of only about 2 or 3 percent mitochondria. The concentration of mitochondria in human muscle cells falls somewhere between the two figures, and it turns out that this density is yet another factor that can be improved with physical activity.</p>
        <p>Apart from the general correlation between small size and high oxygen metabolism, animals of the same dimensions often possess very different aerobic abilities. A gopher and a blue fox, for example, both weigh about 10 pounds, but the fox is far and away more efficient at burning oxygen. Examining why, Dr. Longworth has found that the key is the fox's extremely elevated heart rate. She has been able to show that in the fox, the blood is driven so quickly through the lungs that the pressure of oxygen in the lung spaces is always greater than it is in the bloodstream, a difference that ends up easing the diffusion of oxygen from the lung chambers into the blood vessels.</p>
        <p>Comparing goats with the aerobic miracles, the pronghorns, Dr. Lindstedt found that the antelopes have no structures the goats lack, but merely have more of everything on the oxygen transport pathway. The pronghorns' lungs have five times the surface area, and thus five times the opportunity to pick up oxygen. Their hearts are three times as big and thus can pump three times the volume of blood through the body. Their tracheas are much wider, their muscle mass is greater, their concentrations of hemoglobin in the blood and mitochondria in the muscle cells are much denser. Dr. Lindstedt proposes that the pronghorns evolved the talent for speed as a way to evade now-extinct ancestral cheetahs that once lived on the continent, and evolved their endurance to escape wolves, predators that hunt over long distances.</p>
        <p>But the pronghorns pay a price for their extraordinary design. "They have virtually no body fat," said Dr. Lindstedt. "In a bad Wyoming winter, many of them die of starvation."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
