<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; On TV, Truth Is More Instant Than Fiction</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="612882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D7173DF930A35755C0A965958260" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; On TV, Truth Is More Instant Than Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Television movies based on fact are not just still with us, despite an escalation in warnings over the last couple of decades about blurred lines between fact and fiction; there are, in fact, more of them than ever. And the time lapse between factual event and television dramatization gets shorter and shorter. In recent weeks, NBC broadcast three "instant docudramas" within four days: "Ambush in Waco," "Hurricane Andrew: Triumph Over Disaster" and "Without Warning: Terror in the Towers." Not surprisingly, this particular achievement turned out to be dubious.</p>
        <p>Most productions of this sort are doomed to mediocrity. Rushed into low-budget production, they are saddled with patched-together scripts and B-list actors obviously cruising at minimum-rehearsal speed. Worse, too many of the movies are forced into phony uplift modes, squeezing tearful sleaze out of genuine disasters, natural or man-made, whose survivors may still be distraught. That subtitle "Triumph Over Disaster" sums up prime-time television's determination to eliminate the negative, no matter what.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Television movies based on fact are not just still with us, despite an escalation in warnings over the last couple of decades about blurred lines between fact and fiction; there are, in fact, more of them than ever. And the time lapse between factual event and television dramatization gets shorter and shorter. In recent weeks, NBC broadcast three "instant docudramas" within four days: "Ambush in Waco," "Hurricane Andrew: Triumph Over Disaster" and "Without Warning: Terror in the Towers." Not surprisingly, this particular achievement turned out to be dubious.</p>
        <p>Most productions of this sort are doomed to mediocrity. Rushed into low-budget production, they are saddled with patched-together scripts and B-list actors obviously cruising at minimum-rehearsal speed. Worse, too many of the movies are forced into phony uplift modes, squeezing tearful sleaze out of genuine disasters, natural or man-made, whose survivors may still be distraught. That subtitle "Triumph Over Disaster" sums up prime-time television's determination to eliminate the negative, no matter what.</p>
        <p>It's not, let it be emphasized, that docudramas can't be powerful and quite effective at exploring social issues. Two of the better examples: "Burning Bed" and "Something About Amelia," about, respectively, battered wives and incest. But these days, exploitation usually gains the upper hand over exploration. The three Amy Fisher dramatizations have already entered the record books as a classic illustration.</p>
        <p>Still, distinctions can and should be made, especially as docudramas pounce more on media-saturated events. "Ambush in Waco" can certainly be faulted for rushing into a story that had yet to be concluded in real life. The movie took the story of David Koresh and his Branch Davidian religious cult up to the ill-fated raid on their Texas compound on Feb. 28 by agents of the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms. The final conflagration, which took the lives of more than 70 cultists, many of them children, occurred on April 19, while "Ambush in Waco" was still being filmed. An official Washington investigation into what happened, and why, on both days is still being promised.</p>
        <p>But this particular movie, part of a generally acclaimed series called "In the Line of Duty," proved unusually absorbing as it separately traces the stories of the Davidians and the Federal agents. Played skillfully by Tim Daly, Koresh emerged as part charismatic leader, part sex charlatan. In this instance, there was no effort to do a triumph spin. The lingering picture of innocents led to slaughter and ill-prepared law-enforcement agents painted a singularly disturbing picture of life in these United States.</p>
        <p>Hurricane Andrew in August, an entirely different kind of disaster, might have been thought to stimulate further sobering thoughts about the precariousness of fate. In fact, that did happen when film clips of the hurricane were inserted a couple of months ago into a television movie called "The Fire Next Time," a fictional alert about global warming and other environmental disasters. But purporting to be closer to the real thing, "Triumph Over Disaster" would have none of that negative stuff.</p>
        <p>The hero was a television weatherman who insisted that his station issue serious warnings about the hurricane building off Florida's southern coast. Working around the clock, he was eventually threatened with, gulp, laryngitis. On hand elsewhere were a dopey teen-ager who, against his parents' wishes, took the family boat for a sail; young lovers, he a hot-shot television reporter, she, an employee at the station; two elderly sisters, one with a dying husband, the other with beloved pets, and assorted black and Hispanic characters, including a glimpse of some farm peons scattering for cover.</p>
        <p>All, needless to say, came through admirably. In the end, as Gloria Estefan could be heard singing "Always Tomorrow," viewers were told: "With the storm came a new spirit. People met their neighbors for the first time." Scandalously botched rescue operations and scavenger rip-offs went unmentioned in this film. Instead, the returning teen-ager was hugged by his previously snarling dad and assured: "I love you. To hell with the boat." And, oh yes, tourism was soon booming again in Miami. You have to make sure you don't irritate anyone in these exercises.</p>
        <p>Much the same syrupy approach was employed for "Terror in the Towers," based on the bomb blast at the World Trade Center on Feb. 26. A horrifying breach of security, not just New York's but the nation's, was reduced to a series of heartwarming vignettes. Brave firemen rescued one of their own. Two touring kindergarten teachers from Brooklyn courageously got their students through the ordeal. In a crisis, New Yorkers are magnificent. So what else is new?</p>
        <p>But once again, in a two-bit production unsettling realities were smothered by a torrent of mush. "I am a teacher," one woman said with pride and dignity when told how remarkable she was with the children. Before we wipe away a tear or two, however, we might devote a moment to considering how teachers are woefully underpaid and overworked outside this world of calculated uplift. The last part of the movie followed the police and the Federal Bureau of Investigation's pursuit, which led to the arrests of several suspects, each very foreign-looking and obviously guilty. It was briefly noted that the investigation continues and a trial is to be held in September.</p>
        <p>But the biggest villain of the show turned out to be the press. When one unnamed newspaper insisted on breaking the news that suspects were about to be arrested, one law officer muttered darkly: "Those greedy, number-sucking bastards."</p>
        <p>Speaking of number-sucking, instant docudramas will continue to pile up as long as the ratings stay high enough for networks to make a relatively easy buck. Things are not about to change until viewer appetites demand something more nutritional than mush.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
