<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ice Reveals 250,000-Year Climate Story</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="618638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREENLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greenland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Greenland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDA163BF933A05755C0A965958260" item-length="680" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ice Reveals 250,000-Year Climate Story</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American scientists drilling through Greenland's massive icecap in search of information about past climate have at last reached a rocky layer assumed to lie just above bedrock, 10,013 feet beneath the surface, Michael Morrison, associate director of the project at the University of New Hampshire in Durham, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The annual layers of snow retrievable from the ice core contain information about weather at the time the snow fell, from which scientists can estimate the likelihood of global warming in the future. Now that the core has reached bottom, its climatic record will extend back to 250,000 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American scientists drilling through Greenland's massive icecap in search of information about past climate have at last reached a rocky layer assumed to lie just above bedrock, 10,013 feet beneath the surface, Michael Morrison, associate director of the project at the University of New Hampshire in Durham, said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The annual layers of snow retrievable from the ice core contain information about weather at the time the snow fell, from which scientists can estimate the likelihood of global warming in the future. Now that the core has reached bottom, its climatic record will extend back to 250,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>The hole and one drilled by ateam of Europeans from eight nations, which reached a similar depth 20 miles to the east last year, have produced a record far older than that of the past 160,000 years achieved at a Russian site in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>Unlike previous efforts to drill in Greenland, where it was feared that seaward flow of the ice had distorted the annual layers of snow and rendered their record uninterpretable, the two sites were at the ice summit, 10,500 feet above sea level. With ice there relatively stationary, it is hoped that the annual layers have hardly been disturbed. Flickering Temperatures</p>
        <p>Earlier ice cores from the two Greenland holes have shown that the climate repeatedly "flickered" between warm and cold periods both during the last ice age and the period of transition to the current climate. According to one analysis, the warming sometimes occurred in periods as brief as one to three years.</p>
        <p>Writing in a recent issue of the journal Nature, Dr. Richard G. Fairbanks of Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory has said the evidence for such flip-flops raises the "politically charged question" of whether they could recur.</p>
        <p>Some climate specialists argue that conditions responsible for such "flickers" no longer exist, but yesterday the National Science Foundation said that what was learned from the long core might ultimately allow researchers to understand such past events and help assess whether human activity might "once again set off such changes."</p>
        <p>The Greenland project will be the first to reach bedrock, said a participant, Dr. Debra A. Meese of the Army's Cold Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory in Hanover, N.H. The European hole, while virtually as deep, and an earlier joint project at the radar site Dye 3 extracted ice so near the bottom it was silty but it did not reach the underlying rock.</p>
        <p>Dr. Morrison said in an interview that the counting of annual layers in the cores of extracted ice had reached 40,000 years and that it should be possible to identify annual layers all the way to the bottom.</p>
        <p>Among the clues that make it possible to distinguish annual layers in the ice are summer-winter variations in temperature, indicated by relative abundances of two forms of oxygen in the ice. Identifying the annual layers is easier than at the Russian Vostok site in Antarctica because the much greater snowfall in Greenland produces thicker layers.</p>
        <p>Other clues to annual accumulations are dust grains, measurements of electrical conductivity revealing volcanic dust and identification of ash characterizing eruptions in which the date is known. The cores also contain microscopic bubbles of air captured in the snow before it turned to ice. These bubbles contain gases like carbon dioxide and methane that indicate the nature of past climates.  Sudden Climate Shifts</p>
        <p>The biggest surprise so far, said Dr. Paul Mayewski, chief scientist for the American project, "is that climate changes much more rapidly and frequently than we ever believed before." Evidence from his project has been confirmed by reports from the European ice core, as well as by different kinds of evidence from lake beds in Switzerland, Poland and the Canadian Maritime Provinces.</p>
        <p>Scientists from more than 20 universities and laboratories are participating in the American project, which is part of the Arctic Systems Science initiative of the National Science Foundation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
