<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="603441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D71F3EF93AA25757C0A965958260" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>Consumers are flocking back to the nation's stores as the weather improves, and business executives and economists are breathing easier. Early April cars sales werealso up, and mortgage applications remain at a high level.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>Business pledges to help revitalize poor neighborhoods in Los Angeles have so far done little to change the bleak economic conditions of the inner city.  [ A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>Consumers are flocking back to the nation's stores as the weather improves, and business executives and economists are breathing easier. Early April cars sales werealso up, and mortgage applications remain at a high level.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>Business pledges to help revitalize poor neighborhoods in Los Angeles have so far done little to change the bleak economic conditions of the inner city.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>A dispute has erupted in the Clinton Administration over Vice President Gore's efforts to persuade the President to announce specific steps to reduce the threat from global warming. Because of its potential cost, such a move has met resistance from several Cabinet members, principally Treasury Secretary Lloyd Bentsen and Energy Secretary Hazel R. O'Leary.  [ A17. ]</p>
        <p>The costs of health-care reform may be huge and involve tax increases bigger than any previously proposed.  [ A1. ] International</p>
        <p>Fiat's chairman, Gianni Agnelli, admitted to corporate corruption in Italy's vast kickback scandal.  [ D1 ]  Italians headed to the polls in elections that could restrict the power of the nation's political parties.  [ A8. ]</p>
        <p>Peru has embarked on a privatization program that is the most radical in Latin America. The nation plans to auction off virtually all its state-owned companies over the next two years.  [ D1. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Tandy's chief, John V. Roach, is tightening his grasp on operations at the company's flagship, the nationwide chain of Radio Shack consumer electronics stores. The company disclosed Friday that Bernard S. Appel, a Tandy senior vice president and the chairman of Radio Shack for the last year, would retire June 30 and become a consultant to the company.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Three corporations were ordered to pay $48.3 million in punitive damages in a civil lawsuit over leaky plastic plumbing that flooded some homes. The three are the Shell Oil Company, the United States Brass unit of Eljer Industries and the Hoechst Celanese Corporation.  [ D2. ] The Media Business</p>
        <p>ABC was the only network to gain ground as the official 1992-93 television season ended last night. It moved to second place behind CBS. NBC slid deeply into third place.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Radio stations are consolidating in the wake of the F.C.C.'s easing of regulations to allow a single owner to buy up to four stations in one metropolitan area; 730 radio stations, or nearly 7 percent of the industry, have signed deals that will lead to ownership changes.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Town &amp; Country has appointed Pamela Fiori, a longtime American Express Publishing executive, as editor in chief to shore up the faltering magazine.  [ D11. ]</p>
        <p>Newspapers get some advice on how to compete with television. William Glaberson: Press Notes.  [ D11. ]</p>
        <p>America West Airlines tries to show respect for it customers. Advertising.  [ D12. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>An economist has come up with a new method for predicting trends in the bond market that uses data provided by the Journal of Commerce index of commodity prices. Jonathan Fuerbringer: Credit Markets.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>A more effective way to protect endangered reptiles has been developed by two professors. Patents.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Apple's report of quarterly performance has divided analysts over whether it is good news or bad news. Market Place.  [ D4. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
