<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film; High Anxiety Amid the Vistas</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLIFFHANGER (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDD1638F93BA15756C0A965958260" item-length="956" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film; High Anxiety Amid the Vistas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"CLIFFHANGER," the new high-altitude thriller starring Sylvester Stallone, wastes no time in establishing its first priority, that of sending its audience into a cold sweat. This effect is achieved spectacularly well with a long, death-defying credit sequence set somewhere near the ozone layer. Mr. Stallone, playing a pumped-up Rocky Mountain rescue worker with an incongruously Presidential haircut, does his best to save a young woman who hangs precariously from a rope across a terrifyingly deep abyss. You will be in no hurry to mountain-climb after watching this scene.</p>
        <p>At such moments, and "Cliffhanger" has many of them, thoughts about life insurance come to mind. Was Sylvester Stallone really filmed atop the dizzyingly high, needle-shaped peak that figures prominently in the film's opening? Did he really scale the kinds of cliffs and mountainsides that are seen here? Did he hang in midair from a fraying rope, cross great chasms via rickety bridges or battle over a helicopter about to plunge into oblivion? Obviously, a great deal of credit goes to stunt doubles and optical tricks, but the illusion is still astonishingly effective. "Cliffhanger" really seems to be set somewhere up in the sky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"CLIFFHANGER," the new high-altitude thriller starring Sylvester Stallone, wastes no time in establishing its first priority, that of sending its audience into a cold sweat. This effect is achieved spectacularly well with a long, death-defying credit sequence set somewhere near the ozone layer. Mr. Stallone, playing a pumped-up Rocky Mountain rescue worker with an incongruously Presidential haircut, does his best to save a young woman who hangs precariously from a rope across a terrifyingly deep abyss. You will be in no hurry to mountain-climb after watching this scene.</p>
        <p>At such moments, and "Cliffhanger" has many of them, thoughts about life insurance come to mind. Was Sylvester Stallone really filmed atop the dizzyingly high, needle-shaped peak that figures prominently in the film's opening? Did he really scale the kinds of cliffs and mountainsides that are seen here? Did he hang in midair from a fraying rope, cross great chasms via rickety bridges or battle over a helicopter about to plunge into oblivion? Obviously, a great deal of credit goes to stunt doubles and optical tricks, but the illusion is still astonishingly effective. "Cliffhanger" really seems to be set somewhere up in the sky.</p>
        <p>Featuring beautiful Alpine vistas (much of "Cliffhanger" was shot in Italy, in the Dolomites), this film treats Mr. Stallone as a smaller, more mobile and no less impressive piece of scenery. His muscles bulging, the veins of his neck etched in sharp relief, his jaw set determinedly, Mr. Stallone is every bit as physically impressive as the material requires him to be. As with Steven Seagal, who finally had a big, entertaining film built around him by the makers of "Under Siege," Mr. Stallone has been surrounded by better actors but is unrivaled as his film's main attraction.</p>
        <p>Main animate attraction, that is. All of the performers are upstaged by the film's breathtaking backdrop, and by the fast and furious way Renny Harlin, the director, approaches action sequences. Just as he did in "Die Hard 2," Mr. Harlin concentrates on generating nonstop excitement at the expense of small talk. In fact, his pacing can be so fast that the occasional transition is missing, though the film's staging remains perfectly clear. Quickly and efficiently, Mr. Harlin leads the film from one perilous escapade to another, following a visceral plot that somehow manages to avoid repetition. Even though "Cliffhanger" leads off with a couple of its biggest scenes, a can-you-top-this momentum sustains it all the way through.</p>
        <p>Dialogue is the only real drawback, since the screenplay by Michael France and Mr. Stallone tends to be as drab as the mountains are beautiful. Mr. Stallone plays Gabe Walker, whose morale is badly injured during that opening rescue attempt and who spends the rest of the film getting it back. In the process, he also loses and re-wins Jessie Deighan (Janine Turner), the plucky mountaineer who is part of his rescue team, and proves his grit to Hal Tucker (Michael Rooker), who still bears a grudge against Gabe for the debacle that haunts them both. "If you don't do this now," Jessie tells Gabe, prodding him into action by recalling the trauma, "you're going to be stuck on that ledge for the rest of your life."</p>
        <p>Gabe is forced back into action by a harrowing air crash, which Mr. Harlin stages in typical high-octane style. A plane carrying Treasury Department officials and $100 million in new bills is hijacked in midair, and later goes down in the mountains. When Gabe goes to the rescue, he becomes the captive of a gang led by Eric Qualen (John Lithgow), an urbane Englishman who oozes sarcasm from every pore. Mr. Lithgow's suave delivery is rarely matched by the lame repartee that has been written for him (when someone is called a "piece of work" in this screenplay, it's pretty obvious what the rejoinder will be).  Still, Mr. Lithgow's debonair performance is as refreshing as the snowy panoramas that surround him.</p>
        <p>Until it takes a turn toward nasty sadism in its later stages -- one character is impaled on an icicle, for instance -- "Cliffhanger" remains relatively bloodless and crisp, preferring to concentrate on sheer gamesmanship and clever effects. The sophistication of the latter is one of the film's most enjoyable aspects. Whenever the actors seem to be doing the impossible, it's time to draw back and wonder what was used to help them, but the film works very credibly on its own terms. The special effects seen here are as perfect and hard-won as Mr. Stallone's musculature, and that's saying a lot.</p>
        <p>Ms. Turner and Mr. Rooker contribute as much spark and variety as is humanly possible, which turns out to be a great deal. The film is also helped by John Vallone's rustic production design on those few occasions when it moves indoors. The rest of the time, Alex Thomson's bright, hard- edged cinematography contributes to the film's rugged atmosphere. Even Trevor Jones's music has muscle.</p>
        <p>"Cliffhanger" is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes violence and profanity. Cliffhanger  Directed by Renny Harlin; screenplay by Michael France and Sylvester Stallone, based on a premise by John Long; director of photography, Alex Thomson; edited by Frank J. Urioste; music by Trevor Jones; production designer, John Vallone; produced by Alan Marshall, Mr. Harlin, Gene Patrick Hines, James R. Zatolokin and David Rotman; released by Tristar Pictures. Running time: 118 minutes. This film is rated R. Gabe Walker . . . Sylvester Stallone Eric Qualen . . . John Lithgow Hal Tucker . . . Michael Rooker Jessie Deighan . . . Janine Turner Delmar . . . Craig Fairbrass Walter Wright . . . Paul Winfield</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
