<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Waste-Management Experiment</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="635237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MANURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DAIRY PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ODYSSEY FARM</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIROAUDIT BIOSYSTEMS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEWART, WEIR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dairy Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930918T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D8113EF93BA2575AC0A965958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Waste-Management Experiment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>HILLSDALE, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The farmer has a seat on the stock exchange and a degree in philosophy from Princeton. The cow manure has been inoculated with microbes. And scientists from Houston are teaching laboratory techniques to the farmhands.</p>
        <p>Here in Columbia County, where agriculture is still the biggest industry, a 400-acre dairy operation known as Odyssey Farm is moving ahead with high-tech biological management of manure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The farmer has a seat on the stock exchange and a degree in philosophy from Princeton. The cow manure has been inoculated with microbes. And scientists from Houston are teaching laboratory techniques to the farmhands.</p>
        <p>Here in Columbia County, where agriculture is still the biggest industry, a 400-acre dairy operation known as Odyssey Farm is moving ahead with high-tech biological management of manure.</p>
        <p>Even as the project goes forward, the farm has been linked with publicity about what can go wrong with the old way of farming: a spill of liquefied manure that devastated a nearby trout stream, leaving the farm liable for fines and an incalculable loss of good will from its neighbors.</p>
        <p>Odyssey Farm has survived when other family-held dairy farms have failed, succumbing to a combination of rising land values, rising taxes, stagnant milk prices and an inability to adapt traditional ways. Milk and Waste</p>
        <p>Built up by Weir Stewart, an entrepreneur who made his fortune in the oil business, Odyssey now milks 900 cows three times a day, producing 8,500 gallons of milk. The farm's herd also produces something else: an amount of solid waste equivalent to that produced by a town of 10,000 people.</p>
        <p>Traditionally, farmers have piled manure in heaps to be spread on fields later as fertilizer. Larger farms like Odyssey have turned to liquefying their manure by mixing it with water and storing it in lagoons, making it easier to handle. The liquid is later sprayed on to fields.</p>
        <p>The problem with manure -- both solid and liquid -- is the phosphorus and nitrogen that it contains. Keeping those chemicals out of the water supply is a priority for farmers and for officials whose mandate is to safeguard water supplies. Even New York City is getting in the act, spending more than $3 million on efforts to study ways to improve manure management on the 350 farms in its watershed.</p>
        <p>It was a spill of liquid manure that brought Odyssey Farms a great deal of unwanted attention earlier this year. A liquid manure spreader -- a device much like a lawn sprinkler -- stuck in one position and sprayed into a rivulet that feeds a nearby stream, the Roe Jan Kill, known for its population of native brown trout. Within 24 hours, a two-mile stretch of the Roe Jan had been rendered utterly lifeless. While vultures circled overhead, environmental investigators combed the fish-strewn waters. The New York State Department of Environmental Conservation quickly found Odyssey responsible for the fish kill and water quality violations. 'Horrible and Sad'</p>
        <p>"The whole irony of the spill is that it occurred just as we were about to implement the new process," said Mr. Stewart. "It goes without saying that we feel horrible and sad about the Roe Jan spill, but we think that with this system nothing like that could ever happen again."</p>
        <p>Looking for answers to his manure problems, Mr. Stewart had followed the advice of a friend in the oil business and called C. F. (Buddy) Barnes of Houston. Mr. Barnes, a fellow Princeton graduate, is the founder of a company that treats organic waste by combining it with specially formulated "recipes" of naturally occurring microbes.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Barnes has been involved in cleaning up oil sites, a die works in Zhong Shan, China, and a pig-farming operation in Spain, his company, EnviroAudit BioSystems, had never tackled a dairy farm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barnes was confident that his process would work at Odyssey.</p>
        <p>"Sixty-five percent of the world's waste can be cleaned up using this microbial remediation system," said Mr. Barnes. "The only reason we aren't doing more in the U.S. is because of the bureaucracy involved. New York State happens to be very cooperative."</p>
        <p>After a year of laboratory testing, during which Odyssey workers regularly mailed manure samples in plastic containers and Coca-Cola bottles to Mr. Barnes's company, a formula was devised by a team of biochemists. In August a shipment of aerators and other heavy equipment arrived at the farm. This was followed by a team of environmental engineers, including Mr. Barnes and his son Jason, who set up the system and taught Odyssey workers to maintain and monitor it. Carbon Dioxide and Water</p>
        <p>Then, on a bright August day, with a small crowd gathered along the shores of the 14-million-gallon lagoons, the Barnes team, dressed in red jump suits, started up the aerators and tossed in the first batch of the microbes, which had been dehydrated onto wheat bran. The scene resembled the christening of an ocean liner.</p>
        <p>The microbes are supposed to break down the organic matter, creating carbon dioxide and water. The aerators, which add oxygen to the mix, will stir up the heavy sludge from the bottom of the lagoons. While the process is beginning, gases emanating from the lagoons will produce an even worse smell than before. But after several weeks, this should subside.</p>
        <p>"It's going to be fantastic," said Weir Stewart, sitting in the farm office, which now resembles a chemistry lab, with test tubes and figures scrawled on a chalk board.</p>
        <p>The hope is that water from the lagoon can be used to flush out the farm's barns, a job that now consumes 160,000 gallons of water per day.</p>
        <p>Gerald Moore, spokesman for the State Department of Agriculture and Markets, said a team from Albany will be traveling down from Albany next week to see the system here.</p>
        <p>"If a farm like Odyssey can make this work," he said, "it will be adopted all over the country."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
