<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmentalists Help On Utility's 20-Year Plan</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="650165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSERVATION OF RESOURCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECYCLING OF WASTE MATERIALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSERVATION LAW FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND ELECTRIC SYSTEM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DE133AF936A25752C1A965958260" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmentalists Help On Utility's 20-Year Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While environmental groups have worked with utilities in the past, New England Electric System is going further than any other has so far, allowing a leading environmental group to help develop its new 20-year strategic plan.</p>
        <p>The plan, which is to be announced today in Boston, emphasizes renewable resources like wind power, and will use a wide variety of small-scale generating options and will recycle waste to produce more electricity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While environmental groups have worked with utilities in the past, New England Electric System is going further than any other has so far, allowing a leading environmental group to help develop its new 20-year strategic plan.</p>
        <p>The plan, which is to be announced today in Boston, emphasizes renewable resources like wind power, and will use a wide variety of small-scale generating options and will recycle waste to produce more electricity.</p>
        <p>John W. Rowe, the president and chief executive of the utility, said that one instance in which the environmental group, the Conservation Law Foundation, caused a major shift was to convince the utility to build a pilot plant by 1996 that would convert waste from farms, plants and residential areas into gas.</p>
        <p>"They forced the agenda on that issue," he said. "While we agreed it was a great idea, we did not give it the priority that they gave it."</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview on Friday Mr. Rowe said he was speaking from a conference room of the foundation's headquarters in downtown Boston where he was meeting with its staff -- scarcely a typical place for the head of a utility to be. He said it underscored the trust of the two groups.</p>
        <p>"It was the first time that a utility has made this work as opposed to just talking about it," said Armond Cohen, a lawyer who specializes in energy for the foundation.</p>
        <p>Normally, when a big utility puts together its plan for the next decade, the participants are insiders with perhaps a few outside consultants called in from time to time.</p>
        <p>But in this case the consultants were former adversaries. Not only have foundation lawyers been allowed inside, but they have been encouraged to speak out and to challenge every main assumption of the utility's managers and technicians. A 20-Year Plan</p>
        <p>Now, after eight months of give and take, the utility, which serves 1.2 million homes and businesses in Massachusetts, New Hampshire and Rhode Island, will announce a 20-year strategic plan today on which the conservation group has had considerable impact.</p>
        <p>The utility has enough generating capacity and thus did not need a new plant, but it did need to decide what its mix of fuels should be and what new technologies to try.</p>
        <p>The 27-year-old foundation is a nonprofit group of 17 lawyers who have prodded utilities and other industries to convince them that cleaning up pollution and using resources more wisely can add to the bottom line.</p>
        <p>It gets three-fourths of its $2 million annual budget from other foundations, including the Energy Foundation and the Pew Charitable Trust. The rest comes from 7,000 members.</p>
        <p>The new plan was hammered out in meetings, which at times became intense, those taking part recalled.</p>
        <p>"They were challenging daily whether we should do more of this or more of that," Jeffrey D. Tranen, a vice president of the utility, said.</p>
        <p>The traditional mindset among utilities, Mr. Tranen added, has been to take a narrow path of figuring what fuels are going to be least expensive and then adding more capacity.</p>
        <p>"Everbody, like lemmings, is heading to gas," he said. The lesson of the energy crisis of 1973 and 1979 when utilities in the Northeast found themselves heavily dependent on high-priced oil, was to remain flexible. "It's important not to bet on one fuel too much," he added. Oil and Electricity</p>
        <p>Utilities in the Northeast before 1973 derived about 70 percent of their electricity from oil-powered plants.</p>
        <p>The participation of the environmental group, he said, was to get the management and technical people of New England Electric, to look more toward what are called "renewable resources," like wind power, for which no new fuel is burned.</p>
        <p>The utility plans to build a wind-power plant, the largest on the East Coast, in Maine, and to start operating it by 1995. Still, in the overall scale of things, it will be tiny, generating about 2 megawatts. The utility's capacity is about 5,500 megawatts.</p>
        <p>The utility has two coal-fired plants with 40 percent of its elecricity, and a series of smaller hydroelectric plants generating 20 percent. Nuclear Interests</p>
        <p>The utility also has small interests in every major nuclear plant in New England. It is a medium-sized utility one-third the size of Con Edison.</p>
        <p>Another option pushed by the Conservation Law Foundation was to work with industrial customers to meet power needs by using small co-generating plants and fuel cells.</p>
        <p>Under the usual thinking, a utility would project ahead the needs of its big industrial customers and then seek to build a new plant or expand existing large power plants.</p>
        <p>Current efforts to reduce carbon dioxide emissions and other gases that contribute to the greenhouse effect by 20 percent by the year 2000 will be stepped up. Some of the efforts are unusual. For example, the utility paid lumber companies in a rain forest in Malaysia to improve cutting methods to lessen the damage. The goal is to save trees, sustaining their ability to absorb carbon dioxide.  To be sure, other major utilties have sought the advice of environmentalists on their long-range plans. The Pacific Gas and Electric Company, San Francisco, for example, has had the Natural Resources Defense Council advise its corporate planners, but not on the same scale as New England Electric.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
