<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crying Wolf Over Elephants</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930228T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="588558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUNTING AND TRAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POACHING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELEPHANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOYCOTTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IVORY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECALLS AND BANS OF PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AFRICAN WILDLIFE FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONNER, RAYMOND</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poaching</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ivory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D9123CF934A35751C0A965958260" item-length="4251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crying Wolf Over Elephants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Raymond Bonner;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BONNER, RAYMOND</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With great sadness I find I must write to tell you that the plight of Africa's wild elephants is far more desperate than I could have ever imagined." So began an "urgent memorandum" from the African Wildlife Foundation, a nonprofit conservation organization, to its members and potential donors on Feb. 10, 1988. Signed by Paul Schindler, the group's president, the appeal had been prepared by a California company skilled in direct-mail solicitation. It was designed to shock and raise money. It succeeded in both.</p>
        <p>"In Kenya, there were 165,000 elephants just 15 years ago," the memorandum said. "Today only 20,000 remain." Of the 30,000 elephants that had roamed Tsavo National Park in Kenya in the 1970's, "the remaining 5,000 will be dead in 17 months." In Tanzania, half the 50,000 elephants in the Selous Reserve had been killed in the last eight years. In Uganda, 90 percent "of these beautiful animals have been wiped out." This "slaughter" was caused by the "insatiable greed of the ivory hunters." The memorandum concluded by declaring 1988 the "Year of the Elephant."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With great sadness I find I must write to tell you that the plight of Africa's wild elephants is far more desperate than I could have ever imagined." So began an "urgent memorandum" from the African Wildlife Foundation, a nonprofit conservation organization, to its members and potential donors on Feb. 10, 1988. Signed by Paul Schindler, the group's president, the appeal had been prepared by a California company skilled in direct-mail solicitation. It was designed to shock and raise money. It succeeded in both.</p>
        <p>"In Kenya, there were 165,000 elephants just 15 years ago," the memorandum said. "Today only 20,000 remain." Of the 30,000 elephants that had roamed Tsavo National Park in Kenya in the 1970's, "the remaining 5,000 will be dead in 17 months." In Tanzania, half the 50,000 elephants in the Selous Reserve had been killed in the last eight years. In Uganda, 90 percent "of these beautiful animals have been wiped out." This "slaughter" was caused by the "insatiable greed of the ivory hunters." The memorandum concluded by declaring 1988 the "Year of the Elephant."</p>
        <p>Three months later, at a Washington news conference at the National Zoo and in the yard of the zoo's African elephant, Nancy, Diana McMeekin, the organization's vice president, issued an appeal to American consumers: "Don't Buy Ivory."</p>
        <p>The mailing and news conference were the beginning of one of the most intense conservation campaigns ever. The crusade to ban ivory was marked by increasing hyperbole and gruesome pictures of mutilated elephants and by public emotion and politics. It was a campaign in which conservation organizations paid homage to fund raising and membership. Groups that endorsed a ban found that there was money in elephants -- big money -- and, conversely, that failing to join the crusade might cost them members.</p>
        <p>Only a few months before the news conference, McMeekin herself had been wearing ivory bracelets. The organization saw nothing wrong with it, and even now was proceeding with caution: it did not ask for a ban on ivory trading. Rather, the memo urged, "Don't buy ivory until the situation is brought under control!" The goal was to educate Americans that ivory products come from elephants. To have gone beyond that educational purpose, McMeekin said later, would have put the wildlife foundation on "the slippery slope to an extreme position." The extreme position was a total ban. "We felt that it would be arrogant and inappropriate for outsiders to tell Africa what to do about a natural resource of theirs."</p>
        <p>In the spring of 1988, it would have been hard to find a scientist or conservationist with experience in Africa who</p>
        <p>did</p>
        <p>believe in a total ban as the solution to elephant poaching. "Outright bans would not solve the problem," one of Africa's pre-eminent conservationists, David Western, said at the time of the news conference. Western, who has a doctorate in ecology and was director from 1986 to 1990 of Wildlife Conservation International, the field research arm of the New York Zoological Society, went even further. A ban, he said "would exaggerate the problems with wildlife in Africa, because African nations use the revenue from ivory to help finance their conservation programs."</p>
        <p>Even the most respected elephant researchers were not calling for a total ban in 1988. A ban, even a moratorium for 5 to 10 years, would be far from a solution to the problem, many thought. It might even "endanger elephants," Iain Douglas-Hamilton said in November 1988 at a meeting of representatives of African wildlife departments and Western conservationists, called to discuss the escalating problem of poaching. The African governments unanimously rejected the idea of a ban -- they didn't even like the foundation's call for a consumer boycott -- and Douglas-Hamilton's views were influential. He was "Mr. Elephant," a dashing Scotsman who had engaged in elephant research since the 1960's. In support of his argument, Douglas-Hamilton noted that in Botswana, South Africa and Zimbabwe, elephant populations were "well managed and well protected" and that those countries made money from the sale of ivory.</p>
        <p>Nor did Cynthia Moss see the need for a total ban. Moss, who had begun her elephant research under Douglas-Hamilton's tutelage, had gone on to acquire well-earned fame for her work with elephants in the Amboseli National Park in Kenya. She had named the elephants -- Slit Ear and Torn Ear, Teddy, Tonie and Tilly -- watched them frolic, mate, become parents and die. Wanting other people "to know them, enjoy them and care about them," she wrote "Elephant Memories: Thirteen Years in the Life of an Elephant Family," which was published in 1988. Moss ended her book with a look to "future generations." It was grim. Poaching was going on at a far greater rate than anyone had realized. Still, she wrote, "The situation is depressing but it may not be irreversible." What was needed to reverse it was a "worldwide campaign to reduce the demand for ivory." Notably, she too stopped short of calling for a complete ban on trading.</p>
        <p>In spite of all these reservations, a mere 17 months after the wildlife foundation asked Americans to refrain from buying ivory, the decision was no longer a matter of individual choice and conscience. In October 1989 at Lausanne, Switzerland, by a vote of more than two-thirds of the governments that are signatories to the Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora, known as Cites, the elephant was declared an endangered species, joining, among others, the leopard, rhinoceros, gorilla, the California condor and the blue and fin whales. As a result of the designation, ivory trading became illegal.</p>
        <p>The African Wildlife Foundation, which had overcome its professed concerns about appearing arrogant, had lobbied hard for the complete ban. But it wasn't the only organization or individual that had done a conservation flip-flop. By the time of the Cites vote, it was hard to find a conservationist who was willing to speak out publicly against a ban: Douglas-Hamilton and Cynthia Moss were on board, as was David Western, though he sought a compromise that would have allowed Botswana, Zimbabwe and South Africa, where poaching was not a serious problem, to trade in ivory after a moratorium of a couple of years.</p>
        <p>What explains the dramatic shift? The short answer: public emotion and money.</p>
        <p>All the organizations that called for a ban deny that they were motivated by anything other than the best interests of the African elephant, that if ivory trading were not made illegal it would be impossible to control poaching. Others demur.</p>
        <p>"All groups that have used the elephant as a P.R. gimmick have made bundles, I mean bundles." Craig Van Note, executive vice president of Monitor, a Washington-based consortium of conservation and animal-welfare groups, told me during the Cites meeting in Lausanne. "Elephants are sexy," he said, adding that when it came to raising money, they were more alluring than dolphins or pandas and as popular as whales. From the moment the wildlife foundation started its elephant campaign, McMeekin says, the group was under pressure from the public relations company that did its fund raising to adopt a tougher line. She says the organization resisted, and when it did finally call for a complete ban in May 1989, it was only after "considerable soul-searching."</p>
        <p>AT THE BEGINNING OF 1989, the African Wildlife Foundation was still of the view that a voluntary boycott was the only appropriate approach. But 1989 was the year of the environment. Time magazine's "Man of the Year" was the "Endangered Earth." There were fears about global warming, the greenhouse effect and a hole in the ozone. There were appeals to save Brazil's rain forests, outrage at an oil spill off the coast of Alaska and questions about what to do with the world's hazardous wastes. But no issue reached the public -- its heart and pocketbook -- as deeply as the African elephant. And as Western passions rose, so did the sums of money available to organizations that pandered to them.</p>
        <p>The foundation escalated its "Don't Buy Ivory" campaign on Feb. 12, 1989, with a full-page Sunday ad in The New York Times. "Today, in America, Someone Will Slaughter an Elephant for a Bracelet," the ad declared over a picture of an elephant carcass. "In the past 10 years, the population has been sliced almost in half. In 1979 the total elephant population of Africa was estimated at 1,300,000. Today, less than 750,000 remain. Some 70,000 elephants are killed each year to meet the worldwide demand for ivory." At that rate, the elephant would disappear in Africa by 1999, the ad asserted. "It's a sickening thought. In 10 short years we could have to explain to children why there are no more elephants." The foundation asked readers to help stop "the slaughter" of African elephants by sending in a tax-deductible donation of $25, $50, $100 or more. It provided a coupon for the reader to clip or a toll-free number to call.</p>
        <p>The response was staggering, beyond anything that the foundation, or Saatchi &amp; Saatchi, the international advertising giant that provided its services without charge, had anticipated. It is unusual that an ad raises enough money to pay its cost; organizations place them anyway, to get their message across and their names before the public and in the hope of expanding their mailing lists with the names of people who write in. The Times ad cost $40,000. Twelve hundred people responded, and the organization received $42,526.</p>
        <p>When the foundation had begun its elephant campaign in 1988, it was a small organization with 23,600 members, not very well known outside of a small circle of African wildlife aficionados; its budget was $1.8 million. By the end of 1989, it had 43,000 members, its donations had increased from $1.5 million to $2.5 million and it was established as a major force in the African conservation game. There is no doubt that the elephant campaign was a major factor in the organization's growth, McMeekin says, although the group also engaged in a membership drive during this period.</p>
        <p>The International Wildlife Coalition was the next to get into what was becoming a very lucrative game, with an ad in The Times headlined "African Chainsaw Massacre," This organization claimed the elephant would be extinct by 1997, and it went on: "The last elephant to die will likely be a baby. . . . The last thing this baby will see before it dies will be its mother being killed and mutilated with a chainsaw." Founded in 1983, out of the growing popularity of animal rights, the organization hadn't paid much attention to elephants; it concentrated instead on saving whales, in 1988 spending more than $120,000 on that cause and only $11,000 on elephants (it even spent more on kangaroos and sea turtles than on elephants). The "Chainsaw Massacre" ad cost $22,000 and brought in $25,000, a phenomenal amount given the organization's size and its previous lack of devotion to elephants. In the following year, the organization says, it spent $170,000 on elephants.</p>
        <p>It was not only in the United States that the elephant was loved and lucrative. In South Africa, the Endangered Wildlife Trust, one of the country's major conservation organizations with its headquarters in Johannesburg, raised nearly $150,000 from selling original elephant prints drawn and signed by the wildlife artist David Shepherd. That made it one of the most successful conservation appeals in South Africa, which has a strong and active environmental movement and consciousness. "We rode on the backs of elephants, and rhinos, for years," the trust's director, John Ledger, told me.</p>
        <p>In Britain, the World Wide Fund for Nature, part of the international group known as W.W.F., sent out a four-page letter on behalf of the elephant in late 1988. Bland by the standards of the hyperbole being employed by the African Wildlife Foundation and other United States organizations, it used the word "slaughter" only once while noting the alarming decline of elephants in Kenya, Tanzania and Zambia. The mailing went to 50,000 people and raised $:300,000 (more than $500,000). Seven months later, in July 1989, the fund sent out another elephant appeal. An additional $:200,000 came in. That was twice as much as people sent in response to pleas for sea turtles and gorillas.</p>
        <p>The British group initially had been opposed to the ban. But elephant poaching was the stuff of British tabloids, and The Daily Mail ran tear-jerking stories about baby elephants orphaned when their mothers were killed by poachers, providing coupons for readers to cut out and send to the organization, urging it to call for a ban on ivory imports. No less than 60,000 readers inundated the group with letters and telephone calls -- and $:7,000 in donations.</p>
        <p>At last, public pressure for a ban became too great and, worried about losing members, the group capitulated and voted to support a ban.</p>
        <p>NO PLACE WAS THE conflict between good conservation and the mammon of fund raising more bitterly joined than at the World Wildlife Fund in Washington, also part of the international group known as W.W.F. (Probably best known by its panda logo, the Swiss-based group has national organizations in sometwo dozen countries.) Over a period of more than a year, in what seemed to be never-ending "blood and guts" meetings, the American group debated the ivory ban. Those individuals whose job it was to bring in money and members argued that the organization had to support a ban or else lose members, perhaps a large number. The conservationists opposed it. Among them were Rick Weyerhaeuser, who had studied elephants in Uganda and Tanzania and was the first program officer for Africa at the wildlife fund in Washington; Tom McShane, who had been a Peace Corps volunteer in Niger and had worked in Malawi, and Michael Wright, a vice president whose responsibility was the development of conservation policies that considered the needs of rural people.</p>
        <p>Weyerhaeuser, McShane and Wright argued that a ban was bad conservation and bad for Africans, especially southern Africans. And they asked how the wildlife fund could endorse a ban and at the same time continue to support the doctrine of sustainable utilization. This doctrine, which had been incorporated into the landmark World Conservation Strategy of 1980, says in essence that the use of resources is permissible -- wise and rational use, but use nonetheless. They argued that it would be inconsistent and hypocritical for the fund, which had been one of the doctrine's sponsors, now to endorse a ban on ivory when it wasn't even clear that the species was endangered.</p>
        <p>Though "conservation" has become a generic term embracing all efforts to save the environment and resources, initially it meant the careful and planned use of resources. Opposing the "conservationists" were the "preservationists," who argued on esthetic and ethical grounds that nature should be left undisturbed by man. Most conservationists are probably preservationists at heart: the principle of sustainable utilization was adopted not out of any philosophical commitment but out of the reality of the third world. As the World Conservation Strategy puts it, "Hundreds of millions of rural people in developing countries, including 500 million malnourished and 800 million destitute, are compelled to destroy the resources necessary to free them from starvation and poverty." The drafters of the World Conservation Strategy recognized that the poor of the world were going to use the resources around them to survive, notwithstanding philosophical and ethical appeals by wealthy Westerners. Therefore, they should be encouraged to use them in a sustainable way.</p>
        <p>The most valuable resource in Kenya and many African countries is wildlife. One obvious way to "utilize" wildlife, to make money from it, is through tourism. But more directly profitable forms of sustainable utilization include killing crocodiles, leopards and zebras for their skins; impala, elands and wildebeests for their meat, and lions and buffalos for hunting trophies. Sustainable utilization also permits the killing of elephants for their ivory. In many rural districts of Africa, the sale of ivory from just 1 or 2 percent of the elephant population could generate substantial revenues, at least in comparison with the district's few other revenues, and in many cases would take the districts off the international dole. And allowing rural people to make money from elephants gives them a powerful incentive to protect the species from poachers.</p>
        <p>In spite of its longtime commitment to the principle of sustainable utilization, however, the World Wildlife Fund in Washington was concerned that the concept was "not understood by the vast majority" of its members. "Most of these members are more traditionally orientated toward species 'preservation,' and there is little understanding of the complexities of conservation in Africa in the 1980's," two senior conservationists in Washington wrote in a 1988 memo. Failure to endorse a ban, they added, would have "a seriously detrimental effect on our membership." As Russell Train, the group's chairman, told me in 1991: "We're trying to bring our members along on utilization, but our development people, the fund-raisers, are very nervous because there is no question that the great majority of our membership are animal lovers and have difficulty making the evolution to a more sophisticated understanding of conservation."</p>
        <p>It is indeed difficult to explain sustainable utilization in catchy slogans like "Only Elephants Should Wear Ivory" and "Ban the Bloody Ivory Trade" -- with "Bloody" in dripping red. A slogan like "Buy Ivory, Save Elephants" might not bring in major contributions but it would be honest -- by giving elephants an economic value, Africans would not only have an incentive to protect them but money with which to do it. Funds from the sale of ivory could be used for antipoaching measures and other conservation programs.</p>
        <p>In the end, the fund-raisers at W.W.F. prevailed over the conservationists, and on June 1, 1989, the American branch announced that it "strongly endorsed" the proposal to ban the trade. The international reluctantly joined in. "We caved," Robert SanGeorge, the international spokesman, says simply, explaining the international's decision to endorse a ban. (A few days later, President Bush announced a unilateral ban on the importation of ivory.)</p>
        <p>In calling for a ban, the fund not only sacrificed its principles but, it can be argued, abandoned most Africans as well. Zimbabwe, Botswana and a half dozen other African countries, which together have over half of the continent's elephants, never wavered in their opposition to a ban. In announcing its endorsement, the group said it was doing so "based on new scientific findings." The "findings" were the work of something called the Ivory Trade Review Group, which consisted of scientists, economists and conservationists. The group had been formed in mid-1988 by a variety of conservation groups, including W.W.F., to investigate the ivory trade and determine what effect it had on the declining elephant populations. On June 1, the trade review group called for a ban on ivory trading in a nine-page statement; eventually they would release a 700-page report. This report was the basis on which many conservationists who were originally opposed to a ban endorsed one. The recommendation for a ban, however, did not accurately reflect the views of all members of the group. The group's economists, for instance, opposed a ban. Four days before the release of the statement, David Pearce, a professor of environmental economics in London, had protested on behalf of his colleagues that depriving the African countries of ivory sales was the equivalent of a $50 million tax on their governments. Domestic ivory-carving industries would also be severely hurt. Pearce suggested the affected countries should be compensated by the West with $100 million a year. These views did not appear in the public statement.</p>
        <p>The most serious reservation about the trade review group report, however, derives from the makeup of its contributors. When the group released its statement on June 1, it listed 25 contributors and two co-chairmen. All 27 were white. Fourteen were affiliated with British universities. And only one was a citizen of an African country -- David Western of Kenya. The final report listed 36 contributors, of whom four were African; none of these four had his name on any of the papers in the report.</p>
        <p>AN ELEPHANT SPENDS 16 HOURS A DAY eating, and an average adult bull of six tons consumes 300 pounds of trees and grass and 50 gallons of water every day. A herd of elephants goes through an area like a slow tornado, snapping off branches and uprooting trees, leaving devastation behind. It is not just a matter of esthetics; the destruction of the woodlands by the elephants has meant the destruction of the habitat for other species.</p>
        <p>From the perspective of giving people who are concerned about wildlife in Africa an accurate and honest basis on which to act, however, the most egregious omission from arguments made by advocates of a ban was recognition of the situation in other parts of Africa, particularly southern Africa. What was happening in East Africa -- particularly Kenya and Tanzania -- where poaching was out of control and the elephant numbers were declining, was not representative of all of Africa.</p>
        <p>In Botswana, in Zimbabwe and in South Africa, the elephant, far from being endangered, has been increasing in numbers. World attention focused on Kenya, but the greatest concentration of elephants in East or southern Africa today is in Botswana -- around 56,000, which is double the number of elephants that existed there a decade ago. Zimbabwe's elephant population, according to the Government, has increased from 30,000 in 1979 to 52,000 today, which is more than double Kenya's elephant population, and Zimbabwe is considerably smaller in area. In South Africa, which has the best-run wildlife department on the continent, the elephant population has remained stable and poaching has been negligible.</p>
        <p>Even in parts of Kenya there are too many elephants. It is true that Kenya's elephant population has declined sharply, to about 20,000. But given the country's growing human population and its need for land on which to grow food, that is the maximum number of elephants the country can tolerate. Richard Leakey, the head of the Kenya Wildlife Service, has said their number will have to be kept between 16,000 and 18,000.</p>
        <p>In Amboseli National Park, where Cynthia Moss does her research, there are only 800 elephants, but that is more than the park can handle. The park has been ravaged by the elephants; it looks like someone has dropped napalm on it, the trees dead or dying. Because of the loss of their habitat to the elephants, there are fewer impala, giraffes, bushbabies and monkeys; kudus, bushbuck and genet have disappeared. Everyone agrees, including Moss and Leakey, that the number of elephants must be reduced or at least controlled. Leakey is hoping that some method of birth control for elephants will be developed. But if it isn't, he is prepared to take a more radical step than selling ivory from a few elephants. "If we cannot control the numbers by any other method, we will have to cull," he told me in August. That would be far more controversial than selling ivory, because it involves killing entire elephant families.</p>
        <p>The ivory-ban advocates in the yearlong debate prior to the decision at Lausanne conveniently neglected to mention these facts about the situation in southern Africa and about there being too many elephants in Kenya, and they weren't generally known to the public during the ivory-ban crusade. Paul Schindler, president of the African Wildlife Foundation, wrote to officials from W.W.F. who were criticizing the "urgent memorandum" as being emotional and misleading: "None of us may like the hyperbole that has insinuated itself into the direct-mail business, but Americans are all too familiar with it. A random sampling of U.S. direct-mail appeals will inform you that the last rhinos alive now are headed toward extinction, or that your children's children will have to learn about whales, pandas, etc. from books, because none will exist unless you send in some dollars."</p>
        <p>Schindler noted that when he had come on as the African Wildlife Foundation's president, he had been given some friendly and collegial advice by Russell Train, who had founded the group and later, after serving as head of the United States Environmental Protection Agency, became the president of the World Wildlife Fund in Washington, where he is currently chairman. The direct mail fund-raisers at the fund had advised Train that although he wrote very well, it would be best if he let the fund-raising specialists write the letters and he would just sign them, Schindler said.</p>
        <p>"He complied," he added, "and those ghostwritten letters have raised millions."</p>
        <p>In essence, Schindler's argument was: Yes, we may be guilty of using hyperbole to raise money, but everyone does it. It was the only defense he had, and it was revealing, unintentionally, about the conservation game, where raising money is often more important than the truth or good conservation.</p>
        <p>Raymond Bonner has lived in Africa for the past four years. This article is adapted from "At the Hand of Man: Peril and Hope for Africa's Wildlife," to be published in April by Alfred A. Knopf.</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 28, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in The Times Magazine on Feb. 7 about efforts to protect elephants misstated amounts spent by the International Wildlife Coalition for preservation in 1988. In the fiscal year that began on May 1, 1988, it spent $52,370 on elephants, $34,757 on kangaroos, $40,841 on sea turtles, $72,727 on large whales and $1,233,932 on its whale adoption project, according to the group's financial statement. (The figures were not $11,000 for elephants and $120,000 for whales.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 28, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article in The Times Magazine on Feb. 7 about efforts to protect elephants misstated amounts spent by the International Wildlife Coalition for preservation in 1988. In the fiscal year that began on May 1, 1988, it spent $52,370 on elephants, $34,757 on kangaroos, $40,841 on sea turtles, $72,727 on large whales and $1,233,932 on its whale adoption project, according to the group's financial statement. (The figures were not $11,000 for elephants and $120,000 for whales.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Raymond Bonner has lived in Africa for the past four years. This article is adapted from "At the Hand of Man: Peril and Hope for Africa's Wildlife," to be published in April by Alfred A. Knopf.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
