<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where the Bay Meets the Sea, Thoughts of a Life in Space</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="649998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="ENCOUNTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNCAN, ERIKA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREY, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DE1F3EF937A25752C1A965958260" item-length="2785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where the Bay Meets the Sea, Thoughts of a Life in Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIKA DUNCAN;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNCAN, ERIKA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"EVENTUALLY I would like to think of the earth as a park-like place we could come back to visit from time to time," Jerry Grey, recently the president of the International Astronautical Federation, said to me, with a slight twinkle in his eye. I had stolen a few hours of his time, in between telephone interviews and the relaying of scientific information, as we talked in the upper reaches of his Bridgehampton house on Dune Road, where the bay meets the sea.</p>
        <p>Over the years of his long and varied career in aeronautics and space, Jerry Grey has been chairman of the Congressional Solar Advisory Panel and has served on the Moon Treaty Panel, the Space Nuclear Systems Task Force, the Secretary of Energy's Advisory Board, and as Deputy Secretary General of the United Nations Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Outer Space, to name just a few.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"EVENTUALLY I would like to think of the earth as a park-like place we could come back to visit from time to time," Jerry Grey, recently the president of the International Astronautical Federation, said to me, with a slight twinkle in his eye. I had stolen a few hours of his time, in between telephone interviews and the relaying of scientific information, as we talked in the upper reaches of his Bridgehampton house on Dune Road, where the bay meets the sea.</p>
        <p>Over the years of his long and varied career in aeronautics and space, Jerry Grey has been chairman of the Congressional Solar Advisory Panel and has served on the Moon Treaty Panel, the Space Nuclear Systems Task Force, the Secretary of Energy's Advisory Board, and as Deputy Secretary General of the United Nations Conference on the Peaceful Uses of Outer Space, to name just a few.</p>
        <p>"Although right now much of the cost of travel and building in space is prohibitive, the research is relatively inexpensive," he assures me, explaining that, even with the best of ecological measures and the best use of energy, the problems of sustaining a growing population on earth are insoluble, while the problems of moving into outer space have engineering solutions coming progressively within our grasp.</p>
        <p>"We have only a limited capacity to sustain our current population," he says. "And we cannot keep population stable. We cannot stay still. We must learn all we can about what we need for survival. . . Life is not risk free anywhere. And space is already full of radiation. Out in space we can do a great deal that is dangerous on earth. If we continue to do the things that cause pollution, it is better to do those things in space where the risk is minimal."</p>
        <p>His eyes are flashing excitedly as he explains that "once we have solved the problems of constructing shielding from the radioactivity of space and providing consumables such as water and air, we will be able to build large habitats in space, with parks, swimming pools, everything we now have."</p>
        <p>His whole countenance is animated in the smiling I have so often seen in the faces of scientists working on a certain imaginative and practical level, that joy of being able to actually touch, logically and viscerally, what one was able to envision in the mind.</p>
        <p>Because of the intensity of his belief that "there will come a time when we will have no choice but to expand beyond the planet, if the human race is to survive," he has made himself into a liaison between scientists and the public, scientists and industry, scientists and Capitol Hill. He has written four books meant for consumption by the general public, one of which is designed to be used as a text for young people in high school.</p>
        <p>Even though now at the age of 68 he has formally retired from teaching at Princeton, he continues as a visiting professor there. He never turns down a request for an interview or a television appearance, often working around the clock, sustaining three or four projects at once, working nationally, internationally, wherever he thinks clarification is needed.</p>
        <p>"Of course it would be almost impossible to make Venus habitable," he adds with absolute seriousness. "But Mars could be made livable fairly easily. From an engineering point of view we already know what has to be done. And the moons of Jupiter and Saturn are wonderful places. Some even have atmospheres."</p>
        <p>I watch through the wide and encircling windows how the fog lifts up over the bay that nearly encircles his house, the gray tones becoming the dark green of bluffs pointing seaward, obscured just a minute before, and the gold tones of marsh grasses fading to delicate purples and pinks.  Every little wooden walkway out over the wetlands towards the water needed a special permit, his wife Florence has explained.</p>
        <p>In this third-floor elevation, where there is no clear distinction between window and wall, where there are very few colors but only the natural green of a few subtly placed plants, and the dark natural brown of the dark wood, a few bright ultramarine blues of the blue and white pottery, against a somewhat elliptical expansion of white, I am trying to absorb a world that is so very real to the man who is talking to me, and the line, repeated over and over: "We already have engineering solutions . . . so much has already been proven feasible."</p>
        <p>On a table built into one of the more angular walls is an African cat, from Namibia. On the wall opposite hangs a delicate gray metal sunburst, made by a woman who modeled for Jerry's wife Florence, a fashion illustrator.  Farther away is a simple black structure by Robert Rausch, which, although abstract, gives the distinct impression of an airplane-like creature, with its angular wing-seeming shapes poised gracefully as if for flight, where the spaces that are emptied speak as eloquently as the full.</p>
        <p>In a cubicle beside the living room where we are sitting is the office he shares with his wife, her backlighted drawing board only a few feet away from his desk with his computer, fax and telephone. Since most of his work is done by teleconference, and since he can access his data via notebook computer, he can work anywhere, he explains. But there is something about the coziness of the enclosure, in the midst of all this space, that seems strangely appropriate to me.</p>
        <p>I had hesitated at first to ask too much about our problems here on earth, for I knew that Jerry was one who devoted his whole life to trying to convince people that it was unrealistic not to plan an alternative. I had just returned from Rome, whose warm flesh and sienna-toned stones made me strangely homesick for a beauty and intimacy in the creation of abode that took in the full layering of history and human experience, as Jerry spoke to me of the time when it would be imperative that we begin to move off Earth.</p>
        <p>I had been reading Marguerite Yourcenar's "Memoirs of Hadrian," in which the building of the Pantheon is described, as if through the thinking of Hadrian, another dreamer and expander in his time.</p>
        <p>"My intention had been that this Sanctuary of All Gods should reproduce the likeness of the terrestrial globe and of the stellar sphere, that globe wherein are enclosed the seeds of eternal fire, and the hollow sphere containing all," Yourcenar's Hadrian muses within this layered reconstruction. "The cupola, constructed of a hard but light-weight volcanic stone . . . reveal [ ing ]  the sky through a hole in the center, showing alternately dark and blue."</p>
        <p>I had asked Jerry about solar power, which he heartily approves, and which indeed he himself uses in his Bridgehampton house, and he had told me that "solar energy is fine, but we just don't have enough sunlight to sustain 8 billion people. Out in space we would have limitless sunlight, no night or day."</p>
        <p>I can see with such clarity, suddenly, in this house in the midst of such beauty of earth, and such beauty of struggling sunlight rising up through the fog, the disk of sunlight that Hadrian had described, disappearing each night and reappearing each morning.</p>
        <p>I had asked Jerry whether he would miss the earth, and he of course said yes. But when he is in Florida he doesn't grieve for the bay in Bridgehampton, that he has experienced beauty in many places and in many ways. It is not that he would choose to leave the earth, or to send others to do so, he continued to explain, although he would certainly love to travel in space and to be able to see it. "But there are certain compromises that people always made in order to insure the quality of life."</p>
        <p>And then suddenly we are talking quite seriously about who will go to space when the quality of life on earth gets too impossible. I had been expressing my concern that the poor and the disenfranchised would be the first to be shipped away, although later a friend who reads more science fiction than I do suggested that it would be the other way about, that if ever the earth were to become truly uninhabitable, it would only be the rich and the privileged who would be able to escape.</p>
        <p>In the house where I am sitting and listening and dreaming, and trying to persuade myself that this is not just a dream that will vanish in the blinking of the eye, but that much of what Jerry is speaking about has already been mapped out in clear factual detail, thinking, and perhaps it is true, that solar collectors in space would be a good idea, and that indeed maybe we could bring some of our more badly polluting industries into space, my eye wanders. I think for a moment of something I have read about the disjunction between the eye's experience and the body's experience in outer space, how, in conditions of micro-gravity there will be many strange adjustments to be made.</p>
        <p>"If we are not prepared to move beyond the planet, we will close in upon ourselves and die," Jerry repeats. And now all playfulness has vanished from his voice.</p>
        <p>And did he think that we would survive? I ask softly.</p>
        <p>"Yes absolutely," he says. There would be mistakes, of course, even terrible mistakes, as we explored alternative solutions. Such disasters as flooding or the greenhouse effect were inevitable. "But none of these would be race-threatening." There would also be "the dangers of galactic cosmic radiation, high speed particles coming from stars," that would be encountered in traveling between space stations, although "it would be possible to shield the space stations and habitats themselves with lunar materials."</p>
        <p>I had put off almost until the end my questions about the now moment and all of the suffering on Earth, partly because they were so universal they seemed almost understood, partly because I knew how deeply Jerry believed that money spent for research is not merely a luxury, but a deep, future-thinking necessity.</p>
        <p>In his way of looking at things, space exploration would actually be a way of supporting humanitarian causes down here, he patiently explained when finally I did ask, and he cited as an example the satellite communications program, which started with a relatively small governmental outlay and then quickly became privatized so that now it is more than paying for itself in tax revenues that can be applied to AIDS research, education, medicine and housing, telling me that it is his hope that an increase in the industrial use of space could further support our needs.</p>
        <p>As we speak we are trying to find a meeting place within my conviction that a species able to adjust its "nature" to a new life in space should also be able to find the largeness within to stop living destructively, that we ought to be able to use our super-powered brains to find workable political and ecological solutions to what threatens to destroy us and the planet, and Jerry's insistence that even with the most careful ecological measures, we still would not have enough resources to sustain ourselves, his insistence that exploration is the life force that propels us. We are trying to find a common ground in our experience of the human being as a flexible, self-creating creature, something we both very much believe, although our definitions of where this flexibility should lie are almost diametrically opposed.</p>
        <p>As we move into the political arena he tells me that "for 40 years we worried about the two super powers destroying the earth with nuclear weapons in their struggle against one another. Now the Russians and the Americans are working together." He tells me that at conferences of the International Astronautical Foundation, which he helped to found and which he headed for a while, "every year 1,500 people show up, working together on an international basis.  There are 100 different groups from 40 different countries . . . It has to be global," he says.</p>
        <p>Because part of me is beginning to come along on this journey, and to wonder if it is possible to take some of the space program without accepting it all, I am hesitant to ask whether Jerry still supports the Stars Wars program, even after the end of the Cold War, which allows him to say that "our government is lagging in making military cuts."</p>
        <p>When I finally do ask, Jerry tells me that it is his feeling that "the starving people in the former Soviet republics may have no choice but to sell their nuclear weapons to wealthy terrorists," and that it is more important than ever, with the new kind of world cooperation, to provide protection against terrorist acquisition of nuclear arms.</p>
        <p>For a moment or two once again, I try to turn the conversation to why human beings, so capable in science, cannot figure out equally brilliant solutions in social science, how ahead in a way our minds are over our hearts.  But Jerry, so deeply immersed in his own field, feels that he must leave that thinking for others.  Father a Physician</p>
        <p>Jerry began as a very little boy, making model airplanes on the floor of his father's doctor's office on Bedford Avenue in Brooklyn, "not making them very well, and being frustrated by the balsa wood." He had decided early on that he didn't want to be a medical doctor like his father.  His mother was a mathematician, he told me, although never formally trained. It was in her playing of bridge, by an internal system of computing the odds and probabilities, that she first opened to him the door to mathematical reasoning. His sister, who is 7 years older than he is, was one of the first female engineers in the United States, and worked as a designer of aircraft. She had started out as a mathematician, and went on to be a statistician. When, through a variety of contingencies, she applied for a job as an aeroengineer, she had no background, but she quickly learned.</p>
        <p>By then Jerry himself was also in aeronautics. But the road there had not been direct. At the time of his going to college, Cornell did not offer a degree in aeronautics, so he took his baccalaureate in mechanical engineering, and his master's later in engineering physics. However, early on he was able to see aeronautics as the field to be in if you really wanted to do things that pushed back frontiers. "It was the field also that presented the hardest problems to solve, the place where everything came together -- electrical and chemical engineering, chemistry, physics and civil engineering, structures and mechanics -- in a way that tied everybody together."</p>
        <p>As Jerry talks, I am conscious of the strong sense of community he feels with others in his field. "There are only between 2,000 and 2,500 people doing this kind of work in the world, so that 15 years ago I probably knew half of them personally," he says. "When I started teaching at Princeton at the age of 25, half of the students in the aerospace department were from overseas. Many went back to their countries, so that whenever I would travel I would run into them. I would learn through seeing what they had set up in their countries . . . Long before detente, long before the current situation, there was a feeling of camaraderie, and of sharing discoveries, the scientific sides of which were discussed openly."</p>
        <p>There is something calm and remarkably stable about the demeanor of a scientist that we rarely will find in that of an artist, something untroubled and ready to take the next step. There is a way also of balancing the possible and the impossible without much outward frustration that has never ceased to fascinate me, even as I talk to Jerry about the sense of mastery he so clearly emanates.</p>
        <p>And I notice that even though we have been talking for several hours without stopping, he is, if anything, more animated, rather than tired, that he has about him the same joy and relaxation that seems to come from applying himself around the clock to his work.</p>
        <p>"I never take a formal vacation," he says, describing his often 20-hour-long work day, "and I am on vacation all the time. If I take four hours off in the middle of the day to play tennis, I work the extra four hours at night." And he does take four hours off, almost every day, to play tennis, he adds. I have also heard, through the grapevine, that he and his wife are quite pros in ballroom dancing.</p>
        <p>He and his wife, Florence, have similar rhythms, he says, both operating on deadlines, but both making their own hours. It doesn't matter how much he is doing, he never hesitates to take on a new project or to meet a new deadline, as he shuttles back and forth between Bridgehampton and Princeton, Washington and New York City, Key Biscayne, Fla., or revisits the cities all over the world in which the many conferences that he attends are held, altering his rhythms slightly depending on whether it is winter or summer, but never staying still.  ENCOUNTERS Erika Duncan is an essayist and novelist who lives in Sag Harbor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Erika Duncan is an essayist and novelist who lives in Sag Harbor.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
