<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DB113CF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>APOCALYPSE THEN</p>
        <p>About 150 years ago, the Second Coming of Christ and the end of the world were believed to be imminent and simultaneous realities by hundreds of thousands of Americans.</p>
        <p>The prediction was made by William Miller, a New Englander with his own interpretation of the Bible, who was convinced that the events would occur between March 1843 and March 1844. His crusade across the country began in 1831, thus allowing sufficient time for people to prepare themselves.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>APOCALYPSE THEN</p>
        <p>About 150 years ago, the Second Coming of Christ and the end of the world were believed to be imminent and simultaneous realities by hundreds of thousands of Americans.</p>
        <p>The prediction was made by William Miller, a New Englander with his own interpretation of the Bible, who was convinced that the events would occur between March 1843 and March 1844. His crusade across the country began in 1831, thus allowing sufficient time for people to prepare themselves.</p>
        <p>A re-creation of his unusual mission will be presented at the Connecticut Historical Society in Hartford on Tuesday at 8 P.M. It will feature a dramatic account by Gary Wait, a society staff member, and Jean Smith, an actress, demonstrating Miller's sincere commitment to his cause, and the ridicule that dogged him in spite of his theory' wide acceptance.</p>
        <p>In the belief that material goods would no longer be needed, some farmers left their crops unharvested and people settled debts by giving away their possessions, including a house in one instance.</p>
        <p>Admission will be $4, students $2. The address is 1 Elizabeth Street and the phone number is 236-5621. SOLAR HOME TOUR</p>
        <p>Four passive-solar homes will be open on Saturday from noon to 5 P.M. in Middefield, Durham, Middletown and Wallingford. This will be the 17th Solar Home and Renewable Energy Tour sponsored by the Canton-based People's Action for Clean Energy.</p>
        <p>The houses focus on various technologies. One was built with an earth berm on the north side, large windows on the south side, tiny ones on the east, and air-lock entry and compact fluorescent lighting.</p>
        <p>Another house appears to be an 1800's post-and-beam Colonial, but it is of recent construction and full of energy- and water-saving devices, as are the two other homes. Window quilts, photovoltaic panels that power lights, television, vacuum cleaners and other household appliances, and climate-sensitive tree plantings are some of the elements that cut energy use and monthly bills.</p>
        <p>An exhibition of solar uses and a tag sale of environmental products will be held at the Independent Day School in Middlefield. Tickets and a self-guided tour map will be $12, available on Saturday at It's Only Natural Restaurant, Main Street, Middletown, or call 693-4813 or 693-4664 for tickets, more information and directions. SOUNDS OF MUSIC</p>
        <p>Alvin Lucier, professor of music at Wesleyan University and a pioneer in the use of sound and electronics in musical composition, will participate in a program today at the Yale Art Gallery in New Haven at 3 P.M.</p>
        <p>Performing on electronic instruments, Mr. Lucier will explore the phenomena of sound waves reflected by Richard Serra's sculpture "Stacks," assisted by Hildegarde Kleeb on piano and Roland Dahinden on trombone.</p>
        <p>His sound installations have been exhibited at the Museum of Modern Art and the Whitney Museum of American Art in Manhattan, Real Art Ways in Hartford, at Wesleyan and in Europe and Asia. The gallery is on Chapel Street at York and admission is free.</p>
        <p>Gallery visitors through March 15 may view the recent paintings and sculpture of David von Schlegell, a professor of art at Yale who died last October.</p>
        <p>The son of the Impressionist painter William von Schlegell, and teacher of many professional artists, Mr. von Schlegell painted single-color panels since his retirement in 1990, which were a departure from his style.</p>
        <p>Mr. von Schlegell received numerous awards for sculpture and his work is in the collections of several museums including the Rhode Island School of Design, the Albright-Knox Gallery in Buffalo and the Whitney in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Gallery hours are Tuesday through Saturday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday from 2 to 5; admission is free. ON LOCATION IN STAMFORD</p>
        <p>Films shot in part or entirely in Stamford have been collected for screening free of charge at the Stamford Historical Society through March 14. "Boomerang," Elia Kazan's 1947 drama with Dana Andrews, will be shown today at 2 P.M. Longtime Stamford residents will recognize West Main Street and areas of downtown as they once were.</p>
        <p>Scenes from "The Cardinal," directed in 1963 by Otto Preminger, were filmed in St. John's Church. It will be shown on Tuesday at 12:30 P.M. and runs for three hours. "Horror of Party Beach," a 1959 thriller shot at Cummings and West Beaches, will be part of a double bill with "Curse of the Living Corpse" on Wednesday at 1 and 2:30.</p>
        <p>"Scenes From a Mall" (1991) with Woody Allen and Bette Midler was filmed in the Stamford Town Center and will be shown on Saturday at 2 P.M. The society is at 1508 High Ridge Road and more information may be obtained by calling 329-1183. IRISH SONG AND DANCE</p>
        <p>Cuchullan, a six-member ensemble of traditional Irish singers, instrumentalists and step dancers, will perform on Saturday at 8 P.M. in the Norwalk Community-Technical College Theater, 188 Richards Avenue.</p>
        <p>The founder and 10-time Irish national fiddle champion, Seamus Connolly, named the group after a mythical Irish hero.</p>
        <p>The performance will include a discussion of the history of Irish music; among the selections are two works by Turloch O'Carolans, a blind harpist who traveled throughout Ireland in the 16th century playing his own compositions.</p>
        <p>Tickets are $12, $6 for children. Call 857-7271 for reservations or more information. THEY SHRINK HORSES</p>
        <p>All those inanimate animals at the New England Carousel Museum in Bristol will provide inspiration for a children's workshop in miniature animal-making with papier-mache. Participants must be at least 7 years old, and the classes will be conducted from 1 to 3 P.M. on four Saturdays beginning this week. The fee is $25, which includes materials.</p>
        <p>The museum, at 95 Riverside Avenue, is open Wednesday through Saturday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday from noon to 5. Admission is $4, elderly people $3.50, children $2.50. Call 585-5411 for more information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
