<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Growing</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Men's Fashions of The Times Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="636821"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAIR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUBENSTEIN, HAL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D8133BF935A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="2016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Growing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">by Hal Rubenstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RUBENSTEIN, HAL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I sat there expounding on new directions, new dreams, new goals. My sister wasn't listening. She wasn't even looking at me. Actually, she was looking at me, right at me, in fact, but not in the eye. "You have a hair growing out of the top of your cheek," she said. "Huh?" I replied without comprehension. "A long, golden, brownish hair, like the kind on your head, but it's on your face. Get rid of it," she snapped. "Where? Show me," I declared. I started to pull randomly. "I can't see it. You do it." "No way," said she. "You're my sister. Do it!" I demanded in official big-brother tones.</p>
        <p>She reached over, yanked the hair from just below my cheekbone, flicked it away and then flailed with an "ucch," as if she'd jerked her hand out of a Roach Motel. "Don't let it come back," she groused in best little-sister tones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I sat there expounding on new directions, new dreams, new goals. My sister wasn't listening. She wasn't even looking at me. Actually, she was looking at me, right at me, in fact, but not in the eye. "You have a hair growing out of the top of your cheek," she said. "Huh?" I replied without comprehension. "A long, golden, brownish hair, like the kind on your head, but it's on your face. Get rid of it," she snapped. "Where? Show me," I declared. I started to pull randomly. "I can't see it. You do it." "No way," said she. "You're my sister. Do it!" I demanded in official big-brother tones.</p>
        <p>She reached over, yanked the hair from just below my cheekbone, flicked it away and then flailed with an "ucch," as if she'd jerked her hand out of a Roach Motel. "Don't let it come back," she groused in best little-sister tones.</p>
        <p>I'm over 40. It'll be back.</p>
        <p>No matter how commercials rhapsodize and prophesy about the prospect of bouncy follicles shimmering with life, the only field of dreams they're praising is the batch that springs forth around the top of your head (which, by the way, is as dead as rope). Unfortunately, hair is capable of sprouting about anywhere else, and the older you get, the more inventive and invasive growth patterns become. You can wax your shoulders and wear socks, but what about that other stuff emanating from your kisser? All you probably know is what dad taught you about shaving. Your problem begins there.</p>
        <p>How Are You Fixed for Blades? Remember Gunilla Knutson? If you don't, your father does. She was this Amazonian Scandinavian blonde appearing on TV each time this guy shaved with Noxzema. "Take it off. Take it all off," she'd purr in Nordic tones, as he flipped a razor across his cheek as if it were scooping up warm ice cream. A splash of water and two slaps of after-shave later, Gunilla was stroking the dimpled fellow's smooth-as-iced-vodka chin, languorous as herring in his lap.</p>
        <p>See anyone cooing over your shoulder? Who wants to watch something so bloody, scarring, time-consuming and ultimately fruitless? If that's not bad enough, there is no other regimen in a man's life so ruled by myth. Your dad may be a great guy, but he probably knows as much about his face as he does Scandinavian blondes. And the key to a great shave is proper skin care.</p>
        <p>If time were on your side, you'd be shaving in the evening, when your face is oilier, softer, and you've got time, and your skin could heal while you sleep. But since most men react to radical changes in grooming habits the way high school students greet a substitute teacher, we'll play it your way. This is how you get a great shave.</p>
        <p>1. Start in the evening, anyway. While you're asleep, your face rubs on sheets probably laundered in detergent. Steam heat parches skin of whatever moisture hasn't already been absorbed by the pillowcase. Meanwhile, the better the condition of your skin, the better your shave. Especially in winter, sleep with a humidifier on in the bedroom. And apply a moisturizer before bed. Oh, come on. You don't have to look white and greasy like Gladys Kravitz did spying on Darrin and Samantha each night in "Bewitched." A good moisturizer is absorbed in minutes. No one will know. And you may be surprised by how cool it is to wake up with your face not feeling like the sports section.</p>
        <p>2. Shaving is taking a knife to your skin and ripping some of it off. Plain enough? You're actually exfoliating the top layer, which is good, and one of the reasons why men's skin, though twice as tough as women's, ages less quickly. However, before giving this surface peel a chance to heel, you do it all over again. Scrape your elbow or burn your hand, and you baby it. Treat your face the same way. Anything harsh or full of chemicals, waxes, alcohols, perfumes, has no business being anywhere near that mug.</p>
        <p>Drugstore shelves are filled with what's to shave with. Considering the contents of most of them, you're better off using hair conditioner. "A razor should glide across your beard. You should be able to do it with your eyes closed," insists Linda Silver, founder and president of Roy, a company in Studio City, Calif., that produces a premium shaving line. But rather than encourage investing in a quality product, elders and ad agencies have brainwashed us with a host of faux axioms: Use hotter water. Shave in different directions. Change the blade. Stretch your skin with the other hand.</p>
        <p>a. Never shave with scalding water. It breaks capillaries. It dries skin. Cuts happen more frequently. Either steam your face, place a warm washcloth on it, use a moisturizing scrub to soften skin and stand the beard up, or rub in scalp oil. Boiling water is for coffee.</p>
        <p>b. Use a superior shave cream. One face is the allotment from Portion Control. Make it last. Spend a few bucks. This would sound corny if Wilford Brimley said it, but you will be amazed by the difference. Glycerin, chamomile, aloe vera, almond oil and allantoin -- these are the kinds of ingredients to look for.</p>
        <p>Merely applying Roy's World Class Shaving Cream, Kiehl's Ultimate Brushless Shave Cream, Clinique Cream Shave or Men by Geoff Thompson's Licorice Shave (anise is a natural antiseptic) offers a novel pleasure in shaving. Start, and the blade glides, the way Gunilla likes it.</p>
        <p>c. Don't pull on your skin. "I've watched men yank and tug, making faces like it's martial arts," confides Jami Morse von Heidegger, president and chief executive officer of Kiehl's Since 1851, a skin-care company in New York City. "All it does is promote age lines." Adds Silver: "It breaks elasticity so skin sags." Be gentle. Pretend someone else is shaving you, though not Sweeney Todd.</p>
        <p>d. Don't shave against the grain -- you shouldn't have to. "It's like taking a scissor blade to the back side of the ribbon," says Geoff Thompson, owner of the company in Portland, Ore., that bears his name. "The way ribbon curls, that's how you get ingrown hairs."</p>
        <p>e. As soon as your razor tugs, throw it out. Every beard is different. How razors are stored varies. Your razor will tell you how many shaves you get per blade. Avoid disposables. They're like using a pen knife to carve a turkey.</p>
        <p>f. Don't shave in a magnifying mirror. Face Fact: You have a beard. Try to shave too close and you're going to irritate your skin badly. A regular mirror is fine. What you see is what they get.</p>
        <p>g. Take your time. Screw this up and it doesn't matter what suit you put on.</p>
        <p>3. Now that you've attacked and you're one big surface wound, what did dad tell you to apply? After-shave -- alcohol of the lowest kind, combined with skin-irritating, synthetically made fragrance that you're going to slap on until it stings like hell. What a man! What a jerk. Are you crazy? "If I gave you toothpaste to brush your teeth and it burned, would you use it again?" asks Silver. "That sting is nature's way of saying 'don't do this to me.' " Never put alcohol on your face. Never put fragrance on it. Soothe it. You just hurt it. Once again, you benefit from a product employing premium ingredients: aloe vera gel, camphor, calendula, gentian, allantoin, lemon extract, clove, even marsh mallow. Products that contain combinations of these -- Kiehl's herbal toners, Roy's blissful alcohol- and fragrance-free after-shave, Men's Lemon Moisture Gel -- stave off redness, which actually is due more to the after-shave than the shave, and minimize bumps. Should you cut yourself, stay away from irritating styptic pencils. A spot of cleansing or clay masque works in minutes. Or just use a bit of tissue and be patient.</p>
        <p>4. Use a moisturizer during the day. "The biggest myth is that men don't need skin protection," says von Heidegger. "It's ridiculous. Everyone these days needs it. The ozone layer depletion. Pollution. Sunscreens are no longer an indulgence. All of these affect your skin, which affects your beard. Protect yourself." By the way, stroke moisturizer on upwards. Gravity is taking care of the other direction.</p>
        <p>Man Wasn't Meant to Shave. But the reason many do is because most men's beards and mustaches have a texture closer to that of their pubic hair than what's on their head. "The coarser, curlier and tighter the beard, the more problems you have," says Von Heidegger. Silver explains: "The skin underneath doesn't get to breathe. It perspires, you eat, the wind is drying -- before you know it, that beard's real itchy." And if you're itchy, think how it feels to someone else. Trimming a beard is a process of trial and frustrating error -- your haircutter should show you how -- but maintenance is easier. Shampoo your beard with a mild non-detergent shampoo, no soap. Always condition it. Roy and Keihl's both have products specifically for softening beards and massage oil for the scaliness that develops on the skin underneath. Because of such dryness, don't overshampoo. "Americans overcleanse," claims von Heidegger. If your hair is squeaky clean, you've gone too far. Twice a week for a beard is enough. But condition it each time you wet it. And groom your beard more often than you do your hair. If you can't run your fingers through it, why would anyone else want to?</p>
        <p>How Can You See? It's So Dark in There. Your best friends won't tell you. And they should. Because even braidable nose hairs aren't always easy to spot. By you, anyway. The best way to prevent the start of a second-tier mustache is to pinch your nostrils and pull up, and see what's wafting in the magnifying mirror. Getting rid of them is not nearly as much fun. A coward's way out is offered by battery-operated nose-hair clippers, like the ones Panasonic has put out. They'll eliminate finger-pointing, but they really only give a buzz cut. Small barber scissors are better, but you have to practice; you need a flair. Tweezers are certainly effective, but because of the sensitivity of the area, you risk severe nose infections, which, should they occur, will insure you look real attractive. The smartest compromise is baby scissors, the ones with the rounded ends on the blades, so you can go at it with more determination than skill. Even then, it will still hurt and annoy, so clip when you're alone. The children shouldn't hear such language.</p>
        <p>Can You Say That Again, Please? If you got the hair out of your ears, they wouldn't have to. One of the most distinctive signs of growing venerable is the random harvest suddenly atop and inside your ear. For the former, you do need a magnifying mirror, a razor and some shave cream. However, don't ever cut hair you can't see. Ask your haircutter to trim what's in your ears. Don't move.</p>
        <p>Unfurrow That Brow and Smile. What if you can't? Now, if you like it like that, live and be well. Otherwise, you should wax the small space between the eyes, a less painful process than tweezing, and lasting longer and less risky than shaving. Another sign of dotage is the surprise eyebrow hair corkscrewing like wisteria up your forehead. Tweeze it or razor-cut it. If brows are merely growing more unruly and you're averse to minor surgery, a little lip balm, eye balm or petroleum jelly will arch them back into place. The latter two also are great on lashes after skiing or anytime excessive wind makes them dry and itchy. "I have no scientific proof for this," admits von Heidegger, "but I swear eye balm makes them grow fuller and thicker. At the very worst, you're moisturizing your eyelashes. At the very best, you're getting sexier. And any man who says he doesn't care about having sexy lashes is lying."</p>
        <p>A What? "Men's faces tend to be oilier, have larger pores, have more ingrown hairs," says von Heidegger. "They also don't acknowledge their stress, and stress dries out the skin, which then gets irritated shaving." The solution? Facials. "Men actually need them more than women," she adds. Besides, a good facial technician can help you with blackheads, unruly eyebrows, nose hairs, and especially the occasional freaky hair that pops out of the middle of your face. But then, that's why God made little sisters. Though that's not why he made Gunilla Knutson.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
