<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Study Challenges Theory on Climate Change</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="654825"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE AGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE AGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREENLAND</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, WALTER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greenland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Greenland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D7173DF93AA35751C1A965958260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Study Challenges Theory on Climate Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER SULLIVAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, WALTER</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Dec. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New research casts doubt on a much publicized analysis of ice extracted from the Greenland ice sheet that seemed to show rapid fluctuations of climate during the warm period that preceded the last ice age, from 115,000 to 135,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>The earlier findings, announced in July, seemed to suggest that climactic changes in the current warm period, which began 10,000 years ago, could also be far more rapid -- in spans of decades or less -- than had been thought if the climate gets as warm as it was then.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New research casts doubt on a much publicized analysis of ice extracted from the Greenland ice sheet that seemed to show rapid fluctuations of climate during the warm period that preceded the last ice age, from 115,000 to 135,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>The earlier findings, announced in July, seemed to suggest that climactic changes in the current warm period, which began 10,000 years ago, could also be far more rapid -- in spans of decades or less -- than had been thought if the climate gets as warm as it was then.</p>
        <p>Both the earlier findings and the new ones utilize data on ice layers from two holes drilled through the Greenland ice shelf to bedrock, two miles below the surface. In the first report, the data from each core were considered separately; in the new report, the data were compared.</p>
        <p>The comparison, reported here today by participants in the drilling projects, seems to show completely different climate changes in the layers of ice nearest the bottom. The Culprit? Bent Ice</p>
        <p>The explanation proposed by the researchers is that the lower part of the ice sheet, dating from after about 95,000 years ago, was bent and otherwise altered by flow. Some dust layers in the ice are tilted more than 20 degrees, and evidence for such alterations was found more than 1,800 feet from the bottom, even though radar has shown the bedrock to be relatively smooth.</p>
        <p>The researchers reported evidence that some layers may have been bent or pushed on top of one another, but they did not explain how that could have happened.</p>
        <p>Dr. Willi Dansgaard of the University of Copenhagen, a leader of one drilling project, said it was difficult to imagine what effect under the ice could have caused such changes 1,800 feet above the bottom. Compounding the mystery, he said in an interview, is the discovery that the bottom layers of ice, totaling 225 feet, are flat and seemingly undisturbed.</p>
        <p>It would appear that "something peculiar" happened during the interval between the last two ice ages, Dr. Dansgaard told the fall meeting of the American Geophysical Union here.</p>
        <p>He also said that data from the two ice cores ruled out earlier theories that the Greenland ice melted between those ice ages. It is known that worldwide sea levels rose more than 30 feet above today's levels during that period, but the rise could be explained, at least in part, by heavy melting of Antarctic ice.</p>
        <p>The original study of the ice cores showed what was taken as evidence of radical "flickers" in climate in the 20,000 warm years between the last two ice ages, and it was this that the same researchers questioned today.</p>
        <p>The present warm period has been relatively stable, but the report of previous wild fluctuations led to concern that they might recur in this one. In such an event, farmers might not have time to adjust to altered growing conditions and coastal cities would have to deal with rapidly rising sea levels.</p>
        <p>The revised interpretation was reported both here and in the current issue of Nature.  Details of Drilling</p>
        <p>One of the drilling projects, known as GRIP, conducted by a consortium of European institutions, began at the summit of the Greenland ice sheet at 10,500 feet above sea level and reached bedrock after extracting 9,938 feet of ice. The bottom layers are believed to have formed from snow that fell 150,000 years ago. The other project, 20 miles to the west, was by a team of American institutions and was known as GISP-2. It reached a similar depth and also bored five feet into the underlying rock.</p>
        <p>Comparison of ice from the two holes to a depth of 8,858 feet covering the past 95,000 years, showed the same record of sudden climate changes with astonishing uniformity. But study of the deeper ice shows little conformity between the cores.</p>
        <p>To minimize flowing that might distort the ice layers, GRIP was drilled on what is now the summit of the ice sheet, atop the thickest ice in the Northern Hemisphere. It was assumed that the ice would slowly and uniformly flow seaward. GISP-2 was drilled at a site 100 feet lower, but near enough the summit, it was thought, to minimize flow.  Hope for the Future</p>
        <p>Some of today's speakers said they hoped that layers in deeper sections of the two cores could be still correlated and that ancient climates could be determined by using the varying chemistry of dust in the two cores. Much hope also rests on drilling in Antarctica, particularly at the Russian interior station at Vostok, which rests on ice whose base is estimated to be 500,000 years old. Because precipitation in the Antarctic interior is meager, the annual layers at Vostok are very thin, making for a longer but less detailed record.</p>
        <p>Scientists have determined the climate of each period represented by a layer in the extracted Greenland cores, and have done so in in several ways. Perhaps the most dramatic conformity between the cores has been in the measurements of electrical conductivity. The winter ice tends to be dustier, perhaps because the weather was windier, making the snow more alkaline and hence a poor conductor of electricity.</p>
        <p>As pointed out by Dr. G. S. Boulton of the University of Edinburgh in an accompanying commentary in Nature, dust layers are a clue to storminess of the earth. Also measured in the ice are two forms of oxygen; the amount of a lighter form of oxygen relative to a heavier form is assumed to indicate the climate temperature when the snow fell.</p>
        <p>While comparative study of the cores has shown uncertainty about the earliest climatic record, it has strengthened the belief that there were sudden changes throughout the past ice age. Each of these was usually a sudden warming within a few years, followed by slow cooling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
