<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports Fans, Behold the Devil's Head</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="610386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TORBORG, JEFF</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D81431F932A15756C0A965958260" item-length="847" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports Fans, Behold the Devil's Head</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LIPSYTE, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ultimately, Jeff Torborg was done in by Pat Riley's hair. Not by an outfielder's insecurity or a general manager's ineptitude or the media's ravenous appetite, although he took the rap for all that, too. Torborg was fired because the competition in New Jock City has become an interdisciplinary battle royal and Torborg was compared with a man who is perceived to have given the Knicks collective character, to have squeezed a handful of loose change into a golden coin.</p>
        <p>So why couldn't Torborg have done the same thing, ask the querulous voices of think-tank radio? Why couldn't Torborg, with basically better material than Riley -- at least on paper -- teach, motivate, boot, abuse, do whatever was necessary to make those overripe adolescents earn their amazing salaries? Those are good questions in New Jock City, now that cross-sports comparisons are mandatory for fandom. With the exception of Patrick Ewing, there are no certified superstars on the Knicks, and even Ewing is not the standard at his position. So if the Knicks beat Chicago, the key will be Coach Riley. Meanwhile, the Mets have Doc Gooden, Bobby Bonilla, Eddie Murray, Howard Johnson, Tony Fernandez, and if they can't even beat Chicago, the key must be Manager Torborg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ultimately, Jeff Torborg was done in by Pat Riley's hair. Not by an outfielder's insecurity or a general manager's ineptitude or the media's ravenous appetite, although he took the rap for all that, too. Torborg was fired because the competition in New Jock City has become an interdisciplinary battle royal and Torborg was compared with a man who is perceived to have given the Knicks collective character, to have squeezed a handful of loose change into a golden coin.</p>
        <p>So why couldn't Torborg have done the same thing, ask the querulous voices of think-tank radio? Why couldn't Torborg, with basically better material than Riley -- at least on paper -- teach, motivate, boot, abuse, do whatever was necessary to make those overripe adolescents earn their amazing salaries? Those are good questions in New Jock City, now that cross-sports comparisons are mandatory for fandom. With the exception of Patrick Ewing, there are no certified superstars on the Knicks, and even Ewing is not the standard at his position. So if the Knicks beat Chicago, the key will be Coach Riley. Meanwhile, the Mets have Doc Gooden, Bobby Bonilla, Eddie Murray, Howard Johnson, Tony Fernandez, and if they can't even beat Chicago, the key must be Manager Torborg.</p>
        <p>This is what passes for logic in New Jock City these days, and I'm not sure it isn't on the money. At some point while I wasn't paying careful attention, in the late 1970's and early '80's, the nature of fandom changed in New York. The dominant sports constituency here no longer considers itself the fans of a particular team, or even of a particular sport. They are SPORTS fans now, actually sports consumers, the target market for an exploding entertainment, apparel and collectibles industry.</p>
        <p>Thirty-six years ago, before this New Jock City was built beside the raging river of run-on seasons, upon the landfill of card shows, under an ozone layer of free-agency and hop along franchises, there were three professional baseball teams, one basketball team, one hockey team and one football team in New York, and most fans defined themselves through their passion for one of those six singular signifiers.</p>
        <p>One was never a "baseball fan" per se (although certain people who guiltily attended Yankee games claimed to be followers of the American League), and one was never, never a "sports fan," a dilettantish pose equivalent to being a culture vulture. One was loudly and proudly the follower of an athletic sect that often had ethnic, religious, geographic, class, even political, overtones: There are 50-something men today, stereotypically Brooklyn-born left-wing lawyers and accountants, who are still making professional decisions against men who admit to having been fans of the baseball Giants in 1951. And there are stereotypically 40-something neo-conservatives from Bronxville in television and advertising whose Baltimore catechism includes Johnny U. and whose beau ideal is Frank Gifford.</p>
        <p>There was something very pure and intense in that fandom, but it became increasingly risky as its loyalty was not returned by the owners and the players. One cannot overestimate the emotional impact of the Dodgers and Giants leaving after the 1957 season. A promise was betrayed. The Mets arrived in 1962, a poor ball club fronted by a manager, Casey Stengel, formerly of the Yankees, who led the media drum-and-bugle corps while the front office shucked the expansion has-beens and created a team from scratch. There was time to build then because the media was desperate and so were the fans. There weren't enough players to interview, there weren't enough bubble-gum cards and caps to buy.</p>
        <p>Now it's a buyers' market for caps, cards, autographs, shirts, rumors, books, lawsuits, and the nine major league teams in New Jock City are always crashing through one another's schedules, news conferences, emotional zones. Maybe the Mets should have waited until the basketball season was over, then hired Pat Riley. It's all leadership, right? Ray Handley, Buddy Harrelson, Stump Merrill, Roger Neilson just weren't Man enough for the job. So fire them. Also fire the front-officers who hired them and the superstars who didn't want to play their best for them.</p>
        <p>And that's fine with us citizens of New Jock City because as SPORTS fans, we have created a psychic safety net to save us when a coach, player, team we have come to care about goes away. Once, when our favorite player failed or our favorite team lost, not only did we feel bad, we felt bad for them. Now, we get angry at them. They didn't perform for us. Well, that's fair enough since we know that they are itching to leave us for a city that offers a more favorable tax abatement, a team that bids more money.</p>
        <p>So, hey, we'll just find someone else to love: Rangers flopped we'll cheer the Isles go Knicks the Yanks are coming on Jets got Boomer maybe L.T. has another season who knows if Dallas Green might just be able to scare Vince Coleman off the golf course and Bobby Bo into adulthood. Could be a team there. If he builds it, we will come.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
