<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gasoline Tax Plan Is Reviving</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="580327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, ALBERT JR (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D81331F931A35752C0A965958260" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gasoline Tax Plan Is Reviving</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President-elect Bill Clinton, who repeatedly criticized Paul Tsongas and Ross Perot in the Presidential campaign for supporting an increase in Federal gasoline taxes, is hearing from a lot of his advisers that it is not such a bad idea after all, and he seems to be warming to the idea.</p>
        <p>"There were a lot of good arguments made for the gas tax," Mr. Clinton said at a news conference after the two-day meeting on the economy that he convened in Little Rock, Ark., in early December. But he added, "No matter what the other merits of the gas tax are, you don't want to load it onto the inequality you already have" in the tax system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President-elect Bill Clinton, who repeatedly criticized Paul Tsongas and Ross Perot in the Presidential campaign for supporting an increase in Federal gasoline taxes, is hearing from a lot of his advisers that it is not such a bad idea after all, and he seems to be warming to the idea.</p>
        <p>"There were a lot of good arguments made for the gas tax," Mr. Clinton said at a news conference after the two-day meeting on the economy that he convened in Little Rock, Ark., in early December. But he added, "No matter what the other merits of the gas tax are, you don't want to load it onto the inequality you already have" in the tax system.</p>
        <p>During the meeting in Little Rock, the President-elect seemed surprised that so many speakers had ignored his campaign position on the issue and called eagerly for higher gasoline taxes. Nation's 'Biggest Luxury'</p>
        <p>"I'm for a gasoline tax as a national security measure to reduce dependence on foreign oil, second as a conservation measure and third as a revenue-raising measure," said Felix G. Rohatyn, an investment banker at Lazard Freres &amp; Company and a speaker at the conference. "The biggest luxury this country indulges in is its overuse of energy."</p>
        <p>The Energy Department estimates that a 50-cent-a-gallon tax increase from the current level of 14.1 cents a gallon would cut gasoline consumption by 10 to 15 percent and would reduce oil imports, currently more than 7 million barrels a day, by 500,000 barrels.</p>
        <p>Recognizing that the issue is fraught with political dangers, Mr. Clinton has stopped short of endorsing the idea outright. But one official on his transition team, who insisted on anonymity, explained why an increase in the gasoline tax has marched back onto Mr. Clinton's agenda. "The primary driver is the numbers they have to deal with to reduce the deficit," he said. "That means everything is on the table."</p>
        <p>Advisers said the fact that Vice President-elect Al Gore backs increased taxes on energy has also nudged Mr. Clinton toward a higher gasoline tax. In addition, Alice M. Rivlin, the nominee for deputy budget director, joined a recent call for a $1-a-gallon increase in gasoline taxes, and Leon E. Panetta, the budget director-designee, has long said such a tax must be considered to rein in the deficit.</p>
        <p>But Lloyd Bentsen, Mr. Clinton's choice for Treasury Secretary and a man with close ties to the oil industry, is not a fan of increased gasoline taxes. Some environmentalists say Mr. Bentsen's opposition, along with that of the oil industry and of millions of drivers, could prevent Mr. Clinton from ever embracing the idea. 'Americans Would Rebel'</p>
        <p>"A large increase in the gasoline tax has a low probability of being enacted because the American people would rebel," said William F. O'Keefe, executive vice president of the American Petroleum Institute. "It's incredibly unpopular outside the Beltway."</p>
        <p>Millions of Americans, as well as the oil industry, loathe the idea of higher gasoline taxes, arguing that they would fall harder on those of modest incomes and would disproportionately hurt Americans in Western states, who often live many miles from the nearest big towns.</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Clinton lambasted higher gasoline taxes as unfair, complaining that they would hit the middle class hardest. But he appears to have reversed course, his advisers say.</p>
        <p>A 50-cent-a-gallon increase would produce about $50 billion a year in revenues, and this would take Mr. Clinton a third of the way toward his goal of cutting the deficit by 50 percent, or $150 billion, in 1996.</p>
        <p>One way Mr. Clinton has said he might consider a gasoline tax increase is in a package with other measures that would make the tax system fairer for the middle class.  One Clinton adviser suggested that such a package could be expected to include higher income taxes on the rich and tax cuts for the middle class and might borrow heavily from Ross Perot's plan to raise gasoline taxes 10 cents a year for five straight years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton says a gasoline tax increase would be regressive, meaning it would consume a larger portion of the income of households earning $25,000 a year than those earning $250,000. But among the ways a Clinton Administration might offset that burden, advisers say, would be to couple a gasoline tax increase with an income tax credit or a reduction in the Social Security payroll tax. Burden in Rural Areas</p>
        <p>Rural Americans will no doubt assert that raising gasoline taxes will be unfair. City residents who rely on mass transit far more than cars would be hurt less than Montana residents who live 75 miles from the nearest large town. The American Petroleum Institute says a 50-cent-a-gallon increase would cost households in Wyoming an additional $1,237 a year and households in New York $501 more on average.</p>
        <p>"This would be a killer for North Dakota," the state's Governor, Edward T. Schafer, said in a telephone interview. "In a rural state, a lot of people depend on their autos not only to get to their jobs but during the harvest season to get supplies, to get parts for their combines. An increase in gasoline taxes would affect people here a lot harder. We just don't have mass transportation."</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that an increased gasoline tax will not be so painful, especially if it is phased in over several years. They note that gasoline prices, after accounting for inflation, are about 40 percent lower than a decade ago. And even after a 50-cent-a-gallon tax increase, prices would be half those in Europe and Japan. France places a tax of about $2.80 a gallon on gasoline, while in Italy the tax is more than $3.50 a gallon. In Japan, the tax is about $1.70 a gallon.</p>
        <p>In the United States, state and Federal taxes represent roughly 25 percent of the price of gasoline, with most states' taxes between 10 cents and 20 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>In Japan, taxes represent 42 percent of the price, and in France, 70 percent. Those countries are, of course, smaller than the United States, and their residents drive less. Americans drive more than 8,000 miles per capita a year, double the level in Europe and more than triple that in Japan.</p>
        <p>"Gasoline taxes will push Americans to buy more fuel-efficient automobiles and to drive less," said Representative Pete Stark, Democrat of California. "It will also help reduce pollution, and it raises a lot of money for education, for medical care for the uninsured, for a lot of things." Carbon Tax Proposal</p>
        <p>Mr. Stark is sponsoring a bill to create a carbon tax, and President Clinton's advisers have suggested that he consider such a tax. A carbon tax would apply to coal, oil and natural gas with the aim of skewing energy use toward sources that produce less carbon dioxide. Many scientists believe that increased carbon dioxide in the atmosphere is causing global warming.</p>
        <p>In the face of President Bush's pledge not to accept new taxes, proposals for gasoline taxes and carbon taxes did not move in Congress last year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
