<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Feeling the Bumps in the Road At the Tokyo Auto Show</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="644377"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAZDA MOTOR CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HONDA MOTOR CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TOYOTA MOTOR CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVIN, DORON P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DE123FF937A15753C1A965958260" item-length="1521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Feeling the Bumps in the Road At the Tokyo Auto Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DORON P. LEVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVIN, DORON P</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1985, visitors to the auto show here were treated to a preview of Honda's new Accord, a car that crossed the Pacific and outsold all American models for three years running. The 1989 show marked the first sighting of Lexus, the Toyota luxury sedan that displaced Cadillacs, Mercedeses and Jaguars from garages of the wealthy.</p>
        <p>The once-obscure Tokyo Motor Show, held every other year, had suddenly become a gallery for the dynamic imagination of Japan's auto industry, whose creations provoked nightmares from Detroit to Turin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1985, visitors to the auto show here were treated to a preview of Honda's new Accord, a car that crossed the Pacific and outsold all American models for three years running. The 1989 show marked the first sighting of Lexus, the Toyota luxury sedan that displaced Cadillacs, Mercedeses and Jaguars from garages of the wealthy.</p>
        <p>The once-obscure Tokyo Motor Show, held every other year, had suddenly become a gallery for the dynamic imagination of Japan's auto industry, whose creations provoked nightmares from Detroit to Turin.</p>
        <p>But a visitor to this year's show, which opened to the public yesterday, could see how that nightmare has become less frightening from an American point of view. With Japanese sales slumping at home and abroad -- a result of the country's recession, a soaring yen and Western retaliation in the form of savvier car design and improved quality -- this year's exhibits are heavy on future technology but light on dramatic new models likely to be sold soon in the United States. Japanese auto makers, to save money, are introducing new models more slowly than during the salad days of the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>Still, a close examination of the exhibits suggests that the car companies already are gearing for better days. They evidently are sure that consumers will buy -- and governments will mandate -- cars that pollute less, consume less energy, are easier to recycle and minimize safety hazards. And despite the strong yen, the Japanese are finding ways to cut costs so new technologies will be affordable. For example, Toyota's just-released annual report, which is handed out at the company's exhibit, brags that engineers are saving money by the once-unthinkable practice of using some parts from last year in next year's models.</p>
        <p>Specifically, the report mentions mirrors that can be used on a number of models, thereby saving the development cost incurred each time a new one is designed.</p>
        <p>The money Toyota saves on new mirrors and the like can be spent toward further development of the EV-50, an experimental electric passenger car on view at the show here. Under California law, by 1998, 2 percent of sales in that state by the biggest-selling auto makers, including Toyota, Honda and Nissan, must be of vehicles that are virtually emission-free.</p>
        <p>"The EV-50 is the most important car here, though the company isn't happy about selling electric cars because our engineers say they don't work very well," said James Olson, senior vice president of Toyota's United States sales subsidiary. Powered by lead acid batteries, the four-seater can reach a top speed of just 72 miles per hour, and it has a range of about 155 miles before recharging, which can take several hours.</p>
        <p>(Toyota kept one crucial new car, called Avalon, under wraps in a studio. The auto maker earlier this month announced it will build the six-seat sedan, which replaces the Cressida, in its Georgetown, Ky., plant in 1995. The car will sell in the United States for about $30,000. "Boring," was the description of one Toyota executive of Avalon's looks. "But I'm too young to be a typical buyer.")</p>
        <p>The Mitsubishi Motors Corporation has addressed the electric vehicle's problem of limited range and power with ESR, a prototype of a "hybrid" car that is powered by batteries but also has a small, efficient, low-polluting gasoline engine. The car runs on its batteries alone or in conjunction with its engine, which doesn't directly power the car but instead is used to charge the batteries.</p>
        <p>With the engine giving a boost to the batteries, the ESR claims a range of more than 620 miles and a top speed of 125 m.p.h. -- superior performance among prototypes developed to comply with California law. The ESR, Mitsubishi believes, could meet California's strict emissions requirement, but for now the company does't plan to use the car's hybrid technology. Instead, it is considering a number of other options, including a different electric car on which it is working.</p>
        <p>For the here and now, Mitsubishi displayed a retracting hardtop version of its 3000 GT sports car to be sold within a year in the United States, built in Long Beach, Calif., jointly with the ASC Corporation of Southgate, Mich. With the touch of a button, the metal and glass roof deployed and retracted smoothly into the trunk -- while gawking viewers snapped pictures furiously.</p>
        <p>The Mazda Motor Corporation alone has staked its bet on hydrogen, rather than electricity, as the nonpolluting energy source that can satisfy environmental concerns. Mazda's HR-X2 prototype claims significantly better range, almost 150 miles, than an earlier hydrogen prototype shown two years ago. One reason the range is still modest is the weight and bulkiness of the equipment needed to safely carry hydrogen, which has an explosive nature. But in terms of speed and acceleration, the HR-X2 performs much like a normal car.</p>
        <p>Unlike almost every other combustible fuel, hydrogen does not produce carbon dioxide, which is blamed for contributing to the greenhouse effect and global warming. Burning hydrogen yields water. How an infrastructure would be built to produce and distribute large amounts of hydrogen for drivers remains a mystery, but Japan's Ministry of International Trade and Industry plans to study the possibilities.</p>
        <p>THE HR-X2's body is made of liquid-crystal polymer, a light and easily recyclable material. Mazda thinks the polymer is sturdy enough to pass crash tests. Moreover, the body swiftly detaches from the HR-X2's metal suspension so its components can be sorted upon retiring the vehicle from operation and disassembling it. European countries, Japan and some states are considering tough regulations that eventually may make crushing or shredding entire cars prohibitively expensive.</p>
        <p>Responding to what it hopes will be more immediate market forces, Mazda unveiled a chic-looking, conventionally powered luxury sedan called the Eunos 800, which soon will appear in American showrooms as the Mazda Millenia. The Eunos 800, meant to compete with Acura, Lexus and Infiniti, is a remnant of Mazda's ill-fated Amati line of luxury cars. Amati was to have been a separate franchise, but it fell to the ax in 1992 due to the high yen and sagging sales of Japanese luxury models.</p>
        <p>THE Honda Motor Company showed its EVX electric car, a version of which it is nearly ready to produce. The headlights are designed to use just a tiny amount of power, and solar cells mounted on the vehicle's roof can recharge the batteries a bit when the sun is out.</p>
        <p>But Nobuhiko Kawamoto, Honda's president, voiced skepticism similar to that expressed by other auto executives. "I don't think it will pay as a business," he told reporters. In other words, he said, Honda and others must be ready to bear the expense of electric vehicles if they want to stay in business in California.</p>
        <p>Honda's FSR (for "future safety research") prototype embodies features that Honda engineers believe may appear in cars around the turn of the century. Headlamps that move and cameras on the nose improve visibility on blind curves and at intersections. Reflective paint on the body makes the car more visible at night, particularly from the side. In Japan the single biggest category of traffic fatalities involves pedestrians, so the research is especially relevant here.</p>
        <p>Subaru, the brand name used by Fuji Heavy Industries, brought a few perky prototypes to the auto show, but the only car that mattered greatly was an actual model for sale, the new Legacy. The car resembled most other Japanese sedans of its size, except for a distinctive scooped-out portion onits hood.</p>
        <p>Fuji lost more than six billion yen in the fiscal year ended March 31; that's $50 million at the rate of exchange then in effect. Without improved United States sales from its new Legacy, most analysts say, Subaru has little chance of hanging on as an independent auto maker in the crowded North American market. In the Japanese tradition, Subaru may well be forced into an arranged marriage with a larger, less financially strapped Japanese car maker.</p>
        <p>The problem is that many Japanese car makers are now financially strapped, while many Western auto makers are on the comeback trial.</p>
        <p>That shift in fortunes has had an impact on the status of the auto show itself. Executives from the West used to arrive here, filled with anticipation and dread, to discover what new bombshells would explode in their faces. But now, "the focus point again is Detroit," said Koichi Amemiya, president of Honda sales in North America.</p>
        <p>Indeed, these days Japanese executives are traveling to shows in the United States and Europe with just as much anticipation and dread as their American counterparts felt upon arrival here not long ago.</p>
        <p>The most talked-about car to debut in a show this year was not a Honda or a Toyota. It was Chrysler's Neon subcompact, which grabbed the spotlight last month -- in Frankfurt. The Neon, which is designed to compete directly with small Japanese cars, isn't even on view here this week, because Chrysler at the moment has no plans to sell it in this country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
