<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Think About Science</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="623760"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAPINEAU, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KITCHER, PHILIP</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D91038F936A15754C0A965958260" item-length="1170" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Think About Science</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Papineau;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PAPINEAU, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE Science Without Legend,  Objectivity Without Illusions. By Philip Kitcher. 421 pp. New York: Oxford University Press.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE Science Without Legend,  Objectivity Without Illusions. By Philip Kitcher. 421 pp. New York: Oxford University Press.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE has had a bad press recently. Not so long ago, scientific progress was cast as the savior of humanity. It was going to cure disease, banish poverty and generate unlimited amounts of cheap nuclear power. But this happy optimism about the power of technology has faded along with many other hopes for modernity. Today science is as likely to be thanked for holes in the ozone layer or for Chernobyl as for any benefits it may have brought humankind.</p>
        <p>This repudiation of technology has been mirrored by a shift in philosophical attitudes to scientific objectivity. Earlier this century, the logical positivists portrayed science as the very model of impartial rationality. Albert Einstein, whose purity seemed to be matched only by his genius, stood as the living icon of this view of science.</p>
        <p>More recently, however, the philosophers have lost faith in scientific virtue. Since the publication of "The Structure of Scientific Revolutions," by Thomas S. Kuhn, just over three decades ago, it has become widely accepted that scientists are as likely to be sinners as saints. Just like the rest of us, they are as much moved by ambition, pride and sectional interest as by any impersonal desire for truth. This has persuaded many contemporary philosophers to reject any idea of scientific truth. Instead, they argue that scientific theories are nothing but stories that happen to suit the interests of the scientific elite.</p>
        <p>Of course, this blank relativism about science is an adolescent aberration. Just as it is fatuous to condemn all modern technology for the undoubted evils of pollution and warfare, so it is puerile to condemn all scientific theories for the human failings of their defenders. So what if Galileo was a career opportunist with a clear eye for his patron's wishes, or Newton a neurotic who was obsessed with alchemy and biblical numerology? As anybody with a smattering of physics knows, there is still overwhelming empirical evidence for the truth of their central claims. It is only those with the sophistication of a post-modern philosophical education who are able to construct arguments against Galileo's law of free fall or Newton's laws of motion.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, there are signs that the philosophical pendulum is now swinging back against relativism. Philip Kitcher is a philosopher of science at the University of California, San Diego, who has already written two widely acclaimed books exposing weaknesses in bad science. In "Abusing Science" (1982) he demonstrated the intellectual poverty of creationism, and in "Vaulting Ambition" (1985) he dismissed the overblown claims of pop sociobiology. Now he has turned to the rather more challenging task of explaining the strengths of good science. In "The Advancement of Science" he makes an important contribution that will enable philosophers once more to give credit to those parts of science where credit is due.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Kitcher's view, the logical positivists and their relativist opponents are the opposite sides of the same coin. The logical positivists glorified science for its supposed conformity to otherworldly standards of purity and rigor. The relativists then condemned it for failing to live up to those standards. Their common mistake was to impose unrealistic standards on science in the first place. In their hands, 20th-century philosophy of science has mimicked the suitor who first idealizes his beloved and then rejects her when he finds out she is a normal woman. In response, Mr. Kitcher has chosen as his epigraph Shakespeare's Sonnet 130: "My mistress, when she walks, treads on the ground: / And yet, by heaven, I think my love as rare / As any she belied with false compare."</p>
        <p>The job of science, Mr. Kitcher argues, is not to hold up an ideal of intellectual purity, but simply to provide an efficient means of uncovering truths about nature. Once we accept this, there is no longer any reason to view the moral failings of scientists as in conflict with the aims of science. Indeed, they may positively foster scientific progress. In one of the most interesting sections of his book, Mr. Kitcher suggests that selfishness may often be an essential ingredient in the pursuit of truth. If scientists were driven by nothing but a pure desire for knowledge, they would have little motive to pursue maverick research strategies that are unlikely to succeed.</p>
        <p>But for scientists who want fame, fortune and Nobel Prizes, it may well be a better bet to try unpopular seams of research than to continue scrabbling around in well-staked-out areas. These greedy individuals can hasten the overall community's access to the truth. For even if individual researchers need to be tempted by worldly rewards to pursue maverick strategies, the small chance they might become lucky can still make it worthwhile for an institution devoted to truth to spare them from more orthodox pursuits.</p>
        <p>This analysis of the virtues of selfishness is just one respect in which Mr. Kitcher's book accommodates points made by post-Kuhnian philosophy of science. Similarly, Mr. Kitcher accepts that the truth in science can often guard itself jealously. In an extended metaphor, he likens major disputes in science to extended wars in which the combatants fight skirmishes on the terrain of specific issues. But Mr. Kitcher, unlike the relativists, does not conclude that victory always goes to the big battalions, to scientific power brokers who can bludgeon their opponents into submission by controlling jobs, journals and funds. Instead, he shows, with the help of examples that stretch from Copernicus to Francis Crick and James Watson, that scientific wars end only when some compelling new line of argument eventually emerges to persuade everybody of the truth of one side.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kitcher's use of historical sources is one of the most attractive features of this book. "The Advancement of Science" is written primarily for professional philosophers, but it contains much for lay readers to enjoy. Books on the philosophy of science are usually dry stuff, filled with rarefied reasoning and technical terms, but Mr. Kitcher keeps his feet firmly on the ground. Without cutting any argumentative corners, he writes about science in a way that will make it recognizable to scientists themselves and explain much about its workings to nonscientists.</p>
        <p>If anybody does find this book difficult, it is more likely to be the professional philosophers of science than interested amateurs. Mr. Kitcher is an original thinker who is proposing a new way of thinking about science. To the general run of philosophical readers, many of his suggestions will seem unfamiliar and wrongheaded. I am sure, however, that they will become familiar enough in due course. For this is a book that is destined to be discussed by all those interested in science for some years to come.</p>
        <p>David Papineau's "Philosophical Naturalism" will be published later this year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Papineau's "Philosophical Naturalism" will be published later this year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
