<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Business Diary/June 20-25</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="617893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D81039F934A15755C0A965958260" item-length="1574" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Business Diary/June 20-25</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hubert B. Herring</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COMPANIES At Empire Blue Cross, Definitely a Week to Forget</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COMPANIES At Empire Blue Cross, Definitely a Week to Forget</p>
        <p>"Enormous uncertainty" -- that's what Otto G. Obermaier, a former United States Attorney hired as an investigator by Empire Blue Cross, saw last week. Translated, that means "a mess." Here's the latest: It seems that even in a world increasingly run by computers, Empire decided it was too much trouble to program its computers properly, so it just paid many claims -- about one in six -- without checking for fraud or duplication. Also, the Manhattan District Attorney has begun a criminal inquiry, and the Senate began its own hearings. Trying to put the past well behind it, Empire decided it didn't make sense to keep paying a $205,000 salary to its top financial officer after sending him packing, so it suspended him without pay. And what does Albert A. Cardone, recently ousted as chairman, say to accusations of mismanagement? They are "but another effort by special interests to discredit me and a fine institution."  G.M. Brings Some Jobs Home  Detroit is moving jobs across the border again, but the United Auto Workers thinks it's just fine. That's because this time the route is reversed, with General Motors shifting some Chevrolet Cavalier production from Mexico to Lansing, Mich. As many as 1,000 jobs will be created, with some to be filled by laid-off workers. It's not that G.M. has forgotten how low Mexican wages are -- just that it has felt a lot of union pressure on exporting jobs, and with the American auto market finally stirring to life, it doesn't want to risk any disruption. And last week G.M. and the U.A.W. began talks on a national contract. T. Rex, 38; Arnold, 15  As the film tycoon Charles Dickens once said, "Expectation $19 million, gross $20 million: result, happiness; expectation $21 million, gross $20 million: result, misery." It was misery indeed at Columbia Pictures after "Last Action Hero" grossed "only" $15.3 million its first weekend. Now, for any mortal film, that's a lot of tickets, but the studio was counting on megahit numbers -- $20 million or so -- for this one. To make it worse, "Jurassic Park" made $38.5 million its second weekend. That settles it: with all his undulating muscles, Arnold Schwarzenegger (the star of "Hero") is no match for a dinosaur. One Company, Indivisible  RJR Nabisco is still mainly a tobacco company, no matter how hard it tries to fine-tune that label. In March it made plans for a separate class of stock linked to its food business, hoping to raise $1.5 billion. But last week, citing poor market conditions, it dropped the plan. One problem is that food company shares are not doing well these days. And in any case, the food shares would still have represented ownership of the whole company, smoke and all. With anti-smoking fists raised nationwide, some may see that as a less-than-healthy investment. Cheeriexes? No, Sounds Funny  General Mills, by daring to tamper with an icon of modern civilization, may just have hit on a way to sell more breakfast cereal. As parents well know, if there are children around, a lot of cereal already winds up scattered around the table, on the floor or in the couch's remotest corners. If a cereal maker can just increase the amount that never reaches the mouth, it will clearly sell more. So General Mills may have had a brainstorm last week when it added X's to its Cheerios, inviting tic-tac-toe games with a grid on the box. What's next? At parties that go flat, the hors d'oeuvres could be shaped like chess pieces, and the cheese board divided into 64 squares. INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Closing the Door on Steel  It's the same old story. The world makes too much of something, and a lot of the excess winds up in the ultimate market, the United States. But the United States, trying desperately to hang onto far more than its fair share of the world's plenty, cries foul and slams the door. And then everyone yells at Washington. Last week it was steel, as the Administration announced steep tariffs on steel from 19 countries, saying they were selling it for less than they charge at home. American steelmakers applauded, speaking of the "egregious distortion" that foreign companies create. But the view abroad was harsh, as one official said steel imports were being treated as "a whipping boy" for America's problems. Meanwhile, the recent optimism on a breakthrough in global trade talks seemed premature, as trade ministers meeting in Tokyo failed to achieve a hoped-for accord on reducing many tariffs and were back to square one. 'Low Point' at Lloyd's of London  Lloyd's of London. It sounds so British, so solid. Its dignified backers are not "investors" but "names." But those "names" came face to face with some awfully undignified numbers last week, when the insurer reported its annual loss (a loss, by the way, for 1990; Lloyd's always allows such a civilized interval). And the deficit was huge -- at $4.3 billion, even worse than expected. The loss is "in every way the low point of Lloyd's history in the last 305 years," said David Rowland, the chairman. And a low point for a lot of those "names," too, who are out of pocket, on average, more than $150,000. When added to previous losses, that's put a big dent in a lot of fortunes. New investors are lining up, though -- in part, perhaps, because in the future they will not face unlimited liability. World Falters, Russia Pays  It looked good on paper -- a $4 billion global fund to help Russian enterprises go private. The Clinton Administration, committed to increase Russian aid, proposed the fund in April, and the President is determined to make good on his promises. Congress seemed willing, but this nation's allies may not be. Last week the Administration, facing the reality that Japan and Western Europe might have too many troubles of their own to chip in, said the fund would shrink. The hope now is that half the amount can be agreed to later.  THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>Thank You for Smoking?</p>
        <p>The logic is flawless. Since smoking doesn't cause cancer -- that's what the tobacco industry has maintained all along -- it naturally follows that secondhand smoke doesn't either. The Environmental Protection Agency, of course, says other people's smoke causes up to 3,000 lung-cancer deaths a year, and that declaration has led to a lot more smoke-free restaurants and offices -- most recently, a ban last week on smoking in all Los Angeles restaurants. But the tobacco industry hates to see office workers puffing madly while they huddle in rainy doorways -- some of them might actually quit. So last week an industry group -- one with no ties whatever to the Flat Earth Society -- sued, asking a court to rule that what the E.P.A. has demonstrated just isn't so.  A Worried Economy  This is a nation waiting for two axes to fall -- they're called taxes and health care reform. And while it waits, the economy is treading water -- or so says the Federal Reserve, which in its latest survey of business conditions, out last week, foresaw "slow to moderate" economic growth. Investment and hiring are being delayed, the central bank said, by those twin uncertainties. That certainly seems plausible. But some Administration officials spy another wrinkle, suspecting that when business people say the sky will fall if taxes rise, what they're really doing is a bit of grass-roots lobbying against tax increases. If you've ever seen a 6-year-old predicting the certain end of civilization if she doesn't get ice cream now, that seems equally plausible. For its part, the White House, holding its finger to the economic winds, now says the year's growth will probably be more like 2.5 percent than the 3.1 percent it had projected. Who's Minding the Air?</p>
        <p>Some Federal agency is surely looking out for air quality in airplanes, right? Actually, no. The F.A.A., it seems, mainly covers flight safety. OSHA cares, as long as the problem is on the ground. The E.P.A.? Again, no. But as airlines circulate less fresh air through the cabins, raising levels of carbon dioxide and fumes from cleaners and pesticides, flight attendants and passengers have complained of headaches and other maladies. So last week the Transportation Department stepped into the vacuum, as Secretary Federico Pena ordered a preliminary inquiry into the air quality of plane cabins. A Budget Bill, by a Whisker  For President Clinton, it's make-or-break time. The waffling and missteps and runway haircuts, he hopes, will turn to forgotten dust if he can just cajole and strong-arm his budget plan through Congress. So senators lined up in neat rows last week, each wildly cheering the home team -- the Democrats trying to make their party's day, the Republicans trying to break this enemy Presidency. In a typical Democratic swipe, George Mitchell of Maine said that if Mr. Clinton "sent a bill up here to praise apple pie and motherhood," the Republicans would try to amend it to say "apple pie is evil and motherhood is insidious." As for the Republicans, John Chafee of Rhode Island said, "We were just plain left out." The Democrats held ranks, though, fending off all efforts to peck at the bill. The overall bill, though, squeaked through only on a tie-breaking vote by Vice President Gore. Next stop, a House-Senate conference.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
