<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FLAW IN SHUTTLE STOPS LAUNCHING</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="600607"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCOVERY (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASTRONAUTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CAPE CANAVERAL (FLA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930407T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDF1E3BF934A35757C0A965958260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FLAW IN SHUTTLE STOPS LAUNCHING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., April 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An attempt to launch the space shuttle Discovery was halted today with seconds to go because of a technical failure, the second time in two weeks that a liftoff was canceled at the last moment. The space agency said it would try again on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The effort to launch the Discovery early this morning was cut short when a safety computer aboard the spacecraft detected a possible problem with a valve in one of the three main engines. But the mission's managers decided after meeting with engineers that the problem was actually in circuits that relay signals to the safety computer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An attempt to launch the space shuttle Discovery was halted today with seconds to go because of a technical failure, the second time in two weeks that a liftoff was canceled at the last moment. The space agency said it would try again on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The effort to launch the Discovery early this morning was cut short when a safety computer aboard the spacecraft detected a possible problem with a valve in one of the three main engines. But the mission's managers decided after meeting with engineers that the problem was actually in circuits that relay signals to the safety computer.</p>
        <p>Edward Campion, a spokesman for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, said either a faulty switch or a broken wire did not allow a signal to reach the computer to tell it the valve was closed. When the valve in the fuel system was opened and closed several times after the mission was canceled, temperature changes in the piping matched those seen on previous flights, indicating that the valve was working properly, Mr. Campion said.</p>
        <p>Engineers plan to conduct more tests on the valve on Wednesday when the shuttle is refueled. If it seems to be working, technicians will instruct the computer to ignore the sensor signals, he said. Countdown at 11 Seconds</p>
        <p>The launching of the Discovery, whose mission is to study the Earth's thinning ozone layer and the Sun's effect on the atmosphere, was halted at 2:32 A.M., just 11 seconds before liftoff.</p>
        <p>NASA said it would try again to launch the shuttle during a two-and-a-half-hour period beginning at 1:29 A.M. Thursday, Eastern daylight time. The Air Force said the weather then should be very good, with only a 10 percent chance a flight would be postponed because of scattered clouds that could affect an emergency landing.</p>
        <p>It was the second time in two weeks that a shuttle countdown ended abruptly just before liftoff. The main engines of the space shuttle Columbia shut down three seconds before liftoff on March 22 because a piece of debris clogged an engine valve.</p>
        <p>The Discovery's three engines had not yet ignited when the countdown ended. The shuttle remained bolted to the pad when a computer running safety checks aboard the spacecraft indicated that a valve in the liquid hydrogen fuel system had not closed as it should. Astronauts at Space Center</p>
        <p>If the valve, which allows gaseous hydrogen to bleed off the supercold liquid fuel, had been open during flight, NASA officials said, it could have allowed flammable hydrogen to escape and cause an engine explosion.</p>
        <p>All five astronauts left the shuttle without injury and remained at the Kennedy Space Center here for the next launching attempt.</p>
        <p>The Discovery's planned eight-day mission will be the second of eight shuttle missions planned for this year. The space agency wants to fly the shuttle as soon as possible because it is meant to gather data on atmospheric ozone before the end of April, during the Northern Hemisphere's transition from winter to summer when ozone levels undergo seasonal changes.</p>
        <p>A similar package of atmospheric instruments was flown last March, and scientists want to compare data taken at the same time over a period of years. Scientists fear that the upper atmosphere's layer of ozone gas, which protects against dangerous ultraviolet radiation, is being destroyed by man-made pollutants and possibly volcanic gases.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
