<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Fiction</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="595805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SILVERBERG, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONAS, GERALD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPINRAD, NORMAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRIFFITH, NICOLA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">KINGDOMS OF THE WALL (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DEUS X (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">AMMONITE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD9173DF937A25750C0A965958260" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gerald Jonas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JONAS, GERALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is becoming difficult these days to find a science fiction story that does not in some way confront the question of godhood. Robert Silverberg's KINGDOMS OF THE WALL (Spectra/Bantam, $22.95) is a parable about the danger of seeking more intimate contact with the powers that control the universe. On a distant planet a race of people who superficially resemble humans lives at the foot of a mountain so steep and so tall that it is known as the Wall. Their myths tell of a Prometheus-like First Climber who ascended the Wall and brought back useful knowledge from the gods who live at the summit. In honor of this First Climber, the people periodically choose 40 of their best and brightest as Pilgrims, who try to climb the Wall and parley with the gods. Most fail to return; those who do are invariably mad, and their reports of what they have seen at the summit make little sense.</p>
        <p>The band of Pilgrims to whom Mr. Silverberg directs our attention has better luck. The Wall turns out to be an entire range of mountains offering trial after trial as horrific as any observered by Dante in the Inferno. Many former Pilgrims have ended up in the clutches of monsters capable of stealing one's body, mind and will. The author makes some attempt to distinguish between these monsters, and there are hints that each Pilgrim's fate is determined by his or her character. But since the only Pilgrims we get to know well are those who escape the monsters, the fate of the less fortunate seems more arbitrary than ordained. Higher up the Wall, the obstacles become more subtle; some regions are so pleasant that the Pilgrims are tempted to settle down and forget their mission. What awaits those who persevere is a revelation that calls into question everything they believe (although it will hardly come as a surprise to the seasoned reader of science fiction).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is becoming difficult these days to find a science fiction story that does not in some way confront the question of godhood. Robert Silverberg's KINGDOMS OF THE WALL (Spectra/Bantam, $22.95) is a parable about the danger of seeking more intimate contact with the powers that control the universe. On a distant planet a race of people who superficially resemble humans lives at the foot of a mountain so steep and so tall that it is known as the Wall. Their myths tell of a Prometheus-like First Climber who ascended the Wall and brought back useful knowledge from the gods who live at the summit. In honor of this First Climber, the people periodically choose 40 of their best and brightest as Pilgrims, who try to climb the Wall and parley with the gods. Most fail to return; those who do are invariably mad, and their reports of what they have seen at the summit make little sense.</p>
        <p>The band of Pilgrims to whom Mr. Silverberg directs our attention has better luck. The Wall turns out to be an entire range of mountains offering trial after trial as horrific as any observered by Dante in the Inferno. Many former Pilgrims have ended up in the clutches of monsters capable of stealing one's body, mind and will. The author makes some attempt to distinguish between these monsters, and there are hints that each Pilgrim's fate is determined by his or her character. But since the only Pilgrims we get to know well are those who escape the monsters, the fate of the less fortunate seems more arbitrary than ordained. Higher up the Wall, the obstacles become more subtle; some regions are so pleasant that the Pilgrims are tempted to settle down and forget their mission. What awaits those who persevere is a revelation that calls into question everything they believe (although it will hardly come as a surprise to the seasoned reader of science fiction).</p>
        <p>The trouble with Mr. Silverberg's parable is that, for all its length, it ends too soon. I was more interested in learning how the believers deal with the blow to their faith than in following the rather repetitious challenges they must overcome on their way to the summit.</p>
        <p>DEUS X (Spectra/Bantam, paper, $3.99), by Norman Spinrad, is a witty short novel that asks the question: When does an electronic replica of a personality (a "mere" computer program) become the equivalent of a flesh-and-blood person? The answer is of immediate concern to the Roman Catholic hierarchy -- led by the first female Pope -- who must decide whether these "transcorporeal successor entities" have souls. To find out, Pope Mary I hires a freelance hacker named Marley Philippe, who infiltrates the ghostly world of the transcorporeal to quiz the electronic entities themselves.</p>
        <p>The stakes are even higher than appears at first glance. In Mr. Spinrad's near-future world, all the various environmental disasters prophesied by today's doomsayers have come to pass: global temperatures and ocean levels are rising, the ozone layer is shredding, civilization as we know it may be dying, and the survival of all DNA-based life is in doubt. But what of electronic life? Will the successor entities in fact inherit what is left of the earth? And what kind of deity, if any, will they recognize?</p>
        <p>Aside from a few in-jokes at the expense of the cyberpunk crowd, Mr. Spinrad maintains just the right tone of mock-serious concern for the philosophical and theological conundrums faced by the church. And when an electronic entity rephrases the Gospels to suggest that "God the Father . . . downloaded His software into a fleshly matrix to redeem the world of men," it is clear that the author has got hold of a powerful metaphor for transcendence that he intends to push to the limit -- with thought-provoking results.</p>
        <p>The deity in Nicola Griffith's AMMONITE (Del Rey/Ballantine, paper, $3.99) is a planet known as Jeep. Attempts to colonize Jeep have uncovered a deadly but selective virus that kills all men and most women. Those women who are spared undergo changes that allow them to communicate with one another, and with the planet itself, through a process that might be called molecular telepathy. As a result, two women who bond can give birth to healthy, genetically diverse children. This remarkable fact is discovered by Marguerite Angelica Taishan -- Marghe to her friends -- who is a trained anthropologist with personal problems. To solve the mystery of Jeep, Marghe must give herself up to the planet, body and soul.</p>
        <p>One of the time-honored uses of science fiction is to provide a socially acceptable channel for wish fulfillment. During most of this century young male readers have reveled in stories about omni competent space captains who all but single-handedly conquer galaxies and right wrongs. Ms. Griffith represents a newer school of feminist wish fulfillment. By inventing a virus that eliminates men, she can celebrate womanly virtues on a planetary scale. Because she takes care to create fully rounded characters, her polemical concerns never unbalance the story; the lesbian love scenes are handled with delicacy; and Marghe's life-or-death trial on a snowbound plain inhabited by hostile tribeswomen pays homage to Ursula K. Le Guin's "Left Hand of Darkness" without inviting invidious comparisons.</p>
        <p>XANADU (Tor/Tom Doherty, $18.95) is an anthology of never-before-published stories and poems selected and edited by Jane Yolen, a former president of the Science Fiction Writers of America. The collection is billed as fantasy, which means that the authors are free to ignore both everyday reality and scientific plausibility in constructing their fictions. Since such freedom can induce vertigo in the unsuspecting reader, fantasists often anchor their flights of imagination to some recognizable underpinning. One favorite trick is to borrow the archaic diction associated with medieval romances, fairy tales and rehashed Bible stories. At its worst, this stylistic borrowing leads to un viable hybrids in which characters out of modern-day Westerns and soap operas stalk through misty landscapes spouting pseudomedieval bombast. But in the hands of writers who genuinely appreciate the tradition, fantasies with an archaic flavor can sparkle.</p>
        <p>Pamela Dean's "Owlswater" follows an apprentice sorcerer on an archetypal quest guided by fragments of poetry whose provenance ranges from anonymous ballads like "The Three Ravens" to "The Waste Land" of T. S. Eliot. The protagonist of "The Poacher," by Ursula K. Le Guin, ends up literally inside a fairy tale, although the first-person narrator tells the story in straightforward sentences that are always more concerned with setting a scene than shaping a mood. Anna Kirwan-Vogel's "Jaguar Lord" earns its inflated diction by imagining the coming-of-age hunt of the 14-year-old son of a Mayan lord, whose ambition is shaped by the "true" tales of heroism he is told. And in "The Hound of Merin," Eleanor Arnason breathes life into hoary Homeric conventions by creating an entirely new world where soldiering is a noble profession and love between battlefield comrades is the norm. But as much as I enjoyed these exercises in stylistic reclamation, I was most taken with Frances Stokes Hoekstra's "Pale Moon," which deftly blends wish-fulfillment fantasy with a contemporary tale of adolescent angst that brings to mind the best young-adult books of Judy Blume.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
