<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Government Survey Finds Decline In a Building Block of Acid Rain</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="633114"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACID RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR AND SULFUR COMPOUNDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITRATES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILCHEY, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DD1631F934A3575AC0A965958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Government Survey Finds Decline In a Building Block of Acid Rain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM HILCHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILCHEY, TIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN what is considered a significant payoff of the Federal Clean Air Act, researchers have found a "sharp signal" that pollution linked to acid rain is declining.</p>
        <p>Concentrations of sulfates, key building blocks of acid rain, declined significantly in rainwater collected at 26 of 33 sites monitored from 1980 to 1991 by the United States Geological Survey. Although data were collected in 18 states, most of the monitoring sites were in the eastern half of the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN what is considered a significant payoff of the Federal Clean Air Act, researchers have found a "sharp signal" that pollution linked to acid rain is declining.</p>
        <p>Concentrations of sulfates, key building blocks of acid rain, declined significantly in rainwater collected at 26 of 33 sites monitored from 1980 to 1991 by the United States Geological Survey. Although data were collected in 18 states, most of the monitoring sites were in the eastern half of the country.</p>
        <p>"In the case of sulfates things look pretty clear," said Dr. Timothy A. Cohn, a co-author of the report, which the agency issued recently. "We're seeing a very sharp signal of a downward trend pretty much everywhere."</p>
        <p>Sulfates are a byproduct of sulfur in the atmosphere, produced principally by power plants that burn fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>But the survey had more ambivalent findings on another component of acid rain, the concentration of nitrates, which are a byproduct of nitrogen oxides, produced by automobile exhaust and power plant emissions.  The concentration of nitrates decreased by statistically significant amounts at just 3 of the 33 sites, although data from 24 other sites suggested a downward trend, Dr. Cohn said. The other six sites showed a rise that was not considered statistically significant. A Decrease in Acidity</p>
        <p>In its measure of the acidity of rainwater, the Geological Survey's results were encouraging. The researchers recorded significant upward trends in pH levels, indicating a decrease in acidity, at nine of the collection sites, Dr. Cohn said. Less significant decreases in acidity were found at 16 sites. At the other eight sites, acidity rose, but the increase was considered statistically significant at only one of them.</p>
        <p>The results are very consistent with the reductions that have been observed in sulfur dioxide emissions from power plants over the same period, Dr. Cohn said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Derek Winstanley, the director of the Federal National Acid Precipitation Assessment Program in Washington, said: "We so often hear apocalyptic statements about the environment and things getting worse. I think this is an example of things getting better.</p>
        <p>"There's quite an obvious pattern of sulfate decreases at most of the sites during the 80's. There's a general trend toward decreasing acidity. Although that trend is not as strong as the sulfate signal, this is the first time that we've seen a general trend toward decreasing acidity of the rainfall."</p>
        <p>Since 1970, when the Clean Air Act was passed in an attempt to improve air quality, sulfur dioxide emissions have declined about 30 percent nationwide, Dr. Winstanley said.</p>
        <p>Some 80 percent of all the energy used in America is made by burning fossil fuels. Utilities that burn sulfur-rich coal are responsible for about 35 percent of the nation's sulfur dioxide emissions from stationary sources, Dr. Winstanley said. Nitrogen Oxide Emissions Down</p>
        <p>The Acid Rain Control Program, created in 1990 by amendments to the Clean Air Act, calls for further reductions in sulfur dioxide emissions from stationary sources, which by the year 2000 will be capped at about 15 million tons a year, 42 percent of 1980 levels. Dr. Winstanley said emission reductions of about 9 million tons are to be achieved by the nation's power-generating utilities while steel plants and other factories will account for another 5.65 million tons.</p>
        <p>Nitrogen oxide emissions have declined by about 6 percent in the United States since 1978. Although the 1990 amendments require power plants and factories to reduce emissions of nitrogen oxide by two million tons, or about 10 percent, from 1980 levels, no cap was established. Dr. Winstanley said scientists believe that emissions from automobiles and new power plants and factories are likely to increase the total amount of nitrogen oxide released into the environment by early in the next century.</p>
        <p>Dr. James A. Lynch, a professor of forest hydrology at Pennsylvania State University in University Park, said that although the general patterns suggested by the Geological Survey report were encouraging, the data also indicated that continued monitoring -- and perhaps more stringent regulation of nitrate emissions -- might be needed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lynch said that even as the sulfate component of the acid rain problem appears to have been reduced by tighter emissions controls, researchers have begun to focus more attention on the role of nitrates in the acidification of the nation's lakes and streams. He added that although the acidity of rainfall has declined, the acidity of lakes and streams has increased.</p>
        <p>"We see a continual acidification in the streams we are monitoring -- the pH continues to drop and has been doing so since the early 1960's," Dr. Lynch said. "On the other hand, we see a decrease in the amount of sulfates in the water, and the decrease mimics fairly well what we see in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"However, we see an increase in the nitrate concentration, so there is a strong indication that continued acidification of our streams is being accomplished through a combination of sulfates and increasing nitrates."</p>
        <p>Dr. Lynch also said that the Earth's natural buffering abilities, which result from mechanisms like airborne particles of calcium, magnesium and other base materials, appear to have been reduced over time. As less acid rain is neutralized by these processes, he said, the potential exists for a net increase in the acidity of the nation's water resources even as the amount of pollution that causes acid rain is decreased.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
