<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pac-Man It's Not. The Future of a Presidency and U.S. Health Care, Maybe.</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIDEO GAMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIDEO GAMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAXIS BUSINESS SIMULATIONS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARKLE FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAXIS BUSINESS SIMULATIONS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MARKLE FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MAXIS BUSINESS SIMULATIONS</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKLE FOUNDATION</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DF1F3DF937A15751C1A965958260" item-length="1236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pac-Man It's Not. The Future of a Presidency and U.S. Health Care, Maybe.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>November 1995. National health care has been law for a year, and universal coverage is almost a fact. But costs are already running above projections, and Bob Dole is making wisecracks about voodoo Democrat economics. A value-added tax or Oregon-style rationing would solve the budget problem, but would be suicide to introduce before the elections . . .</p>
        <p>A page from Hillary Rodham Clinton's future? Perhaps. But with a little help from Silicon Valley, the future is now, and open to anyone with access to a zippy I.B.M.-compatible personal computer. SimHealth, a $29.95 computer game produced by Maxis Business Simulations with a grant from the Markle Foundation, gives back-seat ambulance drivers the chance to design their own health care system from scratch and to observe the consequences, including the possibility of being voted out of office.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>November 1995. National health care has been law for a year, and universal coverage is almost a fact. But costs are already running above projections, and Bob Dole is making wisecracks about voodoo Democrat economics. A value-added tax or Oregon-style rationing would solve the budget problem, but would be suicide to introduce before the elections . . .</p>
        <p>A page from Hillary Rodham Clinton's future? Perhaps. But with a little help from Silicon Valley, the future is now, and open to anyone with access to a zippy I.B.M.-compatible personal computer. SimHealth, a $29.95 computer game produced by Maxis Business Simulations with a grant from the Markle Foundation, gives back-seat ambulance drivers the chance to design their own health care system from scratch and to observe the consequences, including the possibility of being voted out of office.</p>
        <p>With its slick graphics and randomly introduced news bulletins, the game may prove as entertaining as Maxis's popular simulations of genetic mutation (SimLife), urban planning (SimCity) and insect colonies (SimAnt).  Budget Policy May Follow</p>
        <p>But this time, the idea is to sugarcoat a maximum-strength civics lesson. Lloyd Morrisett, the president of the Markle Foundation, hopes SimHealth will be the model for making complex public policy understandable to a generation that is used to absorbing the news in video bites. "If people think the game is fun and interesting, we will try it elsewhere," he said, "perhaps with budget policy, welfare reform or the environment."</p>
        <p>The White House has already installed a preview version of SimHealth in a dozen of its computers. And Jeff Eller, a spokesman for the President's Task Force on National Health Care Reform, thinks simulation games could serve policy professionals as well as amateurs by forcing those with different views to examine their assumptions. "You can't dismiss this as another Pac-Man or Tetris," he allows.</p>
        <p>Computer simulation has been a standard industrial design technique for two decades, allowing engineers to test the stability of a new aircraft wing or the adequacy of a factory's quality-control system without investing a penny in the real thing. By the same token, scientists have used simulations to solve problems that resist straightforward mathematical solutions. Forecasts of global warming, for example, depend heavily on the technique.</p>
        <p>Simulations that are both timely and worth the effort have generally had the drawback of requiring immense number-crunching power: Multimillion-dollar supercomputers are still the tools of choice for simulating the explosion of nuclear weapons and tracks of hurricanes. Faster Personal Computers</p>
        <p>Indeed, John Hiles, the general manager of Maxis Business Simulations, notes that only in the last few years have personal computers become fast enough and cheap enough to serve as vehicles for mass-market simulation games.</p>
        <p>But even the most realistic simulations of jet-fighter duels and sports leagues have obvious limitations, being no better than the fixed assumptions that drive them. In SimCity, Maxis's urban planning game, Mr. Hiles points out that the "the nuclear power plant always melts down."</p>
        <p>The Markle Foundation, which is always hunting for ways to bridge the communications gap between complicated issues and a public that has neither the time nor the inclination to spend hours absorbing the often-dreary stuff of policy, had something very different in mind.</p>
        <p>Since the whole point of SimHealth is to create a relatively painless way of exploring the practical problems of providing health care, players are always free to alter either the priorities of the plan or the assumptions about how the moving parts interact.</p>
        <p>"I think SimHealth is an intriguing alternative," Mr. Eller, the Presidential panel's spokesman, said. Playing the Game</p>
        <p>To start the game, a player must make explicit what he or she values most about health care reform. The two broad dimensions of choice, what SimHealth labels "liberty versus equality" and "community versus efficiency," are applied to a variety of core issues.</p>
        <p>On cost control, for example, the player is asked whether competition should take precedence over regulation, whether individuals should take primary responsibility for preventive care and whether standardization of treatment protocols is an acceptable interference in the doctor-patient relationship.</p>
        <p>From then on, the player is free to mix and match policies on the understanding that failure to sustain consistent priorities will cost political support and perhaps end the game with an election.</p>
        <p>One might, for example, choose a Canadian-style single payer system with rationing of individual procedures, paying for it with an income tax and a 10 percent patient co-payment. Or one might opt for managed competition, underwritten by employer-paid insurance and buttressed by caps on the growth of hospital outlays.</p>
        <p>Every policy sets off a stream of consequences for businesses, individuals, hospitals, doctors and government budgets. And a player can always monitor the effects; for example, asking what percentage of household income is going to health care, or how large the budget deficit is. Policy changes require the expenditure of "political chips" that translate into lost votes at election time.</p>
        <p>Most ingenious, perhaps, every policy is linked to a set of relatively optimistic "default" assumptions and a "counter" set of pessimistic assumptions, designed with the help of a panel of health care experts assembled by the Markle Foundation. The game even permits players to custom-design the working parts.  A 'Neutral' Forum</p>
        <p>For example, the decision to increase by 10 percent the number of acute care procedures covered by insurance would ordinarily increase the demand for hospital beds by 2 percent. But under the pessimistic counter-assumptions, a 10 percent increase in coverage generates a 5 percent increase in hospital care demand. "It's about as neutral a forum as you can get," Mr. Eller said.</p>
        <p>Alternatively, a player might experiment with a half-dozen different numbers to see how they would affect hospital crowding or Federal deficits -- or even the profitability of businesses in paying insurance premiums over a period of months or years.</p>
        <p>That flexibility excites Dan Beauchamp, a former Deputy Commissioner of Health in New York State who now teaches public policy at the State University in Albany. "Even very smart policy makers have trouble thinking about several variables rocketing around at once," Mr. Beauchamp said.</p>
        <p>Whether or how SimHealth will influence the national health debate is unclear. The Markle Foundation has distributed a preview version of the game to Congressional staff members and senior Administration officials. But the foundation's major concern at the moment is getting it into the hands of a wider range of opinion leaders, everyone from business executives to doctors to economics professors.</p>
        <p>While he at first considered giving away the game, Mr. Morrisett decided that doing so would make it impossible to distribute it through commercial channels like software vendors, mail-order houses and college bookstores. Instead, the foundation will subsidize promotion and hold the retail price below $40. "No one is going to make money on SimHealth," Mr. Hiles predicted.</p>
        <p>That, of course, is not the primary goal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
