<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Matter the Color, the Cars Are Green</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT CARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREATER NEW YORK AUTOMOBILE SHOW</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTESTS AND PRIZES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRYSLER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHUON, MARSHALL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOUT CARS (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DD1F30F932A25757C0A965958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Matter the Color, the Cars Are Green</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Schuon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHUON, MARSHALL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AMERICA'S oldest automobile show opened its doors for a nine-day run at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center on Manhattan's West Side yesterday, and all the usual hoopla and glitter of its 93-year history were there.</p>
        <p>The Dallas Cowboys cheerleaders were on hand. A marching band was there. Officials of the sponsoring Greater New York Automobile Dealers Association cut a ribbon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AMERICA'S oldest automobile show opened its doors for a nine-day run at the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center on Manhattan's West Side yesterday, and all the usual hoopla and glitter of its 93-year history were there.</p>
        <p>The Dallas Cowboys cheerleaders were on hand. A marching band was there. Officials of the sponsoring Greater New York Automobile Dealers Association cut a ribbon.</p>
        <p>Under the acres of vaulted glass were such things as the spectacular neon-blue Dodge Viper coupe, an Audi concept car whose body gleams like chrome but is really polished aluminum, and the new (and cheaper than before) $350,000 coupe from a California company called Vector.</p>
        <p>The New York show is always the last of the handful of major expositions in this country -- the other notables being Detroit, Los Angeles and Chicago -- so there is little real news left for '93, but Nissan is introducing its '94 Infiniti sedan, BMW has a 325i convertible, and Mazda's AZ-1 micro-mini city car makes its North American debut.</p>
        <p>Even before you get to this year's 1,200-plus offerings, though, you encounter a delightful exhibit that is the key to the show's "green" motif. It is Chrysler's Environmental Education Center, meant to encourage children to start thinking about ways to care for the planet and to put their ideas on paper.</p>
        <p>Just inside the convention center's brass doors, a billboard-sized cartoon of a car greets you. The wheels have tunnels for hubs and kids can crawl through to the exhibit, where they find chairs, tables and drawing supplies. For those of us who creak, there is a more conventional entry -- and while it's less fun, the pictures that already exist will evoke your smiles.</p>
        <p>The exhibit will keep small hands busy all week, but it also culminates a contest for fourth-graders from New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, and the walls are lined with hundreds of sketches, both from the metropolitan area and from the Detroit show, where the contest originated. Each drawing is accompanied by text that explains the artist's concept of an evironmental vehicle.</p>
        <p>Participating schools share a $10,000 grant from the Chrysler Fund to be used for environmental education materials. And, in the interest of full disclosure, yours truly was one of the judges, along with Joan Lunden of ABC's "Good Morning America," and Richard Yelle, chairman of product design at the Parsons School of Design.</p>
        <p>Some of the drawings were terrific but lacked imagination. Others were less polished but showed thought. Environmental concern and artistic merit were what counted. (Feasibility did, too, but we sort of winked at that.)</p>
        <p>First place went to Nicole Marcelino of Manhattan, whose car appropriately was called the Nic.</p>
        <p>"Nic won't run by gas," she said. "It will run by sunlight so carbon dioxide will not come out of the car. My car is driven two inches above the ground and has a cushion on the bottom. This cushion will have air in it, the kind they put in a tire.</p>
        <p>"In the back of the front seat there will be cushions so if the car stops suddenly the people sitting in the back won't get hurt. I would put air bags coming from the sides and front for safety. Nic will have soft doors on the inside so people won't get hurt. The kind of car I would make would be a family car, so four people could ride in it like my family. I would like my car to go fast and slow."</p>
        <p>The second-place winner, Cesar Herrera of West New York, N.J., called his car the S.E.V.J. for Solar Energy Vehicle Jet. "The car can fly in the skies because the solar energy gives it gravity to pull up and fly," he said. "It goes 459 MPS. The mirror on the roof saves energy for a day that is not sunny."</p>
        <p>Debbie Parnes of Ardsley, N.Y., who took third place, named her vehicle the Electricar and said it would have solar cells, rechargeable batteries and a recyclable fiberglass body.</p>
        <p>The manufacturers are thinking about such things, too, and their concepts range from recycling displays at the BMW, Toyota and Volkswagen stands, to electric, methanol and natural-gas vehicles from Ford, Dodge and Volvo.</p>
        <p>Not many are as innovative as the "Grass Eater" drawn by Justin Boles, however. The Detroit third-grader's car presumably grazes along smartly, gaining sustenance from nearby lawns, and the artist notes that it has its wheels on the roof "so when it flips over from a crash it can drive away."</p>
        <p>My favorite, though, was sketched by another Detroit pupil, Elmira Weathers. The innards have little to do with the environment, but her vehicle comes "with desk, beds, TV, restroom and steering wheel."</p>
        <p>It's called the Couch Car. Just my speed.</p>
        <p>ABOUT CARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
