<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Satellite Finds Growing Threat to Ozone</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="602367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UPPER ATMOSPHERE RESEARCH SATELLITE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DD1630F936A25757C0A965958260" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Satellite Finds Growing Threat to Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Satellite measurements indicate an abundance of ozone-destroying chemicals remained in the atmosphere over the Northern Hemisphere much longer this winter than last, researchers said today. They said the finding could portend even greater ozone loss over highly populated parts of the world than in the past.</p>
        <p>Data from the spacecraft, the Upper Atmosphere Research Satellite, also showed that atmospheric ozone levels above parts of Canada, Scandinavia, Russia and Europe were down 10 percent on average from last winter. This is more than twice the usual year-to-year variation, the researchers said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Satellite measurements indicate an abundance of ozone-destroying chemicals remained in the atmosphere over the Northern Hemisphere much longer this winter than last, researchers said today. They said the finding could portend even greater ozone loss over highly populated parts of the world than in the past.</p>
        <p>Data from the spacecraft, the Upper Atmosphere Research Satellite, also showed that atmospheric ozone levels above parts of Canada, Scandinavia, Russia and Europe were down 10 percent on average from last winter. This is more than twice the usual year-to-year variation, the researchers said.</p>
        <p>Researchers from the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., and Edinburgh University in Scotland, said concentrations of a particularly destructive form of ozone-degrading chlorine were unusually high above Arctic areas.</p>
        <p>This level of chlorine monoxide, as the chlorine compound is known, together with colder atmospheric temperatures that persisted a month longer than last year, combined to push levels of protective ozone down by as much as 20 percent in some areas. Daily Decreases Recorded</p>
        <p>"Ozone concentrations in the Arctic in a layer about 12 miles high, where most chlorine monoxide was located, decreased by 0.7 percent per day from mid-February through early March 1993," said Dr. Joe Waters, the chief NASA researcher on the project. Levels of ozone in this part of the atmosphere normally increase during this time of the year, he said.</p>
        <p>In a report in the April 18 issue of the scientific journal Nature, the researchers said the spacecraft had found that chlorine from the lower stratosphere had been almost completely converted to destructive chlorine monoxide in the circulating vortexes of cold air that form over the North and South Poles each winter. These chemicals, along with sunlight and the cold temperatures and ice crystals of the vortex, contribute to chemical reactions that destroy ozone, researchers said.</p>
        <p>Ozone is one type of oxygen molecule. In the stratosphere, it protects the Earth from the sun's dangerous ultraviolet rays. Scientists believe the ozone layer is decaying because of man-made pollutants like chlorine compounds and possibly because of volcanic eruptions. Many scientists believe this could lead to an increase in cancer and other health problems.</p>
        <p>The research satellite's findings on decreased levels of Northern Hemisphere ozone were similar to those of a report last month by the World Meteorological Organization and Canada's national environmental agency. Using measurements from ground-based instruments and other satellites, they found a drop of 9 to 20 percent below average levels. Big Loss Expected in Spring</p>
        <p>In an accompanying article in Nature, Martyn Chipperfield of the University of Cambridge said that because of this winter's colder high-altitude temperatures and the prolonged period of high chlorine monoxide concentration, "substantial ozone loss should be expected in the Arctic spring of 1993."</p>
        <p>The scientists said they found concentrations of chlorine monoxide in the stratosphere to be as high in the Northern Hemisphere as in its southern counterpart, where ozone levels each winter plummet so low that a "hole" develops over the South Pole. However, because Arctic winters are shorter and warmer, no Arctic ozone hole has yet formed, they noted.</p>
        <p>In 1992, the satellite found high levels of chlorine monoxide over Antarctica as early as June 1, said the report.  However, measurable drops in ozone did not begin until sometime between July 10 and mid-August, continuing through September.</p>
        <p>Dr. Waters said in an interview that he and his colleagues speculate that this excess chlorine monoxide is actually destroying ozone earlier than indicated, but that this reaction may be masked by the movement of ozone-rich air from higher altitudes into the area of ozone destruction.</p>
        <p>He speculated that ozone-rich air from as far away as the tropics circulates through the polar regions, losing ozone in the chemical reactions around the poles. He said the air, depleted of some of its ozone, could then flow back toward the equator, spreading the ozone loss beyond the polar regions.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Rolando Garcia of the National Center for Atmospheric Research, in Boulder, Colo., disagreed with this theory. Delays in observed ozone loss were probably the result of a lack of constant sunlight needed for ozone-destroying reactions, rather than a replenishing of ozone by entrance of ozone-rich air, he told The Associated Press.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
