<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuclear Programs In a Meltdown</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Education Life Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGINEERING AND ENGINEERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL SECTIONS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D8153EF933A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuclear Programs In a Meltdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NUCLEAR power has grabbed headlines lately because of the premature retirement of several reactors, but something else in the industry is quietly withering away: its educational infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, only about 1,000 college juniors and seniors are enrolled in nuclear engineering degree programs, down from a peak of about 2,100 in the late 1970's, according to Energy Department surveys. Enrollment in master's programs stands at about 800, down from 1,400 in the mid-70's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NUCLEAR power has grabbed headlines lately because of the premature retirement of several reactors, but something else in the industry is quietly withering away: its educational infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, only about 1,000 college juniors and seniors are enrolled in nuclear engineering degree programs, down from a peak of about 2,100 in the late 1970's, according to Energy Department surveys. Enrollment in master's programs stands at about 800, down from 1,400 in the mid-70's.</p>
        <p>At first glance the department's surveys suggest that doctoral students are bucking the trend: their numbers have risen slightly since the mid-70's, to about 700. But half the students are from abroad. And while foreigners constitute a large proportion of most doctoral engineering programs in the United States, foreign graduates in other fields tend to stay here, university professors report; in the nuclear field they go home, because their countries are building more plants than this country is.  Undergraduates Drop</p>
        <p>Still, at least the doctoral programs can survive on foreign students until a time when more American students might apply. Energy Department figures show the number of undergraduate programs dropping from 80 in 1975 to 53 in the last academic year.</p>
        <p>More precipitous is the decline in the number of research reactors, the tools near the heart of the graduate programs. About 27 survive, down from 76 in the mid-70's. Some succumbed to student losses; others to increasing maintenance and security costs.</p>
        <p>The demise of nuclear engineering programs mimics the industry's slump. Until the mid-1970's, experts were predicting that there would be 1,000 power-generating reactors in this country by the turn of the century, and by 1978 utilities nationwide had placed orders for 250 reactors. But half those orders were canceled, and the reactor population now stands at 111 and falling.</p>
        <p>Most were done in by unfavorable economics; compared with other sources of electricity, reactors were too expensive to build and operate. The 1979 accident at Three Mile Island did not improve the industry's image. But professors say that students do not mention this.</p>
        <p>It's all bad news for engineering schools, said Kenneth C. Rogers, who was president of the Stevens Institute of Technology in Hoboken, N.J., until President Reagan appointed him to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission five years ago. "The problem is that it hasn't been perceived as an expanding, exciting field to go into," Mr. Rogers said.</p>
        <p>The drop in the number of nuclear engineering students would not be an issue if it paralleled the job market. But nuclear engineers, along with other specialists like radiation protection technicians, are likely to be in high demand as the Federal Government begins to clean up its complex for producing nuclear weapons. As a legacy of 40 years of nuclear weapons production, the Energy Department has polluted vast areas and has thousands of buildings to decontaminate.</p>
        <p>The department says that the project is the largest environmental restoration project in history. It will require tearing down old structures and putting up factories to process wastes into safer forms and other "engineered structures," from bunkers to fabricated caves, to store wastes. The project will also require constant attention to radiation exposure and to the potential for concentrating scraps of bomb fuel. If too much fuel is brought together, a chain reaction will result, creating a lethal shower of radiation and spreading the wastes.  Licenses Expiring</p>
        <p>At Pennsylvania State University, Edward H. Klevans, head of the nuclear program and an associate dean in the college of engineering, sees other reasons the nuclear industry may need more engineers. In the next few years some plants will approach the expiration of their 40-year operating licenses and will apply for extensions, Professor Klevans said. Recertifying them would require extensive engineering work.</p>
        <p>But even plant retirements will create jobs, he said, since the fuel must be carefully removed; then contaminated parts must be cleaned or painstakingly cut up with remote-controlled equipment for disposal, and worker exposure to radiation must be minimized.</p>
        <p>And new plants could be built. The energy bill that Congress passed last year simplifies the rules for licensing a new generation of power reactors, and smoothes the way for disposal of nuclear waste, in hopes of eventually spawning a rebirth of the technology.</p>
        <p>Indeed, by some projections there could be more jobs than people to fill them. A 1990 report by the National Academy of Sciences said that if orders for nuclear plants resume, the demand for nuclear engineers could double or triple. "This demand would greatly exceed the output of current nuclear engineering programs even if they were to expand to full capacity," the study found.</p>
        <p>In case of shortage, the industry is likely to rely more heavily on other kinds of engineers, who would be specially trained for nuclear work. Already, nuclear engineering professors say, utilities are following this path. But people trained as nuclear engineers are better suited, experts in the field say, because they have a particularly broad background in physics, chemistry, fluid mechanics, and other areas.</p>
        <p>The civilian nuclear industry had hoped that its fortunes, and its recruits, would be strengthened by the public's recent focus on the environment. From acid rain to global warming, electric utilities are beset with problems that nuclear power would seem to sidestep.</p>
        <p>But that has not lured more students, said Kent F. Hansen, a professor of nuclear engineering at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and a faculty member for 30 years. In discussions with students entering the field, Professor Hansen said, "Only a few said they were concerned about nuclear being environmentally more benign than the alternatives."</p>
        <p>The reasons they did give, he said, were varied and pedestrian: Some had lived near nuclear plants; others had friends and neighbors who were nuclear engineers; still others were interested in an engineering field they consider more exotic than others.</p>
        <p>The industry is trying to shore up this educational base. The Institute of Nuclear Power Operations, a utility group formed after the Three Mile Island accident to increase communication among utilities and bring peer pressure to bear on those with operating problems, last year sponsored 275 undergraduate scholarships and 40 graduate-level fellowships. One goal, said Angelina Howard, a spokeswoman, is to keep talented people "going into the educational pipeline and coming out into the industry."</p>
        <p>But the key, Professor Hansen said, will be the new plant orders. "I don't see how it can carry on without that happening," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
