<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Peering Into a Dismal 21st Century</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="589480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, PAUL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PREPARING FOR THE 21ST CENTURY (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF1539F932A25751C0A965958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Peering Into a Dismal 21st Century</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER LEHMANN-HAUPT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEHMANN-HAUPT, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Preparing for the 21st Century By Paul Kennedy Illustrated. Random House. $25.</p>
        <p>In his previous book, "The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers: Economic Change and Military Conflict from 1500 to 2000," Paul Kennedy brought us the bad news that nations rising to supremacy by winning wars tend to get overextended in a way that undermines the source of their wealth, and that the United States is undergoing such a decline. Mr. Kennedy, who teaches history at Yale, didn't think the fall-off necessarily had to end with a crash. He just meant to sound a warning so that leaders could soften the landing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Preparing for the 21st Century By Paul Kennedy Illustrated. Random House. $25.</p>
        <p>In his previous book, "The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers: Economic Change and Military Conflict from 1500 to 2000," Paul Kennedy brought us the bad news that nations rising to supremacy by winning wars tend to get overextended in a way that undermines the source of their wealth, and that the United States is undergoing such a decline. Mr. Kennedy, who teaches history at Yale, didn't think the fall-off necessarily had to end with a crash. He just meant to sound a warning so that leaders could soften the landing.</p>
        <p>The book set off a debate so lively that conferences had to be organized. At one of them, as Mr. Kennedy explains in his new book, someone got up and told him he should stop worrying about nation-states and start thinking about forces that are "</p>
        <p>trans</p>
        <p>national" in nature. Mr. Kennedy did, and "Preparing for the 21st Century" is the penetrating result. In it, the news gets even worse than it was in "The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers."</p>
        <p>When Mr. Kennedy thought about transnational forces, what first came to mind was the English country curate Thomas Robert Malthus (1766-1834) and his dire observation "that the power of population is indefinitely greater than the power in the earth to produce subsistence for man." Mr. Kennedy reflects that what allowed the British people to escape the fate Malthus predicted for them was first, emigration, second, the improvements in British farming that eventually constituted the Agricultural Revolution and third, the Industrial Revolution. Mr. Kennedy adds that a fourth solution had been suggested by earlier events in revolutionary France, "namely, internal unrest followed by external aggression."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy then writes, "Those same interrelated issues -- overpopulation, pressure upon the land, migration and social instability, on the one hand, and technology's power both to increase productivity and to displace traditional occupations, on the other -- still confront us today, with greater force than ever." The difference is the increased intensity of the problems now compared with the late 18th century.</p>
        <p>Population is exploding, especially in the so-called developing regions of the world, Mr. Kennedy points out.  According to the World Bank's calculations, there may be as many as 11 billion people on the earth by the second half of the 21st century. But the forces that saved humankind from a Malthusian fate, while still in effect, are likely to have more ambiguous consequences.</p>
        <p>The poorer people of the world can still migrate but are less likely to be welcome wherever conditions are more promising. Biotechnological innovation will doubtless revolutionize agricultural productivity, but it "could lead to further tensions over agricultural trade, as food exporting countries like Australia and the United States find that their produce, while needed by developing countries unable to pay for it, is not required by rich nations increasingly able to create their own biotech substitutes at home."</p>
        <p>Robotics and automation are on the verge of creating a new industrial revolution, Mr. Kennedy predicts. But while the resulting boost in productivity will benefit countries with a shortage of labor, like Japan, it will hurt countries with large pools of cheap, unskilled workers.</p>
        <p>To complicate matters further, he argues, the rise of multi-national corporations is blurring the meaning of nation-states. Employing mainly manipulators of information, or "symbolic analysts," as Robert Reich has called them, these extraterritorial companies are likely to widen the gap between the haves and have-nots.</p>
        <p>And on top of everything else, there is the environmental crisis to worry about: the pollution of the air; the depletion of water, forests and natural resources, and what the author regards as the inevitable heating of the planet's atmosphere through the greenhouse effect. While Mr. Kennedy's vision has a far-reaching sweep, it does not make for encouraging reading.</p>
        <p>After reviewing these potential problems, the author turns his attention to "regional impacts," or the varying abilities of different parts of the world to cope. In chapters called "The Japanese 'Plan' for a Post-2000 World," "India and China," "Winners and Losers in the Developing World," "The Erstwhile U.S.S.R. and Its Crumbled Empire," "Europe and the Future" and "The American Dilemma," he analyzes the vulnerabilities of these various nations that are likely to make matters even worse.</p>
        <p>Intended as "a guide to understanding global changes," not "as a technical primer for responses to them," "Preparing for the 21st Century" does not assess in detail the planet's chances of surviving. Still, the book's impact is crushing. Mr. Kennedy writes near the end: "It is inconceivable that the earth can sustain a population of 10 billion people devouring resources at the rate enjoyed by richer societies today -- or at even half that rate. Well before total world population reaches that level, irreparable damage to forests, water supplies and animal and plant species will have occurred, and many environmental thresholds may have been breached." When you come to the end, you are so depressed you barely have the strength to close the book.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kennedy, on the other hand, whistles past the graveyard: "Nothing is certain except that we face innumerable uncertainties; but simply recognizing that fact provides a vital starting point, and is, of course, far better than being blindly unaware of how our world is changing." After all, he points out, even Malthus ended his "Essay on Population" on an upbeat note, allowing for the possibility that humankind could change its ways and avoid the fate predicted for it.</p>
        <p>To this Mr. Kennedy adds, "The same is as true today." Yet one of the main points of his book is that what held for Malthus is</p>
        <p>less</p>
        <p>true today.  Oh, well, maybe a conference can be organized to work things out.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
