<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Try to Save Plane Pentagon Wants to Destroy</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY AIRCRAFT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONDOR-2 (MISSILE)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOEING CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Aircraft</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DD1E3BF934A35750C0A965958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Try to Save Plane Pentagon Wants to Destroy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists say a high-flying robot airplane developed for the military could revolutionize research into ozone depletion and other atmospheric problems, but they fear that it might be cut up and scrapped before it can ever be used.</p>
        <p>The atmospheric researchers are urging Government science agencies to speed their efforts to evaluate and possibly acquire the large pilotless drone, called the Condor. It was built by the Boeing Corporation for the Pentagon as a prototype spy aircraft.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists say a high-flying robot airplane developed for the military could revolutionize research into ozone depletion and other atmospheric problems, but they fear that it might be cut up and scrapped before it can ever be used.</p>
        <p>The atmospheric researchers are urging Government science agencies to speed their efforts to evaluate and possibly acquire the large pilotless drone, called the Condor. It was built by the Boeing Corporation for the Pentagon as a prototype spy aircraft.</p>
        <p>The plane, with a wingspan that is wider than that of a 747 jumbo jet, is estimated to have cost Boeing and the military more than $300 million to develop. It is now stored in a hangar at a Boeing complex at Moses Lake, Wash.  On one of its eight flights it set an altitude record, and Pentagon officials said it met all expectations.</p>
        <p>But the Defense Department agencies that sponsored the plane's development say they no longer have a requirement for such an aircraft. They also say they cannot afford the $1.8 million a year it costs to maintain the plane. Capable of Days Aloft</p>
        <p>Atmospheric scientists both in the Government and outside it say destroying the plane would be a woeful waste. Scientists say the Condor could fly higher than conventional airplanes but well below the orbits of satellites to explore scarcely studied layers of the atmosphere that are critical to global warming and the depletion of the ozone layer that protects the earth.</p>
        <p>In addition, the researchers say, the aircraft could stay aloft for days to explore remote areas of the world where it would be dangerous to send piloted craft as well as to test expensive instruments that would later be flown on satellites.</p>
        <p>"The Condor is really a unique resource, and I'm certainly a scientist who supports saving it," said Dr. William L. Smith, professor of meteorology at the University of Wisconsin at Madison. "Everybody I talk to is appalled by the fact that it may be done away with. The idea of destroying it is criminal, particularly at a time when the Administration is talking about converting military technology to civilian use."</p>
        <p>Scientists have recently begun exploring the idea of using robot aircraft for atmospheric research. The National Aeronautics and Space Administration has commissioned the building of two smaller, far-less-expensive drones to examine the concept. The Means But not the Way</p>
        <p>"The Condor can do many of the things we'd like to do with remote aircraft, and it already exists," said Dr. Adrian F. Tuck of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. "You'll never get the hundreds of millions of dollars it would take to develop a thing like this for scientific research, and that's what makes this so frustrating."</p>
        <p>Dr. Tuck, who is chief of meteorological chemistry at the agency's aeronomy laboratory in Boulder, Colo., added, "Here we have the tool, but we can't seem to figure out the way to use it."</p>
        <p>Boeing and proponents of the Condor have tried for more than two years to get more scientists and Government agencies interested in the plane. But the agencies have been reluctant to pursue the craft because of the estimated $70 million to $100 million cost of converting it to civilian use.</p>
        <p>And the proponents say atmospheric scientists, while acknowledging the plane's potential usefulness, have been slow to get behind the conversion effort until it recently became evident that the craft might be destroyed.</p>
        <p>Last fall, House and Senate conferees appropriated $5 million to store and preserve the Condor and related material. Lawmakers directed the Secretary of Defense to work with NASA and the atmospheric agency to assess whether the plane could be used for environmental research and what the costs would be. One possibility was that several agencies might jointly finance the effort. Results of this study are to be sent to Congress by June 1.</p>
        <p>But spending for this has not been approved by House and Senate committees that oversee classified programs, people in Congress say. The Condor, first flown in 1988, was initially one of the Pentagon's programs that included spy satellites and other top-secret equipment.</p>
        <p>In January, John A. Knauss, then administrator of the atmospheric agency, wrote the National Security Council and asked it to intervene with the military agencies that are in the process of disposing of the Condor.  Noting that Congressional appropriations committees had authorized an assessment of the craft's potential scientific uses, Dr. Knauss wrote that the plane "is being destroyed at a rate faster than the Government can reassess its potential for conversion from a military tool to civilian use."</p>
        <p>Roger Morris, an official with the atmospheric agency, said Friday that it had not yet received a reply to its request from the security council. A White House spokesman for the security council said he was checking on the status of the agency's request.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Koehler, a spokesman for Boeing's Defense and Space Group, declined to say how much the company and the Pentagon had spent on the Condor program. But sources in the industry and the Government familiar with the Condor estimate that Boeing and various Federal agencies have spent more than $300 million to build and test the plane over a decade.  Giant Among Drones</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the Defense Department said they could not comment on the Condor. But documents concerning the program indicate the secretive Defense Support Program Office and the Airborne Reconnaissance Support Program put money into the project.</p>
        <p>Most unmanned drones are about the size of single-engined planes or smaller. By comparison, the 68-foot-long Condor has a wing span of 200 feet and a gross weight of 20,000 pounds. It holds the altitude record for piston-powered aircraft -- 67,028 feet -- and once stayed aloft for two and a half days.</p>
        <p>John Dale of Boeing, who formerly headed flight operations for the aircraft, said: "Everyone who sees it says there is almost no chance that anyone will ever build an aircraft like this for research, and they go away in awe about its potential. This was a technology demonstrator and it would be foolish to throw it away without evaluating it for other uses."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
