<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serenity Amid Chaos: A City Skater's Odyssey</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE SKATING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEBER, BRUCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DA1439F936A25752C0A965958260" item-length="2136" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serenity Amid Chaos: A City Skater's Odyssey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEBER, BRUCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE pleasures of ice skating in New York City are few, its terrors many. I blame this largely on global warming, which, the recent chill stretch notwithstanding, restricts the enterprise to exercise-in-the-round and reduces its grandiose free-spiritedness to something a little more, well, rinky-dink.</p>
        <p>Ice skating, ideally, is travel. But the weather being what it is, you can't even flout the law and zip around on the Central Park lakes anymore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE pleasures of ice skating in New York City are few, its terrors many. I blame this largely on global warming, which, the recent chill stretch notwithstanding, restricts the enterprise to exercise-in-the-round and reduces its grandiose free-spiritedness to something a little more, well, rinky-dink.</p>
        <p>Ice skating, ideally, is travel. But the weather being what it is, you can't even flout the law and zip around on the Central Park lakes anymore.</p>
        <p>Sigh. City living is in many ways, of course, a matter of regularly compromised ideals and it behooves us all to get on with it and compromise effectively. So I spent the last couple of weeks seeking out places to skate and skating on them, hoping to formulate, for lack of a better term, a new, urban-specific skating zen.</p>
        <p>I was taking up the sport again after more than a decade of living in New York. Actually, I bought skates a year ago, but used them only once. The first surprise for anyone doing likewise is that skates have got a lot better -- lighter, more comfortable, more supportive -- than those instruments of ankle and toe torture you remember from when you were a kid. The second surprise is the immediate reward. In skating, unlike, say, tennis or golf, you're noticeably better at it half an hour after you start.</p>
        <p>Anyway, everyone I explained the project to seemed intrigued, reminded that ice skating was something they used to like to do. Thinking I'd hit on a forgotten pleasure, I discovered, in fact, a paradox, akin to what Yogi Berra may or may not have said in reference to a restaurant: "Nobody goes there anymore; it's too crowded."</p>
        <p>Guess what? Skating is popular.</p>
        <p>Not including Madison Square Garden, I found 10 skating rinks in New York City, 6 run by the Parks Department. They are in four boroughs. (The Bronx used to have a couple, but one is now a skateboarding venue, the other a Loehman's department store.) Four are indoors, five are outdoors and one, War Memorial Ice Skating on Staten Island, used to be outdoors but was enclosed in a plastic bubble this past fall.</p>
        <p>The smallest two are, oddly enough, the least congested. (One is Rivergate Ice Rink, which sits in the courtyard of a Manhattan apartment building as if it were a swimming pool and doesn't even have a Zamboni machine; the ice is cleaned manually, by skatemeisters wielding squeegees like push-brooms. The other is the Ice Studio. A loft-sized space on the second floor of an Upper East Side building, it's dangerous with more than half a dozen people on it.) And if you choose your times shrewdly -- at the very beginning or the tail end of a skating session -- you can locate some space at any of them. But in general what they offer in common (aside from the skating surface; to a nonprofessional, ice is more or less ice) is the sensation of being in a familiar nightmare: untrained and unprepared, you've suddenly become an air-traffic controller. Some Can, Most Can't</p>
        <p>The crowds are virtually interchangeable. At any given rink at any given time, only a small minority will really know how to skate, and fewer still how to stop. And the world on skates is divisible into stereotypes at least as much as the world at large. (The people-watching at the rink is invariably good, partly for fashion reasons. You wouldn't believe the colors they make stretch pants in.)</p>
        <p>For example, in the center of every rink, there is an incredibly small female child entertaining a Kristi Yamaguchi fantasy, bent at the waist, skating on one foot, the other held out behind her wavering tentatively like a candle flame. There's generally a grown woman with the same fantasy, except with fur earmuffs, a leopard skirt and black tights. She's likely to have an attitude, and will expect you to get out of her way when she wanders into the free-skating lane with the nose of her skate-blade in the air. (I hope the woman who nearly clipped me under the chin at Rockefeller Center the other morning reads this and gets the message.) There are usually two older men in long coats, wearing those extended-blade skates and cruising along unruffled, Hans Brinker-like, their hands clasped behind their backs. And there are novices of every stripe, whose exclamations make marvelous eavesdropping: "Hey, this is slippery!" or, "I want to go back to Puerto Rico!"</p>
        <p>My favorite is the klatch of teen-age boys, four or five of whom are obviously taking the day off from hockey practice and glide around the rink with humiliating ease, deftly cutting corners, turning abruptly 180 degrees to skate backward a few strokes and ogle a girl, abruptly turning back on one leg and letting their off-blades graze the ice just for the pleasing sound of it. (Sometimes they have a goofy friend who can't skate at all, but who is incredibly good-natured about being pushed around and sprawling on the ice.)</p>
        <p>Mostly, however, there are children, fearless and fearsome, the girls holding onto one another in squealing knots of three or four, the boys tending to venture off on their own, their ankles bent, their faces earnest, pursuing a dream of speed.  Waltzing and Rocking</p>
        <p>This is all conducted at high volume, naturally, which is one reason I prefer the city's outdoor, i.e. echoless, rinks. (The music that is endlessly pumped across the ice is completely unpredictable, I discovered; Sinatra followed by Chopin and Public Enemy. It is in general more intrusive than amenable, in my opinion, though I confess I did find myself unexpectedly waltzing along to "The Blue Danube" the other day.)</p>
        <p>The other reason, of course, is that skating is an outdoor sport, best enjoyed when the temperature is below freezing and the wind occasionally flicks your scarf. Indeed, there is no better reminder that the city was laid down in a wilderness than the view of skyscrapers above trees from Wollman Rink in Central Park as the sun goes down and the amber lights on Fifth Avenue come up. And at Kate Wollman Ice-Skating Rink in Prospect Park in Brooklyn, as you skate away from the entrance you actually see nothing but woods, a brief pastoral adventure repeated on every revolution.</p>
        <p>In fact, it was at Kate Wollman last weekend that I found what I was looking for. It was deep afternoon, the sky slate gray and going quickly black. The rink lights were on and the ice was lightly mobbed, and for a minute I imagined the view from above: a beautiful chaos. Plus, after two weeks of practice I was skating well, leaning hard into turns confident that my blades would hold the ice, darting skittishly off at new and satisfying angles with a flick of one skate or the other. My crossover step had improved, my speed was up. The temperature was in the 20's but I had a pleasing sweat that I could feel in the wind.</p>
        <p>Remember the singer and bandleader Spike Jones? In his crazy act, pies were thrown, horns and sirens went off, glasses were smashed, but amid the comic tumult, the song went on to its conclusion, its harmony and melody unmarred. This is skating in New York. That is, it can be. And as I circled the rink again and again with skaters losing their footing around me, and as I barely, adroitly, managed to miss colliding with one after another, I thought that with life in the city as unbridled, as nuts as it is, what more is there to strive for than controlling myself and making progress? Where to Find the Ice</p>
        <p>Here is a sampling of ice-skating rinks in New York City. Some offer private or group instruction; call for details.</p>
        <p>ABE STARK ICE-SKATING RINK, West 19th Street, between Surf Avenue and the Boardwalk, Coney Island, Brooklyn. Cavernous, noisy, a good-natured mob scene, particularly on weekends. Indoor sessions: Saturday, 12:30 to 4 P.M.; Sunday, noon to 4 P.M.; closed Monday through Friday. Special sessions: Monday, noon to 4:40 P.M.; and Feb. 15-19, noon to 4:30 P.M. Admission: $5.50; skate rentals: $3.50. Information: (718) 946-6536.</p>
        <p>ICE STUDIO, 1034 Lexington Avenue, at 73d Street. Newly reopened after a fire, it's teeny, better suited to kiddie lessons than free skating. But it does have a mirrored wall so you can see how awkward you are. Indoor skating sessions: Tuesday and Thursday, 8:30 A.M. to 10 P.M.; Friday, 5 to 6 and 8:30 to 10 P.M; Saturday, noon to 1 and 5:15 to 6:15 P.M.; Sunday, noon to 1, 2:45 to 3:45 and 5:15 to 6:15 P.M.; closed Wednesdays. Admission: $5 for a one-hour session, or $6 for a one-and-a-half-hour session. Skate rentals: $2.75. Information: (212) 535-0304.</p>
        <p>KATE WOLLMAN ICE-SKATING RINK, Prospect Park, Parkside and Ocean Avenues, Brooklyn. Even though it's often crowded, it still feels roomy, probably because it's set in the woods. Word to the wise: Bring your own locker key. Outdoor sessions: Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Thursday and Friday, 10 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 10 P.M.; Sunday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M.; closed Mondays and Tuesdays. Admission: weekdays, $2; weekends, $2.50 ($1 for children and the elderly at all times). Skate rentals: $3. Information: (718) 965-6561.</p>
        <p>LASKER ICE-SKATING RINK, Central Park near 110th Street and Lenox Avenue. Two rinks, one frequently reserved for hockey leagues. Outdoor sessions: Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 11 P.M.; Sunday, 10 A.M. to 9:30 P.M. Admission: $3 ($1.75 for children under 13 and the elderly). Skate rentals: $2.25 Information: (212) 996-1184</p>
        <p>RIVERGATE ICE RINK, 401 East 34th Street, Manhattan. A small rink, friendly and rather quiet. Good for parents and children. Outdoor sessions: Monday to Friday, noon to 10 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 10 P.M. Admission: $6 ($3 for those under 12 and the elderly). Skate rentals, $3.25. Information: (212) 689-0035.</p>
        <p>ROCKEFELLER PLAZA RINK, between 49th and 50th Streets at Fifth Avenue. A tourist attraction, of course, but still and all rather glamorous. It's also not very crowded early in the morning. Outdoor session: Monday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 1 P.M, 1:30 to 5:30 and 6 to 10 P.M; Friday, 9 A.M to 1 P.M., 1:30 to 5:30 and 6 P.M. to midnight; Saturday, 9 A.M. to noon, 12:30 to 3, 3:30 to 6 and 6:30 P.M. to midnight; Sunday, 9 A.M. to noon, 12:30 to 3, 3:30 to 6 and 6:30 to 10 P.M. Admission: Mondays through Thursdays, $7 ($6 for children and the elderly); Fridays through Sundays, $8 ($6.50 for children and the elderly). Skate rentals: $4. Information: (212) 757-5730.</p>
        <p>SKY RINK, 450 West 33d Street, 16th Floor, Manhattan. A popular spot, it's large enough to reasonably accommodate a Saturday crush. Indoor sessions: Mondays, 12:15 to 1:15 and 8 to 9:45 P.M.; Tuesday and Thursday, 6 to 7:45 P.M.; Wednesday, 12:15 to 1:15, 3:45 to 5:45 and 8 to 9:45 P.M.; Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 12:15 P.M., 1 to 4:45, and 8:30 to 10:45 P.M.; Sunday, 12:30 to 4:45 P.M. Admission: $7.50 for adults ($5 for children and the elderly). Skate rentals: $2.50. Information: (212) 695-6556.</p>
        <p>WAR MEMORIAL ICE SKATING, Clove Lakes Park, Victory Boulevard and Clove Road, Sunnyside, S.I. Enclosed in a plastic dome, it has two rinks, one reserved ostensibly for beginners and small children, but from looking at the crowd it's hard to tell which is which. Sessions: Wednesday, 3:30 to 6 P.M. and 7 to 8:45 P.M.; Friday, 3:30 to 6 P.M. and 7 to 10 P.M.; Saturday, 12:15 to 4:45 P.M. and 7 to 10 P.M.; Sunday, 12:15 to 4:45 P.M. and 7 to 9 P.M.; closed Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays. This Monday, , the rink will be open noon to 4:30 P.M. Admission: $3.50 or $5.50, depending on day and time. Skate rentals: $ 3:50. Information: (718) 720-1010.</p>
        <p>WOLLMAN RINK, Central Park at East 62d Street. Remarkably hassle-free for such a famous public place, it has one of the great urban views. Outdoors, weather permitting. Monday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday to Thursday, 10 A.M. to 9:30 P.M.; Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 11 P.M.; Sunday, 10 A.M. to 9:30 P.M. "Cheapskate Nights," Tuesday and Wednesday after 5 P.M.: $7 admission, including skate rental; $4 for children and the elderly. "Family Nights," Wednesday and Sunday for groups of 5, including one adult, includes admission and skate rentals for everyone for $25. General admission: $6 for adults, $3 for children (under 13) and the elderly. Skate rentals: $3.25. Information: (212) 517-4800.</p>
        <p>WORLD'S FAIR ICE-SKATING RINK, New York City Building, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. The crowds, particularly on weekends, can be forbidding. Indoor sessions: Wednesday, 3 to 5:30 and 8 to 9:30 P.M.; Friday, 1 to 5:30 and 8:30 to 10:30 P.M.; Saturday, noon to 4:30 and 8:30 to 10:30 P.M.; Sunday, noon to 5 and 7 to 9 P.M.; closed Mondays, Tuesdays and Thursdays. Open this Monday, noon to 4 P.M. Admission: $3.50 or $5.50, depending on day and time. Skate rentals: $3.50. Written parental consent is necessary for those under 18. Information: (718) 271-1996.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
