<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Scientists Find a Way To Make Cheaper Methanol</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930124T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="583682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANOL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCIENCE (MAGAZINE)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D71E3EF934A25752C0A965958260" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Scientists Find a Way To Make Cheaper Methanol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of chemists in California has discovered what appears to be a cheaper way to turn natural gas into methanol. If it can be commercialized, the process could create vast supplies of transportation fuel from reserves of gas that cannot now be tapped economically.</p>
        <p>The process is described in the current issue of the journal Science by seven scientists from Catalytica Inc., a company in Mountain View, Calif.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team of chemists in California has discovered what appears to be a cheaper way to turn natural gas into methanol. If it can be commercialized, the process could create vast supplies of transportation fuel from reserves of gas that cannot now be tapped economically.</p>
        <p>The process is described in the current issue of the journal Science by seven scientists from Catalytica Inc., a company in Mountain View, Calif.</p>
        <p>Natural gas is composed primarily of methane, a molecule with a carbon atom at its center and four hydrogen atoms attached. It can be converted to methanol, a liquid, by tearing off one of the hydrogen atoms and replacing it with two atoms that are bonded together, one of oxygen and one of hydrogen. But the process is difficult and expensive because in methane the bond between the carbon atom and the hydrogen atoms is very strong.</p>
        <p>The use of methanol in vehicles is increasing in this country because it creates fewer of the pollutants that cause smog, although it produces other forms of pollution. Burning it in automobiles requires modified fuel pumps, seals and lubricants, but those technical challenges have already been overcome. A Mix With Gasoline</p>
        <p>It can also be used as a raw material to make methyl tertiary butyl ether, which can be mixed with gasoline in conventional cars.</p>
        <p>By 1994 the capacity to produce methanol will be three times what it was at the beginning of last year, according to David A. Zinamon, a fuels expert at Petroleum Industry Research Associates, a consulting firm in New York.</p>
        <p>The world market for methanol could become tight in the middle of this decade, he said, and a new technology would be useful in meeting new demand, although world use of methanol is not expected to increase greatly. Methanol cannot compete with gasoline on the basis of price in this country; a gallon of gasoline sells at wholesale, before taxes, at 50 cents, but a quantity of methanol that delivers the same amount of energy costs 80 cents, Mr. Zinamon said.</p>
        <p>Natural gas reserves nearly equal oil reserves in energy value. But bringing natural gas to market would require huge capital investments. The North Slope of Alaska, for example, has substantial gas reserves, but there is no pipeline to the lower 48 states, and the price of liquefying the gas for tanker shipment is far too high to be justified under current market conditions. Use of Catalyst</p>
        <p>The new system uses a catalyst, a material that speeds up a chemical reaction but is not consumed by it. In this case, a form of mercury with an electric charge is used.</p>
        <p>"You can buy this off the shelf," Roy A. Periana, the project leader at Catalytica, said in a telephone interview. "Any chemist can do this reaction."</p>
        <p>At one point in the process the reaction produces sulfuric acid, and at another it makes sulfur dioxide, but both those chemicals are consumed in later steps. The process occurs at temperatures far lower than conventional methods for making methanol.</p>
        <p>But another researcher, Professor John J. Thomas of the Florida Institute of Technology, warned that the need for acid-resistant containers could drive costs up. In addition, he said, even when a process has been demonstrated on a laboratory scale, substantial engineering work is needed before a pilot plant can be built. "Those two things kill a lot of processes," he said.</p>
        <p>In the Catalytica process, the ingredients required are methane and oxygen from air; at the end it yields methanol, along with carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Periana said that so far chemists had carried on the process in liter quantities.</p>
        <p>"We would not want to represent that it's ready for commercialization, but it is a significant improvement in science, a breakthrough," he said.</p>
        <p>Catalytica has filed documents in preparation for a public sale of stock, and Dr. Periana said that as a result he could not discuss the commercial possibilities in detail.</p>
        <p>The research was financed by Petro Canada and Mitsubishi Oil, he said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 24, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about a new process for converting natural gas to methanol misidentified a chemical. From 1992 to 1994 the United States is expected to triple its capacity to make methyl tertiary butyl ether, which is derived from methanol, not to triple the capacity to make methanol itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 24, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about a new process for converting natural gas to methanol misidentified a chemical. From 1992 to 1994 the United States is expected to triple its capacity to make methyl tertiary butyl ether, which is derived from methanol, not to triple the capacity to make methanol itself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
