<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON TAKES OATH AS 42D PRESIDENT, URGING SACRIFICE TO 'RENEW AMERICA'</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930122T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="584587"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE INAUGURATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INAUGURATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTS AND PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D8163CF932A15752C0A965958260" item-length="2281" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON TAKES OATH AS 42D PRESIDENT, URGING SACRIFICE TO 'RENEW AMERICA'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>William Jefferson Clinton became the 42d President of the United States today, and in an Inaugural Address striking in its appeal for sacrifice, he told Americans that if they assume greater responsibility for their country's future, "there is nothing wrong with America that cannot be cured by what is right with America."</p>
        <p>The 46-year-old Governor of Arkansas, virtually unknown to most Americans 18 months ago and a long shot for the White House, took the oath of office under a stunningly blue sky from Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist. President George Herbert Walker Bush, who once seemed sure to win a second term, watched stoically from his seat on the Capitol steps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>William Jefferson Clinton became the 42d President of the United States today, and in an Inaugural Address striking in its appeal for sacrifice, he told Americans that if they assume greater responsibility for their country's future, "there is nothing wrong with America that cannot be cured by what is right with America."</p>
        <p>The 46-year-old Governor of Arkansas, virtually unknown to most Americans 18 months ago and a long shot for the White House, took the oath of office under a stunningly blue sky from Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist. President George Herbert Walker Bush, who once seemed sure to win a second term, watched stoically from his seat on the Capitol steps.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Clinton's left hand, his wife, Hillary, held a King James Bible given to Mr. Clinton by his grandmother. His 12-year-old daughter, Chelsea, stood at his right as he uttered the traditional oath at 11:58 A.M. Eastern time. He then spoke for 14 minutes to a sea of people, flowing down from the flag-draped Western facade of the Capitol to the Washington Monument. 'What America Does Best'</p>
        <p>"We must do what America does best: offer more opportunity to all and demand more responsibility from all," Mr. Clinton declared in an echo of John F. Kennedy's Inaugural Address. "It is time to break the bad habit of expecting something for nothing, from our Government or from each other. Let us all take more responsibility, not only for ourselves and our families but for our communities and our country."</p>
        <p>In a speech with the recurring theme of renewal, Mr. Clinton implored at one point: "To renew America we must be bold. We must do what no generation has had to do before."  [ Transcript, page A15. ]</p>
        <p>Washington never looked better, or felt better. Cheerful chaos reigned on the streets, in a subway system that is usually weirdly sedate and on the Mall, in front of the Capitol, where something like a quarter of a million people endured mobs and metal detectors and midwinter chill. Schools and Federal offices had a quadrennial holiday, so natives joined tourists beneath a Capitol that was dressed for the day in gowns of red, white and blue, and glittered in the January sun. Walk Through the Crowd</p>
        <p>In a day of ceremonies intended to be casual and intimate -- with lots of Presidential bear hugs for friends and a conscious assertion of the passing of power to the post-World War II generation -- the Clintons walked the last few blocks down Pennsylvania Avenue from the Capitol to the White House. Before the Clintons decided to get out of their new armor-plated Cadillac, the crowds along the route were chanting: "Walk! Walk!"</p>
        <p>From the viewing stand in front of the White House's iron gates, the Clintons watched a politically inclusive parade, encompassing everyone from Arkansas bands to gay groups to Elvis impersonators -- like the rest of the inaugural as meticulously scripted as any Hollywood production. Throughout, Mr. Clinton wore the amazed grin of a man whose lifelong dream had just come true.</p>
        <p>The flag-waving crowds along the parade route were striking both for their enthusiasm and their racial diversity. The upbeat mood of the well-wishers seemed on track with that of recent national polls -- one of guarded optimism about Mr. Clinton's prospects, coupled with a strong desire to give the new President a chance. Short, Informal Speech</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's Inaugural Address, far more compact than the lengthy oratory of his long 1988 Democratic National Convention speech, was informal and almost conversational.</p>
        <p>It was typical of the New Age political style that helped him win the highest office in the land. While Mr. Clinton paid homage to many of the themes that won him the election -- the need for renewal, health-care reform, economic revival and political reform -- his address was not an agenda for action, but rather a call to service.</p>
        <p>"You, my fellow Americans, have forced the spring," he said. "Now we must do the work the season demands."</p>
        <p>The address was at times brutally frank in its assessment of the decline of the country under Mr. Bush and in its chastising of an aloof and self-absorbed Congress, as well as an apathetic American public.</p>
        <p>"We know we have to face hard truths and take strong steps. But we have not done so," said Mr. Clinton, who wore a dark blue suit and no top coat as he spoke on the chilly winter day. "Instead, we have drifted, and that drifting has eroded our resources, fractured our economy, and shaken our confidence.</p>
        <p>"Thomas Jefferson believed that to preserve the very foundations of our nation, we would need dramatic change from time to time. Well, my fellow Americans, this is our time. Let us embrace it. Our democracy must be not only the envy of the world but the engine of our own renewal. There is nothing wrong with America that cannot be cured by what is right with America."</p>
        <p>In the age of satellite communications, which Mr. Clinton put to such good use during the campaign, the new President used his address to speak not only to the hundreds of thousands gathered before him, but also to America's allies and enemies over the horizon. He signaled the world in general, and President Saddam Hussein of Iraq in particular, that while America renewed itself at home it would not abandon its responsibilities abroad.</p>
        <p>"Together with our friends and allies, we will work to shape change, lest it engulf us," said Mr. Clinton, speaking behind a shield of bullet-proof glass. "When our vital interests are challenged, or the will and conscience of the international community is defied, we will act, with peaceful diplomacy whenever possible, with force when necessary." Transfer of Power</p>
        <p>A moment after being sworn in, Mr. Clinton turned and shook hands with Mr. Bush. Their eyes locked for three seconds as they pumped each other's hands in what appeared in many ways to be the real passing of authority. At that moment, Mr. Bush's military aide carrying the locked briefcase of nuclear-warfare codes, and standing on the podium behind him, began taking orders from a new Commander in Chief.</p>
        <p>While every inauguration celebrates the peaceful transfer of power that is the hallmark of American democracy, in the case of Mr. Bush and Mr. Clinton that transfer is all the more amazing. Eighteen months ago, Mr. Bush was at the peak of his political power, the victorious commander of a successful and unusually painless war in the Persian Gulf, riding the crest of polls with 80 percent approval ratings. Most serious Democrat did not believe there was any sense in even trying to challenge him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was then Governor of one of the nation's poorest states, worrying about getting a one-cent sales tax through his legislature, but also burning with enough ambition to set off against Mr. Bush when more cautious Democrats hesitated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton got his reward today. About 1 P.M., he and his wife waved from the Capitol steps as Mr. Bush and his wife, Barbara, flew off by helicopter to an early retirement in Houston -- while a United Van Lines trailer with Arkansas license plates was backing into the White House driveway to move in the Clintons' belongings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Clinton had to work closely during the transition to deal with foreign-policy crises in Haiti and Iraq, and it may have left them with a measure of mutual respect undetectable in their bitter election campaign, when Mr. Bush once dismissed Mr. Clinton as a "bozo" who knew less about foreign affairs than Millie, the Bushes' dog. Salute to Bush</p>
        <p>At the top of his address Mr. Clinton hailed Mr. Bush, saying: "On behalf of our nation, I salute my predecessor, President Bush, for his half-century of service to America."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's inauguration represents not only a change in Presidents and parties but also of generations. The generation symbolized by President Bush was shaped by the patriotism of World War II, sobered by the deprivations of the Great Depression and serenaded by the music of Frank Sinatra.</p>
        <p>It now gives way to a fortysomething crowd who were born into politics during the idealistic, prosperous era of John F. Kennedy, but forged their identities singing along with Bob Dylan through the troublesome seasons of Vietnam, Watergate and acid rain.</p>
        <p>For the first time America has a President and Vice President younger than the Beatles. At age 46, Mr. Clinton is the third youngest President. Only his idol John F. Kennedy, who took office in 1961 at 43, and Theodore Roosevelt, who took office at 42, were younger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's fellow baby-boomer and now Vice President, Al Gore, the 44-year-old former Senator from Tennessee, was sworn in by Justice Byron R. White, as his wife, Tipper, and his four children crowded around. Mr. Gore had chosen the retired Justice Thurgood Marshall, but Mr. Marshall was too ill and had to beg off at the last minute.</p>
        <p>There were 14 official balls and who knows how many unofficial ones tonight, including an "Inaugural Ball for the Not Well Connected" and an affair sponsored by MTV, the only one where women showed up with bats tatooed on their bare backs.</p>
        <p>"Everybody here knows that MTV had a lot to do with the Clinton-Gore victory," Mr. Clinton told the rock-loving crowd, where attire ranged from prom dresses to ripped jeans.</p>
        <p>The MTV crowd greeted the Clintons like celebrities, surging forward with enthusiasm when they appeared. But Tipper Gore, who has opposed violent and sexually suggestive rock lyrics, was visibly shaken when she was booed as she approached a microphone.</p>
        <p>Presidential reserve was thrown to the winds at a ball with fellow Arkansans. The new President grabbed a saxophone from the rhythm and blues musician Ben E. King and played a solo, then topped of a little speech with the Arkansas football holler, "Soooooweeeee, Razorbacks."</p>
        <p>In his speech in the afternoon, Mr. Clinton said, "Today, a generation raised in the shadows of the cold war assumes new responsibilities in a world warmed by the sunshine of freedom but threatened still by ancient hatreds and new plagues. Raised in unrivaled prosperity, we inherit an economy that is still the world's strongest, but weakened by business failures, stagnant wages, increasing inequality and deep divisions among our own people."</p>
        <p>In a line that appeared directed most at the politically reform-minded supporters of Ross Perot, Mr. Clinton included in his address a swipe at the politicians, lobbyists and political forces that he said had made Washington a city synonymous with corruption.</p>
        <p>"This beautiful capital, like every capital since the dawn of civilization, is often a place of intrigue and calculation," Mr. Clinton said, with Senators and Congressmen gathered on the Capitol steps behind him. "Powerful people maneuver for position and worry endlessly about who is in and who is out, who is up and who is down, forgetting those people whose toil and sweat sends us here and pays our way. Americans deserve better." Biblical Flourish</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton then closed with a rhetorical flourish, that blended the Biblical with the political: "From this joyful mountaintop of celebration, we hear a call to service in the valley. We have heard the trumpets. We have changed the guard. And now, each in our own way, and with God's help, we must answer the call."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's first official act was to sign an executive order imposing his new, much stricter ethical standards on senior officials in his Administration, and another order proclaiming Friday as a "national day of fellowship and hope." He also signed nominating papers for his Cabinet appointees.</p>
        <p>Republicans, wary of being drowned in what they see as a reservoir of goodwill greeting Mr. Clinton's inauguration, despite his occasionally rocky transition to power, pledged their cooperation.</p>
        <p>"I think he is going to have a lot of good will," said Senate Minority Leader Bob Dole, who just returned from a Florida vacation. "I was running on the beach and I saw a lot of people and they would shout at me: 'Give him a chance, give him a chance.' So this is Clinton's moment and we won't do anything to interfere with it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's day began, as his term begins, with a focus not on the domestic issues which got him elected but on the foreign crises which threaten to divert his attention. He was briefed at Blair House, one last time, by Brent Scowcroft, President Bush's national security adviser, on the state of the world he is about to inherit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton walked out of Blair House, gripping a mug of decaffeinated coffee, for the short drive to the Metropolitan African Methodist Episcopal Church, a prominent black Baptist church in downtown Washington. A Laugh and a Tear</p>
        <p>While the chorus gave a rousing rendition of the hymns "Holy Ground" and "Precious Lord Take My Hand," Mr. Clinton laughed, nodded, and sang along, dabbing a tear on his left cheek.</p>
        <p>President Bush began his last day in the White House by making a solitary walk around the South Lawn and then returning to the Oval Office to write a note to leave behind for Mr. Clinton, as Ronald Reagan had done with Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reagan's note said: "Don't let the Turkeys get you down." Mr. Bush would not say what his note said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's inauguration was closed by a poem read by his favorite poet, Maya Angelou, who wrote "On the Pulse of Morning" to celebrate Mr. Clinton's inauguration as the dawn of a new era of national unity. It ended with the verses:</p>
        <p>Here, on the pulse of this new day</p>
        <p>You may have the grace to look up and out</p>
        <p>And into your sister's eyes, and into</p>
        <p>Your brother's face, your country</p>
        <p>And say simply</p>
        <p>Very simply</p>
        <p>With hope --</p>
        <p>Good morning.</p>
        <p>THE INAUGURATION  Correction:  January 22, 1993, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the inauguration of President Clinton referred incorrectly to the church where Mr. Clinton attended a morning prayer service. It is African Methodist Episcopal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 22, 1993, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the inauguration of President Clinton referred incorrectly to the church where Mr. Clinton attended a morning prayer service. It is African Methodist Episcopal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
