<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Uncle Smoke to Mr. Clean</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH SUMMIT CONFERENCE (RIO DE JANEIRO)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN COMMUNITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD7123AF930A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Uncle Smoke to Mr. Clean</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gregg Easterbrook;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro last summer everyone knew who the heroes and villains were. Environmentalists and foreign diplomats decried failures by the U.S. contingent and praised European leadership. But since then, as the few people who have observed the fate of the Rio accords are aware, almost everything about the treaty has been stood on its head.</p>
        <p>At Rio, the European Commission, representing Western Europe as a bloc, wanted a legally binding treaty that required each country's emissions of carbon dioxide, the principal greenhouse gas, to be stabilized at 1990 levels by the year 2000. The Bush Administration opposed a binding pact, saying that each country should set reduction goals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro last summer everyone knew who the heroes and villains were. Environmentalists and foreign diplomats decried failures by the U.S. contingent and praised European leadership. But since then, as the few people who have observed the fate of the Rio accords are aware, almost everything about the treaty has been stood on its head.</p>
        <p>At Rio, the European Commission, representing Western Europe as a bloc, wanted a legally binding treaty that required each country's emissions of carbon dioxide, the principal greenhouse gas, to be stabilized at 1990 levels by the year 2000. The Bush Administration opposed a binding pact, saying that each country should set reduction goals.</p>
        <p>The Brazilian news magazine Veja called the U.S. "Uncle Smoke" and the "Earth Summit enemy." Carlos Ripa di Meanna of Italy, the chief European Community environmental official, boycotted the meeting in protest against the American position. Apparently he couldn't bear to be on the same continent with those who would not endorse binding reductions.</p>
        <p>When the moderate U.S. proposal won out, the community nations thumbed their noses at Washington with a self-congratulatory ceremony in which they vowed to affirm binding reductions as a group. For their noble promise, they were warmly praised by Senator Al Gore and many others.</p>
        <p>The Europeans acted as though treaty maneuvers came to a conclusion at Rio. Actually, the meeting was only a beginning. All that happened was that world leaders signed declarations of sentiment. It was up to each country to ratify the agreement and to submit to U.N. oversight of its emission reductions.</p>
        <p>So what has happened? The U.S. Senate ratified the treaty in October and immediately filed it with the U.N. In April, President Clinton committed the U.S. to stabilizing greenhouse gas emissions at 1990 levels. The specifics of his plan are due this month.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the European Community has not ratified the treaty or taken any action as a group. The legislatures of Germany and Denmark tentatively approved the Rio pact but neither country has committed to the U.N. Meeting in June in Copenhagen, the community's Council of Environmental Ministers quietly tabled until December any discussion of when they might propose ratification. The German Environment Minister, Klaus Topfer, acknowledged that the situation makes the community appear "foolish, if not actually devious."</p>
        <p>Yet the total reversal of roles has been overlooked. One explanation is that the pleasure of bashing the U.S. -- a knee-jerk impulse of global-warming politics -- is missing. Another reason is that the Bush Administration's position now seems inconveniently reasonable. Environmentalists cannot abide by this notion. And Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore, having campaigned on the theme that George Bush was an environmental charlatan, have no incentive to acknowledge that one of his major environmental decisions is bearing up well under the test of time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush deserves credit for his sensible position. President Clinton deserves credit for turning that position into a commitment. They have transformed the U.S. from "Uncle Smoke" into the world leader in action against the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>The legacy of Rio includes many questions that have gone unasked.  The most revealing: Will stabilization of carbon emissions really prevent global warming? Not a snowball's chance in, well, Alberta, should the warming occur.</p>
        <p>New policies holding U.S. emissions at the 1990 level in the year 2000 would prevent 100 million metric tons of carbon from being released that year, the White House says. This would represent about 1.4 percent of the expected world emissions. Since naturally occurring carbon emissions outpace man-made emissions by about 29 to 1, U.S. cutbacks would dilute the reduction to just 0.05 percent of total carbon entering the atmosphere. It's inconceivable that this will have any significant effect on temperatures.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, President Clinton was wise to bind the U.S. to the 1990 goal. If an artificial greenhouse effect is coming, society must start learning how to reduce carbon dioxide emissions. And these reductions can be realized mainly through conserving fossil fuels. This can be done at a net profit for society, with energy savings more than offsetting the cost of conservation technology.</p>
        <p>There is also the question of how carbon dioxide reductions will be met. Susan Tierney, an Assistant Secretary of Energy, told Congress in May that the plan might include giving U.S. companies credit toward their emission-reduction targets if they help developing countries cut down their emissions. American companies are sure to find inefficient third world factories from which tons of emissions can be eliminated more cheaply than from their U.S. facilities. Environmentalists oppose this plan, asserting that it violates Mr. Clinton's promise to cut American carbon dioxide output.</p>
        <p>The President ought to embrace Ms. Tierney's sound proposal. After all, the goal of the Rio treaty is to avert a greenhouse effect. All that matters is that tons of carbon emissions are avoided around the world.</p>
        <p>Of course, there was at Rio and remains today a faction for whom the greenhouse issue is more about ceremonial guilt-tripping than reform. It's amazing to think that the leader of that faction is now the European Commission.  Gregg Easterbrook, a contributing editor of Newsweek and the Atlantic Monthly, is author of the forthcoming "A Moment on the Earth," a book about the environmental movement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gregg Easterbrook, a contributing editor of Newsweek and the Atlantic Monthly, is author of the forthcoming "A Moment on the Earth," a book about the environmental movement.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
