<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597480"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D7143EF931A15750C0A965958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A2-9 RUSSIAN CONGRESS STRIKES BACK</p>
        <p>A shaken Russian Parliament resolved to take Boris N. Yeltsin to the Constitutional Court, but the angry legislators stopped short of directly moving against him or trying to block the emergency powers he claimed against them.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A2-9 RUSSIAN CONGRESS STRIKES BACK</p>
        <p>A shaken Russian Parliament resolved to take Boris N. Yeltsin to the Constitutional Court, but the angry legislators stopped short of directly moving against him or trying to block the emergency powers he claimed against them.  A1</p>
        <p>CLASH OF FUTURE AND THE PAST</p>
        <p>As demonstrators gathered in Moscow, their mood reflected a deep division in Russian society between those loyal to President Yeltsin and his programs and those who blame him for the collapse of a way of life that they still hold sacred.  A1 The White House is trying to temper support for President Yeltsin.  A9 European leaders cautiously sided with Russia's President.  A9 U.N. OFFICER SEEKS A TRADE</p>
        <p>The U.N. military chief in Bosnia was seeking an accord under which Bosnia would let Serbs leave the Government-held city of Tuzla in return for allowing food shipments past the Serbian forces besieging a Muslim-held city in the east.  A6 FRENCH SOCIALISTS LOSE AT POLLS</p>
        <p>The governing Socialists of France suffered a crushing defeat in the first round of parliamentary elections. President Mitterrand, whose second term ends in May 1995, now seems certain to name a conservative Prime Minister after runoff elections next Sunday.  A1 CLINTON'S FOREIGN POLICY STYLE</p>
        <p>President Clinton is now ready to be seen as more involved with foreign policy, and is being forced to do so by tumultuous world events, but aides still describe his management style as one of setting broad guidelines and paying spasmodic attention to different issues.A3 ISRAEL IS TIGHTENING SECURITY</p>
        <p>With death tolls rising and many Israelis worried that violence is spinning out of control, the Government decided to expand the national police force and to tighten security checks on Palestinians leaving the occupied territories for work in Israel.  A3 Opposition and religious leaders assailed El Salvador's amnesty.  A2 Mexico City voted on how its local government should be chosen.  A2 Kampala Journal: Asians expelled in the 1970's are returning.  A4 National A10-15, B8 RESCUE PLAN FOR AIRLINES</p>
        <p>The Administration is considering help for the struggling airline industry in a broad approach that may include loan guarantees, tax relief and the lifting of the restrictions on foreign ownership.  A1 WHAT PRICE CLEANUP?</p>
        <p>Almost five years after Congress banned such practices, some argue that that dumping sewage in the Atlantic was less hazardous than most of the disposal methods that replaced it.  A1 Second thoughts about the acid rain rules enacted in 1990.  B8 THREAT TO TOBACCO GROWERS</p>
        <p>Tobacco farmers have weathered increasing health scares and anti-smoking sentiment, but the Clinton Administration may finally prove to be their downfall.  A1 A brief history of Federal subsidies to tobacco growers.A14 PRIME-TIME CONTRARIAN</p>
        <p>Ross Perot bought himself another $500,000 of network television time and served notice on America that he intends to keep playing the political game, all-out.  A10 Doctors go to Washington to seek a voice on health care reform.  A13 SHUTTLE MISSION BLURS</p>
        <p>As NASA prepares for a shuttle launching, the nation's fleet of winged spaceships appears increasingly adrift without a real job.  A13 Executive Brief: Will Janet Reno be able to chart her own course? A15 MORE BASE CLOSINGS CONSIDERED</p>
        <p>The commission deciding the fate of military bases will consider closing or shrinking several more than the Pentagon has recommended, including the two in California spared by the Defense Secretary.  A10 7 MORE LEAVE CULT COMPOUND</p>
        <p>Three weeks after a gunfight between the Branch Davidians and Federal agents, seven more sect members left their compound.  A12 Metro Digest B1 EFFORT TO EASE BITTERNESS</p>
        <p>Korean business owners in New York are using the strength of their numbers to try to increase their political influence, improve their business opportunities and, perhaps most important, mend their often bitter relations with other ethnic groups in the city.  A1 Arts/Entertainment C11-18 New boss at the Shakespeare Festival.  C11 Theater: "Jersey Girls." C14 "The Arrangement." C14 Music: Christa Ludwig recital.  C11 James Brown at Radio City.  C11 Chris McBride's jazz.  C12 Aviva Players.  C15 "The Bundle Man." C15 Elvis Costello at Town Hall.  C15 "Traviata" cast changes.  C16 Rap at Radio City.  C16 Dance: The Ballet du Rhin in Washington.  C11 Dance in Review C12 Word and Image: Austin Wright's "Tony and Susan." C15 Business Digest D1 Obituaries D8 Sports C1-10 Auto Racing: Mansell wins.  C3 Baseball: Mets not worried.  C4 Muelens after full-time job.  C4 Marlins look to Destrade.  C4 Basketball: Knicks romp.  C1 Michigan edges U.C.L.A.  C1 Kentucky routs Utah.  C1 Column: Vecsey on Rangers.  C2 Football: Giants sign Bailey.  C8 Golf: Crenshaw triumphs.  C3 Horse Racing: Which way to Louisville?  C6 Hockey: Devils beat Flyers.  C2 Tennis: Sampras wins Lipton.  C3 Editorials/Op-Ed A16-17 Editorials To the barricades with Yeltsin. Tough talk on open skies. Let this home port die. A welcome signal on college aid. Letters Anthony Lewis: The catharsis of truth. William Safire: Obey the law of S.&amp; D. Abraham Brumberg: Yeltsin's dangerous game. Bradford R. McGuinn: Why the fundamentalists are winning.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
