<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D91031F937A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-17  SIGNED, SEALED AND SHAKEN</p>
        <p>Months of secret negotiations were sealed with signatures and perhaps even more significantly, handshakes, when Israeli and Palestinian leaders met on the South Lawn of the White House.  A1  Dancing, toasts and resignation in Jericho, Israel and Syria.  A17</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-17  SIGNED, SEALED AND SHAKEN</p>
        <p>Months of secret negotiations were sealed with signatures and perhaps even more significantly, handshakes, when Israeli and Palestinian leaders met on the South Lawn of the White House.  A1  Dancing, toasts and resignation in Jericho, Israel and Syria.  A17</p>
        <p>CLINTON'S BURDEN NOW</p>
        <p>After the secret meetings, the drama and the pageantry comes the diplomatic drudgery, and in this case, both the Israelis and the Palestinians have made it clear they will be leaning on President Clinton.  A1  Insomnia, indecisiveness and incredulity behind the scenes.  A1  Arafat comes armed -- with two olive branches.  A15  VIETNAM EMBARGO IS RELAXED</p>
        <p>In a further easing of its economic stance, Washington said that American companies could bid on construction and development projects financed by international lending institutions in Vietnam.  A10  SOMALIA, WHERE PEACE IS SCARCE</p>
        <p>Peacekeepers are everywhere in Mogadishu, the capital of Somalia, but peace itself remains elusive. Heavy weapons are in evdience, United Nations troops are ambushed on patrols and clans settle their differences with bullets.  A3  WORLD COURT RULES ON BOSNIA</p>
        <p>The World Court did not grant Bosnia's request to be exempted from the United Nations arms embargo, but it did demand immediate compliance from Belgrade with orders to cease committing or sponsoring acts of genocide in Bosnia.  A5  A new Japanese economic stimulus plan expected.  A7 Mexican leaders are trying to change election laws.  A8 China releases one of its best-known dissidents.  A6 Gyor Journal: Profit and risk on the eastern frontier.  A4  National A18-23  BLUE-COLLAR VIEW OF TRADE PACT  If there is an emotional heart to the movement against the North American Free Trade Agreement, it may be in Flint, Mich., among the auto workers who fear that the agreement is one more devastating blow to a way of life.  A18  PARKS PLAN TO REQUIRE INSURANCE  In what could be the first step in ultimately charging a range of fees for recreational use of public land, the National Park Service announced it was going to require mountain climbers to pay for rescue missions.  A18  SMITHSONIAN DIRECTOR TO RETIRE  Robert Adams, the ninth person to head the Smithsonian Institution in its 147-year history, announced that he would retire next year and return to writing and teaching.  A20  LAST YEAR'S PROBLEMS PLAGUE BILL  Caught in election politics, a major crime bill died last year as Republicans and Democrats refused to compromise on capital punishment and gun control. This year was supposed to be different, but officials are expressing reservations about the bill's prospects.  A22  STUDY FINDS DAY-CARE SHORTAGE  Working-class parents in the South and Midwest have the greatest difficulties in finding preschools in their neighborhoods, according to a study by the Harvard Graduate School of Education.  A20  OLD ARGUMENTS USED IN GAY CASE  The Clinton Administration, using legal arguments that Bill Clinton the candidate had sharply criticized, appeared in court to defend the old policy that banned homosexuals from the military.  A23  PUSH TO END HOUSE SECRECY RULE  Fueled by the support of Ross Perot and conservative talk show hosts, Republicans are gaining ground in an effort to gut an arcane House procedural rule that allows members to block legislation in secret while supporting it in public.  A22  A judge dismissed a suit filed by apple growers against CBS.  A21  Metro Digest B1  Sports B11-17  Baseball: Steinbrenner lays down challenge.  B13  Phillies shut out Mets.  B13  Basketball: Equality dispute costs coach her job.  B11  Boxing: Judge's misunderstanding may have hurt Whitaker.  B14  Columns: Moran on Lou Holtz.  B11  On Baseball B13  On Pro Football B14  TV Sports B17  Football: Giants' defense a pleasant surprise.  B14  Jets rally round Esiason.  B14  Hostetler boosts Raiders.  B15  Browns defeat 49ers.  B15  Hockey: Devils' coach relaxes atmosphere.  B17  Sports People B16  Tennis: Not an Open to remember.  B17  Track and Field: Another record for Chinese women.  B13  Obituaries B9  Raymond Burr, actor.</p>
        <p>Rita Karin, actress.</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1  Fashion Page B10  Brave new jeans warriors.  Patterns  Science Times C1-9  War of words in the controversy over global warming heats up.  C1  Jocelyn Elders promises to be an outspoken Surgeon General.  C1  Migraine headaches are yielding some genetic clues.  C1  Questions raised about overuse of laparascopic appendectomies.  C3  The "truck gardens" of ancient Mexico City to flourish anew.  C4  Personal ComputersC6  Q&amp;A C8  Peripherals C8  Arts/Entertainment C11-16  Tharp shows her creative process.  C11  Music: Music Notes C11 City Opera's "Mikado." C11  Carole King at the Beacon.  C12  Nyro at the Bottom Line.  C12  Ney Matogrosso.  C14  Dance: Saz Dance Theater.  C14  Books: "Sleeping Beauties," by Susanna Moore.  C15  Television: John Larroquette and Bill Hicks.  C16  Editorials/Op-Ed A24-25  Editorials  "Enough!"  Illiterate Americans.  New York City primary choices.  Letters  A. M. Rosenthal: Now, what Arabs can do.  Russell Baker: Mercy on us all!  Rashid Khalidi: Blind curves and detours on the road to self-rule. Chronicle B5 Bridge C16 Crossword C15</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
