<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Sisterly Guidance For a Coach</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="598537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COACHES AND MANAGERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HUGGINS, BOB</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VAN EXEL, NICK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DA1F3DF93BA15750C0A965958260" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Sisterly Guidance For a Coach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Bobby Knight was coaching at West Point, he used to slip off to the Catskills to visit with Clair Bee, the venerable basketball coach and author, who was retired up in the hills. Bobby Huggins, this generation's tough-minded young coach from the Midwest, has learned a thing or two from Sister Maria Helene.</p>
        <p>"She was the head of the education department at Walsh College," Huggins said, referring to his first head coaching job in Canton, Ohio. "She used to say that the best way to teach something is to repeat it."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Bobby Knight was coaching at West Point, he used to slip off to the Catskills to visit with Clair Bee, the venerable basketball coach and author, who was retired up in the hills. Bobby Huggins, this generation's tough-minded young coach from the Midwest, has learned a thing or two from Sister Maria Helene.</p>
        <p>"She was the head of the education department at Walsh College," Huggins said, referring to his first head coaching job in Canton, Ohio. "She used to say that the best way to teach something is to repeat it."</p>
        <p>This little gem of teaching technique came up as Cincinnati prepared for today's Eastern final with North Carolina. Nick Van Exel, the resident gunner, described how he agrees to disagree with Huggins, his coach.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes I have to tune him out," Van Exel said. "If I miss a layup, I know it."</p>
        <p>"He hears me," Huggins insisted. "I've been known to repeat things over and over again. Sister Maria Helene also told me to write things down, so we do that, too."</p>
        <p>Still, Van Exel said the Cincinnati players sometimes call a meeting to ask Huggins to take a chill. Since sports are sometimes blamed for everything from global warming to scoliosis, it is kind of neat to hear about a dialogue like this.</p>
        <p>College basketball sometimes seems to consist mostly of unappealing bullies like Knight of Indiana and unapologetic dictators like John Thompson of Georgetown. ("Pops don't run no democracy," said Thompson's own son, Ronnie, who chose to play for his dad nonetheless.)</p>
        <p>The screamers have had a tough year, what with Lou Campanelli being fired in mid-season from the University of California. Then there is the quietly manipulative Dean Smith, who is so upright and chatty and liberal that he obscures the fact that he don't run no democracy, either. It will be good for North Carolina to face two pressing teams like Arkansas and Cincinnati 36 hours apart. Dean said so yesterday. So did his players, oddly enough.</p>
        <p>"Coach runs meetings at odd moments like 1:46," said Randy Wiel, the personable assistant. "He says if he calls a meeting at 1 P.M., that's too general, but 1:46 is specific. And he says his clock is Big Ben. The players get there early, just in case."</p>
        <p>Most coaches set up a "my way or the highway" pose. Huggins surely learned from his father, Charles, who reached the Ohio state high school finals eight times with Strasburg and Gradenhutten Indian Valley South. There was also Sister Maria Helene. Huggins had a master's degree by then, and had no problem talking with educators at the tiny school.</p>
        <p>Huggins does not exactly run a loose ship. His wavy hair is always perfectly in place (although he has agreed to a major cranial shave if Cincinnati goes to the Final Four). His don't-mess-with-me smirk is also in place, slightly more benign since his trip to the Final Four last year. Huggins gives the dickens to officials. They all do, I suppose.</p>
        <p>What's more, he yanked Van Exel from the game for blowing a layup midway through the second half. Van Exel is merely an 18.2 points-per-game shooter, with the green light to keep on flinging 3-pointers, but you have to be in the lineup to shoot.</p>
        <p>"He's real intense," Van Exel said. "Sometimes he can get on your nerves. He gets real emotional. The seniors talk to him about it sometimes. Bawl me out. But not for five minutes."</p>
        <p>Well, it was Van Exel's bad luck that he was benched during a television timeout, which can last forever. When he got back on the court, he ran to the other side and tuned out the coach. Or is it more complicated than that?</p>
        <p>"He's made me a better player," Van Exel admitted yesterday. "In high school and junior college, I was the man. I was never forced to play defense. When I first came here, I didn't like it. I was thinking of transferring, but I'm glad I stayed. You can ask him questions. We talk like gentlemen."</p>
        <p>Gender may have nothing to do with it. Huggins said he must listen to his players because "If you ask them a question like 'What are you doing out there?' you'd better listen to the answer. Otherwise, don't ask. I think that's healthy. All the problems in life come from lack of communication."</p>
        <p>He didn't say if he learned that from Charles Huggins or Sister Maria Helene. But he learned it. And as many players discover, their coach gets smarter the longer they stay with him.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
