<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Thirsty Plants Struggle to Survive</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="627409"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWNS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DC1F30F93BA3575BC0A965958260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Thirsty Plants Struggle to Survive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE cows in New Jersey are so hot they don't feel like making milk. The drought in Georgia has deep-sixed the corn. And it almost looks like fall in Central Park.</p>
        <p>What the ground needs is a slow, steady rain that lasts about a week. A sudden heavy downpour will run right off hard-packed soil that in some cases is dry four feet down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE cows in New Jersey are so hot they don't feel like making milk. The drought in Georgia has deep-sixed the corn. And it almost looks like fall in Central Park.</p>
        <p>What the ground needs is a slow, steady rain that lasts about a week. A sudden heavy downpour will run right off hard-packed soil that in some cases is dry four feet down.</p>
        <p>"Some trees have lost most of their leaves," said Tobi Bergman, the park's tree-care coordinator. "The London planes are particularly hard hit. The lawns are all brown, and we're trying our best to save the shrubs."</p>
        <p>Though New York City's Department of Environmental Protection has not declared a drought emergency -- or imposed the water restrictions that ensue -- the city's eight reservoirs and three lakes are low. The normal reservoir level for this time of year is 88.7 percent, but it is down to 73.5 percent.</p>
        <p>"We're definitely concerned, but we're not that close to declaring a drought," said Ian Michaels, a spokesman for the department. "The last time we declared a drought -- the spring of 1992 -- we were 25 percentage points below normal."</p>
        <p>He added: "If we did declare a drought, it's at least three weeks away -- and that's if we went without any rain at all."</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, it sure looks like a drought out there.</p>
        <p>"The ground is so baked, our turf specialist said his teeth almost rattled out of his head when he had to mow," said Edmond Moulin, the director of horticulture at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden. "The colloids of clay in the soil have pulled together so tight, the ground is just like adobe. It's cracked in some places."</p>
        <p>And when soil is that dry, there's not a drop of water left for plants, especially when hot weather is increasing their transpiration. Under normal conditions, plants draw water up from the soil as they photosynthesize, taking carbon dioxide from the air, and release oxygen and water vapor through openings in the leaves called stomates.</p>
        <p>"Plants have an incredibly strong ability to pull water in from the soil even when it appears to be quite dry," said Dr. Wayt Thomas, a botanist at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx. "But when the amount of moisture gets so low, plants can't draw up any more, they will start to shut down and the leaves will wilt."</p>
        <p>Leaves wilt partly because there simply isn't enough water in their cells to keep them turgid, and partly out of self-defense.</p>
        <p>"The plant will cut its losses, shed its leaves and preserve what energy it has left for twigs and stems," Dr. Thomas said. "Not much water can get out through the bark."</p>
        <p>So what's a gardener to do? Water, of course, but choose your rescue efforts well. If you need to conserve water, forget the lawn.</p>
        <p>"Worry about the grass last; the grass will come back if it's well established," said Mr. Moulin at the Brooklyn Botanic Garden. "I've never seen a whole lawn die out anywhere, though you may have bare spots and weeds, which always seem to find enough moisture to grow."</p>
        <p>You can help out your lawn by mowing a lot less. "If it gets real high, maybe take off just half an inch," Mr. Moulin said. "But unless it gets too weedy -- kind of seedy-looking -- keep it about three and a half inches high."</p>
        <p>Brittle grass does not need a good shave to add to its stress. Nor does it need the wheels of a lawn mower rolling over it. Don't even walk on it, if you can help it. (Ever notice how you can leave footprints in a dry lawn? That's because it doesn't have the turgor, or pressure from fluids in its cells, to spring back.) And please, don't fertilize a dry lawn. You don't want to push the poor thing into growing more when it's dying of thirst.</p>
        <p>"Never apply fertilizer to anything when the soil is dry," Mr. Moulin said. "And that includes soluble fertilizer. If the soil is too dry, the soluble salts could end up taking water out of the plant."</p>
        <p>Sarah Price, curator of the Conservatory Garden in Central Park, said the priorities during dry spells are trees, shrubs and lawns, in that order.</p>
        <p>"It's an economic issue, but it's also a structural one," she said. "If you lose your annuals, that's sad, but you can replant next year."</p>
        <p>Ms. Price has 50-year-old lilacs and 30-year-old azaleas with wilting leaves in her garden. "Usually, you don't have to water such established plants," she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moulin said the Brooklyn Botanic Garden has been watering new trees and plants put in this year on a weekly basis. "But even the old ones are showing stress," he said. "Our Oriental summersweet is really flagging. So are the azaleas and rhododendrons." When veterans like these get crispy leaves, it's a sign that even their deep roots are coming up with zero.</p>
        <p>So lay a hose at the base of a flagging tree and just let it drip slowly for a few hours. This method avoids the evaporation that occurs with a sprinkler, and puts precious water just where you want it. If you have a sprinkler, leave it on long enough to give your plants an inch of water a week. Put some coffee cans around the area to see how much accumulates over a period of time.</p>
        <p>"If things are really dried out to the point of wilted, I put the water on for a couple hours," Ms. Price said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas advised: "Water deep. Let it soak in a long time." One of the worst things you can do for plants is to water frequently for short periods of time, because superficial watering encourages shallow roots. Water deeply and roots will follow that moisture deep into the ground.</p>
        <p>Everything should be mulched, of course, with an inch or two of some organic material like wood chips, cocoa hulls, pine needles, shredded leaves or salt hay, to keep whatever moisture there is in the ground.</p>
        <p>"Touch up the bare spots, especially around the base of the plant, where the mulch has washed away, or maybe you planted it too high anyway," said James Cross, a nurseryman on the North Fork of Long Island.  Mr. Cross can't say enough about the importance of good topsoil and compost. "I can show you gardens out here that haven't gotten a drop of water and they're in great shape," he said.</p>
        <p>So if you're planning a new garden or lawn for next spring, invest in good topsoil this fall: eight inches to a foot and a half. Add another four inches of compost. It may seem expensive now, but good soil, which holds moisture and nutrients, is life insurance in a drought.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
