<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Q &amp; A: Dr. Henry Indyk; Want Healthy Grass? Look to the Soil</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAWNS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRASS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, JOYCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">INDYK, HENRY (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landscaping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grass</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DD113BF936A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Q &amp; A: Dr. Henry Indyk; Want Healthy Grass? Look to the Soil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JONES, JOYCE</byline>
      <dateline>SOMERSET</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to grass, Dr. Henry Indyk is king. He has been inducted into the New Jersey Turf Grass Hall of Fame and received the distinguished service award of the Golf Course Superintendents of New Jersey. He has been the National Irrigation Association's Man of the Year, and his expertise was called on during the reconstruction of the Los Angeles Coliseum for the 1984 Olympics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Indyk retired in 1990 after three decades with Rutgers University as a professor and Cooperative Extension specialist in turf management, but at the age of 72 he keeps his hand in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to grass, Dr. Henry Indyk is king. He has been inducted into the New Jersey Turf Grass Hall of Fame and received the distinguished service award of the Golf Course Superintendents of New Jersey. He has been the National Irrigation Association's Man of the Year, and his expertise was called on during the reconstruction of the Los Angeles Coliseum for the 1984 Olympics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Indyk retired in 1990 after three decades with Rutgers University as a professor and Cooperative Extension specialist in turf management, but at the age of 72 he keeps his hand in.</p>
        <p>Last year he reconstituted the home field of the New England Patriots. He has been the grass consultant for the expanded Rutgers University football stadium and its new soccer and lacrosse fields and serves as a turf grass agronomist with a grass consulting company called Turfcon in Horsham, Pa.</p>
        <p>He has even joined with a colleague in patenting a portable grass playing field.</p>
        <p>How does he explain the long-term success of the lawns, fairways, parks and stadiums he has supervised? "I make sure there is good drainage," he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Indyk and his wife, Mary, live in Somerset. They have four children.</p>
        <p>Q. Home lawns make up three-quarters of all maintained grass sites in New Jersey. How do you answer recent criticism that keeping up a lawn harms the environment?</p>
        <p>A. There has been a wave of anti-lawn sentiment. Lawns do require fertilizers and the proper use of pesticides. However, in addition to a lawn being visually more attractive over macadam or concrete, lawns play an antipollution role. They consume carbon dioxide, give off oxygen, cool the atmosphere, deter soil erosion and provide an ideal surface for children to play on.</p>
        <p>Q. What about playgrounds?</p>
        <p>A. Many times youngsters are put in an environment of mud, sand and gravel, precluding them from the pleasure of playing on grass, which is safer and cleaner.</p>
        <p>Q. What about the cost of grass?</p>
        <p>A. Some school boards say they can't afford it. Where a child plays should be as important as where he learns. School systems are beginning to realize this. Currently we are putting in a turf grass program at three athletic fields in Millville. The reconstructed Union Township High School field that we worked on was given a New Jersey Turfgrowers Association recognition award.</p>
        <p>Q. What mistakes do you think the average person makes in lawn care?</p>
        <p>A. While I strongly support pesticides when they are needed, a common mistake is to apply a pesticide just in case, which is costly, wasteful and can add to the potential problem of contamination. It's no different from treating myself, saying, "I am going to take this medicine, just in case I'm going to get sick." A lawn problem may be from an insect or a fungus; the diagnosis is key in deciding the proper material to use.</p>
        <p>Q. What if you can't tell if the damage is from an insect or a fungus?</p>
        <p>A. One source of help is to take a sample to the Rutgers Cooperative Extension office in your county.</p>
        <p>Q. What about the gardener's nemesis, the Japanese grub and beetle?</p>
        <p>A. The important thing is to know the life cycle of the insect. The Japanese beetle lays its eggs in August. The best time to treat for grubs is September and October, after the eggs have hatched and the grubs start to feed on the roots of the grass. In the spring, as the larvae stage is completed, they rise closer to the surface, emerging as Japanese beetles that feed on flowering plants.</p>
        <p>Q. Is there some general timetable to follow to prevent lawn problems?</p>
        <p>A. I am not a strong advocate of applying material on the basis of the calendar alone. The way to control an insect or weed problem is to treat it at the most effective time. There is no point in putting on a chinch bug or webworm killer in March at a time when the insect is not active. For example, to prevent dandelions in the lawn, material should be applied in October, not when they are in flower.</p>
        <p>Q. What's your main focus in establishing healthy grass, and how do you insure it stays in good condition?</p>
        <p>A. Soil conditions are No. 1. We must provide a soil which can drain quickly and be utilized even in the rain. My main concern is not the growth on the top but the root system and the environment in the soil, its physical chemistry plus the bonding characteristics.</p>
        <p>Proper maintenance is vital. I was called in to reconstitute the grass areas in the revamped Bryant Park on 42d Street in New York. Several months later I visited the site and saw that the grass was in poor condition. Subsequently, they changed the maintenance company. The irrigation system began to be used properly and the chemicals correctly applied. The next time I dropped by, it looked great.</p>
        <p>Q. What's an agronomist, and how did you get to be one?</p>
        <p>A. Agronomy is the application of soil and plant sciences to soil management. I grew up on a farm in Jamesburg in Monroe Township. At Rutgers, my first interest was chemistry, but at Cook College I started to focus on soils. My adviser, Dr. Firman Bear, a world-renowned soil scientist, was instrumental in my pursuing a master's and doctorate in agronomy at Penn State.</p>
        <p>After graduation I worked in research at the University of Delaware and then returned to Rutgers as an extension specialist in forage crops. From there, I moved into turf grassmanagement.</p>
        <p>Q. What was your role in improving grasses like Kentucky bluegrass and perennial ryegrass?</p>
        <p>A. I was fortunate at Rutgers to work with Dr. C. Reed Funk, a professosr of grass breeding and selection. Dr. Funk got into the genetics of it, crossing the bluegrasses to make them disease-resistant. He also made a breakthrough in the strains of ryegrass. The genetic material for the improved Manhattan ryegrass, now used successfully on golf fairways, lawns and parks, came out of Central Park in New York.</p>
        <p>Also, in my travels if I saw a good bluegrass or bent grass, I would collect and contribute strains for him to propagate.</p>
        <p>Q. When did you turn your attention to athletic fields?</p>
        <p>A. When I first became interested, physical fitness was not as paramount as it is today. However, I think the motivating issue in the concern about the condition of playing fields has been safety. I credit that to litigation prompted by injuries sustained there. I wish I had known 30 years ago how deeply attorneys would be involved in sports arenas.</p>
        <p>Q. You must have sympathized with George Toma, the caretaker for the Kansas City Chiefs, as he tried to get the rain-soaked Rose Bowl field ready for this year's Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>A. I did. It was George who recommended me to the New England Patriots to reconstitute their home-field stadium. The stipulation was that it would be ready for their season opener. We knew that the stadium management group had scheduled a U2 rock concert in August. What we asked for was a 30-day leeway to repair the damage inflicted by the concert's crowd. We didn't know that a Guns 'n Roses concert in July, which had been canceled because the lead singer took ill, was rescheduled for September, giving us just one week to repair it.</p>
        <p>Q. I suppose experiences like that inspired your work on the patent for a transportable natural grass playing surface.</p>
        <p>A. Yes. What Tom Ripley and I devised is an Integrated Management System which uses self-contained grass-growing modules that can be fastened together to provide an instant natural grass field. Unlike sod, which utilizes only the surface portions of turf, this system installs mature grass with supporting soil to withstand heavy athletic use.</p>
        <p>Q. What will the stadiums of the future be like?</p>
        <p>A. They will be domed; people want to sit in comfort. They will have the flexibility for multipurpose use to accommodate football and soccer on a natural turf surface, which most athletes prefer. A concrete floor to handle the wear and tear of rock concerts can also be turned into an ice hockey rink or a basketball court.</p>
        <p>Q. As an advocate of natural turf, does it bother you that the field at Giants Stadium is synthetic -- as opposed to the nearby grass practice field that you developed?</p>
        <p>A. Of course. At the time of the stadium's construction I pleaded for natural grass, but when Gov. Brendan Byrne said the stadium was for multiple kinds of use, like tractor pulls and car shows, that terminated my interest.</p>
        <p>Q. How do you feel about being back working at Rutgers?</p>
        <p>A. I'm interested in making sure that this renovation process is done properly. I have a strong affinity to Rutgers. Wherever I go to solve turf problems, be it St. Croix, Australia, Europe, I carry the Rutgers banner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
