<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corps of Engineers Looking Warily for New Role</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY BASES AND INSTALLATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHEIMER, JON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DF1F3DF93BA15751C0A965958260" item-length="1659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corps of Engineers Looking Warily for New Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON NORDHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORDHEIMER, JON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Army Corps of Engineers, once the well-oiled machine that could be counted on to move earth and perhaps even a piece of heaven with the right Congressional appropriation, is agonizing in the opening days of the Clinton Administration over reorganization, lean budgets and belt-tightening.</p>
        <p>Appropriations for the Corps have dried up faster than a dammed wetland in the last few years as Federal budget deficits and military cutbacks reduced money for massive engineering projects to a trickle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Army Corps of Engineers, once the well-oiled machine that could be counted on to move earth and perhaps even a piece of heaven with the right Congressional appropriation, is agonizing in the opening days of the Clinton Administration over reorganization, lean budgets and belt-tightening.</p>
        <p>Appropriations for the Corps have dried up faster than a dammed wetland in the last few years as Federal budget deficits and military cutbacks reduced money for massive engineering projects to a trickle.</p>
        <p>The golden age of dam building has long been over for the Corps, technically a branch of the Army that has always balanced large-scale civil works -- mostly on the nation's waterways -- with military missions like building Army posts and Air Force bases.</p>
        <p>In the post-cold-war era, however, appropriations for future military projects are running on empty and a big share of the Corps's current $12 billion budget is for closing bases, not building them.</p>
        <p>By 1996, if not sooner, the money set aside for closing bases should drop to a minimal sum, and Administration budget-cutters are likely to see a fat target in the Corps's $1.75 billion annual payroll for 450 military officers and 39,000 civilian engineers, scientists and technical support teams.</p>
        <p>The Corps's civil workload today is 40 percent of what it was in 1965. Yet personnel strength has remained fairly constant since those days in which Congressional appropriations financed huge civilian projects and the Corps's budget topped $14 billion (in constant 1991 dollars). Back then, critics say, more of the money was going into actual construction while today more is going into study and overhead, and that, they say, is a sign of bureaucratic decay. A Time of Challenges</p>
        <p>Whether the Corps and its friends in Congress can come up with a plan to justify its current payroll is a question that is jangling nerves at the Corps's headquarters in Washington, its 10 regional divisions and its 38 district offices.</p>
        <p>"The Corps is faced with a lot of uncertainties and challenges at the moment," said Lieut. Gen. Arthur E. Williams, the Corps commander and chief engineer. "The attempt to reorganize is a reminder of how complicated the Corps's position is in American life. It has been a very emotional and politically sensitive experience."</p>
        <p>The hope is that the Administration will need the Corps and its expertise in any national effort to stimulate the economy with public works.</p>
        <p>"We think we have a lot of engineering and technical capability to be utilized if called upon," General Williams said in a recent interview, "and we are poised to branch out to new mission areas. We find ourselves in the uncomfortable position of not being able to go out and market ourselves and look like we're after someone else's rice bowl." Changing Priorities</p>
        <p>The Corps is not a construction unit. It studies projects for feasibility and engineering and awards contracts to private companies to do the construction. It does not directly command thousands of Army combat engineers.</p>
        <p>Budget fat, whether of the Congressional pork-barrel variety or of the kind that pays Corps architects to design golf courses and post exchanges on military bases, used to be justified as a necessary expense of the cold war: The United States needed to keep the Corps's engineering expertise at full strength in case it was needed for war or other national emergency.</p>
        <p>The Corps has been mentioned around Washington as a logical entity within the Defense Department to take over the responsibilities of the Federal Emergency Management Agency, a civilian agency that was criticized last year for its initial response to Hurricane Andrew in Florida. The Corps already takes part in disaster relief and issues contracts approved by the emergency-management agency for cleaning up and rebuilding.</p>
        <p>It is also reimbursed by other Federal agencies to do environment-related work and toxic-waste cleanups. Work in those fields is budgeted at a total of about $1 billion in the current fiscal year, General Williams said, and they are possible areas of growth. 'Still Very Much Old Guard'</p>
        <p>For decades the Corps was widely criticized as a despoiler of the environment for its engineering responses to natural challenges and its liberal granting of building permits in wetlands. So cutting out this new role strikes some observers as more pragmatic than heartfelt.</p>
        <p>"The Corps is still very much old guard in its thinking," said a coastal geologist who was formerly a civilian employee of the organization.</p>
        <p>The ex-employee, who spoke only on condition of anonymity, said the Corps motto "Essayons" -- French for 'Let's Try!' -- still reflected "a mentality whose immediate response, when confronted with a problem like eroding beaches, is to find an engineering solution."</p>
        <p>In December the Corps headquarters unveiled a reorganization plan that called for eliminating 2,600 civilian jobs, reorganizing layers of command for the first time in a half-century, closing district offices in Chicago, Dallas, Omaha and San Francisco, and moving the North Atlantic division headquarters from New York City to a military installation near Boston.</p>
        <p>The plan was suspended last month until it could be reviewed by the new Secretary of Defense, Les Aspin. In addition, the proposed move out of New York, scheduled for Feb. 1, ran into a wall of bipartisan opposition from regional political leaders.</p>
        <p>Uncertainty about the Corps's future is already causing what one high-ranking officer described as a "hemorrhage of talent." Some of the organization's best engineers and scientists are leaving for jobs in the private sector, he said. Bonanza in New Jersey</p>
        <p>Some state officials who work closely with the Corps, like Bernard Moore, a New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection administrator, find it surprising that the New York division was selected for closing when the region has some of the largest and most disputed civil works projects on the Corps's plate.</p>
        <p>The bustle of activity in the region is a legacy of two powerful New Jersey Democratic Congressmen: James J. Howard of Spring Lake, who was chairman of the House Public Works and Transportation Committee until his death in 1988, and Robert A. Roe of Wayne, who was chairmen of the public works committee when he retired last year. The committee is the principal Congressional vehicle for doling out billions in Corps appropriations.</p>
        <p>Among the Corps's New Jersey public works are these:</p>
        <p>*An eight-year, $350 million project to dredge a 35-foot-deep channel between Staten Island and New Jersey to accommodate larger container ships. It has been delayed by concerns that the channel bottom contains dioxin-tainted sediment and will not be completed until 1995.</p>
        <p>*A tunnel project to divert floodwaters from the Passaic River into Newark Bay will cost billions if it is finally authorized.</p>
        <p>*A $202 million project to replenish the beach along 12 miles at Sea Bright/ Monmouth Beach. The work, scheduled to begin this spring, is the first leg of beach repair between Sandy Hook and Barnegat Inlet, a project that is expected to cost $1.2 billion. Busy at the Beach</p>
        <p>The nation's coastline, rivers and harbors have always been a major part of Corps activities. Dredging mud and shifting sands from navigable waterways was historically a Corps maintenance chore, but in recent years work to repair or protect storm-battered beaches has evolved into a reliable source of income.</p>
        <p>Pumping millions of cubic yards of sand to build up a narrow beach is expensive, and the beach must be revisited every few years to replace what has been carried away by storms and daily tides. Nationwide, more than $8 billion to date has been authorized for beach projects that will keep private dredges under contract with the Corps for years.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stephen P. Leatherman, director of the Laboratory for Coastal Research at the University of Maryland, has long been a critic of the Corps's policies and looks at the current emphasis on beach work with a skeptical eye.</p>
        <p>"Now that the Corps has dammed all the rivers in the country, its big thing right now is dredging harbors and rivers," Dr. Leatherman said. "Right behind, and becoming more important, is beach replenishment, which used to be a nickel-and-dime operation for the Corps.</p>
        <p>"The trouble with the Corps is that it is not base-level funded. It has to go around scaring up projects or else shrink to a skeleton if no one comes up with the funding to pay all those civilian engineers on their payroll."</p>
        <p>Corps officials maintain that the high expense of their beach projects is warranted by the threat the ocean poses to property and lives. "The beaches are the first line of defense at a time of rising sea level," said Bruce Bergmann, civilian director of planning in the Corps's New York district office. "The beaches are designed to be sacrificed, taking the energy from a storm instead of houses, hospitals and roadways." Change in Thinking</p>
        <p>The Corps seems ready to concede that an agency overhaul was long overdue, in both structure and thinking.</p>
        <p>"We've learned some lessons about mistakes that were made in the past," said Col. Miguel Monteverde, the chief Corps spokesman. The Corps, like most of American society, was not especially sensitive to environmental considerations during the era of dam building, he said.</p>
        <p>"To say we've learned to develop projects that are environmentally sustainable is not said just to keep as busy as beavers and keep people on the payroll," he said.</p>
        <p>But if billions in appropriations fade into history, the worry is that the Corps may not be able to count on too many defenders outside its ranks. Loyalty to the Corps never amounted to much inside the Pentagon, where allegiances are mainly to the fighting branches of the military, and the loyalty of Congress may have been built on a foundation only as solid as last year's budget.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
