<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fate-of-the-Earth Furniture</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Design Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Arts; Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="640086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FURNITURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOOD AND WOOD PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARTOLUCCI, MARISA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/T: Style Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wood and Wood Products</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DC173CF933A25753C1A965958260" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fate-of-the-Earth Furniture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marisa Bartolucci;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARTOLUCCI, MARISA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THESE DAYS, MORE AND MORE of us are thinking green. We bring string bags to the supermarket and buy biodegradable detergents, organic vegetables, even recyclable teakettles. Yet how many of us think of the fate of the earth when selecting a new sofa or table? It's difficult to imagine them as a threat to the environment, much less to one's health. But the truth is that furniture manufacturing is a fundamentally polluting business: Companies often use pesticide-treated wood and apply paints and finishes that contain volatile toxic solvents, as well as glues made with formaldehyde, a likely carcinogen. Not to mention the millions of acres of rain forest that are destroyed in the demand for tropical woods such as mahogany and rosewood.</p>
        <p>Troubled by this environmental toll, a growing number of designers, manufacturers and marketers have embarked on an ecological odyssey in search of cleaner and safer materials and renewable wood sources.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THESE DAYS, MORE AND MORE of us are thinking green. We bring string bags to the supermarket and buy biodegradable detergents, organic vegetables, even recyclable teakettles. Yet how many of us think of the fate of the earth when selecting a new sofa or table? It's difficult to imagine them as a threat to the environment, much less to one's health. But the truth is that furniture manufacturing is a fundamentally polluting business: Companies often use pesticide-treated wood and apply paints and finishes that contain volatile toxic solvents, as well as glues made with formaldehyde, a likely carcinogen. Not to mention the millions of acres of rain forest that are destroyed in the demand for tropical woods such as mahogany and rosewood.</p>
        <p>Troubled by this environmental toll, a growing number of designers, manufacturers and marketers have embarked on an ecological odyssey in search of cleaner and safer materials and renewable wood sources.</p>
        <p>Smith &amp; Hawken, a garden-equipment and outdoor furnishings mail-order company in northern California, went so far as to hire Ted Tuescher, an environmentalist, to evaluate its manufacturers' sources and timber production. The company's extensive line of outdoor furniture is now constructed from teak, cedar and other tropical woods from plantations or natural forests that are either certified as sustainable or, at the very least, approved by the Rainforest Alliance, a nonprofit organization in New York City, as "well managed" (the wood is harvested at a rate that doesn't exceed growth). Smith &amp; Hawken has also found an unusual source for redwood: wine vats made of old-growth timber that are being discarded by neighboring Sonoma County vineyards as they switch over to stainless-steel models. "There's an added benefit to using this wood," Tuescher observes. "It smells of wine."</p>
        <p>Another imaginative recycler is Roy McMakin, the president and chief designer of Domestic Furniture Company in Los Angeles, who has long been involved in the production of environmentally sensitive furniture. His five-year-old company, now a $1 million-plus business, manufactures its Simple Chairs from odd pieces of spruce left over from the construction of piano sounding boards and makes stools from the Douglas-fir floor planks of an old warehouse.</p>
        <p>THE SEARCH FOR better materials also extends to upholstery and batting. The foam in many commercially manufactured cushions is made with chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs), which eat away the ozone layer; the foam can also act as a sponge, absorbing toxic fumes from cigarettes and other indoor pollutants. The upholstery fabric may contain dyes made with highly polluting petrochemicals; frequently formaldehyde is also used to hold the color.</p>
        <p>A more ecological choice is a new CFC-free foam, now being used by some furniture companies. And Domestic Furniture is considering the manufacture of pieces upholstered in an unusual "colored" cotton, called Fox Fibre. Developed by Sally Fox, an entomologist who has also worked as a botanist, Fox Fibre is available from Coyuchi, a small textile company in Point Reyes Station, Calif. Raised organically (conventionally grown cotton is the most highly sprayed agricultural crop), this cotton is indigenous to the Americas and grows, amazingly, in a lovely brown or green hue.</p>
        <p>At the high end of the furniture market, Donghia, based in New York City, is recycling traditional furniture-making methods used before the introduction of synthetics. Several of its furniture lines can be made in this vintage manner, complete with inner springs wrapped in feather and down and upholstered with crimped animal hair and cotton batting instead of foam. The frames are made from farmed maple and the glue that holds them together is derived from rabbit skins. John Hutton, Donghia's furniture design director, admits that this construction method is not altogether green -- the company has yet to determine whether the paint used to prevent the springs from rusting is environmentally sound, and Federal regulations require the animal hair to be moth-proofed. However, Hutton points out, unlike the new CFC-free foam, every bit of the animal hair gets used, while much of the foam is either thrown away or recycled (recycling of plastics requires the addition of more chemicals), a process that is itself potentially polluting.</p>
        <p>Hutton hopes the company will eventually offer this alternative construction for its entire furniture line. But first the customer will have to be educated to appreciate its old-fashioned qualities. "Natural construction breaks down," says Hutton. "It appears rumpled like a comfortable shoe. With foam upholstery, the resiliency is always there. It's more tailored-looking." This tendency to show wear may be why traditional construction, despite its ecological advantages, has yet to entice many customers. Hutton concedes that, so far, most buyers have been people suffering from extreme allergies to chemicals. Observes Dakota Jackson, the New York City furniture designer and manufacturer: "People who can afford high-end furniture feel they have the privilege to buy whatever they want and not worry about environmental considerations."</p>
        <p>Jackson himself is a designer who stresses old-fashioned workmanship, but has gone to great lengths to insure his furniture's longevity. His recently introduced Library Chair, whose frame is reinforced with cast-metal components, has been specifically designed to last 50 years. And the wooden back and seat of his stackable Vikter Chair can be replaced, guaranteeing a longer lifespan.</p>
        <p>Designers and manufacturers are also conserving what they do use. Jackson, who once worked extensively with exotic woods, now employs them only rarely as accent veneers. His solid-wood constructions feature replenishable domestic varieties exclusively.</p>
        <p>This new appreciation of wood resources extends even to mass consumer lines like Workbench. Not long ago, the Manhattan-based furniture chain discontinued manufacturing its butcher-block furniture out of 2-inch-thick hardwood, deeming it wasteful. The company now employs 1 1/4-inch butcher block (more than strong enough for home use), with beveled edges to emphasize its thinness. While the company doesn't actively market its furniture as green, it does consider it environmentally sound. Much of it is manufactured in Scandinavia and Germany, which have some of the strictest environmental regulations in the world.</p>
        <p>A commitment to the environment also pervades every aspect of Ikea's operations. After consulting with the international environmental group Greenpeace, the Swedish home furnishings company with stores throughout the world now publishes its widely distributed catalogue on chlorine-free paper. It has also discontinued products made of plastics containing polyvinyl chloride. This fall, Ikea will introduce the Ogla chair, a variation on Thonet's bentwood bistro design, which is made entirely of recycled plastic. And in California, the company is experimenting with delivering its sofas in reusable plastic bags instead of disposable boxes.</p>
        <p>For companies that still wish to use tropical woods, environmentalists have been encouraging the use of less popular tree species. Ikea, for instance, has chosen to make a number of its wood furnishings from rubber trees, which are harvested only after their supply of latex dries up.</p>
        <p>A growing number of woodworkers and furniture makers are turning to these little-used varieties, thanks to organizations like the Forest Partnership, a Burlington, Vt.-based nonprofit group that helps craftsmen, manufacturers and architects identify woods from well-managed sources. Many of these woods can be ordered through San Francisco's Ecotimber International, which purveys less-known tropical woods harvested exclusively from sustainable forestry operations.</p>
        <p>Of course, when shopping for green furniture, there is another option altogether. It's the one Paul Bierman-Lytle, a New Canaan, Conn., architect and a leader of the ecosensitive architecture movement, first suggests to his clients: "Buy antiques." Bierman-Lytle gives two reasons: first, you are recycling, and so sparing the earth's resources; second, if the piece is more than 50 years old, you can be certain it has been constructed without the use of toxic chemicals and substances. And some antique pieces, like certain 19th-century English designs, can be less expensive than custom-made environmentally sound furniture.</p>
        <p>Never have Grandma's hand-me-downs looked so good.</p>
        <p>Marisa Bartolucci is the senior editor of Metropolis magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marisa Bartolucci is the senior editor of
Metropolis magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
