<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ANTARCTIC OZONE HITS RECORD LOW</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="642843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GASES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC &amp; ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D6163DF93AA25753C1A965958260" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ANTARCTIC OZONE HITS RECORD LOW</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The amount of ozone in the atmosphere over Antarctica reached a record low this month, Government scientists reported yesterday. This was the lowest recorded ozone level anywhere in the world, raising new concerns that measures to restrict the use of ozone-destroying chemicals may not be strong enough.</p>
        <p>The scientists said the area of intense ozone depletion, commonly called an ozone hole, was not quite as wide as it had been a year ago. But balloon-borne instruments showed that ozone, the atmospheric molecules that absorb harmful ultraviolet radiation from sunlight, was totally destroyed between the altitudes of 8.4 and 11.8 miles, creating an unusually thick void.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The amount of ozone in the atmosphere over Antarctica reached a record low this month, Government scientists reported yesterday. This was the lowest recorded ozone level anywhere in the world, raising new concerns that measures to restrict the use of ozone-destroying chemicals may not be strong enough.</p>
        <p>The scientists said the area of intense ozone depletion, commonly called an ozone hole, was not quite as wide as it had been a year ago. But balloon-borne instruments showed that ozone, the atmospheric molecules that absorb harmful ultraviolet radiation from sunlight, was totally destroyed between the altitudes of 8.4 and 11.8 miles, creating an unusually thick void.</p>
        <p>"This is an extension upward of the ozone hole as we have known it in the past," said Dr. David J. Hoffman, a senior scientist with the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, a scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund, a research and advocacy organization, said the announcement was "a grim reminder of how serious ozone depletion is." Data From Satellite</p>
        <p>Research by N.O.A.A. and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, as well as independent scientists, has linked the annual cycle of severe Antarctic ozone depletion to the release of chlorine compounds, notably chlorofluorocarbons, that have been widely used in refrigeration and electronics. The chemicals affect ozone elsewhere, though not as sharply as in the polar regions.</p>
        <p>Some political conservatives have questioned the connection between the chemicals and the ozone loss. But the industrial nations agreed in 1987 to stop production of these chemicals by 1996, a move that scientists say should allow ozone levels overall to recover over the next century.</p>
        <p>Ever since the annual ozone hole was discovered over Antarctica in 1985, spacecraft, balloons and ground-based instruments have regularly monitored the upper atmosphere there. An American ozone-mapping spectrometer on the Russian Meteor 3 satellite provided much of the data for the new measurements.</p>
        <p>Ozone is measured in Dobson units, each of which represents the physical thickness of the ozone layer if it were compressed at the Earth's surface. About 300 Dobson units equal one-tenth of an inch. This is a usual value at the Antarctic in seasons when the ozone layer is not depleted.</p>
        <p>In an announcement by NASA and the atmospheric administration, the satellite readings at the end of September and in early October showed values of less than 100 Dobson units. On Oct. 6, a surface instrument at the South Pole recorded 88 Dobson units. This is the lowest value ever measured, anywhere in the world, the agencies said.</p>
        <p>The largest ozone hole ever observed was in 1992, when the area of severe depletion over Antarctica covered more than 9.4 million square miles. This year it was 9 million square miles. Antarctica itself has a surface area of 5.4 million square miles.</p>
        <p>The Government scientists noted that the severity of ozone depletion this year and last may have been affected by the continued presence of sulfuric acid in the upper atmosphere, residue from the eruption of Mount Pinatubo in the Philippines in June 1991.</p>
        <p>"Nothing can be done about volcanoes, but we can and must swiftly eliminate ozone depleting chemicals," Dr. Oppenheimer said. "The news today effectively puts to rest any claims by special interests far outside of the scientific mainstream that the destruction of Earth's protective ozone layer is not a problem."</p>
        <p>Environmental scientists said that production of other ozone-depleting chemicals should also be eliminated or more strictly regulated. They cited methyl bromide, a widely used pesticide, and hydrochlorofluorocarbons, or H.C.F.C.'s, the industrial chemicals that are being substituted in air conditioners and refrigerators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
