<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TV Weekend; A Politician's Awakening To Drugs in Her Family</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="605513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HALLMARK HALL OF FAME (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BLIND SPOT (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D91038F933A05757C0A965958260" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TV Weekend; A Politician's Awakening To Drugs in Her Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN J. O'CONNOR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'CONNOR, JOHN J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joanne Woodward, who last year shared with her husband, Paul Newman, a lifetime achievment award at the Kennedy Center Honors, has steadily made the most of television. She won Emmy Awards for her performances in "See How She Runs" (1978) and "Do You Remember Love?" (1985). The first was about marathon running, the second Alzheimer's disease. Earlier this year, in Alison Lurie's "Foreign Affairs," she shone as a middle-aged academic finding love where she least expected. And now, this Sunday at 9 P.M. in "Blind Spot," she is a powerfully confident Congresswoman who has to confront drug addiction in her own family.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Woodward, the subject of drugs takes on obvious personal dimensions. In 1978, Scott Newman, Mr. Newman's 28-year-old son from a first marriage, died of an overdose of Valium and alcohol. In the years since, Ms. Woodward and her family have worked closely with the Scott Newman Center, which is dedicated to drug education. In "Blind Spot," co-produced by Ms. Woodward as a "Hallmark Hall of Fame" presentation, the actress extends the reach of that education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joanne Woodward, who last year shared with her husband, Paul Newman, a lifetime achievment award at the Kennedy Center Honors, has steadily made the most of television. She won Emmy Awards for her performances in "See How She Runs" (1978) and "Do You Remember Love?" (1985). The first was about marathon running, the second Alzheimer's disease. Earlier this year, in Alison Lurie's "Foreign Affairs," she shone as a middle-aged academic finding love where she least expected. And now, this Sunday at 9 P.M. in "Blind Spot," she is a powerfully confident Congresswoman who has to confront drug addiction in her own family.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Woodward, the subject of drugs takes on obvious personal dimensions. In 1978, Scott Newman, Mr. Newman's 28-year-old son from a first marriage, died of an overdose of Valium and alcohol. In the years since, Ms. Woodward and her family have worked closely with the Scott Newman Center, which is dedicated to drug education. In "Blind Spot," co-produced by Ms. Woodward as a "Hallmark Hall of Fame" presentation, the actress extends the reach of that education.</p>
        <p>Ms. Woodward's Nell Harrington is a woman who appears to be in control of everything. Her do-goodism encompasses everything from the problems of constituents to the threat of global warming. Nell is ready to run for the United States Senate. Then her pregnant daughter, Phoebe (Laura Linney), and son-in-law, Charlie (Reed Diamond), who is also Nell's top political aide, are in a car accident. She survives; he dies. The police discover cocaine in the car. Drug traces are found in Charlie's system.</p>
        <p>Nell's first response is damage control. She tells a press conference, "I will never assume, as I did, that drug abuse is a problem that happens to somebody else." Then, taking over as usual, she sets about doing what she thinks best for Phoebe and the unborn baby. For Nell, all problems are solvable. Before giving birth, the depressed and resentful Phoebe goes back on cocaine. Nell begins discovering unpleasant truths about her seemingly on-track life. Even her gentle husband, Simon (Fritz Weaver), a medievalist, warns her that "trying to reason with you is like standing in front of a bulldozer."</p>
        <p>"Blind Spot" pushes a good many of the buttons familiar in television's personal-crisis dramas. You know that around the one-hour mark things will start turning around for the better. And they do just that here, but with far less-sunny assurances than are typical of the genre. The possible long-range problems of drug-affected babies do not lend themselves to quick fixes. As Phoebe, Ms. Linney has several scorchingly honest scenes. But it is Ms. Woodward who holds the project together, managing to keep Nell decent and intelligent even while she is being just about impossible. Ms. Woodward makes us care, which is really the point of "Blind Spot." Hallmark Hall of Fame Blind Spot  CBS, Sunday night at 9 (Channel 2 in New York) Teleplay written by Nina Shengold and based on a story by Michael McTaggart and Ellen M. Violett. Directed by Michael Toshiyuki Uno; Joanne Woodward, co-producer; Robert Halmi Jr. and Richard Welsh, executive producers. A Signboard Hill production in association with RHI Entertainment. Nell . . . Joanne Woodward Phoebe . . . Laura Linney Simon . . . Fritz Weaver Charlie . . . Reed Diamond</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
