<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Celebrating the Underrated Annual</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="597130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDE113AF932A15750C0A965958260" item-length="1016" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Celebrating the Underrated Annual</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS I wrote this column last weekend, four inches of snow had fallen on my city fire escape, hurricane-force winds had knocked over my potted Alberta spruce, and thunder had rumbled over the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the official first day of spring. Are these extremes the greenhouse effect or just the age-old vagaries of weather? I don't know, but I've started to note them in my garden journal (March 13: thunder in the blizzard), and I figure that if the incongruities keep piling up, I can sell it as an absurdist play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS I wrote this column last weekend, four inches of snow had fallen on my city fire escape, hurricane-force winds had knocked over my potted Alberta spruce, and thunder had rumbled over the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the official first day of spring. Are these extremes the greenhouse effect or just the age-old vagaries of weather? I don't know, but I've started to note them in my garden journal (March 13: thunder in the blizzard), and I figure that if the incongruities keep piling up, I can sell it as an absurdist play.</p>
        <p>Anyway, I'm celebrating spring by planting some annual seeds in little pots and dreaming of their deep summer colors. Others sit in their little packets like promises of perfection (no weeds, no bugs, no drought) because they do best sown directly in the garden.</p>
        <p>Some are long-forgotten favorites like Abelmoschus manihot, a pale yellow mallow with a deep burgundy center, and some are new to my garden, like Amaranthus caudatus Viridis, whose knobby tassles are not the usual reddish purple of most amaranth, but</p>
        <p>green</p>
        <p>, and a pale chartreuse at that.</p>
        <p>Some of my annual seeds are still to be ordered, because I couldn't resist a few more (O.K., maybe six more) after pawing through Wayne Winterrowd's "Annuals for Connoisseurs: Classics and Novelties From Abelmoschus to Zinnia" (Horticulture/Prentice Hall, 1992). Mr. Winterrowd has been gardening in southern Vermont for 15 years, but the Louisiana native writes with such easygoing authority that I suspect he really started gardening when the glaciers melted.</p>
        <p>(Like Big Foot, he is on my most-wanted-to-be-interviewed-list, and I hope to report back this summer on the beauties in his garden, but meanwhile, you may want to grow some of these flowers.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Winterrowd's descriptions of the underrated annual (e.g., the "winsome, thoughtful stare of pansies" or simply the "brawny castor bean") are pretty irresistible and my excuse for overordering again.</p>
        <p>Forget what you know, he writes, about those all-too-familiar bedding schemes at filling stations and "surf 'n' turf" restaurants where "red pelargoniums or Salvia splendons alternate with orange marigolds and white petunias, with an occasional silver artemisia or cineraria stuck among them." These gruesome combinations are simply the result of misunderstanding a plant's personality.</p>
        <p>White petunias, for instance, have an entrancing fragrance, and Mr. Winterrowd pictures them on a twilight terrace, planted in masses "with no other shades to muddy their purity." He also points out the very way in which the poor petunia has been mistreated: "a petunia draggled in the mud after a summer shower is a petunia in abasement, whereas, in a container, it can spread its white sails unmarred."</p>
        <p>The petunia is one annual that should be started indoors in early February, so I guess I missed the boat on the languorous terrace idea. Of course, if you love petunias, you can always buy masses of them at a local nursery in late May, but the varieties may be run-of-the-mill. Starting your own opens up the infinite possibilities listed in obscure catalogues and petunia societies and so forth, so make a note for next year.</p>
        <p>The nice thing about A. manihot, which is a cousin of okra, is that it can be planted directly in the garden at corn-planting time. (Which is, Mr. Winterrowd says, one week after the apple blossoms fall.) A. manihot is a heat-lover that doesn't come into its own until late August, when this six-footer opens its five-inch flowers on many-branched stalks already decked out in regal, dark green, deeply lobed leaves that are about a foot long and just as wide.</p>
        <p>You can give A. manihot a head start by planting seeds indoors now, but it doesn't like to be transplanted. Mr. Winterrowd suggests sowing only a few seeds to a single peat pot, pinching off all the seedlings except the strongest grower, and then planting the whole thing in the garden. But I'm trying to cut back on my use of peat -- because peat bogs, like wetlands, are not easy ecosystems to restore -- so I pinch back the seedlings in little plastic pots. Then at transplanting time, I just use extreme caution.</p>
        <p>But this is not a lecture on starting seeds. It is an invitation to an addiction to annuals. Like Argemone grandiflora, a white poppy with spiny, deeply lobed sea-green leaves that blooms from June to heavy frost and self-seeds year after year. Or Argemone mexicana, a yellow poppy whose leaves have light-blue veins. The seeds of both can simply be strewn on the ground in early April and lightly scratched in. Later, the plants can be thinned to a foot apart.</p>
        <p>And what about the green zinnia? There's a new form of Zinnia elegans, called Envy, and it's the color of lime sherbet. So don't plant it next to Scarlet Splendor, which I love almost as much as my dog, Molly. Try growing it among alliums, lavender verbena and burgundy-leafed perilla. (I don't get these ideas from divine inspiration; I get them from photos in Mr. Winterrowd's book.)</p>
        <p>I'm going to give Nicotiana sylvestris another whirl this summer. This five-footer, with its huge oval leaves and droopy white flowers that grow more fragrant at night, is one of those fellows out looking for a romantic evening. So leave it to me to have it towering over the lettuce patch; this year, I'm putting it against the mock orange bushes or maybe a whole sea of it around one of the old posts of the grape arbor. (Or will I be committing some other garden crime like attracting aphids to the grapes?)</p>
        <p>There are many other seductive beauties in this book, and the author shares the wealth of his experience in growing them in a "Techniques" chapter that should have been called "Mr. Winterrowd's Secrets." That's how good it is. The book also lists more than 40 sources for unusual annuals. A few of them are: Abundant Life Seed Foundation, P.O. Box 772, Port Townsend, Wash. 98368; the Fragrant Path, P.O. Box 328, Fort Calhoun, Neb. 68023; Seeds Blum, Idaho City Stage, Boise, Idaho 83706, and the Well-Sweep Herb Farm, 317 Mount Bethel Road, Port Murray, N.J. 07865.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
