<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Energy Tax Quest: Levy That Draws Least Outcry</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="614781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61330F931A25755C0A965958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Energy Tax Quest: Levy That Draws Least Outcry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it seeks to find a replacement for the Administration's B.T.U. tax, the Senate is struggling to choose the least ugly of several alternatives.</p>
        <p>It has quickly discovered that every option has somebody ready to loathe it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it seeks to find a replacement for the Administration's B.T.U. tax, the Senate is struggling to choose the least ugly of several alternatives.</p>
        <p>It has quickly discovered that every option has somebody ready to loathe it.</p>
        <p>Westerners who drive a lot hate the idea of a gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>Truck drivers and struggling airlines have dragged out the heavy artillery to shoot down the leading proposal, a broad transportation tax on gasoline, diesel fuel and airline fuel.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists dread another idea -- a sales tax on energy -- because coal, which is dirty, is also cheap. They want a tax that penalizes coal rather than favors it. Besides, senators from the Northeast dislike an energy sales tax because it would hit their region disproportionately since its electricity and energy prices are among the highest in the nation. Looking For Right Tax</p>
        <p>As so often happens in Congress, the selection process appears to be boiling down to the tax that has the fewest, weakest, least vocal opponents.</p>
        <p>But this time there are two other factors complicating the muddle, with environmentalists looking for the tax that will help the environment most, and economists looking for the tax that will hurt the economy least.</p>
        <p>On that last point, there seems to be wide agreement.</p>
        <p>After cutting through all the lobbyists' talk about how such-and-such energy tax will send such-and-such industry back to the Jurassic Age, economists say that a gasoline tax or transportation tax would do less overall damage to the economy than the B.T.U. tax that the Administration trumpeted, and then withdrew.</p>
        <p>The reason is that while the B.T.U. tax and the gasoline tax would each hurt consumers by raising the price of gasoline, the B.T.U. tax would hurt many industries -- and would hurt them in international competition. The B.T.U. tax would be levied on nonrenewable energy sources and be based on the heat content of different fuels as measured in British thermal units.</p>
        <p>"A straight gasoline tax has a much smaller impact on the nation's manufacturing sector," said Philip Verleger, an energy economist at the Institute for International Economics. "But with a B.T.U. tax, there would be substantial job losses in the energy-intensive sector."</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, on the other hand, are unhappy that the B.T.U. tax has been set aside. They like it because it would help shift consumption away from dirty fuels and toward cleaner ones, like natural gas.</p>
        <p>"If you compare the environmental benefits per dollar, a gasoline tax is just half as effective as a B.T.U. tax," said Daniel A. Lashof, a senior scientist with the Natural Resources Defense Council. "The B.T.U. tax creates an incentive to switch from coal to natural gas."</p>
        <p>The energy tax that environmentalists really love -- a carbon tax, based on the amount of carbon dioxide produced by burning each unit of fuel -- is not even being considered by the Senate. The reason: it would hit coal country hardest, and Robert C. Byrd, the powerful Democratic Senator from West Virginia, would not want that.</p>
        <p>The Administration's B.T.U. tax died of 1,000 pinpricks after the National Association of Manufacturers, American Petroleum Institute, American Chamber of Commerce and dozens of other lobbying groups organized to kill it. Because there was so much unhappiness that the tax would hurt manufacturers, several senators concluded that an energy tax that fell mostly on consumers would have a better chance of passage.</p>
        <p>Thus, Senator John B. Breaux, a Louisiana Democrat, is pushing a transportation tax on airline fuel, diesel fuel and gasoline. Under one version, it would raise the price of gasoline by 7.6 cents a gallon, about the same amount as the Administration's B.T.U. tax. When fully phased in, the B.T.U. tax would raise more than $20 billion a year, while Mr. Breaux's transportation tax would raise less than half that.</p>
        <p>Speaking about a 7.6 cent tax on gasoline, William Durbin, associate director of Cambridge Energy Research Associates, said: "A tax that size will only have a marginal impact on the economy. We often see fluctuations of eight-nine cents in the price of gasoline. An increase of eight or nine cents means nothing. In some European countries, the gasoline tax is over $4 a gallon." Opposing Gasoline Tax</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Senator Max Baucus, a Montana Democrat on the Senate Finance Committee, opposes a gasoline tax, saying it would unfairly penalize Montanans who have to drive long distances. According to Resources for the Future, an environmental group, Mr. Breaux's gasoline tax would cost households in the Southwest and Rocky Mountain states about $100 a year, while costing Middle Atlantic households $75 a year.</p>
        <p>"There are a lot of suburbanites on the East Coast who drive long distance to work, and they would probably face the same burden as people in Western states," Mr. Durbin said.</p>
        <p>The Democrats on the Senate Finance Committee met for several hours today as senators took potshots at competing energy plans. They broke for the weekend still divided over what shape the energy tax should take and where spending cuts could be found. The chairman, Daniel Patrick Moynihan of New York, said he expected a consensus could be reached when the Democratic senators reconvene on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>For the committee to approve a bill, the Democrats must stick together. They have a majority of only 11 to 9, and all the Republicans have vowed to vote against the legislation.</p>
        <p>Some form of tax on transportation fuels and spending cuts in Medicare still seem likely to be approved. Senators John D. Rockefeller 4th of West Virginia and Donald W. Riegle Jr. of Michigan said they could not support cuts in Medicare much deeper than the $50 billion over five years that the Clinton Administration has proposed.</p>
        <p>One advantage of Mr. Breaux's proposed tax over a B.T.U. tax is that it would be far cheaper to administer. All it would take would be to increase existing fuel taxes, while administrating the B.T.U. tax would require a huge new apparatus, which some economists say could cost $10 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Convinced that a gasoline tax would be unfair to rural states, the Administration ruled out such a tax early. Treasury Secretary Lloyd Bentsen favored a sales tax, which would be inexpensive to administer. But Vice President Al Gore persuaded the Administration to put forward the B.T.U. tax because it would be better for the environment.</p>
        <p>Some economists favor combining a gasoline tax, which favors the densely populated East, where mass transit is more common, with a straight sales tax on energy, which would favor the West, where energy prices are cheaper. The Northwest would benefit disproportionately from a straight sales tax because hydroelectricty gives the region low-cost power.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
