<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Magazines, a Multimedia Wonderland</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="640338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAGAZINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CD-ROM (COMPACT DISK-READ ONLY MEMORY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONVENTIONS AND CONFERENCES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARMODY, DEIRDRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D6163FF932A25753C1A965958260" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Magazines, a Multimedia Wonderland</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEIRDRE CARMODY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARMODY, DEIRDRE</byline>
      <dateline>ORLANDO, Fla., Oct. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As magazine publishers become dazzled by the seductive possibilities of interactive electronic media, a sea change is occurring in the magazine industry.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is this more evident than at the annual American Magazine Conference, which opens here today with almost a third of the sessions devoted to multimedia publishing. Indeed, this conference, which has traditionally dealt only with magazines, could now be called the Mostly Magazine Festival.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As magazine publishers become dazzled by the seductive possibilities of interactive electronic media, a sea change is occurring in the magazine industry.</p>
        <p>Nowhere is this more evident than at the annual American Magazine Conference, which opens here today with almost a third of the sessions devoted to multimedia publishing. Indeed, this conference, which has traditionally dealt only with magazines, could now be called the Mostly Magazine Festival.</p>
        <p>It seems as if everyone is jumping on the multimedia bandwagon. The Magazine Publishers of America, which sponsors the conference, has just appointed a committee to study new media. And many leading magazine companies, including Time Inc., Hearst, Conde Nast and Times Mirror Magazines, are naming executives and establishing divisions to deal with multimedia development. All Kinds of Combinations</p>
        <p>"They may take some aspects of electronic media, some aspects of print and some aspects of interactive media and mix them together," Donald Kummerfeld, the president of the publishers' group, said. "There are a lot of ways of combining these."</p>
        <p>The moves are driven not only by new technology but by the lure of a new stream of revenue at a time when magazines have tightened their belts and the advertising picture is still grim.</p>
        <p>"Industry costs are under control; there will not be postage rate increases in 1994 and many magazine companies are now lean and mean, having downsized and reduced costs," said Robert J. Teufel, the president and operating chief of Rodale Press and chairman of the publishers' group. "Magazine companies are more aggressive in increasing subscriptions, but we are looking at other ways to increase revenues."</p>
        <p>Taking editorial matter that has already appeared in print and turning it into some form of video is not new. The first electronic boom took place in the early 1980's, when magazines and newspapers rushed to put their material on television. But it was not much of a success. It was not until the industry saw what Mr. Teufel called "the insatiable appetite of cable television for new shows" that editorial matter from magazines began to proliferate on television.</p>
        <p>A non-cable example is Rodale's "Trailside" show on PBS. Its host is John Viehman, the executive editor of the company's Backpacker magazine. Episodes include segments on mountain biking, sea kayaking and family camping -- topics drawn from material that has appeared in the magazine. The On-Line Opportunity</p>
        <p>These days, however, the hottest expansion areas for magazines are on-line services and CD-ROM technology.</p>
        <p>Through on-line services, subscribers can use their personal computers to read text, ask questions and express opinions on articles. The service becomes an electronic bulletin board for the magazine and its readers. Time magazine and Kiplinger's Personal Finance magazine, for instance, are now able to hold computer conversations with subscribers.</p>
        <p>After the first three weeks of its link with America Online, a nationwide computer network, Time magazine found that the service had been used 126,563 times, Time officials said. While some users wrote letters to the editor or sent messages to writers, others browsed through the full text of the magazine on their PC screens. In fact, they could find even more text than readers of the print magazine, because Time put some articles on-line that were not included in print because of lack of space.</p>
        <p>"People write two- or three-paragraph notes, saying things like 'I really disagree with your story,' or 'why haven't you done such-and-such a story,' or 'we really ought to get out of Somalia,' " said Walter Isaacson, an assistant managing editor at Time. "We haven't done any live chats yet, although we are about to."</p>
        <p>Kiplinger's Personal Finance magazine has been offered on-line through Prodigy Services for two years. The service allows readers to ask questions about personal finance.</p>
        <p>"We feel there is a promotional benefit to being on a service like this," said Knight A. Kiplinger, the editor in chief and president of the magazine. "And far from diverting readership from our magazine, we are expanding readership."  The Potential of CD-ROM</p>
        <p>CD-ROM technology, in which text, photographs, sound and moving video images are stored on compact disks, also has appeal for magazines, as more Americans buy the equipment to use it. Magazine officials estimate that three million to five million CD-ROM players will be in American homes by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Last year, Newsweek introduced a quarterly CD-ROM. The most recent has two Newsweek cover stories -- one on the environment and one on baseball -- that run 10 to 15 minutes each as narrative documentaries. With a click of the button, the viewer can call up a text version with highlighted terms, like "greenhouse effect" in the environmental report. If the viewer is not sure what the term means, another click of the button will get the explanation.</p>
        <p>The viewer can also press a search button and get an index of all Newsweek articles on a given subject. Another click will produce a designated story.</p>
        <p>Richard M. Smith, the president and editor in chief of Newsweek, said a subscription for four CD-ROM's costs slightly less than $100. The magazine is testing prices in the $50 range for individual CD-ROM's.</p>
        <p>"The primary reason we are in this business is that we think that given the spread of CD-ROM's, it has the potential to be a good business on its own," Mr. Smith said.</p>
        <p>"The quarterly presentation of material that has been in the magazine is really a data base for the user who wants to go after it," he said. "And the supplementary information is good editorial product." Defining the Market</p>
        <p>Whether the multimedia technology involves on-line services or CD-ROM's, magazines are still testing the waters of its use. No one really knows yet what the market is.</p>
        <p>"There should be a healthy degree of skepticism about how quickly some of these things take hold," said Curt Viebranz, the president of Time Inc.'s new multimedia division. "We are not looking to create some huge infrastructure for a lot of people but rather to create an integrated strategy for multimedia for Time Inc."</p>
        <p>The Hearst Corporation recently named Alfred C. Sikes, a former chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, to head the Hearst New Media Group. He, too, said he was cautious about the possibilities: "The question is, over an extended period of time, is there any market for magazines essentially regurgitated into electronic form?" he said.  "We don't know. And anybody who doesn't admit to ambiguity in this market just isn't being honest."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
