<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Year of Weather: Some of It Was Strange</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="594973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EL NINO (PACIFIC OCEAN CURRENT)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOUNT PINATUBO (PHILIPPINES)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PHILIPPINES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PACIFIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Philippines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC163FF93AA35750C0A965958260" item-length="1484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Year of Weather: Some of It Was Strange</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR the last year, it seems, the Northeastern United States has lurched from one abnormal weather event to another.</p>
        <p>First came the coolest summer in decades. Then one of the worst northeasters on record lashed the Atlantic Seaboard in late fall. December and January were unusually mild. Successive snowfalls surprised the region in February, and hard on their heels last week came yet another damaging northeaster. And while all this was going on, the Far West was enduring monumental snows and drenching winter rains that reversed a 10-year pattern of drought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR the last year, it seems, the Northeastern United States has lurched from one abnormal weather event to another.</p>
        <p>First came the coolest summer in decades. Then one of the worst northeasters on record lashed the Atlantic Seaboard in late fall. December and January were unusually mild. Successive snowfalls surprised the region in February, and hard on their heels last week came yet another damaging northeaster. And while all this was going on, the Far West was enduring monumental snows and drenching winter rains that reversed a 10-year pattern of drought.</p>
        <p>It is a meteorological truism that the abnormal is normal; some place is always experiencing what seems to be unusual weather. Most of it is, in fact, an inevitable product of the global climate system's usual churning, but occasionally the cause really is an out-of-the-ordinary natural force. Two such forces have been at work in recent months, and new developments suggest that the influence of both will continue well into 1993.</p>
        <p>The first is El Nino, the vast pool of warm water that develops every two to seven years in the eastern Pacific Ocean off South America. It reappeared about 15 months ago and set off a chain of atmospheric events that among other things, brought heavy rains to Texas and Mexico in early 1992 and contributed to storms in California and across the country into the Northeast this winter.</p>
        <p>El Nino seemed to be dying out last summer, as typically happens after a spring peak, but it hung on through the fall and into 1993. Now, measurements of ocean currents produced by a new French-American satellite show that another, somewhat smaller pool of warm water appears to be developing off the South American coast. This is likely to revive El Nino, scientists say, producing a one-two punch that while unusual is not unprecedented.</p>
        <p>A resurgent El Nino would probably reinforce a strong subtropical jet stream that has been traversing the Southern United States this winter, bringing more cool, wet weather to much of the Southern tier, said Jim Wagner, an analyst at the National Weather Service's Climate Analysis Center at Camp Springs, Md.</p>
        <p>The second force having an impact on global climate is Mount Pinatubo, the Philippine volcano that erupted in June 1991. New data from another satellite confirm for the first time that the global haze of sulfurous aerosols from the eruption has reflected enough sunlight to cool the earth by about 1 degree Fahrenheit, as climatologists had predicted by using computerized models of the atmosphere. The new measurements are reported in the current issue of the journal Science by Dr. Patrick Minnis of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Langley Research Center and six colleagues.</p>
        <p>Taken together with global temperature observations, the satellite data appear to bolster the modelers' prediction that the cooling effect of the eruption will gradually diminish this year and in early 1994. The modelers expect the earth to warm up again after that; by the late 1990's, they expect average global temperatures to exceed the record levels of the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>While scientists stop short of pinning direct blame for last year's chilly Northeastern summer on the volcano, they say it could have been indirectly responsible by altering large-scale patterns of atmospheric circulation.</p>
        <p>As for this winter's unusual weather on the East and West Coasts, according to meteorologists, the responsibility may be laid more directly, at least in part, on El Nino. In December and January a huge ridge of high air pressure over the Gulf of Alaska diverted the jet stream -- the big, high-altitude river of air that flows around the Northern Hemisphere from west to east -- toward Hawaii. There it picked up moisture, some of it probably produced by the unusually persistent El Nino. Then this "pineapple express," as Mr. Wagner called it, turned eastward and dropped its moisture on the West -- either as rain or, inland and to the north, as snow.</p>
        <p>A new pattern took hold in the first week of February, when the big high pressure system repositioned itself over western Canada, according to Paul G. Knight, a meteorologist at the Pennsylvania State University. This time it directed arctic air down through the central plains. There it encountered moist air from the Gulf of Mexico and from a strong southern branch of the jet stream that owed its strength partly to El Nino. This produced snow storms that moved across the country and eventually hit the Northeast. Volatile Transition Weather</p>
        <p>This pattern ended on Feb. 28, Mr. Knight said, and it is unclear what will replace it. Last week's rains, snows and high winds in the Northeast developed in what Mr. Knight described as a transition period between two stable weather patterns. Such transition periods, he said, can be quite volatile.</p>
        <p>A rejuvenated El Nino could well be part of whatever springtime pattern develops and could even persist into summer. If El Nino lasts through the spring, said Mr. Wagner of the weather service, it could also affect hurricane activity in the Atlantic. By producing a stronger-than-usual west-to-east flow of air across the Southern United States and out into the ocean, it could create a strong subtropical jet stream that would simply "shear apart" the oceanic storm clusters that are spawned in West Africa and can develop into hurricanes.</p>
        <p>But while there may be fewer hurricanes under those conditions, it takes only one to wreak major destruction. That happened last August; Hurricane Andrew almost died out before turning into the monster that struck south Florida.</p>
        <p>El Nino also has global effects, disrupting the weather in South America and causing drought and heat in much of the Southern Hemisphere. The present two-stage El Nino, however, has not been as disruptive as those that occurred in 1982-83 and 1986-87.</p>
        <p>Mount Pinatubo's direct influence -- the 1-degree global cooling -- is too small, by itself, to make any big difference in local weather, with its wide seasonal and daily swings. But scientists at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York say that the 1992 summertime cooling was greater in continental interiors, a regional pattern observed in more extreme form in 1816, the "year without a summer" that followed the eruption of the Mount Tambora volcano in Indonesia.</p>
        <p>The Goddard scientists suspect that because the continental land mass reacts more rapidly to cooling than does the ocean, a large-scale change in the movement of air currents took place last summer. That is, the difference in temperature between the continent and the oceans would have produced a difference in air pressure as well. In the East, this would have resulted in a northeasterly flow of cooler air from the ocean to the coast.</p>
        <p>That, in fact, did happen last summer and could have contributed to the Northeast's abnormal summertime chill. But Dr. James Hansen, a climatologist at the Goddard Institute, warned that the link between the volcano and the weather has not yet been scientifically tested.</p>
        <p>In any case, Dr. Minnis said, it appears that the volcanic haze is steadily dissipating. Based on their computerized model of the atmosphere, Goddard scientists predicted months ago that the global temperature would recover nearly to pre-eruption levels by early 1994. So far, actual temperatures have roughly matched the model's predictions. The model, for example, forecast that the cooling would bottom out in late 1992, and temperature measurements indicate that it did.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hansen and others view the Goddard predictions as an important test of the accuracy of the model, which has also forecast that a buildup of waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide in the atmosphere will cause a significant global warming in the next century. If the Goddard model is right, global temperatures should reach record levels in the latter half of this decade. The two warmest years now on record, 1989 and 1990, immediately preceded the Mount Pinatubo eruption. More of the Same Difference</p>
        <p>While it remains to be seen how this will all play out, Mr. Wagner of the weather service offers this March-through-May forecast for the United States:</p>
        <p>Warmer than normal, with an early spring, in the Northwest. Drier than normal in the north-central part of the country.</p>
        <p>Colder than normal in northern New England and in the Southeast, especially along the Gulf Coast and in Florida. Wetter than normal in South Carolina, Georgia and northern Florida.</p>
        <p>Everywhere else is expected to have a "normal" season, although the middle Atlantic states and southern New England "might squeak out a mild March," said Mr. Wagner. After that the weather should be typical for the season. That is, variable: some mild spells, some cold, some dry and some wet, all adding up to an average spring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
