<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Norwegians Claim Their Whaling Rights</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="626960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SANCTIONS (ECONOMIC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHALES AND WHALING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOYCOTTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORWAY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">REINE (NORWAY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GREENPEACE (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DARNTON, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D91F3CF934A3575BC0A965958260" item-length="1447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Norwegians Claim Their Whaling Rights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN DARNTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DARNTON, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>REINE, Norway, Aug. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Norway has a reputation for being ecologically correct. Its melodramatic mountains and fjords are kept pristine. Hotels are apt to post notes requesting guests to reuse their towels to cut down on the use of detergents. Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland is so widely known as an environmentalist that she has been nicknamed "the Green Queen."</p>
        <p>So it is an odd twist of fate that Norway is becoming a pariah among ecologists and a target for direct action campaigns by groups like Greenpeace. It is the first country to face the serious prospect of trade sanctions by the United States for undermining a conservation effort. Insist on Their Right</p>
        <p>The reason is to be found in this tiny harbor village of 500 people in the Lofoten Islands, 60 miles north of the Arctic Circle. It is home to men who insist that they have a right to do what their fathers did -- to venture across the icy waters to hunt the minke whale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Norway has a reputation for being ecologically correct. Its melodramatic mountains and fjords are kept pristine. Hotels are apt to post notes requesting guests to reuse their towels to cut down on the use of detergents. Prime Minister Gro Harlem Brundtland is so widely known as an environmentalist that she has been nicknamed "the Green Queen."</p>
        <p>So it is an odd twist of fate that Norway is becoming a pariah among ecologists and a target for direct action campaigns by groups like Greenpeace. It is the first country to face the serious prospect of trade sanctions by the United States for undermining a conservation effort. Insist on Their Right</p>
        <p>The reason is to be found in this tiny harbor village of 500 people in the Lofoten Islands, 60 miles north of the Arctic Circle. It is home to men who insist that they have a right to do what their fathers did -- to venture across the icy waters to hunt the minke whale.</p>
        <p>"They say we have to protect the minke," said Bjorn Hugo Bendiksen, a 29-year-old whaler who began learning his trade on his father's boat when he was 15. "There's no reason to protect them. They're plentiful. Killing a minke is no different from killing a deer."</p>
        <p>Sentiments like these horrify Greenpeace campaigners who have been chaining themselves to Norwegian tourist offices and fishing boats this summer as Norway became the first country to resume commercial whaling in defiance of a 1986 moratorium imposed by the International Whaling Commission. The commission was set up in 1949 to regulate whaling at a time when whales were rapidly disappearing.</p>
        <p>So far this season, Norwegian fishing boats, most of them from Reine, have killed 153 minke whales, only 7 short of the commercial quota of 160 set by the Government.</p>
        <p>Other whales remain strictly off limits, and in an effort to head off charges of profiteering, Norway has promised not to export whale meat to consumer countries like Japan.</p>
        <p>But Norway's defiance has touched off an international boycott. A German supermarket chain has stopped buying Norwegian prawns and salmon. A British company has stopped importing Norwegian sleeping bags. And Greenpeace and other groups are promoting a move to keep travelers away from next year's Winter Olympics at Lillehammer. Trade Restrictions Feared</p>
        <p>More worrisome from Norway's view is the possibility that the United States might impose restrictions on some of the $2 billion in imports from Norway under an amendment to the 1967 Fishermen's Protective Act.  [ On Aug. 5, Secretary of Commerce Ronald Brown certified that Norway's actions had "diminished the effectiveness of an international program for the conservation of endangered or threatened species," giving President Clinton 60 days to decide on sanctions. ]</p>
        <p>Given that the House of Representatives passed a resolution condemning Norway, 347 to 0, only six months ago, there is little doubt how the political wind is blowing. "This is more than a scientific question," an American diplomat said. "It's a political issue. When you get a vote of 347 to 0, you can count whales all day, but there's no way we could support their hunt."</p>
        <p>Along Norway's northern coast, where whaling and fishing are part of a mystique of rugged self-reliance, the condemnation from abroad raises puzzled consternation. The outside world has mixed up David and Goliath, the people here say.</p>
        <p>"People in the U.S. are totally misinformed," said Georg Blichfeldt, secretary of the High North Alliance, a pro-whaling group. "They think there's a big whaling industry, factory ships out there hunting down the last few whales. We're just a bunch of stupid little boats owned by families fighting for our rights. The only big organizations living off the whales today are Greenpeace and the Whale and Dolphin Society that use them as symbols for money raising."</p>
        <p>For a whaler like Mr. Bendiksen, being on one of the 28 Norwegian whaling boats, alloted a quota of five or six whales each, has meant the difference between just scraping by and relative affluence. In the early 1980's, when whale quotas were higher, the minke catch doubled his total fishing income, bringing in an extra 100,000 krona, or $15,000. For the last six years, once the winter cod ran out in April, he dreaded the idle summer months.</p>
        <p>Now, after his boat's haul of 33,000 pounds of whale meat selling at about $3.60 a pound, he is breathing easier. He has just purchased a modest house in the center of town for his wife, Nina, and their 7-month-old son, Sverre. On summer evenings when it never really gets dark here, he tosses whale meat onto the barbecue -- "the finest beef in the world," he proclaims -- and as he looks up at the mountains, he feels that all is right in the world.</p>
        <p>Reine is a cluster of two-story pink, yellow, white and brown houses with white picket fences and is surrounded on three sides by sheer cliffs. Still pockmarked with snow, the cliffs disappear into enveloping clouds by mid-morning. On the outskirts of town are brightly painted cottages on stilts over the marshes for itinerant workers.</p>
        <p>The village lives off fishing, and people here say the last six years have been tough.</p>
        <p>"Before the ban there were 80 boats," Mr. Bendiksen said of the village's total fishing and whaling vessels. "Now, there are 40. In another 5 or 6 years, there'll be 6 or 7. We'll have to pack up and move away."</p>
        <p>Norway contends that among the 80 or so species of whales, the minke, which is relatively small at about 30 feet and between 6 and 8 tons, is plentiful enough to sustain a controlled harvest. It cites figures accepted by the Whaling Commission's scientific committee that there are about 87,000 minke whales in the northeastern Atlantic. Although the Government insists that it could kill some 800 minkes a year without depleting the stock, it limited the quota this year to 160. An additional 136 minke whales are hunted by Norway for "research." Census Called Unreliable</p>
        <p>Organizations like Greenpeace assert that Norway's whale census is unreliable and that the country's defiance could cause other whaling nations like Iceland and Japan to turn their backs on the moratorium. They say the whole system to protect threatened species could come tumbling down.</p>
        <p>"Frankly, no one really knows how many whales are out there," said Andy Ottaway, Greenpeace's whale campaign coordinator. "The numbers are uncertain. There are so many unknowns. What's the effect of climate change? Of overfishing? No one can say for sure.</p>
        <p>"Norway has killed more whales than any other nation on earth," Mr. Ottaway asserted. "It's time they were stopped. Whaling's a thing of the past. It belongs condemned to history, to a time when sadly we knew no better."</p>
        <p>Norway insists that there must be a scientific basis to sound ecological management and that a quota system for an abundant species of whales makes sense.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Prime Minister Brundtland said Norway had a long tradition of "sustainable development," or using resources without depleting them. She maintains that campaigns to save an unthreatened species of whale simply divert public attention from the real threats -- the pollution and high energy consumption of countries like the United States, Britain and Germany. 'We Feel Dictated To'</p>
        <p>"Of course we feel dictated to," she said. "It's a completely illogical, irrational, wrongly based campaign."</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister, who is facing an election in September, stands to gain politically from allowing the whaling to resume. But she asserts that she has acted on principle.</p>
        <p>On the other side, ecologists and others argue that the whales are not Norway's to deal with as Norway wishes, since the minke migrates thousands of miles to summer in the Arctic. They have long been outraged that Japan and Norway are allowed to kill even a limited number of whales for "research" -- to obtain information on the effects of pollution, feeding patterns and breeding -- and to sell the meat of the whales thus harvested on the open market.</p>
        <p>As animal welfare groups gain in influence in the ecology movement, there is growing sentiment that the killing of whales is inhumane and morally wrong. Those campaigning for whales view them as unique and majestic mammals of humbling size. There are many stories about their intelligence and their bond of family.</p>
        <p>To the whalers, the minke is just another animal. To appease those worried about inhumane deaths, the Government has sent an inspector on each whaling ship with a stopwatch to time the deaths from an exploding harpoon. The whalers say the average death is well under 4 minutes, but Greenpeace says it is closer to 10 minutes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
