<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton's Economic Opus: A Thousand Lines of Type</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="591895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4D61531F932A15751C0A965958260" item-length="1301" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton's Economic Opus: A Thousand Lines of Type</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Highlights President Clinton proposed an ambitious plan to remake the American economy, raising taxes on energy, business and the rich, making deep cuts in the military, the Federal bureaucracy and health care payments, and trimming the budget deficit. As Republicans dug in their heels, Mr. Clinton and his aides began a cross-country campaign to sell the program to the American people. DEFICIT REDUCTION Over the next four years, the plan would have the Government take in $246 billion in new taxes and spend $247 billion less than planned in present budgets. It would increase other spending on "stimulus and investment" by $169 billion. The net reduction in the deficit over those four years would be $325 billion. But deficit reduction would not begin until next year, because an extra $30 billion would be spent this year to stimulate the economy. (1) (see The Fine Print at right)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Highlights President Clinton proposed an ambitious plan to remake the American economy, raising taxes on energy, business and the rich, making deep cuts in the military, the Federal bureaucracy and health care payments, and trimming the budget deficit. As Republicans dug in their heels, Mr. Clinton and his aides began a cross-country campaign to sell the program to the American people. DEFICIT REDUCTION Over the next four years, the plan would have the Government take in $246 billion in new taxes and spend $247 billion less than planned in present budgets. It would increase other spending on "stimulus and investment" by $169 billion. The net reduction in the deficit over those four years would be $325 billion. But deficit reduction would not begin until next year, because an extra $30 billion would be spent this year to stimulate the economy. (1) (see The Fine Print at right)</p>
        <p>TAX INCREASES Personal Rates: The top marginal income tax rate, now 31 percent, would be raised to 36 percent for couples with a taxable income of $140,000, single heads of household with a taxable income of $127,000 and individuals with a taxable income of $115,000. A taxable income of $140,000 is the equivalent of adjusted gross income of about $180,000. (2) Surtax: A 10 percent surtax would be placed on taxable incomes above $250,000. (3) Captial gains: The top tax rate would remain at 28 percent. Medicare tax: Wealthy individuals would have to pay Medicare tax on all their earned income, not just the first $135,000. Social Security:Retired couples with incomes above $32,000 and individuals with incomes above $25,000 would pay income taxes on 85 percent of their Social Security benefits, up from 50 percent. Energy tax: A tax on most forms of energy would eventually raise families' annual combined bills for gasoline, home heat and electricity by between $100 and $150. (4) Business Rates: The top corporate tax rate, now 34 percent, would be raised to 36 percent on companies with taxable incomes of more than $10 million - about one-tenth of 1 percent of American companies. Deductions limited: Only 50 percent of the cost of business meals and entertainment could be deducted, down from 80 percent. Deductions lost: Lobbying expenses and club dues would no longer be deductible. Businesses would be denied deductions for executives' pay above $1 million a year. (5) Credits Lost: The 100 percent credit for wages paid to workers in Puerto Rico would be reduced to 65 percent. Portfolios: Securities dealers would be required to price their holdings at market value. Multinationals: Taxes would be raised for some multinational and foreign companies doing business in the United States. Users fees: Fees would rise or be imposed for many Government services, including grazing or mining on Federal lands, recreation in national parks and forests, use of inland waterways and registration of airplanes. TAX CUTS Personal Virtually all families with incomes below $30,000 would get earned-income tax credits. Business Capital gains: A special capital gains break would be given for investments in small businesses held at least five years. Investment credits: Small businesses would get a generous investment tax credit for the purchase of new equipment. Real estate: Write-offs of losses from real estate investments would be made more generous for taxpayers in the real estate business. Charity: Taxpayers who make gifts to charitable organizations like museums would be permitted to take deductions for market value, not purchase price. IMMEDIATE ECONOMIC STIMULUS More would be spent this year on construction projects, summer jobs, wastewater clean-up, childhood immunization and other programs. FUTURE SPENDING INCREASES More would be spent on research into nuclear fusion and renewable energy and on making buildings more energy efficient. A program to let students pay off colege loans through national service would be created. More money would go to worker training and Head Start. More community-development grants and tax incentives for businesses and housing in poor areas would be offered. The Government would help pay for a fiber-optic data network. More would be spent on mass transit, high-speed rail, airports and highways. SPENDING CUTS Military spending would be reduced over the next four years by $76 billion more than President Bush planned, mostly by paring 200,000 more troops and most Star Wars spending. New limits would be placed on some payments to doctors, hospital and laboratories under Medicare and Medicaid. Federal workers would have their pay frozen for one year. About 100,000 Federal jobs would be eliminated through attrition. Spending for the space station and the superconducting super collider would be reduced. Loans for veterans housing would cost more, and veterans would pay part of G.I. Bill benefits. To cut interest costs, the maturity of some Treasury securities would be shortened. Scores of other Government programs would be eliminated or timmed back. (The Fine Print) (1) Shifting the Blame In its first two years, Mr. Clinton's plan to reduce the deficit relies mostly on tax increases, not on spending cuts, which are probably even more difficult to get through Congress. In 1994, spending cuts would amount to only $5 billion, while additional taxes would bring in $33 billion. Then the cuts accelerate. By 1997, after another round of Congressional elections, they would climb to $73 billion, while taxes would bring in $68 billion. (2) Who's Middle Class? The Administration says 70 percent of the tax increases would be paid by those with pre-tax incomes over $100,000. It calculates that taxpayers with incomes over $200,000 would see their taxes rise by about 3 percent. Those with incomes between $30,000 and $200,000 would see increase of up to 1 percent. Those below $30,000 would get no increase. (3) Politically Graceful With the surfax, the top marginal tax rate for Americans earning at least $250,000 in taxable income would amount to 39.6 percent. The White House chose to phrase it as a "10 percent millionaire's surfax " - more politically palatable than asking for a rate of nearly 40 percent. (4)So What's a B.T.U. The energy tax is based on the B.T.U. content of different fuels. (It's British Thermal Units, not Buy Thermal Underwear). As a common denominator, it's easier to use than calculating barrels vs. tons vs. cubic feet vs. kilowatts. It also makes more sense than taxing fuels simply on what they cost: $100 worth of coal, for example, contains far more unreleased heat (measured in B.T.U.'s) than $100 worth of natural gas or $100 worth of gasoline. And a B.T.U. tax also would not penalize states that use one fuel instead of another. To discourage dependence on imported oil, oil would be taxed at 60 cents per million B.T.U.'s, whether it's refined into gasoline or jet fuel or burned to make electricity. Coal, natural gas and nuclear power would be taxed at 26 cents per million B.T.U.'s. Solar, geothermal, wind and other renewable sources would not be taxed. Oil used to make things like plastics, chemicals and tires would not be taxed. The tax climbs very rapidly. It is expected to take in only $1.5 billion next year, but $25 billion by 1997. Within 4 years, it is expected to add 7.5 cents to the cost of a gallon of gas and $2.25 to the average electric bill. (5) The Executive Loophole Exceptions could be made for salaries tied to the company's performance; the Treasury has not defined them yet. Many executive pay packages are now tied to some measure of performance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
