<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oxygen Loss Causing Concern in Biosphere 2</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="580942"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOSPHERE 2 (ORACLE, ARIZ)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OXYGEN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDD103DF936A35752C0A965958260" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oxygen Loss Causing Concern in Biosphere 2</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OXYGEN levels within the miniature world of Biosphere 2 in Arizona have dropped more than 28 percent since four men and four women were sealed inside the ecological experiment in September 1991, and no one knows why.</p>
        <p>Project leaders, expecting the decline to continue, have made arrangements to pump tons of pure oxygen into the 3.15 acres of glass domes if the eight inhabitants of the $150 million experiment begin to languish.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OXYGEN levels within the miniature world of Biosphere 2 in Arizona have dropped more than 28 percent since four men and four women were sealed inside the ecological experiment in September 1991, and no one knows why.</p>
        <p>Project leaders, expecting the decline to continue, have made arrangements to pump tons of pure oxygen into the 3.15 acres of glass domes if the eight inhabitants of the $150 million experiment begin to languish.</p>
        <p>The mystery has attracted increasing scientific interest, and one theory is that the oxygen is being removed by a reaction in the soil.</p>
        <p>The oxygen content of the Biosphere's air is now equal to that found at an altitude of about 12,000 feet (twice the height of Mount Washington in New Hampshire, the highest peak in New England). By volume, the amount of oxygen has dropped to about 15 percent from the 21 percent at sea level. Plan for Emergency</p>
        <p>In an interview, Bill Dempster, director of systems engineering at the project, said emergency action would probably come in six months or so if the oxygen thinned to 13.6 percent -- equal to 15,000 feet, near the maximum altitude humans live comfortably in the Andes and Himalayas.</p>
        <p>"We're monitoring the Biospherians very closely," Mr. Dempster said. "This whole thing came as a surprise, but it's the kind of mystery Biosphere 2 was meant to investigate."</p>
        <p>The private project in the foothills north of Tucson began with much fanfare, described as a utopian planet-in-a-bottle where everything would be recycled for two years. The structure was billed as the first large self-contained habitat for humans, as cut off from the planet as a spaceship.</p>
        <p>But extreme secrecy, charges of fakery and a string of embarrassing disclosures about less-than-pristine methods led to a credibility crisis and a recent vow by leaders to be more open about the project's inner workings.</p>
        <p>The two-year experiment is scheduled to end this September -- even, officials now say, if it takes large injections of pure oxygen to help the Biospherians go the full duration.</p>
        <p>"It's very unlikely that we'd come out," Dr. Roy Walford, a 68-year-old physician who is the oldest of the eight Biospherians, said from within the domes in a telephone interview last week. "We'd bring in oxygen." Headaches and Fatigue</p>
        <p>Already, he said, "we're showing some symptoms of oxygen lack, mild headache, sleeping problems at night, fatigue." He added that there was no physical danger, since the oxygen drop had been very slow. "The limiting factor will be that we're too fatigued or too uncomfortable to go on," he said, referring to the low oxygen levels. "The ability to do heavy labor goes down."</p>
        <p>Four of the eight Biospherians have been put on acetazolamide, which reduces symptoms of high-altitude sickness, Dr. Walford said. It counteracts changes in blood chemistry caused by heavy breathing.</p>
        <p>At night some Biospherians have awakened gasping for breath. To avoid such discomfort, their sleeping quarters have now been equipped with breathing gear that carries oxygen concentrated from within the domes. Dr. Walford said that he used the breathing aid nearly every night, and that some of the others used it occasionally.</p>
        <p>The scientific mystery, which is attracting growing interest, is why the oxygen content of the air is going down. The acres of leafy plants, especially during the long daylight hours of summer, produce an abundance of oxygen in the course of photosynthesis. But for some reason, part of this natural production is being lost.</p>
        <p>In theory the culprit could be something as simple as rust, which forms when oxygen binds to iron or steel. But the project's designers, foreseeing this danger, used stainless steel throughout.</p>
        <p>The chief suspect is now the soil, either microorganisms in it or some type of chemical reaction. Soil by nature often tends to respire, taking in oxygen and giving off carbon dioxide. Scientists believe it may be doing more of this than previously suspected.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wallace S. Broecker, a leading geochemist at the Lamont-Doherty Geological Observatory of Columbia University in Palisades, N.Y., has been studying the problem with colleagues, noting in an interview that his efforts were unpaid so as to avoid "the impression that we're hired guns." Possible Causes</p>
        <p>He said, "There's probably 9 chances in 10 that the problem is how they manufactured the soil." But he added that there was a 1 in 10 chance that the answer would have implications for other things, for fundamental principles of ecology.</p>
        <p>Unable to import tons of soil from around the world for Biosphere 2's various climatic zones, which include a rain forest, a savanna and an intensive agriculture section, its designers mixed local soils from the Arizona desert site with "rich organic matter from a swampy area near a cattle watering hole," Dr. Broecker said.</p>
        <p>It contained dung, urine, cactus pads, twigs, leaves and mesquite beans, all trampled down by the cattle over the years into a heady brew.</p>
        <p>Upon learning that, Dr. Broecker said, he and his colleagues did experiments to see if urea in the urine was somehow responsible for the drop. It was not. Another series of experiments, aimed at a different chemical suspect, also came up negative.</p>
        <p>Today a leading theory is that the oxygen is reacting throughout the soil to form calcium carbonate, the material found in limestone and caves. But the idea is hard to test experimentally.</p>
        <p>"The whole oxygen thing remains a mystery," Dr. Broecker said.</p>
        <p>Increasingly uneasy, officials of Biosphere 2 have taken steps to aid colleagues in the domes, if needed. Arrangements have been made to buy tons of liquid oxygen, which would expand into a gas as it was injected into the domes.</p>
        <p>"If we decided to raise the level by 2 percent, that would be 100,000 cubic feet of gaseous oxygen," said Mr. Dempster, the director of systems engineering, adding that the proper fittings for such an operation were already in place.</p>
        <p>"The only delay would be having the supplier bring it," Mr. Dempster said. "That would take two hours, maybe. Certainly not a week. At worst, we're figuring 24 hours."  THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
