<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barnard's President To Head Museum Of Natural History</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="618413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN MUSEUM OF NATURAL HISTORY (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BARNARD COLLEGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUTTER, ELLEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HONAN, WILLIAM H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D91F39F93AA15755C0A965958260" item-length="1702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barnard's President To Head Museum Of Natural History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM H. HONAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HONAN, WILLIAM H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reaching beyond the realm of science for someone they hope will make the American Museum of Natural History more competitive with the city's other major cultural institutions, the museum's trustees yesterday named Ellen V. Futter, who has been the president of Barnard College for 13 years, as the second paid president in the institution's 124-year history.</p>
        <p>The appointment makes Ms. Futter, 43, who had been the youngest person ever to head a major American college, now the first woman to assume full-time leadership in New York City's top tier of museums.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reaching beyond the realm of science for someone they hope will make the American Museum of Natural History more competitive with the city's other major cultural institutions, the museum's trustees yesterday named Ellen V. Futter, who has been the president of Barnard College for 13 years, as the second paid president in the institution's 124-year history.</p>
        <p>The appointment makes Ms. Futter, 43, who had been the youngest person ever to head a major American college, now the first woman to assume full-time leadership in New York City's top tier of museums.</p>
        <p>When she leaves Barnard to take up her duties at the museum in November, she will succeed Dr. George D. Langdon Jr., who announced in December that he intended to step down when he completed his five-year term. Her departure came as a surprise to Barnard's trustees, who learned of her new appointment over the weekend.</p>
        <p>Ms. Futter has no professional training in science; she practiced corporate law before becoming the president of Barnard and comes from a family of lawyers. But she speaks with evangelical fervor about the importance of science and technology today.</p>
        <p>"This is a golden age of science and scientific education," she said in an interview yesterday. "This museum decodes and demystifies life and in that process can help promote understanding in societal terms. It can provide great hope and comfort." New Emphasis on Culture</p>
        <p>William T. Golden, the chairman of the museum, said that the choice of Ms. Futter, who achieved a strong record as a fund-raiser at Barnard, represents the transition of the museum from an institutional wallflower to an aggressive suitor in cultural philanthropy.</p>
        <p>"We have not had the prominence of the Metropolitan Museum, the Met Opera, the New York Public Library and other major cultural institutions because we haven't been tapping the vast water table of financial resources in New York City," he said.</p>
        <p>"For many years," he continued, "the attitude at the museum was if the money came, it came, and if it didn't, it didn't. But now that we have decided to modernize our exhibits and provide more nourishment for our scientific and educational departments, we know this is going to take resources. Ellen Futter's intelligence, managerial skill, fund-raising ability and inexhaustible energy suit her for the job."</p>
        <p>The American Museum of Natural History, whose collections include 36 million artifacts ranging from a 50-foot Barosaurus skeleton to innumerable spiders and a 14-ton meteorite (next door in the Hayden Planetarium) to a 94-foot-long steel-and-fiberglass model of a blue whale, is one of the largest and wealthiest cultural institutions in New York. Its $220 million endowment is close to that of the New York Public Library ($264 million). The lordly Metropolitan Museum of Art has an endowment of $631.7 million.</p>
        <p>Despite the size of its endowment, however, the museum has had a lower profile among New Yorkers than many of the city's other major cultural institutions. While it has about three million visitors annually (compared to 4.4 million for the Metropolitan Museum), a great many of these are schoolchildren, and the museum has not attracted the city's social and philanthropic community to the extent the Met or the New York Public Library has. Issues of Tomorrow</p>
        <p>David A. Hamburg, the president of the Carnegie Corporation of New York and the head of the search committee, praised Ms. Futter's leadership at Barnard, which led to a record-breaking year in applications, with a 19 percent increase in students seeking places in the class of 1997. This follows a 21 percent upsurge for the previous year, he said.</p>
        <p>Barnard College and the museum have closely comparable operating budgets, with the college spending about $60 million a year and the museum $56 million. During Ms. Futter's tenure at Barnard, the 104-year-old college became fully residential for the first time through the construction of two dormitories, including a 17-story tower named after Iphigene Ochs Sulzberger, a Barnard alumna and trustee.</p>
        <p>The trustees of Barnard were taking the matter philosophically at an informational meeting at the college yesterday afternoon. Patricia F. Green, the chairwoman of Barnard, said: "We're very happy for her. Once you get past 10 years with someone as good as Ellen, it's gravy. We were almost expecting it."</p>
        <p>Ms. Green said that Barnard would name an acting president by November and that a full search committee would start work shortly.</p>
        <p>Ms. Futter said yesterday that her four goals were to make the museum "a leading public forum, both nationally and internationally, for the debate of the great scientific issues of our time; substantially enlarging the museum's educative role for both adults and children; dramatically increasing the museum's visibility and influence in New York, and making the museum's scholarly work better known."</p>
        <p>"The issues that this museum will take up -- the environment, biodiversity, ethical questions, human biology and cultural diversity -- are ones that will dominate the political agenda and public-policy debate in years to come," she said.</p>
        <p>In December, when announcing the formation of a search committee to seek a successor for Dr. Langdon, Mr. Golden said candidates' scientific achievements or interests would be considered as well as administrative and fund-raising skills.</p>
        <p>When asked about Ms. Futter's lack of professional training in science, Mr. Golden said, "That quality is in the orchestra, not the conductor." He then spoke highly of Michael J. Novacek, the museum's vice president and dean of science, and said, "his presence makes up for not having that quality in the president."</p>
        <p>As for Ms. Futter's talents, he said, "What prevailed were her leadership qualities, administrative skill, financial acumen and demonstrated fund-raising ability." A Layman's Perspective</p>
        <p>Ms. Futter acknowledged with a laugh that her connection with science and technology is "long on interest and short on achievement."</p>
        <p>She added that her layman's perspective can be beneficial. "I, as an educator and nonscientist, may be particularly effective in helping to translate issues so that lay people can grasp and take delight in them," she said.</p>
        <p>"One of my goals," she continued, "will certainly be to help in the presentation through exhibits, symposiums, software and print materials to help take complex scientific issues and put them in terms that are digestible."</p>
        <p>Ms. Futter was born in New York City and attended high school in Port Washington, L.I.. A Barnard alumna, she graduated from the Columbia University School of Law and practiced corporate law for six years with the Wall Street firm of Milbank, Tweed, Hadley &amp; McCloy.</p>
        <p>She serves on the boards of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, Bristol-Myers Squibb Company, CBS, and the Consolidated Edison Company, among others. Steps Toward Modernization</p>
        <p>In their announcement yesterday, the trustees praised Dr. Langdon for "many enduring accomplishments." Mr. Golden said in an interview that Dr. Langdon, a former president of Colgate University and a specialist in American colonial history, had changed the museum's administration "from a medieval to a modern organization" and deserved credit for guiding the construction of museum's eight-story library, which opened last year; the permanent dinosaur exhibit, which is to open in the spring of 1995, and special exhibitions including "Global Warming," which is now touring the country.</p>
        <p>Several trustees, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said that the board and Dr. Langdon, who became the museum's first paid president in 1988, had mutually decided to let his contract run out and let the museum seek someone who would move more quickly to modernize the exhibitions and improve its educational efforts.</p>
        <p>All the trustees interviewed insisted that accusations in a New York magazine article in March 1992, which pointed with derision at the car and driver and the expensive condominium Dr. Langdon had obtained as part of his contract, were not a factor in the trustees' unwillingness to continue his appointment. "The apartment and the limousine were things the trustees were responsible for, not him," one trustee said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Golden said Ms. Futter's compensation would be consistent with what executives at comparable cultural institutions receive. It includes a rent-free apartment, but not a limousine and chauffeur, he said. The 'Jurassic' Invasion</p>
        <p>A problem facing Ms. Futter immediately is staff dissatisfaction with "The Dinosaurs of 'Jurassic Park,' " a major exhibition that opened on June 11 and combines parts of the museum's collection of genuine paleontological relics with numerous props, videos, story boards and computer-driven mock-ups of dinosaurs used in making the movie "Jurassic Park." Educational texts included in the exhibition frequently call attention to scientific inaccuracies in the film, but some staff members have complained that the fine print is overwhelmed by the visual impact of the pseudo-scientific movie materials.</p>
        <p>Some trustees expressed surprise and concern over the extent of the movie tie-ins in the exhibition, while other gave it cautious or limited approval. "I think it's useful to call attention to the museum," said Helene Kaplan, a member of the boards of both Barnard College and the museum, "although one would not want all exhibits to have that flavor. We don't want to turn the place into another Disney park."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamburg said: "I see no reason why we shouldn't be entrepreneurial, but it has to be done in good taste."</p>
        <p>Ms. Futter, who said she had not seen the exhibition, said: "The movie presents an interesting opportunity to seize acute public interest, but these things call for an exquisite balancing act. The key is to marry scientific authenticity with public accessibility in order to capture and channel the public's interest. I see this as an issue that will recur."</p>
        <p>One of Ms. Futter's first tasks will be to develop activities to celebrate the museum's 125th anniversary in 1995. She declined to discuss details but said the museum planned "a major capital campaign in 1994."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
