<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ancient Desert Rats Leave Clues To Kaleidoscope of Climate Change</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="585850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">URINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF NEVADA-RENO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D7133CF935A15752C0A965958260" item-length="1140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ancient Desert Rats Leave Clues To Kaleidoscope of Climate Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>RENO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THOUGH hardly as glamorous as dinosaur skeletons or fossil-bearing amber, crystallized rat urine has found a place as a window through which scientists are glimpsing fresh details of the earth's environmental history.</p>
        <p>At the Desert Research Institute here, a branch of the University of Nevada, scientists are analyzing glossy black clumps of solidified rat urine, some of it up to 40,000 years old, for indications of changes in ancient climates, bombardments of the earth by cosmic rays, shifts in the earth's magnetic field, and the tribulations of the region's creatures over many millennia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THOUGH hardly as glamorous as dinosaur skeletons or fossil-bearing amber, crystallized rat urine has found a place as a window through which scientists are glimpsing fresh details of the earth's environmental history.</p>
        <p>At the Desert Research Institute here, a branch of the University of Nevada, scientists are analyzing glossy black clumps of solidified rat urine, some of it up to 40,000 years old, for indications of changes in ancient climates, bombardments of the earth by cosmic rays, shifts in the earth's magnetic field, and the tribulations of the region's creatures over many millennia.</p>
        <p>They have learned, for one thing, that the blast of cosmic-ray particles striking the earth's atmosphere 20,000 years ago was 40 percent more intense than it is today. This apparently shows that the earth's magnetic field has strengthened since then, a finding that may shed light on how and why the global magnetic field periodically wobbles and even reverses itself. Clues to Past Climate</p>
        <p>Paleoenvironmentalists have discovered that layers of crystallized urine from desert wood rats and bushy-tailed rats contain an astonishing range of clues to past climate and geological conditions. The last ice age and alternating periods of drought and rain are clearly marked in the urine record, as are the responses of animal and plant species to environmental changes.</p>
        <p>"To raise their broods, rats need sheltered spaces like the fissures in outcrops of rock," said Dr. Peter E. Wigand, a research scientist here. "Century after century, rats use desirable nesting places and leave their traces, just as ancient cities rose on the ruins of former cities." Rats still inhabit the rock fissures where crystallized urine is mined by scientists, but the living animals generally stay clear of their ancestors' latrines.</p>
        <p>Scientists at the University of Rochester in New York, the institute here and the New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology have honed a powerful new tool for gauging cosmic-ray showers from rat urine.</p>
        <p>Dr. Pankaj Sharma of the University of Rochester explains that when a cosmic-ray particle from the depths of space hits the earth's atmosphere, it may collide with an atom of argon, one of the minor constituents of air. By knocking a proton out of an argon atom's nucleus, the impact transforms the argon into a radioactive isotope of chlorine, chlorine-36. Although chlorine-36 gradually disintegrates by spontaneous radioactive decay, it takes 301,000 years for half of any given quantity of it to disappear.</p>
        <p>Rain and snow rapidly carry chlorine-36 from the upper atmosphere to the ground, and the water in which it is dissolved enters the bodies of all living organisms, including rats. In rat bodies, chlorine combines with other elements to become chloride salts, which are excreted in urine.  Preservation of Record</p>
        <p>Since desert rats consume very little liquid water apart from the water in plants, their urine is viscous and thick, and quickly hardens into a crystalline solid, immobilizing the salts it contains, including those carrying chlorine-36.</p>
        <p>Dr. Fred M. Phillips of the New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology extracts the chloride salts from samples of rat urine and sends the extracts to the University of Rochester, which operates one of the most advanced instruments of its kind in the world, an accelerator mass spectrometer.</p>
        <p>Dr. Harry E. Gove and his colleagues at Rochester use this instrument to tease out minute amounts of selected atoms, whose quantities can reveal the ages and other attributes of materials.</p>
        <p>In the case of salts extracted from rat urine, the device bombards the sample with electrically charged atoms of cesium to dislodge atoms from the sample, which are then accelerated by an electric field past a series of magnets. The magnets deflect the atoms by varying amounts, depending on their electric charges and masses. A detector then measures the intensities of various sprays of atoms separated by the magnets, and from this it computes how much of which atomic isotopes are present in the sample.</p>
        <p>A useful feature of crystallized rat urine, Dr. Wigand said, is that it acts as a strong cement, holding its chemical ingredients and biological specimens securely in place for many thousands of years.</p>
        <p>The specimens trapped in rat urine include rat feces, in which scientists are also finding environmental indications. "The size of feces from a given species of rat accurately reflects the animal's body size and its state of nutrition," Dr. Wigand said. "Knowing that a rat whose urine is 10,700 years old was well nourished tells us that environmental conditions were benign at that time."  Founder of Field</p>
        <p>The scientist regarded as a founder of rat's-nest archeology, Dr. Julio L. Betancourt of the University of Arizona, has deduced from rat deposits that the Anasazi Indian civilization that flourished in New Mexico's Chaco Canyon from A.D. 1000 to 1200 died out when an increasingly hostile environment could no longer support it.</p>
        <p>At various times, including the last ice age, rat urine disappears completely from the sedimentary record in Nevada, as it does elsewhere in the world. But even in rat middens where the record is incomplete, assays of chlorine-36 are helping scientists to calibrate and refine the methods used for determining the ages of things.</p>
        <p>For example, a common technique for dating biological material depends on measuring the degree of radioactive decay of carbon-14 in the material. Comparisons can now be made between an object's age as determined by carbon dating with its age as inferred from its chlorine-36 content, thus checking both methods.</p>
        <p>Compacted masses of crystallized urine, feces and other debris are also yielding a harvest of pollen, spores and other remnants of the plants and animals that lived near rats' nests during particular periods.</p>
        <p>Some 12,000 years ago, the record shows, the climate of northern Nevada must have been much colder because the urine record reveals that whitebark pine trees grew at altitudes 3,600 feet lower than they do today. From this Dr. Wigand calculated that the average temperature must have been some 13 degrees Fahrenheit cooler than it is today.</p>
        <p>The changing extent and numbers of other species, as revealed in urine deposits, reflect a variety of catastrophic events, epidemics and fires among them, which sometimes opened ecological niches to new species.</p>
        <p>Scientists are not the only people interested in crystallized rat urine. "Several Native American tribes prepare a kind of tea from crystallized rat urine, which they drink as a medicinal cathartic," Dr. Wigand said. "We try to keep people from disturbing the deposits we use, so we don't disclose exactly where they are. Rat middens have become important resources of science."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
