<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Haze Gets Worse in 2 Eastern Parks, But 10 Parks in the West Fare Better</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="692113"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL PARKS, MONUMENTS AND SEASHORES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR AND SULFUR COMPOUNDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT SMOKY MOUNTAINS NATIONAL PARK</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SHENANDOAH NATIONAL PARK (VIRGINIA)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Tennessee/Great Smoky Mountains National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D6173AF934A35755C0A962958260" item-length="1173" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Haze Gets Worse in 2 Eastern Parks, But 10 Parks in the West Fare Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM HILCHEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONFOUNDING the expectations of environmentalists, a 10-year study of air quality in national parks has found that atmospheric haze increased markedly in Shenandoah National Park in Virginia and the Great Smoky Mountains National Park in Tennessee and North Carolina.</p>
        <p>In 10 parks in the West, however, visibility improved or held steady, two researchers from the University of California at Davis reported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONFOUNDING the expectations of environmentalists, a 10-year study of air quality in national parks has found that atmospheric haze increased markedly in Shenandoah National Park in Virginia and the Great Smoky Mountains National Park in Tennessee and North Carolina.</p>
        <p>In 10 parks in the West, however, visibility improved or held steady, two researchers from the University of California at Davis reported.</p>
        <p>"In the West, measured sulfate levels at a number of these monitoring locations is more or less what we expected," said Marc Pitchford, an atmospheric researcher with the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, "but we didn't expect to see an increase in sulfur particulates in the two southeastern locations, the Great Smokies and Shenandoah."</p>
        <p>"The reason it's unexpected," he continued, "is because all the published information about sulfur dioxide emissions in that region of the country show them going down somewhat or, at worst case, just staying the same, so why are sulfate levels going up?" Reassessing Old Assumptions</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas Cahill, a professor of physics and atmospheric science who has been monitoring air quality in remote national parks for various Federal agencies since 1979, said resolving that question might force policy makers and theorists to reassess the assumptions on which atmospheric pollution models and emission-control laws were based.</p>
        <p>Over a 10-year period beginning in 1982, he and a fellow university physicist, Dr. Robert Eldred, coordinated twice-weekly air sampling at 12 national parks, 10 in the West and 2 in the Southeast. The results of the study, reported in the current issue of the British journal Atmospheric Environment, paint a detailed picture of air quality in the nation's park system.</p>
        <p>"The theory of the Clean Air Act was that sulfur emissions in the East should have been roughly constant," Dr. Cahill said. "The Great Smoky Mountains had visibilities almost as good as some parts of the West back in 1950. It has gone from mean visibilities of over 70 miles to mean visibilities of under 12 in 40 years. That tells you it's not just humidity or something like that. It's really a change in sulfur emission patterns."</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act of 1977 designated most national parks and wilderness areas as sites where the quality of visibility had to be protected, and it required Federal land management agencies to monitor air quality.</p>
        <p>Since 1988, Dr. Cahill and Dr. Eldred have overseen much of the work for an interagency monitoring program financed by the National Park Service, the Forest Service, the Bureau of Land Management, the Fish and Wildlife Service and the Environmental Protection Agency. The program, which was expanded in 1988, now provides about $1 million a year for monitoring at about 70 sites. Rise in Summer Sulfate Levels</p>
        <p>From 1982 to 1992, the researchers found, summer levels of airborne sulfates increased about 39 percent at the Great Smoky Mountains park and 37 percent in Shenandoah. Sulfate levels at the two parks increased 2 to 3 percent each year in that period, although levels declined in the less humid winter months.</p>
        <p>In California, Montana and Oregon, where relatively pristine conditions exist, modest changes in sulfate pollution created the third largest percentage increase. Although the 1992 summer sulfate concentration at Glacier National Park in Montana was only 0.63 micrograms per cubic meter of air, as compared with 8.07 at Shenandoah, the sulfate level at Glacier park had increased about 16 percent in 10 years.</p>
        <p>Results in the Southwest, where most sulfate levels for spring, summer and fall decreased, were much more encouraging, Dr. Cahill said. In winter, however, the opposite was true, with levels at the Grand Canyon National Park increasing at the rate of 4 percent each year. Over all, sulfate pollution in the region decreased, with annual trends showing improvement at six of the seven parks.</p>
        <p>Major air quality improvements during the study period were recorded at Chiricahua National Monument in Arizona and Mesa Verde National Park in Colorado.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cahill linked the 33 percent decline at Chiricahua to a reduction in copper smelting activity. The 25 percent decline at Mesa Verde was attributed to major reductions in sulfur dioxide emissions from nearby coal-fueled power plants, beginning in 1985.</p>
        <p>Bruce Polkowsky, an environmental engineer in the E.P.A. Office of Air Quality Planning and Standards in Durham, N.C., said the study provided grist for further research.</p>
        <p>"We will have to look more closely at the regional distribution of sulfur dioxide emissions across the East because, based on emissions inventories, there have been decreases in sulfur dioxide," Mr. Polkowsky said. "I'm not sure that anyone has looked at regions of the country that would have transport to rural areas, to look at trends in their sulfur dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>"Another question that must be addressed is, over the period of the monitoring, were there conditions that would lead to more particulate sulfate being formed, conditions such as higher temperatures and higher humidity levels?"</p>
        <p>Increased sulfate levels are also a concern because they indicate that the acidity of rainwater may have risen as well, he added. Blurring of Scenic Vistas</p>
        <p>At about 2.5 microns, airborne sulfate particles are so small that they cannot be seen through a standard microscope. But the effect of millions of sulfate particles combines to blur scenic vistas in two ways -- by reflecting light back to the eye like a headlight in dense fog, and by scattering light as it travels through the sulfate haze, Dr. Cahill explained.</p>
        <p>Sampling procedures involved drawing air through Teflon, quartz and nylon filters for a 24-hour period each Wednesday and Saturday. The filters were then shipped to the university and weighed to determine how much matter had been deposited on them.</p>
        <p>A laser light was passed through each filter to determine its opacity. The samples were then subjected to X-ray fluorescence analysis to uncover elements heavier than iron. A particle accelerator was then used to determine the type and quantity of lighter elements, including sulfur and hydrogen, that had accumulated on the filters.</p>
        <p>Tests for carbon and nitrates, two other particulates that can reduce visibility, were conducted for the researchers at other laboratories. In all, some 12,000 samples were analyzed.</p>
        <p>Just 12 parks were analyzed because they were the only sites for which complete 10-year records existed, Dr. Cahill said.</p>
        <p>Last year the air sampling and testing protocols developed by Dr. Cahill and Dr. Eldred were adopted by the United Nations for its Global Atmospheric Watch program. An ad hoc network involving the university and researchers from 17 countries has also formed.</p>
        <p>This is an important development, Dr. Cahill said, because it will provide scientists with a standard method for assessing air quality and promises to yield information vital to understanding global climate change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
