<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Strange Dark World of the Naked Mole Rat</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="680046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOLE RATS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CAPE TOWN (SOUTH AFRICA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CORNELL UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1D8133EF931A25757C0A962958260" item-length="2569" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Strange Dark World of the Naked Mole Rat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
      <dateline>ITHACA , N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN complex burrows under the bricklike soil of East African deserts there lives a mammal more peculiar perhaps than any other on earth. More peculiar, in fact, than the creatures that have emerged from the wild imaginings of Maurice Sendak or the conjurers of otherworldly visitors.</p>
        <p>They are known as naked mole rats -- though they are neither moles nor rats -- and they are challenging scientists to rethink the evolution of a highly structured, cooperative way of life called eusociality, once thought to be limited to group-living insects like bees and ants. The habits of these small, fetal-looking colonial rodents, one of nine species of mole rat, are more insectlike than any vertebrate yet discovered. They are, perhaps, the best living example of what biologists call convergent evolution: the development of nearly identical characteristics in completely unrelated species.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN complex burrows under the bricklike soil of East African deserts there lives a mammal more peculiar perhaps than any other on earth. More peculiar, in fact, than the creatures that have emerged from the wild imaginings of Maurice Sendak or the conjurers of otherworldly visitors.</p>
        <p>They are known as naked mole rats -- though they are neither moles nor rats -- and they are challenging scientists to rethink the evolution of a highly structured, cooperative way of life called eusociality, once thought to be limited to group-living insects like bees and ants. The habits of these small, fetal-looking colonial rodents, one of nine species of mole rat, are more insectlike than any vertebrate yet discovered. They are, perhaps, the best living example of what biologists call convergent evolution: the development of nearly identical characteristics in completely unrelated species.</p>
        <p>Like termites and honeybees, the queen of a mole rat colony bears all the young, sired by only a few mysteriously chosen males. And like those of ants and bees, colonies of naked mole rats exhibit a strong division of labor. Aside from the queen and her few consorts, most of the animals are workers whose various jobs include digging to find food for the rest of the colony, taking care of the young, protecting the burrow from predators and cleaning house.</p>
        <p>Unlike other mammals, naked mole rats do not have an internal furnace to maintain a stable body temperature. And unlike most vertebrates, individual mole rats are not engaged in a Darwinian struggle to endow offspring with superior genes. The great majority of mole rats never reproduce or even try to, sacrificing their reproductive potential to a higher good: helping the colony to survive in a very challenging environment -- an act that behaviorists call reproductive altruism.</p>
        <p>In the most recent studies of this and another species of eusocial mole rat, the Damaraland mole rat, researchers at Cornell University here and the University of Cape Town in South Africa showed that these two subterranean species are forced into communal life and reproductive sacrifice by periodic droughts and patchy food supplies that make it nearly impossible for an animal to survive on its own. Solitary mole rats, on the other hand, live in ground that is easier to dig and where food is more evenly distributed.</p>
        <p>"When the rains come, the eusocial mole rats cooperate and teams of animals dig like the fury," said Dr. Paul W. Sherman, a behavioral ecologist and Cornell professor of neurobiology and behavior. "Together, they are more likely than a solitary mole rat to find a bonanza of tubers to sustain the colony until the next rain. Alone, individuals would starve in that environment. And with a 'super mom' to produce more helpers, individuals willingly give up personal reproduction for indirect reproduction through relatives."</p>
        <p>Dr. Hudson Kern Reeve, a sociobiologist at Cornell, recently showed through DNA fingerprinting that as a result of countless sister-brother and mother-son matings, "mole rat colonies hundreds of animals strong are almost clones." Individuals in a mole rat colony, which typically grow about three inches long and weigh one to two ounces, are genetically more like one another than any naturally bred animals except identical twins. They are as alike, in fact, as laboratory mice that have been inbred for 60 generations.</p>
        <p>It is this genetic similarity that allows worker mole rats to sacrifice their breeding potential, since the offspring of the queen and her mates are genetically identical to what they would be if any of the worker males had sired them, the Cornell scientists maintain.</p>
        <p>Any harmful hidden genes that might once have been able to destroy so incestuous a colony have long since been weeded out. Dr. Stanton Braude, an evolutionary biologist at Washington University in St. Louis who has been studying about 35 mole rat colonies in the field for nearly a decade, said he had found evidence that mole rats also actively outbreed with animals from different colonies coming together to form new colonies.</p>
        <p>Highly inbred or otherwise, mole rats are tough little creatures, surviving in captivity for as long as 16 years in plastic tunnels that serve as laboratory models of their real-world burrows. The Evolution  The Beauty Of Being Ugly</p>
        <p>Being so reproductively limited and living perpetually in the dark as they do, mole rats faced no pressure to evolve a certain physical comeliness that might help attract a mate or inspire popularity. Two-legged vertebrates observing naked mole rats that now dwell in about a dozen zoos here and abroad have been heard to remark, "They're so ugly they're cute!"</p>
        <p>But in the case of the naked mole rat, "ugly" is the consequence of characteristics that have evolved to make them ideally suited for their unusual habitat. As Dr. Paul Sherman, a Cornell biologist, put it in a recent interview: "When you see them alive, there's something charming, even magnificent about these animals. What we regard as ugly is really a bundle of fancy adaptations for living underground."</p>
        <p>Dr. Reeve, a colleague and former student of Dr. Sherman, added: "The naked mole rat is a prime example of natural selection at work. That's what makes them beautiful."</p>
        <p>If, for example, you spent your days slithering through narrow openings, you also might want loose, wrinkled skin that gives, much like the loose-fitting clothing a spelunker wears to avoid abrasions. If you could run backward as easily as forward but had teeny eyes that could see only dim shadows of light and dark, you too might want touch-sensitive whiskers fore and aft to help guide you along your route. You might also profit from a piglike nose loaded with chemical sensors to help you recognize your colony mates and follow scent-marked trails to sparsely distributed food.</p>
        <p>If nature had endowed you with dainty front feet for your underground life, you too might want huge buck teeth to dig your way to food, not to mention lips that close behind the teeth and a fringe of hair inside your mouth to keep you from ingesting the dirt. And if you had to use your mouth for gathering groceries, you, too, might have one-quarter of your muscle mass in your jaw.</p>
        <p>As for the lack of a hairy coat, if your abode stayed year-round at a comfortable temperature and humidity, a cloak of hair or fur would be superfluous and an ability to regulate your own body temperature would be, metabolically speaking, a costly extravagance, Dr. Reeve explained.</p>
        <p>This mammal has the poorest known thermal regulator, and Dr. Sherman said: "When a naked mole rat gets chilly, it simply snuggles up with its colony mates, sometimes in piles three and four animals deep. Or one animal may venture out of the burrow to bask in the warm sun and then return to huddle with the others like a living hot-water bottle."</p>
        <p>And to compensate for the air in mole rat tunnels, where carbon dioxide accumulates at the expense of oxygen, the animals have evolved with hemoglobin that has a very high affinity for oxygen. The Research  Humans Unite Division of Labor</p>
        <p>The fascination with naked mole rats is barely two decades old. In the mid-1970's, Dr. Jennifer U. M. Jarvis of the University of Cape Town, trying to study naked mole rats in the field, was mystified by her failure to find pregnant females in monthly samples of colonies. To simplify her studies of an animal that lives about a meter underground and almost never surfaces, she decided to capture individual animals and establish a laboratory colony. After considerable battles, particularly among the females, the colony eventually settled down and one female -- and only one -- began breeding.</p>
        <p>At about the same time, Dr. Richard D. Alexander, an evolutionary biologist at the University of Michigan, was lecturing widely about the evolution of eusociality, which was then thought to be restricted to social insects like termites and honeybees. In his lecture, Dr. Alexander hypothesized that if there were a mammal that lived a eusocial life -- defined by reproductive altruism, multiple generations living together and strong division of labor -- it would probably be a completely subterranean rodent that fed on large tubers and lived in a tropical region in burrows inaccessible to most predators.</p>
        <p>At one of his lectures, another scientist informed him, "Your hypothetical eusocial mammal is a perfect description of the naked mole rat of Africa," and told him how to contact Dr. Jarvis.</p>
        <p>The naked mole rat soon captured the interest of a handful of scientists who saw in this unusual animal an opportunity to explore how eusociality might have evolved in vastly different animals facing similar environmental pressures. Dr. Eileen Lacey, a behavioral ecologist at the University of California, Davis, said that scientists now recognize a number of vertebrates that live in a eusocial structure, among them the dwarf mongoose, African wild dog and Florida scrub jay.</p>
        <p>"So there is not something unique about the social insects," Dr. Lacey said. "But among vertebrates, the naked mole rat is most like the social insects. No other vertebrate reaches the extremes of behavioral specialization, colony size, reproductive division of labor and morphological differences between group members exhibited by the naked mole rat."</p>
        <p>From a laboratory mole rat colony established in 1980, Dr. Lacey said, researchers at Cornell "have long-term data on animals born in the lab and can trace their entire lives: how they've grown and behaved and how that relates to what else is happening in the colony." Enough is now known about the animal, both in the wild and in the lab, to fill a 518-page book, "The Biology of the Naked Mole Rat," edited by Dr. Sherman, Dr. Jarvis and Dr. Alexander and published in 1991 by Princeton University Press.</p>
        <p>Bur Dr. Sherman suspects that there may be still more eusocial animals. "There are lots of discoveries still to be made underground -- and underwater," he said.  The Hierarchy  Being Lazy Can Pay Off</p>
        <p>As a Cornell undergraduate working with Dr. Sherman, Dr. Lacey helped to determine that the division of labor in mole rat colonies was governed by body size. As with termites and honeybees, the queen is huge compared to her subjects, and she is shaped more or less like a dachshund. She is already among the larger animals when she becomes queen, and as she breeds becomes larger still.</p>
        <p>She can bear as many as 27 offspring at a time, producing a new litter every 70 to 80 days, and pregnant or not, she is able to navigate the narrow tunnels to keep the colony in line. Should she find a lazy worker while on one of her regular patrols, Dr. Reeve discovered, she gives the ne'er-do-well a stimulating shove. And just about the time the worker may begin to slack off again, 10 to 15 minutes later, the queen is back on her rounds. Dr. Reeve also found that "the couch potatoes of the colony tend to be larger animals and less closely related genetically to the queen."</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, it seems to be the lazy workers who grow the biggest and thus have the best chance of becoming a breeder. Other large individuals are assigned the treacherous task of defending the colony. The main threats are mole rats attempting to invade from other colonies and -- most fearsome -- snakes. Snakes are just about the only predators that can gain access to a mole rat tunnel and have been known to dine on as many as three or four of the rodents at one meal.</p>
        <p>Other large nonbreeders are believed to dig for food. Smaller nonbreeders are charged with colony maintenance: transporting nesting material and food, clearing the tunnel of debris and removing obstructions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lacey showed that if a queen or breeding male in the colony dies or is removed, a number of other animals in the colony undergo a growth spurt, vying to replace it. And even though nonbreeding females are sterile, when the queen dies, several females suddenly grow larger, regain their sexual and reproductive prowess and battle one another to replace her. Dr. Lacey found that if a group of large nonbreeders dies, then many of the smaller animals grow faster to fill the gap. And if a colony loses a lot of small nonbreeders, the growth rate of the larger animals slows to fill that slot. The Cooperation  Neatness Counts (Protocol, Too)</p>
        <p>Despite some personal habits that most people would find repulsive -- like ingesting their feces and rolling in the urine and excrement of colony mates, presumably to coat themselves with a common odor -- naked mole rats are meticulous housekeepers. Unlike horses, they do not defecate wherever they happen to be. Rather, the colony establishes a toilet area within the tunnel system that all residents (except nursing newborns) are careful to use.</p>
        <p>And should the smallest bit of sand or other debris drop into the tunnel, worker mole rats with maintenance responsibilities scurry to form a bucket brigade of sweepers to clean it out. The same with digging out the tunnel in search of food. One animal digs with its teeth and sweeps the dirt back with its feet, which are equipped with broomlike hairs between the toes. Then the next animal and the next and the next sweep the dirt along until it can be pushed up and out of the tunnel.</p>
        <p>The animals also establish an underground protocol. When two naked mole rats attempt to pass one another in the tunnel, one animal -- usually the smaller of the two -- crouches down against the bottom of the tunnel while the larger individual crawls over it. To change directions, a mole rat uses a T-shaped tunnel junction to execute a three-point turn. First it passes the junction, then backs up into the branch, then turns and heads the other way.</p>
        <p>A foraging animal that unearths one of the large tubers that are the mole rat's main food supply is obliged to share the cache with the colony. Studies in Cornell's colonies indicate that the animal finding food runs back to its mates, leaving a chemical trail along the route. When the researchers reversed the tunnels in the laboratory colony, the animals followed the piece of tunnel originally traversed by the food finder, suggesting they were guided by a scent rather than a directional clue. Honeybees, on the other hand, do a dance that informs others of the direction to fly in to find food.</p>
        <p>Mole rats also use sounds to communicate, even though they have no external ears. According to Dr. Sherman, "Sound travels well in the tunnel and they have quite a complicated language, producing at least 17 different vocalizations, richest among the rodents and rivaling the vocal repertoire of some primates."</p>
        <p>Dr. Reeve added: "We are just beginning to decipher their language. They have a distinct alarm call when threatened by a snake, for instance, and they make a hissing sound when engaged in aggressive shoving. Also, the queen emits a call in the context of mating, which may be a signal of her receptivity."</p>
        <p>Mole rat workers make sure that nursing young stay with their mother. But once a young mole rat is old enough to leave the teat, it must get to work on colonial chores, with assignments changing according to the animal's size. Dr. Sherman suggested that young people today who come back home jobless after college might learn a thing or two from these industrious eusocial animals.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
