<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Thirsty New Solar Cells Drink In the Sun's Energy</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="729358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ELECTRIC POWER RESEARCH INSTITUTE (EPRI)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMONIX INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3DE1F30F937A35751C1A962958260" item-length="1364" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Thirsty New Solar Cells Drink In the Sun's Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESEARCHERS using an unusual solar cell have set a new efficiency record for capturing power from the sun. And they have high hopes for manufacturing it cheaply because it can be produced by the same factories that make computer chips.</p>
        <p>The cell and associated systems capture and convert to electricity more than 20 percent of the energy in the sunlight that hits them. Commercially available systems are generally only 10 to 12 percent efficient. Scientists have achieved higher capture rates with the new cells -- although only in laboratory models of one square centimeter, not in units big enough to use in the field.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESEARCHERS using an unusual solar cell have set a new efficiency record for capturing power from the sun. And they have high hopes for manufacturing it cheaply because it can be produced by the same factories that make computer chips.</p>
        <p>The cell and associated systems capture and convert to electricity more than 20 percent of the energy in the sunlight that hits them. Commercially available systems are generally only 10 to 12 percent efficient. Scientists have achieved higher capture rates with the new cells -- although only in laboratory models of one square centimeter, not in units big enough to use in the field.</p>
        <p>In the next few weeks, engineers in Arizona will hook up enough of the new cells to generate 20 kilowatts, enough for a cluster of houses. Independently, other utilities around the country are installing cells of an older design, in ever-growing tests that may lead to a mass market.</p>
        <p>The record was set by scientists whose work is financed by the Electric Power Research Institute, a utility consortium in Palo Alto, Calif., that has been working on the technology for nearly two decades. The system was built by Amonix Inc. of Torrance, Calif., a maker of solar-energy systems. Amonix held the previous record too, which was about 15 percent, set just last year using a similar cell.</p>
        <p>The cell is made from crystalline silicon, as are many other photovoltaic cells, but it collects the charge in a different way. In all of these designs, sunlight falling on silicon shakes loose electrons, creating positive and negative charges. But usually, those charges are collected on flat plates; in this model, the charges are collected by thousands of tiny metal contacts, 70,000 of them per square centimeter. The technique increases the likelihood of capturing a charge and using it to make a current before it combines with an opposite charge and cancels itself.</p>
        <p>Because the positive and negative contacts run up from the bottom of the cell, neither casts a shadow on the silicon. (The contact structure of a solar cell is a little like that of a bridge over a river, which can have steel work above or below the roadway; in this case, it is all below.)</p>
        <p>Each cell is mounted under an acrylic concentrating lens that gives it a dose of sunlight 200 to 500 times above normal levels. Intensifying the light this way makes fuller use of the silicon, which is of high purity and therefore is the most expensive part of the system.</p>
        <p>The Amonix cells are mounted on computer-controlled panels that track the sun. A two-kilowatt model -- enough for a small house -- is operating at a test center near Atlanta run by the Georgia Power Company. A 20-kilowatt version, should be completed by the end of the year at the Arizona Public Service Company's solar laboratory in Tempe, Ariz. Including a little elbow room so the tracker platform can swivel to keep the panels within a quarter of a degree perpendicular to the sun, the setup will require a plot of ground measuring 46 feet by 38 feet.</p>
        <p>Other types of solar technology are also promising to yield cost-effective electricity. Some take a markedly different approach from Amonix's.</p>
        <p>For example, the Enron Corporation, the nation's largest natural gas company, recently proposed a 100-megawatt system using thin-film technology, which is the alternative to crystalline silicon. Enron would use silicon and other materials sprayed on glass in layers only a few microns thick. The approach makes such sparing use of expensive materials that the single most costly ingredient is the glass itself -- and it is simply inexpensive window glass. With only small amounts of silicon, there is no need for concentrating lenses.</p>
        <p>Enron wants to construct a centralized system, in the desert of the Nevada Test Site, where the Government used to test nuclear bombs. The Enron system would use thousands of solar panels.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile the Environmental Protection Agency is helping 10 utilities around the country install 18-kilowatt solar arrays for evaluation. Consolidated Edison plans to hook up one in East View, N.Y., just east of Tarrytown, later this month. It is crystalline silicon, but unlike the Amonix array it will sit on fixed panels, angled at 25 degrees to the south, on the roof of a one-story service building the utility owns. The cells were manufactured by ASE Americas, formerly Mobil Solar, of Billerica, Mass.</p>
        <p>One goal of the Con Ed test is to measure the value of the cells in a northern climate. Another is to clock their output hour by hour throughout an entire year, and compare that to the prevailing price for electricity at each hour; this will enable the utility to know the precise monetary value of the electricity produced by the solar array.</p>
        <p>Generally, peak demand for electricity, peak price and peak sunlight all occur at the same time. That is because in many parts of the country, especially on hot summer afternoons, widespread use of air-conditioners requires utilities to run their least-efficient, most expensive conventional generators. It is during such times that solar cells, baking under the bountiful summer sun, harvest the most energy.</p>
        <p>Another matter under study in the Con Ed test is the extent to which having the cells on a customer's roof will enable a utility to avoid installing new transmission lines between conventional power plants and buildings that use electricity.</p>
        <p>THAT is also a key issue for the Electric Power Research Institute, which foresees the use of 500-kilowatt modules -- one two-hundredth the size of the planned Enron installation but 25 times larger than the Arizona test. The institute would put them in neighborhoods where demand is high relative to existing transmission capacity; the idea would be to save the cost of new transmission cables.</p>
        <p>Including such cost consideration in the accounting is key to determining when the use of solar cells is cost effective. The Con Ed cells cost $10,000 a kilowatt, about 10 times what a new conventional plant costs, although there is no fuel cost and nearly no maintenance cost. Costs would presumanbly fall much lower with large-scale production.</p>
        <p>At the Electric Power Research Institute, Edgar DeMeo, the manager of renewable energy research, predicted that the Amonix cells could be produced cheaply, because they can be made in chip foundries, the job shops that produce microprocessors for computers. Although previously, production of solar cells required manufacturing methods even more exacting than those needed in the computer industry, the Amonix cell design allows the level of impurities typically found in computer chips, he said.</p>
        <p>The thousands of contacts are made with the same technology used to make computer chips, and the cells are wired together using circuit-board technology of the kind used in computers and various types of electronic appliances.</p>
        <p>Officials will not say what the 20-kilowatt version will cost because it is a one-of-a-kind prototype, but they say that in volume productions, such a solar-energy system could be made at a cost of less than $2 for each watt of capacity, which would translate to a cost per kilowatt-hour of 5.5 cents to 6 cents. The cost includes maintenance, which is less than 1 cent a kilowatt hour; fuel, of course, is free, and there is no air pollution.</p>
        <p>Like Enron, the institute is counting on driving down costs largely by moving to mass production, spreading the cost of specialized tools and equipment over thousands of units. Dr. DeMeo said that getting costs down would require making "tens of megawatts a year." Currently, he said, total production of solar cells of all types in this country this year is only about 20 megawatts.</p>
        <p>Enron is hoping to build its 100-megawatt system in Nevada over 10 years, adding 10 megawatts a year.</p>
        <p>While such numbers sound ambitious compared with current levels of solar-cell production, they are small relative to conventional plants. Combined-cycle gas turbines, which right now are the most efficient and common form of new production, commonly run 50 megawatts or more. Nuclear plants, when they were still being built, were often larger than 1,000 megawatts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
