<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuomo Appoints a New Head Of New York Power Authority</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK POWER AUTHORITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLYNN, RICHARD M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, S DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFDB1E30F935A15752C0A962958260" item-length="1081" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuomo Appoints a New Head Of New York Power Authority</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to put the foundering New York Power Authority on a sharply different course, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo named S. David Freeman, who has brought radical innovations to several public power agencies, to head the authority yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman, 68, is a former chairman of the Tennessee Valley Authority, at which he abandoned or shut eight nuclear reactors, writing off billions in capital investment, to concentrate resources on several others and push them into operation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seeking to put the foundering New York Power Authority on a sharply different course, Gov. Mario M. Cuomo named S. David Freeman, who has brought radical innovations to several public power agencies, to head the authority yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman, 68, is a former chairman of the Tennessee Valley Authority, at which he abandoned or shut eight nuclear reactors, writing off billions in capital investment, to concentrate resources on several others and push them into operation.</p>
        <p>He is now the general manager of the Sacramento Municipal Utility District, which he took over in a crisis after voters had decided to shut its Rancho Seco nuclear reactor. He is widely credited with rescuing the district, through such steps as auctioning off the furniture in executive offices, buying up thousands of old and inefficient refrigerators and planting half a million trees near houses to reduce the need for air-conditioning and to cut the demand for power. Record Fines Paid</p>
        <p>The New York Power Authority has recently paid record fines to the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for violations at its two nuclear plants, both of which are on the commission's "watch list" of the worst-run plants in America. They are Indian Point 3 in Buchanan, near Peekskill, which has been closed for nearly a year, and James A. FitzPatrick, in Scriba, near Syracuse.</p>
        <p>The authority, which provides a quarter of the electricity used in the state, fears that it will face tough competition in the wholesale electricity markets from independent power producers.</p>
        <p>The power authority has also been criticized by outsiders for doing relatively little about energy conservation. The Sacramento Municipal Utility District, by contrast, has one of the most aggressive conservation programs in the country.</p>
        <p>"David Freeman is vision incarnate," said Peter Bradford, the chairman of the New York Public Service Commission.  "His vision in the 1970's is the conventional wisdom of the 1990's." A large part of that wisdom is that rather than producing more power, utilities should help customers use electricity more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman will replace Richard M. Flynn as chief executive officer of the power authority. Mr. Flynn, 62, whose resignation takes effect Feb. 1, has been criticized not only for the authority's business problems, but also for using the authority's airplane to fly between a summer home in Rhode Island and authority meetings or plants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flynn plans to head a private group, the Northeast Corridor Initiative, that will seek improvements in rail transportation in New York, New England and Canada.</p>
        <p>As a White House official, Mr. Freeman advised President Richard M. Nixon that electricity consumption, which was doubling every 10 years, could not continue on that path, and as the head of a research group at the Ford Foundation he predicted in the early 1970's that all energy use would have to reach a plateau. He was bitterly denounced by energy companies for his prediction, but was proved right. In fact, after the 1973 oil shock, energy use stabilized at a level 15 percent lower than he had predicted.</p>
        <p>His views were never universally popular. Yesterday Carl Goldstein, a spokesman for the United States Council for Energy Awareness, the nuclear industry's public relations arm, said: "I wish him luck. I hope he felt comfortable in that scenario last week." Mr. Goldstein was referring to a series of blackouts in the Middle Atlantic states, brought on by electricity shortages. The utilities traced the shortages to frozen coal piles, fuel barges stuck in icy rivers, and roads over which fuel trucks could not travel. Avant-Garde Views</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman's current views are still outside the mainstream. He is an aggressive supporter of electric vehicles, and is trying to incubate a new industry in Sacramento to manufacture them. He is also a backer of renewable energy sources, like windmills and photovoltaic cells. As head of the Tennessee Valley Authority, Mr. Freeman directed his efforts at projects that were environmentally benign and economically advantageous.</p>
        <p>In choosing Mr. Freeman, Governor Cuomo also reorganized the authority. Since 1985, Mr. Flynn has been the chairman and chief executive officer of the authority. Mr. Freeman will be the president and chief executive officer. Mr. Cuomo has nominated Thomas G. Young, a former Mayor of Syracuse, to replace Mr. Flynn as chairman.</p>
        <p>The power authority provides electricity to municipalities and government agencies, like the Metropolitan Transportation Authority. Under direction from the State Legislature, it provides large blocks of very cheap power to upstate municipal utilities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman said in a telephone interview yesterday that one of the challenges would be to induce customers upstate to conserve electricity that costs them less than 2 cents a kilowatt-hour. Fostering conservation is easier in New York City or on Long Island, say experts, because power there costs seven or eight times as much.</p>
        <p>He said he was "motivated to accept this job more by the opportunities than the problems," adding, "If all the job entailed was fixing the nuclear plants, I think there are a number of people in the country who they could have recruited for that."</p>
        <p>In Albany yesterday, Senator James L. Seward, the chairman of the Senate Energy Committee, complained that Mr. Freeman had been selected with "only nominal participation and little input by the trustees of the power authority" and said that his committee would hold hearings on the selection process.</p>
        <p>The Senate, which is Republican-controlled, does not have to confirm the president of the authority. That was done today by the trustees, at the behest of the Governor.</p>
        <p>That vote was delayed today while Mr. Freeman and the authority worked out details of his contract. It is for three years, beginning March 1, and he will be paid $197,000 a year, a housing bonus of up to $3,000 a month and moving expenses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Freeman said yesterday that his appointment was "almost poetic," coming after his last few jobs. He had been chairman of the T.V.A., which was established by President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and the Lower Colorado River Authority in Austin, Tex., which is known as the "little T.V.A.," and was now coming to manage what he called "the grandfather," the New York Power Authority, which was founded by Franklin D. Roosevelt when he was Governor of New York, and was the model for the T.V.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
