<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Computer Vision of Global Warming: Hardest on Have-Nots</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MODELS (SIMULATIONS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PITT, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENZWEIG, CYNTHIA (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARRY, MARTIN L (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E4D81630F93BA25752C0A962958260" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Computer Vision of Global Warming: Hardest on Have-Nots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. PITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PITT, DAVID E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>USING a combination of computer models, an international team of scientists investigating the effects of global warming on agriculture has summoned up a detailed vision of the future that will cheer farmers and commodity traders in the northern latitudes, but not people in developing countries.</p>
        <p>Experts say the three-year study is apparently the first in what is likely to be a torrent of interdisciplinary, computer-assisted projections of the myriad biophysical and socioeconomic consequences of climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>USING a combination of computer models, an international team of scientists investigating the effects of global warming on agriculture has summoned up a detailed vision of the future that will cheer farmers and commodity traders in the northern latitudes, but not people in developing countries.</p>
        <p>Experts say the three-year study is apparently the first in what is likely to be a torrent of interdisciplinary, computer-assisted projections of the myriad biophysical and socioeconomic consequences of climate change.</p>
        <p>The study predicts that rising temperatures resulting from greenhouse gas emissions will cause only a "slight to moderate" decline in world grain production, causing prices to rise, but leaving most industrial nations more or less unharmed -- and actually increasing crop production in some.</p>
        <p>But people in already impoverished tropical and subtropical countries are likely to face more starvation and malnutrition than ever before, despite the best efforts of farmers to counter the effects of rising temperatures on their harvests, according to the study's principal authors, Dr. Cynthia Rosenzweig of Columbia University and the Goddard Institute for Space Studies, and Prof. Martin L. Parry, director of the Environmental Change Unit at Oxford University in England. Efforts to Assess Risks</p>
        <p>The study was published a month before the more than 150 governments that have signed the 1992 United Nations treaty to combat global warming are to gather for talks in Geneva.</p>
        <p>Until recently, much of the advanced research on climate change focused on whether significant global warming was likely to occur at all. This debate is far from settled, but many scientists are convinced that without drastic measures to reduce the burning of fossil fuels, average temperatures are likely to rise 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit by the year 2100. Efforts are turning more and more to making precise assessments of the likely risks if this turns out to the case.</p>
        <p>Earlier computer models of climate change predicted similarly disparate effects on crop yields, with some northerly regions benefiting while developing countries suffered. But until the Rosenzweig-Parry study, other scientists say, no assessment had incorporated so many variables into a series of precise, comprehensive predictions.</p>
        <p>"They've done a terrific job in gradually learning about the agricultural system and how it might change, then building models that will simulate those changes," said Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund, an advocacy group. "Any one scenario that they ran might not tell you much, but they've run a lot of them, and the sort of underlying themes which emerge within the broad range of uncertainty tell you something about what the future may actually look like."</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency, which largely financed the project with technical help from the United States Agency for International Development, is also sponsoring studies on the effects of global warming on natural ecosystems, human health, river basins and the rise of sea levels.</p>
        <p>The Rosenzweig-Parry findings, published in the current issue of the British journal Nature, involved 60 economists, agronomists and atmospheric scientists from 25 countries who helped prepare "general circulation" models of the atmosphere; global food-trade patterns and crop growth in 18 countries, 12 of them in the developing world.</p>
        <p>The study used crop-yield data supplied by agronomists from Argentina, Australia, Bangladesh, Brazil, Canada, China, Egypt, France, India, Japan, Mexico, Pakistan, the Philippines, Thailand, Russia, the United States, Uruguay and Zimbabwe. The crop figures were then examined under three different models of climate change. The researchers then juxtaposed the data with world food-trade projections to obtain a picture of how many people would be put at risk of hunger. A Surprising Finding</p>
        <p>The study found that although the amount of warming was expected to be highest in the northern latitudes, harming some growing areas and expanding others, the effect on crops was likely to be more uniformly severe in the southern latitudes. This is because the basic subsistence crops the study looked at, including wheat, maize, rice and soybeans, would not fare as well under the stress caused by increased heat and higher evaporation rates.</p>
        <p>"This is the most surprising part of our study," Dr. Rosenzweig said. "It shows that even with lower amounts of warming, the vulnerability of the low-latitude places, where developing countries tend to be located, is very much present. The high temperatures will push the crops very near the edge."</p>
        <p>According to the study, crop yields will be stunted by higher temperatures and damaged by increased difficulty in retaining water. And, because increased heat accelerates the growth cycle, the crops that will be produced will have less time to accumulate carbohydrates and are thus less nutritious.</p>
        <p>The study says the problem will be compounded by sharp increases in world cereal prices resulting from the climate-induced declines in harvests.</p>
        <p>"These increases in price affect the number of people at risk of hunger," the study said, noting that because of global warming, an additional 60 million to 350 million people, most of them in the developing world, could face critical food shortages by the year 2060.</p>
        <p>The study also found that although the presence of heightened levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere would increase crop productivity in the northern latitudes by enhancing photosynthesis rates, its beneficial effects would probably be limited in the southern latitudes by the damaging effects of heat.</p>
        <p>Experts differ over whether the study is based on unrealistically rosy or overly negative assumptions, especially about whether farmers can compensate with new planting techniques or capital-intensive measures like irrigation and new fertilizers.</p>
        <p>"I think some of their scenarios are fairly optimistic about the ability of farmers to adapt, particularly in terms of the likely availability of capital and technology," said Alden Meyer, director of the climate change program of the Union of Concerned Scientists, an environmental research and advocacy group.</p>
        <p>But John Reilly of the Economic Research Service, a private study center in Washington, writing in the same issue of Nature, suggests that the study underestimates the determination of farmers in developing countries to overcome obstacles "if it pays them to do so."</p>
        <p>He also asserts that the study's "focus on crops that are staples of temperate agriculture may have led to an overestimate of the negative impacts in tropical countries."</p>
        <p>Dr. Rosenzweig acknowledged that "further research clearly needs to be done on other crops that are very important in these areas, things like cassava and millet."</p>
        <p>"The real strength of our study was that it was interdisciplinary," Dr. Rosenzweig said. "There's a move to make very integrated models now, and have one model do everything. I like our approach, in which we let the state-of-the-art models in each discipline handle each of the three aspects, and then we work together as scientists to see where the linkages are."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
