<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Drought Devastating Many Crops in Suffolk</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="702999"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DROUGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SUFFOLK COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINZBURG, RALPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6DE1439F932A05754C0A962958260" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Drought Devastating Many Crops in Suffolk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RALPH GINZBURG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GINZBURG, RALPH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT some farmers and farm officials are calling the worst drought since the  mid-1960's is devastating crops in Suffolk County.</p>
        <p>"Crops are withering everywhere," the extension agent at the Cornell Cooperative Extension in Riverhead, Bill Sanok, said. "Corn is stunted, potatoes are reduced to the size of marbles and some crops of cucumbers, snap beans, cabbage, cauliflower, pumpkins and others of the 60 varieties grown here are suffering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT some farmers and farm officials are calling the worst drought since the  mid-1960's is devastating crops in Suffolk County.</p>
        <p>"Crops are withering everywhere," the extension agent at the Cornell Cooperative Extension in Riverhead, Bill Sanok, said. "Corn is stunted, potatoes are reduced to the size of marbles and some crops of cucumbers, snap beans, cabbage, cauliflower, pumpkins and others of the 60 varieties grown here are suffering.</p>
        <p>Those farmers who are not being ruined altogether -- that is, those who are able to irrigate -- are running up fierce extra costs of $300 an acre for fuel to operate pumps and for labor. These extra costs represent a dead loss. On 15,000 acres under irrigation here, it totals $4.5 million.</p>
        <p>"And that assumes that the dry spell we've experienced since May ends soon. Minor showers of the past few days are not nearly enough. We need several weeks  of heavy precipitation."</p>
        <p>The sandy, glacial soil of Suffolk County, Mr. Sanok said, "requires nearly two inches of rainfall a week, and we have a lot of catching up to do."</p>
        <p>Evidence of languishing crops is abundant, Mr. Sanok added, including at the  County Farm in Yaphank, where corn is stunted, rows are uneven and cobs have few edible kernels.</p>
        <p>"This has been the driest year since the mid-60's," he said. "For farmers, it is approaching catastrophic proportions, and consumers may feel the pain of higher prices by late summer. If it stays dry like this for much longer, the County Agricultural Committee will be applying for disaster relief."</p>
        <p>Suffolk reaps the highest gross farm income of any county in the state, $133  million a year, according to the United States Department of Commerce's Census of Agriculture. Experts did not offer estimates on how much the drought might reduce that.</p>
        <p>Adding to the dryness is searing heat. Richard Hendrickson of Bridgehampton,  who has collected weather data for 63 years, said:</p>
        <p>"We've had more hot days this year than ever recorded for a similar period since 1900. I have gone back over the old records and tallied the number of days when the temperature exceeded 90 degrees, an unusual level for the region east of Riverhead out to the ends of the Twin Forks."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hendrickson, a retired farmer and the longest-serving volunteer weather watcher in the county, furnishes data to the National Weather Service every day.</p>
        <p>"From 1901 to 1929," Mr. Hendrickson said, "we had a total of only 24 days over 28 years. From 1930 to 1962, we had 70 days. But from 1963 to 1994 we've had 85 days of 90 degrees plus. This year alone we've had six days so far."</p>
        <p>Global warming, Mr. Hendrickson said, "may be a matter of controversy elsewhere on Earth, but here in Suffolk County it is an indisputable, authenticated fact."</p>
        <p>"And it is devastating," he added.</p>
        <p>Early potatoes being dug now, Mr. Hendrickson said, are tiny, with yields less than half normal levels. The crop is running less than 100 bushels an acre, he reported, compared to the usual 200.</p>
        <p>"And nobody wants these tiny potatoes," Mr. Hendrickson said. "Ditto for the  local sweet corn, which is smaller. Some farmers won't even harvest it, because  consumers won't buy it. The American public demands perfect vegetables."</p>
        <p>Phil Schmitt 3d, retired vice president of the Long Island Farm Bureau, is one of the few farmers who has not been significantly hurt. "We're planted lettuce and other crops that thrive in desertlike weather," he said. "We expect  to fetch higher prices, but please don't say I said that. My neighbors, whose fields are parched, are really hurting, and they'll shoot me."</p>
        <p>The extent of damage varies by location and crop. The South Fork traditionally receives markedly greater rainfall than the North Fork, and farmers there have generally not installed irrigation equipment. As a consequence, they are being hit much harder by the drought than farmers on the North Fork.</p>
        <p>Organic farmers are among those most severely affected. "Because we are organic, there are very few sprays we are permitted to use," said Ray Halsey, owner of the Green Thumb Farm in Water Mill. "In this hot, dry weather, the flea beetles keep coming back and we can't control them. This affects our various herb crops, among others.</p>
        <p>"Also, we have had a hard time getting seeds germinated with the soil so dry. Normally we plant various new crops about every week or 10 days, including radishes and many other small-seed vegetables. But we're finding it nearly impossible to get them started. We're losing a lot."</p>
        <p>Organic farming, Mr. Halsey added, is "labor intensive, so that adverse weather is all the more costly to us."</p>
        <p>"This drought will cost us incalculable thousands," he said. "The only thing  we can do is pray for rain."</p>
        <p>As for fruit, orchard owners are sustaining less damage than truck farmers. David Davis of the Davis Peach Farm in Mount Sinai, with 10,800 trees of peaches, plums, apricots, apples and nectarines, said:</p>
        <p>"The drought has not affected us that much, strictly because we're running irrigation pumps constantly. I expect to be out only about $5,000 for fuel and labor, provided my well does not break down. If it should, I'd be out $100,000 or more. But to look at the bright side, dry weather does tend to make fruit sweeter."</p>
        <p>Pumps Are Running 18 Hours</p>
        <p>Clark McCombe, whose family owns the Briermere Farm in Aquebogue and grows strawberries, blackberries, raspberries, apples, peaches and pears on 300 acres, said he was running water pumps 18 hours a day.  "Here on the North Fork," Mr. McCombe said, "we're prepared for it. Our orchards are completely set up with trickle irrigation, and so the drought is not a major big deal for us. What we orchard men worry about are hurricanes' coming through. The greater heat is a problem for us, however. All plants tend to dry out and become more stressed."</p>
        <p>Anne Wickham of Wickham's Fruit Farm on Route 25 in Cutchogue said: "We're irrigating around the clock. I've been in farming here for over 60 years, and it's definitely the very worst we've ever had."</p>
        <p>Lyle Wells, 38, runs what he believes is the oldest farm on the Island. His 50 acres at Aquebogue have been in the Wells family for 12 generations, since 1661.</p>
        <p>"We grow vegetables from A to Z, from asparagus to zucchini," Mr. Wells said. "This drought is really killing us. We have no irrigation on the home 50 acres here. Sugar snap peas, green beans, zucchini, cucumbers, potatoes, cut flowers will yield little or no return whatsoever on investment.</p>
        <p>"To plant, maintain, apply insecticide, etcetera costs $700 to $1,300 per acre. Multiply an average of $1,000 per acre times 50 acres and you can see that our loss will be $50,000. This is the greatest we have ever suffered in over three centuries."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
