<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patterns</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="680000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">OZONE SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SPINDLER, AMY M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRADA, MIUCCIA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FASHION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DA133EF931A25757C0A962958260" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amy M. Spindler</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SPINDLER, AMY M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Welcoming the World</p>
        <p>Much of the audience had seen the collection, but the surprise when Prada showed in the big tent in Bryant Park on Saturday night was how much more impressive the collection looked here than it did in Milan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Welcoming the World</p>
        <p>Much of the audience had seen the collection, but the surprise when Prada showed in the big tent in Bryant Park on Saturday night was how much more impressive the collection looked here than it did in Milan.</p>
        <p>It's no secret why Miuccia Prada, the first designer of the season to take hemlines to the knee, wanted to show in New York. Prada not only won the Council of Fashion Designers of America's best accessories award for 1993, but also plans to open a New York headquarters, at 28 East 70th Street, with a store and sales and publicity offices early next year. Ms. Prada said, "Everyone says our things are right for New York, and I feel very near to the city."</p>
        <p>It will be the third Prada store in America, after the ones on 57th Street and in Beverly Hills, Calif., and Ms. Prada said there would be six to eight more in the next four years.</p>
        <p>The German luxury goods house Escada is also plunking itself into the middle of the New York scene today by showing a 3-D movie by Robert Leacock. It is a staged look backstage starring many of New York's favorite fashion hangers-on. The message: Escada is as much a part of the New York firmament as any company.</p>
        <p>So, it looks like the designers council is making good on its promise to build a world-class showcase. But the effort is not without risk to American designers, who are still learning about theatrics for big venues. Only Anna Sui has put together the rallying music that Gianni Versace offers each season, for example.</p>
        <p>Fern Mallis, president of the council, said the group would consider European designers' requests to show next season, but only primary lines, and only collections premiering here -- which rules out Prada's again showing in both Milan and New York.</p>
        <p>"We do not want to lose sight of the fact that we created Seventh on Sixth to be a showcase for the American designers," Ms. Mallis said. "But we also don't want to be like the French and Italians and have our head in the ground and ignore the rest of the world." An Accessory to Die for</p>
        <p>When Mimi is dying in "La Boheme," the earrings of her best friend, Musetta, are sold to buy her a fur muff. But by next fall, acquiring this quaint accessory should not involve any drastic measures at all, considering all the updated versions being shown on the runways.</p>
        <p>Chanel showed a white muff with the company's logo on it. Vivienne Westwood's was as imposing as the bustles on her dresses. In the Label collection by Laura Whitcomb, there were fuzzy ones, which the models wore behind their backs. Lauren Sara had one of fake beaver. The fake fur cuffs on Todd Oldham's jackets made muffs when hands were clasped.</p>
        <p>Manolo's muff, which he will show tomorrow in a collection inspired by the Brooklyn Bridge and the Lincoln Tunnel, is made of wool, nickel, chromium and monofilament. Like other muffs, his will have a pocket inside, but unlike any muff seen before, it is covered with big spikes instead of soft fur. "My muff is to keep your change in, and to keep people at arm's length," Manolo said.</p>
        <p>And to give comfort. As Mimi sings in Puccini's opera with her muff on: "My hands are much warmer now. I just want to go to sleep."</p>
        <p>Then, of course, she dies. They Should Come in Green</p>
        <p>Last week, the Ozone Society, a nonprofit organization dedicated to preserving the ozone layer, showed a collection of clothes to provide full-body protection from radiation. Sexy they aren't. But Wendy Heather, an Australian designer who created the Ozone Aware line, is convinced that high fashion for high levels of radiation is an inescapable trend. "Fashion is not going to be dictated by the couturiers of the future," she said. "It will be dictated by the environment."</p>
        <p>One designer has learned the truth in that statement. Sylvia Heisel discovered a fabric used for sails, and when she picked fluorescent yellow and Day-Glo pink, she was warned by the fabric's maker that after a few months in the sun, it would fade to gray because of ozone depletion.</p>
        <p>Which didn't deter Ms. Heisel: at her show on Saturday, she said the arresting sailcloth coats would evolve with wear. But she does charge less for those coats, $300, than she does for the coats she makes with Nomex, a fabric that is used in astronaut suits and that will outlive any shopper.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
