<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deeper Look at Cold, Snowy Winter Reveals Balmier Future</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DD1738F93BA35751C0A962958260" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deeper Look at Cold, Snowy Winter Reveals Balmier Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE the end of a record cold snap nearly three weeks ago, the Northeast has continued to shiver in below-average temperatures much of the time. One big reason is a snow cover that has lingered for about six weeks in many places, including parts of metropolitan New York; without it, nighttime and early-morning temperatures that have been in the teens and single digits would probably have been some 10 degrees higher.</p>
        <p>But if the global climate system behaves this year as it has in recent years, scientists say, April and May will bring the latest in a series of abnormally warm springs. This would shrink the snow cover of the entire Northern Hemisphere to a historically small area, and with the cooling effects of the snow lessened, the springtime climate would warm even more. The result: a canceling out of the cold of January and February that would, on balance, make the first half of 1994 warmer than normal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE the end of a record cold snap nearly three weeks ago, the Northeast has continued to shiver in below-average temperatures much of the time. One big reason is a snow cover that has lingered for about six weeks in many places, including parts of metropolitan New York; without it, nighttime and early-morning temperatures that have been in the teens and single digits would probably have been some 10 degrees higher.</p>
        <p>But if the global climate system behaves this year as it has in recent years, scientists say, April and May will bring the latest in a series of abnormally warm springs. This would shrink the snow cover of the entire Northern Hemisphere to a historically small area, and with the cooling effects of the snow lessened, the springtime climate would warm even more. The result: a canceling out of the cold of January and February that would, on balance, make the first half of 1994 warmer than normal.</p>
        <p>The vagaries of climate are almost guaranteed to bring regional exceptions to this overall hemispheric pattern, but the pattern itself seems well established. Scientists who have analyzed it lately believe a generally warming global climate, most likely produced by growing emissions of heat-trapping industrial gases in the atmosphere, is responsible.</p>
        <p>Snow cover wields a powerful influence on climate and weather. It reflects solar energy back into space, thereby exerting a cooling effect on the planet, especially where the snow lies. It also acts as a blanket, preventing the escape of heat absorbed by the ground before the snow fell. This, too, helps to cool the air. When warming winds try to moderate the local temperature, they cool off instead if they blow over the snow. So, in the depths of winter when snow is on the ground, the weather has a hard uphill struggle toward higher temperatures.</p>
        <p>Eventually, of course, the warmth of spring melts whatever snow remains in temperate lowlands, and the hemisphere's snow cover shrinks to a summer nadir. What seems to have been happening in the last two decades is that springs have been getting warmer, on average, and the extent of the annual snow cover has consequently declined by about 10 percent in North America and Eurasia over the last 20 years.</p>
        <p>The decline is directly related to the temperature in these regions, according to a study published recently in the journal Science by Pavel Groisman of the State Hydrological Institute in St. Petersburg, Russia, and Thomas R. Karl and Richard W. Knight of the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C. Role of the Greenhouse Effect</p>
        <p>The three described a circular feedback effect that begins when increasingly warm springtime temperatures generally cause more snow to melt. This, in turn, releases more latent heat from the ground and allows the earth to absorb more solar energy, thereby intensifying the warming effect and making April and May temperatures higher than in earlier years. The emission of heat-trapping industrial gases like carbon dioxide is "the most likely candidate" for delivering the first shot of extra warmth, said Mr. Karl.</p>
        <p>Climatologists say it is clear that the average global temperature has increased by about 1 degree over the last century, but there is no general agreement as to the cause. Many believe the emission of heat-trapping gases is responsible and predict that this greenhouse warming will continue, but few are willing to to say this is unequivocally true; the warming is still too small to be distinguished from natural climatic variability.</p>
        <p>An especially warm spike in the late 1980's and early 1990's was interrupted by the cooling effects of the June 1991 eruption of Mt. Pinatubo in the Philippines, but climatologists say there are signs that the trend turned upward again in 1993.</p>
        <p>In any case, said Mr. Karl, "snow cover and spring warming go hand in hand" at least since the early 1970's, when satellite observations of the snow's extent first became available. He and his three colleagues wrote in Science that "the global warming that has occurred in the spring is likely to have been significantly enhanced by corresponding changes in snow cover."</p>
        <p>The pattern has been observed not only in the Northern Hemisphere at large but in the United States in particular, said Mr. Karl. "The last 10 years have been very warm in the spring," he said, "and we believe the snow-cover feedback effect is a contributor to why the first half of the year has been warmer and the second half hasn't seen so much change."</p>
        <p>An extensive analysis of photographs taken from satellites over the last two decades has found that the Northern Hemisphere snow cover has been below normal since 1987, and that spring was the season in which the "snow deficit" was most pronounced, said Dr. David A. Robinson, a climate expert at Rutgers University. Record-breaking Snow Last Fall</p>
        <p>The spring warm-up is especially significant, he said, since fall and early winter in the last two years have brought especially extensive snow packs to the hemisphere. "Last year going into the winter," he said, "we had the second most extensive snow cover over the Northern Hemisphere" since the satellite readings began. But by last February, he said, the cover in Eurasia had fallen to one of the lowest levels on record, while North America stayed high. By April the North American cover had also fallen below normal, despite a storm of the century in March that blanketed most of the Eastern United States with snow. Though extensive and deep, the March snowfall was no match for the warming spring atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Last fall "things began to become snowy again in the Northern Hemisphere," said Dr. Robinson. "As a matter of fact, November had the most extensive hemispheric snow cover on record." That pattern changed somewhat in December, which ranked as only the 10th snowiest December in 22 years.</p>
        <p>Last month's snow cover in North America was the seventh most extensive on record, Dr. Robinson reported, but Eurasia's was the second least extensive, making the cover of the hemisphere as a whole the third least extensive.</p>
        <p>The United States east of the Mississippi River had its fifth most extensive January cover, with 46 percent of the land surface under snow. This compares with a 23-year average for January of 35 percent. The middle of the country, from the Mississippi to the Rockies, experienced its 12th most extensive cover for the month, with 43 percent of the ground covered, compared with an average of 41 percent. From the Rockies to the Pacific Ocean, the picture was the reverse of the East: the extent of cover ranked 20th out of 22 years, with 45 percent of the ground blanketed, compared with a January average of 54 percent.</p>
        <p>For the hemisphere as a whole, Dr. Robinson said, the below-normal snow cover for January "doesn't necessarily mean we're going to have low totals this spring, but it's beginning to hint at that" -- especially if the spring is as warm as its six predecessors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
