<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pushing for the Free Trade Pact From 1,500 Feet Down</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="717008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SODA ASH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS AND JOB REDUCTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DA103DF93AA35753C1A962958260" item-length="1502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pushing for the Free Trade Pact From 1,500 Feet Down</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>GREEN RIVER, Wyo.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FIFTEEN hundred feet under the sagebrush of the southwestern Wyoming desert here lie the world's biggest soda ash mines. One mine alone has 2,400 miles of tunnels, nearly five times the combined length of the streets of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>So plentiful are the deposits that geologists estimate they could supply the entire world for 2,300 years at current rates of consumption. Soda ash is similar to baking soda and serves as the raw material for glass, toothpaste, powdered soaps and laundry detergents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FIFTEEN hundred feet under the sagebrush of the southwestern Wyoming desert here lie the world's biggest soda ash mines. One mine alone has 2,400 miles of tunnels, nearly five times the combined length of the streets of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>So plentiful are the deposits that geologists estimate they could supply the entire world for 2,300 years at current rates of consumption. Soda ash is similar to baking soda and serves as the raw material for glass, toothpaste, powdered soaps and laundry detergents.</p>
        <p>This mother lode has turned the United States into the world's lowest-cost producer, allowing it to claim nearly one third of the world market. And if the House and Senate approve a new global free trade agreement at the end of November, it will mean even more jobs in the soda ash industry, which had sales of $734 million last year. That makes the industry an unusually clear winner from a highly complicated pact.</p>
        <p>The losers will be the foreign producers of soda ash. The low production costs here have prompted other countries to raise steep tariffs to protect their less efficient chemical factories that make synthetic soda ash. Desperate European multinationals have even sued American producers, including one of their own mines here, accusing them of dumping soda ash at unfairly low prices in the European market.</p>
        <p>"It's like calling in an air strike on your own position," said Dennis Kostick, a soda ash geologist at the United States Bureau of Mines.</p>
        <p>The soda ash industry offers a mirror image of the dilemma that usually confronts Americans when they think about trade as a choice between job losses and lower prices for consumers.</p>
        <p>The traditional dilemma is best seen in the American clothing industry, which has much higher labor costs for sewing than its foreign competitors. Lowering trade barriers in the apparel industry at home and abroad means cheaper clothing for American consumers. But it also means throwing thousands of Americans out of work.</p>
        <p>Soda ash is a different case. Since foreign soda ash is much more expensive, the United States imports virtually none and is unlikely to do so regardless of trade agreements. For this industry, then, a global free trade agreement will only mean more overseas sales, more jobs here and more economic activity that the Government can tax.</p>
        <p>Other American industries hoping for big gains in exports from lower tariffs include producers of paper, pharmaceuticals, beer, processed foods, construction equipment and farm equipment.</p>
        <p>If the pact is approved and other countries lower their barriers, miners here are ready to step up production, said John V. Corra, the manager of the FMC Corporation's mine here, as he drove with a visitor through miles of 9-foot-high, 16-foot-wide corridors, all the while keeping an eye on the rough ceiling from which foot-long stalactites hung like Vermont icicles.</p>
        <p>The curving walls of the corridor still bear the inch-wide grooves where giant boring machines sliced through the rocks. These machines have two sets of 8-foot-wide rotating blades, so that they resemble a pair of huge electric shavers clamped together. Smaller blades also tear at the ceiling and floor to produce a smooth, oval-shaped corridor.</p>
        <p>As the blades chew through the ore, the crumbled rock falls on the front of a conveyor belt that carries the ore back through the middle of the 110-ton machine and dumps it out the back on a shuttle car. The shuttle car then carries the ore down a few passages to one of the mine's big conveyor belts, which extend for 20 miles and carry the ore to an immense freight elevator that hauls up 22 tons of ore in each car.</p>
        <p>Tariffs for soda ash would be among 198,000 tariffs around the world that the 123-nation trade pact would reduce. The pact would also extend the free-trade rules of the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade to farming and a few service industries, like accounting.</p>
        <p>With the failure of President Clinton's health care overhaul, the trade pact has emerged as the Administration's top legislative priority for the rest of this year. But the bill putting the pact's provisions into American law faces an uncertain future because of election-year politics and because Senator Ernest C. Hollings, the South Carolina Democrat who is chairman of the Commerce Committee, has forced an eight-week delay in the Senate vote. Mr. Hollings's home state is a big producer of textiles and clothing, but he attributes his opposition to a general skepticism of free trade.</p>
        <p>The dollars involved in the soda ash industry here are not large by trade standards: by one Government estimate, the trade pact's lower tariffs would mean an extra $80 million a year in American soda ash exports, representing an increase of about one third, and 300 to 400 more mining jobs here.</p>
        <p>But such gains add up quickly. Administration economists predict that annual American economic output could be $100 billion larger within a decade if the trade bill passes. But opponents contend that the gains would be no more than $2 billion a year.</p>
        <p>So economically important and politically powerful is the soda ash industry here that one of the state's two Republican senators, Malcolm Wallop, flew from his ranch in Wyoming to Geneva and back last December just to spend a day lobbying for lower European tariffs on the substance.</p>
        <p>BECAUSE of a fluke of geology, the United States is the only country with huge reserves of soda ash that can be readily mined.</p>
        <p>Soda ash ore, known as trona, is formed when sodium is combined with carbon dioxide and water in fairly precise ratios. Geologists believe that the deposits here formed 50 million years ago as continental drift pushed up mountain ranges around a large lake. The lake gradually dried out and the plant matter in it died and decayed, producing large quantities of carbon dioxide. At roughly the same time, numerous volcanic eruptions in northwestern Wyoming blanketed the region in sodium-rich ash, while the lake bed itself held some sodium-rich rocks.</p>
        <p>The only other big veins of soda ash ore lie in a remote area of Turkey and in China near the Mongolian border. Neither is being mined because there are no nearby railroads or highways to ship the ash.</p>
        <p>Industry executives once hoped that the trade pact's benefits for American soda ash would be even more substantial than they turned out to be. But the final pact is the sum of many compromises over seven years of negotiations.</p>
        <p>The pact calls for all countries to limit their soda ash tariffs to 5.5 percent, but does not eliminate them entirely, as the United States had sought. This will force the European Union to cut its 10 percent tariff nearly in half.</p>
        <p>"The reduction in tariffs," said William L. Breunig, the soda ash marketing director at FMC, "will make the market open to us and increase exports." Industry at Odds With Itself</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON -- THE soda ash industry holds a certain distinction in international trade circles: its corporations abroad have tangled with their subsidiaries here, even accusing one in a lawsuit of dumping goods at unfairly low prices in the parent's home market.</p>
        <p>While rare, if unheard of, in other industries, similar suits could become increasingly common in the next few years as ever more companies set up operations around the globe and more countries enact anti-dumping laws. The reason: such laws effectively require a domestic producer suffering from low-priced foreign competition to sue all producers in another country or none.</p>
        <p>Sometimes that may mean a company must sue its own subsidiary. Solvay S. A. of Belgium blames low-priced shipments from the United States for ruining the profitability of its synthetic soda ash factories in Europe. So it formed a coalition of European companies that filed anti-dumping complaints with the European Union in Brussels. The action seeks steep tariffs on all soda ash from the United States -- even though the Europeans own mines in southwestern Wyoming that account for a third of American production.</p>
        <p>Solvay says its huge American mining operations have stopped shipping to Europe but it must sue them because of legal technicalities.</p>
        <p>The European companies filed their case in late 1992, and a decision is due later this year or early next year. If the European Union decides to impose tariffs, the global free trade pact now before Congress is unlikely to prove any help to American producers.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration insisted during the final days of negotiations last December in Geneva that the pact not put many restrictions on anti-dumping claims, which the American steel industry has used often against foreign rivals.</p>
        <p>The final pact does call for several highly technical changes in the rules for anti-dumping cases.</p>
        <p>A few soda ash executives, including William L. Breunig of the FMC Corporation, contend that the new rules will help Americans defend themselves by making the European anti-dumping process less secretive. But many others are less optimistic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
