<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cold Comfort; Hardy Iceboaters Sail Into Winter</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICEBOATING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHEIMER, JON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DD1030F930A15752C0A962958260" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cold Comfort; Hardy Iceboaters Sail Into Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON NORDHEIMER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORDHEIMER, JON</byline>
      <dateline>RED BANK, N.J., Jan. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iceboaters live in an upside-down world.</p>
        <p>While everyone else plots ways to stay indoors and turn up the heat, they think up excuses to get out on the ice with the wind scraping their faces like rusty razors.</p>
        <p>Normal people pray for temperatures to rise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iceboaters live in an upside-down world.</p>
        <p>While everyone else plots ways to stay indoors and turn up the heat, they think up excuses to get out on the ice with the wind scraping their faces like rusty razors.</p>
        <p>Normal people pray for temperatures to rise.</p>
        <p>Iceboaters' spirits soar as the mercury plunges.</p>
        <p>But the weather this week was too much even for those who dream of ice conditions only a polar bear on a pair of skates could love. When the temperature is barely above zero and the northwest wind is hitting 20 knots or more, those riding on a fast-moving boat can be dealing with a windchill factor of minus 70.</p>
        <p>Outside the frosted windows of the North Shrewsbury Ice Boat and Yacht Club the Navesink River gleamed like a frozen cliche for as far as the eye could see: one foot thick with a surface as smooth as glass.</p>
        <p>"God's Zamboni has been working overtime to give us perfect ice conditions and now it's so cold it's a health risk to go sailing," said Dominick DeLorenzo, referring to the ice-polishing machine used at hockey arenas, as he huddled inside the clubhouse.</p>
        <p>"Air's so cold out there it will frostbite your lungs," said Borden (Brub) Hance, 74 years old, whose great-uncle, Dr. Edwin Fields, founded the club in 1880, a period remembered in local lore as providing frigid weather and rock-hard ice every winter.</p>
        <p>In the last decade, with few exceptions, mild winters produced only skim ice and depressing talk of a greenhouse effect that one day, iceboaters direly predicted, would sprout palm trees on beaches at Sandy Hook, where the Navesink and Shrewsbury Rivers converge to spill into the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>"When I was a boy in the 1950's we used to blame warm winters on atomic bomb tests," recalled John Holian, commodore of the 132-member club. "But for the past 10 years, outside of a couple of weeks in 1987 and 1989, if you wanted iceboating you had to trail your boat to northern New Jersey or New England."</p>
        <p>With January's Arctic blasts, hope inside the clubhouse was running as high as a fuel oil baron's fantasy that a new cycle of hard winters was in store.</p>
        <p>"If you're an iceboater, you have to be an optimist," Mr. Holian said. Snow Is the Enemy</p>
        <p>It is optimism that inspires a forecast that temperatures will remain below freezing for the next two months without producing significant snow, a despised enemy of iceboaters.</p>
        <p>Snow of an inch or more will stop an iceboat dead in its tracks. Snow will turn slushy and refreeze in granular, rutty ways that jar and snag the steel runners of an iceboat and cause treacherous spills. While last week produced snowfalls elsewhere in New Jersey, only rain and freezing rain fell along the coast.</p>
        <p>Inland estuaries like the Navesink are brackish with a low level of salt water that freezes at 28 degrees, said George Fournier, 71, a retired boat builder who first went iceboating in the 1930's. Puddling rainwater freezes at 32 degrees on top of the frozen river, he said, providing an insulating cap that can extend good iceboating for weeks.</p>
        <p>"We have the best conditions in the entire region," he said. "Every lake and river north of here is covered with snow." The Lure of Perfect Ice</p>
        <p>It's not all good news.</p>
        <p>Perfect ice attracts skaters, walkers and running dogs, as well as children employing every kind of wind-propelled device, from umbrellas to parabolic kites, to whoosh themselves along on sleds, skis, bikes and sailboards. Cars, pickup trucks and motorcycles test the strength of the ice and the operator's bravado.</p>
        <p>"We don't own the river so we can't keep them off but it gets darned crowded out there on a weekend," Mr. Fournier said as the club prepared for a series of races this weekend, when temperatures are expected to be more moderate.</p>
        <p>Iceboats zip along at 50 to 100 miles an hour, a feat made possible by aerodynamics that accelerate the craft to three times the speed of the wind force. Though sailed like a boat in water, iceboats are trickier to handle when it comes to turning and stopping because of the speeds and the lack of friction of steel blades on glare ice. In heavy wind, they often hang on the edge of becoming airborne.</p>
        <p>"An iceboat is a beast once it gets going," Mr. Peterson said. "The closing rates" between iceboats and other objects "are so fast that if you have to think about what to do it's probably too late."</p>
        <p>At Red Bank, the Navesink measures one mile at its widest point. Holes chopped in the ice for eel traps, bubbling systems that keep dock pilings free of ice, and stretches of water kept open by tide and wind present hazards of a different kind. Iceboats occasionally hit an ice hole and partly submerge in the bone-chilling water, but club members have not been involved in any fatal accidents, Mr. Fournier said.</p>
        <p>"We've had guys run into buoys and break ribs but not much worse than that," he said. A Mostly Male Diversion</p>
        <p>In these parts, iceboating is a man's game.</p>
        <p>No woman is a member of the North Shrewsbury club, though the officers say a real enthusiast would not be denied membership if she applied. Women, they say, enjoy the sailing part of iceboating but find the effort involved daunting. Carrying ice boats or 400-pound parts occupies more time than actual sailing, which the threat of frostbite keeps to 5- or 10-minute bursts.</p>
        <p>Tough work in cold weather along with speed and sense of danger are part of the appeal. The enthusiasts come from many walks of life, bound by the sense that a rugged 19th-century sport still had purpose in a world of creature comfort abundance.</p>
        <p>Brum Hance, who won his first iceboating championship in 1938 on the two-seater Icicle, questioned the ability of those in the heated clubhouse to meet old-time standards of toughness.</p>
        <p>"After a 10-year spell of no ice to speak of you'd think they'd be breaking down the doors to get out there," he said at noon as younger men downed steaming bowls of chili as they drank beer or coffee. "I never thought I'd hear real iceboaters say it was too cold out there."</p>
        <p>After lunch, when the wind died a little, Mr. DeLorenzo took up the challenge of the ice. (He is, after all, the owner of an ice plant in Neptune.) The day before he had purchased the lovingly restored Icicle and was aching to take it for a spin.</p>
        <p>Pretty soon he had the Icicle gliding across the smooth surface with a soft scraping noise of steel against hard ice, picking up speed in the middle of the Navesink where there was more wind.</p>
        <p>He let out a sharp cry of pleasure as he turned the boat perpendicular to the wind and the Icicle responded with a surging reach toward a distant shore. The wind hummed in the sail and the boat made a throaty rumbling sound as it accelerated.</p>
        <p>Except for tears streaming from his eyes, Mr. DeLorenzo seemed not to notice the cold. "Isn't this heaven?" he shouted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
