<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDB1630F93BA25752C0A962958260" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-10  PRISON FOR 2 GERMAN SKINHEADS  Two German skinheads who attacked a group of American athletes in October were sentenced to prison, one for two years and eight months and the other for one year.  A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-10  PRISON FOR 2 GERMAN SKINHEADS  Two German skinheads who attacked a group of American athletes in October were sentenced to prison, one for two years and eight months and the other for one year.  A3</p>
        <p>DE KLERK COURTS ZULU KING  F. W. de Klerk tried to win the support of the King of the Zulus, Goodwill Zwelethini, for South Africa's universal elections in April.  A3  YELTSIN TRIES TO KEEP A TOP AIDE  President Yeltsin accepted the resignation of Yegor T. Gaidar, the architect of Russia's economic reforms, and negotiated to retain the Finance Minister, Boris G. Fyodorov.  A6  ISRAEL HOPEFUL, WARY ON SYRIA  Israel said it saw greater promise of peace with Syria, but expressed extreme caution about the Syrian President's statement that he was ready for normal relations.  A8  MEXICO ENVOY HEARS FROM REBELS  A special Mexican envoy said the Government had received its first formal contact from rebels in the peasant uprising in the south.  A10  SAUDI DEAL IS NEAR ON PAYMENTS  Saudi Arabia is nearing agreement with five of the biggest American military contractors to stretch out $10 billion in payments that are due over the next two years.  A8  DISCORD AT MEETING ON HAITI  The Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide ended a gathering of Haitian politicians with a call to unite against the military in Haiti, but the gathering exposed basic differences among those who back his presidency.  A10  ARGENTINA TO JOIN ATOM TREATY  Argentina plans to end four decades of defiant policies by joining Latin America's agreement against the spread of nuclear arms.  A10  WAR-CRIMES EFFORT CALLED SLOW  The United States delegate to the United Nations has accused unspecified countries of not cooperating with efforts to prosecute war criminals in the former Yugoslavia.  A10  John Major denied any role in the export of weapons to Iraq.  A6  Paris Journal: Pamela Harriman brings some cachet to her job.  A4  National A14-21, B10  BIG QUAKE HITS LOS ANGELES  A strong predawn earthquake near Los Angeles snapped highway overpasses, leveled buildings, ignited scores of fires, cut off electricity and water to millions, killed at least 30 people and injured hundreds.  A1  APARTMENT HOUSE COLLAPSE  In the apartment building where the loss of life in the earthquake was greatest, shaken residents remembered waking up to find themselves airborne, falling into the floors below. At least 15 people were killed when the building fell.  A1  TRANSPORTATION NIGHTMARE  In the metropolitan area that most depends on the car and the truck to carry on its life, the destruction of primary superhighways is a colossal blow, and one that will be felt for months.  A1  FINDING A NEW WAY OF LIFE  The streets were ghostly, the litter and clutter of destruction everywhere, but slowly in tentative and sometimes unexpected ways the people of the Los Angeles area began to reinvent ways to carry out the business of living in their rattled city.  A1  The highway renovation program helped, engineers said.  A18  Devastation in a neighborhood close to the earthquake's epicenter.  A19  The geology of how the earthquake occurred and why.  A20  Electricity, gas, telephones and water services suffered.  A20  Federal disaster teams went to the area immediately.  A21  SWARTHMORE CAMPUS ABUZZ  It was not the paralyzing snow storm that was the talk of the campus as students returned to Swarthmore. Rather it was the case of the student accused of sexual harassment and intimidation.  A14  Two old cases involving race are back in Mississippi courts.  A14  At a King observance, the President promoted his programs.  B10  The Clinton real estate matter is going to a grand jury.  B10  Metro Digest B1  Science Times C1-13  A new view of the shifting boundaries of the desert.  C1  A mysterious royal burial in the Yucatan.  C1  A cancer gene shows fingerprints of environmental damage.C1  A new understanding of how TB becomes resistant to drugs.  C3  Projections of the impact of global warming on human hunger.  C4  Personal Computers C9  Q&amp;A C9  Peripherals C11  Sports B12-17  Baseball: Owners meet again on old issues.  B17  Basketball: Ewing paces Knick victory.  B13  Georgetown tops Seton Hall.  B16  Columns: Anderson on Montana B13  TV Sports B14  On Basketball B16  Figure Skating: Inquiry into money trail.B13  Skaters return to ice.  B15  Old champions face new.  B15  Football: Salary cap and Giants.  B13  Giants' spirit is unbroken.  B14  Hockey: Panthers edge Islanders.  B15  Tennis: Courier gains in five sets.  B17  Fashion Page B11  Couture recalls bygone glamour.</p>
        <p>Patterns  Business Digest D1  Neediest Cases B2  Obituaries D23  Leo A. Larkin, lawyer.</p>
        <p>Herve Alphand, former French Ambassador to the United States.</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C15-20  A daring German theater director takes center stage.  C15  One-day strike at the Modern.  C15  Bronze Age bells from China show technical virtuosity.  C15  Music: Marilyn Horne tribute.  C15  Orchestra of Westchester.  C17  Dance: Hungarian folk works.  C17  Books: Louise Erdrich returns to North Dakota.  C20  Television: Limits of code breaking.  C20  Mentally ill on the streets.  C20  Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23  Editorials  Tests for Mr. Giuliani.  A warning exit in Moscow.  Aftershock.  The Veep signs on.  Letters  Russell Baker: The won't-do guy.  A. M. Rosenthal: Giuliani, violence and trouble-peddlers.  Scott Anderson: The price of peace in Ulster.  Daniel Pipes: Trust Assad? Not yet. Bridge C16 Chronicle B5 Chess C20 Crossword C16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
