<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Balloon Teams Vie to Be First Around World</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940608T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="692109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BALLOONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Balloons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6D6173AF934A35755C0A962958260" item-length="2333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Balloon Teams Vie to Be First Around World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO ride the winds around the world in a balloon has been the dream of aeronauts for two centuries, but despite many attempts -- some of them disastrous -- none has succeeded. Now, at last, the smell of success is in the air, and world-class balloonists are scrambling to join competing teams for what may be the greatest balloon race of all time.</p>
        <p>As many as five teams may try for the ultimate ballooning achievement: a nonstop circumnavigation of the globe. Hopes are riding not only on high spirits but on new technologies and the innovative balloon designs that the competing groups have devised. Some of the contestants hope to fly higher than any previous balloonist, and they will carry sophisticated scientific apparatus to conduct experiments in the upper atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO ride the winds around the world in a balloon has been the dream of aeronauts for two centuries, but despite many attempts -- some of them disastrous -- none has succeeded. Now, at last, the smell of success is in the air, and world-class balloonists are scrambling to join competing teams for what may be the greatest balloon race of all time.</p>
        <p>As many as five teams may try for the ultimate ballooning achievement: a nonstop circumnavigation of the globe. Hopes are riding not only on high spirits but on new technologies and the innovative balloon designs that the competing groups have devised. Some of the contestants hope to fly higher than any previous balloonist, and they will carry sophisticated scientific apparatus to conduct experiments in the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>All participants know that they can easily be lost at sea, downed in a hostile Iraqi desert, stranded in a trackless Siberian forest or killed outright. At the very least, an accident could mean a financial loss of much more than $1 million -- the bare minimum cost of a manned balloon designed to fly around the world. Even if a team does succeed, no cash prize will await it.</p>
        <p>Instead, the reward is the chance of entering the official record books kept by the International Balloon Federation, which sends referees to monitor every record attempt. The federation places a sealed recording altimeter aboard each balloon to make sure the craft makes no landing along the way that will disqualify it, and each balloon must return to the longitude from which it started. But even after achieving the glory of a round-the-world record, some of the aeronauts could find themselves in debt indefinitely.</p>
        <p>Far from discouraging potential contenders, recent failed attempts seem to have engendered a burning competitive urge in balloonists who previously watched from the sidelines.</p>
        <p>The most recent failure occurred last January, when the Earthwinds balloon and a three-member crew headed by Larry Newman were forced to land a few hours after launching from Reno Stead Airfield, Nev.; it was Earthwind's fourth failure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman himself hopes to make another attempt next November with the $7 million Earthwinds balloon, which is financially backed by the hotel magnate Barron Hilton. But this time, other groups are nipping at his heels. The competition has been likened to the trans-Atlantic airplane race that culminated in Charles Lindbergh's New York-to-Paris flight in 1927.</p>
        <p>Besides attracting most of the world's leading long-distance balloonists, the current rash of balloon projects has kindled the interest of engineers and scientists who hope to gain important information from some of the flights. Instruments in the Stratosphere</p>
        <p>For example, a round-the-world attempt planned by an Albuquerque, N.M., group in its ultrahigh-altitude Odyssey balloon would carry instruments provided by Los Alamos National Laboratory and other scientific institutions into the stratosphere. From their perch nearly 25 miles high, the crew could directly measure chemical reactions occurring within the upper atmosphere's protective ozone layer and study mysterious X-ray emissions from electrical storms over the Himalayas that were detected by spacecraft.</p>
        <p>None of the balloon teams intends to coordinate its launching date with that of any of the others. Indeed, each group says it will proceed with its flight even if a competing team has already succeeded in flying around the world. Nevertheless, competition at a personal level has become intense and, in some cases, bitter. Teams are competing not only for commercial sponsorship of their multimillion-dollar projects, but also to outdo rivals in high-flying grudge matches.</p>
        <p>The five teams are at various stages of readiness and, equally important, financing. Two teams, Earthwinds and the Holland-Flyer, seem to be furthest along on both counts; their crew-carrying capsules are completed, their lifting bags are either nearly assembled or available ready-made from a manufacturer, and both teams have the money needed to get their craft into the air. (While crew capsules, light-weight metal submarine-type structures, can be used more than once, the lifting balloons for these types of high-altitude balloons can usually fly only once; such a balloon costs a minimum of $100,000.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Newman believes that Earthwinds will succeed this time. An airline pilot and seasoned long-distance balloonist, he was a crew member of both the first manned balloon flight across the Atlantic Ocean, in 1978, and the first trans-Pacific flight, in 1981.</p>
        <p>The front-runner among Mr. Newman's competitors appears to be Henk Brink, a Dutch helicopter instructor and balloonist who hopes to launch his Holland-Flyer from Nijmegen, the Netherlands, next January. The Holland-Flyer is a compound balloon, with an upper compartment that is filled with helium and a lower section that contains hot air heated by propane burners. To increase lift, the burners are used to heat both the air and the helium above it. This type of balloon is called a Rozier, named after Jean Francois Pilatre de Rozier, who made the first manned balloon flight in 1783. He was later killed when his balloon, of the type that now bears his name, caught fire and crashed.</p>
        <p>In 1986, Mr. Brink, his wife, Evelien, and Willem Hageman became the first Europeans to cross the Atlantic in a balloon, departing from Newfoundland. Their piloting was so skillful that they landed only a few miles from the Brinks's home in the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>"It's just for public relations that Newman predicts a November launch," Mr. Brink said in a telephone interview. "The weather for a round-the-world flight is always too stormy that early in the season. If he goes, it will be in January or February, about the same time we go. But I don't think he has much chance."</p>
        <p>Another balloon project, called Windstar, has been undertaken by several former Earthwinds team members who left that project after a welter of mutual recriminations and legal squabbles alienated them from Mr. Newman. Russian Involvement</p>
        <p>The flight crew is led by Tim Lachenmeier, a balloon engineer with Raven Industries Inc., the Sioux Falls, S.D., manufacturer that designed and built the complex Earthwinds balloon, as well as many high-altitude scientific balloons. Mr. Lachenmeier and Tom Barrow, a former launch master for Earthwinds, plan a balloon of their own based on an innovative new design using helium as the lifting gas and air as the ballast.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lachenmeier recently visited ballooning colleagues in Russia, some of whom expect to collaborate in the venture. The pressurized capsule needed for the flight may be built in Russia, Mr. Lachenmeier said, and Russia may contribute one of its astronauts as a crew member. (Because of a rift between Raven Industries and Mr. Newman, Mr. Newman is buying his Earthwinds lifting balloon from another manufacturer, the Winzen Company of Sulphur Springs, Tex.)</p>
        <p>Another crew member will be Joe W. Kittinger, a retired Air Force test pilot who made a solo balloon flight in 1984 from Maine to Italy, and who once made a 16-mile free-fall jump from a balloon, a world sky-diving record.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lachenmeier said his balloon would be a "cocoon" consisting of two balloons, one inside the other -- an inner lifting balloon filled with helium and an outer, pressurized balloon containing air. To maintain constant altitude without releasing precious helium during the warmth of the day -- and without having to dump metal-shot ballast in the cool of night -- the cocoon's crew will use the air in the outer balloon as a replenishable form of ballast. To add weight if the balloon should rise too much, the crew could pump nearly a ton of compressed air into the outer balloon, thereby adding weight while compressing the helium balloon and reducing its lift. If the balloon were to descend too far, the crew could lighten it by releasing compressed air.</p>
        <p>"It's basically the same system we designed into the Earthwinds balloon," Mr. Lachenmeier said, "but it's more compact and elegant. Earthwinds has an external anchor balloon that serves the same ballasting purpose as our outer balloon. We would have designed Earthwinds the same way, but at the time we were uncertain about the reliability of the new Spectra balloon fabric for the cocoon design."</p>
        <p>Spectra, a light fabric made by Allied Signal Inc., is based on ultrastrong polymer fibers and is commonly used as armor in bulletproof vests. Its great strength was essential to the design of a huge balloon that must contain compressed air without ripping. Raven Industries gained experience fabricating four Spectra anchor balloons for Earthwinds, Mr. Lachenmeier said, and he is now confident that Spectra can be used for his cocoon design.  Going the Other Way</p>
        <p>Sponsors of the cocoon may include the British balloonist Richard Branson, the president of Virgin Atlantic Airways, balloonists involved in the competition say. Mr. Branson could not be reached.</p>
        <p>An entirely different approach has been adopted by the three-man crew of Odyssey; they plan not only to cruise much higher than the other contestants, but also to fly in the opposite direction. All the would-be globe circlers except Odyssey's crew expect to fly eastward at about 33,000 feet, taking advantage of jet-stream winds that would pull them along at speeds up to 200 miles an hour. They could thus complete the trip in 10 to 12 days. By contrast, Odyssey would ride much gentler winds at altitudes up to 130,000 feet, taking some 22 days to fly westward around the world.</p>
        <p>Odyssey is not ready to fly, and its estimated cost of $1.3 million -- the cheapest of all the currently planned transglobal balloons -- has been only about one quarter subscribed by sponsors, said Bob Martin, a crew member. Moreover, the balloon's launching will be constrained by wind patterns at high altitude that restrict the timing of a launching to a one-week period in July. Mr. Martin predicts that Odyssey will rise from its pad at Fort Sumner, N.M., in July 1995.</p>
        <p>"Even if we're not the first balloon around the world," he said, "we have a good chance at winning both the altitude and endurance records, and perhaps also the distance record. Besides, we would be the first to circle the Earth in a westward direction."</p>
        <p>Of the competing balloons, Odyssey would be the largest and simplest -- large enough to contain a football stadium, with ample room to spare. Unlike the others, Odyssey will carry no engine to generate electric power and will incorporate very few frills. The power needed to operate radios will be supplied by solar panels and a lithium battery.</p>
        <p>The lifting part of the craft will be a balloon made of polyethylene film -- essentially the same material used in sandwich bags. Some 28 million cubic feet of helium pumped into this huge bag will lift a pressurized aluminum capsule with spartan furnishings and a three-member crew. All three will wear pressure suits at critical times during the flight in case they should have to abandon the craft in the space-like environment of the upper atmosphere. 'Balloons Sometimes Do Fail'</p>
        <p>The chief engineer of the Odyssey project, Dr. Robert L. Golden of New Mexico State University, is a professor of astrophysics who has spent much of his career sending heavy scientific payloads to the edge of space aboard huge unmanned balloons. His best-known scientific achievement was the discovery in 1979 of antiprotons as a component of cosmic rays hitting the Earth from the depths of space. The discovery, which Dr. Golden made using instruments aboard a balloon flying at 110,000 feet, established the fact that antimatter existed in nature, not solely as the artificial product of nuclear collisions in laboratory accelerators.</p>
        <p>"We've had lots and lots of experience with high-altitude scientific balloons," Dr. Golden said. "Some unmanned balloon flights carrying scientific payloads have actually completed two or more circuits of the earth, and we're confident that our balloon will carry a human crew safely.</p>
        <p>"These balloons sometimes do fail at high altitude, especially around noon, when the sun warms them up," he said. "But Odyssey's crew capsule will be attached to a big parachute that's already deployed and ready to open automatically. Also, each crew member will have a personal parachute."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lachenmeier, whose balloon design is as complex as Odyssey's is simple, gives Odyssey little chance of success. "Bob Golden and his colleagues are gifted and brilliant scientists, but as balloonists, they're amateurs," he said. "They're going to have to stay up for three weeks, and that balloon will be very lucky indeed to make it around the world before running out of steam."</p>
        <p>Dr. Golden responded: "Ours is the simplest and best-tested of all the designs in the field. We've successfully flown hundreds of similar but unmanned balloons, carrying loads up to 8,000 pounds. Some have gone around the world. Why shouldn't Odyssey also succeed?" Financial Problems</p>
        <p>A fifth balloonist, Julian Nott of England, has spent much of the past decade developing and seeking financing for his Endeavor, a balloon that, like Mr. Brink's Holland-Flyer, would use the combined lifting power of helium and hot air to stay aloft. Among Mr. Nott's previous flights was one in 1980 that reached an altitude of 55,134 feet -- the highest ever achieved by a hot-air balloon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nott had hoped to launch his round-the-world balloon from Australia, but financial problems and Mr. Nott's difficulties in attracting enough sponsors have kept Endeavor grounded.</p>
        <p>"None of us agrees on which group has the best chance," said Mr. Lachenmeier, "but that's what makes for a horse race."</p>
        <p>Dr. Golden added: "We all hope to add to mankind's store of scientific knowledge, and we have a good shot at that. But let's face it: the main thing for all of us is the chance to participate in high adventure."</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 8, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A diagram in Science Times yesterday about balloons competing to be the first to circumnavigate the world nonstop misidentified the one that is to carry instruments from Los Alamos National Laboratory and other institutions. It is Odyssey, not Windstar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 8, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A diagram in Science Times yesterday about balloons competing to be the first to circumnavigate the world nonstop misidentified the one that is to carry instruments from Los Alamos National Laboratory and other institutions. It is Odyssey, not Windstar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
