<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Electricity Industry Needs Competition</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="698659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARKOVICH, BARBARA R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DF153FF933A25754C0A962958260" item-length="315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Electricity Industry Needs Competition</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Ralph Cavanagh argues that allowing electricity consumers to choose their suppliers (called retail wheeling or direct access) will be bad for the environment. Customers who support retail wheeling want lower rates. Even the newly fashionable proposals for incentive rate making cited by Mr. Cavanagh are no substitute for direct competition. Current California electricity rates are almost 50 percent higher than the national average. One can hardly blame customers for wanting to maximize the pressure to bring them down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Ralph Cavanagh argues that allowing electricity consumers to choose their suppliers (called retail wheeling or direct access) will be bad for the environment. Customers who support retail wheeling want lower rates. Even the newly fashionable proposals for incentive rate making cited by Mr. Cavanagh are no substitute for direct competition. Current California electricity rates are almost 50 percent higher than the national average. One can hardly blame customers for wanting to maximize the pressure to bring them down.</p>
        <p>Customers who support retail wheeling also simply want a true choice of supplier. Too many utility customers have learned how hard it is to negotiate with a monopoly. The greater wholesale competition recommended by Mr. Cavanagh will not solve these problems because the ultimate customer still only has one supplier.</p>
        <p>California consumers who support retail wheeling have paid more than their fair share to develop renewable energy and new energy efficiency technologies because of state legislative and regulatory policy. Since Mr. Cavanagh sees these investments as so worthwhile, wouldn't it be reasonable for citizens of other states to share in their costs or to refund to California consumers a share of the benefits they have received?</p>
        <p>Energy and other efficiency improvements for industry are increasingly motivated by the need to be competitive in tough international markets. Utility energy efficiency programs provide incentives to customers through rebates and loans to spur such investments, with the cost being spread across all customers. In a market with retail competition, the utilities can still provide energy efficiency assistance. BARBARA R. BARKOVICH  San Rafael, Calif., June 20  The writer is a principal of Barkovich &amp; Yap Inc., an energy and utility regulatory consulting firm in Emeryville, Calif.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
