<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Vietnam Combat: Coke vs. Pepsi</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOFT DRINKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMBARGOES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VIETNAM</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">COCA-COLA CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PEPSICO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHENON, PHILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Vietnam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DB1638F934A35751C0A962958260" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Vietnam Combat: Coke vs. Pepsi</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHENON, PHILIP</byline>
      <dateline>HO CHI MINH CITY, Vietnam, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what seems the realization of the worst nightmare of a generation of dedicated Vietnamese Communists, the Vietnam War has now given way to the opening volleys of the Cola War.</p>
        <p>In the first days after a 19-year-old American trade embargo against Vietnam was lifted, most large American consumer products companies are still nowhere to be seen here. Their people are not yet in place; their advertising campaigns are still weeks away.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what seems the realization of the worst nightmare of a generation of dedicated Vietnamese Communists, the Vietnam War has now given way to the opening volleys of the Cola War.</p>
        <p>In the first days after a 19-year-old American trade embargo against Vietnam was lifted, most large American consumer products companies are still nowhere to be seen here. Their people are not yet in place; their advertising campaigns are still weeks away.</p>
        <p>But not Coke and Pepsi. The two soft-drink giants, those potent symbols of American capitalism, are already battling in the streets of the country's largest city -- the southern Vietnamese city once called Saigon -- at the start of a campaign for the hearts and minds of Vietnam's 71 million people.</p>
        <p>"The enthusiasm among the Vietnamese is unbelievable," Barry J. Shea, Southeast Asian president of Pepsi-Cola International, said. "And we think Pepsi has the opportunity to totally dominate." A Booming Market</p>
        <p>After leading a tour of the modern assembly line on the outskirts of Ho Chi Minh City where Pepsi began production only hours after President Clinton announced the end of the embargo, Mr. Shea was asked about the challenge from Coke in Vietnam. "To describe it as war may be a little strong," he said. "But we're certainly not friendly."</p>
        <p>Both companies predict that within a decade, Vietnamese soft-drink sales could amount to hundreds of millions of dollars a year, making it potentially one of Asia's largest markets.</p>
        <p>About 40 million cases of soft drinks -- there are 24 bottles in a case -- are currently sold each year in Vietnam. Soft-drink analysts think the number could rise to more than 200 million cases in several years, given Vietnam's booming economy and its embrace of the free market.</p>
        <p>Both Coke and Pepsi expect to sell a 10-ounce bottle for the equivalent of 15 cents, far less than in the United States but a substantial amount in Vietnam, which is still one of the world's poorest countries. Its per-capita income is less than $500 a year.</p>
        <p>Pepsi comes to Vietnam with a disadvantage. Many Vietnamese, especially in the distant countryside, have never heard of it. Pepsi had just opened its first bottling plant in South Vietnam when the country was overrun by the north in 1975.</p>
        <p>By that time, Coca-Cola had been in Vietnam for more than a decade and was selling nearly 20 million cases, or 480 million bottles, a year. The collapse of South Vietnam forced it to abandon its five bottling plants.</p>
        <p>But Coke stayed behind in Vietnam even after the last American soldiers had pulled out. For years, Coke has been finding its way into Vietnam, usually smuggled by the shipload from Singapore, Malaysia and Thailand. Today Coke remains the soft drink of choice for millions of Vietnamese, north and south, including senior Communist Party officials who can be seen guzzling Coke at official receptions. 'A Legacy Here'</p>
        <p>"Coca-Cola has a legacy here," Mark Ohlson, the region manager of Coca-Cola Indochina, said. "When they think of cola, they think of us. And I don't see any reason for that to change."</p>
        <p>Coke's new advertising slogan emphasizes the fact that it is not new to Vietnam: "Vui Mung Gap Lai Cac Ban," or Good to See You Again.</p>
        <p>Sipping Vietnamese tea in the lobby of a plush Saigon hotel, Mr. Ohlson said he had not been flustered by the early publicity blitz staged by Pepsi, which is advertising itself with billboards that proclaim it "Su Lua Chon Cua The He Moi," -- the Choice of a New Generation.</p>
        <p>Pepsi opened the cola war just before noon on Friday here, seven hours after the White House announcement, when bottles of Pepsi began rolling off the assembly line of the International Beverages Company, which is Pepsi's partner in Vietnam. The company is a joint venture between the city government and a Singapore company.</p>
        <p>The Pepsi concentrate had been sitting here for weeks, awaiting action from Washington. The first day's production, 40,000 bottles, was trucked to the center of the city and passed out as free samples, along with some cans. The result in some parts of the city was a near-riot. "They were climbing over each other," Mr. Shea said.</p>
        <p>On Friday evening, Pepsi broadcast its first television commercials. This week, it is scheduled to begin a larger television advertising campaign featuring Miss Vietnam, Ha Kieu Anh, who is 18."I would say that she's Vietnam's current sweetheart -- talented, ambitious, optimistic, with a lot of dreams for a better Vietnam," John Englehart, general manager of Ogilvy &amp; Mather Thailand, the advertising firm behind the campaign, said. "We were thrilled to have her." Slower to Bottle</p>
        <p>Although it has already shipped in six tons of advertising signs and other publicity materials, Coke's publicity campaign has been muted by comparison. Coke production is not expected to start in Vietnam for two or three weeks. The concentrate and its trademark glass bottles are still not here yet. For now, Coke will flood the market with bottles imported from other parts of Asia.</p>
        <p>Coke's partner is the Vietnamese Government, and company officials concede that the Government-owned bottling plant that will produce Coke requires some refitting and expansion. The Pepsi plant, by comparison, is the most modern soft-drink factory in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>Coke's television commercials are ready, but it has so far been unable to buy advertising time, which is sold out for the next several days because of local ads linked to Tet, the lunar new year, which begins Thursday. Pepsi is getting its commercials broadcast because it bought the advertising time that its partner had prebooked for other, non-American soft drinks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ohlson said a delay of a few days for the television campaign posed no problem, given Coke's name recognition in Vietnam.</p>
        <p>"Two days or five days or two weeks, it's not going to make a difference," he said of the television campaign. "The thing is, when you are the No. 1 soft drink, it's very important that you maintain a good image. There's no reason to be frenetic."</p>
        <p>Indeed, Pepsi's feverish return to streets of Ho Chi Minh City this weekend did leave a bad taste in a few mouths. The first day's production of the drink tasted funny. The plant had used a type of carbon dioxide that gave the fizz an unpleasant sulfuric taste, typical of Vietnamese soft drinks. "As soon as we tasted it, we changed the CO2 supplier," Mr. Shea said. "Now, it's perfect."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
