<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Buying Air-Conditioners: An Environmental Guide</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E1D8153CF933A05755C0A962958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Buying Air-Conditioners: An Environmental Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SHOPPER went to a discount store, Tops Appliance City, in East Hanover, N.J., earlier this month to look for a window air-conditioner. He made a tentative selection, a $700 model, and then asked if the machine used Freon, the Du Pont trade name that is commonly used to refer to chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, the chemicals blamed for eating a hole in the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Yes, the salesman said, and the machines are notorious for leaking, he added, so buy our service contract, too, for $149.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SHOPPER went to a discount store, Tops Appliance City, in East Hanover, N.J., earlier this month to look for a window air-conditioner. He made a tentative selection, a $700 model, and then asked if the machine used Freon, the Du Pont trade name that is commonly used to refer to chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, the chemicals blamed for eating a hole in the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Yes, the salesman said, and the machines are notorious for leaking, he added, so buy our service contract, too, for $149.</p>
        <p>Well, said the shopper, do you have any that don't use Freon?</p>
        <p>Oh, sir, said the salesman, you wouldn't want one of those, because the replacement refrigerant corrodes the machine's innards. Buy the service contract instead, he said again.</p>
        <p>What's an environmentally conscious shopper to do?</p>
        <p>First, stop listening to the salesman.</p>
        <p>"The salesman is flat-out wrong" about the refrigerant used in air-conditioners, said T. R. Reid, a spokesman for the Whirlpool Corporation in Benton Harbor, Mich., which produces window units under the Whirlpool, Kitchenaid, Roper and Kenmore brand names.</p>
        <p>(On Monday, the Tops store manager said someone from company headquarters would respond. No one did.)</p>
        <p>No window units use CFC's like Freon. Instead, they use a compound called R-22, part of a class of chemicals called HCFC's. HCFC's do some ozone damage, but at the moment, no one markets a completely ozone-friendly window air-conditioner, so the only alternative is to swelter.</p>
        <p>With a warm spring and a reasonably strong economy, the industry expects to sell more than three million window air-conditioners this year, all using R-22, and nearly all of that refrigerant will eventually be vented into the atmosphere, either because the machines leak or because they break down and are dumped in landfills.</p>
        <p>For now, buy whatever you can find in the stores, because window air-conditioners are not prone to leak, at least not in the first decade or so.</p>
        <p>Window air-conditioners are not as big a problem as cars. The 1994 cars and many of the 1993's use a new refrigerant called R-134a, which does not hurt the ozone layer; older models use R-12, which persists in the atmosphere for decades and breaks down stratospheric ozone molecules that protect life on the earth's surface from the sun's ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>Car air-conditioners are prone to leak: they are powered by a belt from the engine, which spins a shaft, and the seal around the shaft gradually breaks down. In addition, car air-conditioners must be free to bounce and vibrate, so they use hoses instead of pipes, and the hoses leak, too. But production of R-12 will be banned after this year, and repairing air-conditioners, expensive now, will become harder and harder.</p>
        <p>Window air-conditioners are more durable because the motors and spinning shafts are inside a sealed box. Most have a life span of 12 to 15 years.</p>
        <p>But the refrigerant they use, R-22, is scheduled to be phased out, too. Almost all production will stop in 2020. According to the air-conditioning industry, R-22 does only 5 percent as much damage as R-12.</p>
        <p>Not everyone agrees that R-22 is acceptable even in the short-term. John W. Passacantando, the executive director of Ozone Action, a Washington environmental group, said that in the next few decades, R-22 will have an impact much larger than 5 percent, maybe 20 or 25 percent.</p>
        <p>The 5 percent figure, he said, was based on damage over the next 200 years, but the most intense period of ozone destruction will occur much sooner, in the next century. Industry executives do not agree, but they anticipate that the current phase-out for R-22 will be accelerated. Thus they all have replacements on the drawing boards or ready to mass-produce.</p>
        <p>The problem is that an air-conditioner using R-134a, if it were the same size as current units, would be 30 percent less efficient, said A. Bruce Buchholz, the vice president for window air-conditioners at the Carrier Corporation in Syracuse. At the same time, the United States Department of Energy is proposing regulations to make all air-conditioners more efficient. Manufacturers can make window units more efficient by adding more coils, but that makes them bigger, noisier and costlier.</p>
        <p>So the industry, along with the chemical companies that make the refrigerants, is still looking for a better substitute than R-134a.</p>
        <p>Companies that make dehumidifiers, which have traditionally used R-12, are switching to R-22 because it won't be banned until 2020, said Robert J. Laurent, a spokesman for the Fedders Corporation in Peapack, N.J.</p>
        <p>Carrier, a United Technologies subsidiary, has built a window unit that runs on R-134a and is ready to mass-produce it, but for the European market. "In Europe a room air-conditioner sells for double what it does in the U.S.," Mr. Buchholz said. "There's a margin to work with there."</p>
        <p>Whole-house air conditioners also run on R-22, but Carrier introduced a model earlier this year that runs on R-134a. Size is generally not a consideration in whole-house models, because the machinery is outdoors.</p>
        <p>Buying a whole-house unit that runs on R-134a would be better for the environment, but people who buy units that use R-22 will probably be able to find refrigerant for as long as the air-conditioners last, at least under the current phase-out schedule. That puts a ceiling on production beginning in 1996 and cuts production to 65 percent by 2004, to 35 percent in 2010 and to 10 percent in 2015.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
