<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Electricity Stalls Power of Wind As a Statewide Source of Energy</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="679938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINDMILLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EED7123EF931A25757C0A962958260" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Electricity Stalls Power of Wind As a Statewide Source of Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>STAMFORD, Conn., April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the cost of the technology dropping, windmills could help the Northeast meet its energy needs more cleanly, experts said today at a conference on renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>The catch is that, right now, the region is awash in cheap electricity, so there is little economic incentive to invest in windmills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the cost of the technology dropping, windmills could help the Northeast meet its energy needs more cleanly, experts said today at a conference on renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>The catch is that, right now, the region is awash in cheap electricity, so there is little economic incentive to invest in windmills.</p>
        <p>California is by far the largest user of wind, with windmills producing 1.2 percent of its electricity, and up to 7 percent in peak-demand periods. If every site were used, the state could generate one-third of its electricity with wind, said Donald Aiken, senior energy analyst at the Union of Concerned Scientists.</p>
        <p>But New York State has even more wind power available than California, and could use wind to meet half its electricity needs if all potential sites were used, Mr. Aiken said. Low Winds Forecast</p>
        <p>Wind projects are scattered around the Northeast, including one in New York State. But Bernard Fox, the president and chief executive of Northeast Utilities, which serves most of Connecticut and large parts of Massachusetts and New Hampshire, said, "We're not going to be ordering much of anything for the next few years."</p>
        <p>The combination of the recession and conservation efforts means that the company will not need any new generating stations until well into the next decade, he said.</p>
        <p>In addition, the company will not pay more for renewable energy than it has to, Mr. Fox said. Northeast is now paying $215 million a year for electricity from plants that burn wood or garbage that it could generate itself for $50 million. The reason is that it priced the power in the early 1980's by comparing it to the cost of oil, which was then high, and the estimated future cost, which was even higher. But the price of oil fell.</p>
        <p>Utilities' use of renewable energy is important because electric companies consume more than 40 percent of all fuels used in the nation, and the proportion is rising; if the economy moves to non-depletable resources, the utilities will play a huge role.</p>
        <p>The conference, organized by the Northeast Sustainable Energy Association, of Greenfield, Mass., drew hundreds of utility executives, scientists, environmentalists and others to the Sheraton Hotel here for three days of workshops and lectures. Wind, rain and sun each got their own conference room this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Photovoltaic cells, which make electricity from sunlight, are also dropping in cost. Jane M. Weissman, coordinator of an inter-utility testing group, said that in Boston, despite three feet of snow in February, there were still 16 days of strong sun.</p>
        <p>Solar-cell manufacturers have high hopes for the Northeast, particularly New York City and Long Island, which have the highest electric rates of almost anywhere in the country. Their product cannot make electricity nearly as cheaply as a conventional power plant, but the cells can produce electricity for less than the retail cost.</p>
        <p>The technology that is closest to making its way in the competitive market on an unsubsidized basis -- and is beginning to do so -- is wind.</p>
        <p>Hydro-Quebec, the Canadian provincial utility that exports hydro-electric power to the states in the Northeast, plans to install about 300 wind machines, with a capacity of 100 megawatts, on the south shore of the St. Laurence River in the next two years, a $110 million project. The wind will produce as much energy as 30 megawatts of hydroelectric capacity -- enough to power 15,000 houses, the utility says, and up to 40 megawatts on windy days in the winter, when demand is highest.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
