<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stiglitz, Idea Man Among the Economic Advisers</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COUNCIL OF ECONOMIC ADVISERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STIGLITZ, JOSEPH (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASAR, SYLVIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE3DD1438F93AA35751C0A962958260" item-length="1413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stiglitz, Idea Man Among the Economic Advisers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIA NASAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASAR, SYLVIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Joseph Stiglitz was invited to join the President's Council of Economic Advisers, many wondered whether the ivory-tower theorist from Stanford University could possibly navigate the currents of real world policy-making. The council's role, played mostly behind the scenes, is to inject as much economic rationality into Administration proposals as politics allow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stiglitz, 51, had written hundreds of papers on the economics of information, public finance and economic development, won the prestigious John Bates Clark medal in 1979 and was widely expected to collect a Nobel someday. He was also the quintessential absent-minded professor, who has dashed into class and lectured on the wrong subject, and often turned up with his tie or shirt collar seriously askew. Repairing Markets</p>
        <p>In fact, as the council's chairwoman, Laura D'Andrea Tyson, must have recognized when she chose Professor Stiglitz, he and Washington circa 1993 were made for each other. He has spent his professional life focused on the idea that markets are imperfect and need to be repaired. "What ends up in the Government's portfolio are the things where the market is having problems," Mr. Stiglitz said, "Government can make a major difference for the good if you structure policies appropriately."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Joseph Stiglitz was invited to join the President's Council of Economic Advisers, many wondered whether the ivory-tower theorist from Stanford University could possibly navigate the currents of real world policy-making. The council's role, played mostly behind the scenes, is to inject as much economic rationality into Administration proposals as politics allow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stiglitz, 51, had written hundreds of papers on the economics of information, public finance and economic development, won the prestigious John Bates Clark medal in 1979 and was widely expected to collect a Nobel someday. He was also the quintessential absent-minded professor, who has dashed into class and lectured on the wrong subject, and often turned up with his tie or shirt collar seriously askew. Repairing Markets</p>
        <p>In fact, as the council's chairwoman, Laura D'Andrea Tyson, must have recognized when she chose Professor Stiglitz, he and Washington circa 1993 were made for each other. He has spent his professional life focused on the idea that markets are imperfect and need to be repaired. "What ends up in the Government's portfolio are the things where the market is having problems," Mr. Stiglitz said, "Government can make a major difference for the good if you structure policies appropriately."</p>
        <p>That sentiment is in keeping with everything that the Administration has done, or is thinking about, whether it is overhauling the nation's health care, ushering in the electronic information age or reducing the country's emissions of greenhouse gases. And while economists -- including the ones who work for the White House -- rarely have the last word on policy, many of those who have worked with him say that Mr. Stiglitz is having an impact by suggesting creative solutions to complicated problems.</p>
        <p>"What he brings to the table is a fountain of ideas," said Alan Blinder, the third member of the economic council.</p>
        <p>Take a recent contribution to the nuts and bolts of the Administration's environmental policy, the new plan to reform the Superfund. The Government's program to get companies to clean up polluted industrial sites has practically become synonymous with government waste and inefficiency. It was Mr. Stiglitz's idea to replace part of the current system of liability -- which encourages costly legal suits more than cleanups -- with a system of arbitration and a set of economic incentives to encourage companies to stay out of court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stiglitz sold his contribution to the lawyers on the interagency task force that crafted the Administration proposal partly by the cogency of his arguments and partly by his ability to suggest compromises and alternatives when the discussion seemed to be heading for a stalemate.</p>
        <p>"He always brings a new idea and perpetual good humor," said Alicia Munnell, Assistant Treasury Secretary for economic policy. "He always has another notion of how this deal could be worked."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stiglitz is also helping shape the Administration's thinking on ways to help politically powerful but economically weak states like California and New York without playing havoc with the budget agreement.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Stiglitz sometimes compares himself to the greatest economists of all time, from Adam Smith to Paul Samuelson, many in Washington are disarmed by his tendency not to take himself too seriously -- he played an elaborate practical joke on the council staff soon after arriving and showed up at the C.E.A. Christmas party dressed as Santa -- his ability to listen and his genuine enthusiasm for other people's ideas. No Sign of Arrogance</p>
        <p>"Joe brings a lot of intellectual power to problems," Ms. Tyson said, "but how you bring it matters as much as what you bring, and Joe doesn't bring even the slightest trace of arrogance."</p>
        <p>Of course, Presidents rarely do what their economists tell them. Michael Boskin, President Bush's chief economist, recalls that he had to threaten to quit to get an interview with his boss at the height of the recession. President Reagan wanted to disband the Council of Economic Advisers. President Clinton uses the council, among other things, to help with Chelsea's homework.</p>
        <p>But it is completely characteristic of Professor Stiglitz, a born can-do optimist, not to dwell on the half-empty cup of his influence. Twinkly eyed, smiling and comfortably rotund, he is simply having too much fun munching his way through "the smorgasbord of interesting problems" that wind up on the council's agenda. "I have the greatest job in Washington," he said. The biggest surprise, he added, is the fact that Washington isn't populated by a bunch of back-stabbers.</p>
        <p>"When a decision is informed, when we've had an intelligent discussion," he said, "I don't feel bad when people don't go along with our recommendations."</p>
        <p>Endless meetings don't exhaust him. Instead, he says, he's invigorated. And he still has energy to spare for playing with his two young children, Siobhan and Michael, and his dog, Woofie; making feasts for friends, and taking an occasional expedition to California, though his frequent and far-flung travels ("Joe is the person you'd be most likely to meet at the head of the Amazon," a friend said ) have temporarily been put on hold. The Perks of Office</p>
        <p>"He was tickled when Clinton walked over to us and said, 'Hi, Joe,' " said Jane Hannaway, his wife, who added that her husband relished the chance to eat at the White House mess and take out-of-town guests to the President's box at Kennedy Center. "But he couldn't exist on that," she continued. "For most people in Washington, a good problem is something Congress will pass. To Joe, it's one that's interesting,"</p>
        <p>The work Professor Stiglitz has done in the past gives important clues to advice he'll give in the future.</p>
        <p>His analysis of insurance markets concludes that such markets frequently break down because it is impossible for insurance companies to know as much as individuals do about their true health status. His solution? Universal coverage.</p>
        <p>His theories about credit markets suggests that high rates may not ease credit crunches because they attract poor credit risks. And his analysis of labor markets suggests that discrimination can be self-reinforcing, not self-correcting as conventional economic models imply. Shifting the Paradigm</p>
        <p>"What I've tried to do for first time is to shift the paradigm," Mr. Stiglitz said. "The key to economics is problems of information -- who knows what -- and these problems of information are core to our understanding of all our institutions."</p>
        <p>George Ackerloff, an economist at the University of California at Berkeley, said: "The old-style economics is the standard story of perfect competition. The new style of economics makes you focus very heavily on imperfections in markets and their consequences."</p>
        <p>Some other economists question whether market breakdowns in theory are pervasive enough in reality to warrant an entirely new economic paradigm. "Markets get the wrong answer. That's a logical pass that can't be ruled out," said Robert Lucas an economist at the University of Chicago "But he never turned the corner into quantitative research. It doesn't give you a prescriptive apparatus either."</p>
        <p>Others worry that Mr. Stiglitzis is too ready to believe that government intervention will work as benignly as intended. Overcoming Naivete</p>
        <p>John Taylor, a close friend at Stanford and a member of the economics council under President Bush, added that he, for one, was confident that a spell in Washington would remedy any such naivete. Professor Stiglitz's recently published introductory economics text -- some call it a potential rival for the Samuelson classic -- contains hundreds of pages on market failures, but just a couple on government foul-ups. "There will be more stories about government failures in the second edition," he said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps. What's certain is that the sojourn in Washington is not likely to tarnish his reputation as an absent-minded professor.</p>
        <p>Twenty minutes into a recent meeting of the Administration's economic team, for example, the budget director, Leon Panetta, who had been staring at Professor Stiglitz, jumped up, exclaimed, "I can't stand it any more!" and walked over behind the economist, grabbed the latter's tie and put it in its rightful place. Professor Stiglitz -- and not, his colleagues say, for the first time -- had tied the tie on top of his collar instead of underneath it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
