<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Utilities, New Clean-Air Plan</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NIAGARA MOHAWK POWER CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ARIZONA PUBLIC SERVICE COMPANY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL DEFENSE FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D71331F93BA25752C1A962958260" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Utilities, New Clean-Air Plan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opening the door to a lower-cost method for reducing "greenhouse" gases that contribute to global warming, two big electric utilities have made a first-of-its-kind deal to trade air pollution allowances.</p>
        <p>The agreement, scheduled to be announced today by Niagara Mohawk, serving upstate New York, and Arizona Public Service in Phoenix, is the first in which the right to emit one type of pollutant is being swapped for another.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Opening the door to a lower-cost method for reducing "greenhouse" gases that contribute to global warming, two big electric utilities have made a first-of-its-kind deal to trade air pollution allowances.</p>
        <p>The agreement, scheduled to be announced today by Niagara Mohawk, serving upstate New York, and Arizona Public Service in Phoenix, is the first in which the right to emit one type of pollutant is being swapped for another.</p>
        <p>Even more significant, part of the deal involves using a portion of the million-dollar proceeds from a tax break to finance experiments in reducing climate-warming emissions outside the United States.</p>
        <p>At first, the experiments will be modest. One reportedly high on the utilities' list is a plan to generate electricity in India with waste heat from sugar refineries that now just goes up the stack. Another is reforestation in Mexico, where Arizona Public Service is already building strategic alliances with electric utilities.</p>
        <p>But the experiments could deliver immense benefits in the future. Almost all of the cheapest opportunities for reducing emissions of gases that are warming the atmosphere lie outside North America, Western Europe and Japan. Modernizing electricity production in China, for instance, offers one of the best prospects because the economy there is growing so rapidly, requiring China to burn enormous amounts of coal in highly inefficient power plants. An even simpler way to control emissions would be to repair leaks in Russia's poorly maintained natural gas pipelines, which spew methane into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Government officials aware of the utility deal say it may point to a better way of meeting Washington's expected obligations under future international agreements to limit global warming.</p>
        <p>The utility deal, by demonstrating the advantages of going abroad to reduce greenhouse gases in the least expensive way, also could open the way eventually to an international trade in pollution allowances.</p>
        <p>"If we are going to deal with climate warming efficiently," said Robert Stavins, an environmental economist at Harvard University, "there will have to be international trading in which Western countries get credit for reducing emissions elsewhere."</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act of 1990 put a cap on utilities' emissions of sulfur dioxide, a byproduct of fuel burning that contributes to acid rain. But it allows utilities to meet their obligations by buying emissions "allowances" from other companies.</p>
        <p>This market-based approach, the Environmental Protection Agency says, is already saving rate payers $400 million to $600 million a year. It works because one utility that finds a cheaper way to cut emissions can profit by doing more than the law requires, selling the right to pollute to another utility that would have found it more expensive to achieve those reductions itself.</p>
        <p>Arizona Public Service can easily meet the requirements of the law in its own territory because it earlier agreed to pay for equipment to reduce the haze above the Grand Canyon. In the process, it is reducing sulfur emissions.</p>
        <p>Niagara Mohawk is also in good shape because it relies on huge amounts of nonpolluting hydropower to meet the needs of its customers.</p>
        <p>But both Arizona Public Service and Niagara Mohawk have a separate obligation to contain climate-warming gases, which for the most part consist of carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels. The utilities signed the Clinton Administration's Climate Challenge Accord in April 1994, a voluntary agreement to do their part in meeting America's international treaty commitment to keep emissions of greenhouse gases under the levels produced in 1990.  William E. Davis, the chief executive of Niagara Mohawk, says the company hopes to demonstrate that its method offers a better approach than "command and control regulations by Congress."</p>
        <p>Niagara Mohawk expects no difficulties in hitting its greenhouse gas target. But Arizona Public Service does: "Demand for power in our service area is growing at double the national rate," said O. Mark DeMichele, the chief executive of Arizona Public Service, and "power consumption is already three years ahead of projections."</p>
        <p>The Arizona utility thus needed help, which was forthcoming from Niagara Mohawk. Under a deal brokered by the Environmental Defense Fund, the New York utility agreed to absorb 1.75 million tons of Arizona Public Services' obligation to reduce carbon dioxide emissions in return for 25,000 tons of sulfur dioxide allowances.</p>
        <p>Since Niagara Mohawk has no foreseeable need for the sulfur allowances it is reaping, the utility plans to donate the allowances to a nonprofit group (as yet unnamed), which will retire them permanently. Niagara Mohawk still benefits because it will be able to claim a corporate income tax deduction of about $150 a ton. "Northeast Utilities did precisely the same thing, donating sulfur allowances to the American Lung Association," said Joseph Goffman, senior lawyer for the Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
        <p>Utilities have been exchanging sulfur dioxide allowances for cash for some time, both in private agreements and through a commodities exchange maintained by the Chicago Board of Trade. The price of the allowance, however, has remained below earlier expectations.</p>
        <p>The Climate Control accord deliberately offered utilities maximum leeway in meeting emissions reduction targets -- anything from insulating houses to subsidizing electric cars. The deal between Arizona Public Service and Niagara Mohawk shows that American utilities may be able to fulfill their obligations even more cheaply by finding foreign sources of pollution that they agree to clean up.</p>
        <p>The Department of Energy, which has been not-so-quietly urging such experiments, plans to help by amassing a data base to be used for arranging international trades and verifying compliance.</p>
        <p>The deal does have a few weak spots. This is not a free lunch for everyone: Some of the money to finance the experiment is coming from taxpayers in the form of deductions for the sulfur emissions. More is coming from rate payers and stockholders, since the utilities could choose instead to sell their extra sulfur allowances for a profit rather than donating them to charity.</p>
        <p>But Hazel R. O'Leary, the Secretary of Energy, defends the deal as a very cheap lunch. "Market solutions to environmental problems," she said, "will always be cheaper than direct regulation. And the utilities are anxious to play."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
