<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>That's No Joke About Cows and Methane</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="692166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METHANE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIVESTOCK</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DE143AF934A35755C0A962958260" item-length="346" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>That's No Joke About Cows and Methane</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your microreport on a Federal grant of $500,000, "to find out if cattle belch enough methane to contribute to global warming," will produce much sophomoric mischief. In this case the Environmental Protection Agency seems to be investing our money wisely, contrary to the tone in "Of Global Warming and Burping Cows" by The Associated Press (some editions, May 29).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your microreport on a Federal grant of $500,000, "to find out if cattle belch enough methane to contribute to global warming," will produce much sophomoric mischief. In this case the Environmental Protection Agency seems to be investing our money wisely, contrary to the tone in "Of Global Warming and Burping Cows" by The Associated Press (some editions, May 29).</p>
        <p>Methane, an abundant trace gas in our atmosphere, has been increasing rapidly at about 1 percent a year over the decade. It absorbs infrared radiation and, to the extent that it does so, contributes to warming our atmosphere and thereby changing it.</p>
        <p>Additionally, methane, in the troposphere, affects the abundance of other important trace gases such as carbon monoxide, ozone and the hydroxyl radical (OH). In the stratosphere it has a profound effect on ozone and chlorine chemistry and water vapor.</p>
        <p>The major sources of methane are well known: landfills, such as Staten Island's Fresh Kills, biomass burning, clearing forests and grassland for grazing, burning wood and fossil fuels, and leakage from natural gas pipelines. Anaerobic bacteria living in the shallow waters of rice paddies and in the digestive systems of ruminants and termites also produce significant amounts of methane.</p>
        <p>Camels, cattle, sheep, goats, antelopes are among the hoofed grazing animals with three or four compartments in their stomachs. When they rechew plant material, they expel methane when they open their mouths. There are fairly reliable estimates of the present and projected millions of domestic ruminants we keep, but it is hard to measure how much methane they produce -- although it is considerable.</p>
        <p>Our atmosphere is important. It has an important budget. We need to know where things are coming from, and where they are going. The air we breathe came from somewhere, and its supply is not infinite, although it may seem so. We have only to look toward the other planets in our system and as far as we can see with our best technology. JIM SCANLON  San Rafael, Calif., May 30, 1994</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
