<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Theory Would Reconcile Rival Views on Dinosaurs' Demise</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="733666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DINOSAURS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METEORS AND METEORITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARS (PLANET)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLCANOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALEONTOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E1D6173BF934A15751C1A962958260" item-length="1616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Theory Would Reconcile Rival Views on Dinosaurs' Demise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the last decade or so two main schools of thought have clashed furiously over the question of what did in the dinosaurs. One school holds that a massive object from outer space slammed into the Earth, kicking up a worldwide pall of dust that blotted out the Sun and killed off many plants and animals. The other school prefers to seek the cause of the global mayhem in natural processes like big volcanic eruptions.</p>
        <p>Each side has accumulated a lot of evidence to support its case, though lately the advocates of an asteroid collision seem to have had the upper hand.</p>
        <p>Now, however, an elegant theory has been proposed that neatly combines both conflicting ideas into a single mechanism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the last decade or so two main schools of thought have clashed furiously over the question of what did in the dinosaurs. One school holds that a massive object from outer space slammed into the Earth, kicking up a worldwide pall of dust that blotted out the Sun and killed off many plants and animals. The other school prefers to seek the cause of the global mayhem in natural processes like big volcanic eruptions.</p>
        <p>Each side has accumulated a lot of evidence to support its case, though lately the advocates of an asteroid collision seem to have had the upper hand.</p>
        <p>Now, however, an elegant theory has been proposed that neatly combines both conflicting ideas into a single mechanism.</p>
        <p>It posits that a speeding rock from outer space, exploding on collision with the force of millions of hydrogen bombs, would have shot gargantuan shock waves through the Earth. The waves would have coalesced at the side opposite to the impact crater, an area known as the antipode, breaking the ground there and heating it and triggering huge volcanic outflows. Both the impact and its repercussions in the other hemisphere, the theory goes, would have contributed to the mysterious decline of the dinosaurs and many other species some 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Antipodal volcanism, as the theory is sometimes called, was first discussed in relation to the dinosaurs in the early 1990's and is now taking on new weight as computer modeling begins to suggest its plausibility and as planetary scientists keep finding apparent examples of it in the heavens.</p>
        <p>Dr. David A. Williams and Dr. Ronald Greeley of Arizona State University recently reported in the journal Icarus that the largest impact basin on Mars, Hellas Plenitia, is antipodal to Alba Patera, an eruption that sprawls for nearly 1,000 miles across the Martian surface and is the largest volcano in the solar system. Moreover, they calculate that the impact's reverberations at the antipode were strong enough to tear open fractures more than 10 miles deep, perhaps helping to trigger a titanic flow of lava.</p>
        <p>As for the Earth, a team of scientists at the Sandia National Laboratory in Albuquerque, N.M., recently used a powerful computer to simulate the damage a speeding asteroid some six miles in diameter -- the estimated size of the dinosaur killer -- would have wrought at the impact's antipode. They discovered that the crust there would have heaved as high as 60 feet in a series of catastrophic tremors. In comparison, the ground at the great San Francisco earthquake of 1906 moved a few feet at most.</p>
        <p>"The Earth acts like a lens," said Dr. Mark B. Boslough, a Sandia physicist who is leading the simulation effort. "It focuses the energy. There's been a lot of speculation about this in relation to asteroid impacts and volcanic eruptions, but we've done the first rigorous modeling to show where the energy actually goes."</p>
        <p>Dr. John T. Hagstrum, an early advocate of the theory who works at the United States Geological Survey in Menlo Park, Calif., cautioned that antipodal volcanism was far from proved even though it has taken on new substance.</p>
        <p>"It explains a lot of coincidences," Dr. Hagstrum said. "I think it has merit. But it could fall flat on its face. Right now, I'm waiting for the smoking gun. I'd call the whole thing intriguing."</p>
        <p>The idea that a doomsday rock did in the dinosaurs was first proposed in 1980 by Dr. Walter Alvarez, a geologist at the University of California at Berkeley. He and his colleagues had found unusually large amounts of the rare metal iridium in sediments laid down about the time the dinosaurs died out, at the end of the Cretaceous period. They proposed that the iridium came from a cosmic catastrophe.</p>
        <p>A weak link in the theory was the lack of a crater of the correct size and age. But then scientists identified a giant scar more than 100 miles across on the northern edge of the Yucatan Peninsula in Mexico, long buried by erosion and sedimentation. It is now the leading candidate for the impact crater.</p>
        <p>But skeptics called the crater evidence shaky and said the extinctions were probably earthly rather than extraterrestrial in origin. Dr. Charles B. Officer and Dr. Charles L. Drake of Dartmouth College found that the iridium layer was deposited over a period of up to 100,000 years and could have come from large volcanic eruptions originating deep within the Earth. Volcanoes also release chlorine, sulfur dioxide and carbon dioxide, all of which can seriously disrupt the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The dinosaur extinctions, the two scientists noted, occurred around the time that a huge eruption in what is now India created a great lava field known as the Deccan Traps.</p>
        <p>Other experts generalized on the volcanic idea, finding that 9 of the 10 greatest mass extinctions of all time -- including that of the dinosaurs -- more or less coincided with enormous floods of lava in various parts of the world.</p>
        <p>The link between the two schools of dinosaur extinction is being constructed from well-known scientific principles. For instance, geologists have long known that strong earthquakes send out shock waves that propagate through the Earth and focus at the quake's antipode. Indeed, the phenomenon has been exploited to study the Earth's deep interior.</p>
        <p>The geologic focusing is similar to what happens in a large room with a domed roof. A person whispering on one side can sometimes be heard clearly on the other as sound waves bounce off the curve and are focused. So too, shock waves that radiate outward through the Earth are reflected from the crust and bent by materials of differing density that make up the planet's mantle and core.</p>
        <p>Celestial evidence has also come into play. Starting in the early 1970's, astronomers began to identify areas on the Moon, Mercury, and icy satellites where impact craters were antipodal to volcanoes and unusual patches of broken crust.</p>
        <p>Taken with such evidence, Dr. Hagstrum of Geological Survey and a colleague, Dr. Brent D. Turrin, in 1991 published a outline of the antipodal extinction idea, suggesting that giant bombardments over the eons had touched off heavy volcanic flows, with the linked upheavals combining to cause mass extinctions. But evidence was hard to assemble. Weathering of the Earth's surface over the ages tended to rub out craters, and the constant rearrangement of land masses and ocean beds by the action of plate tectonics made it difficult to ascertain with confidence the exact positions of lava flows and known craters over many millions of years.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hagstrum theorized that 65 million years ago, during the great dying off of the dinosaurs, the Deccan Traps of India were antipodal not to the Yucatan Peninsula where the great crater lies but to a spot in what is now the eastern Pacific Ocean. And the seabed there, he wrote, bears some evidence of a major impact.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, some experts suggested, two or more celestial objects hit the Earth simultaneously.</p>
        <p>The theorizing was joined in 1992 by Dr. Michael R. Rampino, an earth scientist at New York University, and Dr. Ken Caldeira, a geologist at Pennsylvania State University. In a paper, they concluded that hot spots within the Earth that are responsible for enormous lava floods tend to occur in antipodal pairs, suggesting that they might have been triggered by cosmic bombardments.</p>
        <p>The most recent work has been done by the Sandia group, which in addition to Dr. Boslough includes Dr. Eric P. Chael, Dr. T. G. Turcano and Dr. David A. Crawford. In October, they presented a paper on their simulation work at a scientific symposium in Santa Fe, N.M.</p>
        <p>A six-mile-wide asteroid hitting the Earth at a speed of 45,000 miles per hour, they said, would have dug out a colossal crater that a few seconds after impact, would have measured more than 15 miles deep. Top pressures generated by the impacting asteroid would have been about six million times greater than the force exerted by the Earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>It would have taken about 80 minutes for the shock waves rippling through the Earth from this catastrophe to travel by various routes to the antipode, where they would have converged in a series of catastrophic waves that shook the upper 100 miles or so of the Earth's crust, creating a pipeline of destruction from the depths to the surface.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Boslough said the team had yet to do the computer simulations of how much of the mechanical energy of the gargantuan waves would have been turned into heat and melting of rocks, possibly triggering large-scale volcanism. But he said the antipodal stimulus appeared to be enough to trigger major upheavals.</p>
        <p>The heat calculations, he said, might take another year and required the use of supercomputers at Sandia, which is an arm of the Department of Energy. Until then, he said, caution was the watchword.</p>
        <p>"It's hard not to like the theory, but you don't want to get carried away," he said. "You have to do the rigorous modeling and you have to believe what the modeling says." He also said a wide range of field studies could be pursued to try to detect antipodal clues.</p>
        <p>Reaction to the theory generally seems to be one of interest among scientific generalists, although die-hards of both extinction camps are said to be skeptical of almost any idea that ventures to reconcile the conflicting schools.</p>
        <p>"The more extreme members of the volcanism crowd are not very open to anything from outside of the Earth," said Dr. Clark R. Chapman, a senior scientist at the Planetary Science Institute in Tucson, Ariz., and a backer of the impact hypothesis. "An open-minded person would just wait to see how the evidence plays out. To me, it's a very intriguing possibility."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
