<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Pests? To a Nematode, They're Lunch.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEMATODES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE4DF1539F93BA35756C0A962958260" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Pests? To a Nematode, They're Lunch.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO you have grubs in your lawn? Black vine weevils eating holes in the rhododendron leaves? Cutworms felling those little cabbage plants like trees?</p>
        <p>Before reaching for a toxic pesticide like diazinon, you might want to try beneficial nematodes, tiny parasitic roundworms that can be stirred up with water and sprinkled or sprayed on the lawn or garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO you have grubs in your lawn? Black vine weevils eating holes in the rhododendron leaves? Cutworms felling those little cabbage plants like trees?</p>
        <p>Before reaching for a toxic pesticide like diazinon, you might want to try beneficial nematodes, tiny parasitic roundworms that can be stirred up with water and sprinkled or sprayed on the lawn or garden.</p>
        <p>And don't be surprised if you can hardly see them.</p>
        <p>"If you have some in a glass, they look like specks of dust swimming around," said Michael Villani, a soil insect ecologist at Cornell University's Agriculture Experiment Station in Geneva, N.Y. "You could have a million in an eight-ounce glass, and the water will just look cloudy."</p>
        <p>These good nematodes can kill a grub within 48 hours and, when applied correctly, prove highly effective against many other garden pests. And don't confuse them with the bad guys, like the root-knot nematodes that attack about 1,300 species of plants, from beans to peonies.</p>
        <p>Beneficial nematodes are safe to use and do not harm earthworms, but you have to get to know them a little if you want them to work.</p>
        <p>To begin with, there are two different kinds of beneficial nematodes, so it's crucial to choose the right one.</p>
        <p>"Some species, like Steinernema carpocapsae, tend to stay closer to the surface of the soil," said Dr. Harry Kaya, a nematologist at the University of California at Davis. "We call these the ambushers, the wait-and-see strategists. They're like those hunters that wait in trees with a bow and arrow. And they're good for mobile insects like caterpillars and cutworms."</p>
        <p>They also ambush sod webworms and billbugs, because these lawn pests travel close to the ground surface.</p>
        <p>But Steinernema isn't too effective against a Japanese beetle grub, which is as much of a couch potato as Steinernema is. A more active type of organism, Heterorhabditis bacteriophora, is the insect for killing grubs.</p>
        <p>"It's a searcher, a cruiser," said Prof. Randy Gaugler, an invertebrate pathologist at Rutgers University. "It's highly mobile and very good for these sedentary types."</p>
        <p>The worms are now being used to control everything from mole crickets on golf courses to fleas in backyards to citrus root weevils in Florida orchards. They also kill iris borers, cabbage root maggots and strawberry root weevils.</p>
        <p>"And they're safe: you could bathe in them," Professor Gaugler said. "I've eaten them before, accidentally, by sucking a little too hard on my pipette when I'm getting them into the petri dish."</p>
        <p>For the gardener, they are a viable alternative pest-control method. Most companies sell them on a sponge or in some type of paste, which must then be mixed with water.</p>
        <p>Gardens Alive, a mail-order organic products company in Lawrenceburg, Ind. -- telephone, (812) 537-8650 -- recommends using 10 million Heterorhabditis bacteriophora nematodes per 600 square feet, at a cost of $18.95.</p>
        <p>It also sells a $2.45 garden syringe for injecting nematodes into plant stems to control squash vine borers and corn earworms.</p>
        <p>Many garden centers also now offer nematodes, as do organic lawn services. "I've used them since 1990 and they're pretty effective," said Michael Warren Thomas, who owns Naturally Green Inc. in Rochester.  "I've used them against grubs, black vine weevils, cutworms and squash borers."</p>
        <p>There are a few important rules to follow in the nematode game, if you want them to work.</p>
        <p>First of all, the lawn or soil must be moist. So apply them with a sprayer or watering can after a light rain, or sprinkle the lawn first. But don't put them down on a lawn so wet that it has puddles.</p>
        <p>"Nematodes evolved from an aquatic environment, so they do require a certain amount of moisture," Dr. Kaya said. "But if there's too much standing water, they'll lack oxygen and die."</p>
        <p>Nematodes are also very sensitive to ultraviolet light, so put them down in the evening.</p>
        <p>They also don't like it too cold -- or too hot. "Most nematodes don't work well when soil temperatures are below 60 degrees," Dr. Villani said. "But it can get too hot for them, too. So don't put them down on bone-dry soil that's 95 degrees. They get fried."</p>
        <p>If the lawn is moist, the nematodes will move along the film of water, down into the roots of the grass blades and then, depending on what type they are, either wait around for an unfortunate pest to stumble by or go in search of one.</p>
        <p>"There's a lot of research being done on how they find the insects," Dr. Villani said. "They may cue into the carbon dioxide or the other waste products the grubs give off."</p>
        <p>When a nematode locates a grub, it moves in through the insect's mouth, anus or spiracles (little breathing holes on its sides). Once inside, the nematode injects lethal bacteria that kill the grub within 48 hours. Several nematodes may enter at once, which is a good idea for their reproductive purposes, since they begin feeding on the grub and multiplying for several generations before their nutrition runs out.</p>
        <p>"Then the grub sort of disintegrates, and a big cloud of new nematodes is released into the soil," Dr. Villani said. In the ideal world, of the petri dish, that is.</p>
        <p>"It's a dog-eat-dog world down there in the soil," Dr. Kaya said, "with lots of things that eat nematodes, like mites and springtails, and fungi that parasitize them."</p>
        <p>The grub, of course, has its own protective mechanisms, he added. "They tend to get agitated, to prevent the nematodes from getting inside," he said. "Or they'll defecate them out. Or their blood cells will encapsulate them."</p>
        <p>So the more nematodes, the merrier, so to speak. Though the grub wouldn't see it that way.</p>
        <p>It's also crucial to have healthy nematodes. "The biggest cause of failure is getting poor nematodes from the supplier," Dr. Villani said.</p>
        <p>He suggests a little home experiment. When your nematodes arrive, dig up a few grubs from the lawn. (And by the way, nematodes like white grubs as much as Japanese beetle grubs.) Put one each in two paper cups; then, add a little plug of soil and grass. Sprinkle in a little water and a few nematodes mixed in solution. Keep the cups moist and wait a week.</p>
        <p>"If those grubs aren't dead in a week's time, chances are you don't have healthy nematodes," Dr. Villani said.</p>
        <p>But keep trying. "When they work, they work spectacularly," he said. He calls them, affectionately, "guided missiles."  CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
