<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Embarks on High-Tech Scrutiny of Environment</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="679667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDEAVOR (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFDD153EF933A25757C0A962958260" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Embarks on High-Tech Scrutiny of Environment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six astronauts set out today on a space shuttle mission to test an advanced radar technology that may enable people to manage the environment better in the future -- and perhaps catch some tantalizing glimpses of life in the past.</p>
        <p>The shuttle Endeavour, carrying a $366 million Space Radar Laboratory in its cargo bay, rocketed into orbit at 7:05 A.M. Eastern daylight time, as the sun rose over the Atlantic. The liftoff into a clear blue sky came after a one-day delay caused by high winds. Operations aboard were normal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six astronauts set out today on a space shuttle mission to test an advanced radar technology that may enable people to manage the environment better in the future -- and perhaps catch some tantalizing glimpses of life in the past.</p>
        <p>The shuttle Endeavour, carrying a $366 million Space Radar Laboratory in its cargo bay, rocketed into orbit at 7:05 A.M. Eastern daylight time, as the sun rose over the Atlantic. The liftoff into a clear blue sky came after a one-day delay caused by high winds. Operations aboard were normal.</p>
        <p>On the nine-day flight, the astronauts plan to put the Endeavour through 460 maneuvers, more than on any previous mission, to point the shuttle's picture-making radar at a wide variety of landscapes and seascapes. Scientists want to see how well the technology can map different terrains and distinguish between natural and human-induced environmental changes taking place on Earth.</p>
        <p>Several hours after liftoff, an amplifier for one of two radar instruments aboard Endeavour failed, and researchers missed a viewing opportunity, The Associated Press reported tonight. Ground controllers later managed to start it. Meanwhile the other radar took its first images over the Upper Peninsula of Michigan.</p>
        <p>The mission's primary radar targets include mountains in Europe and South America, ocean currents and wetlands, forests, farmland and deserts. By penetrating the dry sands, the radar may also be able to chart the course of the Nile River in antiquity, survey a buried "lost city" on the Arabian Peninsula and discover centuries-old ruins along the Silk Road in western China. Exploring the Inaccessible</p>
        <p>Dr. Diane L. Evans, a geologist and the project's chief scientist at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., said radar was the only way scientists can easily explore many inaccessible regions. The new system should give them a detailed "look at the planet in a way that's never before been possible," she said.</p>
        <p>On the ground, international teams of scientists and graduate students are in position to make simultaneous measurements of vegetation, soil moisture, snow, water and weather conditions at 19 primary radar sites. A comparison of their findings with the radar data will be made to assess the radar's capabilities and guide scientists in interpretation.</p>
        <p>The 23,000-pound radar laboratory, with instruments developed by the United States, Germany and Italy, is scheduled to be flown again in August to survey the same sites in a different season. Results of the two tests will be studied by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration to determine the value of adapting the technology for unpiloted satellites making long-term radar observations of the entire world.</p>
        <p>No such mission has been authorized, but it could be part of the agency's Mission to Planet Earth, a program of remote-sensing space flights expected to begin in 1998 to monitor the environment. 'Most Sophisticated Radar'</p>
        <p>"This is the most sophisticated radar the world has seen in space flight," said Dr. Miriam Baltuck, NASA's chief scientist for the radar program.</p>
        <p>Although several military and civilian space missions have used radar, NASA scientists said, this is the first system capable of making simultaneous observations at three wavelengths to produce sharper, three-dimensional images and to "see" through obstacles like foliage, snow and sand. Previous spacecraft radars operated at a single wavelength, usually the 6-centimeter wavelength known as C-band. This system has instruments for the shorter X-band (3 centimeter wavelength) and longer (23 centimeter) L-band, as well.</p>
        <p>Radar operates by transmitting pulses of microwave energy toward a target and receiving signals that are reflected back. The returning signals can be read in ways that show the shape and nature of the surface. The most obvious advantage of imaging radar over regular photography is its ability to collect data over virtually any region at any time, day or night, in sunshine or clouds.</p>
        <p>Scientists, comparing the improved capabilities of multiple-frequency radar to previous imaging radars, likened the difference to that between photographing the human body in X-ray and in ordinary light. Seeing Beneath Treetops</p>
        <p>The combination of three radar frequencies, for example, interacts with vegetation at different scales, providing more detailed imaging of forests and seeing beneath treetops to the ground. It is expected to produce measurements of the volume of vegetation and soil moisture. The L-band is particularly effective at penetrating the ground. Data produced by different wavelengths can provide estimates of the amount of snow covering the ground and even the moisture content of that snow.</p>
        <p>The German and Italian space agencies developed the instruments for the X-band radar. The Jet Propulsion Laboratory developed the American instruments for observing at the other wavelengths.</p>
        <p>The combined instruments are expected to survey more than 18 million square miles of Earth's surface over 50 hours of planned operations. More than 400 targets on land and in the oceans have been identified, but the focus is to be on 19 places, or "supersites." These were chosen to represent different environments and objectives for geology, hydrology, oceanography, biology and ecology.</p>
        <p>Supersites in the United States are forests in Michigan and North Carolina, waterways in Oklahoma and the arid wasteland of Death Valley, Calif. Others are in Central Europe, Egypt, Australia, the Amazon and Andes of South America and the volcanic geology of the Galapagos Islands, off Ecuador. More than 50 scientists from 13 countries are directing research projects using the data.</p>
        <p>Although NASA emphasizes the radar's potential for environmental studies, archeologists have been eagerly awaiting the mission ever since a simpler radar system was flown on two early shuttle missions. On one flight, the radar signals penetrated as deep as six feet under the Sahara and revealed the traces of ancient tributaries of the Nile and possible sites of early civilizations. Images from another flight revealed the tracks of camel caravan routes in the Arabian desert, which helped archeologists discover in Oman what they think is the lost city of Ubar, once a rich emporium in the frankincense trade.</p>
        <p>Dr. Evans said a mosaic of radar images of Egypt should reveal the buried outlines of ancient rivers, including what scientists call the proto-Nile. Such data could provide insights into the climate changes over thousands of years. Other objectives, she said, included a more detailed look at Ubar and its surroundings and a search for buried ruins of caravan outposts near Hotan, China, where the Silk Road used to run through Taklamakan Desert. The region is primarily being studied for its potential mineral resources and for indications of past climate change.</p>
        <p>"We really do think we will do imaging that will be very interesting for archeologists," Dr. Evans said.</p>
        <p>Altogether, the radar tests should yield 32 trillion bits of data, or the equivalent of 20,000 encyclopedia volumes. A few images are to be processed and made public during the flight, but most of the results are not expected to be available for five months.</p>
        <p>The astronauts on this mission are Col. Sidney M. Gutierrez, Col. Kevin P. Chilton and Lieut. Col. Michael R. Clifford, all of the Air Force; Dr. Linda M. Godwin and Dr. Jay Apt, physicists, and Dr. Thomas D. Jones, a planetary scientist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
