<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ultraviolet Studies May Revise Understanding of Food Chain</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="697663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALGAE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ULTRAVIOLET LIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILCHEY, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DA1E3CF936A35754C0A962958260" item-length="850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ultraviolet Studies May Revise Understanding of Food Chain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM HILCHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILCHEY, TIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a development that may change the way scientists think about the food chain, Canadian researchers have found that ultraviolet light, which in the short term is known to inhibit the growth rate of algae, may in the long term encourage it. Although the radiation is harmful to the algae, it is also harmful to the organisms that feed on them, curbing their population over a period of time and allowing the algae to rebound.</p>
        <p>In experiments conducted over four summers beginning in 1990, Dr. Max L. Bothwell, a research scientist with Environment Canada, the Government's environmental agency, found that more algae accumulated in artificial stream beds exposed to ultraviolet radiation than in stream beds protected from the rays.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a development that may change the way scientists think about the food chain, Canadian researchers have found that ultraviolet light, which in the short term is known to inhibit the growth rate of algae, may in the long term encourage it. Although the radiation is harmful to the algae, it is also harmful to the organisms that feed on them, curbing their population over a period of time and allowing the algae to rebound.</p>
        <p>In experiments conducted over four summers beginning in 1990, Dr. Max L. Bothwell, a research scientist with Environment Canada, the Government's environmental agency, found that more algae accumulated in artificial stream beds exposed to ultraviolet radiation than in stream beds protected from the rays.</p>
        <p>"The majority of research on the impact of ultraviolet radiation has largely focused on the deleterious effects of ultraviolet-B radiation on algae," Dr. Bothwell said. "Many people have shown that in the short term UV-B is harmful to algae and that it reduces their growth and photosynthetic rates."</p>
        <p>The first time he saw this result, Dr. Bothwell said, was in 1990. It was an unexpected finding. "The paradox that we were faced with in 1990," he said, "was that in long-term experiments you can actually end up with more algae in the presence of UV light than in its absence." Effects on Midge Larvae</p>
        <p>Over the next three summers, Dr. Bothwell and Darren M. J. Sherbot and Colleen M. Pollock, two students working with him at the National Hydrology Research Institute in Saskatoon, systematically reproduced his original results.</p>
        <p>Their experiments also showed that the midge larvae that eat the algae also appear to be sensitive to UV-B, the most biologically damaging form of ultraviolet light. After about three weeks, Dr. Bothwell said, the reduced grazing pressure from fewer larvae allowed the algae population to rebound. The results of their study are reported in the current issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>"What we have done so far is simply identify a mechanism by which UV-B could exert a larger impact on aquatic ecosystems," Dr. Bothwell said. "What we don't know, because this was all done experimentally, is whether this is actually happening in nature."</p>
        <p>Both types of ultraviolet light that reach the earth's surface, UV-A (wavelengths of 320 to 400 nanometers) and UV-B (280 to 320 nanometers), have been shown to reduce growth rates of algae.</p>
        <p>The effects the researchers have identified are not associated with ozone depletion, but rather are "fundamental effects of ultraviolet radiation." Nevertheless, Dr. Bothwell said, the findings go to the heart of the ongoing ozone debate. Because ozone in the stratosphere acts as a giant global sunscreen by selectively absorbing UV-B radiation, scientists fear that the thinning of the ozone layer may lead to major UV-B-related changes in the earth's ecosystems. Further Tests Planned</p>
        <p>This summer, Dr. Bothwell said, he plans to conduct testing in natural stream beds "to see if we can identify whether these deleterious effects of UV-B are actually occurring in real rivers."</p>
        <p>He said a second goal would be to develop an experimental data set that would allow researchers to "determine roughly how much the deleterious effects of UV-B, in terms of its impact on midges, for example, would increase with a given percentage increase in UV-B radiation associated with global ozone depletion."</p>
        <p>Dr. Bothwell's findings are serendipitous as well as momentous. In 1990, while awaiting the completion of other experiments, he decided to extend a two-week algae-growth study on the South Thompson River in British Columbia in which he had confirmed the short-term growth-inhibiting effects of ultraviolet light.</p>
        <p>For several more weeks he allowed river water to continue flowing through centimeter-deep Styrofoam troughs that were variously exposed to full-spectrum sunlight or were shielded from UV-B or both UV-A and UV-B light. Solar intensity was also varied, with some troughs receiving 90 percent of ambient solar intensity while others received only 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Weeks later, Dr. Bothwell discovered that algae were more plentiful in the troughs that had been exposed to full-spectrum light than the ones shielded against ultraviolet light. He also found that while the 50 percent reduction in solar intensity appeared to eliminate the inhibitory effects of ultraviolet light on algal growth rates, midge larvae continued to be affected. Possible Unexpected Harm</p>
        <p>Dr. Bothwell said this indicated that exposure to UV-B radiation might be harming some parts of an ecosystem, even though the microscopic plants at the bottom of the food chain seemed healthy.</p>
        <p>If the organisms along the food chain respond differently to ultraviolet radiation, he said, then researchers who rely on short-term measurements of the effects of UV-B on algae -- the most common type of study -- also found that while the 50 percent rduction in solar intensity appeared to eliminate the inhibitory effects of ultraviolet light on algal growth rates, midge larvae continued to be affected.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
