<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; For the Environment, Compassion Fatigue</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="723478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5DF123EF935A35752C1A962958260" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; For the Environment, Compassion Fatigue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE 1990's could hardly have begun better for the national environmental movement. A new Clean Air Act to clear the skies of toxic chemicals became law. Polls indicated that Americans overwhelmingly supported tough environmental rules and said they would pay more for them. Democrats elected a new team to the White House, in part because the Vice President was sympathetic to ecological concerns and wrote a best-selling book on the subject.</p>
        <p>But midway through, the decade is shaping up as a period of turmoil for the environmental movement. Membership and budgets have dropped for most of the national groups. A well-organized counter-movement of landowners, city officials and industrial executives steamed into Washington and halted Congressional work this year on strengthening environmental laws. They argued that environmentalists were exaggerating and using inconclusive data to frighten people and influence lawmakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE 1990's could hardly have begun better for the national environmental movement. A new Clean Air Act to clear the skies of toxic chemicals became law. Polls indicated that Americans overwhelmingly supported tough environmental rules and said they would pay more for them. Democrats elected a new team to the White House, in part because the Vice President was sympathetic to ecological concerns and wrote a best-selling book on the subject.</p>
        <p>But midway through, the decade is shaping up as a period of turmoil for the environmental movement. Membership and budgets have dropped for most of the national groups. A well-organized counter-movement of landowners, city officials and industrial executives steamed into Washington and halted Congressional work this year on strengthening environmental laws. They argued that environmentalists were exaggerating and using inconclusive data to frighten people and influence lawmakers.</p>
        <p>Those criticisms, and its own frustration, have brought the movement to a state of self-doubt it never faced before.  The Problem With Congress</p>
        <p>In Washington, environmental leaders blamed poisonous partisanship for what Blakeman Early, a Sierra Club lobbyist, called "the worst environmental Congress in two decades." Another Capitol Hill veteran, Representative Mike Synar, Democrat of Oklahoma, who was one of the strongest environmental voices in Congress for eight terms, was defeated in the primary in part because of his steadfast support for tougher rules on a range of environmental issues.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Synar said something more basic than politics and legislative strategy is at work, and that is the environmental movement's message that every problem is a crisis, an emergency worthy of public alarm. "If I could give the environmental community one piece of advice, it is to do outreach to people who have not traditionally been part of their movement," he said. "They need to establish relationships with cities, with rural water districts, with county commissioners. They are not going to be able to do what they want by sowing fear."</p>
        <p>Since Earth Day in 1970, environmentalists have built a movement and achieved legislative and judicial successes by showing that industrial development produced polluted water and air, nuclear radiation, abandoned toxic waste dumps, destruction of forests, loss of species and erosion of farmland.</p>
        <p>By the 1990's, though, a web of statutes written in part and advocated by environmental groups had sharply reduced air and water pollution and alleviated other problems. The vocabulary of devastation was applied to new issues -- electromagnetic radiation, genetic engineering, global warming and overpopulation -- that were said to be even more threatening.</p>
        <p>The language of emergency that suffused debate about the environment has become institutionalized in large part because it was effective in reaching the public and Congress. But now some observers are noting psychological and political problems with the message itself.</p>
        <p>"I agree with the urgency of the issues, but my judgment is that the environmental movement got grounded in a one-dimensional psychology," said Theodore Roszak, a history professor at California State University in Hayward and author of "The Voice of the Earth -- An Exploration of Ecopsychology" (Simon &amp; Schuster, 1992). "The movement wants a lot of change very rapidly and tries to get this by scaring people and shaming people. It's bad psychology. People resent being talked to that way, and if you continue to talk that way without helping them understand and make the changes, they stop listening. That's what is happening. My concern is that they need a better way to talk to the public."</p>
        <p>Martin W. Lewis, who teaches environmental conservation at the University of Wisconsin, reached a similar conclusion in "Green Delusions -- An Environmentalist Critique of Radical Environmentalism" (Duke, 1992). He said that mainstream environmental organizations were adopting some of the tactics of groups like Earth First! and that the entire movement was coming to be perceived by the public as hostile to capitalism, new technology, industry, even modern civilization itself.</p>
        <p>"Radical environmentalism is dismissive of modern life, but it seemed to be growing more prominent and risked discrediting the mainstream environmental movement," said Professor Lewis. "Any philosophy that says economic growth must end, that technology needs to be dismantled, and that we must turn away from science -- most people find that threatening."</p>
        <p>Jim Maddy, president of League of Conservation Voters in Washington, said most groups did not adopt a radical position. He also said that environmental leaders have by no means accepted the premise that they are exaggerating problems. "I don't see any evidence of that in the polling that we are doing," he said. "The public believes we are telling the truth."</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddy added that national environmental leaders were very concerned about their legislative failure in Congress and its causes. One problem, he said, may be how the movement is talking about itself and its work. In a departure, Mr. Maddy said, leaders are starting to tout their accomplishments. Until recently, environmentalists were reluctant to do so because they thought it would lull the public into thinking the problems had been solved.</p>
        <p>In addition, it's not startling that public alarm would wane in an Administration that is sympathetic to environmental concerns. No Satisfaction</p>
        <p>"It's inherent in advocacy organizations," said Mr. Maddy. "If you are in the business of advocating progress in this relatively broad range of issues, you are not in the business of being satisfied. At the same time, we are not in the business of being blind to progress."</p>
        <p>Other environmental leaders are watching the Environmental Defense Fund, one of the few national groups whose membership and budget is growing.</p>
        <p>The New York-based organization has been working with large corporations to develop business practices that reduce waste and lower costs. In the group's newest project, several of the country's largest buyers of paper, including Time-Warner, McDonald's and Johnson &amp; Johnson, are working with the group to develop purchasing standards that improve forestry practices, reduce pollution in manufacturing and encourage recycling of finished paper products.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Defense Fund periodically comes under fire from colleagues who view its ties to industry as too close. Fred Krupp, the organization's executive director, said his goal was not to attack big business but to "get environmental results."</p>
        <p>"Being willing to consider new ways to regulate and being willing to talk with business in a businesslike way is not the same as being in favor of halfway compromises," Mr. Krupp said. "We are experimenting with new approaches and as those approaches get results, more people are using them."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
