<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EASTERN UTILITIES IN UNUSUAL PACT: A SMOG TRADEOFF</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="674692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC SERVICE ELECTRIC &amp; GAS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E1DA113DF935A25750C0A962958260" item-length="1043" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EASTERN UTILITIES IN UNUSUAL PACT: A SMOG TRADEOFF</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first deal of its kind across state lines, a New Jersey utility will clean up its generating stations so boilers in Connecticut can emit more smog-producing chemicals.</p>
        <p>The deal will bring a small reduction in pollution regionwide and probably will cut smog in New York and New Jersey, but that is not the main goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first deal of its kind across state lines, a New Jersey utility will clean up its generating stations so boilers in Connecticut can emit more smog-producing chemicals.</p>
        <p>The deal will bring a small reduction in pollution regionwide and probably will cut smog in New York and New Jersey, but that is not the main goal.</p>
        <p>It will change where the pollutants are emitted and at what time of year, reducing the damage, and it will help companies meet the reductions required by the Clean Air Act of 1990 at the lowest possible cost, proponents say.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act authorized what amounts to a free market in pollution.  It encouraged businesses to reduce their emissions more than the law required by giving them the right to sell their surplus savings -- in effect, rights to pollute -- to companies that found it cheaper to buy the rights than to cut their emissions themselves.  Trades for Sulfur Dioxide</p>
        <p>Similar trades have been made with sulfur dioxide, the chemical that causes acid rain, drawing criticism from environmentalists. But trades in smog-producing nitrogen oxides are not expected to attract such criticisms, in part because the deals must be approved by environmental officials in the states where the extra pollutants will be emitted.</p>
        <p>In fact, a New Jersey utility is able to sell pollution rights to a Connecticut company because Connecticut is downwind of it. Fewer emissions in New Jersey benefit both New Jersey and New York without creating more smog in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>The New Jersey utility, Public Service Electric and Gas, said today that it would cut its emissions of nitrogen oxides during the next five years by 2,400 more tons than the law requires, probably by adjusting a coal-fired plant in Jersey City, among other steps.</p>
        <p>Northeast Utilities, which serves most of Connecticut and parts of Massachusetts and New Hampshire, will buy the rights to emit 500 of those tons, and pass them along to customers, like small factories or hospitals that operate boilers, that would find it extremely costly to comply with the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Both utilities called the sale an experiment, intended to create a market in which the rights to emit hundreds of thousands of tons will be traded every year.</p>
        <p>"It's a toe in the water, a kick at the tires," said Eric B. Svenson, manager of regulatory support at Public Service Electric and Gas, based in Newark. The purpose, he said, is to encourage other potential buyers and sellers to come forward, "to encourage people to make reductions where it is most cost-effective to do so."</p>
        <p>Trading in pollution credits, which is favored by economists and some environmentalists, seeks to achieve emissions reductions at the minimum cost by allowing the cleanup to be made wherever it is cheapest.</p>
        <p>For example, to reduce nitrogen oxides by one ton it might be cheaper to have a utility switch a generating station from coal to natural gas than to have a university install a scrubbing system on a small boiler used to provide steam heat on campus. The utility estimates it can create the reduction for $1,000 a ton, and the university can buy it, avoiding its own cost, which could be hundreds of dollars a ton higher.</p>
        <p>An auto body shop, which might have to build a painting booth to control emissions from wet paint, might face a cost of $15,000 or $20,000 to cut a ton of smog-producing chemicals, experts said.</p>
        <p>The price for pollution credits, advocates hope, will be determined by trading among hundreds of buyers and sellers. A Pollution Broker</p>
        <p>In this case, the pollution credits will be bought by a broker, the Clean Air Action Corporation of Tulsa, Okla., at cost. Clean Air Action will sell them at market price. The allowances Northeast Utilities is buying will be priced at whatever the market price eventually turns out to be.</p>
        <p>Ben G. Henneke, president of Clean Air Action, said his company would retire 10 percent of the credits, so total nitrogen oxide output would be 140 tons lower over five years. In addition, he said, Clean Air Action will pay Public Service Electric and Gas to create the allowances in summer, when smog is a problem. But buyers would use them all year long. So some pollution would be shifted into winter, when smog is not an issue.</p>
        <p>Since smog drifts across state lines, some states can achieve clean air only if upwind neighbors clean up. Mr. Henneke said that the only way states like Connecticut and Massachusetts could meet the standards, without "invading New Jersey or Pennsylvania," would be to approve deals like this with upwind states. Directional Correctness</p>
        <p>Unlike trading in the right to emit chemicals that cause acid rain, the nitrogen-oxide trades are supposed to be "directionally correct." That means that the sellers must generally be upwind of the buyers. The effect of the trades, then, is to have the pollutants emitted further downwind, with fewer people to be exposed to ozone before it blows out to sea.</p>
        <p>Officials not directly involved in the trade praised it. Langdon Marsh, Acting Commissioner of Environmental Conservation in New York, said that if companies in Connecticut bought 500 tons from New Jersey, that was 500 tons that did not blow over New York. Pointing to the interstate nature of smog, he noted that one of the monitoring stations that the Federal Environmental Protection Agency uses to determine New York's compliance is in Stratford, Conn. A Regional Market</p>
        <p>At the Northeast States for Coordinated Air Use Management, an organization of top air pollution officials from New England, New York and New Jersey, Michael Bradley, the executive director, said, "It could be a catalyst to a regional market that would help quite substantially in reducing the ozone levels in the summertime."</p>
        <p>Finding a way for the small companies to comply at low cost is essential, said William L. Stillinger, Northeast Utilities' director of technology and transmission planning, "if we're going to try to avoid businesses' shutting down and moving out of area."</p>
        <p>The agreement in the announcement is simply a memorandum of understanding, partly because neither New Jersey nor Connecticut has completed writing the regulations under which such trades could take place.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
