<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; A study says global warming may help U.S. agriculture.</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MENDELSOHN, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORDHAUS, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAW, DAIGEE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D81138F93BA3575AC0A962958260" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; A study says global warming may help U.S. agriculture.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>REMEMBER global warming? For the policy wonks, that was yesterday's worry; they have moved on to nuclear proliferation, ethnic slaughter and the reliability of DNA tests in identifying O. J. Simpson's blood.</p>
        <p>But the near-consensus that civilization is playing high-stakes games with Mother Nature has not changed since the 1992 Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro. Nor has Washington's belated commitment to reduce the emissions of so-called greenhouse gases, mostly carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels, to 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>REMEMBER global warming? For the policy wonks, that was yesterday's worry; they have moved on to nuclear proliferation, ethnic slaughter and the reliability of DNA tests in identifying O. J. Simpson's blood.</p>
        <p>But the near-consensus that civilization is playing high-stakes games with Mother Nature has not changed since the 1992 Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro. Nor has Washington's belated commitment to reduce the emissions of so-called greenhouse gases, mostly carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels, to 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Yet the results of the newest and, probably, the most careful analysis of the effects of climatic warming suggest that the fear of greenhouse gases decimating American agriculture may no longer be well founded. The study concludes that on balance, global warming will likely benefit American agriculture. And, if that is the case, finding the political support for paying to combat global warming may not be easy.</p>
        <p>Greenhouse gases -- gases that trap solar heat -- lead to higher average temperatures and, on average, more rain because of increased evaporation from the oceans. And while the infant science of climate change will no doubt come up with some surprises, it does look as if the planet is heading for hotter times with radically altered patterns of rainfall.</p>
        <p>Some places, including good chunks of Canada and Russia where growing seasons are perilously short, would undoubtedly find the change refreshing. But the handful of detailed economic studies done in the last several years suggested that American farmers would come out as big losers.</p>
        <p>Some studies suggested that a doubling of atmospheric carbon would generate enough temperature change and rain at the wrong time to cause American crop losses on the order of $20 billion annually. "The specter of global warming calls up the vistas of corn blistering on the stalk," write the authors of the new contrarian analysis -- Robert Mendelsohn and William Nordhaus of Yale University and Daigee Shaw of the Institute of Economics in Taipei, Taiwan.</p>
        <p>The trio's new assessment, to be published this month in The American Economic Review, is based on heavy-duty number-crunching of climate and soil data from 3,000 counties across the United States. But the underlying economics that drives their revisionist analysis is straightforward.</p>
        <p>Earlier studies, they note, were all based on "dumb farmer" assumptions, in which the hewers and tillers, despite climate changes, kept doing whatever they had been doing. But that is not how farmers with access to technology and capital behave when production costs change. They adjust by changing seeds, fertilizers, growing techniques and even crops.</p>
        <p>It may not be possible to simulate these adjustments directly, but the three economists offer a clever alternative. They have used their data on rain, temperature, soils and the crops that grow best under differing conditions to isolate the statistical impact of weather on agricultural productivity. This has enabled them to determine not only the impact of temperature and rainfall on crop yields but also the impact of changing from one crop to another under pressure from climatic change.</p>
        <p>A uniform increase of 5 degrees Fahrenheit and a rise of 8 percent in precipitation -- the ballpark impact from a doubling of atmospheric carbon -- generate surprisingly modest changes in agricultural productivity, they found. Indeed, if the county data are weighted by the value of crops rather than just total acreage, global warming produces more winners in the United States than losers.</p>
        <p>The key to understanding what is going on here, the three economists suggest, is the fact that climate-sensitive corn and wheat crops from the Plains states rarely account for more than a fifth of the value of America's farm output. And, more importantly, global warming appears to be good for fruits, vegetables, cotton and rice, which generally do better in warmer weather and are grown so densely that irrigation can economically offset variations in rainfall.</p>
        <p>"These results do not amount to a declaration of war against tree huggers," noted Robert Hahn, an economist at the American Enterprise Institute.  Uncontrolled climate change, he said, could still make a mess of lots of places and people. It might also increase the risk of catastrophe to levels that wake everybody up: Imagine a world with once-a-century floods or hurricanes happening once or twice a year. And even where it does not reduce economic output, global warming could radically change the pace and direction of plant and wildlife evolution.</p>
        <p>But the study should serve as a warning not to assume popular support for this cause. For unlike dirty water and air that cause disease, or unrestricted hunting that decimates species that are good to eat or nice to cuddle, global warming will not automatically cause problems that unite people to fight it.</p>
        <p>"It may take some fancy political footwork," Mr. Hahn predicted, "to sustain a consensus once the costs really begin to bite."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
