<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Five Years Later: Eastern Europe, Post Communism -- A special report.; A Wall of Resentment Now Divides Germany</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="717873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EUROPE, EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LEIPZIG (GER)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINZER, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUHRER, CHRISTIAN (REV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GAUCK, JOACHIM (REV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DE143CF937A25753C1A962958260" item-length="3231" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Five Years Later: Eastern Europe, Post Communism -- A special report.; A Wall of Resentment Now Divides Germany</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KINZER, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>LEIPZIG, Germany</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the peaceful revolution against East German Communism had a birthplace, it may well have been the Nikolai Church in Leipzig, where the Rev. Christian Fuhrer organized weekly "prayers for peace" that grew into vast street demonstrations in which tens of thousands of protesters took part.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Fuhrer looks back with justifiable pride on the movement he helped lead, but like many of his neighbors he also laments some of what German unification has brought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the peaceful revolution against East German Communism had a birthplace, it may well have been the Nikolai Church in Leipzig, where the Rev. Christian Fuhrer organized weekly "prayers for peace" that grew into vast street demonstrations in which tens of thousands of protesters took part.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Fuhrer looks back with justifiable pride on the movement he helped lead, but like many of his neighbors he also laments some of what German unification has brought.</p>
        <p>"People here feel a real schizophrenia," he mused one recent morning. "No one wants to go back to the days of dictatorship, but at the same time we're not really happy with the new system.  It's full of challenges for which we were totally unprepared."</p>
        <p>"From a purely economic standpoint things are definitely better than before, although far too many of our people have lost their jobs. But even those who have jobs and have cars and take nice vacations are worried about what is happening to our society. Brutal competition and the lust for money are destroying our sense of community. Almost everyone feels a level of fear or depression or insecurity."</p>
        <p>On the eve of the second all-German election, life in the eastern part of the country is, by most objective measures, far better than it was during the Communist era. Nearly all easterners are happy that the Berlin wall is gone, that Communist rule has collapsed and that Germany has been unified. Yet many wish they had not been forced to give up job security, blanket social guarantees and other state-sponsored aspects of the lives they lived before 1989.</p>
        <p>This discontent is likely to play a role in the all-German election on Oct. 16, the second since unification.</p>
        <p>National public opinion polls continued to show Chancellor Helmut Kohl's government coalition ahead but not by much, with a total of between 48 and 50 percent of the vote (if Foreign Minister Klaus Kinkel's Free Democrats win the 5 percent required to get into Parliament), and the opposition Social Democrats and Greens with a combined 43 to 45 percent.</p>
        <p>The result could still hinge on how well the former Communists in the east, the Party of Democratic Socialism, capitalize on widespread discontent. If they manage to get into Parliament by winning a plurality in three eastern Berlin electoral districts, Mr. Kohl and his main opponent, Rudolf Scharping of the Social Democrats, could end up in a standoff and even be forced into a grand coalition, the first since 1969.</p>
        <p>What makes eastern Germany fundamentally different, however, from the rest of the formerly Communist world is that it has a wealthy patron, the Bonn Government, which is willing to spend whatever it takes to assure that the economic transformation under way here ultimately succeeds. But although success is on the horizon, the horizon still seems very far away, and for the moment many easterners are frustrated and angry.</p>
        <p>Politicians and commentators agree that Germans have not managed to tear down the "wall in our heads," to achieve the elusive goal of "inner unity."</p>
        <p>"No one on either side of the wall had any idea how far apart we had grown in 40 years," said the Mayor of Leipzig, Heinrich Lehmann-Grube, a Westerner who moved here in 1990. "Only now are we beginning to understand it. I can tell you that if West Germany had absorbed Italy or France, the problems would have been far less than they are with the absorption of East Germany."</p>
        <p>"Imagine if the United States, overnight, had to adopt the entire Chinese bureaucratic, legal, political and economic system," Mr. Lehmann-Grube suggested. "That gives you an idea of how traumatic the change has been over here."</p>
        <p>The shock of the changes that eastern Germans have had to accept is compounded by their realization that Westerners have not had to change at all. While every detail of life in the east has changed radically, nothing whatsoever has changed in the West, except that people there must pay higher taxes to support the costs of unification. In fact, if Westerners had no access to newspapers or television or radio, many would probably not even notice that unification had happened.</p>
        <p>This has led to a sense of bitterness in the east. Many easterners say that Germany was not really unified, because unification implies a blending or mixing that produces something new and different. They say that what happened in 1990 was not a unification but an anschluss, the gobbling up of one small and weak state by another that was infinitely richer and more self-confident.</p>
        <p>Travels throughout eastern Germany and conversations with scores of residents suggest that the mood here is not as negative as it is sometimes portrayed in the German press. Anger over the way unification was handled remains strong, but it is accompanied by a growing sense that slow progress is being made.</p>
        <p>Although eastern Germans resent the fact that they remain far behind their western cousins by nearly every standard, they realize that they are the envy of people in virtually every other formerly Communist country. Caught between these two impulses, they feel what the renowned German-American scholar Fritz Stern has called "exuberant pessimism." The Changes  A Transformation Produces Turmoil</p>
        <p>The economic progress that eastern Germany has made since unification is clearly visible, both in comparison with the old days and in comparison with lands farther east.</p>
        <p>"Seen from a strictly economic perspective, the great majority of eastern Germans are doing considerably better than four or five years ago," asserted Meinhard Miegel, who heads a Bonn-based economic research institute and also teaches at Leipzig University.</p>
        <p>"But many of them still think they can combine the best of two worlds. They want western levels of goods and services, but they also want the social and economic guarantees they had before. That can't work. In order to enjoy a western standard of living, they have to produce more and accept tougher competition."</p>
        <p>"They say, 'Bring us jobs.' I tell them, make jobs yourself. They say, 'That's too hard.' Of course it's hard. It's hard in one place, why should it be easier anywhere else? Easterners want to have jobs, apartments, kindergarten places and everything else served to them. Who's supposed to provide all of this? The state? To do that we would have to go back to totalitarian rule."</p>
        <p>Easterners, even the most sophisticated among them, view this problem from a somewhat different perspective. Joachim Gauck, a Lutheran clergyman who is custodian of the files left behind by the East German secret police, predicted that regardless of the level of economic progress in eastern states, it would take two generations for easterners to recover psychologically from the effects of life under repressive rule.</p>
        <p>"You have to remember that people here lived under dictatorship without interruption for almost 60 years," Mr. Gauck said.  "That experience turns people into subjects.  It destroys their sense of what it means to be a citizen, an active participant in life and society. Only a minority of the people in eastern Germany understand what it is to design and be responsible for their own future.</p>
        <p>"Germany has been a sick society," he said. "After 12 years of Nazism, the Allies arrived in West Germany, and they were the doctors who slowly cured people of their sickness by introducing democracy and free enterprise. Western Germany has recovered, and it is now healthy. Eastern Germany is not. We need time, a good deal of time, to recover from what was imposed on us for 60 years."</p>
        <p>One sign of the insecurity that has spread through eastern Germany is the spectacular drop in birth rates here. The number of children being born in the five eastern states is less than half what it was before unification. In addition, the marriage rate has fallen by an astonishing 62 percent, and sterilizations, of which there were less than 400 per year during the Communist era, now total over 6,000 annually in the state of Brandenburg alone.</p>
        <p>Taken together, specialists say, these statistics mean that eastern Germany will lose 25 percent of its population by 2010.</p>
        <p>"We are in a situation of sudden and profound change," said Rainer Munz, a demographer in Berlin. "Many people can't imagine how they will cope with the future." The Background  How Germany Grew Apart</p>
        <p>Much complaining in eastern Germany is based on the deep-rooted economic problems here. Few outsiders, including specialists in West Germany who passed themselves off as experts, had any idea of how weak the East German economy had become by the time Communism finally collapsed in 1990. It seemed relatively healthy, but economists now say that appearances were deceiving in part because East German authorities falsified many statistics and in part because many industries depended entirely on now-vanished markets in other Communist countries.</p>
        <p>The land on which East Germany sat constituted 30 percent of the divided German nation and contained 20 percent of the total German population. Yet it accounted for only 8 percent of the combined German gross national product and just 2 percent of its industrial production.</p>
        <p>Making matters worse, the East German economy was based on about two dozen giant industrial complexes -- from textiles to electric power to steel -- each of which employed thousands or tens of thousands of people. Such complexes are dinosaurs in the modern world, and the process of dismantling them has been extremely painful.</p>
        <p>The Treuhand agency, set up after unification to administer and sell off companies formerly owned by the East German state, has dramatically slashed the work force at many of these complexes and has shut others completely. In so doing, it has thrown tens of thousands of people out of work and onto welfare rolls, including many over 50 who have little hope of ever finding new jobs. As a result, it has become the most hated public agency in eastern Germany.</p>
        <p>"Never in peacetime has so much social wealth been destroyed," proclaims a leaflet used by the Democratic Socialist Party, successor to the East German Communists, in recent election campaigns. "With the goal of privatizing East German property in the shortest possible time, companies and property are being sold at far below their true value. The result is well known: de-industrialization and mass unemployment in the east."</p>
        <p>In an interview, the head of the Treuhand, Birgid Breuel, an expert in public finance, insisted that her agency has sold its properties for the best possible price, and has sought commitments from buyers to maintain as many jobs as possible.</p>
        <p>"I understand that people who took to the streets in 1989 to demonstrate for freedom and are now unemployed don't feel very positive about what has happened," Mrs. Breuel acknowledged. "They ask why unification has caused such painful shocks.  From a human standpoint, this is completely reasonable. But they are forgetting that we have to clean up the mess left behind by 40 years of backward economic policy.</p>
        <p>"I know we're not popular in the east, and of course it bothers me," she said. "We think we're helping the development of the east, laying the groundwork for its future prosperity. But people in the east are constantly criticizing us and complaining about our work. They say we're driving them to unemployment and bankruptcy. It's not pleasant, but I understand it."</p>
        <p>The unemployment rate in eastern Germany is officially put at 14.6 percent, compared with 8.8 percent in the west. It would be considerably higher if Bonn had not flooded the east with make-work projects which now employ hundreds of thousands of people.</p>
        <p>Easterners who have jobs earn an average of just 65 percent of what westerners earn for comparable work. Officials in Bonn say the difference must be maintained because businesses and public employers cannot afford to pay more, and because productivity in the east is lower than in the west. In addition, they say, if wages rise too quickly in the east, employers will be tempted not to invest here at all, preferring to set up shop in countries further east where workers can be hired for much less money.</p>
        <p>Despite these facts, the difference in wage scales for workers in eastern and western Germany is a source of great dissatisfaction in the east. Many people here take the difference as proof that westerners consider them second-class citizens. The Costs An Immense Bill That Still Rises</p>
        <p>Since German unification in 1990, the Bonn Government has poured huge amounts of money into the east, between $80 and $100 billion per year. The Government recently announced that the 7.5 percent income tax surcharge that Chancellor Helmut Kohl introduced in 1991, promising that it would last only one year, will be reinstated in 1995 and remain in effect for at least five more years.</p>
        <p>"This is an enormous sum we have to finance," said Friedrich Bohl, one of the Chancellor's top aides. "No one can say with any certainty how long we will have to bear the burden left behind by socialism."</p>
        <p>More hard currency flows into eastern Germany in the average week than some formerly Communist countries see in a year. This flow virtually guarantees that when the painful transition period finally ends, eastern Germany will be the most successful part of what was once the Communist world. It may also become one of the most modern regions in all of Europe, built almost from scratch to 21st-century standards at a cost of hundreds of billions.</p>
        <p>Most of the money which is supporting this vast reconstruction is coming from the pockets of western taxpayers, who grumble ever more loudly about the burden. When they hear easterners complaining about their problems, they often explode in disbelief. Many of them think easterners should be showering them with gratitude.</p>
        <p>Bonn's effort to promote investment in eastern Germany, which some westerners think is too expensive and many easterners consider too halfhearted, is showing results.  Chancellor Kohl recently attended ground-breaking ceremonies for two major new projects which he described as evidence that the eastern states "are becoming highly modern centers of product development, research and production."</p>
        <p>One of the new projects, a microchip factory backed by Siemens A.G. which will bring 1,200 new jobs to Dresden, was evidence that at least some important western companies are willing to invest in the region. The other, an oil refinery in Leuna which is to be the most modern in Europe when it opens in 1997, gave hope that the poisoned chemical region around Bitterfeld may not be dead after all.</p>
        <p>Few easterners have any background in private enterprise, but some have launched small companies of their own, and although many of the companies have quickly gone bankrupt, more than a few have survived and are growing. But they often face problems doing business in the west.</p>
        <p>For example, when the environmental organization Greenpeace offered a prize for development of a refrigerator that did not produce dangerous chloroflourocarbons, which erode the earth's protective ozone layer, a group of researchers in the east came up with the prize-winning design.  Western companies like Siemens at first scoffed at the design, saying the new refrigerator was too heavy and used too much energy, but they soon copied it. Now many dealers in western Germany urge customers to buy western models rather than the original prize-winner, which is made by easterners in the Saxon town of Scharfenstein.</p>
        <p>"Don't take a chance on that stuff from the east," one western dealer told a customer recently. "You're much better off buying from Siemens or Bosch. Choose a company you know and trust." The Outlook Will Healing Take Decades?</p>
        <p>Another factor inhibiting both economic growth and psychological peace in eastern Germany is the continuing battle over property rights. Under provisions of the 1990 Treaty of Unification, former owners of property in the east who were dispossessed by the Communist Government have the right not merely to seek compensation, but to reclaim their property, regardless of what has happened there in the intervening decades.</p>
        <p>In almost every city and town in eastern Germany, potential investors have been scared away by the maze of claims on prime real estate. None will take the chance of building on land which may, at some point in the future, be awarded to the descendants of some former owner.</p>
        <p>In Potsdam, most of the buildings on Helene-Lang-Strasse, potentially a prime development area, are the subject of property disputes. In the depressed industrial city of Halle, less than 15 percent of claims have been adjudicated. In Leipzig, the process of adjudication is expected to last until well into the next century. And in the town of Klein Machnow, near Berlin, more than half the homes have been claimed by former owners, so none of the current residents, many of whom have been there for decades, will spend a cent for renovation or maintenance.</p>
        <p>What makes this a psychological as well as an economic problem is that few of the claimants want to come back and live in the homes or to revitalize the factories they once owned. In fact, many claimants have never even seen the properties and do not want to see them. They are simply people from western Germany or from abroad who, upon reading about the Government's position, have dug up long-forgotten deeds left behind by parents or grandparents and filed claims.</p>
        <p>"I visit the Czech Republic quite often, and I'm struck by how much better the mood is there than it is here," said Lothar de Maiziere, who served in 1990 as East Germany's first and last non-Communist prime minister.</p>
        <p>"That shouldn't be the case, because people here are doing much better economically. I think the reason is that the Czechs designed their new system themselves, and they feel personally responsible for both its failures and successes. Here it's different.  Everything was imposed from Bonn. Even if the end result looks better on paper, people have the sense that they were not and are not masters of their own destiny. They feel that once again, things were done for them by some big brother who is supposed to know better."</p>
        <p>"Remember that Moses led his people through the desert for 40 years, and that after 20 years people began to complain," Mr. de Maiziere added. "They told Moses that life in the desert was too difficult, and that at least when they were slaves they had food and water and places to sleep. Moses' friends asked him how long he thought people would be complaining like this, and he replied, 'Until the last person born under slavery has died.' "</p>
        <p>"Our situation here is very similar, Mr. de Maiziere said. "The psychological gap between eastern and western Germany will last for at least a generation, or perhaps until the last person born under Communism passes away."  Five Years Later</p>
        <p>Further reports on Eastern Europe after communism will examine the lessons learned from the outbreak of ethnic violence that engulfed the Balkans; the struggle to improve the environment, and the uneasy relationship between Russia and its former republics and Warsaw Pact allies. Previous articles explored the successes and pitgalls of introducing capitalism to countries long accustomed to state-run economies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
