<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDB1138F93BA3575AC0A962958260" item-length="641" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>Japan and the United States are making progress on trade. The two nations' negotiators said that they were moving toward agreements to open Japan's markets in insurance and government purchasing, but that talks on getting Japan to buy more American cars and auto parts were still deadlocked.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>The huge task of desegregating Northern Ireland's economy and making opportunity more equitable can be seen at the Mackie factory in Belfast. The plant, once a bastion of Protestant employment, has sought to hire Roman Catholics. But as business leaders look to breathe new life into the economy, employment discrimination remains a deep-rooted problem.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>Japan and the United States are making progress on trade. The two nations' negotiators said that they were moving toward agreements to open Japan's markets in insurance and government purchasing, but that talks on getting Japan to buy more American cars and auto parts were still deadlocked.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>The huge task of desegregating Northern Ireland's economy and making opportunity more equitable can be seen at the Mackie factory in Belfast. The plant, once a bastion of Protestant employment, has sought to hire Roman Catholics. But as business leaders look to breathe new life into the economy, employment discrimination remains a deep-rooted problem.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>An accord with Cuba on phone service appears likely, telecommunications officials said.  [ A10. ] Companies</p>
        <p>I.B.M. will introduce a new version of its OS/2 software that will be more powerful and easier to use. The operating system has been overwhelmed by the popularity of Microsoft's Windows software. But analysts see a chance for I.B.M. to gain ground amid a delayed product introduction by Microsoft.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Equitable Life has come back remarkably since Richard H. Jenrette became chairman of the company in 1990. Its insurance business is standing on its own and expanding rapidly.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A Federal appeals court decision could pave the way for Japanese vehicle makers to re-enter the two-door sport utility market. The court ruled that the two-door Nissan Pathfinder should be subject to only a 2.5 percent tariff, not 25 percent.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A committee of outside directors will run the Dart Group to avert a showdown between Herbert H. Haft, Dart's chairman, and his son, Ronald S. Haft, its president.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A key Kidder, Peabody executive, Michael D. Madden, moved into a new post -- executive vice president in charge of global origination -- that puts him in line to become president of the beleaguered firm sometime next year.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Home Shopping Network and America Online announced plans for electronic shopping malls. Home Shopping bought the Internet Shopping Network for an undisclosed amount. America Online set up new divisions for advertising and shopping.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>UAL's chairman, Gerald Greenwald, quit Tatra, the Czech truck maker. His American management team, which arrived in 1993 amid great expectations, left under criticism from shareholders and board members, and after demands for a promised equity stake in the company.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Digital Equipment introduced a new Alpha AXP 64-bit chip, saying it was the world's fastest chip.  [ D4. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks were mixed in cautious trading ahead of tomorrow's report on producer prices. The Dow fell 12.45 points.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury prices slipped as reports of higher commodity prices and labor costs fanned investors' fears about inflation.  [ D18. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar gained against the mark after a Bundesbank official said the bank had room to cut interest rates.  [ D15. ]</p>
        <p>Wheat prices climbed, spurred by pending U.S. export sales and a drought in Australia. Sugar prices rose.  [ D15. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Global warming could benefit American agriculture, a study concludes. If that is the case, maintaining political support for expenditures to reduce emission of greenhouse gases may not be easy. Peter Passell: Economic Scene.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>Johnson &amp; Johnson's acquisition strategy is winning praise on Wall Street. Recent deals for Neutrogena and Eastman Kodak's diagnostic products line would bolster its position as the world's largest diversified health care company. Market Place.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>A less fuddy-duddy image for Canadian Club whisky is the aim of new ads with the theme "the world's favorite club." The wryly humorous campaign bears some resemblance to the long-running series of ads for Absolut vodka. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D6. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
