<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="682243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTERTAINMENT AND AMUSEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0DE1031F931A15757C0A962958260" item-length="1061" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dulcie Leimbach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEIMBACH, DULCIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This year, Earth Day (officially today) has spawned two buzzwords in New York City: cleanup and green-up. The celebration has spread from one big bash at a single location into neighborhoods, parks and even homes. (The New York City Department of Sanitation is offering to pick up hazardous household waste. Information: (212) 219-8090.) Here are some events scheduled this weekend. 'Clean-Ups and Green-Ups'</p>
        <p>Various New York City parks  Recommended for all ages  Tomorrow</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This year, Earth Day (officially today) has spawned two buzzwords in New York City: cleanup and green-up. The celebration has spread from one big bash at a single location into neighborhoods, parks and even homes. (The New York City Department of Sanitation is offering to pick up hazardous household waste. Information: (212) 219-8090.) Here are some events scheduled this weekend. 'Clean-Ups and Green-Ups'</p>
        <p>Various New York City parks  Recommended for all ages  Tomorrow</p>
        <p>Children who aren't inclined to clean up their rooms usually have little trouble picking up litter, say, in parks. (Funny how that works, but it's true.) Especially if Captain Planet is coaching them. The environmental superhero, the subject of a television show and a comic book, is to guide children through parts of Central Park in Manhattan and Prospect Park in Brooklyn, painting lampposts green, weeding and picking up trash. Anyone lucky enough to help out will receive a Captain Planet power ring.</p>
        <p>The program starts in Prospect Park at 10 A.M. at Wollman Rink (entrance at Ocean and Parkside Avenues entrance). By noon Captain Planet will be at the Dairy in Central Park (entrance at 60th Street and Fifth Avenue), where more work will be done with children. He'll swoop up to the Charles A. Dana Discovery Center (near Fifth Avenue and 110th Street) by 1 P.M., rain or shine. Information: (212) 226-7171.</p>
        <p>In Riverside Park in Manhattan, another green-up will be happening from 10 A.M. to 1 P.M. (rain date: Sunday). This project is sponsored by the Riverside Park Fund, a nonprofit environmental group, and the City Department of Parks and Recreation. Anyone can join in removing trash, raking and sweeping. There will be 13 work sites, from 74th to 150th Street, with a group leader at each. Work gloves, trash bags and tools will be provided. Information: (212) 870-3070.</p>
        <p>In Queens, cleanups and green-ups will be going on feverishly. In Elmhurst, the Clement Clarke Moore Homestead Park at 82d Street and Broadway, near 45th Avenue, is cleaned every morning year-round by neighborhood volunteers. The group of about 20 uses shovels and dustpans made from cooking-oil cans. After they work, everyone socializes or exercises. "It's a tradition back home," said Gabriel Lim, a volunteer who emigrated from South Korea. Newcomers, including children, are more than welcome to help, but beware: the group convenes at 6 A.M. Information: (718) 520-5368.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Queens, the Urban Park Rangers will discuss park histories while supervising cleanups, starting at 10 A.M., rain or shine, at MacNeil Park, Poppenhusen and 119th Avenues, College Point, and at Baisley Pond Park, Baisley Boulevard and 156th Street, Jamaica. Information: (718) 699-4204.</p>
        <p>For information on neighborhood cleanups, the Earth Day New York phone number is (212) 255-1219 for recorded information and (212) 226-7171 for additional information. 'Environmental Expo'</p>
        <p>South Street Seaport  Pier 16  South and John Streets  Lower Manhattan  (212) 686-4905  Recommended for all ages  Tomorrow and Sunday</p>
        <p>At this event, children won't be asked to pick up any trash except their own. Instead, they can visit booths promoting things like sneakers made of old tires. Remember that blow-out on the highway last year? Deja Shoes of Portland, Ore., may have turned the tire into a pair of recycled sneakers, tread and all.</p>
        <p>Other booths will show how to recycle household products and how to plant trees and seeds. A movable walk-through museum allows children to learn about global warming: videos and interactive computers simulate how it affects rain forests and the Arctic Circle.</p>
        <p>The free expo runs from 2 to 5 P.M. 'Arbor Day and Sun Day 1994'</p>
        <p>Alley Pond Environmental Center  228-06 Northern Boulevard  Douglaston, Queens  (718) 229-4000  Recommended for all ages  Tomorrow and Sunday</p>
        <p>Breezing by this small center on busy Northern Boulevard, one would never know that behind it are 618 acres teeming with woodlands, wetlands and meadows, 50 of which are for walking. The center has rolled Arbor Day and Earth Day into one weekend, with tree plantings and exhibitions on renewable energy sources.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow from 1 to 3 P.M., 20 native trees will be planted at Oakland Lake on the property. You'll see tulip, cherry, crab apple, maple, oak, willow and fruit-bearing trees like buckthorn, hackberry, serviceberry and alders. All you need to take is an arboreal spirit to make this a genuine celebration. A litter sweep throughout the park is also on the agenda.</p>
        <p>To reach Oakland Lake from Manhattan by car, take the Long Island Expressway to Clearview Expressway North; exit at Northern Boulevard; turn right onto Northern Boulevard and go 2.5 miles; turn right onto 223d Street and drive about a block.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, visitors can revel in renewable energy: solar, wind, hydroelectric and others. A Con Edison bus, outfitted with exhibitions, offers information on lighting, appliances and air conditioning. Children can learn that compact fluorescent bulbs use much less energy than incandescent bulbs, for example, or how to figure out what type of air-conditioner is best for the size of their bedroom.</p>
        <p>There will be tours of Alley Pond's working windmill-water pump and a solar-power exhibition set up by Sun Solar Products, a solar-heating systems manufacturer in Bohemia, L.I. The programs are from noon to 5 P.M.; a $1 donation is suggested. Alley Pond can be reached by the Q12 bus from the No. 7 subway station at Main Street, Flushing. 'My Tree Has a Way of Speaking'</p>
        <p>Charles A. Dana Discovery Center  110th Street and Fifth Avenue  Manhattan  (212) 860-1370  Recommended ages: 5 and up  Sunday</p>
        <p>Trees do have a way of talking, but you need to listen very closely. In this theatrical program, a fox, a tree and a bird tell how one seed gave birth to the planet Earth and its seasons. A tree is the main character in this theater piece, performed by the Touchstone Center Theater Ensemble of New York. Its programs are intended to unearth the "poetry of language in all living things," said Richard Lewis, the director.</p>
        <p>Afterward, children can make a tree with twigs and clay. More of the mystery unfolds as the children's trees become reflections of themselves or metaphors for their inner selves. The free program starts at 2 P.M.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
