<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Design Could Make Solar Cells Competitive</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="693549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SILICON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF NEW SOUTH WALES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Silicon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7DD1F3AF937A25755C0A962958260" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Design Could Make Solar Cells Competitive</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A LEADING laboratory for photovoltaic cells has developed a new design that appears to allow the use of cheap, low-quality materials in the devices, which make electricity directly from sunlight. The laboratory, at the University of New South Wales, near Sydney, Australia, says the innovation will eventually cut costs by 80 percent, which would make the cells competitive with conventional power sources.</p>
        <p>The laboratory, the Center for Photovoltaic Devices and Systems, already holds the world record for efficiency in a major type of cells, those made of crystalline silicon. But existing designs require crystals of very high quality, or the electrons that are knocked loose by sunlight are diverted by impurities or flaws in the crystal before they can be gathered into current. The new design leads the electrons along a much shorter path, so the cell should be able to tolerate flaws and impurities 100 times to 1,000 times greater.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A LEADING laboratory for photovoltaic cells has developed a new design that appears to allow the use of cheap, low-quality materials in the devices, which make electricity directly from sunlight. The laboratory, at the University of New South Wales, near Sydney, Australia, says the innovation will eventually cut costs by 80 percent, which would make the cells competitive with conventional power sources.</p>
        <p>The laboratory, the Center for Photovoltaic Devices and Systems, already holds the world record for efficiency in a major type of cells, those made of crystalline silicon. But existing designs require crystals of very high quality, or the electrons that are knocked loose by sunlight are diverted by impurities or flaws in the crystal before they can be gathered into current. The new design leads the electrons along a much shorter path, so the cell should be able to tolerate flaws and impurities 100 times to 1,000 times greater.</p>
        <p>"It's a conceptual breakthrough," said Dr. Paul A. Basore, a leading solar scientist at the United States Department of Energy who recently visited the laboratory. But he and others cautioned that what had been achieved so far was only a promising design, not a working device and that problems might arise in fabricating the device. "They've demonstrated several pieces of this puzzle, but they have yet to demonstrate the new technology itself," he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Basore, a senior member of the technical staff at Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque, N.M., said the Australian center, which receives $50,000 a year from the United States Department of Energy, was "the world's leading research center" for silicon solar cells.</p>
        <p>The director of the New South Wales laboratory, Prof. Martin A. Green, said in a statement, "We have developed a new design strategy which should eventually meet all nations' needs for cheap and environmentally sound energy supplies."</p>
        <p>The new cell design muddies the distinction between the two major solar cell types now in production: amorphous thin films and crystalline silicon.  Feasibility of Solar Power Plants</p>
        <p>It would, if produced as the designers predict, replace both of them, and replace many conventional power plants. The designers predict that in 10 years it would produce power at $1 a peak watt, as against wholesale prices of about $4 a peak watt today.</p>
        <p>The $1 figure implies construction costs about the same as those of a power plant running on fossil fuels. The solar plant could not, of course, run 24 hours a day, but it would have nearly no operating and maintenance costs, and would produce no air pollution.</p>
        <p>The new cell is designed to work like all crystalline cells, with sunlight striking two different active layers of silicon. One layer, the "n" layer, is "doped" with traces of a substance that enables electrons, which have a negative charge, to escape and move freely; the other, the "p" layer, is doped with material to allow positive charges, the "holes," to move through the crystal lattice. The moving charges are gathered into electric current.</p>
        <p>But the charges must migrate from the interior of the layer to the boundary area between the layers, which can be a distance of 200 microns, and they must do so without encountering impurities or flaws in the crystal.</p>
        <p>"It only takes a few atoms per billion of the wrong stuff to impact the performance of the device," Dr. Basore said in a telephone interview. In practice, the deeper regions of the layers are often not useful, largely because of the difficulty that the charge has in migrating.</p>
        <p>The New South Wales design is for n and p layers only three microns thick, with the shorter travel distance reducing the chance that an imperfection will be encountered, and thus permitting lower-quality materials.</p>
        <p>"By reducing the distance by a factor of 10," Dr. Basore said, "you can tolerate up to 100 times as many obstacles." A cell would consist of alternating n and p layers, like a ham and swiss sandwich with alternating slices.</p>
        <p>To slice such exquisitely thin layers would be impossible; a stack of 10 layers, which is what a finished cell might consist of, would only be one-third or so of the thickness of a human hair.  Spraying On Layers</p>
        <p>Instead, the layers would be sprayed on like spray paint, in a vacuum chamber, an industrial process that is already used in manufacturing the other major type of cell, amorphous silicon. Those cells are relatively cheap to make but have much lower efficiency, because the atoms are randomly lined up, and thus "amorphous," rather than being locked into a crystalline structure.</p>
        <p>Normally the crystals used in crystalline cells are far too big for this, but Dr. Green's design is for smaller crystals -- large on the atomic scale, perhaps a billion trillion atoms in diameter, but only a few microns across, far too small to be seen by the naked eye. Again with less distance for the charge to travel, there is relatively little problem with smaller crystals and more boundaries between crystals.</p>
        <p>"Our design is very much more tolerant," Dr. Alistair B. Sproul, a senior researcher at the center, said in a telephone interview from the laboratory, which is in Kensington, Australia.</p>
        <p>The first cells of the new type will use silicon as a substrate, or supporting surface, Dr. Sproul said. The silicon has a texture that makes it easy to stack subsequent layers of deposited materials, much the way a second layer of oranges in a grocery store display is easy to stack on the first layer. Eventually, though, the laboratory plans to use glass, which is far cheaper.</p>
        <p>A laser cuts grooves in the stack of layers, so all the n layers can be connected to each other, and all the p layers can be connected to each other. Metal contacts are laid into the grooves.</p>
        <p>The laboratory says that both sides of the stack of layers should be covered with a transparent material. Mounted on a rack over a bed of white pebbles, which would reflect sunlight, the back would also absorb solar radiation and produce energy.</p>
        <p>Another solar expert, Dr. Robert Wills, who is the technical director of the annual American Tour de Sol race of solar and electric cars, said other designers had talked about such a two-way cell, but no one had manufactured one. Dr. Wills said he was hopeful. "There have been many announcements over the last 10 years of miracle solar cells, and most of them have not come to fruition," he said. But he added, "Martin Green is probably the world's most respected photovoltaic researcher."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
