<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="716671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3D7103DF93BA35753C1A962958260" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 2-6  IRAQI THREAT TO KUWAIT  Iraqi troops moved toward the border with Kuwait, prompting President Clinton to send American forces to the region and to warn that the United States would defend its Persian Gulf allies.  1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 2-6  IRAQI THREAT TO KUWAIT  Iraqi troops moved toward the border with Kuwait, prompting President Clinton to send American forces to the region and to warn that the United States would defend its Persian Gulf allies.  1</p>
        <p>KUWAIT LIVING WITH DREAD  Kuwait lives with a strong sense of insecurity, more than three years after the end of the Persian Gulf war, with many young Kuwaitis feeling hopelessness about the future of their country.  1  C.I.A. TIES TO HAITIAN GUNMEN  The head of Haiti's most infamous paramilitary group was on the C.I.A. payroll for two years, even after his group helped chase away American troops preparing for the exiled leader's return.  1  NARROW AMNESTY IN HAITI  The Haitian Senate approved a narrow amnesty proposal that would excuse leaders only from political offenses, not criminal ones, increasing the pressure on them to leave the country.  4  SOUTH AFRICA A HARD SELL  American executives remain wary about investing in South Africa, despite their applause for President Nelson Mandela. Currency controls, trade barriers and a militant labor force are seen as obstacles.  39  WARRANT IN SWISS DEATHS  An arrest warrant was issued for the founder of a Swiss cult, 48 of whose members were found dead, as evidence mounted that at least some of the deaths were murder rather than suicide.  6  SOUTH KOREA CRITICAL OF U.S.  The South Korean leader, in an interview, criticized the United States for its role in negotiations with North Korea, saying that the United States has been too flexible and should apply more pressure.  3  REPROACH GROWS IN INDIA  Bombay journal: With the pneumonic plague epidemic abating, India focused on the economic impact, with demands to do something about the urban squalor that was considered responsible.  2  China carried out an underground nuclear test.  3  National 7-10, 30  PRESIDENT STRIKES BACK  After months of watching Congress shoot holes in his legislative agenda, President Clinton fought back by saying the Republicans had pursued a strategy to "stop it, slow it, kill it or just talk it to death." 1  CONTINUED IMPASSE IN CONGRESS  Congress crawled toward adjournment with hardly any votes on anything. The most decisive action was a Republican victory that resulted in the death of legislation on rules for lobbying.  9  RECYCLING'S NEW MARKET  Recycling is becoming a big business as the nation's economic recovery has increased the demand for raw materials.  1  EXECUTIVES AND CRIME  In an indication of the nation's preoccupation with crime, a group of business executives took up the subject at a retreat more normally associated with rounds of golf.  30  GOING TOO FAR?  A plan by the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation to re-create a slave auction has raised the hackles of people who say it trivializes a painful part of American history.  7  UNUSUAL SIGHT IN DENVER  A 5.3-mile-long light rail system opened in downtown Denver, a city that has had its share of transportation woes with an new airport that is long overdue to open.  7  OZONE HOLE RETURNS  The seasonal hole in the ozone layer over Antarctica has reappeared, but it is no larger than last year.  7  NEW CASES FOR COURT  The Supreme Court added important cases on welfare benefits and health care regulation to its docket, insuring that the Court as well as Congress will be a focus of debates on these subjects.  10  VITAMIN BILL ADVANCES  The House passed a bill allowing general health claims for vitamins and dietary supplements.  10  MAPS FROM SPACE  The space shuttle Endeavour began creating radar maps of the planet that might one day enable scientists to predict earthquakes.  10  CHURCH PONDERS NEXT MOVE  Beliefs: A respite from sex-abuse accusations, a priest argues, is the perfect time for the Roman Catholic Church to seize the initiative and to be seen as embarking on a broad, clear plan of action. But there is resistance by bishops.  30  A nurse was accused of raping unconscious hospital patients.  30  Metro Digest 25  WORK PROGRAM WITH WELFARE  In a program modeled after Westchester County's, Mayor Giuliani says he will require able-bodied childless adults on welfare to work 20 hours a week starting Jan. 1.  1  VOICES FROM QUEENS  Mario M. Cuomo had no trouble persuading his borough to send him to Albany three times. But as he requests a fourth term, he is finding there is no longer much enthusiasm for him in Queens.  1  Business Digest 39  Arts/Entertainment 11-18  Book up for award is kept from reviewers.  18  Film: "The Specialist." 11  "Satantango." 11  "Postcards From America." 14  Music: "Symphony for Two Worlds." 11  Sports 32-36  Basketball: Knicks open camp.  33  Column: Rhoden on celebrations.  33  Football: Hurricanes at the crossroads.  33  Hockey: N.H.L.'s new opening night in doubt.  33  Obituaries 31  Timothy Asch, anthropologist.</p>
        <p>Niels K. Jerne, immunologist and a co-winner of a Nobel Prize in 1964.</p>
        <p>Robert K. Match, ex-president of Long Island Jewish Medical Center.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed 22-23  Editorials  Congress's sour finish.  Sex, American style.  Fixing a mess at Youth Services.  Small strides in curbing arms.  Letters  Anna Quindlen: Quid pro quo.  Russell Baker: Just common scents.  Aryeh Neier: South Africa's lesson for Haiti.  James S. Kunen: No justice for these lawyers. Bridge 14  Chronicle 24  Crossword 16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
