<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panels in Congress to Act on Improving Air Quality on Aircraft</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="682819"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PESTICIDES AND PESTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMERICANS ABROAD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AUSTRALIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEAHY, PATRICK J (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OBERSTAR, JAMES L (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0D81131F937A15757C0A962958260" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panels in Congress to Act on Improving Air Quality on Aircraft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN TOLCHIN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOLCHIN, MARTIN</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two chairmen of Congressional panels say they will take action to improve the quality of air in airline cabins.</p>
        <p>One of them, Senator Patrick J. Leahy, Democrat of Vermont, who is chairman of the Agriculture Committee, said this week that he had had the "very unpleasant experience" of being sprayed with an insecticide before his aircraft landed in Australia, one of more than 20 countries requiring such spraying. He said he may introduce legislation to protect Americans who travel to those countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two chairmen of Congressional panels say they will take action to improve the quality of air in airline cabins.</p>
        <p>One of them, Senator Patrick J. Leahy, Democrat of Vermont, who is chairman of the Agriculture Committee, said this week that he had had the "very unpleasant experience" of being sprayed with an insecticide before his aircraft landed in Australia, one of more than 20 countries requiring such spraying. He said he may introduce legislation to protect Americans who travel to those countries.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Representative James L. Oberstar, a Minnesota Democrat who is chairman of the aviation subcommittee of the Public Works and Transportation Committee, scheduled a hearing for May 18 on the problems of air quality in airline cabins on domestic flights.</p>
        <p>He said the hearings would focus on the health effects of a 50 percent reduction of fresh air in airline cabins that occurred in the late 1980's, and whether this unduly exposed passengers to bacteria, viruses, carbon dioxide and fumes from materials used to construct or maintain the cabins.</p>
        <p>The hearings will also study insecticide spraying and whether smoking should still be permitted on international flights, Mr. Oberstar said. "We need to improve air quality in airline cabins," he said.</p>
        <p>Senator Leahy noted that countries in the Caribbean, South American and the South Pacific require the spraying of d-phenothrin, sold commercially as Black Knight Roach Killer, 30 minutes before a flight lands to kill disease-bearing insects.</p>
        <p>That means, he said, that crew members turn off the ventilation and walk down the aisles spraying the insecticide, which then settles on the skin and clothing of passengers and crew and is inhaled.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has said that even though the insecticide has low toxicity to humans, the spraying could create medical problems for people with allergies, chemical sensitivities, asthma or other respiratory problems. Flight attendants and passengers have complained of headaches, nausea, fatigue, seizures and, in extreme cases, memory loss, a reduction in cognitive skills or a depressed immune system.</p>
        <p>"I would like to see public opinion and the power of persuasion end the practice, " Mr. Leahy said, "but if that doesn't work, I think we have a legitimate right to enact legislation to protect Americans who travel."</p>
        <p>He said he was seeking a worldwide campaign warning of the perils to the health of passengers and crew members from spraying insecticide. Suggests a Warning Label</p>
        <p>Mr. Leahy also said that he wanted all tickets to countries requiring such spraying to bear a large yellow label saying, "Warning: You Will Be Sprayed With Pesticide During This Flight." He said signs with similar wording should be posted at airport ticket counters and gates.</p>
        <p>United Airlines and American Airlines, which fly to the Caribbean and South America, inform passengers of the spraying only when they are on board the aircraft, shortly before the spraying occurs, unless a traveler requests such information when buying a ticket, the airlines' spokesmen said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leahy said that in 1988, he and all other passengers on Air Force Two were sprayed on a trip to Australia, as required by the Australian Government. "I tried not to breathe," he said. "We just had to sit there and take it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Leahy, who is also chairman of the foreign operations subcommittee of the Appropriations Committee, said that he planned to use his influence as an overseer of foreign aid to persuade governments to comply with a recent request by the Administration to disclose whether the spraying of insecticides is required.</p>
        <p>"If this becomes a worldwide consumer issue and creates a precipitous drop in tourism, most of these countries are going to find alternatives," Mr. Leahy said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
