<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WINTER FORECAST: FRIGID. BUT DON'T BE FOOLED</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="719865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OXYGEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINER, JONATHAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEELING, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEELING, RALPH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DF153CF930A15753C1A962958260" item-length="1594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WINTER FORECAST: FRIGID. BUT DON'T BE FOOLED</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Weiner;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING IS a topic that my friends tend to avoid around me, out of politeness. They know I wrote a book about it a few years ago, and they assume I got the story wrong.</p>
        <p>The long-term forecast that everyone is talking about right now is the one in the Old Farmer's Almanac, which says this winter will be as bad as the last one, stormy and cold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING IS a topic that my friends tend to avoid around me, out of politeness. They know I wrote a book about it a few years ago, and they assume I got the story wrong.</p>
        <p>The long-term forecast that everyone is talking about right now is the one in the Old Farmer's Almanac, which says this winter will be as bad as the last one, stormy and cold.</p>
        <p>When I ask people if they ever think about the greenhouse effect, they like to remind me that ice paved the streets last January, trees fell across power lines in February and the North Pole insinuated itself through the windowpanes even in March.</p>
        <p>Has the problem gone away? To find out, I looked once again into the science of global warming, and I started with the singular record that brought the problem to prominence in the first place, the Keeling curve.</p>
        <p>The Keeling curve is the lifework of Charles David Keeling, of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif. Keeling is the chemist who perfected a technique for measuring the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere. He made that discovery in the 1950's, and has spent his career repeating the same measurement. The hall outside his lab at Scripps is always crowded with canisters of air from Mauna Loa, Christmas Island, the South Pole.</p>
        <p>In 1958, the first year of Keeling's record, the average concentration of carbon dioxide in the planet's atmosphere was 315 parts per million. In 1959, it was 316 parts per million. In 1960, it was 317. The figure went on rising year after year, with seasonal ups and downs, tracing the ascending squiggle that is Keeling's curve.</p>
        <p>A rise of one part per million may not sound like very much. But it was enough to confirm that the gas really is accumulating. It went on accumulating throughout the 1960's and 1970's, with Keeling keeping track, and with a few earth scientists trying to calculate the consequences. Their crude computer models projected sweltering summers, droughts, melting icecaps, rising seas, and drowning ports and deltas, early in the next millennium.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1988, the Mississippi almost ran dry, Yellowstone caught fire and global warming became a household word and worry. Millions of people began talking about carbon dioxide gas and its power to trap heat in the atmosphere: the so-called greenhouse effect. Meanwhile, Keeling went on adding data points to his record as carefully as ever. He is still extending the curve.</p>
        <p>I called Keeling this summer at his old family homestead in Montana, where he was making a rare escape from the laboratory, and from a heat wave in Southern California. I'd heard rumors that his curve had reversed and begun to go down for the first time. Keeling told me the rumors were false. The gas did accumulate more slowly than usual last year; but now the rate seems to be picking up again.</p>
        <p>I asked him for his latest figures.</p>
        <p>"Right now it's about 359, seasonally adjusted," Keeling said. That's 44 parts per million higher than it was when he started. The level of carbon dioxide is now about 30 percent higher than it was before the Industrial Revolution -- and counting. Levels of other greenhouse gases are also climbing.</p>
        <p>Gregg Marland, a senior scientist at Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee, keeps track of the amount of fossil fuels burned annually, the source of most of the carbon we are adding to the atmosphere. He has the data set done through 1991. That year, enough coal and oil were burned to put more than six billion tons of carbon into the air; that's more than a ton for every human being on the planet. The oil fires in Kuwait alone put up more than 100 million tons of carbon that year. No one contests Marland's statistics, just as no one contests the Keeling curve.</p>
        <p>In San Diego I had lunch with one of Keeling's children, Ralph Keeling, who is 37 years old. The last time I had spoken to him he was working on a new kind of gas analyzer. Now he has finished it and has gone into his father's line, so to speak.</p>
        <p>Ralph has figured out how to measure the amount of oxygen in the atmosphere in parts per million. He has repeated the measurement year after year since 1989, and has found that the level of oxygen in the air is falling, tracing a descending squiggle, a mirror image of his father's.</p>
        <p>You don't need much chemistry to understand these curves. The carbon dioxide level is rising because we are burning things. The oxygen level is falling because when we burn things, we turn oxygen into carbon dioxide. We're not about to run out of oxygen; but there is no question that carbon dioxide is piling up in the atmosphere, or that carbon dioxide is a heat-trapping gas.</p>
        <p>Over lunch, Ralph explained that you can see more in two curves than you can in one. By reading between the lines Ralph hopes to figure out why only half the carbon dioxide we put into the air each year stays up in the air, and why and where the other half comes down. The answer may help earth scientists predict how fast carbon dioxide levels will increase in the future.</p>
        <p>Ralph told me he expects the global-warming story will turn out like the ozone story. We knew for years that the buildup of chlorofluorocarbons could hurt the ozone layer. We thought these changes would show up some time in the next millennium. We watched, waited and argued. Then a hole opened out of the blue, as it were, much sooner than anyone had imagined, in the Antarctic, where nobody was looking for it.</p>
        <p>For all the world's monitoring efforts, the first dramatic effects of carbon dioxide will probably come where and when we least expect them, because we are playing with something much more complicated than we understand. Then scientists' attention will shift from watching for signs of warming to arguing about what happened. "That seems to be the way these things evolve," Ralph said.</p>
        <p>CLIMATE EXPERTS AGREE THAT the carbon dioxide we have added to the air is now heating the surface of the planet by about two watts per square meter. Earth's surface area is about a trillion square meters. In effect, we have put a tiny pilot light just above each one of those trillion squares of land, sea and ice, and each light is shining down on its plot of earth by day and night.</p>
        <p>In the jargon of the field, the trillion pilot lights are known as a forcing factor. They are one of many factors in the atmosphere -- including the level of ash in the stratosphere and the opacity of clouds -- that force the climate to change.</p>
        <p>But the atmosphere is touched by many other spheres of influence, including the hydrosphere (the sea), the cryosphere (the ice sheets), the biosphere (life on earth) and the lithosphere (the rocky shell of the earth itself). These spheres are all in perpetual change and motion, as is the sphere of fire, the sun.</p>
        <p>How will the climate change, and how fast? Has it begun to change already? Earth's temperature has risen about 1 degree Fahrenheit over the past 100 years, though the experts still debate tenths of a degree. The year 1990 was the hottest in at least 100 years. In 1991, however, the Philippine volcano Pinatubo erupted, casting such a pall of smoke, dust and sulfur dioxide into the atmosphere that it appears to have forced the average temperature at the surface in the opposite direction, and cooled us off. Global temperatures have set no records since. The last traces of Pinatubo's eruption have been settling out of the stratosphere this year, and climate experts around the world are waiting to see what will happen next.</p>
        <p>Stephen Schneider, a climatologist at Stanford University, is cautious. "I'd say there will be a global hot year in the next two or three years," he told me. "Can't be sure, but the probability is 50 or 60 percent." Other climatologists are holding their bets. No one really knows what those trillion points of light will do to the surface temperature of the planet, or to the Antarctic icecap, or to the level of the sea. No supercomputer weather model is powerful enough to do more than paint possibilities -- and no one who runs these rather clunky models has ever claimed otherwise.</p>
        <p>Maybe we'll be lucky. According to one current line of thinking, the polluted haze that rises from smokestacks and exhaust pipes -- the cloud from the human volcano -- forces a cooling, while carbon dioxide forces a warming. Maybe the two factors will cancel each other out; or maybe some other haphazard event will help us. One of the optimists in the greenhouse is Richard Lindzen, a meteorologist at M.I.T. whose degree of skepticism puts him in a minority in the field. Lindzen thinks the uncertainties in the models are so great that global temperature is just as likely to drop as to rise. "Anyone wants to make a bet, I'll take it," he told me, feistily.</p>
        <p>But I don't see how anyone with a feeling for the complexity of the planet can look at the Keeling curves without feeling at least a twinge. Back in 1958, at the start of the curve, we were adding two billion tons of carbon to the atmosphere each year; now we add more than three times that much. Meanwhile, when we live through freak weather of any kind -- a bad winter or a bad summer -- we notice how fragile our situation really is. We are changing the conditions under which we and all the other species on the planet have flourished, and we don't know what will happen next. To me the Keeling curves remain as sobering as the sight of the 100-year-old oak that fell out of our woods on a quiet morning this summer, after holding up all winter, and landed 10 feet from the sandbox.  Jonathan Weiner's book "The Beak of the Finch" won the 1994 Los Angeles Times Book Prize for Science.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Weiner's book "The Beak of the Finch" won the 1994 Los Angeles Times Book Prize for Science.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
