<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cuomo Legacy, as He Would Tell It</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="714803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK TIMES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DF113AF93BA1575AC0A962958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cuomo Legacy, as He Would Tell It</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Governor Cuomo was asked what legacy he thought he had left to New York after 12 years in office, and what he hoped to accomplish in another term.</p>
        <p>CUOMO I don't talk about legacies. This is a big argument I had with my son a long time ago and he said unless you go out there and talk about legacy and pick one thing and say it over and over they'll never remember you for anything. And that's probably the way it will come out. Except I was against the death penalty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Governor Cuomo was asked what legacy he thought he had left to New York after 12 years in office, and what he hoped to accomplish in another term.</p>
        <p>CUOMO I don't talk about legacies. This is a big argument I had with my son a long time ago and he said unless you go out there and talk about legacy and pick one thing and say it over and over they'll never remember you for anything. And that's probably the way it will come out. Except I was against the death penalty.</p>
        <p>Q.  What do you want to be remembered for?</p>
        <p>A.  What do I want to be remembered for?  [ Smiling. ]  Being a four-term governor.</p>
        <p>. . .</p>
        <p>Q.  Have you changed your mind about anything in 12 years as Governor?</p>
        <p>A.  Well, I've changed my mind about how to deal with the Legislature. The things I mentioned to you before, about traveling.</p>
        <p>Q.  What do you mean about traveling?</p>
        <p>A.  I haven't traveled enough.</p>
        <p>Q.  Around the state, you mean?</p>
        <p>A.  No, no, no, around the country. Oh, the state, that I will never fault myself for. Thank God, I mean, I have seen more of the state than anybody who ever lived, I'm sure. And I love it. I mean, that's been all the joy. So, no, traveling around the state. Traveling internationally, everybody was after me in the early years, you have to travel and I was naive about that. I liked the desk. I liked the work. I liked feeling that I'm dealing with it and I know what's happening and I didn't think it was important for me to go to Brazil.  . . .</p>
        <p>Q.  To put it another way, what have you learned in 12 years?</p>
        <p>A.  Oh, God. I have to go to the diary. I can -- I learn every day. Oh, I mean -- what can I tell you. I mean, I'm not sure I can distill it down to -- I've learned a lot about communication. I've learned a lot about how difficult it is. I've learned that the only way to communicate successfully . . . is simplicity and reiteration. Constant reiteration of simple ideas. . . .</p>
        <p>Q.  To use the word you like, what is really the rationale for a fourth term?</p>
        <p>A.  I took you through two recessions. And at the same time laid a foundation for a powerful new economy. More powerful than any you've ever had in the state. In the process of doing that, we changed all sorts of things dramatically. We created the first centers of advanced technology and gave you an infrastructure you never had before. We changed your taxes to the lowest level in 30 years. We changed your roads and bridges with the biggest building program in our history. . . .</p>
        <p>We changed with Battery Park, which I built almost all up with Stuyvesant, with structures like that, all over the state. We introduced the first environmental protection fund, the first acid rain law, the first park fund, a whole series of firsts. We gave you one of the best Court of Appeals in the country with the first woman, the first woman Chief Judge, the first two blacks, the first Latino, and that after 200 years of waiting. We gave you an ethics law that I had to fight the Legislature to get and the strongest ethics law in our history. We're giving you a whole new approach to elementary education. We gave you 500,000 new jobs and 50,000 new businesses. And we gave you a whole new high-tech economy.</p>
        <p>[ But that was in the past, the Governor was reminded. What would he tell New Yorkers about the future? ]</p>
        <p>CUOMO Well, the recession is behind us. Happy days are near again. Happy days will be here again before I'm through. The evidence is clear -- you've had 90,000 new jobs from July of '93 to July of '94. You have all those indicators I gave you before about things getting better here. You have high-tech products being invented and sold around the world. You have exports growing faster and investment growing faster than anywhere else. This will be the high-tech capital of the United States of America. This will be the higher education capital of the United States of America -- over the next four years. It's very close to that now.</p>
        <p>This will be the health services capital of the United States of America. It's very close to that now. We will be the primary care capital of America. We're very close to being, if we're not there already, the most progressive welfare system in the United States of America. . . .</p>
        <p>[ The Governor was asked whether he thought he would win. ]</p>
        <p>CUOMO I don't think about that. I never have. I don't live that way. I really don't. I'm planning on winning. I'm filled with things that we have to do after we win. . . .</p>
        <p>I'm very proud of what we did with energy last week. And the taxes. You'll like what we're going to say about the taxes. It will still be very reasonable, we're saying we're not, if we can't do it without hurting the city, we're not going to do it. I know I'm very eager to get at the Legislature again. I'm very eager to keep the voice of this state civil, sound, balanced, intelligent, honest. . . .</p>
        <p>I have always been luckier than I deserve. I can't imagine anything happening to me that would make me feel sorry for myself. So I'm not troubled so much. I would be very disappointed if I didn't succeed this time. I've wanted this one more than any of the previous three. Because this is a different moment in American history. There is a harshness and a negativism and a fear out there that concerns me and that New York can help relieve because we are seen and heard everywhere. . . .</p>
        <p>So I would be very disappointed if I don't get the chance.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
