<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Dinner for 600 Squirmy Friends</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDD1030F930A15752C0A962958260" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Dinner for 600 Squirmy Friends</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anne Raver</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S one thing to talk about worms and it's another thing to live with them. For a couple of years now, I've been extolling the virtues of indoor worm composting. That occurs when you put a pound or so of worms in a wooden box or a plastic bin, give them some banana peels and lettuce to eat, top them off with a little damp bedding of shredded newspaper and voila!, in a few months, your icky garbage is sweet-smelling compost.</p>
        <p>I'd seen this magic trick performed at botanical gardens and schools and such, but I'd never tried it myself. And so, early last month, I ordered a Worm-a-way bin made of recycled plastic and a pound of red worms -- Eisenia foetida, a type of earthworm famed for its ability to eat garbage -- from Flowerfield Enterprises in Kalamazoo, Mich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S one thing to talk about worms and it's another thing to live with them. For a couple of years now, I've been extolling the virtues of indoor worm composting. That occurs when you put a pound or so of worms in a wooden box or a plastic bin, give them some banana peels and lettuce to eat, top them off with a little damp bedding of shredded newspaper and voila!, in a few months, your icky garbage is sweet-smelling compost.</p>
        <p>I'd seen this magic trick performed at botanical gardens and schools and such, but I'd never tried it myself. And so, early last month, I ordered a Worm-a-way bin made of recycled plastic and a pound of red worms -- Eisenia foetida, a type of earthworm famed for its ability to eat garbage -- from Flowerfield Enterprises in Kalamazoo, Mich.</p>
        <p>You might say that Kalamazoo has become the epicenter of vermiculture (a fancy name for worm composting) since a biologist named Mary Appelhof, who owns Flowerfield Enterprises, started shoveling her own garbage into the voracious little maws of a bunch of red worms and wrote a book about it called "Worms Eat My Garbage" (Flower Press, 1984). It didn't exactly hit the best-seller list, but over the years, the book has sold 50,000 copies. In the worm world, that's a lot.</p>
        <p>Now, as Ms. Appelhof explains in her book, you can build a perfectly good little worm box out of plywood, and some people use old fruit-shipping boxes and drawers and so on. But I decided somebody should try out Ms. Appelhof's invention.</p>
        <p>It arrived just before Christmas: a heavy plastic green bin, about the size and shape of a laundry hamper, with two plastic cylinders that serve as aerating tunnels through the bottom half of the bin, and a lid with two circular vents. A Cadillac of bins.</p>
        <p>Assembling this worm box was a cinch. Even I can stick two plastic tubes through a set of holes. The hard part was getting my worms situated. A pound of them -- which could mean 600 to 2,500 wrigglers, depending on how many babies and adults there are (but who's counting?) -- were packed snugly into damp peat moss in a little cardboard box. (It looked like it might contain homemade cookies.) They might be a bit sluggish, Ms. Appelhof notes, but don't worry. They perk up as soon as they are bedded down and fed.</p>
        <p>The bedding, she instructs, can be made from shredded newspaper, but it must be damp. A worm's body is about 75 to 90 percent moisture, and since it "breathes" through its skin -- actually exchanging oxygen and carbon dioxide -- it mustn't dry out.</p>
        <p>What is damp to one person might be sopping wet to another, but not to worry. My instructions gave the ratio: 3 pounds of water to 1 pound of dry bedding. And since my worm box called for 5 pounds of shredded paper, that meant 15 pounds of water! That was how damp worms like it. Imagine. It's not one of those things you learn at Mother's knee.</p>
        <p>The problem was, I didn't have a scale to weigh my newspapers, and I hadn't the foggiest idea how much water weighed. But the worm book reminded me that "a pint's a pound the world around." So, O.K., 7 1/2 quarts would weigh 15 pounds. I was getting a headache.</p>
        <p>Now, for the newspapers. I had a five-pound chicken in the refrigerator, and I balanced it in one hand and a pile of newspapers in the other. It was a free-form kind of job, but so is most of my gardening. My worms would have to get used to it.</p>
        <p>I was surprised at how nervous I was. After all, this wasn't like getting a puppy. They were just worms, thousands of them. So what if they died. But these wrigglers were now in my house. They were pink and innocent-looking. They were dependent upon me for their well-being.</p>
        <p>I shredded the paper, I sprinkled on the water, I fluffed it up like spaghetti. Then I moved on to the food preparation. My worm book informed me that a pound of worms need about a half pound of garbage a day, or 3.5 pounds a week. This was a problem, since I hadn't cooked at home for a couple of weeks.</p>
        <p>I did find some old sesame noodles in the back of the refrigerator, a limp carrot, a broccoli stalk, two wrinkled apples and a bunch of parsley I'd bought at the Greenmarket in one of my I-want-to-cook-soup frenzies that usually end up at the Angelika Film Center. So I got out my chopping board and my chef's knife and made a little dinner for my worms.</p>
        <p>What did worms like to eat, I wondered. Was broccoli too hard for their soft little mouths? It wasn't on the list of preferred foods in the worm book (apples, baked beans, banana peels, cabbage, orange peel, corn bread, deviled eggs, tea leaves, tomatoes, biscuits and more), but it was in the cabbage family. And could I overdo it on the coffee grounds? (I always have tons of grounds.) As I chopped, I had the rather odd sensation that I was cooking for friends. It made me feel homey. I figured I should cook at home more often.</p>
        <p>I added a little potting soil to give my worms some grit for their gizzards. Worms have no teeth, so they prefer food that has been softened by bacteria or moisture. They are basically just long intestines, taking food in one end and turning out compost at the other. They also have an active sex life, which the book has fun explaining.</p>
        <p>Worm castings are full of thousands of bacteria and enzymes, as well as undigested plant residues that will eventually be broken down by microorganisms and other worms. The castings are also full of humus, a soft black substance that can readily absorb nutrients like calcium, iron, potassium, sulfur and phosphorus, and release them to plants. Humus is the ambrosia of soil, and plants can't get enough of it.</p>
        <p>I set my worm box in the kitchen next to a window that has no radiator, because red worms thrive at temperatures between 55 and 77 degrees. They can survive 50 degrees, the book says, and at 84 and above they start panting. By about 90 or so, they're history.</p>
        <p>Then, I placed dinner in one corner of the bin, filled it with damp bedding, and let out my wrigglers. They would find their way to the bottom, the instructions assured me, and start doing the one thing they do well -- eating garbage. All I had to do was keep the bedding damp and aerated -- to avoid the bad smell that comes from anaerobic bacteria -- and churn out enough kitchen scraps to keep my worms happy.</p>
        <p>One night I bought a bag of spinach for them but ended up eating some myself, so the worms are actually improving my diet. I've started to cook at home more for my friends.</p>
        <p>This worm book is really impressive. It answers everything. When I had to go away for four days, I wondered if my worms needed a baby sitter. Never fear, the book says: "One favorable aspect of having worms as pets is that you can go away without having to make arrangements with the vet or a neighbor. You can go away for a weekend, a week, even two weeks, and not worry about your worms." A month or more, though, and you should board them out.</p>
        <p>It really is amazing to reach into my worm bin and pull out a handful of rich, sweet soil, wriggling with worms. "Look!" I say to my friends. "Later!" they say. But my houseplants love the stuff. They're growing bigger and bigger. They're leaning over their pots, urging on the worms, which are multiplying (the worm book tells how to build an annex). My sister says I should count them and name them. But I'm not that weird. Though you do get attached.</p>
        <p>If you want to have your own adventures with worms, you may write Flowerfield Enterprises, 10332 Shaver Road, Kalamazoo, Mich. 49002; or call (616) 327-0108. Prices for the worm kit (book, worms and bin) vary by size, from $73 to $85.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
