<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Emissions Must Be Cut to Avert Shift in Climate, Panel Says</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERGOVERNMENTAL PANEL ON CLIMATE CHANGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E1DB1F3BF933A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="1407" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Emissions Must Be Cut to Avert Shift in Climate, Panel Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVEN if worldwide emissions of carbon dioxide were capped at present levels, atmospheric concentrations of the heat-trapping gas would continue to increase for at least two centuries, rising well beyond the point at which the earth's climate would be disrupted, an international panel of scientists has reported.</p>
        <p>Just holding the atmospheric concentration at double today's amount would require cutting global emissions below 1990 levels, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change said in a report last week. A doubling of today's concentration would raise the earth's average surface temperature by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit and cause substantial climatic change, the panel found earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVEN if worldwide emissions of carbon dioxide were capped at present levels, atmospheric concentrations of the heat-trapping gas would continue to increase for at least two centuries, rising well beyond the point at which the earth's climate would be disrupted, an international panel of scientists has reported.</p>
        <p>Just holding the atmospheric concentration at double today's amount would require cutting global emissions below 1990 levels, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change said in a report last week. A doubling of today's concentration would raise the earth's average surface temperature by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit and cause substantial climatic change, the panel found earlier.</p>
        <p>The latest report from the panel, which advises the United Nations, is designed to guide parties to the climate treaty signed two years ago at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro as they discuss whether the treaty should be strengthened. The discussion is expected to begin at the parties' first meeting next March in Berlin. As ratified by more than 80 countries, including the United States, the agreement requires developed countries to take actions aimed at capping carbon dioxide emissions at 1990 levels by the year 2000. There are no specific requirements for other countries.</p>
        <p>But even if this target were applied globally and fully met, the new report says, the atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide would still approach a doubling of its preindustrial level by the end of the next century. The reason, essentially, is that too much of the gas is already being spewed into the air as a result of the burning of coal, oil and natural gas and the destruction of forests to be absorbed quickly by remaining terrestrial vegetation and the oceans. As a result, the gas builds up.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric carbon dioxide is the most important of a number of trace gases, including methane, that trap heat in the form of infrared radiation emitted by the earth after its surface is heated by the sun's rays.</p>
        <p>It has long been recognized in a general sense that stabilizing carbon dioxide concentrations would require cutting emissions, and the Rio target has been widely considered a first step only. But the new analysis is the panel's first attempt to pin down more specifically and quantitatively the relationship between various levels of emissions, the long-term concentrations that result and the time periods involved.</p>
        <p>"If you want to stabilize eventually, you've got to consider what you do now; that's a message that comes clearly through from the figures in our report," said Sir John Houghton, a British atmospheric physicist who is co-chairman of the intergovernmental panel's scientific working group, which issued the new report in Maastricht, the Netherlands. Dr. Houghton said he was speaking for himself, not the group.</p>
        <p>The intergovernmental panel, which consists of 2,500 scientists and experts from around the globe, was created by the United Nations in 1988 to assess the state of knowledge about climate change. In scientific reports in 1990 and 1992, the panel said that a doubling of atmospheric carbon dioxide would cause the earth's climate to warm by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit. By way of comparison, various estimates say the earth has warmed by 5 to 9 degrees since the depths of the last ice age.</p>
        <p>This magnitude of warming, many climatologists say, would at the very least upset the earth's climate by altering atmospheric circulation patterns that determine where it is hot and cold, where and how much rain falls, where and how often storms strike and how violent they are.</p>
        <p>Since cutting carbon dioxide emissions would have major economic impact, the idea that the emissions could bring climatic disaster has been disputed by political conservatives and some industry spokesmen. The intergovernmental panel's assessments on the climatic impact of carbon dioxide have also been attacked by scientists who reached contrary conclusions. The panel is preparing a reassessment of the response of climate to the continuing rise in heat-trapping gases, to be completed in about a year.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the group's new report outlines a daunting challenge to parties to the climate treaty as they grapple with the question of stabilizing carbon dioxide at a safe atmospheric level, as the treaty requires.</p>
        <p>The new findings are based on a range of computer models of the global carbon cycle, in which recycled carbon moves continuously, over varying periods of time, among animals, plants, microbes, the atmosphere, the oceans and sedimentary rocks. In recent millenniums, scientists say, this flux produced a concentration of atmospheric carbon dioxide that was more or less constant at about 280 parts per million. Since the dawn of the industrial age, the level has risen to about 360 parts per million, an increase of 28.5 percent.</p>
        <p>In the last century, the average surface temperature of the earth has risen by about 1 degree, but scientists say this warming could as easily have been produced by the climate system's natural fluctuations as by the increase in heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>Many uncertainties surround the new analysis of emissions and concentrations. The carbon-cycle models differ in their estimates by plus or minus 15 percent, and they include a number of simplifications, assumptions and missing elements. For instance, scientists have long been unable to account for the fate of about 20 percent of the carbon dioxide emitted as a result of human activity. The oceans and the atmosphere take up the bulk. The new report says that some of the remainder is probably being absorbed by the regrowth of forests in the Northern Hemisphere. And a substantial part of the missing fraction may be residing in the deep roots of grasses planted to make way for cattle in South American savannas, according to a report by scientists at the International Center for Tropical Agriculture in Cali, Colombia, appearing in the current issue of the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>In any case, the model studies found that if carbon dioxide emissions were maintained at today's levels, atmospheric concentrations of the gas would increase for at least 200 years, reaching about 500 parts per million -- almost twice the pre-industrial concentration -- by the end of the next century.</p>
        <p>The analysis also found that concentrations can be stabilized at any and all levels up to 750 parts per million, about twice today's concentration, only by cutting emissions below 1990 levels. The ultimate stabilization level depends on total accumulated emissions and is unaffected by the schedule on which they are reduced, the report said. But it said higher emissions in earlier decades would require lower ones later.  "You can have a bonanza for a time and burn what you want," said Dr. Houghton, but "then you've got to come down with a bang." In that case, he said, higher emissions in the earlier decades would cause some measure of climate change.</p>
        <p>Since bringing an immediate halt to carbon dioxide emissions is considered an economic and political impossibility, some further rise in overall concentrations appears inevitable. Environmentalists consider it unacceptable to settle for a capping of emissions at today's levels -- itself no easy task -- because, they say, it risks a highly unstable climate. The task before parties to the climate treaty may be to seek some climatically, economically and politically acceptable middle ground.</p>
        <p>For instance, said Dr. Houghton, again speaking as an individual, a reasonable goal might be to stabilize the carbon dioxide concentration around 450 parts per million. This might be accomplished, he said, by holding global emissions roughly constant for the first half of the next century, and then beginning to reduce them.</p>
        <p>"That would be a pretty demanding target, but one that might be just about achievable," he said. "I think that to talk about tougher targets than that would be extraordinarily difficult."</p>
        <p>In any case, he said, "we should start to do what we can do now and also begin to plan to do more" and "not wait 10 or 20 years till things are more clear." If climate change turns out to be on the mild end of the range predicted by the intergovernmental panel for a doubling of carbon dioxide, he said, it might be possible to stabilize concentrations at 650 or 750 parts per million.</p>
        <p>But to stay at even those levels, he said, emissions "need to come down."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
