<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Studies How to Clean Up the Wakes of Motorboats</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="687919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLEAN AIR ACT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NITROGEN OXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROCARBONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILCHEY, TIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELE, ANDRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GERMAN, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6D71738F934A25756C0A962958260" item-length="1588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Studies How to Clean Up the Wakes of Motorboats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM HILCHEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILCHEY, TIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is a beautiful day on the lake. As a two-cycle outboard motor surges, a powerboat and tethered skier leap forward to race atop the water in a scene that for many Americans is synonymous with summer. In the wake, silent and unheeded, a film of unburned gasoline and lubricating oil, perhaps as much as one-third of all the fuel that passes through the motor, spreads out on the surface of the lake.</p>
        <p>The fact that recreational powerboats are spraying gas and oil into the water is not in dispute. But at the heart of a recently joined debate between the powerboat industry and environmentalists are two questions: How much pollution is created by recreational motorboats each year? And what, if any, harm is done to the environment?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is a beautiful day on the lake. As a two-cycle outboard motor surges, a powerboat and tethered skier leap forward to race atop the water in a scene that for many Americans is synonymous with summer. In the wake, silent and unheeded, a film of unburned gasoline and lubricating oil, perhaps as much as one-third of all the fuel that passes through the motor, spreads out on the surface of the lake.</p>
        <p>The fact that recreational powerboats are spraying gas and oil into the water is not in dispute. But at the heart of a recently joined debate between the powerboat industry and environmentalists are two questions: How much pollution is created by recreational motorboats each year? And what, if any, harm is done to the environment?</p>
        <p>How those questions are answered by the Environmental Protection Agency, which is expected to issue standards for marine engine emissions this fall under the Clean Air Act, may have profound effects on the design and cost of products sold by the recreational boating industry.</p>
        <p>"I don't think anybody realized the level of emissions that are coming from these outboard motors," said John German, the project manager for the E.P.A.'s Nonroad Engine and Vehicle Emission Study, completed in 1991. "Quite frankly, we were astounded by what we found."</p>
        <p>The study concluded that nonroad engines, those on lawn mowers, chain saws, ski mobiles, boats and other equipment, contribute more than 19 percent of the hydrocarbons, 15 percent of the nitrogen oxides and 14 percent of carbon monoxide released into the nation's air each year. The study did not break down the amount contributed by each engine category.</p>
        <p>"The problem you have with two-stroke engines is that a third of the gasoline goes through unburned," Mr. German said. "The reason they haven't been regulated up to now is because they were considered to be fairly small potatoes. What our study indicates is that we probably made a mistake by not worrying about them." Think 15 Exxon Valdeze's (or More)</p>
        <p>In his book, "Polluting for Pleasure" (W. W. Norton, 1993), Andre Mele, a former boat designer who lives in Kingston, N.Y., estimated that 150 million to 420 million gallons of unburned fuel are exhausted into the environment each year by the nation's 12 million gas-powered pleasure boats. By comparison, Mr. Mele (pronounced MAY-lay) wrote, the Exxon Valdez spilled about 10 million gallons of crude oil into Prince William Sound in Alaska.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mele, who belongs to the Society of Naval Architects and Marine Engineers, writes that pleasure boats produce as much airborne hydrocarbon pollution each year as all the cars, trucks and buses in America.</p>
        <p>Gregory Proteau, a spokesman for the National Marine Manufacturers Association, a trade group based in Chicago, said: "His overall conclusion is a little bit late in that the industry has been working toward a clean-up for years. I don't think there's any question that the author is well-intentioned, but we think that his research is just not up to snuff and that he doesn't give credit where credit is due."</p>
        <p>Mr. Proteau said that outboard motor makers are studying direct-injection two-cycle engines that he called 60 to 80 percent cleaner than today's models, but that they are awaiting the E.P.A. emissions regulations before investing in factories. Once the targets are set, he said, older outboard designs could be phased out within three to five years.</p>
        <p>Since outboards on average are used for more than 20 years before they are discarded, Mr. Mele said, today's two-cycle outboards will be in use well into the next century. Although inboard motorboats also pollute, Mr. Mele said the old-fashioned automotive V-6's and V-8's that most often power them emit only 7 percent of the hydrocarbons found in two-cycle exhaust.</p>
        <p>In a rebuttal to Mr. Mele, Mr. Proteau set the "industry's best estimate" of total hydrocarbon emissions from recreational marine engines at 149 million gallons a year. By comparison, the E.P.A. estimates emissions at 272 million to 414 million gallons annually. The Worst Polluters</p>
        <p>"Whether my figures are right or not is just not the issue," Mr. Mele said. "If motorboats worldwide are contributing a large percentage of the environment's global hydrocarbon intake each year, that is something that warrants looking at."</p>
        <p>The Government, Mr. Mele and the marine industry do agree on at least one thing: two-stroke or two-cycle outboard engines are the worst hydrocarbon polluters. But how extensive is that pollution?</p>
        <p>Unlike four-cycle engines, which have an up-and-down piston cycle dedicated to expelling exhaust gases, a two-cycle motor combines the functions of compressing the fuel-air combustion mixture and exhausting the cylinder in a single piston upstroke. This allows unburned fuel to mix with post-combustion gases and be expelled.</p>
        <p>Manufacturers have favored two-cycles engines for many reasons, said Laurin Baker, director of public affairs for the Outboard Marine Corporation, a leading boat and engine manufacturer in Waukegan, Ill. Pound for pound, two-cycle engines are more powerful than four-cycle engines, and they are generally cheaper to make.</p>
        <p>"We as an industry have found that there is sometimes an oversimplification in terms of the nation's debate on air pollution," Mr. Baker said. "Yes, you do get a higher stream of unburned hydrocarbons in the exhaust of a two-cycle. Conversely, you get a very low incidence of nitrogen oxides, which is an often overlooked point."</p>
        <p>Airborne hydrocarbons play a role in the formation of ozone and smog, while nitrogen oxides are building blocks of acid rain. Factors in Toxicity</p>
        <p>Dr. John Farrington, the associate director for education at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution in Massachusetts, has been studying the biogeochemistry of organic compounds in marine environments for more than two decades and has written extensively on oil spills. He said that the toxicity of gasoline and oil discharges depends on how long they remain in the water. Their fate is governed by factors like water temperature, wind and tidal actions, and solar and biochemical degradation, among others.</p>
        <p>Dr. Farrington said the lubricating oils used in two-cycle engines are "not thought to be very toxic in and of themselves, other than if they coat something." Unburned gasoline contains benzene, toluene and other aromatic compounds that in high concentrations have been shown to be toxic in the short term to various aquatic organisms, he added.</p>
        <p>When thinking about the long-term effects of two-stroke engines, an additional factor must be considered, Dr. Farrington said. Burning the fuel, he explained, creates a class of compounds known as polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons, which are known to be carcinogenic and mutagenic.</p>
        <p>"The lubricating oil and the higher molecular weight polycyclic aromatics formed by combustion will stay around in the environment a lot longer than the gasoline," he said. "They will tend to sorb onto particles in the water, like natural debris from phytoplankton or aquatic weeds or silt.</p>
        <p>"For organisms that feed on detritus, they'll come in through the particulate matter in the feeding process. They'll also be taken up by organisms that take oxygen out of the water across gill surfaces."</p>
        <p>Partly in response to Mr. Mele's book, researchers have recently begun to look specifically at how powerboats affect the environment.  Biochemical Effects</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Moore, a visiting researcher at Woods Hole, said his laboratory there has for many years been studying the biochemical effect of polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons and other compounds on aquatic life, bottom fish in particular.</p>
        <p>"The observation has always come up that any area wherein there is any degree of motorboating activity always shows a significant degree of induction of enzymes in the liver of these bottom fish," Dr. Moore said. Very often, he added, those changes "are in the absence of any other obvious inputs," like sources of sewage or road runoff.</p>
        <p>"From a toxicological point of view, it may or may not be significant, but it certainly does show that there is some biochemical effect," he said. "Suffice it to say that there are some toxicological questions that should be aired and discussed."</p>
        <p>In an attempt to better understand how outboards affect the environment, Dr. Moore said researchers this summer would study freshwater ponds in the Falmouth area of Cape Cod, where recreational boating and septic systems are believed to be the only important pollutant sources.</p>
        <p>While others have been looking for the effects of pollution below the surface, Dr. John Hardy, the director of the Center for Environmental Sciences at Western Washington University, has worked on the Washington coast examining the top millimeter of water, often referred to as the microlayer. More recently, he has been examining the microlayer of lakes and streams.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hardy said his research shows that although evaporation and other forces tend to remove or degrade gasoline in the microlayer within weeks or months, "there's a certain residence time where toxins build up a concentration" that is potentially harmful for fish, water fowl, swimmers and any other organism that touches that surface water.</p>
        <p>"We're not talking about environmental catastrophe that wipes out a lake and all of a sudden makes national headlines," he said. "It's subtle. But it's often cumulative, subtle things that in the end matter a great deal."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
