<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conservation Agency Chief Is Named</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="668265"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL CONSERVATION DEPARTMENT (NYS)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DAO, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARSH, J LANGDON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JORLING, THOMAS C (COMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DF1038F931A25751C0A962958260" item-length="477" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conservation Agency Chief Is Named</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DAO, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Feb. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Mario M. Cuomo today nominated J. Langdon Marsh, the second-ranking official in the State Environmental Conservation Department, to replace the department's Commissioner, Thomas C. Jorling, who is resigning next month to join a paper company.</p>
        <p>The choice of Mr. Marsh was applauded by environmental groups, whose leaders described him as an accessible administrator and able spokesman for the agency and its policies over the last decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Mario M. Cuomo today nominated J. Langdon Marsh, the second-ranking official in the State Environmental Conservation Department, to replace the department's Commissioner, Thomas C. Jorling, who is resigning next month to join a paper company.</p>
        <p>The choice of Mr. Marsh was applauded by environmental groups, whose leaders described him as an accessible administrator and able spokesman for the agency and its policies over the last decade.</p>
        <p>"I can't imagine a more qualified person in the country to run New York's Environmental Conservation Department," said Lee Wasserman, executive director of the Environmental Planning Lobby. "He's willing to talk to anyone and seriously consider their views in a way that I haven't seen in many state officials."</p>
        <p>Mr. Marsh's nomination is not expected to encounter opposition in the Republican-controlled State Senate, which approves all commissioners.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jorling will step down on March 2 from the position he has held since 1987 to become vice president for environmental affairs for the International Paper Company.</p>
        <p>If his appointment is approved, Mr. Marsh, 52, will oversee an agency with 3,900 employees and an annual budget of $281 million that has endured repeated cutbacks amid the tight budgets of recent years.</p>
        <p>He will also wield broad regulatory powers over development, state parks, industrial pollution, water quality and transportation -- powers that require balancing the often competing concerns of environmentalists against those of property owners, business and car drivers.</p>
        <p>Among the new Commissioner's first responsibilities will be to develop regulations to bring New York into compliance with stricter Federal air pollution standards. Those regulations could have a major effect on an array of everyday matters, ranging from how people commute to work to what kind of lawn mowers they buy.</p>
        <p>The new Commissioner will also face major decisions this year involving a state lawsuit to strengthen Federal acid rain regulations, new rules to reduce toxic chemicals in manufacturing and legislation to broaden protections against development in Adirondack State Park.</p>
        <p>He will be paid $95,635 a year.</p>
        <p>After graduating from Harvard Law School, Mr. Marsh worked for the Peace Corps in Ethiopia, then joined a private law firm in New York City. In 1973 he joined the Environmental Conservation Department as a counsel and rose through the ranks to deputy commissioner. He left the department in 1979 to become director of the Government Law Center for Union University's Albany Law School.</p>
        <p>He returned to the department in 1983 as executive deputy commissioner and has held that position ever since.</p>
        <p>In a written statement, Mr. Marsh praised Mr. Jorling for being "acutely aware of the crucial linkage between our environmental and economic futures" and vowed to follow a similar path.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
