<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bringing Sunlight Indoors</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="682673"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, ANDREE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DF1331F937A15757C0A962958260" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bringing Sunlight Indoors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREE BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, ANDREE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LETTING in the sunshine, and getting a panoramic view of flowers, trees and wildlife, is becoming a popular way to enhance the value of a home while improving its livability.</p>
        <p>Though demand dropped off sharply during the recession, sunspaces are now among the more sought-after modifications, according to the February edition of Remodeling News, a monthly trade magazine. They even outshine screened porches and a finished basement as one of the "most popular remodeling projects," according to the Remodelers' Council of the National Association of Home Builders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LETTING in the sunshine, and getting a panoramic view of flowers, trees and wildlife, is becoming a popular way to enhance the value of a home while improving its livability.</p>
        <p>Though demand dropped off sharply during the recession, sunspaces are now among the more sought-after modifications, according to the February edition of Remodeling News, a monthly trade magazine. They even outshine screened porches and a finished basement as one of the "most popular remodeling projects," according to the Remodelers' Council of the National Association of Home Builders.</p>
        <p>Demand has been fueled in part, industry experts say, by improvements in glass technology and sunspace construction. Earlier models tended to leak or become untenable at extreme temperatures; newer designs do not. They have also gained credibility as a marketing tool, making the investment less speculative.</p>
        <p>"People don't want 'boring' anymore," observed Susan Spetrini, a sales agent with the Beazley Company of Hamden, Conn. "They want to feel close to nature, with lots of light." And that, she said, usually means a sunspace.</p>
        <p>A few weeks ago, she said, she was showing what she termed a "plain Jane" ranch house that would normally be agony to sell, but a two-story sun room addition at the rear made all the difference. Even in a downpour, she said, "everyone commented on it."</p>
        <p>Sunspaces are also gaining adherents because homeowners are using them year-round for a wider variety of purposes -- as home offices, exercise rooms, family rooms, dining rooms or entertaining areas. And builders increasingly recommend a sunspace to solve the problem of a dark kitchen or living room: Because it extends outward, the addition draws more natural light deeper into the house.</p>
        <p>A free-standing sunspace addition most often arrives at the house as a prefabricated three-sided package and is professionally installed by the manufacturer. This kind is normally separated from the main house by an existing wall and may utilize an existing roof and foundation.</p>
        <p>A second kind may require the more extensive services of a local builder or contractor to remove an outside wall and lay a foundation to incorporate the sunspace into an existing room.</p>
        <p>Whatever the type, homeowners are seeking more square footage than in the early days, said Rick Jones, president of Patio Enclosures of Macedonia, Ohio, one of the larger sunspace manufacturers and installers. The typical size, he said, is now 12 by 14 feet, larger than most rooms.</p>
        <p>Moreover, although sunspaces used to have to serve as passive solar heating areas to qualify for the generous renewable energy tax credits available in the early 80's, they no longer even have to be on the south, or sunny, side of a house. So even the term "sunspace" has become somewhat misleading.</p>
        <p>Since a large part of the current appeal is bringing the outdoors in, "you can put them wherever it's most convenient," said David Coprio, a building consultant in Weston, Conn. This way, he noted, even heavily wooded lots become suitable locales. Indeed, he said, he often recommends a spot where deciduous trees can keep the room shaded in summer yet permit sunlight to pour in in the winter.</p>
        <p>Another change is in the configuration of the roof. The earliest sunspaces were modified greenhouses, so they tended to have glass roofs as well as glass walls. No longer. The most fashionable and sought-after sunspaces these days, say contractors and brokers, tend to have regular sloped roofs lined with skylights.</p>
        <p>"Traditional roofs are an easier sell," said Ms. Spetrini.</p>
        <p>A traditional roof also helps to prevent overheating or excessive cooling, said Mr. Coprio, explaining that even the finest insulated glass cannot match the insulating properties of ordinary roofing materials. Further, he said, operable skylights allow heat to escape through the roof in summer; glass roofs are less likely to offer such an option.</p>
        <p>The average cost of creating a sunspace is now around $22,000, according to the National Association of the Remodeling Industry. That sum would typically buy a 12- by 16-foot custom-built sunspace that includes a foundation, tinted or insulated glass for temperature control, a paddle fan on the ceiling (considered essential these days for maximum comfort), a tiled floor and a heating and cooling system tied into the house's main systems.</p>
        <p>For example, Patricia and Alexander Nieto of Larchmont, N.Y., are paying $23,000 to convert a deteriorated 12- by 16-foot rear porch into an insulated glass-and-redwood sunspace for year-round use. It was not the cheapest of the eight quotes they sought, but one that they said offered them a sophisticated product and highly qualified installers.</p>
        <p>However, homeowners should be aware that they may still face pitfalls. One of the most serious, said Mr. Jones, the manufacturer, is using a product that's not really geared to the region.</p>
        <p>"Be sure you've chosen the kind that's capable of withstanding the maximum snow load for the area and the most severe wind conditions," he said. And it must conform, he said, to the town's building code.</p>
        <p>So the homeowner should be wary if the contractor or manufacturer insists it is not necessary to get a building permit -- a problem faced, incidentally, by the Nietos.</p>
        <p>"Too many of them told us not to bother," said Mrs. Nieto.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coprio cautioned the homeowner to check the arc of the sun in all seasons against the likely effect of neighboring buildings. How that blockage might affect the room during certain months can often come as a shock, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coprio also favors a sunspace that can be separated from the rest of the house. Despite manufacturers' claims, he said, the best of these spaces can develop heating and cooling problems. If separation is not feasible, he said, the area should have a backup heating and cooling system or be made part of a separate heating zone.</p>
        <p>Insulating blinds or other window treatments are equally essential. Yet too many homeowners lose some of the initial benefit by taking a "wait and see" approach. For example, Mr. Jones, the manufacturer, has found that only 60 percent of his buyers are willing to incorporate shades or blinds into the initial budget but that as many as 90 percent install them within a year or so.</p>
        <p>The Nietos maintain it is safer and cheaper to use a dedicated sunspace manufacturing company that installs its own product.</p>
        <p>"You spend less money on middle people," said Mrs. Nieto.</p>
        <p>The couple also felt it was important to personally visit other homes where sunspaces had been installed by the manufacturer they were about to select.</p>
        <p>"You choose them for their ideas," added Mrs. Nieto, "as well as their work."  YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
