<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gas Prices Up 5 Cents, With More Increases Seen</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="715141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCQUISTON, JOHN T</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDF1F3AF933A0575AC0A962958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gas Prices Up 5 Cents, With More Increases Seen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN T. McQUISTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCQUISTON, JOHN T</byline>
      <dateline>JERICHO, L.I., Sept. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gasoline prices have jumped an average of 5 cents a gallon at most filling stations on Long Island and throughout the New York-New Jersey region this week. They may increase again, perhaps by as much as 25 cents a gallon, in three months when gasoline that has been reformulated to meet new Federal air-quality standards will go on sale, retailers and consumer advocates said today.</p>
        <p>Retailers in the region are required to switch by Saturday to oxygenated gasoline, which by Federal law must be sold from Oct. 1 through April 30 to help reduce fuel emissions during the cold winter months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gasoline prices have jumped an average of 5 cents a gallon at most filling stations on Long Island and throughout the New York-New Jersey region this week. They may increase again, perhaps by as much as 25 cents a gallon, in three months when gasoline that has been reformulated to meet new Federal air-quality standards will go on sale, retailers and consumer advocates said today.</p>
        <p>Retailers in the region are required to switch by Saturday to oxygenated gasoline, which by Federal law must be sold from Oct. 1 through April 30 to help reduce fuel emissions during the cold winter months.</p>
        <p>Motorists will be asked to pay still more on Jan. 1, when Federal regulations take matters a step further by requiring that all gasoline sold in the nation's heavily populated metropolitan areas be reformulated to help protect the earth's damaged ozone layer.</p>
        <p>While some drivers said today that they did not mind the price increases if the changes would improve air quality, some New York State officials and representatives of gasoline retailers said they were concerned about rising prices.</p>
        <p>"Such high, rapid increases could be a jolt to an already troubled economy," said Richard M. Kessel, executive director of the State Consumer Protection Board, who called on the Federal Government to closely monitor gasoline pricing over the next several months "to protect consumers against unfair practices by the oil industry."</p>
        <p>"Prices could go through the ceiling this winter," Mr. Kessel said.  "We could see regular gas going for a dollar-and-a-half a gallon, yet the supplies of oil and gasoline are plentiful."</p>
        <p>Gasoline retailers in New Jersey and Connecticut are also worried about the impact of the price increases, which could be as much as 8 cents a gallon by Saturday, officials said.</p>
        <p>The price for regular gasoline posted today at the Turnpike Texaco Gas Station here on the Jericho Turnpike was $1.25, reflecting a 5-cent-a-gallon increase for the oxygenated fuel.</p>
        <p>The station served as the setting for a news conference called by Mr. Kessel, Assemblyman Thomas Di Napoli, chairman of the New York State Assembly Consumer Affairs and Protection Committee, and Mary Ann Ragona, executive director of the Long Island Gasoline Retailers Association.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kessel said that oxygenated fuel had been on the market for the last two winters and that during each season prices rose by as much as 12 cents a gallon, despite industry projections that the increases would be only 3 to 5 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>"While we laud the goals of the 1990 Clean Air Act, we also must look out for the interests of consumers," Assemblyman DiNapoli said.</p>
        <p>Motorists who stopped at the Texaco station said they were unaware that any changes had occurred. They did express concern, though, about whether the oil companies might be using the situation to make additional profits.</p>
        <p>"I have no way of knowing whether I'm paying a fair price," said Ellen Lazarus, who with her 4-year-old daughter, Jillian, stopped to fill the tank of her Jeep Cherokee. "I guess paying more is worth it for clean air."</p>
        <p>Andy Harris, the owner of the Texaco station and president of the Long Island Gasoline Retailers Association, said his 5-cent-a-gallon increase was based on the cost of his latest delivery. He said that the increase for the consumer would soon be more than 5 cents, because he will likely pay more for his next delivery.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ragona said that while gasoline suppliers basically set the price, there was a free market, based on supply and demand, and that consumers could have an impact by "shopping around for the best deal."</p>
        <p>There are no industry estimates of the cost of reformulating gasoline. But the American Petroleum Institute, an industry trade group based in Washington, disclosed earlier this week that an analysis of gasoline futures trading suggested an increase of 6 cents a gallon was coming in January as a result of the new Federal requirement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
