<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Today's Poland Would Rather Just Ignore Nazi Death Camps; Means of Preservation</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="664252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAZI ERA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCENTRATION CAMPS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">POLAND</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Poland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nazi Policies Toward Jews and Minorities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Concentration Camps</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DC1130F937A15752C0A962958260" item-length="338" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Today's Poland Would Rather Just Ignore Nazi Death Camps; Means of Preservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re your Jan. 5 article, we at the Polish Historical Society would like to suggest a novel proposal for preserving the relics of the Auschwitz-Birkenau camps and developing the site.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re your Jan. 5 article, we at the Polish Historical Society would like to suggest a novel proposal for preserving the relics of the Auschwitz-Birkenau camps and developing the site.</p>
        <p>Because, half a century after the war, our knowledge of the Auschwitz-Birkenau camps is still evolving (as illustrated by the constantly changing, up and down, total victim count), it is imperative that the site and the remaining Birkenau structures, where most of the gassings occurred, be left untouched for future generations of investigators to study.</p>
        <p>We suggest that in this era of inexpensive plastics, the deteriorating ruins of the crematories and the gas chambers can be easily preserved by elevated transparent roofs. They would protect the relics from dissolution by acid rain and degradation by vegetation growing out of control.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the water table at Birkenau should be lowered to the wartime level by cleaning the drainage ditches dug out during the war, mostly by Soviet war prisoners. This would slow erosion of inorganic artifacts. It would also reduce deterioration of still-to-be-found notes or memoirs of victims and prisoners who buried them in cans or jars on the territory of Birkenau. The project should cost no more than $250,000.</p>
        <p>For $500,000 more, a full-scale model of the largest crematory and the subterranean gas chamber could be built in the nearby fields. This would not disturb and desecrate the ashes of victims (if any remain at the original sites) or the relic ruins at the camp proper, as restoration would do.</p>
        <p>A full-scale model of the crematory and the gas chamber will permit the visitors to get a feel of the mechanics of the operation of the camp without the slightest chance of damaging the relics. Remaining funds should cover operating expenses of the reconstructed crematory and gas chambers, preservation and cataloging of Nazi documents, and additional research.  ZBIGNIEW ZIELINSKI  President, Polish Historical Society Stamford, Conn., Jan. 14, 1994</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
