<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is Broadway Fogbound In a Special-Effects Age?</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="662184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE1D61531F935A25752C0A962958260" item-length="1669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is Broadway Fogbound In a Special-Effects Age?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT CANBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CANBY, VINCENT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six weeks into a new job covering theater, after nearly 25 years looking at movies, I feel a little like Buster Keaton in "The Navigator" when he takes his chauffeur-driven limousine to call on his beloved. The car makes a stately U-turn and deposits Buster across the street.</p>
        <p>Switching from films to theater is like moving next door. It's not only that so many Broadway shows already exist in the mind as memories of movies seen earlier. It's also that the theater is going through -- and has been for some time -- an escalating evolution in stage trickery roughly equivalent to movies' infatuation with, and emphasis on, ever-more-special special effects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six weeks into a new job covering theater, after nearly 25 years looking at movies, I feel a little like Buster Keaton in "The Navigator" when he takes his chauffeur-driven limousine to call on his beloved. The car makes a stately U-turn and deposits Buster across the street.</p>
        <p>Switching from films to theater is like moving next door. It's not only that so many Broadway shows already exist in the mind as memories of movies seen earlier. It's also that the theater is going through -- and has been for some time -- an escalating evolution in stage trickery roughly equivalent to movies' infatuation with, and emphasis on, ever-more-special special effects.</p>
        <p>Ask almost any six people what they remember most vividly about "Miss Saigon" and they'll probably say the landing of the helicopter. In "The Phantom of the Opera" it's the collapse of the chandelier. "Tommy" will be recalled for the volume of the music and the hypnotic use of lights but also for the sequence in which paratroopers appear to jump from a perilously high platform through a stage-floor opening the size of a Broadway manhole. As the paratroopers fall, the members of the audience think as one: any false move and some unfortunate actor is going to go splat. The fright is delicious, even if it is bogus.</p>
        <p>All these images can be captured with such ease on film that, for movie patrons, they carry no shock effect whatsoever. Movie patrons know that the special-effects people are capable of doing virtually anything. They want "Jurassic Park" with dinosaurs and "Terminator 2," in which a live actor, in a single unbroken take, turns into what appears to be walking, man-shaped mercury. When a car blows up in a "Die Hard" film, it creates a fireball of brilliance to match an A-bomb's.</p>
        <p>The image of the parachute drop in "Tommy" is not unusual, or even essential to the meaning of the show. It's a triumph of theatrical craft. Here is the art of the production designer, and of all those associates who make happen things that shouldn't be able to happen, at least in a live theatrical performance. It's spectacle but, for the most part, it's soothingly benign spectacle devoted to discovering the astonishing in the commonplace. The theater captures our imaginations by conquering the limitations that differentiate it from movies. The paradox: Once we become convinced the theater can do anything, the fun will disappear.</p>
        <p>For better and worse we are in the Age of Scenery and Set Decoration, a time when each succeeding show must somehow up the ante and be more eye-popping than the one before. It's also a time when last week's innovation is this week's cliche. In the theater, as in films, the new gimmick ages faster than a farm-fresh egg. Consider stage fog.</p>
        <p>I have the impression that never before have various kinds of fog machines been so busy on Broadway. They are pumping out their photogenic vapors in everything from "The Phantom of the Opera" to "Angels in America," frequently to engulf not only the stage but also the first rows of the orchestra. Fog, your lovely spell (and occasional sweetish scent) is everywhere.</p>
        <p>Fog announces each descent of the angel in the two parts of "Angels in America" -- "Millennium Approaches" and "Perestroika" -- and also helps to create a dreamlike Antarctica. Fog attended Abe Lincoln's departure from Springfield for Washington in the recent Lincoln Center production of "Abe Lincoln in Illinois." It's even used briefly in "All in the Timing" Off Broadway. The main purpose of dry ice in the embassy ball scene of "My Fair Lady" seems to be to obscure the (one assumes) dancing feet of Richard Chamberlain and Melissa Errico. Otherwise, why would fog be rolling around the floor at such an elegant gathering? Did someone leave the French doors open?</p>
        <p>Good designers somehow manage to stay ahead of their own game. Think of John Napier, a name that should be on the tip of your tongue, though it probably isn't. Mr. Napier is the English wizard who designed "Nicholas Nickleby," "Cats," "Les Miserables," "Miss Saigon," and the new "Sunset Boulevard" now playing in Los Angeles and London.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of the first act of "Sunset Boulevard," the show's gigantic principal set -- on which Glenn Close is careering up and down a grand staircase -- slowly levitates to reveal another, equally complicated set below. The audience laughs with astonishment and pleasure. Even if it's merely the equivalent of a split screen in a film or the cross-cutting between two simultaneous actions, the effect is breathtaking onstage. The moment is as integral to the narrative and to the entire "Sunset Boulevard" experience as the music by Andrew Lloyd Webber.</p>
        <p>For the theater to survive, or so the reasoning has gone in the past, it must offer audiences something they cannot find elsewhere, meaning movies. The thought used to be that this demand could be met simply by the sense of a live performance: audiences' awareness that, during the time of any play, they and the actors are sharing a singular event, one never to be repeated in exactly the same way.</p>
        <p>Such no longer holds. Television, through the magic of what's called live-on-tape, effectively packages and preserves forever not only spontaneity but also the ephemeral nature of the once-in-a-lifetime performance.</p>
        <p>There was also a time when Broadway audiences supported the work of such idiosyncratic writers as Pinter, Beckett, Mamet and Stoppard, among others. Not now. Talk radio is scarcely the reason for the decline of this kind of theater-of-language, but it offers syntax and locutions of a bizarre craziness not even these playwrights can equal. A revival of Harold Pinter's "No Man's Land" is scheduled to open at the end of this month on Broadway, but that is a rarity.</p>
        <p>Most straight plays now head directly for Off Broadway, while Broadway knocks itself out seeking new ways to dazzle patrons who are paying through the nose. It's not a good situation, but it isn't all bad. Spectacle has always been an important part of the theater scene, and if the intellect isn't served by the sight of a helicopter landing on a Broadway stage, the illusion liberates the imagination in a way that the "Die Hard" fireball doesn't.</p>
        <p>"Miss Saigon" has had this effect on a lot of people, though "Sunset Boulevard" would seem to be Mr. Napier's most elaborately realized, most visually interesting show to date. "Sunset Boulevard" commands attention both for what the designer successfuly pulls off and for those effects that don't quite work. The main set, the movie-palace-inspired house of a forgotten silent-film star, is mesmerizing not only because of its surprising upward mobility but also because of its atmosphere. Like the movie star herself, who is no longer completely functional, it is larger than life, a bit spooky and beautiful. So, too, is the designer's evocation, onstage, of the star's 1920's swimming pool.</p>
        <p>Less effective is Mr. Napier's attempt to place a frenzied car chase on the stage, which he does with the help of projected movie images. There's an especially odd moment when the actor at the wheel of one car is seen, peculiarly small but live, peering out of a hole in a scrim curtain on which an image of the car's accelerating speedometer is projected in a gargantuan close-up. It's a bold and valid attempt to satirize movie techniques. Yet it also calls attention to everything that's taken for granted in films and everything that isn't worth realizing onstage, including car chases.</p>
        <p>The pleasures to be derived from gaudy stage mechanics aren't inexhaustible. One result of a six-week crash course in big musicals is an increased appreciation for one-set shows done with a minimum of trickery. They provide serene respite from the relentless busyness of productions on the order of "Miss Saigon" and "Les Miserables."</p>
        <p>I think of realistic sets, like Santo Loquasto's stunning Coney Island high-rise apartment for the recent "Loman Family Picnic" revival. Also, the spare, open design provided by Marina Draghici for Caryl Churchill's "Mad Forest" several seasons ago. Using a minimum of realistic details, Ms. Draghici's work perfectly suited a play that was simultaneously as fluid as a movie but utterly theatrical.</p>
        <p>Neither "The Loman Family Picnic" nor "Mad Forest" used even one cubic centimeter of machine-made fog, which, it seems, has become a cliche that may be hazardous to the health. At the prompting of its membership, Actors' Equity recently retained Consultech Engineering Company to conduct "an in-depth evaluation of the effect of glycol-based fog upon performers," as well as of glycol-based fog when used in combination with liquid nitrogen or dry ice. (Because it is heavier than air, dry ice -- or frozen carbon dioxide -- is often used as a floor cover; old-fashioned steam bursts, for example, employ liquid nitrogen, which dissipates almost immediately. To make glycol-based fog, a fluid combining various chemical glycols and deionized water is heated until the mixture atomizes into fog.)</p>
        <p>It seems that Equity members, those who have been in fog-decorated shows, have been complaining of everything from burning eyes and sore throats to nose dryness, increased mucus, shortness of breath, dizziness and voice changes. (Some actors also report slipping on fog-sprayed stages.) In 1991 the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health did "an on-site evaluation" of what was happening at four shows: "Les Miserables," "Miss Saigon," "Grand Hotel" and "Phantom."</p>
        <p>The evaluation found that actors in fog shows reported "significantly more mucous-membrane irritative symptoms" than performers in nonfog shows, and one of the recommendations was to "relocate" the fog machines so they did not spit directly into anyone's eye.</p>
        <p>Equity members were not satisfied. Hence the new study. While they're at it, they might also want to poll the big spenders who sit in the first rows of the orchestra at these shows. How are their mucous membranes?  SUNDAY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
