<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How to Keep a Warm House From Turning Dangerous</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713606"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASPHYXIATION AND SUFFOCATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SECURITY AND WARNING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTHAMPTON (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONSUMER PRODUCT SAFETY COMMISSION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GERULAITIS, VITAS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CONSUMER'S WORLD PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDC173AF931A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How to Keep a Warm House From Turning Dangerous</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VITAS GERULAITIS was not the first person to die from carbon monoxide from a faulty heater, but his celebrity has focused attention on the problem. At least 250 people are fatally poisoned this way every year, according to the Consumer Product Safety Commission, and 5,000 or so more suffer injuries, some of them permanent.</p>
        <p>Propane equipment, the apparent villain in the death of the former tennis star whose body was found Sunday afternoon in a cottage in Southampton, L.I., is a common cause, along with natural gas heating systems, but oil furnaces and even wood stoves can be deadly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VITAS GERULAITIS was not the first person to die from carbon monoxide from a faulty heater, but his celebrity has focused attention on the problem. At least 250 people are fatally poisoned this way every year, according to the Consumer Product Safety Commission, and 5,000 or so more suffer injuries, some of them permanent.</p>
        <p>Propane equipment, the apparent villain in the death of the former tennis star whose body was found Sunday afternoon in a cottage in Southampton, L.I., is a common cause, along with natural gas heating systems, but oil furnaces and even wood stoves can be deadly.</p>
        <p>"Anything that has a combustion process is capable of providing carbon monoxide," said B. W. Ward, the manager of technical services at the American Society of Heating, Refrigerating and Air-Conditioning Engineers, known as Ashrae. The key, Mr. Ward and others said, is proper installation and maintenance.</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide is a colorless, odorless gas that is produced whenever a fuel is burned without enough oxygen on hand. Carbon atoms in the fuel that normally join up with two oxygen atoms to form carbon dioxide, which is harmless, end up instead with only one oxygen atom. Absorbed through the lungs, carbon monoxide latches onto hemoglobin, the molecule in blood that normally shuttles oxygen to the cells, and refuses to let go.</p>
        <p>When 25 percent of the hemoglobin has absorbed carbon monoxide, serious headache and nausea set in; at 50 percent, many victims are dead.  People who die from smoke inhalation from fires in buildings die primarily because of carbon monoxide, said Arthur E. Cote, the chief engineer at the National Fire Protection Association in Quincy, Mass.</p>
        <p>In every winter cold snap, there are nearly always a few people who die from carbon monoxide poisoning, most often from faulty space heaters. Sometimes there are spectacular cases: a Burlington, Vt., couple and their older daughter were killed as they slept in December 1988; the younger daughter survived because her bedroom window was open. The former owner of the house, who had known something was wrong with the heater, was convicted of involuntary manslaughter.</p>
        <p>In another case, a type of gas furnace manufactured in the Chicago area from 1984 to 1988 was linked to 10 deaths in separate incidents. The Consumer Product Safety Commission arranged a recall but has had difficulty finding all the furnaces sold.</p>
        <p>The commission has been moving toward requiring carbon monoxide detectors in newly built homes, an idea that divides experts in the field. But the commission and others who have studied the problem agree that the toll is far too high. "The tragedy for all victims of carbon monoxide poisoning is that their deaths are entirely preventable," said Ann Brown, the chairman of the commission, in a statement after Mr. Gerulaitis's death.</p>
        <p>The best defense, experts say, is annual inspection by a heating contractor or a technician from the local gas utility. Inspectors can spot flaws by sight and use hand-held sniffers to detect carbon monoxide, said Joseph F. Hilyard, a spokesman for the Gas Research Institute in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Any heating unit can go bad, but when that happens, systems that use forced hot air are the most dangerous, because the air ducts distribute the carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>Some engineers say that gas units are in general somewhat more prone to kill without warning, because oil smoke is more visible and acrid and the residents of a house are more likely to smell a problem in time to take action. Still, even an oil furnace can kill a sleeping family.</p>
        <p>The presence of carbon monoxide in the living area means that exhaust gas from the heater is leaking in. In a forced-air system, it may be because of a leak in the plenum, essentially a metal box that is heated by the flames. Clean air is pumped through the plenum to be warmed and then through ducts around the house, but if there is a hole, the air can be contaminated.</p>
        <p>Systems that circulate hot water through radiators are also vulnerable, because holes can develop in the flue, the path for exhaust gas inside the chimney.</p>
        <p>Even without a hole, smoke can get in. Most systems have an opening where some room air is drawn out of the house to run up the flue, increasing the draft and carrying away smoke. If animals get into the flue, they can block it and the smoke will come back out of that hole.</p>
        <p>"Natural gas burns the cleanest, so you don't have a soot buildup, but you can have a squirrel's nest or a bird's nest or a dead bird," said William V. Federici, a spokesman for Brooklyn Union Gas. The company sends out notices with its bills, urging its customers to have annual inspections. Brooklyn Union also suggests that chimneys have wire mesh or a cage over the opening.</p>
        <p>Flues can also stop working effectively if the house has powerful exhaust fans, say in the kitchen or bathroom, that create a negative pressure when operated.</p>
        <p>Flues can also be subject to damage from sulfuric acid, formed in the furnace or boiler from sulfur in the fuel. Experts caution that this may be a special problem for homeowners who have replaced old systems with new, high-efficiency models.</p>
        <p>"High efficiency" means that the system is designed to get as much heat value as possible out of each gallon of oil or cubic foot of gas, by extracting more heat from the combustion gases and sending cooler exhaust up the stack. That is fine, but if the exhaust is cool enough, sulfur that would otherwise be in gaseous form, flowing up the stack harmlessly (if you don't count acid rain), will instead condense back into a liquid and attack the flue walls.</p>
        <p>Electronic carbon monoxide detectors, which are about the size of smoke detectors and generally cost from $50 to $80. Trade associations like the Gas Research Institute and the American Gas Association have taken no position on them, and some utilities oppose them; Mr. Federici said they could be set off by things like hair spray. They can also be set off by a whiff of exhaust from a car as it is being parked in a garage under the house.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cote of the National Fire Protection Association, on the other hand, said carbon monoxide detectors are "relatively inexpensive protection."</p>
        <p>They are not foolproof, Mr. Ward of Ashrae said. "A carbon monoxide detector would be an excellent investment," he added. "However, you've got to know where to put it."</p>
        <p>A detector in the basement will do little good if the flue develops a hole near the roof line, he said; the concentrations of carbon monoxide around the house would also differ according to the speed and direction of wind outside, he continued, so a detector on the wrong side would fail to recognize a problem.</p>
        <p>Consumer Reports recommends placing the detector near the sleeping area and installing any additional units in living areas.</p>
        <p>Several manufacturers make chemical carbon monoxide detector cards, which sell for a few dollars each and are supposed to change color when exposed. Consumer Reports tried three and found that only one worked. Even if the color change occurs, the magazine pointed out, the resident still has to look at the card to know if there's a problem. It advised against them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
