<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In School; A remote island that finds it hard to keep teachers loses a treasure.</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Education Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="693637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MATINICUS ISLAND (ME)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIMER, SARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCKIBBEN, TOM</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDUCATION PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2D71F3AF936A25755C0A962958260" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In School; A remote island that finds it hard to keep teachers loses a treasure.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sara Rimer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIMER, SARA</byline>
      <dateline>MATINICUS ISLAND, Me.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is hard keeping teachers on this remote island, but Tom McKibben took to the one-room school and the people -- all 45 of them -- and stayed a record six years. June 15 is his last day at Matinicus Elementary School. At the age of 31, he has decided it is time to move on, back to the mainland.</p>
        <p>A lot has happened. Mr. T., as he is known, wrote and directed a hit school play -- "Lenny the Blue-Backed Lobster." He and his students cleared a nature trail. The teacher put in time on the water, as a sternman on Joe Bray's lobster boat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is hard keeping teachers on this remote island, but Tom McKibben took to the one-room school and the people -- all 45 of them -- and stayed a record six years. June 15 is his last day at Matinicus Elementary School. At the age of 31, he has decided it is time to move on, back to the mainland.</p>
        <p>A lot has happened. Mr. T., as he is known, wrote and directed a hit school play -- "Lenny the Blue-Backed Lobster." He and his students cleared a nature trail. The teacher put in time on the water, as a sternman on Joe Bray's lobster boat.</p>
        <p>And he met Kristy Rogers, the daughter of a local lobsterman and an aide at the school. "Kristy was my guide," he said. "She introduced me to the customs -- like you don't ask people how many lobster traps they have. That's a state secret."</p>
        <p>Kristy said, "I thought he'd be gone in a year -- like all the other teachers."</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Mr. T. and Kristy married. Everyone on the island attended.</p>
        <p>Mr. T.'s unofficial title is "dean of the island teachers." Eight other islands in Penobscot Bay have schools. But it would be out of character if he were planning a major farewell speech. "I'll say a few words, something funny," he said the other day. "I don't want to overshadow Nick. It's his day."</p>
        <p>Nick Philbrook is 13 years old. He is graduating from the eighth grade on June 15. He is the sole graduate. There are only five other students at the school: Nick's sister, Samantha, and Crystal Bemis, fifth graders; Crystal's sister Blair, and Shannon Ames, first graders; and Shannon's cousin, Josh, a kindergartener.</p>
        <p>There is no high school on the island, so Nick is also moving to the mainland, where he will board next year at a private school.</p>
        <p>"Mr. T., I'm going to wear my oil pants to graduation," Nick said recently.</p>
        <p>"Nick, you're not going to wear your oil pants," Mr. T. said.</p>
        <p>Nick's yellow vinyl oil pants are for lobstering. He would rather be out hauling traps, like his father, Clayton Philbrook, than cooped up at school. "It drives me nuts, being inside," Nick said. Perhaps that is because as a little boy he spent too much time in bed. He had leukemia.</p>
        <p>"I know how he feels," said Mr. T., who likes to run along the dirt roads in the morning.</p>
        <p>With the sun pouring through the school's big windows, Nick was working on his graduation speech. His mother, Wanda Philbrook, said, "Nick's a man of few words." Mr. T. helped get him started with an outline. A few categories: what Matinicus means to Nick; Nick's thoughts on life; what is important to Nick?</p>
        <p>Nick wrote that to him the island means freedom. Friends are important. As for his thoughts on life, Nick intends to finish high school. Then, he wrote, "live on the island, go lobstering, make a few extra dollars and go into carpentry."</p>
        <p>Nick has plenty to say about lobstering. "You go out there, 6 A.M., come in 2:30, 3," he said. "You haul 250 traps. Last weekend I made 220 bucks, one haul. We got a good spring spurt now."</p>
        <p>Still, he worries about the future. "My dad seems to think it won't last too long," he said. "There's not enough lobsters for everybody. That's kind of why I'm looking for something else to do."</p>
        <p>To Mr. T., the island has also meant freedom: "Getting around, doing what I want to do, how I want to do it."</p>
        <p>At his school, the students have a voice. They make the rules. They go to the bookstore, on the mainland, and buy their own books with school money. They put out a weekly newspaper, The Friday Flash.</p>
        <p>There is no bureaucracy at the Matinicus Elementary School, just Mr. T. and Kristy. There is a part-time superintendent, Bill Sternberg, but he lives on the mainland. "I go over there about once a year," Mr. Sternberg said, speaking by telephone. "I've never felt I had to check up on Tom."</p>
        <p>Mr. T. arrived here after three years as a special education teacher outside Bangor, Me. "I had always been the renegade of the family," he said. "Then my parents moved to England, and my brother quit his job at The New Yorker and moved to the Adirondacks. So I moved to an island."</p>
        <p>His brother, Bill McKibben, a former writer for The New Yorker, is the author of "The End of Nature" (Random House, 1989), about the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Before hiring Mr. T., the three-parent school board tried to talk him out of the job. "You've got to tell teachers what it's like out here in the winter," said Mrs. Philbrook, the chairwoman. "You tell them how hard it is to get on and off the island. You have to feel out the island people, and the ones who romanticize about the island."</p>
        <p>Matinicus is the most remote of all the Maine islands, about 20 miles off shore; the ferry stops here only once a month, even in summer. There is a daily mail plane -- if it is not grounded by fog -- but a ride costs $60 one way, $21 for each passenger if there is more than one.</p>
        <p>Mr. T., as it turned out, was an island person. "It's simpler out here," he said. "When I was in Bangor, I had to drive 15 miles to work. I never felt part of where I was teaching." Here, his house was a three-minute walk from school.</p>
        <p>The Matinicus School Board has hired a new teacher, Christina Quigley, 25, who lives on the island and has been commuting on the mail plane to a teaching job on the mainland.</p>
        <p>Mr. T. wants to pursue his master's degree, so he took a job at an elementary school outside Portland. The next ferry arrives on June 24. The teacher and his wife, and all their belongings, will be on it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
