<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EXPLOSION IN EDISON: The Scene; Everyone Had One Thought: Run, Fast, in All Directions</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="676455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EXPLOSIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PIPELINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EDISON (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEINFELD, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Explosions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFD6103CF936A15750C0A962958260" item-length="1227" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EXPLOSION IN EDISON: The Scene; Everyone Had One Thought: Run, Fast, in All Directions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD,</byline>
      <dateline>EDISON, N.J., March 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They ran. In every direction, as fast as they could, they ran.</p>
        <p>In pajamas, underwear or nothing at all, some sped for the woods. Some chose the path through the creek. Some danced their way down the railroad tracks. And some, in cars and on foot, converged along the skinny road that was the only way out of the housing development. Some people had grabbed coats, but they didn't need them. Behind them a tower of gas burned at 1,000 degrees. Some had grabbed flashlights, but they didn't need them, either. The blinding light was brighter than anything they knew. It was day when it should have been night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They ran. In every direction, as fast as they could, they ran.</p>
        <p>In pajamas, underwear or nothing at all, some sped for the woods. Some chose the path through the creek. Some danced their way down the railroad tracks. And some, in cars and on foot, converged along the skinny road that was the only way out of the housing development. Some people had grabbed coats, but they didn't need them. Behind them a tower of gas burned at 1,000 degrees. Some had grabbed flashlights, but they didn't need them, either. The blinding light was brighter than anything they knew. It was day when it should have been night.</p>
        <p>Some cars banged into one another like bumper cars, and people shoved laggards aside and even inadvertently trampled them in their delirious dash to flee what many feared was the end of the world.</p>
        <p>When a huge natural gas explosion brought a sense of Armageddon to the sprawling Durham Woods Apartments here shortly before midnight on Wednesday, the 1,500 residents did not know what evil had visited them. They imagined that it was a tornado, a plane crash, an alien ship from outer space, a hydrogen bomb or the final revenge of global warming. But they all had the same feeling: run. At Day's End</p>
        <p>"It was getting lighter and lighter out and it sounded like it was getting closer and closer," said Barbara Williams, who lives in building 59 of the complex. "Nobody had to give me directions. All I wanted to do was to get out of there as fast as I possibly could and, let me tell you, I ran like there was no tomorrow."</p>
        <p>Disasters don't choose their moment out of any consideration, and this one called at a particularly unhandy time. Almost everyone was asleep, lapsing into dreams. For the most part, Durham Woods rises early -- streams of car snake their way out of the 63-building development between 5:30 and 7 in the morning -- and so it retires early.</p>
        <p>Joy Anunwa and her husband and two daughters were sleeping in building 43. "When I heard the roar I thought it was a thunderstorm," she said. "Then I thought it was a rocket from outer space. I opened my eyes. Everything was yellow. There was too much light. I pinched myself. Was I in heaven? I woke up my husband, and we opened the door, and the heat was like an oven. So we shut it.</p>
        <p>"We got everyone together and then we just ran out. We had no shoes. We didn't have a dime. Everyone was running in all different directions. They were screaming, 'Run, run, run for your lives!' It was right out of a disaster movie. We headed for the woods and jumped over two chain-link fences and got to the road. We made it to a friend's house, and that's where we stayed."</p>
        <p>The complex of two- and three-story brick-and-wood apartment structures lies off New Durham Road. Reading Road is the one way in and out. The development is bordered by woods, and a creek runs along the back and railroad tracks along one side. The explosion came from near the railroad tracks, sending roaring flames dancing hundreds of feet into the air.</p>
        <p>When the pipeline blew, hundreds of residents piled into their cars -- if they still had any. A number of cars parked closest to the inferno exploded. Windows blew out. Tires and seat cushions melted like taffy. One man was about to slide into his car when he saw that the passenger-side door had blown off.</p>
        <p>When Bill Bowers touched the door handle of his car, he recoiled in pain. It was scorching hot. He was not surprised. He wore bedroom slippers, and they were all but disappearing off his feet. A Corvette nearby had been covered with a canvas draping. It had burned off. "I swear it was 500, 600 degrees out," he said. Panicky, he told himself: "Do it, do it." He grabbed the door handle quickly, yanked it open and sped away in "the hurry of my life." Prayers for Guidance</p>
        <p>Eight apartment buildings were leveled. One was building 21. Inside apartment P, George and Victoria Thornes had watched "Melrose Place" on television, drunk some banana daiquiris and drifted off to sleep.</p>
        <p>"It was a huge explosion," Ms. Thornes said. "I dropped to my hands and knees beside the bed and started praying. I asked the Lord to bless me and guide me through this. Then we ran toward the front door to try to open it, but the pressure from the explosion was so hard that we couldn't open it. Then we ran upstairs, and there was this orange light. We sat there for 10 minutes and waited. The apartment building next to us was on fire. Then we finally got the door open. And we just started running toward the woods, because the exit was on fire."</p>
        <p>They had four cars. All four were destroyed.</p>
        <p>When Terrence Reed, a security officer, felt his apartment shake and saw the glow, he called his father in Piscataway to tell him that a nuclear bomb had been dropped.</p>
        <p>James Cooper, a bank sorter operator on the night shift, was still at work four miles away and heard the explosion there. He phoned his wife at their apartment in Durham Woods.  Somehow she was still asleep. He told her and their two children to leave.</p>
        <p>Anna Leon thought that the noise was a tornado and woke her daughter and said they had better hide in the bathroom. Her daughter said it was a fire and to run. They ran.</p>
        <p>When she saw the brilliant light, Marlene Steinberg, 34, a pharmaceutical worker from building 49, decided that it was the perverse conclusion to global warming. She rushed outside and saw the marching wall of flames.</p>
        <p>"There was mass hysteria," she said. "People were running in every direction helter-skelter. It was almost like going out of bondage in Egypt. I had a pajama top and no shoes. People were pushing others aside and climbing over one another. Some were yelling, 'The world is coming to an end.' We were all running, running aimlessly. We didn't know where we were going, but we kept going."</p>
        <p>Some residents in the buildings closest to the eruption suffered burns, and many people in bare feet incurred gashes. They left footprints of blood. Few people were dressed for outdoors. Melanie Leon was wearing stretch pants and jeans and one shoe, and when she passed a woman with nothing on, she shed her jeans and gave them to her.  'Wall of Flames Coming Toward Us'</p>
        <p>George Moices, an assistant warehouse manager, had his television set on and was reading an article in the newspaper about how to live long. His wife and three children were asleep.</p>
        <p>"The lights went out, and I heard a rumbling noise like a sonic boom, and then something I had never seen before -- a light so bright that I actually thought the bomb had been dropped," he recounted. "I went outside and saw this inferno, this wall of flames coming toward us. I saw people running all over, toward the woods and toward the back, where the playground is. At first I thought I was going to go. I thought we would all die, and I was thinking that I wanted to go with my whole family."</p>
        <p>Then he steeled himself, woke everyone up and hustled them out the door. "We ran toward the woods," he said. "Then we stopped, and I went back to the house to get the diaper bag for our infant. I also got some jackets for the kids and some flashlights. I don't know why I did that. It was so hot and so bright. I looked for our cat Smoky, but when cats get scared they hide, and I couldn't find him. I left the balcony door open. At this point all I can do is hope Smoky got out."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
