<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="686928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E0D91139F930A25756C0A962958260" item-length="890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-11  LATINS REJECT FORCE IN HAITI  Several Latin American nations rejected the use of force in Haiti, dimming prospects for approving of any United State-led intervention to settle the standoff there.  A1  U.S. BOMBS STILL KILL IN VIETNAM  In the battle for Khe Sanh in 1968, United States forces dropped 100,000 tons of bombs, some of which are still killing Vietnamese.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-11  LATINS REJECT FORCE IN HAITI  Several Latin American nations rejected the use of force in Haiti, dimming prospects for approving of any United State-led intervention to settle the standoff there.  A1  U.S. BOMBS STILL KILL IN VIETNAM  In the battle for Khe Sanh in 1968, United States forces dropped 100,000 tons of bombs, some of which are still killing Vietnamese.  A1</p>
        <p>BOSNIAN GOVERNMENT IS BUOYED  With its army less stretched and somewhat better armed, the Muslim-led Bosnian Government feels confident in fighting the Serbs.  A10  The Senate backed efforts to lift the Bosnian arms embargo.  A10  SETBACK FOR BRITAIN'S LABORITES  The leader of Britain's Labor Party died suddenly, just as it appears to have gained the upper hand on the Conservative Party.  A11  POSTMORTEM ON RAID IN SOMALIA  In a hearing on the failed Army raid in Somalia last year, commanders said the American military was divided about trying to capture a faction leader and about the amount of firepower needed for the effort.  A8  Athens Journal: Digging for a subway yields a rich trove.  A4  Nuclear inspectors plan to press their mission in North Korea.  A7  A lull in the attack on Rwanda's capital enabled food to arrive.  A5  National A12-22, B8  ABORTION CLINICS PROTECTED  The Senate approved legislation making it a Federal crime to attack or blockade abortion clinics.  A1  SIGNS OF AN ECONOMIC LULL  New Government reports suggested a lull in economic expansion, which could ease some concerns about future inflation. Retail sales fell in April while first-time claims for unemployment benefits climbed unexpectedly. in the first week of May.  And inflation at the producer level was nonexistent in April.  A1  ICE CURTAIN ON BERING STRAIT  With post-cold war business ventures floundering and some cultural exchanges turning sour, Alaskans and Russians wonder if it was easier to like each other when their governments hated each other.  A12  FIRST CASE UNDER OZONE LAW  The owner of a car-repair shop in St. Louis became the first person prosecuted under a law regulating Freon to protect the ozone layer.  A12  SKIPPER OF VALDEZ TESTIFIES  In his first public testimony, the former captain of the oil tanker said that Exxon had known of, and ignored, his drinking problem.  A14  HARVARD'S FUND-RAISING EFFORT  The university that already has the largest endowment of any private university will try to raise $2.1 billion over five years.  B8  SUPERIORITY AS CURRICULUM  A Florida school board said schools should teach that American culture is superior to all others.  A16  OVERHAULING THE NANNY TAX  The House voted to simplify Social Security laws that turned household employers into tax cheats and embarrassed Clinton nominees.  A17  TOBACCO RESEARCH DOCUMENTS  Documents show tobacco companies knew of smoking hazards in the 1960's and discovered a crucial step for making a safer cigarette.  A20  WARNING ON BLUE CROSS PLANS  The General Accounting Office said that 11 Blue Cross and Blue Shield plans were financially weak.  A22  IMPEACHMENT OF JUSTICE BEGINS  Pennsylvania legislators started impeachment proceedings against a State Supreme Court Justice.  B8  TEXAS GANG BUYOUT PLAN  Fort Worth is offering gang leaders $10,608 a year to dissuade fellow gang members from crime.  B8  Law Page B18  An embezzlement scandal ravages a career at a leading law firm.  At the Bar: When payment for writing violates the law.  How much need a prospective juror disclose of herself?  Metro Digest B1  LEGISLATION ON VIOLENT CRIME  The New Jersey Senate approved legislation that would require mandatory life imprisonment for a person convicted of violent crimes on three or more occasions.  A1  SCHOOL CUSTODIAN CONTRACT  The Giuliani administration set the stage for a showdown with the school custodians' union over contracting out work to private companies.  A1  MIDLIFE CAREER CHANGES  Mid-level, mid-career executives are finding new niches for themselves, as owners of sandwich shops, printing centers and other small businesses.  A1  Business Digest D1  Weekend C1-30  New wing at the American Museum of Natural History.  C1  For Children C29  Theater: On Stage, and Off C2  Film: Cannes Festival preview.  C1  Spike Lee in a tender mood.C5  "Trading Mom." C10  "The Conviction." C10  Dance: Choreography without release.  C5  Margaret Illman stars.  C10  Restaurants C20-21  Art: Two schools of painting.  C1  Old Masters at the Armory.  C23  Cartier-Bresson events.  C24  Books: "Judge Learned Hand." C28  Television: TV Weekend D17  Home Video D17  Sports B10-16  Baseball: Yankees beat Indians in 10th.  B11  Obituaries B8-9  Erik H. Erikson, psychoanalyst.  B9  Editorials/Op-Ed A30-31  Editorials  Stay calm on Haiti.  Mr. Bratton's wise policing.  Racial injustice in the Senate.  Save health care for N.Y. children.  Letters  A. M. Rosenthal: Clinton's honor saved!  Anthony Lewis: Wreckers at work.  David L. Boren: Why I am leaving the Senate.  Franklyn G. Jenifer: Hate speech is still free speech. Chronicle B8  Crossword C28</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
