<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health; Making sure that children play it safe with the sun.</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="695032"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNBURN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED9103DF931A15755C0A962958260" item-length="1288" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health; Making sure that children play it safe with the sun.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCHOOL is almost out and millions of youngsters will be outside playing from dawn to dusk. But while they frolic in the summer sun, many will be overexposed to the sun's skin-damaging ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>Although wrinkled, leathery skin and skin cancers may seem too remote to matter to a 5-year-old, the aging effects of sunlight are cumulative, and children spend three times as much time in the sun as adults do. Eighty percent of the typical American's lifetime exposure to cancer-causing ultraviolet radiation occurs before the age of 20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCHOOL is almost out and millions of youngsters will be outside playing from dawn to dusk. But while they frolic in the summer sun, many will be overexposed to the sun's skin-damaging ultraviolet rays.</p>
        <p>Although wrinkled, leathery skin and skin cancers may seem too remote to matter to a 5-year-old, the aging effects of sunlight are cumulative, and children spend three times as much time in the sun as adults do. Eighty percent of the typical American's lifetime exposure to cancer-causing ultraviolet radiation occurs before the age of 20.</p>
        <p>This year, doctors will diagnose more than 700,000 cases of highly curable but sometimes fatal skin cancer and about 32,000 cases of often-deadly melanoma. Cases and deaths, growing steadily for years, are expected to continue increasing as the earth's protective ozone layer thins and millions of sun worshipers reach their 40's and beyond, when the sun's toll typically becomes obvious. Unless sun-related attitudes and habits change, one of every six children will eventually develop skin cancer.</p>
        <p>It is never too soon to start worrying about skin cancers. Parents and anyone else who cares for children must be sure they play it safe in the sun and develop lifelong habits that will protect their skin from ultraviolet damage.</p>
        <p>Experts estimate that the consistent use of sunscreen with a sun protection factor (S.P.F.) of 15 during the first 18 years of life could reduce the lifetime risk of developing non-melanoma skin cancer by 78 percent. (A recent study in mice that questioned the value of sunscreens in preventing melanoma is not considered by some experts to be relevant to human sun exposure.) Suffering just one blistering sunburn as a child or teen-ager is associated with a doubling of the risk of eventually developing melanoma. Begin With Babies</p>
        <p>Along with feeding, diapering and bathing infants, parental responsibilities include keeping babies out of the sun. The skin of newborns has little or no ability to protect itself from sun damage, and sunscreens are not recommended for babies under 6 months old. Shade is their best protection. Carriages and strollers should be fitted with hoods or umbrellas, and babies should always wear hats with brims.</p>
        <p>But even when shaded from above, skin can be attacked from below by ultraviolet rays reflected off sand, water and concrete (as well as snow and ice). So it is best to protect babies with clothing that covers them when they are going to be outdoors for any length of time. And never put baby oil on a baby's skin before taking the baby outdoors; it makes skin translucent and renders solar rays even more damaging.</p>
        <p>For children who are 6 months old or older, a sunscreen with an S.P.F. (sun protection factor) of 15 or higher should be applied 30 minutes before the child goes out, which allows time for the protective ingredients to interact with the skin. Reapply sunscreen every two hours, and more often if the child goes into the water or sweats a lot, even if the sunscreen is supposed to be water resistant. Wearing a T-shirt in the water offers some protection, depending on the tightness of the weave; the skin under it should still be coated with sunscreen.</p>
        <p>Even dry, many garments let a lot of ultraviolet light through, so it is best to coat the child's entire body, especially areas that will be covered by sheer clothing. Dermatologists recommend sunscreens with a cream or lotion base for young skin and a stick sunscreen or lip balm with an S.P.F. of 15 for the hands, face, ears and lips of babies and toddlers. (It is not known whether sunscreens with higher S.P.F. ratings are any more effective.)</p>
        <p>Teen-agers with acne should ask their doctors to recommend a sunscreen that is unlikely to aggravate their condition. Children who burn very easily can use zinc oxide on sensitive areas like the nose and ears.</p>
        <p>To avoid attracting insects, use a product that has no scent. And to prevent sensitivity reactions, do a patch test before using a new sunscreen. Apply the sunscreen to the inside of the child's wrist a day or more before you will need to apply it widely; if the test site develops an irritation or rash, switch to a product with a different active ingredient (for example, look for one that is PABA-free) and do another patch test. Certain medications, like tetracycline, can result in a heightened sensitivity to the sun, so check with your child's doctor if your child is taking any medication before taking the child out in sunlight, even with sunscreen protection.</p>
        <p>Do not assume that because you or your child has dark skin, no protection is needed. Blacks can get sunburned and also get skin cancer, though not as often as light-skinned people. Those most vulnerable are people with blue, green or gray eyes, fair skin or freckles, as well as redheads, blonds and those with light brown hair. Any child who burns before tanning or who never tans is also at greater than average risk. And children born with birth marks called congenital nevi, which look like big freckles, or who develop dysplastic nevi, skin blemishes that show abnormal changes, seem to be particularly vulnerable to developing melanoma.</p>
        <p>Try to avoid outdoor activities year-round between 10 A.M. and 3 P.M., when the sun's ultraviolet rays are most intense at the earth's surface. As Dr. Perry Robins, dermatologist at New York University Medical Center and president of the Skin Cancer Foundation, cautions in "Play It Safe in the Sun," a resourceful and entertaining book for children 5 years old and older: "It's safer to play outside in the early morning or late afternoon. Play inside or in the shade during the middle of the day."</p>
        <p>Make sure anyone who cares for your children is knowledgeable about the sun. That includes day-care workers, teachers, baby sitters, coaches and relatives. Studies have shown that few teachers apply sunscreen to their charges or encourage children to wear hats when they go out to play.</p>
        <p>Finally, set a good example by always using sunscreen and wearing a hat, sunglasses and protective clothing when out in the sun. One company, Sun Precautions in Seattle, makes lightweight sunblocking garments with an S.P.F. of more than 30 for children and adults. The garments are marketed by mail. The company can be reached by phone at (800) 882-7860 from 6 A.M. to 7 P.M., Pacific time, Monday through Friday, or 9 A.M. to 1 P.M. on Saturdays. Treating Sunburn</p>
        <p>There are times when even the best-intentioned caretaker errs and a child suffers a painful sunburn. Dr. Mary Spraker, a pediatric dermatologist at Egleston Children's Hospital in Atlanta, and others recommend this:</p>
        <p>Do not apply first-aid cream or sunburn spray, which may cause an allergic rash and will not help to heal the burn. Neither should you apply ointments, butter or any other greasy substances, which seal in the heat and make matters worse. Do not use any medicated cream, like hydrocortisone or benzocaine, unless it is recommended by the child's doctor.</p>
        <p>Apply cool compresses or place the child in a cool bath. But avoid showers, as these can sting and intensify sunburn pain. Do not apply alcohol.</p>
        <p>If you have an aloe vera plant or aloe vera extract (available in most health food stores and many drugstores), apply the juice directly on the burned skin.</p>
        <p>Give the child acetaminophen or aspirin to relieve pain and fever.</p>
        <p>Give the child lots of water or diluted fruit juices to replace lost body fluids.</p>
        <p>Call the child's doctor if the sunburn is severely painful and widespread or blisters, if the child's eyes hurt when looking at lights, if the child develops a fever of 101 or higher or faints, or if the child is lethargic or appears to be very sick.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
