<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europeans to Build Supersonic Plane</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="679098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">JOINT VENTURES AND CONSORTIUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SST (SUPERSONIC TRANSPORT)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCORDE AIRPLANE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH AEROSPACE PLC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AEROSPATIALE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEUTSCHE AEROSPACE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0DF173EF93BA35757C0A962958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europeans to Build Supersonic Plane</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With Europe and the United States increasingly jockeying for leadership in efforts to build a new generation of supersonic passenger aircraft, the leading French and British aerospace companies said today that they would link up with their German counterpart to step up development of a successor to the Concorde.</p>
        <p>British Aerospace and Aerospatiale of France, which built the Concorde together and which have been studying the possibility of a new supersonic plane for the last four years, said they would now be joined in that effort by Deutsche Aerospace, their partner in the Airbus consortium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With Europe and the United States increasingly jockeying for leadership in efforts to build a new generation of supersonic passenger aircraft, the leading French and British aerospace companies said today that they would link up with their German counterpart to step up development of a successor to the Concorde.</p>
        <p>British Aerospace and Aerospatiale of France, which built the Concorde together and which have been studying the possibility of a new supersonic plane for the last four years, said they would now be joined in that effort by Deutsche Aerospace, their partner in the Airbus consortium.</p>
        <p>Today's announcement was seen by some within the industry as an attempt to present a united front to the governments of Europe in the quest for more financial aid. The European companies have been lobbying for more government money for research into supersonic aircraft to compete with the American industry, which is heavily involved in research sponsored by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Growth on Long Routes</p>
        <p>"We are looking for government to be supportive," said Ian Woodward, a spokesman for British Aerospace.</p>
        <p>With much of the growth in airline traffic coming from long-haul routes like those from the United States and Europe to Asia, the aerospace industry worldwide has been increasingly enthusiastic about a new plane that would slash flying times and offer greater range and seating capacity than the Concorde.</p>
        <p>In their announcement today, the European companies said they believed airlines would purchase between 500 and 1,000 of the new planes if and when they became available, presumably sometime after the turn of the century. Because of cost and environmental concerns, British Aerospace and Aerospatiale sold only 14 Concordes, seven each to British Airways and Air France.</p>
        <p>Every major aerospace company in the United States, Europe and Japan has been working on supersonic research, and the companies have been cooperating to a certain degree through a joint international study group established four years ago. Competition Is Intense</p>
        <p>But beneath the veneer of international cooperation, there is intense competition. The Europeans, having built the Concorde, want to maintain their leadership in the field, with all the jobs and money that a big new project would bring.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the Boeing Company, which designed a supersonic plane in the late 1960's only to abandon it in the face of protests about noise, and the McDonnell Douglas Corporation both have active programs going, as do the major engine manufacturers, the General Electric Company and the Pratt &amp; Whitney division of United Technologies.</p>
        <p>Under American law, much of their work cannot be shared with foreign companies because it is partly financed by NASA. However, executives from both the United States and Europe said today that any plane that was built would have to involve partners from all over the world, if only because of the huge development cost; estimates start at $10 billion. Still, it is likely that one company or group will emerge as the prime contractor.</p>
        <p>But such a plane faces daunting hurdles, including concerns about the noise from its sonic boom and its powerful engines, and its effect on the ozone layer. Overcoming Concorde's Legacy</p>
        <p>Moreover, it will have to overcome the legacy of the Concorde, which was a financial disaster both for its builders and for the British and French Governments, which subsidized it.</p>
        <p>"This airplane will not be built by Boeing unless it's economically viable and environmentally benign, and the barriers between the present situation and that eventuality are very significant," said Randy Harrison, a spokesman for Boeing in Seattle. But he added: "We do feel that progress is being made. Momentum is building."</p>
        <p>The European partners said they had now decided on the general features of the plane, including a range of 6,200 miles, which is 2,500 miles more than the Concorde and sufficient to reach Asia from the United States or Europe. Passenger capacity would be 250, or 150 more than the Concorde, and it would offer three classes of service to Concorde's one. Like the Concorde's, its cruising speed would be about 1,500 miles an hour, or twice the speed of sound.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most ambitiously, they said the new plane would have to operate cheaply enough that airlines could charge only slightly more than normal subsonic fares. The standard round-trip fare between London and New York on the Concorde is about $7,700, compared with about $6,000 for a normal first-class seat and under $500 for discounted economy fares.</p>
        <p>"How much of the available market a supersonic aircraft will actually capture depends on how close it proves possible to come to the design objectives, and in particular the objective that fares for supersonic flights should not be significantly greater than normal subsonic fares," the companies said in a statement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
