<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Wants to Strengthen Global Pact on Air Pollution</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940820T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="706544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EED71030F935A2575BC0A962958260" item-length="1077" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Wants to Strengthen Global Pact on Air Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration has concluded that the 1992 treaty to reduce the threat of global warming needs to be strengthened and that in any case the United States may already be doing too little to comply with it.</p>
        <p>While that first conclusion pleases many environmentalists who are worried about possible changes in the world's climate, both it and its corollary are also likely to put pressure on the Government to take stronger steps to reduce emissions of certain gases, particularly those from gasoline combustion in automobiles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration has concluded that the 1992 treaty to reduce the threat of global warming needs to be strengthened and that in any case the United States may already be doing too little to comply with it.</p>
        <p>While that first conclusion pleases many environmentalists who are worried about possible changes in the world's climate, both it and its corollary are also likely to put pressure on the Government to take stronger steps to reduce emissions of certain gases, particularly those from gasoline combustion in automobiles.</p>
        <p>International negotiators will meet next week in Switzerland to re-examine the treaty, which was signed during the Bush Administration and calls for reduction of gases like carbon dioxide and methane that many scientists say act like a global blanket to trap the sun's energy in a greenhouse effect and create global warming.</p>
        <p>At the Geneva negotations Clinton Administration officials will support European nations like Germany and the Netherlands in calling for tougher long-term steps to curtail such greenhouse gases in the next century.</p>
        <p>"Virtually all nations are in agreement that current efforts are not adequate to the task at hand," Timothy E. Wirth, the Under Secretary of State for global affairs, said at a recent briefing on the negotiations.</p>
        <p>But so far there is no sign that the Administration is willing to take a step favored by many environmentalists: raising the Federal requirement for fuel efficiency in automobiles.</p>
        <p>And some Administration officials worry that even the current short-term plan to control carbon dioxide, methane and greenhouse gases will not meet the emissions targets set for the year 2000. Troubling Forecasts</p>
        <p>New forecasts, they said, suggested that the United States would be producing more carbon dioxide in the next few years than was assumed when the short-term plan was put together and adopted last October.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Hazel R. O'Leary said in an interview that lower-than-expected oil prices had encouraged higher consumption, and other officials pointed to the increased use of coal in power plants rather than natural gas and to strong economic growth generally, which has increased industry's energy use.</p>
        <p>Mrs. O'Leary said officials from several Federal agencies were already drafting "further steps" to cut emissions of greenhouse gases from their fastest-growing source, automobiles.</p>
        <p>"My clear leaning is to put a lot more emphasis on all alternative-fuel vehicles and to get electric vehicles out of the closet," Mrs. O'Leary said.</p>
        <p>The Administration's October plan, adopted as a first step toward meeting the United States' treaty commitments, relies heavily on voluntary measures by industry to reduce gases like carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels. Many scientists believe that the greenhouse effect caused by these gases affects many climatic trends, not just how hot the planet becomes.</p>
        <p>Among those praising the Administration's new, tougher stance is Daniel F. Becker, Washington director of the global warming and energy program at the Sierra Club. "We applaud the Administration for recognizing that the problem is terribly serious," Mr. Becker said. "But they need an action plan that has got real action, not just jawboning for industry. They need to do much more about transportation, and the major thing they need to do is raise automobile fuel efficiency standards."</p>
        <p>But John Shlaes, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition, a group that represents more than 50 business trade associations and companies, said his group was "disturbed by the implication that the President's voluntary climate action plan, which is just getting under way, will be inadequate and that more stringent measures may be needed domestically."</p>
        <p>In a draft report that the State Department circulated among industries and environmentalists early this month, the Administration warned that new controls on emissions of greenhouse gases could become necessary, particularly steps to cut gasoline consumption.</p>
        <p>The report cited a previously unpublished Government forecast of United States energy use indicating that "trends of emissions are significantly above the levels used in developing the October 1993 action plan."</p>
        <p>"The new data suggest there may be a need to modify the action plan should these trends persist," it said.</p>
        <p>The report, which is the Government's official description of American policies to prevent global warming, will be given to other nations under terms of the climate treaty.</p>
        <p>The treaty, one of two major environmental pacts drafted in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, calls for the signers, especially the industrialized countries, to move quickly to stabilize atmospheric concentrations of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Because the science of climate change is so new, the signers realized that they would have to re-examine the treaty's goals every few years. The first full conference of the signers is scheduled to occur in Berlin next spring, and preliminary negotiations are under way.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 22, negotiators will gather in Geneva for two weeks to discuss, among other things, whether it is enough for the industrial nations to return their emissions of greenhouse gases to 1990 levels by the year 2000. The conference in Berlin must decide that issue. 'Inevitable Next Steps'</p>
        <p>On Aug. 3 at a State Department meeting of environmentalists, industry groups and other interested parties, Mr. Wirth called on the audience to "prepare together for the inevitable next steps under the climate treaty."</p>
        <p>"As a first priority for the future, we need to set an aim that can guide our efforts for the initial period after the year 2000," he said.</p>
        <p>During his campaign for the Presidency, Bill Clinton promised to set higher standards for automotive fuel efficiency, but his Administration has instead favored a largely voluntary approach, which has done little to reduce automotive pollution.</p>
        <p>Budget cuts are also making it hard for the Administration to meet its goal for reducing greenhouse gases. The House and Senate are negotiating a compromise spending bill that could cut the Energy Department's conservation programs by $150 million to $233 million in 1995, depending on which house's version prevails.</p>
        <p>Mrs. O'Leary has testified that a cut of just $120 million would put the target for lower emissions "at substantial risk" and that a greater budget cut would make the target "virtually impossible to meet."</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 20, 1994, Saturday</p>
        <p>A chart on Aug. 16 about carbon dioxide emissions in various countries listed its sources incompletely. The figures were calculated and distributed by Population Action International, from data provided by the United Nations and the Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 20, 1994, Saturday</p>
        <p>A chart on Aug. 16 about carbon dioxide emissions in various countries listed its sources incompletely. The figures were calculated and distributed by Population Action International, from data provided by the United Nations and the Carbon Dioxide Information Analysis Center.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
