<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weather Theories to Dig Out With; Northeast's Severe Winter Is Not Unusual, but That Doesn't Mean the World Is Safe</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940211T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORTHEASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDY, MATTHEW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDF1538F933A25751C0A962958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weather Theories to Dig Out With; Northeast's Severe Winter Is Not Unusual, but That Doesn't Mean the World Is Safe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDY, MATTHEW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As lunch-hour pedestrians high-stepped over snow banks and cabs schussed through slushy Times Square, Brenda Milliner, the resident preacher of doom in the doorway of the vacant Nathan's Famous delicatessen, had altered her monologue to address the question plaguing the populace: Why does bad weather happen to good people?</p>
        <p>"The earthquake, the fires and the mudslides in such a short period," Ms. Milliner said. "The flooding in the Midwest, this terrible weather we're having -- I believe God is fed up with the sins of America. I've been in New York for 17 years. This is the coldest, wettest winter. God is fed up."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As lunch-hour pedestrians high-stepped over snow banks and cabs schussed through slushy Times Square, Brenda Milliner, the resident preacher of doom in the doorway of the vacant Nathan's Famous delicatessen, had altered her monologue to address the question plaguing the populace: Why does bad weather happen to good people?</p>
        <p>"The earthquake, the fires and the mudslides in such a short period," Ms. Milliner said. "The flooding in the Midwest, this terrible weather we're having -- I believe God is fed up with the sins of America. I've been in New York for 17 years. This is the coldest, wettest winter. God is fed up."</p>
        <p>Sodom and Gomorrah got fire and brimstone, she said, and New York and the Northeast are getting snow and ice.</p>
        <p>In fact, there's a more scientific reason for what is demonstrably one of the worst winters for cold and snow the region has seen in decades, meteorologists say, and a quick check with history casts doubt on the notion that the world may be ending. On New York's Coldest Anniversary</p>
        <p>"This is the anniversary of New York's coldest reading, minus 15, on Feb. 9, 1936," David Ludlum, a Princeton, N.J., historian and weather buff, said yesterday morning. "This has been real tough, but it's happened before."</p>
        <p>That anniversary turned into yet another snow holiday from work and schools as tens of thousands of people in the New York City region bowed to the elements. Sledding replaced studying; shoveling snow replaced pushing papers. Roads throughout the area had light traffic as a result, making plowing easier.  [ Page B8. ]</p>
        <p>With sunny skies and temperatures in the mid-20's predicted for today, there were even some who were hoping for more snow. At Newark Airport, which was closed much of Tuesday and reopened yesterday with some flights delayed, Tyler Orwig was on his way to Colorado with skis in hand. "The snow is better there," he said.</p>
        <p>There was plenty of carping, too. But Marshall Robert of Lawrenceville, N.J., breakfasting at the Colonial Diner on Route 1, issued this advisory: "It's winter, people. Remember that. As much as everyone likes to complain, remember it snows in the winter and rains in the summer." Some Exquisite Timing</p>
        <p>Even snow apologists like Mr. Robert have to admit that this winter has been extreme. And Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University, not only confirms that the perception of the woeful weather is accurate, but he offers an explanation for why this year is different from most other years.</p>
        <p>"There has been some exquisite timing going on up in the atmosphere," said Mr. Gadomski, expressing wonder at the weather that has many cursing.</p>
        <p>He said that in most winters, cold air masses from central Canada and warm air flows from the southern United States have alternated, causing precipitation only when they overlapped. But this year, he said, opposing air masses have settled over the region simultaneously and frequently, causing the repeated periods of cold and snow.</p>
        <p>"This winter, there have been unusually frequent marriages between the cold air masses and the warm surges," Mr. Gadomski said.</p>
        <p>And why does that happen after years of mild, relatively dry winters? 'There Is No Because'</p>
        <p>"You always arrive at a point where you can't explain it any further," he said. "You reach the point where there is no because to the why. It just becomes a matter of chance."</p>
        <p>Chance seems to follow a pattern too. The late 1950's and 1960's were a period of relatively heavy snow in the Northeast, Mr. Gadomski said, followed by relatively low levels of snowfall in the early to mid-1970's. In turn, 1977, 1978 and 1979 were again years of high snowfall. The 1980's, particularly late in the decade, through the early 1990's had unusually dry and moderate winters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gadomski says he has heard from many Baby Boomers that they remember heavy snows during their childhoods in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>"If you're a boomer and you thought it snowed more when you were a kid, you're right," he said. "Although I've never met anyone who didn't think there was more snow when they were younger. It's a perception. As time goes by you don't remember the mild weather; you remember the spectacular snowfalls. And indeed, we were shorter."</p>
        <p>In Princeton, Mr. Ludlum, who has a doctorate in American history and spent his career selling equipment for predicting the weather and writing books about its history, said yesterday, "People don't have any memory, meteorologically." More Mammoth Snowfalls</p>
        <p>At the age of 83, that does not seem to be his problem, and he said history records an ebb and flow of periods of extreme weather. And looking way back into history reveals what a trivial event this weather really is.</p>
        <p>"Remember we had the ice age when northern New Jersey and New York were covered by thousands of feet of snow and that was only 10,000 years ago," Mr. Ludlum said. "We're in an interglacial period. I expect there will be another ice age -- I'm not a real geologist, but probably within 10,000 years."</p>
        <p>But for those living in real time, wondering whether it's a loafer or Totes kind of day, there are more immediate concerns.</p>
        <p>Here's one from Stephen H. Schneider, a Stanford University biologist, who says there is a possibility -- and he stresses possibility -- that global warming, caused in part by the spewing of chemicals into the atmosphere could be enhancing the variable weather patterns that exist naturally to begin with.</p>
        <p>"Nonuniform heat changes will give rise to nonuniform changes in wind patterns, which by definition is bizarre weather," he said. "We've tweaked the system in so many ways I think it's unreasonable to rule out that we may have had an effect." The Televangelist Theory</p>
        <p>All of which returns to Ms. Milliner's constant suggestion through a bullhorn in Times Square that prayer for redemption is in order.</p>
        <p>Don't expect prayers on the subject from Lawrence Cunningham, a former Roman Catholic priest who is now the chairman of the theology department at the University of Notre Dame. While channel surfing, he has heard the televangelist theory that the earthquakes and floods and ice and snow and mudslides are all messages from on high.</p>
        <p>He even heard it from his mother -- somewhat offhandedly, he said -- after the California earthquake.</p>
        <p>"She said, 'I think maybe God is trying to tell us something,' " Mr. Cunningham said. "I tend to be a post-Enlightenment person who thinks there was a fissure that needed to adjust itself."</p>
        <p>Indeed he sees nothing apocalyptic in all the natural forces at work in the country. But he's not without worries.</p>
        <p>"If I would look for portents that civilization is going to end I would not look towards the weather," Mr. Cunningham said, "but to the fact that the Bobbitts are on TV."</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 11, 1994, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the severity of this winter's weather misstated the date of the coldest temperature recorded in New York City; a reading of minus 15 was recorded on Feb. 9, 1934, not Feb. 9, 1936. The article also misidentified a diner in New Jersey where a patron, Marshall Robert, talked about the snow. It was the Princetonian Diner in West Windsor, not the Colonial in Lawrenceville.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 11, 1994, Friday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the severity of this winter's weather misstated the date of the coldest temperature recorded in New York City; a reading of minus 15 was recorded on Feb. 9, 1934, not Feb. 9, 1936. The article also misidentified a diner in New Jersey where a patron, Marshall Robert, talked about the snow. It was the Princetonian Diner in West Windsor, not the Colonial in Lawrenceville.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
