<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If the Truth Be Told</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="686131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE NIGHT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARTIES (SOCIAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAW, DAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DA1F30F93BA35756C0A962958260" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If the Truth Be Told</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dan Shaw</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHAW, DAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Uptown -- In the Celeste Bartos Forum of the New York Public Library on April 28, Steven Brill's three children were eating chateaubriand with their babysitter at the 15th-birthday party for The American Lawyer, the muckraking magazine founded by their father. Since Mr. Brill is also the founder of Court TV, the trial-oriented cable station, his daughters speak with the candor of children who have heard the phrase, "Do you promise to tell the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth . . ." many times in their young lives.</p>
        <p>Sophie, 9, said her favorite Court TV case was the trial of Erik and Lyle Menendez, who claimed to have murdered their parents in self-defense. "I think they are guilty," she said with conviction. "If their parents really did abuse them, they can only claim self-defense if they were threatened right on the spot when they killed them."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Uptown -- In the Celeste Bartos Forum of the New York Public Library on April 28, Steven Brill's three children were eating chateaubriand with their babysitter at the 15th-birthday party for The American Lawyer, the muckraking magazine founded by their father. Since Mr. Brill is also the founder of Court TV, the trial-oriented cable station, his daughters speak with the candor of children who have heard the phrase, "Do you promise to tell the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth . . ." many times in their young lives.</p>
        <p>Sophie, 9, said her favorite Court TV case was the trial of Erik and Lyle Menendez, who claimed to have murdered their parents in self-defense. "I think they are guilty," she said with conviction. "If their parents really did abuse them, they can only claim self-defense if they were threatened right on the spot when they killed them."</p>
        <p>Sophie, not surprisingly, plans to go to law school, but she doesn't want to be an attorney. "I'll probably go into politics," she said.</p>
        <p>Her sister, Emily, 11, won't even be going to law school. "I don't take that much interest in what my dad does," she said. "It's kind of boring. It's too real."</p>
        <p>"I'm definitely going to be an actress and a singer," she continued, as her 5-year-old-brother, Sam, in a blue blazer and tie, nodded as though he'd heard this before. "I really like Madonna. 'Material Girl' is my favorite pop-rock song. I know all the words really well. I've listened to it since I was 2."</p>
        <p>MTV, apparently, has been more important to her than Court TV. Mellowing With Age</p>
        <p>Several of the guests at the 20th-anniversary party for High Times, the magazine that celebrates and consecrates hemp and marijuana, were stone-cold sober.</p>
        <p>"Everyone assumes I'm a pothead because I have dreads and the whole nine," said Eric Coles, 29, a music-industry executive who was a guest at the party on April 27, at Ten, a club on East 60th Street. "Fortunately for me, I'm mellow and happy most of the time. When I get stoned, I get so mellow I just fall asleep."</p>
        <p>Mr. Coles's colleague, Robert Jerald, 23, a Los Angeles-based songwriter, doesn't use marijuana either. "I've smoked pot three times, and actually, I liked it," he said. "It's more of a religious thing with me. I don't believe in drinking or using substances that alter your senses."</p>
        <p>Mr. Coles took a cellular phone out of his leather backpack. "I thought twice about pulling it out in a roomful of natural, earthy granola people who would frown on my using it," he said.</p>
        <p>He need not have worried. While there were plenty of hip-hop hippies at the party, many marijuana advocates now resemble conservatives more than they do members of the counterculture. "There are a lot of people who you'd expect to smoke pot who don't," said Richard Cowan, the balding, 53-year-old national director of Norml, the National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws, who wore a tie and jacket. "And there are a lot who you'd never expect who do -- and not all of them are in Washington!"</p>
        <p>John Holmstrom, 41, the balding, button-downed publisher of High Times, does not smoke pot these days either. "I'm in an off period," said Mr. Holmstrom, who also wore a jacket and tie to the party. "I got busted for smoking hash with five friends when I was 16. The police ripped the car apart. It made me paranoid forever! It ruined my life! I had to miss Woodstock because I had to go to court."</p>
        <p>Queens -- Lily Auchincloss, Anne Bass, Claire Bloom, Issey Miyake and 200 others journeyed to the rough-hewn warehouse district of Long Island City on April 30 to see Robert Wilson perform at a benefit at the Isamu Noguchi Garden Museum.</p>
        <p>But getting people to visit the museum, whose galleries and garden contain more than 200 of Noguchi's sculptures, along with photographs and models of his gardens, fountains, playgrounds and stage sets, is one of the great challenges for Bruce J. Altshuler, the museum's director. "It's such an effort to come out here that when people do come, they really spend time here," he said. "You don't just run in for 15 minutes."</p>
        <p>Noguchi, who died in 1988 at age 84, has recently been turned into a pop-culture icon, which may attract a new generation of museum-goers.</p>
        <p>"Have you seen the Gap ad?" asked Priscilla Morgan, a museum trustee, at the reception after Mr. Wilson's performance. Like Picasso, Hemingway and Kerouac, Noguchi wore khakis.</p>
        <p>The Bronx -- On Monday, Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan was following through on some legislation, checking up on the plans for the new library and herbarium at the New York Botanical Garden. He was being honored at the garden's Founders Award dinner-dance for having secured more than $5 million in Federal funds for the $32 million project.</p>
        <p>"When do you start building?" he asked Gregory Long, the garden's president, during a V.I.P. tour before dinner.</p>
        <p>"We'll dig the hole in the fall of '95," Mr. Long told him.</p>
        <p>"The sooner you start digging, the sooner you'll get the money," Mr. Moynihan reminded him.</p>
        <p>In a reading room, Dr. Brian M. Boom, the garden's vice president for botanical science, showed him some lichens from 1925. "They're indicators of air quality," he explained.</p>
        <p>"I'm more of an acid rain fellow myself," Mr. Moynihan said, laughing at his own joke. "We just spent $1 billion on acid rain, and I think every penny was wasted."</p>
        <p>The Senator, who is often called the most intellectual member of Congress, seemed genuinely curious about everything. "What's epiphytic mean?" the Senator asked as he examined some old documents.</p>
        <p>"Plants that grow on other plants," Dr. Boom said, and the Senator smiled, happy to have added a word to his vocabulary.  THE NIGHT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
