<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Does Viewer Discretion Begin?</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="680881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CORCORAN GALLERY OF ART (WASHINGTON, DC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, VICKI</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PERESS, GILLES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1D7133EF934A25757C0A962958260" item-length="1515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Does Viewer Discretion Begin?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vicki Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, VICKI</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE SIGN ON THE DOOR SAYS: "This exhibition contains stark images of war. Viewer discretion is advised." The show is "Farewell to Bosnia: New Photographs by Gilles Peress" at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, some of the images are stark enough, and the idea that we should view Bosnia with discretion adds a mordant note to the politics of art.</p>
        <p>A wall labeled "Dismemberment" includes the image of a young boy, his face tactfully left out of the picture, holding up two stumps at the ends of his arms; a man on an operating table, fully awake, his entire leg clamped open and displaying its secret structures; and on a shelf in the prosthetic unit, three gleaming feet made of some up-to-date synthetic, the toenails meticulously drawn in.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE SIGN ON THE DOOR SAYS: "This exhibition contains stark images of war. Viewer discretion is advised." The show is "Farewell to Bosnia: New Photographs by Gilles Peress" at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, some of the images are stark enough, and the idea that we should view Bosnia with discretion adds a mordant note to the politics of art.</p>
        <p>A wall labeled "Dismemberment" includes the image of a young boy, his face tactfully left out of the picture, holding up two stumps at the ends of his arms; a man on an operating table, fully awake, his entire leg clamped open and displaying its secret structures; and on a shelf in the prosthetic unit, three gleaming feet made of some up-to-date synthetic, the toenails meticulously drawn in.</p>
        <p>The rest of the show (on view through May 2), though well stocked with dead bodies, is more concerned with loss and breakage and dislocation, the jagged destruction of normal ways of life, the dark foreclosure of futures. It is part of a long-term project Peress calls "Hate Thy Brother," about the re-emergence of ethnic conflict in postwar Europe.</p>
        <p>Peress, who was born in France in 1946, has an eye for oppressive realities and a keen sense of the symbolic weight of fragments, incongruities and tilted horizons. His black-and-white pictures are universally stark but for the most part neither bloody nor violent. Dark, with little detail in the shadows, abrupt and chaotic even when relatively calmly composed, they have an atmosphere of grayness and grit that seems polluted far beyond the potential of acid rain.</p>
        <p>Item: neatly tied plastic body bags carefully lined up behind a branch of flowering rhododendron. Item: the body of a man in a business suit at the morgue. His shoes, magnified by a close camera, are thrust in the viewer's face; his legs are too loosely twisted, as if he were a doll with poorly made joints. Item: an inconsequential, trash-lined, black and deserted street, in what might be one of the better residential neighborhoods in hell, viewed through a windshield blurred by small, dirty smudges of falling snow.</p>
        <p>Stark enough. My own reaction to all this was less shocked -- after the many high-color television horrors -- than oppressed, weighed down, hopeless, vaguely guilty. Where does viewer discretion begin? Television movies sometimes flash an advisory, but the news, capable of far greater grisliness, usually just announces that viewers who stay tuned are fair game for confrontations. Sometimes the screen says, "Material for mature audiences." Where do we find them?</p>
        <p>And when did museums start issuing warnings about the content of their shows? Sex probably brought this on -- the Whitney's 1988 Mapplethorpe show carried a warning -- and Jesse Helms made it urgent. The 1993 Whitney Biennial had a viewer advisory, and the Met's Lucian Freud show cautioned that it might be considered inappropriate for children, surely the best argument for viewer discretion. The Hayward Gallery in London recently mailed out warnings to protect delicate sensibilities from Salvador Dali.</p>
        <p>Violence gets greater leeway. I don't recall any curator ever cautioning people about Goya's "Desastres de la Guerra," infinitely more brutal than Peress's photographs, or about work by Max Beckmann or George Grosz. Yet photographs, still generally dependent on actual occurrences, are more threatening: they present facts without the filters imposed by painting and printmaking.</p>
        <p>And times have changed. Now that it is tacitly agreed that no one must be offended, almost everyone is. Overwhelmed by images, people are increasingly aware of their unsettling power. Images are powerful, possibly even dangerous: art is subversive, photographs propagandistic, television relentless.</p>
        <p>Peress speculates that Yugoslavian memories of World War II were so grim that people were forced to relive them. In a letter from Bosnia that will be published in the forthcoming book of this work, he speaks of "mental images so horrific that one is compelled to actually 'see' them to deal with them. And to see them, you have to act them out" -- a stunning claim for images.</p>
        <p>But at least in situations short of war their power has its limits, and only the potential for taking offense does not. Like doctors warding off malpractice suits, some museums feel constrained to limit their liabilities. The International Center of Photography's discreet sign about Eugene Richards's "Cocaine True, Cocaine Blue" and Andrew Savulich's "Urban Realities" begins: "These exhibitions contain photographs that some individuals may find disturbing . . ."</p>
        <p>"Some individuals may" just about covers the waterfront. Perhaps all museums should have blazoned on their doors, "Viewer Discretion Suggested." Severed heads at the Met! Naked women at the Modern!</p>
        <p>Then there is the question of what kind of material belongs in a museum anyway. Museums were originally founded to preserve and display works of art from the past, not the news of the day, but the very concept of the museum is in process of change. Art is a much more elastic term than it was, partly because of photography, which by its nature makes the traditional definitions quaver. Walker Evans was a documentarian and W. Eugene Smith a photojournalist, and both stand alongside art photographers and artists on museum walls.</p>
        <p>Peress's photographs of Bosnia are poised somewhere between photojournalism and art. They superimpose his own harsh, disjunctive, off-balance style on the language of photographers who changed the rules in the not-so-distant past: the scratchy surfaces and impenetrable blacks of Robert Frank, the rude close-ups and abrupt perspectives of William Klein. A photograph of a city through a window pierced by a bullet hole looks like a wartime commentary on an Andre Kertesz picture of Paris with the hole of a broken photographic plate at its center.</p>
        <p>Peress emphasizes the art-non-art character of his photographs by neither framing nor isolating them in the standard museum manner. These large-scale, 30-by-40 photographs, each ringed with the black outline of the negative carrier, circle the room in lines two or three pictures deep, butted together like a story board and fixed to the wall with grommets. The result is like a film without a narrative, a succession of frames arbitrarily lifted out of an ongoing disaster. (The exhibition was organized by Philip Brookman, curator of photography and media arts at the Corcoran, and Urs Stahel, director of the Foto museum Winterthur in Switzerland, where a duplicate show closed last month.)</p>
        <p>BOSNIA IS NOT MERELY THE nightly news; it is a moral dilemma for our times, and it is here that the new and emerging character of the museum is put to the test. How deeply should museums engage in debates of politics and conscience? Political art runs riot in certain places -- the Whitney Biennial, the New Museum -- but seldom does it have any guts or clout, any power or conviction. (A useful rule of thumb: any work of art that can be discussed primarily in terms of deconstruction will not have a strong political impact.) Photographs specifically tackle the issues: Salvador, Kuwait on fire. Putting Bosnian lives and deaths so forthrightly on the wall links the museum directly to international tensions and personal conscience.</p>
        <p>It is probably impossible to look at such images without being revolted by the atrocities there and the sense that somehow lives could have been saved if only the lessons of the past had been learned. So this show is a kind of appeal to rethink a tangled issue -- not before the flash of blood on the screen, not within earshot of government officials mulling the costs, but in a setting dedicated to conserving the achievements of civilization.</p>
        <p>Sometime in the 60's, museums began to pay attention to a larger community. Recently a few have been far more involved in current affairs and have invited more active viewer participation. When the National Endowment for the Arts was attacked, the Brooklyn Museum addressed postcards to Congressmen, asked visitors to sign them, then sent them to Washington. After the Corcoran ducked on the Mapplethorpe show, the Cincinnati Museum took up the challenge and became the eye of the storm. Museums all over the country participate in the Day Without Art, and in Boston, the Museum of Fine Arts asked visitors to write about how AIDS had changed their lives, then displayed the results for a week.</p>
        <p>The Corcoran is trying to make connections by putting out pen and paper and asking people to "respond to this exhibit and share your thoughts with the people of Bosnia"; the letters will be sent on. Peress is one of many documentary photographers who, conscious that the national magazines no longer have much use for them, seek new ways to keep their dialogue and their work alive. He has spoken about his hope that museums may be the basis for another kind of community, where ideas can be exchanged. It's a wonderful, perhaps a utopian idea, that art and images should be a meeting ground for a thoughtful populace.  PHOTOGRAPHY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
