<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Technology; Rethinking Plastics From the Ground Up</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="711406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIORDAN, TERESA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DESIMONE, JOSEPH (PROF)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DC1F38F932A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Technology; Rethinking Plastics From the Ground Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERESA RIORDAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RIORDAN, TERESA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FROM diapers to fast-food packaging, plastics have long been reviled by the environmentally conscious for their propensity to sit in landfills for decades without breaking down.</p>
        <p>Yet some say the pollutants and waste created in the process of manufacturing plastics pose a greater environmental threat than what happens to them after they have been discarded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FROM diapers to fast-food packaging, plastics have long been reviled by the environmentally conscious for their propensity to sit in landfills for decades without breaking down.</p>
        <p>Yet some say the pollutants and waste created in the process of manufacturing plastics pose a greater environmental threat than what happens to them after they have been discarded.</p>
        <p>The United States plastics industry generated 567 million pounds of toxic waste in 1992, according to the Environmental Protection Agency, which began recording the levels of industry waste in 1991. About one-quarter of the plastic industry's 1992 waste was released directly into the nation's land, air and water.</p>
        <p>Now Joseph DeSimone -- an associate professor at the University of North Carolina in Chapel Hill who at 30 is a Wunderkind of chemical engineering -- has come up with an environmentally friendly way to make the polymers that are formed into plastics by using a form of carbon dioxide, the benign gas found in carbonated beverages ranging from beer to champagne.</p>
        <p>The process, Professor DeSimone says, holds great potential for lessening the environmental burden, but perhaps just as important is the promise it offers for creating new materials "whose use we haven't yet imagined."</p>
        <p>Professor DeSimone, who published a paper on the new process this summer in the journal Science, presented his research last month at the American Chemical Society's national meeting in Washington.</p>
        <p>The work already has generated a lot of interest in the chemical industry. So far, four companies -- Du Pont, Hoechst Celanese, Air Products and Chemicals, and Eastman Chemical -- are participating in a consortium that is financing further research in Professor DeSimone's laboratory. Several other companies are expected to sign on to the consortium soon. In exchange for underwriting the research, the companies retain the option to license different aspects of the technology, which received its first patent in May.</p>
        <p>For Professor DeSimone, success has come early. He received his doctorate only four years ago at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University in Blacksburg, and last year he was among 15 American scientists whom the White House named Presidential Faculty Fellows.</p>
        <p>To continue his work with so-called supercritical carbon dioxide -- a pressurized form of the gas that has some unusual liquid-like properties -- this year Professor DeSimone received one of the first grants to be given out under the Environmentally Benign Chemical Synthesis and Processing program, a new effort jointly administered by the National Science Foundation, the main Federal financing agency for basic science research, and the E.P.A.</p>
        <p>The first supercritical fluid was concocted more than 100 years ago, but supercritical fluids did not command attention until the 1970's, when they were widely touted as a way to reduce energy consumption by replacing chemical solvents, most of which are petroleum-based and take enormous amounts of energy to distill.</p>
        <p>The unique properties of supercritical fluids can make them ideal solvents. By changing the amount of pressure or the temperature, a chemist can adjust the fluid's density -- that is, how closely its molecules are packed together -- and therefore how well it might dissolve a given substance. By contrast, the density of the liquid is fixed and cannot be manipulated.</p>
        <p>Although the food industry has made use of supercritical carbon dioxide to decaffeinate coffee, purify spices and extract oils from hops to make beer, the supercritical bandwagon lost momentum by the early 1980's. By then the energy crisis had receded from memory and it had become abundantly clear that, given the expensive equipment needed to pressurize supercritical fluids, petroleum-based solvents were still the cheapest way to go.</p>
        <p>BUT in the last couple of years, supercritical fluids, in particular carbon dioxide, have been resurrected, this time not as energy savers but as environmental saviors in an era when industry generally faces increased regulatory scrutiny on the production of hazardous byproducts.</p>
        <p>"Supercritical carbon dioxide is an exciting area because it's nonpolluting," said Margaret A. Cavanaugh, a program director in the division of chemistry at the National Science Foundation. "If you can find a way for it to be used in a lot of chemical processes, it would be a major reduction in the use of petroleum solvents."</p>
        <p>Currently, huge quantities of chemical solvents are used by the pharmaceutical, chemical and polymer industries to extract, separate and manufacture chemicals and to carry out or ease reactions.</p>
        <p>In one example of the way supercritical carbon dioxide can be used in place of chemical solvents, Union Carbide now uses it as a thinner for industrial spray-painting. As a result, the company has reduced hazardous emissions associated with that process by as much as 80 percent.</p>
        <p>Professor DeSimone, however, is pursuing what some consider a more difficult end: using supercritical carbon dioxide not just to dilute or extract, but to effect entirely new chemical reactions.</p>
        <p>"He's a superstar," said Val J. Krukonis, a co-author of "Supercritical Fluid Extraction" and president of the Phasex Corporation, a company based in Lawrence, Mass., that specializes in technologies based on supercritical fluids. "He's one of the few polymer chemists who understands the potential of supercritical carbon dioxide. He's using it to make new methods and new materials."</p>
        <p>Traditionally in the early phase of plastics production, molecules called monomers are suspended or dissolved into either a chemical solvent or plain water along with a so-called linking agent. The monomers are chemically attached, much like beads on a string, into long lengths of polymers -- which eventually can be formed into plastics, rubbers and fibers.</p>
        <p>The current methods of production, however, generate large amounts of solvent and water waste.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Professor DeSimone's approach uses supercritical carbon dioxide as the solvent. When the polymers have been formed, the pressure is turned down, allowing the carbon dioxide to return to its gaseous form and to be vented off. Much of the gas can then be recycled.</p>
        <p>In 1992 Professor DeSimone's research team first demonstrated that fluoropolymers, which are Teflon-like materials, could be made with supercritical carbon dioxide. But the scientists ran into problems trying to make other more common polymers like acrylic. For example, methyl methacrylate monomers, used to make plexiglass, would dissolve easily enough but would grow into only very short strands of polymers before becoming insoluble again.</p>
        <p>To find a way to keep the polymers dispersed until they grew to more desirable lengths, Professor DeSimone's research team turned to surfactants, chemicals that form the basis of detergents and have long been used to keep molecules evenly dispersed in solution.</p>
        <p>For methyl methacrylate, Professor DeSimone and his team designed a special surfactant that at one end had an affinity for carbon dioxide, and therefore dissolved easily, and at the other end had an affinity for the growing polymers and not the carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>"The breakthrough was finding the right surfactant," said Professor DeSimone, whose research team is testing about 30 different surfactants tailored to different polymers.</p>
        <p>In addition to its environmental advantages, supercritical carbon dioxide promises to allow chemists to create new types of polymers. Unlike regular solvents, it does not interact with growing polymers, a property that might allow chemists to exert more control over the type of polymers being developed.</p>
        <p>"There are lots of people interested in making particles of controlled size, and there aren't too many technologies that can do that," Professor DeSimone said.</p>
        <p>In addition, Professor DeSimone said, the gas-like properties of supercritical carbon dioxide allow it to slip in between molecules, holding out the promise that it might be used to create specialized porous polymers for use in pharmaceuticals, herbicides and cosmetics.</p>
        <p>Despite the apparent advantages of the new technology, it still faces a big hurdle that kept supercritical fluids from taking off longer than a decade ago: the capitalization costs of specialized, high-pressure equipment.</p>
        <p>But as George A. Serad, a technology manager with Hoechst-Celanese in Charlotte, N.C., points out, "The equipment is expensive, but then so are the clean-up costs associated with traditional methods."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
