<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>California Regulators To Meet on Electric Cars</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="686782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC VEHICLES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2D71039F931A25756C0A962958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>California Regulators To Meet on Electric Cars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California's air-quality regulators will meet today and tomorrow in Los Angeles to decide whether their requirement that auto makers put tens of thousands of "zero emission vehicles" -- electric cars -- into dealer showrooms in three and a half years is still a good idea.</p>
        <p>The meeting, a review by the California Air Resources Board to determine if the state's four-year-old program is technologically feasible, has national significance because the plan has been adopted by New York and Massachusetts, and 10 other Eastern states and the District of Columbia are trying to join it. By Federal law, states that adopt the California plan, which is the national model, are automatically bound by later revision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California's air-quality regulators will meet today and tomorrow in Los Angeles to decide whether their requirement that auto makers put tens of thousands of "zero emission vehicles" -- electric cars -- into dealer showrooms in three and a half years is still a good idea.</p>
        <p>The meeting, a review by the California Air Resources Board to determine if the state's four-year-old program is technologically feasible, has national significance because the plan has been adopted by New York and Massachusetts, and 10 other Eastern states and the District of Columbia are trying to join it. By Federal law, states that adopt the California plan, which is the national model, are automatically bound by later revision.</p>
        <p>Early indications are that California will stay with its requirement that 2 percent of the cars offered for sale in the 1998 model year be electric, rising to 5 percent in 2001 and 10 percent in 2003. But no one really knows. A Change in Atmosphere</p>
        <p>The review, an event scheduled every other year, takes place in an atmosphere that has changed from the time the program began in September 1990; California is barely emerging from a deep economic slump for which business people partly blame costly government regulation. And the chairwoman of the California Air Resources Board, Jananne Sharpless, who championed the program, has been replaced by Jacqueline E. Schaefer, a former environmental official in the Reagan and Bush Administrations.</p>
        <p>"People are holding their cards pretty close to the vest," said Diane Wittenberg, manager of electric transportation for Southern California Edison, a big backer of electric cars.</p>
        <p>Electric utilities, the conventional auto makers and a raft of fledgling companies that make electric cars are watching the review closely. Some environmentalists plan to argue that California's plan is crucial to worldwide reductions in conventional pollutants and carbon dioxide, which scientists believe to be responsible for climate change.  A Plea From Auto Makers</p>
        <p>At the two-day public meeting, perhaps 100 speakers are expected to offer their views. Auto manufacturers will plead for the dropping of the requirement that they offer for sale a number of electric vehicles equal to 2 percent of their projected sales for the 1998 model year.</p>
        <p>After the meeting, the 11-member Air Resources Board could leave the standards in place, or it could schedule a hearing, which would signal a desire to amend them. Decisions of the board, an independent agency, can be appealed only to the courts.</p>
        <p>The board's staff has predicted that electric cars will sell well. But critics say Californians may like the idea in the abstract, but not when it comes to buying a car. "There's no consumer demand for them in the magnitude" that the California Air Resources Board wants to mandate them, said Douglas F. Henderson, executive director of the Western States Petroleum Association, an oil industry group. "It seems to us to be a program that's doomed to fail." 'Poison the Well'</p>
        <p>Ford voiced a related fear. Albert M. Chambers, a spokesman for the company, said that if the auto maker was forced to market the cars, it would do so because "we don't break the law." But the vehicle would perform so poorly, he said, that it would "poison the well" for electric vehicle technology. The company has been working on a sodium-sulfur battery, which Mr. Chambers said would propel an electric car or van almost as far as consumers would expect, but he added, "the cost is off the chart."</p>
        <p>Ford plans to ask the board today to negotiate a program whereby electric vehicles would be sold for use in fleets, like delivery trucks, rather than to the general public. Ford would also be willing to sell to electric-car companies new cars without gas tanks, engines and drivetrains, for conversion, if legal issues could be resolved. Ford wants to insure that it has no warranty or liability responsibility, and that the finished product is not labeled "Ford."  New Battery Technologies</p>
        <p>But the board's staff says it thinks electric cars will be ready for general use by the 1998 model year. Batteries needed for a successful electric car are not in mass production, the staff said, but three technologies seem likely to bear fruit by then. They are nickel-metal hydride batteries, developed by the Ovonic Battery Company, of Troy, Mich., and now coming to market in laptop computers; sodium-nickel-chloride batteries being developed by the AEG Corporation, of Somerville, N.J., a subsidiary of Daimler-Benz, and sodium-sulfur batteries, which are already in use in demonstration vehicles built by the Ford Motor Company.</p>
        <p>Leading the board as it reviews the decision is Ms. Schaefer, who served in various environmental posts in the Reagan and Bush Administrations.</p>
        <p>In January, she said to reporters at the Los Angeles Auto Show that "I have a bias toward retaining the ZEV rule," -- ZEV referring to zero-emission vehicle. In testimony before a committee of the State Legislature in Sacramento in March, she said that in the long run electric vehicles would work only if a free market developed for them.</p>
        <p>But, she said, "While these vehicles may not have the same range as a gasoline car, I think you'd be surprised at how well they perform."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
