<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; A Bleak Vision</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="673057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC MONTHLY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAPLAN, ROBERT D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3DA1F3AF934A35750C0A962958260" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; A Bleak Vision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A particular nightmare, for most human beings, would be to live in a society without order of any kind, without predictability: in a country that has no effective government, subject to crime and disease and primitive rapacity without recourse to any saving authority.</p>
        <p>That is the future foreseen for much of the world in an extraordinarily chilling and, alas, compelling article. It is "The Coming Anarchy" by Robert D. Kaplan, who has reported from many parts of the world and written among other books "Balkan Ghosts." His anti-utopian vision of the future appeared in the February Atlantic Monthly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A particular nightmare, for most human beings, would be to live in a society without order of any kind, without predictability: in a country that has no effective government, subject to crime and disease and primitive rapacity without recourse to any saving authority.</p>
        <p>That is the future foreseen for much of the world in an extraordinarily chilling and, alas, compelling article. It is "The Coming Anarchy" by Robert D. Kaplan, who has reported from many parts of the world and written among other books "Balkan Ghosts." His anti-utopian vision of the future appeared in the February Atlantic Monthly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan's theme is that maps, with their neat boundaries and colors, have less and less to do with reality in the third world. Borders and the very states they supposedly contain are disintegrating under the pressures of poverty, population growth, lawlessness and the resulting chaos.</p>
        <p>The oncoming reality is exemplified by West Africa, Mr. Kaplan says. In both the French- and English-speaking states hardwood forests are being cut down at an accelerating rate, and populations are moving from the interior to the littoral towns, where they live in unending shantytowns presenting "a Dickensian spectacle to which Dickens himself would never have given credence." Rebellion and massacre flow across national boundaries, and government's writ does not run outside a few towns -- in the daytime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan sees West Africa becoming "the symbol of worldwide demographic, environmental and societal stress, in which criminal anarchy emerges as the real 'strategic' danger." He sees a world of "disease, overpopulation, unprovoked crime, scarcity of resources, refugee migrations, the increasing erosion of nation states . . ."</p>
        <p>As a grim example he describes Sierra Leone, which was once a pleasant small West African country. Now it is riven by half a dozen armies and local warlords. There can be -- there is -- no law.</p>
        <p>"Sierra Leone is a microcosm of what is occurring, albeit in a more tempered and gradual manner," Mr. Kaplan writes, "throughout West Africa and much of the underdeveloped world: the withering away of central governments, the rise of tribal and regional domains, the unchecked spread of disease and the growing pervasiveness of war."</p>
        <p>When there are riots and other violent upheavals around the world, he says, the press ascribes them to ethnic and religious conflicts. "But as these conflicts multiply, it will become apparent that something else is afoot, making more and more places like Nigeria, India and Brazil ungovernable."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan's "something else" begins with environmental scarcity. He recognizes that many Americans yawn at the word environment, or mock it as Rush Limbaugh does. But he argues, I think persuasively, that it is "the national-security issue of the early 21st century."</p>
        <p>"The political and strategic impact of surging populations, spreading disease, deforestation and soil erosion, water depletion, air pollution and, possibly, rising sea levels in critical, overcrowded regions like the Nile Delta and Bangladesh -- developments that will prompt mass migrations and, in turn, incite group conflicts -- will be the core foreign policy challenge."</p>
        <p>Over the next 50 years the earth's population is expected to grow from the present 5.5 billion people to more than 9 billion. If all the world had the agricultural and industrial levels of the developed countries, that growth might be manageable. But 95 percent of the increase will be in the world's poorest regions, where governments have trouble functioning as it is.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaplan cites India and Pakistan as countries where the question of democracy "is less and less relevant to the larger issue of governability." He asks whether the central bureaucracy in New Delhi is the best mechanism to improve the lives of the diverse peoples of India: 866 million now, approaching 1.5 billion by 2025.</p>
        <p>Given overworked crop lands, declining water levels and communal tensions, he says, "it is difficult to imagine that the Indian state will survive the next century."</p>
        <p>Is Mr. Kaplan too gloomy? Probably he is. Human beings have astonishing resilience, and so do their political constructs. Recent trends in India and parts of Latin America have been favorable at least on the surface. But Mr. Kaplan's assessment reminds us that there are longer-run concerns, showing us convincingly that the real issues of the future are not those that preoccupy us today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
