<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. to Require Cleaner-Burning Gas in Polluted Areas</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHANOL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY (EPA)  ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTIONAGENCY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethanol</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE7DC1739F932A35754C0A962958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. to Require Cleaner-Burning Gas in Polluted Areas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency said today that beginning next year it will require that gasoline used in areas with severe air pollution contain more  oxygen to make it burn cleaner, and that at least some of the additive come from renewable sources.</p>
        <p>By doing so, the Clinton Administration opened the way for ethanol to play a  significant part in providing a cleaner-burning gasoline for the smoggiest cities. Ethanol, also known as grain alcohol, is produced from corn and is the only renewable oxygenate that can meet the volumes demanded by the clean gasoline program.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency said today that beginning next year it will require that gasoline used in areas with severe air pollution contain more  oxygen to make it burn cleaner, and that at least some of the additive come from renewable sources.</p>
        <p>By doing so, the Clinton Administration opened the way for ethanol to play a  significant part in providing a cleaner-burning gasoline for the smoggiest cities. Ethanol, also known as grain alcohol, is produced from corn and is the only renewable oxygenate that can meet the volumes demanded by the clean gasoline program.</p>
        <p>The agency's decision represents a significant victory for farmers. They stand to gain substantially from the sale of the estimated 230 million bushels of corn that will be needed to make the ethanol when the program goes into full  effect in 1996.</p>
        <p>Oil companies, which have favored a petroleum-based oxygenate made from methanol, have contended that the Government should not favor one fuel additive  over another. Industry analysts predict that the decision by the environmental agency to favor renewable energy like ethanol will probably be challenged in court and perhaps also in Congress.</p>
        <p>Diversifying Energy</p>
        <p>Carol M. Browner, the agency administrator, said the Administration sought to promote renewable energy, primarily ethanol, because "it is important to our efforts to diversify energy resources and promote energy independence."</p>
        <p>Ms. Browner said the cleaner gasoline would emit 15 percent fewer toxic and smog-causing pollutants than the fuel now used and "benefit the one in four Americans who are still breathing unhealthy air in our cities." The cleaner-burning gasoline will be required in the nine cities with the worst air  pollution, and more than a dozen states, primarily in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>The cities are New York, Philadelphia, Baltimore, Chicago, Houston, Los Angeles, Milwaukee, San Diego, and Hartford. So far, 11 Northeastern states from Maine to Virginia, as well as Texas, Kentucky and the District of Columbia, have agreed to require the cleaner-burning gasoline.</p>
        <p>The environmental agency has been caught in the middle of a debate over what  kind of oxygenate should be used and whether corn-based ethanol should be given  a preference over petroleum-based methanol.</p>
        <p>At stake are tens of millions of dollars for farmers. The new reformulated gasoline will account for about one-third, or about 37 billion gallons, of all the gasoline sold each year in the United States, beginning next January. It is  expected to add 3 cents to 5 cents a gallon to the cost of gasoline.</p>
        <p>The environmental agency will require that at least 15 percent of all of the  oxygenates in gasoline beginning next January be from renewable sources -- primarily ethanol or an ethanol derivative called ETBE. The portion of renewable oxygenate would be increased to 30 percent beginning in 1996. Phasing in the requirement is an effort to insure adequate supplies.</p>
        <p>Raise in Corn Price Seen</p>
        <p>Last year, farmers grew 476 million bushels of corn to produce nearly 1.2 billion gallons of ethanol. The American Farm Bureau has said the increase in demand could raise corn prices by as much as 10 cents a bushel, with farmers and ethanol producers reaping as much as $1.5 billion a year.</p>
        <p>Farmers and their political allies have waged an intense lobbying effort to have ethanol considered as an oxygenate, arguing that otherwise the petroleum-based MTBE, which is made from methanol, would dominate the multibillion-dollar oxygenate market.</p>
        <p>The petroleum industry has argued that the environmental agency should let the market determine what kind of oxygenate should be used. The industry argued  that ethanol would raise gasoline prices because it is more expensive to produce than MTBE. Ethanol supporters argue that the increased competition will eventually reduce gas prices.</p>
        <p>Members of Congress from farm states have also argued that the home-grown and renewable fuel additive will help the United States reduce its dependence on foreign oil and help the environment.</p>
        <p>But both of those claims have been challenged by environmentalists as well as the oil companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
