<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forget PCB's. Radon. Alar</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="60" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="711217"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THIRD WORLD AND DEVELOPING COUNTRIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">EASTERBROOK, GREGG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3DB1538F932A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="2826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forget PCB's. Radon. Alar</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gregg Easterbrook;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EASTERBROOK, GREGG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT ENVIRONMENTAL PROBLEMS kill human beings in huge numbers today? Not ozone depletion or Alar. What kills them is dung smoke and diarrhea.</p>
        <p>Throughout the world, many more people die each year from filthy air and dirty water than from asbestos, dioxin, electromagnetic radiation, nuclear wastes, PCB's, pesticide residues and ultraviolet rays -- the sorts of ecological issues that obsess Western environmentalists. Problems like dioxin and nuclear wastes are real enough and must be dealt with. But Western public consciousness and environmental groups continue to focus on such issues while all but ignoring millions of annual deaths from polluted air and water.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT ENVIRONMENTAL PROBLEMS kill human beings in huge numbers today? Not ozone depletion or Alar. What kills them is dung smoke and diarrhea.</p>
        <p>Throughout the world, many more people die each year from filthy air and dirty water than from asbestos, dioxin, electromagnetic radiation, nuclear wastes, PCB's, pesticide residues and ultraviolet rays -- the sorts of ecological issues that obsess Western environmentalists. Problems like dioxin and nuclear wastes are real enough and must be dealt with. But Western public consciousness and environmental groups continue to focus on such issues while all but ignoring millions of annual deaths from polluted air and water.</p>
        <p>Dangerous air levels have become almost unknown in the West, but 1.3 billion people in the developing world live in zones of dangerously unsafe air. According to the World Health Organization, last year 4 million third-world children under the age of 5 died from acute respiratory disease, brought on in most cases by air pollution. This is about as many people of all ages who died of all causes that year in the United States and the European Union combined.</p>
        <p>Urban air pollution is worse in Calcutta, Lagos and Mexico City than in any Western metropolis, including Los Angeles. The developing world also has an insidious form of air pollution unknown in the West: rural smog. "Most of the four million annual child deaths from respiratory distress stem from children living in poorly ventilated huts where fuel wood, cow dung or agricultural wastes are used for heating and cooking," says Gurinder Shahi, an official of the United Nations Development Program.</p>
        <p>In the third world, polluted air is more than matched by polluted water. Some one billion people lack access to drinking water that meets the crudest safety standards. Unicef reports that 3.8 million developing-world children under age 5 died last year from diarrheal diseases caused mostly by impure drinking water. In the West, diarrheal deaths are practically unknown; in the developing world, diarrhea kills far more people than cancer.</p>
        <p>Most of Africa, the Indian subcontinent and Latin America have no waste-water treatment facilities; raw human and industrial sewage is discharged directly into the same bodies of water used for drinking. Mothers draw for their children water of lower quality than the process effluent discharged from American factories. In India, ritual bathers enter the Ganges seeking spiritual purity while exposing their bodies to a wide range of toxicants and pathogens. In China, an estimated 25 billion tons of unfiltered industrial pollutants went directly into the waterways in 1991, which means there was more toxic water pollution in that one country than in the whole of the Western world.</p>
        <p>Yet such problems do not seem to be on the priority lists of Western environmentalists. "Things like African sewage are not sexy issues, so they always fall to the bottom of the agenda," says Deborah Moore, a staff scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund and one of the few Western environmentalists advocating a focus on basic third-world reform.</p>
        <p>A large faction within the environmental movement concentrates on the comparatively minor ecological problems of developed nations in order to support the view that Western materialism is the root of all ecological malevolence. The low point of such thinking was reached at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. There, institutional environmental groups got the attention of the world and its heads of state, but what message did they choose to proclaim? That global warming is a horror. The sole environmental area in which the United States is the leading malefactor is carbon dioxide emission, which contributes to the greenhouse effect; in virtually every other ecological category, America is the world leader in progress.</p>
        <p>To make Rio a fashionably negative event about Western guilt-tripping and America-bashing, the prospect of global warming was put above the urgent loss of lives in the third world from water and air pollution. Rio concluded with Western leaders' agreeing to devote billions of dollars to controlling global warming, while not lifting a finger for the 7.8 million poor children who die each year mainly from what they drink and breathe.</p>
        <p>ERIC CHIVIAN IS A psychiatrist on the faculty of Harvard Medical School. In the days of the arms race, he helped found International Physicians for the Prevention of Nuclear War, which in 1985 won the Nobel Peace Prize. When nuclear weapons began to be dismantled, Chivian enlarged his agenda to include pollution in the developing world. He has started a new program, the Project on Global Environmental Change and Health, and last year edited a powerful but little noticed technical book, "Critical Condition: Human Health and the Environment."</p>
        <p>Chivian finds that he can hardly get anyone interested in his new group. "I've had great difficulty interesting environmental organizations in human health in poor countries," he says. "They all want to talk about forest loss and species diversity in the South" -- the developing world -- "but have much less interest in human health there."</p>
        <p>Last year, notes Chivian, two teams of university researchers produced evidence that particulates -- fine bits of soot and ash caused by incomplete combustion -- were a much greater health threat than was previously realized. In the United States each year, particulates may account for 20,000 to 30,000 premature deaths due to respiratory failure. "Environmentalists in the United States were disturbed by this finding," Chivian says. "But if these studies are right, then the particulate emergency is happening in the third world, not here. The problem is a thousand times worse for them than for us."</p>
        <p>Under American law, particulates have long been closely regulated. Most developing nations do not regulate particulate emissions, even though the factories and vehicles in these countries employ the sort of inefficient engines likely to emit more soot. According to David Bates, a professor emeritus of medicine at the University of British Columbia, airborne particulate readings 10 times higher than peak allowable American levels are common in the developing world. Within dwellings heated by wood or dung, particulates are higher still. A child's lungs are more sensitive than an adult's and, Bates points out, children in the developing world face heavy doses of air pollutants whether they live in the city or the country.</p>
        <p>"If a developing-world child lives in a city," Bates says, "that child will be exposed to high levels of airborne lead from vehicle exhaust, since no third-world country is even close to mandating unleaded gasoline and catalytic converters." (Lead is a poison linked to I.Q. loss.) Since unleaded gasoline went on the market in the mid-1970's, ambient airborne lead levels in the United States have fallen 95 percent. During the same time, airborne lead levels have risen in developing-world cities where only leaded gasoline is burned. Lead is now so prevalent in Mexico City air that parents are advised to keep young children indoors as much as possible.</p>
        <p>"The city child in the developing world will also be exposed to high levels of airborne sulfur and smog," Bates says. Poor nations lack the factory emissions controls found in the West, do not require catalytic converters on vehicles and allow fuel stations to sell gasoline and diesel far too dirty to meet Western refinery standards. For example, in the Indian industrial city of Agra (home to the Taj Mahal), levels of airborne sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, are 10 times higher than the maximum found in the United States.</p>
        <p>"But at least the child in the developing-world city has electricity and propane as home energy, sparing constant indoor exposure to smoke," Bates continues. "In the country, the child is spared sulfur and lead in the air, but then gets the choking home air pollution from the wood or dung fire."</p>
        <p>ROBERT S. LAWRENCE, DIRECTOR of health sciences for the Rockefeller Foundation in New York, draws a chart of developing-world home fuels. In it, a slope starts with dung and crop wastes, moves past wood, charcoal, kerosene and propane, and ascends to electricity. "Through the early 1980's," Lawrence says, "many third-world countries were headed up the slope of cleaner fuels. In recent years, with the global economy stagnant, people are sliding back down the slope, from electricity back to propane, from fuel wood back to dung. Respiratory deaths are rising in concert."</p>
        <p>Sliding down the slope from clean fuels isn't just a threat to human lungs. It threatens forests as well. Though environmental orthodoxy holds that third-world deforestation is caused by rapacious clear-cutters and ruthless cattle barons, penniless peasants seeking fuel wood may be the greatest threat to forests. Fuel wood consumption in the developing world rose 35 percent between 1975 and 1986, with replanting rare by peasants. Jodi Jacobson, director of the Health and Development Policy Project, an environmental organization, believes fuel wood supplies are becoming critical in Haiti, India, Nepal, Mexico, sub-Saharan Africa and Thailand. A new saying among rural Indian women, Jacobson says, is "It's not what's in the pot but what's under the pot that worries you."</p>
        <p>In many developing countries, women do the wood gathering, just as they do most of the heavy labor. Gurinder Shahi, of the U.N. Development Program, estimates that in Nepal rural women spend five or six hours a day on foot searching for fuel wood and carrying it home. Such labors deny them the time for education and result in health damage to themselves and their children. In the high-altitude mountain areas of Nepal -- places many people presume are pristine wonderlands -- women, Bates notes, often suffer from a disease similar to anemia. The illness is caused by carbon monoxide in the bloodstream, a result of long-term exposure to crude energy sources like indoor cooking fires.</p>
        <p>WESTERN ENVIRONMENTAL thinking has great difficulty coming to terms with such realities. That third-world economists would call propane and kerosene "clean fuels," and speak longingly of the day when their countries are wholly electrified like the West, horrifies Western environmentalists, or enviros, as they are known in Washington. According to ecological orthodoxy, fossil fuels are hideous and central electric generation promotes an artificial greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>What developing nations need to free their populations from death by extreme air pollution is hydroelectric dams, advanced petroleum refining installations, high-efficiency power plants for the clean combustion of coal. But Western environmental lobbies oppose nearly all new central energy production facilities for the developing world, especially hydroelectric plants. Greenpeace, the Natural Resources Defense Council, the Sierra Club and other major environmental advocacy groups are pressuring Washington, Tokyo, Paris, London, Bonn and the World Bank not to support the Three Gorges and Xiaolangdi dams in China; the Narmada River dams in India; the Bio-Bio River dams in Chile, and power dams proposed for Malawi, Pakistan and elsewhere. In most cases the campaigns have succeeded. The World Bank, for example, recently withdrew from the Narmada project.</p>
        <p>The principal objection to hydroelectric power is that reservoirs are formed by inundating pristine areas, sometimes including the habitats of rare wildlife. This does happen, even though planned dams for the Yangtze River in China and for the Narmada River Valley in India would also stop seasonal downstream flooding, which annually kills hundreds to thousands of people and destroys wildlife habitats.</p>
        <p>Enviros correctly object to third-world hydropower initiatives' having budgets bloated by graft and involving displacement of peasants, which in developing nations always means more hardships. Yet they seem uninterested in the upside of such projects -- mainly, huge amounts of zero-emission, zero-fossil-fuel energy for nations where runaway air pollution is a daily threat to life. While passionately concerned about wildlife habitat losses from hydroelectric plants, enviros seem indifferent to the clear health benefits deriving from a reduction in indoor smoke.</p>
        <p>Similarly, many enviros oppose oil field development in countries like Ecuador, and are fighting the construction of new coal-fired power plants -- even ones that employ advanced antipollution equipment -- in China and elsewhere. Enviros contend that small-scale solar energy and "bio-gas" (dung fermented into methane, a clean fuel) are appropriate for the developing world. Often this is true. But how many Western enviros are willing to live at the limits of current solar technology? Today's solar converters can provide basic power requirements, but they usually do not provide enough wattage for refrigeration, which is badly needed in developing countries. (About a quarter of third-world food production is lost to spoilage.)</p>
        <p>One reason few environmentalists go solar is that it costs more than conventional electricity from big generating stations. Prices for solar converters have been falling, but solar cell systems still cost four to five times as much per new kilowatt-hour as fossil fuel systems, even ones with advanced pollution controls. And if small solar is too expensive for the Sierra Club set, why is it a great idea for peasants in Malawi?</p>
        <p>Many enviros think the need for improved water purity can be dealt with in small ways. Deborah Moore, of the Environmental Defense Fund, and groups like Unicef have been pressuring development agencies to fund community-based water-purity and sewage-control programs. As with small solar, there are many instances in which small water projects will provide the best returns. But in the expanding third-world cities where a billion of the world's poor reside, small is hardly the solution.</p>
        <p>In Karachi, only a third of the homes have piped water. In Madras, only about a third of dwellings connect to anything like a sewer system. In Kinshasa, there is no sewage system at all. The situation for numerous other third-world cities is the same. Often, the poor of developing cities must get safe drinking water from water-sellers. The poorest of the world's poor therefore end up paying more for water than do the rich.</p>
        <p>What is needed, Chivian says, is "basic water infrastructure" -- pipes, filtration plants, waste-water treatment facilities, sometimes dams and aqueducts. Such big water-diversion projects, however, offend environmental orthodoxy.</p>
        <p>WHY ARE SO MANY ENVIROS paying more attention to greenhouse computer projections for the 21st century than they are to millions of children dying from impure water and air? When pressed, environmentalists say words like: "The human species is not imperiled; look at the incredible number of births in the developing world. We must concentrate on protecting species and habitats that are imperiled."</p>
        <p>Population growth is the core environmental problem for most of the world. But better environmental health will help slow that growth, not expand it. "The technical literature is unanimous that when you improve basic health, especially child and reproductive health, birth rates go down," Chivian says. "Many environmentalists don't understand this, but it is the essential fact of the issue. If you want species and habitats preserved, protecting human health so that fertility rates decline will accomplish far more than building walls around wildlife preserves."</p>
        <p>In poor nations, women become pregnant many times to be confident of having a few children survive till adulthood and provide for the parents' old age. As education, women's rights and childhood survival rates improve, numbers of pregnancies decline. In the 1960's, the typical developing-world woman gave birth to six live children; today, the figure is four. Fertility rates are declining in developing countries that have positive indexes for issues like safe water and progress on the clean-energy slope. Fertility rates remain high mainly in Africa and the Indian subcontinent, where deaths from dirty water and dung smoke are concentrated.</p>
        <p>Given the crisis in basic environmental needs among the world's disenfranchised, Western environmentalists and governments would do well to shift their focus from the ecological problems of the developed world. A dollar spent protecting the environment will accomplish 10 times as much in the third world as in the first.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, Western environmental groups succeeded in drawing international attention to the loss of tropical rain forests. Since then, deforestation rates have fallen. If Western environmentalists devoted as much energy and concern to human health in the third world, progress might be seen there as well.  Gregg Easterbrook is a contributing editor to Newsweek and The Atlantic Monthly. His book on the environment, "A Moment on the Earth," will be published next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gregg Easterbrook is a contributing editor to Newsweek and The Atlantic Monthly. His book on the environment, "A Moment on the Earth," will be published next year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
