<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond Dinosaurs</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="730506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DE1039F932A25751C1A962958260" item-length="2901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond Dinosaurs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EMBEDDED in New York's consciousness as a repository of totem poles, taxidermy and dinosaur bones, with bright yellow school buses perpetually parked outside, the American Museum of Natural History is a bit of a dinosaur itself. But slowly, in small steps, it is cracking through its musty Victorian shell, struggling to become a more modern museum.</p>
        <p>Part of the change is generational, with a fresh crop of thirty- and fortysomethings heading up, and striving to reawaken, many of the major research departments. Part is social, like trying to bring more women and minorities into science careers, and onto the museum's professional staff. And part is simply inevitable, as technology and mass culture overlap with the museum's specialties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EMBEDDED in New York's consciousness as a repository of totem poles, taxidermy and dinosaur bones, with bright yellow school buses perpetually parked outside, the American Museum of Natural History is a bit of a dinosaur itself. But slowly, in small steps, it is cracking through its musty Victorian shell, struggling to become a more modern museum.</p>
        <p>Part of the change is generational, with a fresh crop of thirty- and fortysomethings heading up, and striving to reawaken, many of the major research departments. Part is social, like trying to bring more women and minorities into science careers, and onto the museum's professional staff. And part is simply inevitable, as technology and mass culture overlap with the museum's specialties.</p>
        <p>What everyone hopes that adds up to is a change in public perceptions, among them that the museum is basically just a place for children.</p>
        <p>"You always hear that this museum is fantastic for kids, but that the Met is where the grown-ups go," said Melanie L. J. Stiassny, an associate curator of ichthyology who shares her office with two cichlid fish named Brutus and Cruella. "I think that's changing."</p>
        <p>For the average New Yorker who regards the museum as a sentimental relic of childhood, all this can be both jarring and endearing, a bit like seeing an elderly uncle whiz by on in-line skates. For a Boston University professor who spent his teen-age years hanging out at the museum and considers it "a sort of Jerusalem," scientifically speaking, it is about time.</p>
        <p>"What you're hopefully seeing is the formation of a real community of doers who are both in touch with the public and with the problems at hand," said the professor, Les Kaufman, who teaches marine science. "I only hope it accomplishes something."</p>
        <p>The museum is getting in touch with its not terribly scientific public in a variety of ways. In the new Lila Acheson Wallace Wing, the visitor can interact through video with today's mammals and their extinct relatives. A Biodiversity Hall is expected to open in 1997 and will use walk-through installations and other techniques to discuss current research into extinction and evolution and how the world got where it is today. Satellite gift shops have sprung up in previously empty corners, selling T-shirts and other souvenirs.</p>
        <p>And then there's the dinosaur embryo. It sits just inside the Rotunda on Central Park West, in a small case with a sign on top that announces "New Discovery: Dinosaur Embryo." This is a genuine big deal, scientifically: the acclaimed specimin, unearthed last year in the Gobi Desert, is the first fossilized embryo of a carnivorous dinosaur ever found. Its presentation, featuring a video starring some of the museum's paleontologists talking about their discovery and its significance, is a telling illustration of how the museum is trying to show itself off these days.</p>
        <p>The scientists seem young and hip, in the video anyway, and getting these experts out from behind closed doors is one of the museum's principal efforts to engage the public, offering role models and maybe even attracting donations.</p>
        <p>Museum officials see all the changes as the fulfillment of twin missions: to engage in important research, and to help educate a public that is largely science-illiterate (though it is increasingly popular-science-conscious, what with rain-forest rock concerts and cocktail-party chatter about biodiversity).</p>
        <p>"The challenge is to enhance scientific literacy in this country, and we look to do that two ways," said Ellen V. Futter, who became president a year ago. "One is the programs within our walls, and the other is using the new technologies to make the collections and learning available to people, with curriculum modules, teacher training, software, interactive video and CD-ROM." She also talks about "growing in influence, in terms of being a real player in research and public policy."</p>
        <p>Still, even with a $230 million endowment and what officials describe as generous private and corporate support (only a quarter of its financing comes from government sources), they are also training a hard eye on the financial picture. In fiscal 1994, the museum's expenses came to $60.7 million, with research consuming the largest single portion -- $14.6 million.</p>
        <p>"Big science is very expensive, and our exhibitions are also very expensive," said Ms. Futter. The five-year Gobi expedition has cost close to $1 million museum officials say, and in the last several years staffing has increased slightly and salaries have risen to match those paid by other academic institutions.</p>
        <p>The man most often cited as a force for change at this 125-year-old hulk on Central Park West, professional home to Roy Chapman Andrews and Margaret Mead, is the dean of science, Michael J. Novacek, who also heads the paleontology department and helped recover the embryo. Since his arrival in 1982, Dr. Novacek has pushed the museum's research ever deeper into modern-day applications, like global warming and computer analysis of DNA.</p>
        <p>"Before Novacek, the research was just kind of plodding along and safe," said Terry Root, an associate professor of ornithology at the University of Michigan. "Now they're broadening. They're really leading the systemic world and pulling everybody into it."</p>
        <p>There have, of course, been a few mutterings of discontent, but all in all, the internal changes seem to have been accomplished amicably. "They've done much better than the Museum of Natural History in London," said Dr. Kaufman. "The reorganization there was like the breakup of the Soviet Union."</p>
        <p>Still, amid all the talk of biodiversity, the museum acknowledges a need to be more diverse itself. In addition to Ms. Futter, a woman, Anne Sidamon-Eristoff, leads the board of directors, but there are less than half a dozen women and minorities among a professional staff of 50.</p>
        <p>Everyone seems to blame this situation on a shortage of qualified candidates that is reflected across the world of academic science. So several years ago, the museum began giving internships, jobs and other help to minority students in the hope that some might become curators a decade or two down the road.</p>
        <p>All the while, the museum is immersing itself in technology. A four-year-old molecular biology lab tucked near the eaves of a 19th-century building spins out DNA data from specimens of all ages, and an office was cleared out last year to make way for a supercomputer, designed by an invertebrate specialist, that analyzes and compares DNA. Bit by bit, the items in the collection are being recorded in an electronic catalogue, some of it with three-dimensional computer imaging.</p>
        <p>Of course, some things probably will never change, like the dioramas in the shadowy Akeley Hall of African Mammals, where the clustered elephants are ringed by examples of gemsbok, bongos and the like. The live birds in flight are gone, along with the Department of Animal Behavior, but no one need worry too hard that the museum will stop being famously eccentric, the kind of place where a roomful of beetles are employed to clean mammal skeletons by nibbling away their flesh, where a back-office drawer yields a group of bats, sewn up and stuffed with cotton, their papery skulls and bones neatly labeled and boxed.</p>
        <p>But more and more, Ms. Futter said, new research will be on view.</p>
        <p>"The science has always been in the exhibitions, but at the same time, I don't think there's been a self-conscious endeavor to put the recent science on the floor," she said. "We want to make the material available to the public as quickly as we can, so they can understand what it can mean to our lives today."</p>
        <p>This research, much of which tries to link its findings to problems like finding a balance between society's needs and those of endangered species, is being conducted by Dr. Stiassny and dozens of others, some of whose stories follow.  ET TU, CRUELLA!</p>
        <p>Melanie Stiassny loved animals as a child. As she became a scholar, she turned her attention to fish and their evolution throughout the millennia.</p>
        <p>Her research focuses on cichlids, a type of freshwater fish found in Madagascar and parts of South America. Brutus and Cruella, the white-speckled pair she keeps in a roomy aquarium in her office, are products of the first-ever breeding of cichlids in captivity, which she chaperoned.</p>
        <p>Analyzing cichlids, she has found that fish are excellent informants on the state of the world. For example, she found that in the Serengeti region of Tanzania, freshwater fish -- which lack the powerful lobby that, say, dolphins have enjoyed in recent years, and are therefore at great risk of being annihilated -- were able to survive the dry season by hanging out in deeper pools that never dried out. When the rains came, the fish were simply washed back into other swamps and streams.</p>
        <p>The opening of a tourist lodge in the Serengeti disrupted all this, because tourists showering away their equatorial heat and dust depleted aquifers the pools depended on.</p>
        <p>"We were able to show them what was happening, and they instituted a water-rationing plan," Dr. Stiassny said. "They told the tourists not to take showers all the time."</p>
        <p>She is one of just five curators at the museum who do not fit the white-male mold, and she realizes there should be more like her. She is active in sponsoring minority junior-high and high-school students who work on her projects, part of a museum program, the Precollege Science Collaborative for Urban Minority Youth, that began a couple of years ago and enrolls 35 students.</p>
        <p>Students in the program are enrolled for two years at a time, attend twice-weekly training sessions in methodology and lab techniques at the museum, and design their own research projects. They present the research at their schools.</p>
        <p>Now, she says, after seven years at the museum, she may soon see some results. "I'm reaching the point," she said, confessing that it makes her feel old, "where kids I had in high school are coming out of graduate school."  CAVE CRAWLING</p>
        <p>Ross D. E. MacPhee preoccupies himself with patterns of extinction -- how and why various animal species have disappeared from the globe. He looks at possible causes, like an animal form of AIDS, and ties much of the damage to man's arrival in a particular place. His special focus has been Cuba, where he has traced rodents, primates and sloths that lived 17 million years ago. On Puerto Rico, since the arrival of humans, he has found a total extinction of the native animal species.</p>
        <p>"If we can find a pattern of disease-related extinctions, that will modify our attitudes toward future extinctions," he said. "There are reservoirs out there in nature that we're disrupting all the time, as we're cutting down the rain forest, and that's possibly putting everybody at great risk."</p>
        <p>Working with a geologist from the Museum of Natural History in Havana, Manuel A. Iturralde Vinent, Dr. MacPhee has pursued his theory, making seven trips to Cuba so far, crawling through caves and sifting through fossils. "There's a lot of evidence that we're in a biodiversity crisis," he says.</p>
        <p>The kind of devastation that Europeans brought when they set foot on Caribbean shores, he believes, may have been a repeat of what happened when people first encountered animals. So far, the museum's fossil specimens have been crucial in exploring that theory. "This place has the collections to determine what species existed and when," Dr. MacPhee says. His favorite part of the museum? "My office." BUG DNA, THEN AND NOW</p>
        <p>Ward Wheeler's eyes are bright and blue, like those old Sylvania flashbulbs, even though he has been up half the night with a coughing child. At 31, he is an associate curator of invertebrates, but perhaps even better known as the resident DNA whiz kid.</p>
        <p>First he helped sequence fossil DNA from a termite preserved in amber, showing that DNA could survive for millions of years, at least 25 million, in this case. His latest achievement is writing the software and building the computer that can analyze lettered chains of DNA in everything from fossils to latter-day specimens, helping scientists track differences between the species and learn more about subtle changes in the material that determines so much of life, then and now.</p>
        <p>With endless varieties of combinations and comparisons to be made, no person could complete such analysis quickly or efficiently. "Aligning DNA sequences and sequence analysis presents problems that do not have solutions in polynomial time," said Dr. Wheeler.</p>
        <p>Enter, then, his supercomputer, essentially 11 powerful processors wired together inside a high-ceilinged former office on the fifth floor of the museum's Romanesque main building. The computer breaks problems down into components, assigning one to each of 10 machines. By solving the components simultaneously, results are achieved much faster with a single machine. The 11th processor collects the results and continues processing the information until it has a solution.</p>
        <p>The DNA is extracted and coded individually by machines in the museum's molecular-biology lab, tucked atop a building along West 77th Street. A second lab is scheduled to open next year. Tracing subtle differences between DNA molecules gives insights that scientists might use in all kinds of applications, including tracing patterns of evolution and extinction.  STARDUST MEMORIES</p>
        <p>"A rock is really a history book," Martin Prinz was saying the other day. "And when it comes to meteoritic material, there's a lot more history, all about that big event four and a half billion years ago, when the sun formed from a molecular cloud floating out there."</p>
        <p>His specialty is geology, particularly the geology of outer space, and how the bits of matter that periodically arrive on this planet help define humanity's place in the solar system, as well as the history of it all. If all the species are considered to comprise a tree of life, the firmament would be the enormous backyard in which the tree took root.</p>
        <p>No matter which theory of the universe you subscribe to, it is a pleasure to join the easygoing Dr. Prinz on an impromptu tour of the meteorite collection he oversees as curator of mineral sciences. Of course, the big ones, like the 34-ton Cape York meteorite retrieved from Greenland by the legendary Robert E. Peary, are on exhibit. But in a room across the hall from his office, Dr. Prinz can hold in his hand a small moon rock, retrieved by Apollo 11, a smaller piece of Mars, a weighty meteor decorated, by some spontaneous internal chemistry, with crisscrossed bands of iron-nickel alloy. Then there is Orgueil, found in a French town of that name in 1864. It's not too attractive, consisting of some grayish-black granules, "but it's the closest thing we have to the sun," Dr. Prinz said. "When astronomers measure the composition of the sun, it matches Orgueil.</p>
        <p>"You know, we really are made of stardust. This material was being generated in space, some of it became the sun, some coagulated to become the earth and the comets. We are all interconnected in a philosophical way with the stars. It's a good thing for us to think about as we get involved with our wars and our problems." They'll Satisfy Your Science Craving, Too</p>
        <p>THE Museum of Natural History is not the only institution in the city that offers exhibitions on with various aspects of science. Here are some of the others:</p>
        <p>NEW YORK HALL OF SCIENCE 47-01 111th Street, Flushing Meadows-Corona Park, Queens. (718) 699-0005. Hours: 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Wednesday through Sunday. Attractions include "Hidden Kingdoms" exhibit, about microorganisms, and "Sound Sensations," about audio technology.</p>
        <p>AQUARIUM FOR WILDLIFE CONSERVATION West Eighth Street and Surf Avenue, Coney Island. (718) 265-3400. Hours: daily 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $6.75 for adults, $2 for children ages 2-12 and seniors. Under 2 free. Attractions include beluga whales. BROOKLYN CHILDREN'S MUSEUM 145 Brooklyn Avenue, Crown Heights. (718) 735-4432. Hours: 2 P.M. to 5 P.M., Wednesday through Friday, and noon to 5 P.M., Saturday, Sunday and some holidays. Suggested contribution: $3. Programs include "Fun With Science." Exhibits include "Animals Eat: Different Feasts for Different Beasts."</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S MUSEUM OF MANHATTAN 212 West 83d Street. (212) 721-1234. Hours: 1:30 P.M. to 5:30 P.M., Monday, Wednesday and Thursday, and 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Fridays through Sundays, and all school holidays, Admission: $5 for adults and children; seniors pay $2 and children under 2 are free. Exhibits include the Sussman Environmental Center, which focuses on topics like recycling through various activities.</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BOTANIC GARDEN 1000 Washington Avenue, Crown Heights. (718) 622-4433. Hours: 8 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., Tuesday through Friday, and 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Saturday and Sunday. Exhibits include evolutionary trail of plants. Classes include horticulture and composting.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK BOTANICAL GARDEN Kazimiroff Boulevard and 200th Street, the Bronx. (718) 817-8700. Hours: 10 A.M. to 4 P.M., Tuesday through Sunday. Admission: $3 for adults, $1 for seniors, students and children ages 6-16. Children under 6 are free. Saturdays from 10 A.M. to noon, everyone enters free. The sister institution of the American Museum of Natural History in terms of research on plant life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
