<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>6 Astronauts Are Launched Into Space</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="722862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATLANTIS (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DD143EF937A35752C1A962958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>6 Astronauts Are Launched Into Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., Nov. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The refurbished space shuttle Atlantis rocketed into orbit today on a planned 11-day mission to study Earth's atmosphere, particularly the effects of solar radiation interacting with man-made chemicals on the ozone layer high in the atmosphere, which protects the planet from harmful ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>It is the third shuttle flight in as many years to carry an array of environmental-science instruments called the Atmospheric Laboratory for Applications and Science, or Atlas. On Friday, the astronauts are to deploy and later retrieve a German-built satellite for further atmospheric studies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The refurbished space shuttle Atlantis rocketed into orbit today on a planned 11-day mission to study Earth's atmosphere, particularly the effects of solar radiation interacting with man-made chemicals on the ozone layer high in the atmosphere, which protects the planet from harmful ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>It is the third shuttle flight in as many years to carry an array of environmental-science instruments called the Atmospheric Laboratory for Applications and Science, or Atlas. On Friday, the astronauts are to deploy and later retrieve a German-built satellite for further atmospheric studies.</p>
        <p>The liftoff occurred at noon, after a delay of less than four minutes while uneasy mission officials at the Kennedy Space Center here checked one more time with meteorologists on the weather at emergency landing sites in Spain and Morocco. It was a spectacularly beautiful blue-sky day at the launching pad on this side of the Atlantic. But crosswinds had been unacceptably stiff at the trans-Atlantic landing sites.</p>
        <p>Finally, the winds were reported to have abated just enough at the Moroccan air base. The "go" was given for liftoff. The six astronauts took off in a rumble of fiery exhaust, their spaceship climbing to a 190-mile-high orbit.</p>
        <p>Later today, flight controllers at the Johnson Space Center in Houston said both the shuttle and the crew were in excellent condition, making preparations for round-the-clock environment observations. The failure of one small steering jet was of no concern, they said. The flight is scheduled to end with a landing at the Florida center on Nov. 14.</p>
        <p>It is the seventh and last shuttle mission for the year, the 66th since the shuttle flights began in 1981. For the Atlantis, it is a shakedown cruise after being grounded more than two years for a $96 million overhaul, including extensive modifications making it the most versatile of the four-vehicle shuttle fleet. Many of the changes were designed to extend the shuttle's mission duration to at least 16 days from the previous capability of 12 days.</p>
        <p>Of most immediate importance, said Loren J. Shriver, a shuttle manager at the Kennedy center, the Atlantis is now equipped with new plumbing and wiring so that it can be used for a flight to link up with Russia's Mir space station. After the current flight, a new air lock and docking mechanisms are to be installed in the Atlantis for the Mir link-up, scheduled for next May. The shuttle-Mir mission is expected to be a major step in a wider program of space cooperation between the United States and Russia.</p>
        <p>The first shuttle flight of the Atlas environmental instruments, in 1992, made measurements of concentrations of chemicals at various altitudes that resulted from the breakdown of industrial compounds known as chlorofluorocarbons, which are used to run refrigerators, air-conditioners and electronics equipment. The measurements were critical in confirming the relationship between such chemicals and the alarming depletion of the protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The thin ozone layer shields Earth from solar ultraviolet radiation that can cause skin cancer and cataracts in humans and be detrimental to crops and farm animals. Nations have agreed to a treaty to phase out the use of chlorofluorocarbons by 2000.</p>
        <p>Since the depletion of ozone over the Antarctic begins in late August and subsides in early October, Dr. Ellen Ochoa, one of the Atlantis astronauts, said, "We'll have the opportunity to try to understand more about how the atmosphere recovers from this annual event."</p>
        <p>The Atlantis pilots are Lieut. Col. Donald R. McMonagle and Lieut. Col. Curtis L. Brown, both of the Air Force. Other astronauts are Joseph R. Tanner, Jean-Francois Clervoy and Dr. Scott E. Parazynski.</p>
        <p>At a news conference, Jean-Jacques Dordain, director of planning and policy of the European Space Agency, said, "Today, for the first time in history, two E.S.A. astronauts are in orbit at the same time." He was referring to Mr. Clervoy, a Frenchman flying on the Atlantis as a representative of the European agency, and Dr. Ulf Merbold, a German astronaut who has flown on the American shuttle and is now aboard the Russian Mir space station. Dr. Merbold is to return to Earth on Friday.</p>
        <p>On another historical note, Dr. Parazynski, a physician, was born July 28, 1961. That means he is the first American astronaut to fly in space who was born after Americans first began flying in space, with the 15-minute suborbital flight of Alan B. Shepard Jr. on May 5, 1961. And so the world turns.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
