<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; Bored to the gills with boutique beers? How does a scratch-and-sniff magazine campaign sound?</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="721997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ODORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOSTON BEER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Odors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2DE1E3FF932A05753C1A962958260" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: Advertising; Bored to the gills with boutique beers? How does a scratch-and-sniff magazine campaign sound?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Ramirez</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEE-YEW! Scent strips, those pinch-your-nostrils stink bombs that hawk bafflingly named perfumes in high-gloss magazines -- why would anyone want to use that cliche in their advertising?</p>
        <p>"Well," said James Koch, chuckling, "we thought we could bring a new twist to it."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEE-YEW! Scent strips, those pinch-your-nostrils stink bombs that hawk bafflingly named perfumes in high-gloss magazines -- why would anyone want to use that cliche in their advertising?</p>
        <p>"Well," said James Koch, chuckling, "we thought we could bring a new twist to it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Koch (pronounced cook) is founder of the Boston Beer Company, brewer of Samuel Adams beer. He and the Boston advertising agency Gearon Hoffman are using scent strips to sell beer.</p>
        <p>In recent issues of Sports Illustrated, Rolling Stone, and Newsweek, Samuel Adams was one of the first non-perfume products to be advertised with a nose-catching scent strip. Above a picture of hops, the dried flowers that give most beer its flavor, is a strip filled with hops aroma.</p>
        <p>Samuel Adams, named after the polemicist and political figure of American Revolutionary times, is one of the nation's fastest-growing specialty brands in the otherwise slow-growing beer business. Last year, Mr. Koch's company sold 450,000 barrels of Samuel Adams beer and this year expects to sell about 700,000 barrels, or more than 230 million bottles of beer.</p>
        <p>But in the world of brewing, that's small beer. Samuel Adams's 1993 market share was less than three-tenths of 1 percent. And even though it attained national distribution only last month, the brewer's previous attempts at national advertising have been frustrating.</p>
        <p>Enter the scent strip. When Mr. Koch was in Bavaria earlier this year buying the Hallertau Mittelfruh hops that give Samuel Adams its distinctive flavor, Mr. Koch's hops dealer offered him an intriguing idea.</p>
        <p>The Munich dealer had just heard of a new process of extracting the aromatic essence of hops resins. "In other words, we could make a piece of paper smell like hops, instead of perfume," Mr. Koch said.</p>
        <p>Until now, most of Boston Beer's advertising had been local -- generally 30- or 60-second radio spots devoted to why Samuel Adams won more prizes and cost more than mass-market brands (because the higher-quality German hops cost 10 to 11 times the domestic variety).</p>
        <p>The last time Boston Beer advertised nationally was four years ago, when the company bought ads in Time magazine, comparing pictures of Samuel Adams beer with those of five premium competitors.</p>
        <p>"I saw no visible impact from that ad," Mr. Koch recalled. But with a scent ad, "you've really got something that people could use as a basis of comparison, so I jumped right on it."</p>
        <p>Working with technical experts from the Minnesota Mining and Manufacturing Company, Boston Beer used liquid carbon dioxide to reduce the Bavarian hops to a sticky and powerfully aromatic tar. The tar is broken up and sealed inside tiny beads, and then printed like sticky ink on a rectangle the size of a large postage stamp.</p>
        <p>Unlike peel-and-sniff scent strips, Samuel Adams's scratch-and-sniff strips are less likely to unleash their scent prematurely because the resins are securely sealed in the beads. It requires the force of a fingernail to release the smell, rather than the minimal force of magazines piled on top of each other or handled roughly during distribution.</p>
        <p>The next step was to figure out what the ad should say. Dan Gearon, a founder of the Gearon Hoffman agency and a former bartender, said the strategy was to have a one-page, two-sided ad with the first side linked thematically to the magazine it appeared in and the other side carrying information about hops and brewing.</p>
        <p>"It meant that with S.I. we could play around with sports, with Rolling Stone we could be psychedelic, and with Newsweek we could be direct and logical," said Bob Hoffman, the agency's other principal and the head of the creative campaign.</p>
        <p>For the Sports Illustrated ad, for example, a photograph of a grimacing baseball player fumbling a ground ball carries the caption, "Bad Hop." Below is the picture of a leafy hop with a scratch-and-sniff strip labeled, "Good Hop."</p>
        <p>Boston Beer isn't the only scent-strip pioneer. General Foods U.S.A. recently used a peel-and-sniff strip for its Kahlua Cafe instant-coffee product.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koch wants to use the scent technology again, but this time for the more complicated task of pitting the aroma of Samuel Adams against those of competing beers. But hop resins have only a hundred or so organic compounds that can be smelled and transferred to a scent strip; a complex beer like Samuel Adams has many hundreds of compounds, not all of which have been chemically identified.</p>
        <p>"It may not be possible, but we'll see," Mr. Koch said.</p>
        <p>For its part, Gearon Hoffman does not foresee using scent strips for any other clients. "We also represent long underwear and work boots," Mr. Gearon said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
