<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antarctica's Ozone Layer Is Threatened By Depletion</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="716696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D6103DF93BA35753C1A962958260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antarctica's Ozone Layer Is Threatened By Depletion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once again a seasonal hole the size of North America has appeared in the protective ozone layer above Antarctica, allowing a flood of dangerous ultraviolet radiation to reach the ground. But scientists see some consolation in the fact that the depth and extent of the hole are no greater than at the same time last year.</p>
        <p>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration reported yesterday that various American instruments aboard a Russian spacecraft, on high-altitude balloons and on the ground had detected a springtime ozone hole over Antarctica, in which the concentration of atmospheric ozone has fallen to 90 Dobson units from the normal concentration of about 250. Dobson units are a measure of the ability of the atmosphere to absorb certain wavelengths of light, especially in the ultraviolet range.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once again a seasonal hole the size of North America has appeared in the protective ozone layer above Antarctica, allowing a flood of dangerous ultraviolet radiation to reach the ground. But scientists see some consolation in the fact that the depth and extent of the hole are no greater than at the same time last year.</p>
        <p>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration reported yesterday that various American instruments aboard a Russian spacecraft, on high-altitude balloons and on the ground had detected a springtime ozone hole over Antarctica, in which the concentration of atmospheric ozone has fallen to 90 Dobson units from the normal concentration of about 250. Dobson units are a measure of the ability of the atmosphere to absorb certain wavelengths of light, especially in the ultraviolet range.</p>
        <p>The ozone hole has opened up each Southern Hemisphere spring since the mid 1980's, always reaching its maximum extent in early October and then slowly closing. A much smaller seasonal hole has begun to appear each spring over the North Pole, and the high-altitude ozone layer in all regions of the globe has been somewhat depleted.</p>
        <p>The cause of this depletion, most scientists believe, is a set of chemical reactions involving chlorine, which has been introduced into the stratosphere by chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, and related chemicals. These chemicals have been widely used since the 1940's as refrigerants, in the manufacture of plastic foam, as solvents for cleaning electronic circuits and many other applications.</p>
        <p>Although ozone (a molecule of oxygen containing three oxygen atoms instead of the usual two) is poisonous, its presence in the upper atmosphere is regarded as vital to the survival of many forms of life. By blocking ultraviolet radiation produced by the sun, ozone protects humans from damage to the immune system and increased risk of cataracts and skin cancer. It also protects marine organisms at the base of the world's food chain from depletion caused by solar radiation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jay R. Herman, a research scientist at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center at Greenbelt, Md., said that the pattern of ozone loss in the Antarctic this year was "much the same as last year" and that the hole was somewhat smaller than the record 9.4 million square miles of Sept. 27, 1992.</p>
        <p>Since the signing of the Montreal Protocol in 1987, the first of a series of international agreements to limit and finally ban the manufacture and use of ozone-destroying chemicals, the rate of increase in the destruction of the ozone layer has somewhat declined.</p>
        <p>Although most of the world's developed nations, including the United States, have agreed to halt production of the chemicals most destructive to the ozone layer by Jan. 1, 1996, and have sharply curtailed or halted production, other less destructive chemicals will remain in production for years. In addition, developing countries have been given dispensation to delay implementing the ban.  Enormous quantities of CFC's will remain in use in refrigerators, freezers and air conditioners well into the next century when the appliances using them begin to wear out.</p>
        <p>"There are some early indications that the rate of change of depletion has improved a little," Dr. Herman said, "although we're likely to have to wait between 30 and 50 years to see real improvement."</p>
        <p>A much gloomier assessment was recently reported by Dr. Jonathan Shanklin of the British Antarctic Survey. Based on data collected by Britain's Halley Station in Antarctica, Dr. Shanklin and his colleagues calculated that at the present rate of destruction of the ozone layer, the ozone in the seasonal Antarctic hole would be fully depleted by the year 2005.</p>
        <p>As the ozone level over Antarctica declines, the penetration by dangerous wavelengths of ultraviolet rays known as UV-B has increased, Dr. Shanklin said, and it is likely that the still shorter wavelengths of UV-C will eventually begin to reach the earth's surface. UV-C would be a major threat to Antarctica's wildlife and marine plankton.</p>
        <p>The major concern is that after the ozone hole recloses each spring, the depletion of ozone it represents is spread by wind and convection to lower latitudes, helping to dilute ozone throughout populated regions. This process of Antarctic dilution of the global ozone shield worsens the less severe depletion taking place throughout the world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
