<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuclear Waste, With Nowhere to Go</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="677161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NUCLEAR WASTES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RED WING (MINN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRAIRIE ISLAND NUCLEAR POWER PLANT (MINN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Minnesota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E7DF163FF93BA15750C0A962958260" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuclear Waste, With Nowhere to Go</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>RED WING, Minn., March 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After three decades of looking for a place where waste from the nation's nuclear reactors could someday be disposed of, that someday has arrived.</p>
        <p>The two reactors in Red Wing have run out of storage space and no place has been found to put the waste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After three decades of looking for a place where waste from the nation's nuclear reactors could someday be disposed of, that someday has arrived.</p>
        <p>The two reactors in Red Wing have run out of storage space and no place has been found to put the waste.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Prairie Island nuclear plant may have to close permanently next year, a little more than halfway through its expected lifetime. Other utilities have built temporary storage in steel or concrete casks, but building those here would require action by the State Legislature, which is balking.</p>
        <p>If the twin reactors are shut, opponents of nuclear power will try the same tactic elsewhere, and experts say more shutdowns could result.</p>
        <p>Around the country, thousands of tons of nuclear waste are piling up in earthquake-proof pools near each reactor. The storage is generally considered to be safe for years to come, but it requires a significant level of surveillance and maintenance.  Utility's Argument</p>
        <p>The owner of the Red Wing plant, the Northern States Power Company, insists that the casks and the reactor are safe. And if the plant is forced to shut, said James J. Howard, the company's chairman and chief executive, the likely result is that the plant will be decommissioned, requiring removal of all the fuel from the pool. That would mean 38 casks, instead of the 17 that the utility is now seeking.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Howard said, Northern States would have to buy replacement power, which it says would come from coal and would each year create emissions of 10,000 to 15,000 pounds of sulfur dioxide, a cause of acid rain. Plant opponents say cleaner power sources like windmills could be found.</p>
        <p>The company also says that closing the plant could mean a 9 percent rate increase for some of its customers. The rate is now 1.5 cents a kilowatt-hour. A 'Temporary' Action</p>
        <p>The Red Wing plant, built on a sandy island in the Mississippi River 28 miles southeast of Minneapolis, was designed in the 1960's with a small steel-lined pool. The idea was to hold the spent fuel for up to a few years until it could be hauled away for recycling, but recycling was banned by President Jimmy Carter.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government has repeatedly promised to take the fuel. It has collected billions of dollars from the utilities, including Northern States, under a contract in which it agreed to take the waste beginning in 1998. But now the Energy Department says it is unable to meet the deadline.</p>
        <p>Northern States, which serves a 49,000-square-mile area with a population of three million people in five states, gets 20 percent of its electricity from Prairie Island. The company, whose operating record here is envied around the nuclear industry, wants to put some of the fuel in 122-ton sealed casks with steel walls nine inches thick. The casks would be parked outdoors on a concrete strip about the size of four basketball courts laid end to end, surrounded by barbed wire and earthen berms.</p>
        <p>But a state law that was intended to prevent the Federal Government from establishing a national high-level nuclear waste repository in Minnesota has been interpreted by state courts as prohibiting the casks unless the Legislature approves.  Opposition From Tribe</p>
        <p>Prominent among opponents of the cask plan is the Sioux tribe whose reservation shares the island with the reactor. Environmentalists also oppose the plan, mostly because using the casks would keep the plant operating.</p>
        <p>"When you find you're digging yourself into a hole, the first thing to do is to stop digging," said George Crocker of the Prairie Island Coalition Against Nuclear Storage.</p>
        <p>The tax-hungry city of Red Wing, which annexed the island when the plant was built, wants the plant to continue operating.</p>
        <p>The utility's plan calls for the casks to be used until Northern States can take the waste elsewhere. The company has struck a preliminary storage agreement with the Mescalero Apache tribe in Mescalero, N.M., which is trying to establish an "interim repository" on its reservation, until the Energy Department can open a permanent one, probably at Yucca Mountain, Nev., in 15 to 20 years.</p>
        <p>A committee of the Minnesota House approved a bill to allow the casks, but a similar measure failed in a Senate committee. The utility believes it can win on the Senate floor if it can get the bill there, but even Northern States says its prospects on the House floor are uncertain. To keep running, the company says, it needs action before the legislative session ends, probably in April.</p>
        <p>[ On March 24 the State Senate's Environment and Natural Resources Committee approved an amended bill that would let the company have enough casks to last until 2002, at which time the fuel would have to be shipped off site or the plant would close. The vote allows the issue to reach the full Senate. ] Indians' Concerns</p>
        <p>The Indian tribe living near the plant, the Prairie Island Mdewakanton Sioux, says the plant threatens members' health and livelihood. Six tribal members worked at the plant until the cask issue arose, and three of them have since quit.</p>
        <p>One of the tribe's main economic projects, the Treasure Island casino, is just half a mile from the reactor. The tribe also has a marina and a recreational-vehicle park but has stopped planning for tourist expansion, said Darelynn Lehto, the vice president of the tribal council, because it does not know how potential visitors would react to a nuclear waste dump.</p>
        <p>All in all, the plant provides 500 jobs in the area and pays $22 million in local taxes. But Ms. Lehto said all the money went to the City of Red Wing while the tribe got all the risk.  Good Performance Record</p>
        <p>An industry survey of reliability ranked both reactors here among the 10 best in the United States, and they also rank well in low radiation exposure to workers and backlog of maintenance work. To "demystify" the technology and counter public fear of things nuclear, the company has taken the unusual step of opening up the control room and other areas to tours, and 6,000 people have already come through.</p>
        <p>Six American nuclear plants already use casks. If their use is barred here, both supporters and opponents of the Red Wing plant predict, environmentalists will seize on the tactic around the country.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Hazel R. O'Leary was a Northern States vice president before joining the Clinton Administration last year. One responsibility in that job was to prod the Energy Department to live up to its promise. In her current job, Mrs. O'Leary has raised the possibility of helping utilities cover their excess costs for storage. She has also taken steps like opening the department's files on human radiation experiments as a way to build credibility, so that the department can return to the nuclear waste problem.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Howard talks of the industry "taking our destiny into our own hands" and arranged a private deal with the Mescaleros, who could command millions of dollars a year in rent from utilities.</p>
        <p>But many doubt that arrangement will go through. For one thing, New Mexico's non-Indian population is mostly against it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
