<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pamela Chasek, Langston James Goree</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="673956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASEK, PAMELA (PAMELA GOREE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOREE, LANGSTON JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E4DF163DF930A25750C0A962958260" item-length="560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pamela Chasek, Langston James Goree</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lois Smith Brady</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you ask Pamela Chasek and Langston James Goree when they met, they'll give you two dates: one for when they met electronically and another for when they met physically.</p>
        <p>They first encountered each other in September 1990, on the Internet, the global computer network. Ms. Chasek, now 32, was living in Washington and working on a Ph.D. in international politics at Johns Hopkins University. Mr. Goree, now 40 and an environmentalist who is so proficient with computers that friends call him a "techno-lord," was living in the Amazon rain forest in Brazil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you ask Pamela Chasek and Langston James Goree when they met, they'll give you two dates: one for when they met electronically and another for when they met physically.</p>
        <p>They first encountered each other in September 1990, on the Internet, the global computer network. Ms. Chasek, now 32, was living in Washington and working on a Ph.D. in international politics at Johns Hopkins University. Mr. Goree, now 40 and an environmentalist who is so proficient with computers that friends call him a "techno-lord," was living in the Amazon rain forest in Brazil.</p>
        <p>The two electronically exchanged ideas, academic papers and opinions on ecological topics like population control, managing the world's forests and the ozone layer. Mr. Goree, who is known as "Kimo," likens the information superhighway to New York City. It is a place, he said, where anyone, no matter what their background, sleeping habits, age or interests, can find soul mates. "If you like to stand on your head and spit pickles in the snow, on the Internet there are at least three other people just like you," he said.</p>
        <p>Several months after their electronic friendship began, the couple met at a United Nations environmental conference in Geneva. There, they discovered that they not only had good E-mail chemistry, but also the old-fashioned kind.</p>
        <p>After the conference, he returned to the rain forest and she to Washington and for the next year they exchanged E-mail letters almost daily. "There aren't a lot of lovers who write to each other and can go back to a packet of letters and say this was how we met and courted," Mr. Goree said. "No one has telephone conversations recorded. Pam and I have floppy disks of how we got to know one another and slowly, bit by bit, day by day, told each other a little bit more about ourselves."</p>
        <p>The couple live in Manhattan, where they co-produce The Earth Negotiations Bulletin, a nonpartisan report on United Nations meetings with ecological agendas, which is available in conventional journal form and on the Internet (enb@igc.apc.org). On Feb. 20, they married at the Church Center for the United Nations before about 150 guests who had traveled to the wedding from many different countries, including Belgium, Mexico, Denmark, Canada and Brazil.</p>
        <p>Some guests had begun -- as well as ended -- romantic relationships via E-mail. "It's a very efficient way of breaking up," said Charlotte De Fontaubert, a Ph.D. candidate in marine-environmental policy. "All you have to do is delete all the messages in the mailbox."</p>
        <p>A few kept in touch with friends and lovers through low-tech means. The best man, Wim Groeneveld, communicates with his wife, Leticia, by handwritten, posted letter. He lives in western Brazil; she lives in the north, in an area so remote he has to take a bush plane to the closest airstrip, then canoe up river for 12 days to visit her.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goree and Ms. Chasek rarely write old-fashioned letters to each other. Whenever they're apart these days, they resume their E-mail correspondence, which for them is like revisiting the place they met.</p>
        <p>"In December, I was off to Tanzania and Pam was off to Austria," Mr. Goree said. "It was fun to sit down at the computer again. There's nothing that takes the place of being together physically, but there is also something very comforting about taking up writing again."  VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
