<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726109"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2D81331F93BA25752C1A962958260" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Sony is taking $3.2 billion in losses on its Hollywood studios, Columbia and Tristar. The loss is one of the largest reported by a Japanese company and is emblematic of the problems the Japanese have had with landmark American investments.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Tele-Communications reorganized into four business groups and planned to issue stock in each of them. In effect, Tele-Communications is creating separate securities that will rise and fall based on the performance of each of the four individual units.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Sony is taking $3.2 billion in losses on its Hollywood studios, Columbia and Tristar. The loss is one of the largest reported by a Japanese company and is emblematic of the problems the Japanese have had with landmark American investments.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Tele-Communications reorganized into four business groups and planned to issue stock in each of them. In effect, Tele-Communications is creating separate securities that will rise and fall based on the performance of each of the four individual units.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Niagara Mohawk and Arizona Public Service agreed to trade air pollution allowances. The deal opened the door to a relatively low-cost way to cut "greenhouse" gases that contribute to global warming and may presage similar international deals.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T is trying to buy a stake of Groupe Bull in an effort to break into the protected French telecommunications market.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>In the modem market, a brand name does not mean much, a lesson that Hayes Microcomputer Products learned the hard way. The company, which set the standard for modems, filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy protection on Tuesday.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The proposed exchange of RJR Nabisco stock for Borden will be timed differently, a move that set off much speculation.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Hilton Hotel is considering a sale or a spinoff among other options. The announcement sent its shares surging.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. said it expected to license the Macintosh operating system from Apple Computer and install it on I.B.M. PC's.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>A rising star at Nynex has made it to the top. Ivan G. Seidenberg, who started his career at the age of 19 as an assistant for telephone repairmen at New York Telephone, will succeed William C. Ferguson as chairman and chief executive.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Rockefeller Center Properties arranged to borrow $225 million, averting what had been a looming financial crisis.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>Attwoods of Britain rejected a sweetened takeover offer of</p>
        <p>$615 million from Browning-Ferris Industries.  [ D19. ]</p>
        <p>General Motors sued to bar the Government from holding a hearing based on Transportation Secretary Federico F. Pena's contention that as many as six million G.M. pickup trucks may pose the risk of killing their drivers and passengers.  [ A16. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>Housing starts fell 5.2 percent in October, weakened by higher mortgage rates. It was the first decline in four months.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>A case in Philadelphia focuses attention on sexual harassment in the workplace by superiors of the same sex.  [ A24. ] International</p>
        <p>The vote on the world trade agreement will be a crucial early test for Senator Bob Dole, the likely majority leader.  [ A1. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks declined as investors became increasingly worried that higher interest rates might choke off economic growth. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index fell 2.05 points.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury prices slipped after the report on housing starts failed to calm concerns about accelerating inflation.  [ D19. ]</p>
        <p>Orange juice prices surged after an increase by Brazilian producers. Crude oil and cotton prices also gained.  [ D20. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar was little changed in quiet trading.  [ D20. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>"Miracle on 34th Street" without Macy's? A remake of the 1947 film will soon open without any references to the New York department store. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>One sign of the troubles plaguing Spectrum Information Technologies: top jobs continue to go unfilled. Market Place.  [ D8. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
