<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Allstate's size helps profits, but also makes for added risk.</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="724698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HURRICANES AND TROPICAL STORMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTHQUAKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSURANCE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALLSTATE CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEARS ROEBUCK &amp; CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUINT, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHOATE, JERRY D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DB1F3EF932A25752C1A962958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Allstate's size helps profits, but also makes for added risk.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Quint</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">QUINT, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS one of the nation's largest insurers of homes and autos, the Allstate Corporation reaps the rewards of name recognition and economies of scale that in normal times help make it very profitable.</p>
        <p>But with that size comes additional risk that the company would just as soon avoid, or at least reduce. A $2.7 billion loss in 1992 from Hurricane Andrew in Florida and a $1.3 billion loss from the Los Angeles earthquake early this year have wreaked havoc on Allstate's profits. After a loss of $500 million in 1992, the company saw profits jump to a record $1.3 billion in disaster-free 1993, but earnings have slumped to $320.7 million in the first nine months of this year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS one of the nation's largest insurers of homes and autos, the Allstate Corporation reaps the rewards of name recognition and economies of scale that in normal times help make it very profitable.</p>
        <p>But with that size comes additional risk that the company would just as soon avoid, or at least reduce. A $2.7 billion loss in 1992 from Hurricane Andrew in Florida and a $1.3 billion loss from the Los Angeles earthquake early this year have wreaked havoc on Allstate's profits. After a loss of $500 million in 1992, the company saw profits jump to a record $1.3 billion in disaster-free 1993, but earnings have slumped to $320.7 million in the first nine months of this year.</p>
        <p>Despite the company's success in recent years in building up both its property insurance and its life insurance businesses, cutting overhead expenses and maintaining a good record for limiting its ordinary loss claims, the vulnerability to disasters has cast a shadow over its stock price.</p>
        <p>Since June 1993, when Sears, Roebuck &amp; Company, sold nearly 20 percent of Allstate for $2.36 billion -- the largest initial public stock offering of any company -- its stock rose from $27 to a peak of $34.25 in October last year only to slide to yesterday's close of $24.125, down 75 cents.</p>
        <p>Because of Sears's plan to distribute the remaining 360 million Allstate shares to Sears shareholders, some traders expect the stock to come under additional pressure.</p>
        <p>A. Michael Franquilli of Salomon Brothers said before the Sears announcement that Allstate's growth and success in controlling costs and day-to-day claims losses justified a buy recommendation. Others, such as Weston M. Hicks of Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, have neutral opinions, partly because of its vulnerability to disasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hicks said that the company was not likely to improve on the stellar performance of its automobile insurance business. He reduced his estimate for 1995 earnings yesterday to $3.05 a share from $3.15 because ending the ties with Sears will eliminate some tax benefits.</p>
        <p>Jerry D. Choate, Allstate's chief executive, says reducing the exposure to catastrophe losses was his top priority. But in an interview yesterday, he did not offer much hope for a quick solution.</p>
        <p>By not accepting new customers in California and large parts of Florida -- and declining to renew any customers in three Florida counties, soon to be five -- he said the company was making good progress toward reducing its estimated maximum loss from any single event to $1 billion by 1997. But he added that Allstate had still not purchased reinsurance to reduce its losses from disasters "because it is too expensive" and unavailable in the amounts Allstate would need.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Mr. Choate said he watched the weather channel on TV "a lot more than I would like."</p>
        <p>John Snyder, senior vice president at the A. M. Best Company, a rating firm, said that operating without the reinsurance that most other companies buy "is a viable strategy for Allstate because they are big enough to survive." But the absence does mean "that from time to time they will suffer some very big losses and have to pick themselves up."</p>
        <p>How lucky Allstate will be can only be a guess. But other insurers expect even more costly disasters. Munich Re, a German company and the world's largest reinsurance company, said earlier this week that it planned to reduce its exposure in many parts of the world because climatic changes, including global warming, would lead to more severe storms in areas where population growth and real estate development have sharply increased insurers' risks. "If I was a betting man, I could offer you a bet that the records of recent years will be beaten by new damage records," Wolf Otto Bauer, a director, said in a recent article in The Financial Times of London.</p>
        <p>But even if Allstate continues growing and improving its efficiency and is lucky enough to avoid new disasters, some analysts assume that many Sears shareholders will want to sell the stock, thereby depressing its price. Managers of index funds, for example, are big investors in Sears because of its place in the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 Stock Index, but would have no reason to hold Allstate, which is not part of that index.</p>
        <p>Institutions that own both Sears and Allstate may find themselves with more of the insurer than they want. Fidelity Management of Boston, for example, is the largest outside holder of Sears, with 19 million shares at midyear, and also one of the largest holders of Allstate, with 10.7 million shares. Fidelity declined comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
