<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thinning Ozone Layer Implicated in Decline Of Frogs and Toads</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FROGS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ULTRAVIOLET LIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CASCADE MOUNTAINS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DF153AF932A35750C0A962958260" item-length="1421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thinning Ozone Layer Implicated in Decline Of Frogs and Toads</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YOON, CAROL KAESUK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCIENTISTS investigating a worldwide decline in frogs and other amphibians have found the first strong evidence identifying a likely global culprit: the rise in ultraviolet radiation caused by the thinning of the atmospheric ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Researchers from Oregon State University say a new study shows that a form of radiation in sunlight called ultraviolet B is killing off eggs of frogs and toads known to be in decline in the Cascade Mountains of Oregon. Biologists found that the species that are in decline appear to have relatively limited abilities to repair damage from this natural radiation, which alters the structure of the genetic material, DNA.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCIENTISTS investigating a worldwide decline in frogs and other amphibians have found the first strong evidence identifying a likely global culprit: the rise in ultraviolet radiation caused by the thinning of the atmospheric ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Researchers from Oregon State University say a new study shows that a form of radiation in sunlight called ultraviolet B is killing off eggs of frogs and toads known to be in decline in the Cascade Mountains of Oregon. Biologists found that the species that are in decline appear to have relatively limited abilities to repair damage from this natural radiation, which alters the structure of the genetic material, DNA.</p>
        <p>In addition, they found evidence that many amphibian species probably lack the ability to protect themselves from increases in UV-B radiation. Their study was published today in The Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>"This paper provides something close to a smoking gun for the causation of the disappearances," said Prof. Michael Soule, chairman of the department of environmental studies at the University of California at Santa Cruz. "It's very convincing. The work is excellent. And it's important because it provides a reasonable and intuitively attractive hypothesis for these disappearances."</p>
        <p>Dr. William Dunson, professor of biology at Pennsylvania State University, agreed, calling the study "excellent." He said, "The most exciting thing is that of all the global scenarios, this is the one that's most likely to be happening."</p>
        <p>Loralei Saylor, a researcher with the Declining Amphibian Populations Task Force, an organization of scientists who are concerned with causes of and potential remedies for the decline, praised the study.</p>
        <p>But researchers cautioned that it remained to be seen just how big a role ultraviolet damage played in the overall decline of amphibians. Some suggested that it might not in the end turn out to have any single global cause. And researchers agree that factors like acidification and pollution come into play and are known to be contributing in some regions. In any case, they say, these sensitive indicator species are most likely undergoing attack from multiple threats in their environment.</p>
        <p>Researchers only very recently began considering the hypothesis that increases in ultraviolet radiation caused by a thinning ozone layer might be the invisible threat doing in amphibians.</p>
        <p>The reasoning was that these animals might be especially susceptible to increasing UV-B rays, which can cause cancer and cataracts in humans, since their gelatinous eggs are unprotected by shells or leathery covers and their skin is bare of feathers or hair. Researchers also noticed that many of the species that were disappearing for no apparent reason lived at high altitudes, regions where an animal would be more at risk from the sun's radiation. Researchers' Initial Skepticism</p>
        <p>But with scant data on UV-B increases in most parts of the world and no data to suggest that naturally occurring levels of UV-B could seriously harm amphibian species, most, including those who carried out the new study, had remained skeptical of the cosmic culprit.</p>
        <p>"We were shocked," said Dr. Andrew Blaustein, a population ecologist at Oregon State who is an author of the new study. "We didn't think we'd find anything. We said, 'Oh yeah, sure, UV, ha ha ha.' When we got the results, we still didn't believe it. So we replicated it and now we believe."</p>
        <p>When a DNA double helix in the nucleus of a cell is exposed to UV-B radiation from the sun, a single strand can bond to itself, forming abnormal ringlike structures. DNA damaged in this way can become balled up enough to prevent replication as well as the production of proteins. The amphibians' answer to this problem is photolyase, an enzyme that repairs the DNA by returning it to its normal structure.</p>
        <p>The UV-sensitivity hypothesis predicts that UV-B is indeed a significant threat to amphibians. If that is true, researchers say those species whose eggs are exposed to more sunlight should have evolved to have more photolyase activity to protect them. The Oregon State researchers compared 10 species whose habits ranged from hiding their eggs to laying them in uncovered, shallow water and found that photolyase repair activity was indeed greatest in those suffering the highest exposure and least in those most protected by shade.</p>
        <p>"I thought we'd see roughly the same amounts of repair activity in all the animals," said Dr. John Hays, a molecular geneticist at Oregon State University who was another author of the study. "I was very skeptical of the theory and I was very surprised when we saw hundredfold differences from one species to another."</p>
        <p>But was the variation in repair ability seen in the laboratory actually playing itself out in the survival of individuals in the wild?</p>
        <p>Three of the species native to the Northwest, the Pacific treefrog, the Western toad and the Cascades frog all lay their eggs exposed in shallow, open water but were found to vary widely in photolyase activity. The Pacific treefrog showed the highest activity of any species in the study. While the Western toad and Cascades frog showed more activity than species that hide their eggs, they showed significantly less than the treefrog.</p>
        <p>Monitoring the species' eggs when exposed to the sun in mountain lakes under natural conditions, scientists found the Pacific treefrog's eggs did best, with nearly 100 percent of eggs hatching. Only about 45 to 65 percent of the other two species' eggs hatched into tadpoles. Researchers also found they could sharply improve the survival of Western toad and Cascades frog eggs by shielding them with a filter that blocked UV-B light.</p>
        <p>And just as the UV-sensitivity hypothesis would predict, the Western toad and Cascades frog are undergoing a marked, recent decline, while the Pacific treefrog is not. Scientists say it appears that the photolyase in these eggs might once have been enough but that the repair abilities of the now declining species are no longer great enough to counteract the amount of UV-B they are receiving.</p>
        <p>Just as the Cascades frog and Western toad seem to point to a rise in UV-B, atmospheric scientists have found that their instruments agree. In a paper published late last year in the journal Science, researchers in Toronto reported an increase in UV-B radiation along with a decrease in ozone over the last four years. The study provided the first long-term data documenting the suspected increases outside Antarctica.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jim Kerr, head of ozone research and monitoring at Environment Canada, an author of the Science paper, said: "It's important because there's no reason why what we observed with UV-B in Toronto would be very much different from what is happening in Oregon, which is at a similar latitude, global changes in ozone being dependent upon latitude."</p>
        <p>Although it is a powerful hypothesis, UV-sensitivity cannot easily explain all the disappearances. Dr. Blaustein says the new study indicates that high altitude species that lay their eggs in the open are most likely to suffer from UV-B increases. But some of the world's disappearing amphibians are lowland species, which researchers say are less likely to be affected. And even some seemingly likely candidates are probably not, including the golden toad.</p>
        <p>Known from only one location in the mountain cloud forest in Monteverde, Costa Rica, the golden toad's populations went from healthy hundreds in 1987 to nearly none in 1988. None have been seen in the last two years. Dr. Martha Crump, a behavioral ecologist who is an adjunct professor at Northern Arizona University, said that despite matching the profile of an at-risk amphibian, the golden toad probably was not extinguished by UV-B, as its eggs are laid in a dark and misty forest.</p>
        <p>Dr. Blaustein said he and colleagues were now looking into whether other species and other life stages besides eggs were also affected by UV-B radiation. Scientists say it remains to be seen whether whole groups of plants or fish, for example, are also suffering.</p>
        <p>"The implications are that the thinning of the ozone layer may already be affecting wildlife," said Dr. Soule, "and if further work supports that conclusion, it means that we can't rest on our laurels. We'll have to do something about repairing the ozone layer, come up with therapies for the ozone, rather than doing what governments are doing, which is just waiting for it to stop getting worse."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
