<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fog Thickens on Climate And Origin of Humans</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="687904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WALKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONKEYS AND APES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KENYA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINGSTON, JOHN D (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILL, ANDREW (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARINO, BRUNO D (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Hiking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Walking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monkeys and Apes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D81738F934A25756C0A962958260" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fog Thickens on Climate And Origin of Humans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN one of evolution's fateful transitions, especially from the human perspective, some tree-dwelling creatures split off from the main line of apes sometime before five million years ago. They dropped out of the trees and learned to forage over an ever-widening range. Since they were not built to walk on all fours, but needed an efficient way to get around on the ground, they pulled themselves up from their knuckle-dragging stoop and, once standing upright, began walking about on two legs.</p>
        <p>Upright walking, bipedality, was a definitive characteristic of the earliest hominids, the group of apelike animals that included ancestors of modern humans. How bipedality came about remains one of the mysteries of human evolution, though many theories have been proposed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN one of evolution's fateful transitions, especially from the human perspective, some tree-dwelling creatures split off from the main line of apes sometime before five million years ago. They dropped out of the trees and learned to forage over an ever-widening range. Since they were not built to walk on all fours, but needed an efficient way to get around on the ground, they pulled themselves up from their knuckle-dragging stoop and, once standing upright, began walking about on two legs.</p>
        <p>Upright walking, bipedality, was a definitive characteristic of the earliest hominids, the group of apelike animals that included ancestors of modern humans. How bipedality came about remains one of the mysteries of human evolution, though many theories have been proposed.</p>
        <p>Researchers have now challenged one of the favorite explanations. They say they have found evidence disputing the idea that upright walking was an evolutionary response to drastic climate change. With the coming of cooler, more arid conditions, the theory holds, much of the eastern African forest disappeared, forcing these human ancestors out of their natural habitat and into open grasslands where they had to develop new strategies for survival.</p>
        <p>By analyzing ancient soils from the Rift Valley in Kenya, the scientists detected carbon residues indicating that for the last 15.5 million years the mix of forest and grasses was always much the same as it is today.</p>
        <p>"There's no evidence for any dramatic shift in vegetation over this time," Dr. John D. Kingston, an anthropologist at Yale University, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>If hominids evolved in this part of East Africa, as suggested by some fossils, the new findings suggest that they did so in an ecologically diverse setting and apparently were not influenced by sharp climatic changes. Dr. Kingston's research team reported this interpretation of the soil studies in the current issue of the journal Science. The other authors of the report are Dr. Andrew Hill, another Yale anthropologist, and Dr. Bruno D. Marino, a geologist at Harvard University.</p>
        <p>"While the course of human evolution was surely affected by environmental change," the researchers wrote, "our data suggest that interpretations of the origin of hominids in East Africa should be considered within the context of a heterogeneous mosaic of environments rather than an abrupt replacement of rain forests by grassland and woodland biomes."</p>
        <p>As Dr. Kingston said, the results alerted scientists that the adaptation of upright walking was probably a more complicated process than the climate-change and disappearing-forest theory would seem to indicate.</p>
        <p>"This will force people to look at other factors to explain bipedalism," he said.</p>
        <p>The transition from the trees to upright walking may have also been influenced by competition from other animals for food and the opportunity to occupy a more promising ecological niche, the grassland dotted with trees and known as savanna.</p>
        <p>Paleontologists were generally cautious in their reaction because the results fly in the face of scientific thinking going back to Darwin. An accumulating body of evidence from Arctic ice cores and deep-sea sediments has identified pronounced global climate changes over this period and revealed that some of them seemed to coincide with major developments in human evolution. The pattern appeared clearest, scientists said, in the last three million years, when the dating of sediments and fossils has been more precise.</p>
        <p>A cold, dry spell 2.8 million years ago, for example, has been associated with the appearance of expansive grasslands in parts of sub-Saharan Africa where there had been dense forests. At this same time, the genus Homo emerged. Another cold period a million years ago coincided with the extinction of the genus Australopithecus, a parallel hominid lineage, and what may have been the expansion out of Africa of Homo erectus, the increasingly humanlike species that preceded Homo sapiens.</p>
        <p>Dr. Elisabeth S. Vrba, a Yale paleontologist who has championed the climate hypothesis of human evolution, said: "It's very exciting data.  But I'm a little cautious about exactly what it means." Meaning of Findings</p>
        <p>The findings, she said, may indeed be correct and reveal that in at least this one part of Africa there was little change in vegetation through time. Another possibility, she added, is that "this kind of measurement is not capturing what is really happening," perhaps because significant but short-term changes do not stand out from overall conditions.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kingston examined ancient soils taken from outcroppings at 95 sites over an 800-square-mile area in the Tugen Hills region of the Rift Valley, the deep tectonic scar running through East Africa. The soils were analyzed for the proportion of two types of carbon residue. One type reflects the presence long ago of trees, shrubs and grasses preferring wet growing conditions. Another type is linked almost exclusively to grasses and sedges in warm, arid and open habitats.</p>
        <p>"We didn't see the signature for any sharp change from forests to savanna," Dr. Kingston said.</p>
        <p>While proponents of the climate-change hypothesis usually cite conditions in the last three million years, Dr. Kingston said there has been a virtual absence of supporting evidence for the period from 10 million to 5 million years ago, when bipedalism is supposed to have developed. The new study helps fill that gap and leaves scientists with a new puzzle: If there were global climate fluctuations, as seen in the marine cores, how did they manifest themselves, if at all, in East African habitats?</p>
        <p>If the new study is correct, said Dr. Eric Delson, a paleontologist at Lehman College of the City University of New York, this would accord with a view that is gaining adherents. "Human ancestors," he noted, "may have moved to the ground more to take advantage of opportunities on the open ground and less because they were forced to."</p>
        <p>Dr. Kingston conceded that an abrupt environmental change might have occurred elsewhere in Africa during this time. Other paleontologists felt that more research in other parts of Africa was required before they would consider abandoning support of the climate-change theory.</p>
        <p>"This shows that in one test place, and a very important one, Kingston doesn't pick up the major pulses of environment change," said Dr. Henry McHenry, a paleontologist at the University of California at Davis, who specializes in hominid evolution. "West and central Africa were probably sites of some of these transitions, but we just don't have any fossils from there." Theory on Parting From Apes</p>
        <p>But Dr. Yves Coppens, a paleontologist at the College of France in Paris, thinks the Rift Valley itself could explain the divergence of hominids from the other apes. He described this idea in the current issue of Scientific American.</p>
        <p>From the fossil record, scientists find, early hominids were present in Ethiopia, Kenya and Tanzania by eight million years ago, but there has been no sign there of any precursors from the other branches of the ape family, the chimpanzee and the gorilla. Their remains are confined to regions west of the Rift Valley, where their descendants mostly live today.</p>
        <p>So Dr. Coppens proposed that "a tectonic crisis" eight million years ago set the hominids on their separate course. A seismic split in the earth at that time, recognized by geophysicists, deepened the Rift Valley. This formed a biological barrier between east and west. The sinking of the valley produced an upthrust of mountains to the west, disturbing atmospheric circulation and leaving the land west of the valley more humid and arboreal, while the east was dominated by savanna.</p>
        <p>The common ancestors of the hominids and the chimpanzees (the gorillas had already diverged) thus found themselves divided. Those adapting to the humid west evolved into the chimpanzee family. Those left in the more arid east, Dr. Coppens wrote, "invented a completely new repertoire in order to adapt to their new life in an open environment."</p>
        <p>Dr. Coppens calls this hypothesis the "East Side Story" of how some apes came down from the trees, learned to walk upright and eventually evolved into humans. One would expect the soil study to show signs of such a sudden appearance of savannas on the east side, said Dr. Hill, one of Dr. Kingston's co-authors, but there has been not a trace. So where in the ancient soils is the evidence from hypothesized environmental changes? That is Dr. Kingston's question.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
