<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="812521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DB1139F932A35751C1A963958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>G.M. to Recall Cadillacs In Settlement With U.S. General Motors agreed to recall nearly a half-million late-model Cadillacs and spend nearly $45 million in fines and other costs, settling a Federal complaint  that the auto maker had installed devices that caused the cars to emit illegal amounts of carbon dioxide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>G.M. to Recall Cadillacs In Settlement With U.S. General Motors agreed to recall nearly a half-million late-model Cadillacs and spend nearly $45 million in fines and other costs, settling a Federal complaint  that the auto maker had installed devices that caused the cars to emit illegal amounts of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Government lawyers said they believed the company knew the design change would cause pollution problems, an assertion the company denied. G.M. called the case "a matter of interpretation" of complex rules. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Barings Trader Pleads Guilty To 2 Charges in Singapore  Nicholas Leeson pleaded guilty to fraud and forgery charges, two of 11 charges he faced in Singapore in the trading scandal that led to the collapse of Barings P.L.C. under $1.38 billion of debt. Lawyers said the plea bargain suggested he would be sentenced to one or two years in prison, rather than the 14 years he might have faced. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Colgate Consolidates Account  Colgate-Palmolive moved $150 million to $200 million of advertising billings from Foote, Cone &amp; Belding, to Young &amp; Rubicam, in one of the biggest realignments in the industry. Young &amp; Rubicam ends up with about $550 million of Colgate's total billings. [D5.]</p>
        <p>A Bleak November for Stores  Retailers had more depressing sales in November. The sales rose a mere 2.9 percent from November 1994, as mild weather, price deflation and a slowing economy all played roles. Apparel and department stores did poorly, but luxury stores showed gains. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Orders for durable goods fell 1 percent in October, as demand plunged for aircraft. The drop was the first in three months, and led economists to conclude that the economy seems to be softening again. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Deal Proposed by Sara Lee  Sara Lee offered to sell its food-distribution business to JP Foodservice in an  $821 million stock transaction that would give Sara Lee a majority interest in JP. [D6.]</p>
        <p>Stocks End a String of Records  Late computer-driven selling pushed stocks lower. The Dow Jones industrial average tumbled 31.07 points to 5,074.49, after reaching new highs for six straight sessions. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell, while the Nasdaq  composite index inched up. Bonds soared nearly a point, with the yield on a 30-year Treasury bond slumping  to 6.13 percent, a two-year low. [D6.]</p>
        <p>Tribune Invests in Softkey  Softkey won a key ally in the Tribune Company as it wages a hostile bid for the  Learning Company. Tribune would invest $150 million in Softkey if the deal is completed, and will swap a new-media property for Softkey stock. [D2.] Packard Bell Denies Problems Packard Bell denied experiencing financial problems and said that 1995 sales would exceed $4.6 billion, a gain of 45 percent. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Cosby to Start Show on CBS  CBS is to announce plans for Bill Cosby's first situation comedy since his "Cosby Show" was TV's biggest hit in the 1980's. The deal is said to be one of the biggest financial commitments a network has made in recent years, and will guarantee the new show a two-year run. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Lazard Out of Municipals  Lazard Freres is getting out of the municipal finance business, where a series of missteps cost the firm clients and money. [D16.]</p>
        <p>Celebrities Fight AIDS  Celebrities are beginning to appear in ads that encourage the fight against AIDS. They are the central elements of public-service campaigns for World AIDS Day, being observed today. The trend indicates that personalities known to consumers are becoming more comfortable helping to combat a disease that still carries a stigma among many Americans. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [D5.] Health Systems Accuses Wellpoint Health Systems accused Wellpoint Health Networks and Blue Cross of California of breaching an agreement to acquire Health Systems for $1.89 billion in stock. [D15.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
