<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acid-Rain Pollution Credits Are Not Enticing Utilities</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="767052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1990</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DF1339F936A35755C0A963958260" item-length="1324" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acid-Rain Pollution Credits Are Not Enticing Utilities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What do you get when you cross a free-market economist with an environmentalist?</p>
        <p>First, a Federal law that allows companies to buy and sell the right to pollute. Next, a market for the right to pollute -- and a price tag on the value of that right.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What do you get when you cross a free-market economist with an environmentalist?</p>
        <p>First, a Federal law that allows companies to buy and sell the right to pollute. Next, a market for the right to pollute -- and a price tag on the value of that right.</p>
        <p>But in the end, maybe a lot less than was predicted.</p>
        <p>Five years after the system was passed into law, trading in pollution rights is slow, and the price for the right to put a ton of acid-rain pollutants into the atmosphere, which had started low, has collapsed.</p>
        <p>In fact, the price is now so low -- a tenth of what some utility lobbyists had predicted -- that it raises questions about the assumptions that Congress used when it established the system and accompanying pollution limits. Another interpretation is that the market is simply not working.</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act of 1990 cut the allowable emissions of sulfur dioxide by roughly half. And it created a new regulatory system to reach that goal, a system described by proponents as bringing the efficiency of a free-market economy to the expensive problem of pollution control.</p>
        <p>Here is an example of how it was supposed to work:</p>
        <p>To comply with the new Federal sulfur dioxide limits, Plant A and Plant B each have to cut one ton of the pollutant. The reduction would cost $1,200 at Plant A and $1,500 at Plant B, or $2,700 total. But under the system, Plant A is allowed to reduce its pollution by two tons and sell Plant B the right to emit the second ton. The result is equal pollution reduction for $2,400, for a savings of $300. On a national basis, the savings could total billions of dollars on the cost of cutting emissions by about 10 million tons annually.</p>
        <p>"It's one of those things that looked terrific in theory," said Peter Jump, a spokesman for the Edison Electric Institute, the Washington-based trade association for the utility industry. "But once you get into the practice of it, some things don't turn out the way you expected."</p>
        <p>One clear difference is price. When Congress was debating the emission limits, utilities predicted that a one-ton allowance would sell for $1,000 or more; some said $1,500. The Environmental Protection Agency said $500 to $600.</p>
        <p>The price of a one-ton allowance is now less than $140. In 1992, when the first trades were made, it was about $250, and it has fallen every year.</p>
        <p>"Everybody was stunned," said Brian J. McLean, director of the Environmental Protection Agency's acid rain division. The industry estimates during debate on the bill, he said, may have involved some "gaming," meaning utility executives picked high numbers in an effort to dissuade Congress from imposing stricter standards. But no one thought the price would be so low, he said.</p>
        <p>The economists' theory was that if the price was low, utilities whose costs were higher would rush to buy the right to pollute. But utilities appear reluctant to buy or sell, even though the General Accounting Office said earlier this year that the utilities could cut costs if they participated more.</p>
        <p>"The lesson so far is its potential has not been realized," said Peter Guerrero, an author of a December 1994 report by the accounting office on trading pollution rights. "Trading has effectively reduced the cost of compliance, but there are far greater reductions that could result."</p>
        <p>According to the G.A.O., the annual cost of compliance in 2009, when the stricter pollution standards are fully phased in, will be about $2 billion, assuming heavy use of trading. In 1990, when Congress was debating the law, the environmental agency put the cost at twice that. In other words, the amount that Congress thought it was committing the power companies to spend -- a cost to be picked up by electricity consumers -- was fiction. The nation will achieve the pollution reduction for far less, while spending what Congress thought it was requiring would have bought far more pollution reduction.</p>
        <p>If Congress was striking a balance between environmental toughness and financial mercy, it could have required tougher standards for the amount it had agreed to make utilities spend.</p>
        <p>And some environmentalists say that the trades have made the acid rain problem worse than it would have been with a simple order that each plant reduce its pollution. New York State tried unsuccessfully to intervene when one utility cleaned up more than required and made the excess emission credits available to utilities in the Midwest -- a region whose emissions blow back into New York, aggravating the state's acid rain problem.</p>
        <p>The unanticipated twist in the market may have implications for other trading schemes that are proposed or now beginning. On Thursday, a New Jersey utility, Public Service Electric and Gas, announced a sale to a drug company, Merck, of the right to emit nitrogen oxides, which cause smog.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. is supposed to issue regulations soon on a trading system for nitrogen oxides, and economically minded environmentalists -- or perhaps, environmentally minded economists -- are predicting all kinds of permutations, including entrepreneurs who will generate credits by, for example, buying up and junking old, polluting cars. They would then sell the credits to hordes of waiting buyers.</p>
        <p>But if the utilities are an example, that kind of market is far in the future. For one thing, utilities are still choosing in-house solutions, like building scrubbers or switching to cleaner fuel, even if the cost is more than the market price of an emission credit. "You have a lot of really bright engineers who have a preference for technology over financial tools," said Christian J. Colton, a vice president of Cantor Fitzgerald, a New York firm that is a broker for emissions trades.</p>
        <p>The engineers have been helped by a drop in the price of natural gas, which produces less sulfur dioxide than coal. Coal producers have also found lower-sulfur sources. And scrubber manufacturers have cut their prices.</p>
        <p>This is not bad, said Mr. McLean of the E.P.A. "Trading is not the bottom line," he said. "Tons coming out of stacks is the relevant piece of information. My goal was to reduce emissions at the lowest possible cost, not to see 1,000 trades occur." As far as he is concerned, the cheaper an allowance gets, the better.</p>
        <p>But the price means little if utilities are reluctant to enter the market to buy or sell.</p>
        <p>They face two problems. One could be called the Robert Citron effect: they fear becoming like the former treasurer of Orange County, Calif., who put public money into complex financial instruments and lost it. If the utilities buy allowances now to stockpile for later use, and the price drops later, state regulators could argue that the purchases were imprudent and the financial loss should not be borne by customers, but by shareholders. Conversely, if they sell now and prices go up later, they could also look dumb.</p>
        <p>If utilities cut costs through the trading system, they could lower their rates, or raise their dividends to shareholders. But Mr. Colton said that only Connecticut has so far agreed to let any of the benefit flow back to shareholders. Faced with risking a loss to shareholders and no possibility of benefit, many have apparently decided not to bother.</p>
        <p>Second, the industry itself is in turmoil as it moves toward open competition in electricity, where customers can leave their utilities for the lowest-priced supplier. As a result many old plants may be retired in the next few years. "They don't know if they're going to be using the plants in a year or two," said Mr. Jump of the trade group.</p>
        <p>The market could pick up in the next few years. Many utilities are believed to be stockpiling allowances for Jan. 1, 2000, when a second phase of the acid rain program takes effect and the emission limits become stricter. But some attitudes may have to change first.</p>
        <p>"Toes have got to be stuck in the water," said Mr. Jump, "and that's taking some time to do."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
