<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Keeping the Ozone Whole</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="798688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOBEL PRIZES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED6143EF936A25753C1A963958260" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Keeping the Ozone Whole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST week, for the first time ever, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences awarded a Nobel Prize to scientists for work on an environmental problem -- in this case, the role of industrial chemicals in weakening the earth's protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>The award boosted the prestige of an area of scientific research long considered somewhat soft. It also dealt a blow to the small minority of American scientists and conservative politicians who have characterized the ozone problem as an overblown, unwarranted scare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST week, for the first time ever, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences awarded a Nobel Prize to scientists for work on an environmental problem -- in this case, the role of industrial chemicals in weakening the earth's protective ozone shield.</p>
        <p>The award boosted the prestige of an area of scientific research long considered somewhat soft. It also dealt a blow to the small minority of American scientists and conservative politicians who have characterized the ozone problem as an overblown, unwarranted scare.</p>
        <p>The Nobel prize for chemistry went to two Americans and a Dutch citizen based in Germany -- Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland of the University of California at Irvine, Dr. Mario Molina of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Dr. Paul Crutzen of the Max Planck Institute for Chemistry in Mainz, Germany.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's and 1980's, the scientists discovered and explained the processes by which chlorofluorocarbons, chemicals widely used at the time as refrigerants, plastic foams and aerosol propellants, destroy the stratospheric ozone layer. If the ozone layer were substantially depleted, ultraviolet rays from the sun could cause more skin cancer and cataracts, damage to the immune system and harm to natural ecosystems. And if the ozone layer disappeared completely, plants and animals could not exist on land. Even Industry Agreed</p>
        <p>The Nobel citation said the three ozone scientists "have contributed to our salvation from a global environmental problem that could have catastrophic consequences." The scientists' work led to the adoption, in 1992, of a global phaseout of chlorofluorocarbons, or CFCs, that is to culminate in an ban on the production of the chemicals by the end of this year.</p>
        <p>When their findings were published, the two Americans were criticized by industry. But in the end, even industry endorsed the need to protect the ozone. That, Dr. Molina said, was "very rewarding," as was the role of the Nobel award in certifying the atmospheric sciences as "a valid academic discipline."</p>
        <p>Scientists almost never achieve unanimity on any issue, but on the ozone question they have come unusually close. Still, conservative Republicans in Congress have seized on the views of the small number of dissenters to justify legislation to repeal the CFC ban in the United States. That legislation, recently introduced, has never been considered likely to pass any time soon. And now that the Nobel committee has weighed in, the possibility seems even more unlikely. WILLIAM K. STEVENS  THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
