<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Use of Hydrogen as Fuel Is Moving Closer to Reality</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="755544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROGEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDE173AF935A25757C0A963958260" item-length="1673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Use of Hydrogen as Fuel Is Moving Closer to Reality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Buoyed by renewed political interest and technological promise, efforts are being stepped up to make hydrogen an important source of energy in the United States.</p>
        <p>For decades, advocates of hydrogen have promoted it as the fuel of the future: an abundant, environmentally clean source of energy for power plants, airplanes, automobiles, homes and just about everything a modern society finds essential.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Buoyed by renewed political interest and technological promise, efforts are being stepped up to make hydrogen an important source of energy in the United States.</p>
        <p>For decades, advocates of hydrogen have promoted it as the fuel of the future: an abundant, environmentally clean source of energy for power plants, airplanes, automobiles, homes and just about everything a modern society finds essential.</p>
        <p>Advocates of a hydrogen economy say that unlike gasoline and other fossil fuels, with their noxious combustion byproducts, hydrogen produces nothing worse than water when it burns. And it can be used to produce electricity directly through chemical reactions in a device called a fuel cell.</p>
        <p>Surely hydrogen would be the preferable fuel in many cases, its supporters have argued, if only a few problems could be overcome, like finding a cheap method for extracting it from water or natural gas, and setting up a storage and distribution network.</p>
        <p>Although the technical problems remain, hydrogen's political future suddenly seems brighter. One of the gas's leading advocates is Representative Robert S. Walker, Republican of Pennsylvania, who became chairman of the House Science Committee in January. He is sponsoring a bill to increase the Department of Energy's $10 million annual budget for hydrogen research by $100 million over the next three years.</p>
        <p>"Hydrogen has amazing potential and it should have its chance," Mr. Walker said in an interview. "We have the ability to overcome a lot of the problems other people see with hydrogen and, if we can make it work, it would fundamentally change the country." Mr. Walker, who is also vice chairman of the House Appropriations Committee, said his bill had a good chance of surviving the new, budget-cutting Congress because it would redirect Energy Department money from other projects and calls for no new spending.</p>
        <p>The advantages of hydrogen as a fuel include energy independence and perhaps dispensing with many antipollution regulations, "and that's something that's attractive to conservatives like myself," Mr. Walker said.</p>
        <p>Representative George E. Brown, the California Democrat who formerly headed the Science Committee, said he previously supported work on hydrogen but opposed the bill because it would drain money from other energy research. "I don't think you can justify that rapid an increase in funding," he said, "particularly since everything we do siphons money from something else. There will be some increase in funds for hydrogen, but I don't think the Appropriations Committee or the House will vote for all the money he wants."</p>
        <p>Senator Tom Harkin, a Democrat from Iowa, said he would be promoting a similar bill on the other side of the Capitol, but could not guess what its prospects were. "I don't know if it's high on anybody's agenda except mine right now," he said. Generally, the Government should support only basic research, he said, but in the case of a few technologies like hydrogen, it should assume a more active role, like sponsoring demonstration projects with industry and purchasing hydrogen-fueled vehicles to help create a market.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen researchers from universities, Government laboratories and private companies say their incipient industry has already produced cars and trucks that would be ready to market if problems of fuel supply and distribution could be solved. At an annual meeting sponsored by the National Hydrogen Association, held last month in a Washington suburb, participants rode in a modified golf cart powered by electricity from a new type of fuel cell and cruised around in a Ford pickup with an engine that engineers at the University of California at Riverside had modified to burn compressed hydrogen.</p>
        <p>Edward Trlica, president of Energy Partners, a company in West Palm Beach, Fla., that makes the modified cart, said such vehicles were ready for fleet use now in places where there could be an assured hydrogen supply, like bus and shuttle routes that operate from fixed depots. By the end of the year, he said, the company expected to be operating five of the 11-passenger carts as a test at the airport in Palms Springs, Calif.</p>
        <p>John J. Kennedy, an executive at Allied Signal Inc., who is chairman of the board of the association, said hydrogen work was being pursued aggressively in Japan and across Europe, where gasoline prices are three to four times as high as in the United States. "In this country, people are in a wait-and-see mode because oil prices are so low," he said, "and that's why we still need some Government assistance to move the technology until the market here is ready."</p>
        <p>Economics and concerns about hydrogen's safety could limit its wider use for decades, others contend. Current ways of producing hydrogen from water or natural gas are expensive and require large amounts of energy, said Dr. Saifur Rahman, director of the Center for Energy and Global Environment at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and University in Blacksburg. In addition, he believes people will probably balk at having hydrogen pipelines or storage tanks put in their communities because of concerns about cost and safety.</p>
        <p>Advocates say hydrogen, even when stored under pressure, can be handled safely. The fuel in the tank of a hydrogen-powered car, for instance, is far less volatile than gasoline and, if the tank is ruptured, hydrogen gas would dissipate quickly into the air. Even if a spark ignited the gas, proponents say, it would burn away rapidly and cause less damage than gasoline. "People are used to gasoline and forget how dangerous it can be," said James Heffel, an engineer working with the University of California hydrogen truck.</p>
        <p>Neil P. Rossmeissl, manager of the hydrogen program at the Energy Department, said the nation spent about $10 million a year on hydrogen research through the National Renewable Energy Laboratory in Golden, Colo. In addition, he said, the Government spent more than $110 million on research related to hydrogen work.</p>
        <p>"We are working on the production, storage and infrastructure for distribution of hydrogen," Mr. Rossmeissl said. "Hydrogen has been considered the long shot for the country's energy needs, something that wouldn't be ready until 2030. But we have fuel cells and engines now that can use hydrogen, and should have other end-user technology ready by 2000 or 2005. A problem is getting production technology ready at the same time."</p>
        <p>Hydrogen is an extremely abundant element, since there are two atoms of it in every molecule of water. Unfortunately, the atoms are so firmly locked that present methods use more energy to extract hydrogen than can be produced by the fuel. This cost inefficiency makes it suited only for specialized needs, like fueling space rockets or running fuel cells on spacecraft.</p>
        <p>Advocates hope the production cost can be brought down with methods like photoelectro-chemistry, a technique developed at the University of Hawaii. In the procedure a thin semiconductor suspended in water produces hydrogen using only the energy of sunlight. This method is being scaled up from laboratory size and could produce a working system in five years, Mr. Rossmeissl said.</p>
        <p>Another promising approach, under development at the Government hydrogen laboratory in Colorado, the University of Miami and elsewhere, is based on photobiology, and involves illuminating certain algae or bacteria suspended in water vapor. When exposed to sunlight, the organisms would function as part of a self-generating, living reactor that produced hydrogen and oxygen from the water.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen advocates also have hopes for a method that could solve both the production and distribution problem: generating hydrogen from natural gas. Gas companies already make commercial quantities of hydrogen from natural gas in devices called reformers. Natural gas mixed with intensely hot steam produces hydrogen.</p>
        <p>If small-scale reformers could be developed and installed at places like airports and the nation's more than 150,000 gasoline stations, the mechanical systems needed for a hydrogen economy could emerge by using the natural gas pipe system already in place, proponents say.</p>
        <p>But current reformer technology was developed 25 years ago, Mr. Rossmeissl noted, and little work had been sponsored by the industry to improve it. "We want to develop some base technology in reformers that could be applied to large and small applications, but nothing is being done now," he said. "Some people have some ideas about this, but there is no money for it."</p>
        <p>Hydrogen has another major problem: storage. Lightweight hydrogen contains less energy per unit of volume than gasoline or even natural gas, and it must be either compressed or liquefied at extremely low temperatures to be concentrated enough to be a useful fuel. Heavy, bulky vessels, which would consume extra space in vehicles, would be required for storage.</p>
        <p>To overcome this problem, researchers have turned to solid-state storage methods that use materials like metal alloys and activated carbon to absorb and retain hydrogen. When containers of these materials are cooled and hydrogen is forced in, the scientists say, the carbon or the alloys, called metal hydrides, can hold concentrations of the fuel comparable to compressed gas systems, but with less weight and bulk. Heating these storage systems or decreasing their internal pressure causes the hydrogen to be released, they say.</p>
        <p>Although prototype hydride storage systems are being tested in cars and for other uses, Mr. Rossmeissl said more research was needed on these solid-state storage systems to find the best materials, to see if they could be economically produced and to check whether they remained durable and maintained their storage capacity with repeated loading and unloading.</p>
        <p>"Some of the best science being done right now is in hydrogen research," he said. "The biggest problem with hydrogen is still its costs, the cost of producing and storing it, and changing the infrastructure of society to use it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
