<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="789847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALSACE (FRANCE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France/Alsace-Lorraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D91F30F933A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A FRIEND about to leave for a canal trip in the Alsace region of France recently showed me the wine list for his particular barge. It was a short list -- canal barges are not known for their extensive cellars -- but it was made up entirely of Burgundies, with one forlorn Bordeaux at the end. It offered not a single Alsatian wine.</p>
        <p>I thought: does Hubert Trimbach know about this? Or Johnny Hugel or Lionel Humbrecht or Colette Faller or any of the other producers of great Alsatian wines? Regional pride, not to mention commercial realities, would seem to demand some sort of protest on their part.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A FRIEND about to leave for a canal trip in the Alsace region of France recently showed me the wine list for his particular barge. It was a short list -- canal barges are not known for their extensive cellars -- but it was made up entirely of Burgundies, with one forlorn Bordeaux at the end. It offered not a single Alsatian wine.</p>
        <p>I thought: does Hubert Trimbach know about this? Or Johnny Hugel or Lionel Humbrecht or Colette Faller or any of the other producers of great Alsatian wines? Regional pride, not to mention commercial realities, would seem to demand some sort of protest on their part.</p>
        <p>Sad to say, Alsatian wine makers have grown philosophical about their relationship with the rest of the French wine community. They have come to accept that each new generation of wine enthusiasts, particularly in the United States, is going to be surprised to discover that Alsace is truly part of France.</p>
        <p>Despite its proximity to Germany, that it has even been part of Germany at various times and that its place names and even its grapes are Germanic, Alsace is entirely French.</p>
        <p>What better proof than the two daily German invasions? During lunch and dinner, the parking lots of the Auberge de l'Ill and the other top Alsatian restaurants are filled with Mercedes, BMW's and Porsches with German license plates.</p>
        <p>The Alsatian wine region is in the far northeast corner of France, between the Vosges Mountains and the Rhine River. The best vineyards are on the lower slopes of the Vosges chain. The vineyards stretch about 70 miles from Marlenheim, which is northwest of Strasbourg, south to Thann, which is west of Mulhouse. This grape-growing area is narrow, rarely more than three miles wide.</p>
        <p>A separate 500-acre wine enclave, far to the north along the German border and surrounding the French town of Wissembourg, is considered part of the Alsace appellation.</p>
        <p>As is the case in neighboring Germany, a small amount of red wine is made in Alsace, but the area is overwhelmingly a white-wine region. The most important grapes are riesling and gewurztraminer, but there are many others, principally pinot blanc, sylvaner, chasselas, muscat, pinot noir and pinot gris.</p>
        <p>Alsatians adopted the use of varietal names long before the current vogue for identifying wines by the grape names -- chardonnay, cabernet sauvignon, merlot. This may have been, in part, because under German domination from 1871 until World War I, the Alsatian vineyards were used to produce cheap wines, often from hybrid grapes, to be used in blending with better German wines. After that war, the Alsatian growers set about replanting the noble varieties, only to see most vineyards destroyed in fierce fighting toward the end of World War II.</p>
        <p>Replanting resumed in the 1950's, and in 1962 the entire region was awarded the French Government's quality status, Appellation Controlee. In 1983, wines made from grapes from the finest vineyards were permitted to add those vineyard names to their labels. That year also produced the first set of rules for making sweet vendange tardive -- literally, late harvest -- wines.</p>
        <p>Late-harvest wines are made from grapes that are left on the vine after the regular harvest to increase their sugar content. The process is similar to that used in the Bordeaux region to make Sauternes. A vendange tardive wine must come from one of four varieties -- riesling, gewurztraminer, muscat or pinot gris.</p>
        <p>A further refinement of the vendange tardive process, introduced in recent years, is called selection de grains nobles and identifies wine of even higher sugar content than that found in vendange tardive wines. Selection de grains nobles wines can sell for $100 or more a bottle. For that reason, many producers are trying to make them, but quality varies.</p>
        <p>Most Alsatian wines undergo chaptalization, in which sugar is added before or during fermentation. This does not make the wines sweeter, because the sugar is converted into alcohol and carbon dioxide along with the natural sugar in the grapes. But it does increase the alcohol content. Vendange tardive and selection de grains nobles wines do not undergo chaptalization.</p>
        <p>Riesling makes Alsace's most elegant wines. Alsatian rieslings, unlike most German and American rieslings, are bone dry. The best, like Trimbach's Cuvee Frederic Emile, need up to 10 years to reach their best. It has been said that because Alsatian riesling is so subtle and complex that it is a connoisseur's wine.</p>
        <p>Gewurztraminer is easily the most popular Alsatian wine. While it is fermented to be dry, it gives the impresssion of being sweet, because its bouquet and taste are so flowery and fruity. High alcohol and low acidity also contribute to the impression of sweetness. Zind-Humbrecht's Grand Cru Goldert is a perfect example of a gewurztraminer that gives the impression of sweetness but is, in fact, completely dry.</p>
        <p>These wines are not inexpensive. Trimbach's Cuvee Frederic Emile 1989 is about $20, its Clos Ste-Hune 1988 is about $50, and Zind-Humbrecht's Grand Cru Goldert is about $30. The late-harvest wines are in another category altogether. A 1989 gewurztraminer Cuvee Anne from the Domaines Schlumberger is around $80, and Zind-Humbrecht's selection de grains nobles pinot gris from the Clos Jebsal vineyard in Turckheim, France, a tremendously concentrated, heavy-bodied sweet wine, sells for well over $300 a bottle.</p>
        <p>Does this mean fine Alsace wines are for the fortunate few? No. Trimbach's regular 1992 gewurztraminer sells for about $11, and the pinot gris reserve from the same vintage is about $10. A delightful sylvaner 1992, from Hugel, is about $9.</p>
        <p>If you should find yourself cruising the waterways of Alsace with only Burgundy to slake your thirst, mutiny. Or ask for shore leave and head for the nearest wine cellar. TASTINGS Le Jaja de Jau, Chateau de Jau (Languedoc-Roussillon). About $6. There has been a big effort in recent years to promote the varietal wines of southern France. Cabernet sauvignon, chardonnay, merlot and sauvignon blanc dressed in handsome bottles have replaced the traditional hot-climate grapes and unfamiliar place names that made wines from this region difficult to sell. The new varietals are well priced, but the old rule that you get what you pay for still applies. Many are just boring. Le Jaja de Jau is not a varietal. There are four different Mediterranean grapes in it, all from young vines: mourvedre, syrah, grenache and carignan. Nor is it boring. It's fresh, lively and unpretentious. When lightly chilled, it goes with anything. Jaja is said to be slang for everyday wine in the south of France. The attractive label is by the fashionable Swiss graffiti artist Ben.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
