<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Seeks To Streamline Nuclear Labs</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="740923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATOMIC WEAPONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LAWRENCE LIVERMORE NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ALAMOS NATIONAL LABORATORY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILTS, PHILIP J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEED91E39F931A35751C0A963958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Seeks To Streamline Nuclear Labs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HILTS, PHILIP J</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The longstanding rivalry between the nation's two nuclear weapons design laboratories, Livermore and Los Alamos, should be ended, said a Federal advisory report released today. The study said several other large national physics laboratories should be made more efficient and taken out of the Government's hands.</p>
        <p>The Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in Livermore, Calif., established to compete with the Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico in designing nuclear weapons, should turn over all the design work to its rival, the advisory panel said. The panel included both scientists and industry executives and was headed by Robert W. Galvin, chairman of the executive committee of Motorola Inc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The longstanding rivalry between the nation's two nuclear weapons design laboratories, Livermore and Los Alamos, should be ended, said a Federal advisory report released today. The study said several other large national physics laboratories should be made more efficient and taken out of the Government's hands.</p>
        <p>The Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in Livermore, Calif., established to compete with the Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico in designing nuclear weapons, should turn over all the design work to its rival, the advisory panel said. The panel included both scientists and industry executives and was headed by Robert W. Galvin, chairman of the executive committee of Motorola Inc.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Hazel R. O'Leary said she accepted the general thrust of the report, which will be the basis of recommendations to Congress. The new Republican majority is likely to be more open to plans that call for privatization and spending cutbacks. Despite the much reduced workload of the weapons' labs, the report did not recommend closing down any of them.</p>
        <p>The panel was asked to look at the Department of Energy's 10 premier physics laboratories, often referred to as national assets because of their high level of physics expertise. Those at Los Alamos, Livermore and the Sandia National Laboratories in Albuquerque, N.M., are concerned directly with the design and function of nuclear warheads; the others conduct research on nuclear energy, high energy physics and an increasing range of other subjects as they search for new roles in the aftermath of the cold war.</p>
        <p>They are the Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton, L.I., the Argonne National Laboratory in Illinois, the Idaho National Engineering Laboratory in Idaho Falls, the Oak Ridge National Laboratory in Tennessee, the Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory in California, the National Renewable Energy Laboratory in Golden, Colo., and the Pacific Northwest Laboratory in Richland, Wash.</p>
        <p>The panel, given the cumbersome name of the Energy Advisory Board Task Force on Alternative Futures for the Department of Energy National Laboratories, concluded that while some of the finest scientific research in America was done in the national laboratories, "the current system of governance of these laboratories is broken and should be replaced with a bold alternative."</p>
        <p>Secretary O'Leary said that the Government had not managed the laboratories well and that they had grown "too fat and too heavy" with needless bureaucracy and duplicated functions, and would do much better if her department interfered less in their management.</p>
        <p>Altogether, the Energy Department oversees more than two dozen national laboratories at a cost of $6.8 billion, or one-third of the department's entire budget. The labs now employ about 50,000 people.</p>
        <p>The report did not set specific targets for budget reduction. The Department of Energy already has a goal: to cut 15 percent of its entire budget within five years.</p>
        <p>Among the panel's recommendations were these:</p>
        <p>*Shrinking the size of the national labs over several years. Though no figure was given, the labs are so inefficiently managed that 30 to 50 percent of the current costs can be saved by streamlining, Mr. Galvin said.</p>
        <p>*Devising a new system for governing the laboratories. Congress should undertake this, and Mr. Galvin said the labs should be run "exactly like a private corporation" but entirely with public money. He suggested establishing a board of directors of executives of major corporations, who would oversee the 10 labs as if they were subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>*Eliminating work on weapons production at the Livermore, Los Alamos and Sandia laboratories and shifting to weapons maintenance, housed mostly at Los Alamos and Sandia. Livermore should shift from work on weapons design to work on issues of nuclear proliferation, treaty verification and intelligence.</p>
        <p>None of the laboratories should be closed, the report said, because all have strong scientific work being carried on. The mission of each should be more clearly outlined, the report said, and work that duplicates that of other labs should be transferred or eliminated.</p>
        <p>Peter Didisheim, a special assistant to Secretary O'Leary for science and technology, said there was a general agreement that since the laboratories had been created as joint ventures between contractors and the Government, the Government had become the primary partner. Mr. Didisheim said a proposal that was an interesting compromise suggestion came from Dr. John P. McTague, a vice president of the Ford Motor Company. He suggested that a board of directors for the labs be created within the Department of Energy and include top agency officials and corporate executives.</p>
        <p>Butler Derrick, a member of the Department of Energy Advisory Board, the parent body of the panel issuing the report today, called Mr. Galvins's proposal for a board from outside the Government unrealistic. He said someone would have to "live in a dream world" to believe that Congress would give $6 billion in laboratories to corporate executives and not oversee their work.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
