<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hiss! Crackle! Sputter!</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIREPLACES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROMANO, JAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fireplaces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF1630F931A15753C1A963958260" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hiss! Crackle! Sputter!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAY ROMANO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROMANO, JAY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE are few things more likely to arouse warm, cozy feelings than the scent of a wood fire in October. That is, of course, as long as the smoke isn't filling your den.</p>
        <p>Autumn is when even the most cerebral homeowners roll up their shirtsleeves and engage in the ancient art of building a fire in their living quarters. Some quickly succeed, and, after seemingly little effort, repose in the glow of a crackling scarlet blaze. Others aren't so lucky.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE are few things more likely to arouse warm, cozy feelings than the scent of a wood fire in October. That is, of course, as long as the smoke isn't filling your den.</p>
        <p>Autumn is when even the most cerebral homeowners roll up their shirtsleeves and engage in the ancient art of building a fire in their living quarters. Some quickly succeed, and, after seemingly little effort, repose in the glow of a crackling scarlet blaze. Others aren't so lucky.</p>
        <p>Some exhaust every combustible material within reach just to get it going. Some succeed only to find that a family of nesting squirrels fled the chimney but left their home behind. Others get the bad news even sooner when they realize they forgot to open the damper.</p>
        <p>People make fires in their homes for all sorts of reasons. Some even use them for heat. Here's how to keep your home fires burning -- and why doing it right might even save you some money.</p>
        <p>But first things first.</p>
        <p>"Clean your chimney!" said Walter William Carlson, the owner of W. W. Carlson Chimney Repair in Newtown, Conn.</p>
        <p>Believe it or not, there is actually stuff in your chimney that can burn. It's called creosote -- the black, fluffy substance that accumulates on the inside of a chimney or stovepipe. Creosote is what remains of what was supposed to go up in smoke. If enough accumulates, it can catch fire in all the wrong places and make life downright miserable.</p>
        <p>Experts like Mr. Carlson recommend a professional chimney-cleaning each year before the first fire. With the right equipment, of course, industrious homeowners can probably clean their chimneys themselves. (With the right equipment, they could probably clean their septic tanks, too.  But who would want to?)</p>
        <p>"Cleaning an ordinary chimney costs about $75," Mr. Carlson said, adding that homeowners who insist on stretching their luck should at least look up (or down) the chimney to see if birds or squirrels have made nests inside over the summer. At the very least, such an inspection will insure that the damper gets opened.</p>
        <p>Chip Brown, the owner of Pipe Dream Stove and Chimney Shop in Ashford, Conn., said that wood-burning stoves should be checked for leaks or cracks at joints and for worn gaskets on the door. Glass fireplace doors, Mr. Brown said, should also be checked for gaps and leaks where the frame meets the hearth.</p>
        <p>And whether your combustion chamber of choice is a standard fireplace or a wood-burning stove, it is important to burn only "seasoned" wood. It lights easier, burns better and makes less nasty creosote. "Wood used for burning should be cut, split and stacked for a year," said Scott A. Robinson, manager of Nordic Woodstove &amp; Fireplace in Old Greenwich, Conn. "If it hisses when it's burning, that's a sign it's too wet."</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson also said that wood stored outside should be protected from rain and snow. "But cover only the top and leave the sides open," he said. "People cover the whole woodpile with those big blue tarps and they create a greenhouse effect in there."</p>
        <p>Most experts agree that the best wood for burning is "anything that's hard." Maple and oak are good choices, they say, as are walnut, apple, cherry and even poplar.  (Avoid cedar -- it burns easily with much noise and pretty flames, but it also creates lots of creosote and makes sparks that can fly across the room. Also, those fake logs are all right for fireplaces but should not be used in wood stoves -- they need lots of air to burn properly.)</p>
        <p>Now, for the hard part -- ignition.</p>
        <p>Just about anyone who has ever tried to build a fire in a fireplace has asked the question: "How do forest fires start when I can't even get a dried-out, six-year-old log to burn?" The trick, it seems, is to start small.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson of Nordic Woodstove said that a layer of small, dry twigs on top of some crumpled-up newspaper should be topped with another layer of slightly larger pieces of wood and lit from the bottom. Once the fire starts, he said, larger pieces of wood can be added.</p>
        <p>For those who would rather spend their time uncorking a bottle of wine, "instant" fire-starters are available at most hardware stores.</p>
        <p>However you choose to start your fire, the most important thing to remember is the draft. Smoke wants to go up a chimney because warm air is lighter than cold air. Air from the outside wants to come down the chimney for the opposite reason. If the chimney itself is cold, the air from the outside wins.</p>
        <p>"A chimney will not draw if it's cold," said Bernie Przywara, owner of Pocono Stove in Daleville, Pa. So the idea is to start with a fire hot enough to warm the chimney as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to the subject of heat.</p>
        <p>"A fireplace with a chimney is like a big tube stuck in the middle of your house sucking heat out," said Mr. Brown of Pipe Dream Stove and Chimney Shop.</p>
        <p>Modern wood-burning stoves, Mr. Brown said, are from 70 to 80 percent efficient, meaning that only 20 to 30 percent of the heat created by the stove goes up the chimney. Open-hearth fireplaces, on the other hand, send as much as 80 or 90 percent of their heat into the great beyond.</p>
        <p>In addition to being more efficient, Mr. Brown said, wood-burning stoves manufactured after 1988 -- when federally imposed emission standards took effect -- burn much cleaner than earlier stoves.</p>
        <p>"Older stoves put up to 60 grams of solids per hour into the atmosphere," Mr. Brown said. "Today's stoves are as low as 1 gram per hour."</p>
        <p>Timothy Colwick, the owner of Afterglow Energy Center in Meriden, Conn., said that clean-burning, high-efficiency wood stoves can be used to "zone heat" areas of a house where people spend most of their time, thereby saving money on central heating costs.</p>
        <p>And to be fair to fireplaces, it should be noted that modern hearths -- particularly prefabricated, gas-fired units -- are far more efficient than their romantic but notoriously inefficient predecessors.</p>
        <p>"Fireplaces have come a long way," said Don Turano, the owner of the Fireplace Store in Seaford, L.I.  "Some direct-vent sealed units are over 75 percent efficient," he said, referring to newer fireplaces that burn so cleanly they don't even need a chimney but can be vented directly through a wall, as is done with a clothes dryer.</p>
        <p>"There are even free-standing, direct-venting, gas-fired wood stoves on the market that are more efficient than regular wood stoves," he said. "But people aren't concerned about energy these days. A lot of people just want them for looks."  YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
