<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Punta Arenas Journal; A Hole in the Heavens (Chicken Little Below?)</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746400"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHILE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PUNTAS ARENAS (CHILE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAGAS, BEDRICH (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMS, CALVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DC1238F930A35750C0A963958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Punta Arenas Journal; A Hole in the Heavens (Chicken Little Below?)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMS, CALVIN</byline>
      <dateline>PUNTA ARENAS, Chile</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The people of this quiet port city, on the Strait of Magellan at the bottom of the world, do not venture outside without first rubbing sunblock over their exposed skin and donning dark glasses.</p>
        <p>For this practice, the 113,000 residents of Punta Arenas have one man to thank, or to despise: Bedrich Magas, an electrical engineering professor at the University of Magallanes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The people of this quiet port city, on the Strait of Magellan at the bottom of the world, do not venture outside without first rubbing sunblock over their exposed skin and donning dark glasses.</p>
        <p>For this practice, the 113,000 residents of Punta Arenas have one man to thank, or to despise: Bedrich Magas, an electrical engineering professor at the University of Magallanes.</p>
        <p>It was Mr. Magas who first alerted the people of his hometown to the dangers of a large hole in the ozone layer above Punta Arenas that exposes the area to what he says are unsafe levels of radiation.</p>
        <p>For the past eight years, Mr. Magas has appeared on television and radio and lectured to community groups, schoolchildren and agricultural associations, warning people to avoid long exposure to the sun.</p>
        <p>As he walks through Punta Arenas, whose fair-skinned residents and gabled houses are reminiscent of Maine or Nova Scotia, Mr. Magas is often approached by mothers who complain that their children's skin turns bright pink when they play outdoors and farmers who say their sheep are going blind from cataracts that they attribute to the sun's rays.</p>
        <p>Mr. Magas tells them to shield themselves from the sun during the peak hours of the day and to put pressure on the Government to finance research into the impact radiation may have on them.</p>
        <p>"It is much too early in the process to say for certain that the problems these people are experiencing are due to ozone depletion," Mr. Magas said. "But what we do know is that such high levels of radiation are dangerous and destroy. We are facing a worldwide emergency that is starting in Antarctica and spreading north and something must be done."</p>
        <p>Under an international treaty, production of the gases that cause the ozone depletion is being phased out, and the rate at which the gas is accumulating in the atmosphere has declined.</p>
        <p>Dora Trananez, a store clerk, said she first learned about the ozone hole from a television program featuring Mr. Magas.</p>
        <p>"God bless him, he's a very good man because he's the only one telling us how to protect ourselves," Mrs. Trananez said. "I've lived here for more than 30 years and I can feel the sun is much stronger than before."</p>
        <p>But not everyone thinks Mr. Magas is the voice of reason. To many in the scientific and business communities here, Mr. Magas is Chicken Little, irresponsibly frightening residents without any scientific evidence to back up his claims.</p>
        <p>The last provincial mayor here publicly called Mr. Magas an "ecoterrorist" and said he was destroying the lucrative ecological tourist industry that Punta Arenas desperately needs as its sheep industry declines. The city has become the major gateway to the Antarctic, producing jobs related to the cruise ships that call here and the flights that stop here.</p>
        <p>"Magas is a very smart man but he's running around like crazy scaring people out of their wits," said a prominent local travel agent, who spoke on condition that he not be identified. "There's no reason to be alarmed until there is concrete evidence."</p>
        <p>While there are no conclusive studies that show a link between an increase in ultraviolet radiation and strange happenings in Punta Arenas, tales of rabbits so blind that hunters grab them by their ears and rumors of blind salmon caught in Tierra del Fuego are often repeated.</p>
        <p>Doctors here said there has been no increase in the rate of skin cancer caused by solar radiation since the ozone hole was detected in 1986, but they note that such an increase would not be evident for decades.</p>
        <p>What is certain is that Punta Arenas, the world's southernmost city, is the only place on earth where large numbers of people live under a giant hole in the ozone layer. Ozone is a thin layer of gas that protects the earth from ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>Scientists believe the ozone hole, which is centered over Antarctica, was caused by the use of chlorofluorocarbons, commonly called CFC's, once used heavily as propellants for aerosols and now limited mostly to refrigerants and plastic foams. The CFC's destroy ozone, and have created a marked thinning in the layer over the South Pole. The hole expands and contracts, and typically from late August to early December it covers the tip of South America.</p>
        <p>Gino Casasa, director of Antarctic programs at the university, said that while he respects his colleague's intentions to raise concerns about ozone depletion, he thinks Mr. Magas is an alarmist.</p>
        <p>"Everybody agrees that ozone is a big concern, but the problem I see is that the population doesn't understand that there's no scientific data showing any impact on biological life here," Mr. Casasa said. "People are spreading myths about rabbits and buying expensive eyeglasses and creams without any basis."</p>
        <p>Mr. Magas counters: "Why shouldn't we speak as loudly and as accurately as possible about this problem that will have a tremendous impact on the Earth. I have been careful not to create a panic over the ozone hole, but people are hard-headed and you have to constantly hit them over the head again and again for them to fully realize the ramifications of the situation."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
