<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nations Pledge to Set Limits By 1997 on Warming Gases</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="753630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KINZER, STEPHEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDC1039F93BA35757C0A963958260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nations Pledge to Set Limits By 1997 on Warming Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KINZER, STEPHEN</byline>
      <dateline>BERLIN, April 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defying the pessimistic predictions of some environmentalists, delegates at a United Nations conference agreed today to open negotiations to fix new limits on heat-trapping gases that threaten to change the global climate.</p>
        <p>Delegates from industrial countries pledged that by 1997 they would conclude a protocol containing specific limits and goals for further reductions "within specified timeframes, such as 2005, 2010 and 2020." Negotiations are to begin this summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defying the pessimistic predictions of some environmentalists, delegates at a United Nations conference agreed today to open negotiations to fix new limits on heat-trapping gases that threaten to change the global climate.</p>
        <p>Delegates from industrial countries pledged that by 1997 they would conclude a protocol containing specific limits and goals for further reductions "within specified timeframes, such as 2005, 2010 and 2020." Negotiations are to begin this summer.</p>
        <p>Scientists say the earth's climate is slowly warming, and that carbon dioxide and other "greenhouse gases" emitted by factories, power plants, automobiles and airplanes could be the cause. They fear that such warming could have devastating effects, changing agricultural patterns and swamping islands and coastal regions as the ocean rises.</p>
        <p>At the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, industrialized countries agreed that by the turn of the century they would reduce their emissions to 1990 levels. Although some progress has been made toward those goals, it appears that several countries will fail to meet their commitments.</p>
        <p>The Rio treaty made no provision for reducing emissions in developing countries, where the desire for fast economic growth is leading to sharply increased emission of greenhouse gases. In a significant step in Berlin, both industrial and developing countries accepted the need to set limits on emissions. But although developing countries agreed to join in "an effective and appropriate international response" to global warming, they did not join industrial countries in promising to set emission limits by 1997.</p>
        <p>"I can't imagine an outcome better than what we got, within the limits of what was feasible," Timothy Wirth, the Undersecretary of State for global affairs, said. "Ahead of us we have a very, very hard negotiation to reach a legally binding agreement. No one should fool themselves that it's going to be easy, but I look forward to getting on with it."</p>
        <p>Michael Oppenheimer, a senior scientist for the Environmental Defense Fund who was in Berlin, said he was pleased by the outcome of the 11-day conference.</p>
        <p>"I come out of this optimistic," he said. "I see a process in place that could lead to overall reductions in emissions. Now I'm waiting to see the political willingness to back up this process. We've taken the horse to the trough. Will he drink? Come back in two years and I'll tell you."</p>
        <p>Some delegates, led by those representing small island nations, had sought to impose immediate new obligations on industrial countries, but they were rebuffed. Tuiloma Slade, a delegate from Samoa, said he regretted that the world has "not yet been able to find words as clear and true as the fear we islands feel for our own fate and for the fate of the climate system."</p>
        <p>Some environmental lobbyists said they, too, were disappointed by the results. " 'Tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow' isn't just a line from Macbeth, it's also the heart of the Clinton Administration's plan on global warming," asserted David Danzig of the Sierra Club. "The Clinton Administration has been continually low-balling the expectations for this conference, and when they come up with what amounts to a slight bit more than nothing, they portray it as a great victory."</p>
        <p>The intensity of lobbying here underscored the fact that industrial countries, developing countries and business interests were jockeying for competitive advantage in a highly complex process in which the economic stakes are at least as great as the environmental ones.</p>
        <p>John Schlaes, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition, which represents American oil companies and other large producers and consumers of fossil fuels, was among business lobbyists unhappy with the outcome. He said he feared that the coming negotiations would produce crippling restrictions on the American economy while allowing developing nations to continue virtually unchecked growth.</p>
        <p>"I'm going to express concern and disappointment," Mr. Schlaes said. "Some very profound concepts have been put on the table which I think change the relations between sovereign countries and the United Nations. This could have very significant implications. It could be a way of capping our economy, and that's something we want to look at most seriously."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
