<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nations to Consider Toughening Curbs on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950302T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="744589"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DC163DF932A15751C0A963958260" item-length="1099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nations to Consider Toughening Curbs on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER world leaders met in Rio de Janeiro nearly three years ago and signed a treaty to prevent human interference from causing dangerous changes in the earth's climate, the question quietly slipped down the international agenda. It was drained of urgency not least by an interruption of the global warming trend that had propelled the issue to the forefront in the 1980's and early 1990's.</p>
        <p>But the issue has simmered along as scientists advising the 120 nations that have ratified the treaty continue to warn of grave risks if humanity persists in pumping heat-trapping industrial waste gases like carbon dioxide into the atmosphere. And next month, as new signs emerge that the warming trend may have resumed, the parties to the treaty will meet for the first time, in Berlin, to confront the issue of whether stronger measures are necessary.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER world leaders met in Rio de Janeiro nearly three years ago and signed a treaty to prevent human interference from causing dangerous changes in the earth's climate, the question quietly slipped down the international agenda. It was drained of urgency not least by an interruption of the global warming trend that had propelled the issue to the forefront in the 1980's and early 1990's.</p>
        <p>But the issue has simmered along as scientists advising the 120 nations that have ratified the treaty continue to warn of grave risks if humanity persists in pumping heat-trapping industrial waste gases like carbon dioxide into the atmosphere. And next month, as new signs emerge that the warming trend may have resumed, the parties to the treaty will meet for the first time, in Berlin, to confront the issue of whether stronger measures are necessary.</p>
        <p>Global temperatures have not climbed back to the record level of 1990, and the issue has not regained the immediacy it had. Partly as a result, there is no unanimity on whether stronger steps are necessary. This was made clear over the last two weeks as the international committee that negotiated the climate treaty, meeting here in its final session, attempted to frame the questions to be grappled with in Berlin.</p>
        <p>The questions are not trivial, since any significant reduction in carbon dioxide emissions, which have been relentlessly increasing as industrial societies burn ever-larger quantities of fossil fuels like coal and oil, would have a large economic impact. The world economy runs on fossil fuels, and powerful interests oppose any attempt to reduce their use.</p>
        <p>As the first step toward a broad objective of stabilizing atmospheric concentrations of heat-trapping gases short of dangerous levels in time to prevent disruption of world agriculture and natural ecosystems, the treaty calls on industrialized countries to aim at capping emissions of the gases at 1990 levels by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>That is only a first step because there is so much excess carbon dioxide in the atmosphere that only a reduction in emissions will stabilize the overall concentration at any level up to double today's, according to a panel of scientists advising the treaty parties. In fact, say the scientists, capping emissions at 1990 levels would not lead to overall stabilization of concentrations for two centuries.</p>
        <p>A doubling of today's concentrations, say the scientists, would cause the average global temperature to rise by 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit some time in the latter part of the next century, disrupting the global climate and making sea levels rise.</p>
        <p>The leading "hawks" among treaty signatories are the small island countries, which fear that rising seas will bring them disaster and possible obliteration. At the United Nations meeting, Trinidad and Tobago proposed an addition to the treaty that would require industrialized countries to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide to 20 percent below 1990 levels by the year 2005. The proposal is to be transmitted to the treaty parties when they meet in Berlin, along with a statement reaffirming that measures already taken amount to only a first step.</p>
        <p>The European Union, while stopping short of supporting the island states' proposal, said here that it considers the present requirements to be inadequate and called for a protocol to strengthen the treaty.</p>
        <p>The parties in Berlin "most probably" will decide to start negotiations on such a protocol, said Raul Estrada-Oyuela of Argentina, the chairman of the now-defunct negotiating committee.</p>
        <p>The United States, which does not support the Trinidad and Tobago proposal, nevertheless said that the "first and overriding objective" of the Berlin meeting should be to establish a "new aim," and that this new aim should be negotiated no later than 1997. The United States also believes that the new aim should govern actions as far ahead as the year 2020, since some measures to reduce greenhouse gases that might be effective in the long term might not be so in the short term and therefore might not be adopted.</p>
        <p>Both the Europeans and the United States have domestic political reasons for caution. In the meeting here, as required by the treaty, 15 industrialized countries for the first time offered for scrutiny their plans for reducing emissions and their projected emissions for the year 2000. The plans rely mostly on improved energy efficiency, and for 9 of the 15 countries, including the United States, further measures will be necessary if the aim of reducing emissions to 1990 levels is to be met.</p>
        <p>Reductions substantially below 1990 levels would require much more difficult actions. The United States' actions so far are based on voluntary energy-efficiency measures, and the conservative takeover of Congress makes it more unlikely than ever that stronger measures like a tax on carbon emissions will be enacted in the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>Last week environmentalists said a failure of leadership by the Europeans and Americans had allowed hard-line opponents of stronger measures to dominate discussion. Over the last two weeks, China -- which is counting on its large coal reserves to fuel its economy -- emerged as perhaps the most formidable opponent of stronger action, making common cause with the oil-producing countries and the coal, oil, metals and automobile industries in the industrialized nations.</p>
        <p>China, like other developing countries, is not yet bound by any precise targets or timetables. But the assumption is that in time it will be. In an apparent effort to help postpone that day, China took the lead in arguing that no further commitments to reduce emissions should be undertaken until the industrialized countries meet the existing targets. China also questioned the conclusions of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the group of scientists advising the treaty parties.</p>
        <p>Bert Bolin, the Swedish chairman of the panel, acknowledged that many uncertainties plague efforts to determine how serious the risk of climate change is. The panel is now in the midst of a full reassessment of the question and is to report the results later this year.</p>
        <p>Chances are that large uncertainties will remain. In that event, divisions among and within countries are almost sure to persist as indifferent public opinion gives governments no reason to galvanize for stronger action. But some diplomats believe that if global temperatures set new records for warmth between now and 2000, as some climatologists predict, or if climatic disruption becomes more evident, or both, all bets will be off.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 2, 1995, Thursday</p>
        <p>A table in Science Times on Feb. 21 with an article about global warming, showing developed nations' 1990 levels of carbon dioxide emissions and projections for the year 2000, omitted three final zeros from the figures, thus understating them. The levels are in millions of tons. The figure for Australia's estimate of emissions for the year 2000, also understated, included an additional error. It should have read 370,491,000 tons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 2, 1995, Thursday</p>
        <p>A table in Science Times on Feb. 21 with an article about global warming, showing developed nations' 1990 levels of carbon dioxide emissions and projections for the year 2000, omitted three final zeros from the figures, thus understating them. The levels are in millions of tons. The figure for Australia's estimate of emissions for the year 2000, also understated, included an additional error. It should have read 370,491,000 tons.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
