<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="763892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTERTAINMENT AND AMUSEMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DC113AF932A15756C0A963958260" item-length="3959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSIC BARON ARTS CENTER Vasily Yankovich, vocalist, performs in a celebration of the traditional sounds of Eastern Europe and the Balkans. Friday at 8 P.M. Free. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (908) 745-4489. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE A chamber-music concert performed by six teen-agers, featuring the works of Chopin, Mozart and Kreisler. Today at 2:30 P.M. $4 suggested donation. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSIC BARON ARTS CENTER Vasily Yankovich, vocalist, performs in a celebration of the traditional sounds of Eastern Europe and the Balkans. Friday at 8 P.M. Free. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (908) 745-4489. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE A chamber-music concert performed by six teen-agers, featuring the works of Chopin, Mozart and Kreisler. Today at 2:30 P.M. $4 suggested donation. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248.</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY MUSIC FESTIVAL The Shirim Klezmer Orchestra, today at 8:30 P.M., and Hesperus, Wednesday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12; $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. COUNT BASIE THEATER The Monmouth Symphony Orchestra will perform a concert featuring Francis Perry, guitarist. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $12; $10 for the elderly; students free. Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (908) 758-1760. EAST BROWN THEATER In "Music of the Seasons," the Carnegie Chamber Players explore the sounds of nature and the way they have inspired composers through the ages. Today at 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $5. Eric Brown Theater, J.C.C. on the Palisades, 411 East Clinton Avenue. Tenafly. (201) 569-7900. FIVE CORNERS LIBRARY Milena Grodsky, violinist. Today at 2:30 P.M. Free. Newark and Summit Avenues, Summit. (201) 547-4543. HOLIDAY INN The Moonlighters, an 18-piece band, play music from the 30's and 40's. Admission: $15; $12 for the elderly. 50 Kenney Place, Saddle Brook. (201) 445-7506. NEW JERSEY SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA Masterworks Series with Zdenek Macal, conducter, and Tzimon Barton, pianist, featuring Larsen's "Overture: Parachute Dancing" and Beethoven's Fifth Symphony. Today at 3 P.M. at Symphony Hall in Newark. Tickets: $45, $35, $30, $25 and $15. (201) 624-8203. RIDGEWOOD COMMUNITY HYMN FESTIVAL More than 100 singers from 15 churches in the area will sing anthems and hymns chosen to express each aspect of prayer: praise, confessions, petition, intercession and thanksgiving. Today, 8 P.M. $5 suggestion donation. Our Lady of Mt. Carmel Church, 1 Passaic Street, Ridgewood. (201) 652-2868. RIVER VALE FREE PUBLIC LIBRARY Sharon Levin, on flute, and Susan Dadian, on guitar, perform the third and final spring concert. Today, 3 P.M. Free. 412 Rivervale Road, River Vale. (201) 391-2323. TEMPLE EMANUEL OF NORTH JERSEY The Choral Society's 64th annual concert, with excepts from the works of Brahms, Schubert and Gershwin. Today at 3:30 P.M. Tickets; $10; $7 for students and the elderly. Broadway and East 33d Street, Paterson. (201) 684-5565. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Sunday Series" continues with David Massengill, singer and storyteller. Today at 7 P.M. Tickets: $8. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. THEATER BARN THEATER "Follies," a musical by Stephen Sondheim and James Goldman. Today at 3 P.M.; Friday and Saturday, 8 P.M.; next Sunday, 3 P.M.; and June 2 and 3, 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Skyline Drive, Montville. (201) 334-9320. CENTENARY LITTLE THEATER The Centenary Young Performers Workshop will present two musicals -- "Company," today at 7 P.M., and "Tom Sawyer," today at 4 P.M. Tickets: $7, or $5 for students and the elderly. Campus of Centenary College, Hackettstown. (908) 852-1400, ext. 203. CHATHAM COMMUNITY PLAYERS "Nunsense," today at 3 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 3 and 8 P.M. Tickets: $14, or $10 for students. The Playhouse. 23 North Passaic Avenue, Chatham. (201) 635-7363. CROSSROADS THEATER COMPANY "Two Hah Hahs and a Homeboy," with Ruby Dee, Ossie Davis and their son, Guy Davis. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $20, $25. "Genesis 1995: A Celebration of New Voices in African-American Theater," a series of performances: Rita Dover's classically inspired verse play "The Darker Face of the Earth," Wednesday at 8 P.M.; "An Evening of One Acts," written and performed by Ozzie Jones and Josslyn Luckett, Thursday at 8 P.M.; "The Screened-In Porch" by Marian X, Friday at 8 P.M. "Crossroads Celebrates the Civic League of Greater New Brunswick" with the Martin Luther King Players, Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. 7 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 249-5560. DOUGLAS COLLEGE STUDENT CENTER Filipino folk tales will be interpreted through dance and narration. Today, 2 P.M. Free. George Street and Nichol Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 745-4489. ELIZABETH PLAYHOUSE "Kinfolks," by Karon Semones, based on the novel by Gurney Norman. Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $4. 1100 East Jersey Street, Elizabeth. (908) 355-0077. GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE "Of Mice and Men," Tuesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through June 4. Tickets: $30, $26 and $22. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 246-7717. GUGGENHEIM THEATER The Two River Theater Company presents George Bernard Shaw's "Misalliance." Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $15 on Wednesday and Thursday, $22 on Friday and Saturday, and $18 on Sunday. Monmouth University, Cedar Avenue, West Long Branch. (908) 291-4114. HENDERSON THEATER The Premier Theater Company presents "Thank You and Good Night." Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20. 850 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 758-1118. LITTLE FIREHOUSE THEATER The Bergen County Players present "A Few Good Men." Today at 1 and 5 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for matinees. 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200. McCARTER THEATER Brian Friel's "Wonderful Tennessee," today at 2 and 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $26 to $30. "Rhyme and Punishment." Friday and Saturday, 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $17 to $22. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The National Stage Company presents Sam Shepard's "Fool for Love" and Strindberg's "Miss Julie." Today at 3 P.M., Thursday through Saturday at 8 P.M., and next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $18, or $14 for students and the elderly. Matinees are $15 and $12. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 489-0322. MILL HILL PLAYHOUSE The Passage Theater Company presents "Three More Gone," by Bruce Jacoby. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $25, $20 and $15. Front and Montgomery Streets, Trenton. (609) 392-0766. MODERN JEWISH REPERTORY THEATER "Two" by Ron Elisha. Wednesday, 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Saturday, 8 P.M., Sunday at 7 P.M. and 2 P.M. Through June 11. Tickets: $25. Blooming Grove Theater, 544 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 325-8154. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL "Love's Labour's Lost," Tuesday through Saturday, 8 P.M., Sunday, 7 P.M. Through June 10. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater. Drew University. 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-3278. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Lerner and Loewe's "Brigadoon." Wednesday through Sunday at 8 P.M.; matinees Thursday at 2 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. Tickets: $29 to $44. Through May 28. (201) 376-4343. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART FORMS "Paintings, Works on Paper and Sculpture," with works by Richard Stout, John Kochansky, Boris Zherdin and Paul Hirsch. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M., Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Sunday 1 to 4 P.M. Through May 31. 16 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (908) 530-4330. ART WORKS Paintings of Dante's "Inferno," by Eric Fowler. Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays through June 24. Opening reception today, 3 P.M. 19 Everrett Alley, Trenton. (609) 394-9436. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE Photographs by local teen-agers. Ends today. "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. Through Aug. 10. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Wilderness of Waves," featuring the oils and watercolors of John Powers. Through next Sunday. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Exposure," an exhibition of photgraphs by Carol Seitz. Through June 2. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. Opening reception today, 3 to 6 P.M. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CRAFTSMAN FARM "Time of Transition: Textiles of the Arts and Crafts Movement" displays a variety of textiles, including table scarves, pillow covers, pocketbooks, bedspreads and clothing. Through June 4. Thursday, noon to 3, Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $4; $3 for students and the elderly. Route 10 and Manor Lane, about 3 miles west of Route 287, Parsippany. (201) 540-1165. EXTENSION GALLERY Cast metal sculptures will be on display in "Concavo -- Concave" through June 1. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. John Atelier Building, 60 Ward Avenue Extension. Mercerville. (609) 890-7777 GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Omaha -- An Artist's Journey: Memories of D-Day," with drawings and collages by Ugo Giannini. Through June 5. Tuesday through Thursday, 6 P.M. to 8 P.M.; Friday, 10 A.M. to noon; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Through June 25. Opening reception today, 3 to 5 P.M. Wedesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. KERYGMA GALLERY "A Sense of Place," works by Townsend Howe, a realist painter with an impressionistic style. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Reception today, 2 to 5 P.M. 38 Oak Street, Ridgewood. (201) 444-5510. MIDDLESEX COUNTY COLLEGE The Fifth Annual Alumni Art Exhibit. Through May 31. Daily, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. The College Center Gallery. 155 Mill Road, Edison. (908) 906-2566. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the paper-making town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through June 11. Admission: $3. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through June 25. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission, $4; the elderly and students with ID, $3. 3 South Mountain Avenue. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found," an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimensional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through June. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through June. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY AUDUBON SOCIETY Photographs of New Jersey wildlife by John Collins will be displayed and available for sale. Proceeds will benefit New Jersey Audubon's Scherman-Hoffman Sanctuaries. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Through May. Hardscrabble Road, Bernardsville. (908) 766-5787. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through June 11. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibit celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. 205 West State Street, Trenton. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M. and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through June 18. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. RIVERRUN GALLERY "Face -- Feelings," 40 works in oil, watercolor and mixed media by Edward Adams. Through June 5. Noon to 5 P.M. daily. Closed on Tuesdays. 287 South Main Street. Lambertville. (906) 397-3349. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY An exhibition of Ukrainian folk art, showing samples of pysanky (Ukrainian Easter eggs), ceramics, wood carvings, clothing and embroidery. Through nest Sunday. 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday through Friday. Walsh Library Gallery, South Orange. (201) 761-9476.  SHOESTRING GALLERY "Hung Up," paintings and sculptures by Bill Barrell. Through June 17. Saturdays, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 111 1st Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STEAMROLLER GALLERY Paintings by Sara Pasti. Through June 10. Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 52 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-7279. TRENTON CITY MUSEUM The Trenton Artists Workshop Association presents the mixed-media work of Katharine Bruce. Through next Sunday. "When Trenton Baseball Roared Like Thunder" and "Extra Innings." Through next Sunday. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. (609) 989-3632. UNTITLED (#130), LTD Paintings, sculpture and photography by Joanna Thompson, Jennifer Freid and Frank Fernicola. Friday, 1 to 9 P.M., Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M. and Sunday noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Shine On," color photographs of last year's solar eclipse. Through May 30. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. Free. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WYCKOFF GALLERY "Spring Rhapsody," featuring traditional and abstract works in various media. Through June 12. Tuesday through Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM More than 100 prints document the development of "Printmaking in America" from 1960 to 1990. Drawn from private collections and museums around the country, the exhibition includes works by Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Roger Brown and others. Through June 18. Free. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. SPOKEN WORD BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE H. Maenami will lead a workship on the basics of Ikebana, the Japanese art of arranging cut flowers in decorative designs. Reservations are recommended. Fee: $7. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. CARRIAGE HOUSE AT SKYLANDS Barbara Ferrante, an art history teacher, will discuss American landscape painting of the 19th and 20th centuries. Today, 3 P.M. Free. Morris Road in Ridgewood State Park, Ridgewood. ((201) 962-7527. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Norman David will talk about his grandfather, Norman H. David, a prominent American diplomat in the period between the World Wars. Tuesday, 8 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. ETHICAL CULTURE SOCIETY OF ESSEX COUNTY Charles Strozier, a professor at the Institute for the Study of Violence at John Jay College of Criminal Justice in New York City, will discuss "Apocalypse, Violence and America." Today, 11 A.M. Free. 516 Prospect Street, Maplewood. (201) 763-1905. JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Presenting Poetry and Prose Series," with Alicia Suskin Ostriker, poet. Wednesday, 8 P.M. Free. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. MONMOUTH COUNTY HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION Garry Wheeler Stone, of the New Jersey Division of Parks and Forestry, and Daniel Sivilich, of the Friends of Monmouth Battlefield, will discuss the restoration of the battlefield. Monday, 6:30 P.M. Admission: $10. 70 Court Street, Freehold. (908) 462-1466. RIVER VALE FREE PUBLIC LIBRARY Sylvia Gaddi, supervisor of reference and information services at the Paramus Public Library, will discuss "Using Investment Resources." Tuesday, 8 P.M. Free. 412 Rivervale Road, River Vale. (201) 391-2323. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF BERGEN COUNTY Dr. Charles Schaefer, a child psychologist, will discuss "Discipline and Your Preschooler," offering advice on preventing disciplinary problems in young children. Tuesday, 8 P.M. Tickets: $12. 605 Pascack Road, Washington Township. (201) 666-6610. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM "The Original Print: Then and Now," a talk on authenticity in print production. Free. Today, 3 P.M. "Printmaking in America," a gallery talk, Tuesday, 12:15 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. FOR CHILDREN CHATHAM COMMUNITY BAND Third annual interactive children's concert, with a repertory of concert pieces, marches, novelty numbers and solo instrumentalists. At the end of the concert, audience members will be allowed to try out instruments with band members. Today, 3:30 P.M. Free. Chatham High School, 223 Lafayette Avenue, Chatham Township. (201) 635-5101. GROWING STAGE THEATER "Cinderella." Today, 4 P.M.. Tickets: $10; $8 for children. Williamson Building, Main Street, Chester. (908) 879-4946. MEADOW THEATER "The Meadow Kids Rock 'n' Roll." Today at 1 P.M. Tickets: $5. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. MERCER COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE Kaleidoscope Theater presents "Goldilocks and the Three Bears." Saturday, 2 and 4 P.M. Tickets: $7. West Windsor Campus, 1200 Old Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 584-9444. MIDDLESEX COUNTY COLLEGE The Felt Group and the Middlesex County College Backstage Players present "Peter Pan." Today, 2 P.M. Tickets: $5. Performing Arts Center, 155 MilL Road, Edison. (908) 906-2566. MUSEUM OF EARLY TRADE AND CRAFTS Reverse Painting Workshop, demonstrating the art of painting images backward on glass. Workshop painting will be done on clear mylar so there will be no sharp edges. Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $2; $1 for children. Materials fee: $2. Main Street and Green Village Road, Madison. (201) 377-2982. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M., and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS Sand Bottles and Sand Painting Workshop for children ages 4 to 8. Children will create colorful designs in bottles and on flat surfaces in Native American style. Tuesday, 3:45 to 5:15 P.M. $20, with materials fee included. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC. BOOK SALE Annual Friends of the Englewood Public Library book sale. Today, noon to 6 P.M. Renaissance Office Center, 15 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through June 17. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. CAT SHOW The Tristate Cat Fanciers of New Jersey present their 8th annual judging ring championship show. Saturday and next Sunday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $5; $4 for the elderly. Westfield National Guard Armory. 500 Rahway Avenue, Westfield. (201) 379-2816. CRAFT FAIR The second annual Sugarloaf Spring Somerset Crafts Festival features more than 300 artists and craft designers who will discuss and sell their works. Today, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Admission: $6. Garden State Exhibit Center, 50 Atrium Drive in Somerset. (908) 469-4000. FLAT ROCK BROOK NATURE CENTER A "Nature Day" celebration, with canoe rides on the pond, pony rides in the woods, guided nature walks on the trails and plenty of animals. Children can create nature crafts, have their faces painted and create origami animals. They can also meet Mr. Lizard and his Creepy Crawly Creatures and the Butterfly Lady, Marion Hill. Admission: $2; $1 for children and the elderly. 443 Van Nostrand Avenue, Englewood. (201) 567-1265. INDIAN LORE "Seeds of Peace, a Native American Indian Powwow," with dancers, singers, storytellers, music and historical re-enactments. Today, noon to 7 P.M. Tickets: $6; $4 for children. Matarazzo Farms, 10 Doe Hollow Lane, Route 519, Belvidere. (908) 475-3872. MOUNT HOPE HISTORICAL CONSERVANCY The Morris County Park Commission sponsors a guided walking tour of the historic Richard Mine Tract, the remains of an iron mining operation that began in the 1700's. Saturday and next Sunday, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. Free. Pre-registration is required. (201) 326-7644. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL "Faust," June 2 and 3, All shows at 7 P.M. Tickets: $4. Rutgers University, College Avenue campus, George Street and Seminary Place, New Brunswick. (908) 932-8482. RANKOKUS INDIAN RESERVATION The Powhattan Renape Nation presents its Annual Juried American Indian Arts Festival, with more than 100 Native American artists and entertainers representing 50 tribes throughout the Americas. Saturday and next Sunday and Monday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Tickets: $7; $3 for the elderly. Rancocas Road, Westhampton Township, Burlington County. (609) 261-4747. SINGLES DANCE PARTY "Sunday Night Fever," a 50's dance party sponsored by Cosmopolitan singles, a group for Jewish professionals ages 3 to 55. Today, 8 P.M. Admission: $8. Ramada Hotel, 265 Route 3 East, Clifton. (201) 736-3200 ext. 381.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
