<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>55 or Faster?</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="753804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="UP FRONT: CHATTER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPEED LIMITS AND SPEEDING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speed Limits and Speeding</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D71139F93AA35757C0A963958260" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>55 or Faster?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHOULD the speed limit on New Jersey highways be raised to 65 miles per hour, or is the current limit, 55, right? Burning Fossil Fuel</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHOULD the speed limit on New Jersey highways be raised to 65 miles per hour, or is the current limit, 55, right? Burning Fossil Fuel</p>
        <p>The best reason I can think of to keep the limit where it is? Pollution.  The faster we go, the more non-replaceable fossil fuel we burn, and the sooner we super-heat the planet, deplete the ozone layer and ruin the air, water, and land. We cannot see these effects, so we don't deal with them very well as a society. So keep it at 55; we'll live longer. RALPH COPLEMAN Lawrenceville Raise Gasoline Tax</p>
        <p>Ralph: Rather than keep the speed limit unrealistically low, how about taxing gasoline so that it's priced commensurate with its toll on the environment? In real terms, gasoline is cheaper now than it was when I was a kid (and gas was 25 cents a gallon). If people thought twice about buying a Ford Explorer that gets 10 or 15 miles per gallon because of what fuel cost, maybe we'd have some impact on pollution.</p>
        <p>JOSH DUBNICK Hopatcong Take Traffic Into Account</p>
        <p>Let's be practical but fair. It is often difficult to do 45, let alone 55, on the Turnpike north of Newark in rush hour. South of the Raritan Plaza on the Parkway, the only vehicles driving 55 and under are the troopers. And don't forget the casino buses setting records. Raise the limit where we need it and keep it at 55 where traffic warrants. JEFFREY STRASHUN Hillside How About a Grace Limit?</p>
        <p>No, we should not raise the speed limit. We should have a grace limit of 10 m.p.h. If you go over 55 you are speeding, but if you go over 65 you get a ticket and whatever goes with it. If you make it 65, people go 75. VERNON W. CAMPBELL Jersey City Don't Raise the Threshold</p>
        <p>My business demands that I spend a lot of time on the road. On the major highways (the Parkway, Routes 80, 280, 78, etc.), I'll set my cruise control at 69 m.p.h. I have gone through perhaps 200 radar traps without being stopped. The unwritten rule seems to be, "Don't stop them for speeding under 70 m.p.h." Raise the posted limit and you most likely raise the ticket threshold. Why bother? Let's face it. The speed limit on our major highways is already 69 m.p.h.  CHARLES BALETTI Essex Fells A Fact of Life</p>
        <p>The 55 m.p.h. speed limit demonstrates that government bureaucrats and insurance company executives fail to understand a basic principle of transportation, proven through the ages: Faster is better.</p>
        <p>TOM SWIFT Holmdel How to Talk Back</p>
        <p>Each week, this column summarizes responses to one question and poses another. Readers can post in the @times area of America Online; comments will also be accepted by E-mail to jersey@nytimes.com, by fax to (212) 556-7219, or by mail to Chatter, New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Published messages become the property of The Times; they may be edited and may be republished in any medium. For information about America Online, call 1-(800) 548-5201. Next week's topic: What is your long-range view for New Jersey? Do you think that 10 or 15 years from now, the state will be a better, worse, or about the same?  UP FRONT: CHATTER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
