<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health; Ignoring an easy way to cut risks of crib death.</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="748867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIB DEATH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sudden Infant Death Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDC1F3CF936A25750C0A963958260" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health; Ignoring an easy way to cut risks of crib death.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a letter published recently in The New York Times, a distressed grandmother complained that she had been banished from baby-sitting for her 6-week-old grandson after the parents caught her putting the baby to sleep on his stomach.</p>
        <p>"Don't you know about SIDS?" the equally distressed father hissed, referring to the growing evidence that babies who sleep face down are at increased risk of sudden infant death syndrome.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a letter published recently in The New York Times, a distressed grandmother complained that she had been banished from baby-sitting for her 6-week-old grandson after the parents caught her putting the baby to sleep on his stomach.</p>
        <p>"Don't you know about SIDS?" the equally distressed father hissed, referring to the growing evidence that babies who sleep face down are at increased risk of sudden infant death syndrome.</p>
        <p>She had, and she knew of the current advice to avoid the prone position for all but a relative handful of babies. But she replied that she could not get the baby to settle down on his back and surely both baby and baby-sitter needed some rest.</p>
        <p>She is not alone. Despite strong warnings, millions of American infants are being put to sleep in positions or on soft bedding now considered potentially hazardous. As of last June, 45 percent of babies in the United States were still sleeping on their bellies. Many parents and care givers have not heard the advice, others choose for various reasons to ignore it and still others are too poor to replace equipment now considered unsafe for their infants.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in several countries where a vast majority of babies are now put to sleep on their backs or sides instead of their bellies, the rate of SIDS, or crib death as it was long called, has dropped by 50 percent or more.</p>
        <p>The SIDS rate in this country, about 1 in 800 live births, is much lower than in these other countries, and experts here do not expect as large a drop in unexplained infant deaths if most American babies are switched from the prone position. But they insist that this is one of the simplest measures families and care givers can adopt to reduce crib deaths, which each year claim the lives of about 6,000 infants in this country. Why Babies Die</p>
        <p>Many factors have been associated with an increased chance that a seemingly healthy baby might die without any apparent cause. Among them are exposure to tobacco smoke both before and after birth, lack of prenatal care, premature birth, a recent infection and bottle feeding. The presence of any such factors adds to the risk that a baby sleeping on its stomach will succumb to the syndrome.</p>
        <p>Concern about sleeping position, followed by concern about the surfaces babies sleep on, has been growing over the last two decades, but not until 1992 did the American Academy of Pediatrics advise parents to avoid putting babies to sleep on their stomachs. At the time, 75 percent of newborns here were sleeping face down. Last June, with evidence mounting that prone sleeping was risky, a coalition of Federal and private child health organizations began a national education campaign, "Back to Sleep," to persuade parents to put healthy babies to sleep on their backs or sides.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bradley T. Thach, neonatologist at Washington University in St. Louis, said, "Throughout history, most babies throughout the world have been placed on their backs, as was the case in the United States up until the 1930's." Then, he said, American experts, including Dr. Benjamin Spock, promoted prone sleeping, believing it would reduce the risk of babies' choking to death or developing aspiration pneumonia if they vomited while asleep.</p>
        <p>But there is no evidence for this, Dr. Thach said, and in Australia and England, where babies have now been switched to sleeping on their backs, there has been no increase in any cause of infant death, only a sharp decrease in crib death.</p>
        <p>There is even a suggestion that babies who sleep on their backs are healthier than belly sleepers. Dr. Marian Willinger, a leading researcher in the field at the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development in Bethesda, Md., noted that in the Australian state of Tasmania, where sleep position has been intensely studied since 1988, the switch away from belly sleeping has been associated with a decline in visits to child health clinics, colds and vomiting after feeding.</p>
        <p>Complicating the issue of sleep position, however, is the type of material on which the baby sleeps. The Consumer Products Safety Commission recently warned against putting babies to sleep on soft bedding, which the commission's studies indicated could be responsible for as many as 1,800 infant deaths a year. Although bereaved parents have long been reassured that their babies who died of SIDS did not suffocate, in fact many apparently do when sleeping face down.</p>
        <p>Dr. James Kemp, a pediatric pulmonologist at Washington University, has studied how various kinds of bedding materials might smother healthy infants. He has shown that soft bedding, like sheepskins, natural-fiber mattresses and quilts, placed under a baby sleeping on its belly can trap exhaled air and cause the baby to rebreathe it, resulting in a gradual rise in carbon dioxide in the baby's blood.</p>
        <p>For various reasons, including defects in the arousal mechanism or damage to the part of the brain that detects rises in carbon dioxide, some babies may fail to wake up in time to take lifesaving breaths that are richer in oxygen, Dr. Willinger explained.</p>
        <p>Very young infants lying face down on a soft surface may be unable to raise or turn their heads enough to breathe fresh air. Dr. Kemp said that 20 percent to 50 percent of SIDS babies die with their noses and mouths sunk into soft bedding. And a new study of 200 SIDS infants in California revealed that while 66 percent usually slept on their stomachs, 80 percent of the victims were found lying face down. What Is Safe?</p>
        <p>Although the jury is still out on the role that prone sleeping may play in SIDS deaths here, there appears to be little reason not to abandon it for most babies. But there are important exceptions. The pediatrics academy says that premature infants with respiratory tract disease, those with reflux of food between the stomach and esophagus and infants with certain malformations of the upper airway should sleep on their stomachs.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kemp said the safest sleeping surface for infants was a firm mattress covered by a tight-fitting sheet. A receiving blanket or quilt could be placed on top of the baby, but nothing should be placed underneath, he advised, nor should there be pillows or soft toys in the baby's bed.</p>
        <p>When a baby is put to sleep away from home, an infant seat or portable crib is preferable to a quilt or rug. Also, babies should not sleep in bed with an adult or older child. Some studies have found a large increase in the risk of the syndrome among babies who sleep in their parents' bed, especially if one or both parents smoke.</p>
        <p>The peak age for SIDS is from 2 to 4 months. After about five months, it may make no difference how babies are put to sleep, since many then learn to flip over on their own, Dr. Willinger observed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
