<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In California, a Move to Give Consumers a Choice on Utilities</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="817430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC UTILITIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7D81439F932A15751C1A963958260" item-length="928" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In California, a Move to Give Consumers a Choice on Utilities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>California consumers would be the first in the nation to be able to choose which electric utility to patronize as a result of a decision yesterday by the California Public Utilities Commission.</p>
        <p>But the commission's decision, which was adopted in a 3-to-2 vote, calls for  setting up an elaborate system to give the state's own utilities time to adjust  to outside competition and to recover the huge costs they would incur in the process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>California consumers would be the first in the nation to be able to choose which electric utility to patronize as a result of a decision yesterday by the California Public Utilities Commission.</p>
        <p>But the commission's decision, which was adopted in a 3-to-2 vote, calls for  setting up an elaborate system to give the state's own utilities time to adjust  to outside competition and to recover the huge costs they would incur in the process.</p>
        <p>Under the decision, the state would set up an independent power pool by 1998 that would buy power from the lowest-cost producers and then resell it to the state's utilities. The goal is to bring down the cost of power in the state.</p>
        <p>California has some of the highest rates in the country, averaging 10.28 cents a kilowatt-hour -- about 50 percent higher than the national average.</p>
        <p>Out-of-state, low-cost utilities and independent power producers could compete with the California utilities to sell power to the pool, which would be  run by an independent operator.</p>
        <p>The in-state utilities would buy the power and pass it on to their customers  at no added cost. They would also turn over the control of their transmission systems to the independent operator.</p>
        <p>The radical revamping of the industry may not lead to lower rates for many customers in the short term, but the hope is that rates will fall as the system  evolves.</p>
        <p>One reason that major rate reductions are not expected in the early phases is that customers will have to pay charges to offset some of the huge costs that will be incurred by the state's utilities as they become competitive.</p>
        <p>Daniel Fessler, the commission's president, said in San Francisco that the state's utilities would have to phase out less efficient plants, for example.</p>
        <p>Another major cost to be recovered involves the long-term contracts under which utilities must buy power from independent power producers at prices much higher than those on the wholesale market.</p>
        <p>The proposal adopts many of the key elements from a compromise reached in the fall by various groups, including the Southern California Edison Company, one of the state's largest utilities; some major consumer and industry groups; a major  environmental group, and the independent power producers.</p>
        <p>Since the moves would have such wide impact, the commission said it would seek to build consensus with the state Legislature, the Governor, the utilities  and consumers, all of whom could influence the outcome. The Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, which oversees the industry, will also play a role in the changes.</p>
        <p>The commission's decision is expected to speed efforts in other states, including New York, to break down the monopolies that utilities have long enjoyed.</p>
        <p>The step, however, is also filled with uncertainties. Many in the industry and those who follow it, contend that larger industrial customers may get the benefits of lower rates before smaller residential and commercial users see their rates go down substantially.</p>
        <p>"There is a question of whether rates will come down for all classes of customers," said Michael Hope, a partner in Andersen Consulting, who follows the industry. "There is real pressure for rates to come down faster for industrial customers."</p>
        <p>The decision is also a retreat from the commission's 1994 plan to open its utilities to direct competition since it sets up a buffer between the state's utilities and outsiders by using the pool concept.</p>
        <p>After several years of wrangling with the Legislature, consumer groups, the three major utilities and the independent power producers, the commission is now proposing to create a new layer of regulation in its effort to deregulate the industry.</p>
        <p>Under the commission's proposal an independent system operator would take control of the transmission system of the state's major utilities, including the Pacific Gas and Electric Company, the Southern California Edison unit of SCEcorp and the San Diego Gas and Electric Company.</p>
        <p>The operator would find the most efficient mix of plants to supply electricity. Various power producers would be able to bid to sell their power to the pool.</p>
        <p>How all these forces will play out and how this will change how consumers are served and their costs are still largely unknown.</p>
        <p>Many major industrial customers have already been able to win rate cuts from  local utilities by threatening to move plants or to help local communities form  municipal systems.</p>
        <p>The proposal also carries risks for shareholders, who may see their stocks battered as utilities find that some of their plants, particularly expensive nuclear plants, are no longer competitive. The utilities that find it hard to compete may be forced to cut their dividends, a major source of income for many  retired people.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups are also concerned that as utilities are forced to focus on becoming low-cost producers they will no longer support efforts to develop renewable energy and programs aimed at cutting down the use of electricity.</p>
        <p>Despite such concerns, however, there is a wide agreement that the utility industry is already undergoing rapid change and that state regulators and governments will have little choice but to prepare for greater competition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
