<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sampras Starts Strong and Sticks to Basics</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="737394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUSTRALIAN OPEN (TENNIS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINN, ROBIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAMPRAS, PETE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COURIER, JIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHANG, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DC1539F934A25752C0A963958260" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sampras Starts Strong and Sticks to Basics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINN, ROBIN</byline>
      <dateline>MELBOURNE, Australia, Jan. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Preferring comfort to novelty, Pete Sampras, the Australian Open's defending champion, wore old sneakers and used an old racquet today to produce a familiar result: a first-round victory without a hitch.</p>
        <p>"Hopefully things will work out for me here," Sampras said after his 73- minute demolition of Gianluca Pozzi of Italy by 6-3, 6-2, 6-0.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Preferring comfort to novelty, Pete Sampras, the Australian Open's defending champion, wore old sneakers and used an old racquet today to produce a familiar result: a first-round victory without a hitch.</p>
        <p>"Hopefully things will work out for me here," Sampras said after his 73- minute demolition of Gianluca Pozzi of Italy by 6-3, 6-2, 6-0.</p>
        <p>What constitutes things "working out" here for Sampras, who has been No. 1 for the last 90 weeks, is nothing less than a two-week reaffirmation of his dominance on the Grand Slam frontier.</p>
        <p>"I'm here to defend my title; anything less is simply not good enough," said the 24-year-old Sampras, for whom title defense has become habitual. Last year he was rewarded on six of seven defense attempts.</p>
        <p>"Trying to defend a title is something I've gotten used to," he said. "Nobody remembers who comes in second."</p>
        <p>Sampras admitted he was anxious to regain the same early season form that carried him through the first five months of 1994 with only two losses.</p>
        <p>"I was basically just unbeatable; I felt unbeatable," Sampras recalled of an aura of invincibility that came to an abrupt halt just after he repeated as Wimbledon's champion.</p>
        <p>After a summer of battling sore feet and sore ankles as he tried to break in new sneakers, Sampras failed to reclaim his United States Open crown.</p>
        <p>"Not playing well at the Open really hurt," said Sampras, who is wearing old shoes here while Nike puts the finishing touches on a pair of sneakers guaranteed to be friendly to his feet. "My New Year's resolution was to stay healthy all year."</p>
        <p>After a weekend of rain that forced the closure of the stadium's retractable roof, today the sun blistered through what little is left of the ozone layer above Australia and, helped along by a mitigating breeze, the year's first Grand Slam got through its opening-day schedule on schedule. And it was devoid of any of the first-round upsets of seeded performers that seem customary at the three other Grand Slam events.</p>
        <p>Besides the top-seeded Sampras, two other Americans with Grand Slam credentials, the fifth-seeded Michael Chang and the ninth-seeded Jim Courier, twice a champion here, passed the first round without incident.</p>
        <p>Courier, for whom tennis has turned sweet again after a sour 1994 in which he fell from third to 13th in the ranking, was in full control against David Rikl of the Czech Republic. With the exception of a third-set lapse that he corrected in the ensuing tie breaker, Courier advanced with ease, 6-4, 6-0, 7-6 (7-2).</p>
        <p>"I'm trying to get back up the mountain," said Courier, who ended a 17-month title drought in Adelaide two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>After tuning up for this event by humbling Sampras in an exhibition final at the Open's former headquarters at Kooyong on Saturday, Chang eliminated the first of the 27 Australians entered here with a 6-2, 6-4, 5-7, 6-2 victory over Paul Kilderry, the wild card.</p>
        <p>Chang skipped the Australian last year, and in two previous appearances has never ventured beyond the third round. But Chang, like Sampras, said he is not here simply for the exercise.</p>
        <p>"I wouldn't have shown up here if I didn't think I could win it," he said.</p>
        <p>Courier was followed onto Court 1 by the 14-year-old Martina Hingis, who shares the distinction with Andre Agassi of being the Australian Open's most highly hyped newcomers. The 73d-ranked Swiss player, who holds junior titles from the French Open and Wimbledon, made an impressive main-draw debut with a creative 6-0, 7-6 (7-2) defeat of the 90th-ranked Jolene Watanbe.</p>
        <p>"It's always a step more, from the 14's to the 16's to the level of the adults, but I wasn't nervous," said Hingis.</p>
        <p>While Flinders Park was kind to the teen-aged Hingis, it failed to treat the older generation with any indulgence. Mats Wilander, who won the last of his three Australian Open titles in 1988, was despatched by Jacco Eltingh of the Netherlands, 6-3, 7-6 (7-3), 6-4. And the local favorite Pat Cash, the player who was runner-up to Wilander in 1988, failed to survive his Court 1 encounter with Alex O'Brien, losing by 4-6, 6-4, 6-4, 6-2 to the four-time all-American from Stanford. MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>The fourth-seeded MARY PIERCE trounced TINA KRIZAN of Slovakia, 6-1, 6-0. One American man who didn't experience a positive result was the 30th-ranked MALIVAI WASHINGTON. A year ago he posted his best Grand Slam finish with a visit to the quarterfinals here, but on Monday Washington was ambushed, 6-4, 7-5, 6-2, by JAN SIEMERINK, a Dutch wild card ranked 66th. . . . In a night match, STEFAN EDBERG survived against the thunderous play of MARK PHILIPPOUSSIS, an 18-year-old Australian ranked No. 274, by 4-6, 6-3, 7-6 (7-1) 7-5. Also, CONCHITA MARTINEZ of Spain defeated BARBARA RITTNER of Germany, 6-3, 6-2.  TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
