<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Brother, a Sister, Their Town and Their Paper</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="765208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWSPAPERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HIGHTSTOWN (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HIGHTSTOWN GAZETTE (NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ONISHI, NORIMITSU</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DENNIS, KATHRYN S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DENNIS, W PALMER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D91438F93BA15756C0A963958260" item-length="1416" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Brother, a Sister, Their Town and Their Paper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ONISHI, NORIMITSU</byline>
      <dateline>HIGHTSTOWN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Gazette owners have been asked many times to be interviewed and many times turned them down. Many people, especially those who work for large newspapers, television or house organs, do not understand weekly newspapers. They are different from dailies and television and that's the way it should be.  -- "Through the Years With The Gazette," The Hightstown Gazette, June 6, 1991</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Gazette owners have been asked many times to be interviewed and many times turned them down. Many people, especially those who work for large newspapers, television or house organs, do not understand weekly newspapers. They are different from dailies and television and that's the way it should be.  -- "Through the Years With The Gazette," The Hightstown Gazette, June 6, 1991</p>
        <p>W. PALMER DENNIS is perched over the flatbed press, hand-feeding a sheet into the blackened, inky machine. A moonlighter from a Trenton daily, a freshly lighted cigar clenched between his teeth, sits in front of an organlike machine, typesetting the coming issue. And his sister, the voice of the paper, fields phone calls and greets visitors in the anteroom, the newsroom.</p>
        <p>"You walk in here, you walk into the 19th century," said Mr. Dennis, smoothing paper into the 99-year-old printing press as if he were changing a roll in a giant fax machine. "No one does this kind of thing anymore."</p>
        <p>At The Hightstown Gazette, things are like that these days, and, by all accounts, things were little different in the old days. In an age when local newspapers are increasingly owned by chains, The Gazette is the oddest of oddities: a 146-year-old weekly owned and run by a brother and a sister, both septuagenarians, who share the title of publisher.</p>
        <p>The paper has no color, no photos, no computer-generated graphics; its contents date from the era of journalism before schools started emphasizing analysis and story-telling in news. And by the owners' admission, it is a publication whose glory days were at least four decades ago, and whose future is unmistakably limited.</p>
        <p>Despite overwhelming competition from a neighboring chain-owned weekly, The Gazette remains the paper of record for Hightstown and the surrounding township of East Windsor, in Mercer County. It is published every Thursday and mailed to 1,200 subscribers, made up mostly of a shrinking pool of longtime residents for whom living in the area is inseparable from reading The Gazette. The Gazette also publishes about three special supplements year, including a popular Christmas insert, with photos.</p>
        <p>Sgt. John Reppy, a two-decade member of the Hightstown police force, dropped by the other day. "In a town like this, there's been a number of changes over the years," he told a visitor. "But this is one place that's never changed."</p>
        <p>The front page of the May 4 edition is a representative sample. While most local weeklies have a standard front page -- a feature article with a photo, a news article -- The Gazette's front page speaks to another era: seven narrow columns, filled with three obituaries; notices of a planning board meeting, a community fair and a coming visit by Governor Whitman; a recycling update written by the County Executive, two paragraphs on a seventh grader who won a poetry contest, and a running column, "From The Gazette Desk," in which Kathryn S. Dennis ruminates on global warming and old songs.</p>
        <p>Inside the eight-page paper are full-page ads of a church directory and of fire extinguisher safety tips, as well as service articles and legal notices from the two municipalities.</p>
        <p>Except for "From The Gazette Desk," the articles are short and filled with practical information. They resist the tendency of modern journalism to interpret and analyze. Why the need for interpretation when you are writing for people just like yourself?</p>
        <p>"We live here," Miss Dennis said. Although she says she respects her rival, The Windsor-Hights Herald, she added that something is lost whenever chains acquire an independent weekly like hers: "They don't have the true local perspective."</p>
        <p>As she leafed through bound volumes of papers from the 1940's, Miss Dennis pointed here and there to a photo (the paper stopped using photos about four years ago because of rising costs), as if she were perusing a family album. "He opened a rug company," she commented. "He died not too long ago."</p>
        <p>Mayor Scott Caster, 44, who remembers visiting The Gazette building with his mother when he was 5. "The competition reports more spot news," he said. "However, The Gazette usually has a finger on the pulse or consciousness of the town. Kathryn knows the players, and has a historic context to relate the present with the past."</p>
        <p>NOTHING has been preserved with purpose inside 114 Rogers Avenue, a one-story, two-room concrete building just off downtown Hights town. But the machines here are so old, so blackened and dust-blanketed by age that when they are running, they infuse the publisher's words of stepping into the 19th century with a deeper meaning. The wood floor, the gray concrete walls are blackened by decades and by the grinding of a thousand press runs.</p>
        <p>Sunlight, pouring through rooftop windows on the building's south side, floods that half of the office in white light as the other half sinks into darkness, old unused machines fading into dark recesses and corners. The contrast is an odd chiaroscuro -- no colors here, just black and white, no beige or soft blue from the modern newsroom.</p>
        <p>The Gazette moved into this building, which was built for the paper, in 1930, more than 80 years after its birth as The Village Recorder on June 30, 1849. For years, it was the only newspaper to cover Hightstown, the busy service center of a farming region and home to the Peddie School, a private boarding school. George P. Dennis, a stringer for dailies in New York, bought The Gazette in 1912 after moving from Ventura, Calif.</p>
        <p>Miss Dennis said the building bustled with activity as her father, who also worked as borough clerk from 1919 until his death in 1955, turned the office into an extension of local government.</p>
        <p>The years went by peacefully, though one time a subscriber, angry over an article, threatened to kill her father. The threat was taken seriously enough that the family received 24-hour protection, and to this day, Miss Dennis remembers a patrol car passing regularly by the family's house, flashing its headlights each time.</p>
        <p>Of the seven Dennis children, Palmer, 76, says his younger brother, George F., was destined to take over the newspaper. But he was killed in World War II, and Palmer Dennis -- who had planned to settle with his new bride in her native Montana -- became the heir instead. Mr. Dennis was a journalism graduate of Rutgers. (His favorite newspapers, now extinct, were The Newark Evening News and The New York Herald Tribune.)</p>
        <p>AS FOR Miss Dennis, after working 12 years as a school librarian, she returned to the family newspaper in 1955 after her father's death. Eventually, as her brother preferred working behind the scenes, Miss Dennis, at council meetings or in other public events, came to represent the newspaper.</p>
        <p>It was also during those years, before the increasing popularity of television and the advent of The Windsor-Hights Herald, that The Gazette reached its peak in ads and circulation. Today at a quarter an issue, or $15 for an annual subscription, the paper is hanging in there, Mr. Dennis says. Out of loyalty to The Gazette, the two municipalities still place all their legal notices in its pages, although The Herald has a wider circulation of 5,000.</p>
        <p>With no younger family member interested in taking over the paper, one wonders why the Dennises have rejected offers to sell The Gazette or why, in their 70's, they drive themselves so hard. Neither, for instance, has taken a vacation in 25 years. The reason lies perhaps in Miss Dennis's belief that a local newspaper is a vital ingredient in creating real communities, not just people and dwellings bound by a ZIP code.</p>
        <p>"People in the community should know what is happening, how their taxes are being spent or whether there's some planning meeting tomorrow," she said. "Isn't that what a newspaper is for? To straighten people out."</p>
        <p>And although, as Mayor Caster says, Miss Dennis's voice can sometimes grow caustic and accusatory, no one seems to question her ardor and intentions. Ellen Kimmelman, The Herald's office manager, said: "She's very respected. She calls it like it is. She'll have insights in her columns, the old-fashioned newsy little bits."</p>
        <p>Palmer Dennis hints that he will go on as long as his sister, whom he calls his partner, wants to. Miss Dennis, who declines to reveal her age, expresses no desire to stop. The passion is still there, as she showed in a column about the school board.</p>
        <p>"I called them stupid," she said. "He crossed it out and put in 'unwise.' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
