<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Study Calls Household Materials Especially Toxic</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="748828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAZARDOUS AND TOXIC SUBSTANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INFORM INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLUSHA, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DC123BF936A25750C0A963958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Study Calls Household Materials Especially Toxic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN HOLUSHA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLUSHA, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chemicals found in everyday products like carpeting and particleboard may pose greater long-term environmental hazards than industrial chemical wastes, a study conducted for the influential environmental group Inform has concluded.</p>
        <p>One result may be increased pressure on manufacturers, particularly in the chemical industry, to reduce the use of substances suspected of causing cancer or reproductive problems; more paperwork requirements could follow, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chemicals found in everyday products like carpeting and particleboard may pose greater long-term environmental hazards than industrial chemical wastes, a study conducted for the influential environmental group Inform has concluded.</p>
        <p>One result may be increased pressure on manufacturers, particularly in the chemical industry, to reduce the use of substances suspected of causing cancer or reproductive problems; more paperwork requirements could follow, too.</p>
        <p>The 522-page report, based on a computer analysis of data submitted by companies to Federal and state governments, notes that toxic substances used in product manufacture often make their way into the air and water, harming those who come into contact with them.</p>
        <p>For example, formaldehyde, which the Environmental Protection Agency classifies as a probable human carcinogen, is contained in carpeting and particleboard and is gradually released into the air over the long life of those products. Concentrations of 16 contaminants under study are greater indoors than outside, according to an E.P.A. study cited in the report.</p>
        <p>"We are systematically fouling our nests," said Joanna D. Underwood, president of Inform Inc., which is based in New York. "But we do not know which substances have the potential to cause cancer and nerve damage. We are dealing with materials that simply did not exist in any quantity until about 40 years ago."</p>
        <p>Inform uses information to advance an environmental agenda and often provides the intellectual underpinning for other advocacy groups. It was one of those groups that successfully suggested that Congress require corporations to make annual disclosures of their emissions into the air, land and water, a process now known as the Toxics Release Inventory.</p>
        <p>Morton L. Mullins, vice president for regulatory affairs for the Chemical Manufacturers Association, said he was "disturbed by the tone" of the group's announcement and feared that it was using "alarmist rhetoric to create a new set of concerns" for the public.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mullins said he was afraid that the study would lead to increased pressure on business to reduce the use of materials labeled toxic, even in cases where the risk of harm was very low.</p>
        <p>But he also said that Inform had "done important and good work over the years" and that he would attend a panel discussion of the study in Washington.</p>
        <p>The basic premise of the study is that thousands of artificial substances have been developed and used in the last four decades, with little assessment of the hazards they might pose for human health and the environment.</p>
        <p>"Many of these chemicals pose unknown risks to humans, other animal species or ecosystems because they are relatively new and being poured into our society in great quantities," it said. "Also, they are unlike toxic chemicals that have existed in nature for millions of years, against which ecosystems and life forms have had a chance to evolve defenses."</p>
        <p>The study noted that seemingly benign substances had turned out to have ugly side effects. A family of chemicals called chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, were seemingly ideal as refrigerants and industrial solvents because they were not toxic to people and were fireproof, cheap and effective. It was not until the 1970's that they were linked to deterioration of the ozone layer that protects the earth from solar radiation.</p>
        <p>Another family of chemicals, polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, seemed well suited as the fluid in electrical transformers, until they were found to be highly toxic, persistent in the environment and have a tendency to accumulate in the fatty tissue of humans and animals.</p>
        <p>The manufacture of both has been banned, but there are plenty of PCB's in old transformers and CFC's in old refigerators that are at risk of being released into the environment.</p>
        <p>The Inform study noted that the Environmental Protection Agency had blocked the introduction of 9 percent of the new chemicals submitted to it for approval since 1979, suggesting that many of those grandfathered before then would not pass muster today if examined.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mullins of the chemical trade group said the industry shared the environmentalists' concerns about the effects of toxic chemicals on people and the environment. He said the industry's Responsible Care program pushed manufacturers to monitor how customers used their products as a safeguard against uses that presented needless risk.</p>
        <p>But he defended many of the chemicals labeled as toxic as "the basic building blocks" for the plastic, pharmaceutical and semiconductor products needed in a modern society.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
