<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's New</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769780"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="WORD &amp; IMAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANKEL, MAX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D9113EF93BA25755C0A963958260" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's New</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAX FRANKEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRANKEL, MAX</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE IS CONTROVERSY ABOUT THE nature of news. People think the media are too negative or too cynical or too opinionated. That the loudest of these complaints come from the most negative, cynical and opinionated talkers on radio does not disprove them. They are in fact chronic complaints and not now the most serious heard about the news business.</p>
        <p>The public, as measured by opinion polls, does not so much object to "bad" news as it wants a balanced diet, with more "good" news. The public, as measured by its reading habits, wants considerably less news of every kind. And the public, as measured by television ratings, favors trashy gossip about the rich and famous, "magazine" exposes of skulduggery and hourly updates about a certain murder trial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE IS CONTROVERSY ABOUT THE nature of news. People think the media are too negative or too cynical or too opinionated. That the loudest of these complaints come from the most negative, cynical and opinionated talkers on radio does not disprove them. They are in fact chronic complaints and not now the most serious heard about the news business.</p>
        <p>The public, as measured by opinion polls, does not so much object to "bad" news as it wants a balanced diet, with more "good" news. The public, as measured by its reading habits, wants considerably less news of every kind. And the public, as measured by television ratings, favors trashy gossip about the rich and famous, "magazine" exposes of skulduggery and hourly updates about a certain murder trial.</p>
        <p>The response inside the news business has been mounting anxiety. Editors and reporters beat their breasts and confess to elitism; they have been persuaded that their education and income leave them "disconnected" from ordinary readers. Broadcasters fear that the proliferation of cable channels, portable cameras and interactive services is eroding the authority of responsible network news. Newspaper executives, similarly frightened by technology, denounce their own editors for being hooked on "old-fashioned" news and impervious to the "data gathering" and "packaging" skills that are required of modern "content providers."</p>
        <p>Producers and customers alike are fussing about the true nature of news. Yet for all the hand-wringing, there is remarkably little discussion anywhere of what constitutes news, what it should be and how its definition is being altered.</p>
        <p>In most newsrooms, the nature of news, like language itself, is taken for granted. When the editors of The Times design their front page, they work like chefs preparing a sauce -- no recipes needed. This is a good yarn, they'll agree, in ranking the day's events, utterances and reportorial discoveries. And that is the best story of the day. Asked why, they'll tell you a yarn is good if it's important or interesting or, better yet, both. Pressed to define important, they'll say it's news that's likely to have a psychic or material effect on world affairs, American society or local life. As for interesting, why that can be the birth of a panda in Beijing or a bear's rampage in Times Square -- you know, off-beat, wacky, cute, arresting.</p>
        <p>Their instincts are superb but their definitions are hardly illuminating. The biggest news can be predictable (the inauguration of a President) or surprising (the bribing of a Vice President). It can be good news (a stock market surge) or bad news (a train crash). It can be yesterday's big event (a tax cut) or a glacial trend (global warming).</p>
        <p>Since no one can precisely define the nature of news, virtually anyone can claim to be a journalist. Cynics often remark that freedom of the press exists only for people who own one, but no diplomas, certifications or registrations are needed to practice the craft. Newsletters peddling guns or stocks have the same standing in law as The Times or ABC News. The merchants of reckless gossip on "American Journal" can claim the same interest in news as The Wall Street Journal. The news business is a cacophony, if not exactly a democracy.</p>
        <p>However amorphous the idea of news, serious journalists are not hard to define. Deep down, they think of packaging news not as a business but as a public service. They want to provide the information and analysis that a citizen would -- or should -- want to have to make political choices, to prevent abuses of power and to enhance the quality of life. But it's public service with a show-biz flavor. To make the news tastier, the best editors also look for gripping narrative, tales of human heroism and depravity that illuminate life, and then they'll sprinkle in some entertaining spice. To help pay the bills, they will also give generous space to features that sell papers (TV listings and sports stats) or advertising (whole sections about food or automobiles).</p>
        <p>Only occasionally will editors stop to examine their basic habits. A. M. Rosenthal of The Times remembers the day he decided to stop covering Sunday sermons and to cover religions instead. I remember leading a discussion after the collapse of the Soviet Union about how important news would now shift from diplomatic and military concerns to international economics and trade. But being thoughtful about the news is not yet being smart about the news business. In sorting through the current complaints and anxieties, newsmongers need to think about some seismic shifts in their environment.</p>
        <p>Who's first? The great scoops that used to send newsboys running through the streets shouting "Extra" don't count for much anymore. Most scoops don't last long enough for anyone to run three blocks. One reporter's news of a highly visible event, like an explosion in Oklahoma City, or an easily verified plan, like a Cabinet appointment, is easily matched by phone, fax and computer by a hundred other reporters. Even broadcasters rarely beat the competition by more than a few minutes. Nowadays, real scoops that really cannot be easily matched are reports that require extensive (and expensive) investigation and analysis. In the modern news business, brains beat out legs and elbows.</p>
        <p>What's my line? Contrary to what they say, most people don't want their news "straight down the middle." They are really looking to have their opinions confirmed and reinforced. And major news operations now serve such large audiences that they cannot stray very far from center on any issue. So feisty "niche" magazines and arrogant talk shows will continue to take the place of what were once partisan papers.</p>
        <p>When's it playing? Lists of things to do and places to go and apartments for sale and trades in stocks will soon cease to be news on paper. They are much more efficiently compiled and kept fresh by computers, which can customize every need, spit out relevant background material and even execute a transaction.</p>
        <p>Where's the fun? As the last of America's evening papers die out, it should be obvious that the tired consumer seeking mainly diversion at the end of the day finds it more readily on television. All news is, in a sense, entertaining, but television shows are clearly better than even television newscasts at providing the frothy, passive entertainment once available only in the comics and columns advising the lovelorn. News teams that try to compete in this league are doomed.</p>
        <p>Why, why, how and why? It's the last of the five W's they teach in journalism class that will surely define the craft in the foreseeable future. Readers and audiences that want primarily to be entertained, serviced and pandered to will not need traditional news outlets. Those that seek to ease the anxieties of modern life with news will want to understand the forces that shape their lives: why systems fail, why prices go up, how power is amassed, why someone won't do something. More than ever, they will want news that enlightens and liberates, news that only well-educated and well-supported journalists can provide.</p>
        <p>Whether many enterprises can succeed at that trade remains very much to be seen.  WORD &amp; IMAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
