<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In West, Wildflowers Have Jump on Spring And the Tourists Glow</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="749955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DESERTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SONORAN DESERT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAVER, ANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deserts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1DF113DF933A15750C0A963958260" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In West, Wildflowers Have Jump on Spring And the Tourists Glow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAVER, ANNE</byline>
      <dateline>TUCSON, Ariz.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you figure spring by the earth's dance around the sun, it'll show up on March 20 at 9:14 P.M., Eastern time. But out in the desert, it first stirs in January, when the Minnesotans start calling the Arizona Sonoran Desert Museum and asking, "When will the wildflowers bloom?"</p>
        <p>"They want to know which weekend it will peak here -- the exact place and date," said Dr. Mark Dimmitt, the museum's curator of plants, as he drove west across the desert that surrounds Tucson. "They're very insistent."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you figure spring by the earth's dance around the sun, it'll show up on March 20 at 9:14 P.M., Eastern time. But out in the desert, it first stirs in January, when the Minnesotans start calling the Arizona Sonoran Desert Museum and asking, "When will the wildflowers bloom?"</p>
        <p>"They want to know which weekend it will peak here -- the exact place and date," said Dr. Mark Dimmitt, the museum's curator of plants, as he drove west across the desert that surrounds Tucson. "They're very insistent."</p>
        <p>It has been a mild winter all over the country, the third warmest winter on record, in fact (1990 was the warmest; 1954, runner-up), and a little wetter than usual in the Southwest.</p>
        <p>Watching the weather quickened Dr. Dimmitt's blood, as if he were some desert toad waiting under the sand for a puddle of water. He watched the fall rains come in early November, good timing for seed germination. He kept track of the generous rains that fell with lovely regularity throughout the winter. In January, he saw the flatlands turn as green as a pasture. It was exactly the same sequence of events he had noted in 1979 -- the last banner year for wildflowers!</p>
        <p>It looked so good that Dr. Dimmitt, a normally cautious man, threw caution to the winds.</p>
        <p>"It's time to call the folks in Michigan and tell them to get out here in March," he exclaimed back in January. "This one's going to be real good, the best in 15 years."</p>
        <p>Midwesterners stood poised by their big campers.</p>
        <p>But the desert, which can be as mysterious as the weather, has Dr. Dimmitt as bamboozled as the New Yorkers who bought all that salt this winter -- waiting for the 50 inches of snow that never came.</p>
        <p>Last week, he roared across the desert with a van full of spring-starved wildflower lovers.</p>
        <p>"Oooh!!" his passengers chorused as they passed a patch of golden poppies.</p>
        <p>"That's nothing -- I saw four miles of them in 1979," Dr. Dimmitt said.</p>
        <p>"Stop!" they yelped as the van zoomed by a luscious mass of purple owl clover and deep blue lupines.</p>
        <p>"You want to stop for that?" he sneered, like a botanist betrayed. More than once he muttered, "This is unbelievably bad."</p>
        <p>Bad? Desert marigolds are carpeting Picacho Peak to the north. The yucca trees in Joshua Tree National Park in California are heavy with white creamy blossoms. The ocotillos -- those scraggly spined sticks that grow 12 feet into the air -- are starting to sport the blood-red tubular flowers that will lure the hummingbirds up from Mexico.</p>
        <p>The rains and the mild winter have conspired to produce a rich variety of blooms.</p>
        <p>"There are so many different flowers this year," said Gary Paul Nabhan, a biologist who has spent 15 years in this desert, learning its plants and its secrets from the Papago Indians, the Desert People. "It's a year of diversity rather than grandstanders."</p>
        <p>But the big blonds of the desert, the Mexican poppies that set a volcanic mountain on fire, and the blue lupines that can flow over the scruffy old desert floor like the shallow seas that once covered the flatlands 700 million years ago, well they're there. But they're here and there. They're not exploding in that cover-girl way.</p>
        <p>And nobody knows why.</p>
        <p>"We do know that good bloom depends on an early and wet rainy season," Dr. Dimmitt said. "But beyond that there are many, many details, and we have no idea what they are." There are 2,500 species of plants in the Sonoran Desert, half of which are annuals, and every one of those species has different exact requirements.</p>
        <p>It's going to be a great year for perennials thanks to the mild rainy winter, and any lizard that can climb is scooting into the golden brittlebushes to snap up the insects wallowing in the pollen-laden flowers.</p>
        <p>"And anything that eats seeds will be happy," Dr. Dimmitt said, cheering up a bit. "We're expecting a big boom in insects, lizards, birds and mice." But never again will you catch Dr. Dimmitt predicting when the annuals will bust out.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's all those European grasses, the botanist said darkly. "I saw sand verbena in the Mojave that was four inches tall, completely covered up by four-foot mustard and Russian thistle."</p>
        <p>There's a certain grass-is-greener-on-the-other-side syndrome infecting those on the wildflower trail. You call the Wildflower Hotline and hear that the poppies are peaking at Picacho Peak State Park. You get there and the assistant park manager, Tamara Westberg, says, "Well, about four weeks back, the temperatures climbed into the 80's, so the flowers started going to seed without reaching maturity."</p>
        <p>It's like a snark hunt, this wildflower business. You drive down toward Nogales searching for wild chilies (they grow in the canyons, in the shade of the hackberry bushes) with Dr. Nabhan, and a man in Tubac says the mountains on the Arizona-New Mexico border are covered with Mexican poppies.</p>
        <p>"The hills were gold -- you could see them from 10 miles away," said Harry March, who owns the Tubac Country Market. Mr. March loves wildflowers so much he turned his cattle ranch into a wildflower farm.</p>
        <p>The ranchers down at the Cow Palace, the local watering hole in Amado, used to love to ask, "Harry, going to round up some seeds today?"</p>
        <p>And Harry would reply: "Well, I'm getting about $550 a pound for my poppy seeds. How much are you getting?"</p>
        <p>Mr. March did O.K. with poppies, but he couldn't crack the code for enough others to make much money. So he sold the ranch and went into Indian art.</p>
        <p>Dr. Nabhan, steeped in the patience of the Papago Indians, laughed. He dug up a Papago onion, which has a delicate little lavender star of a flower, scraped off its brown furry coat and invited his guests to take a bite. The mild, starchy root was one of the first plants to feed the Desert People in the early spring. He offered tastes of wild spinach, too.</p>
        <p>He pointed out a creosote bush covering itself with little yellow flowers. Greasewood, the Papago call it, using it to treat everything from sore throats to diabetes. They say it was the first plant to appear out of the darkness -- when Earth Maker took some soil from his chest and flattened it in the palm of his hand. It was here 17,000 years ago. And it resprouted in Yucca Flats, Nev., 10 years after the Sedan nuclear explosion of 1962.</p>
        <p>But some age-old signs of spring are ominously silent. The Tarahumara frogs that used to swim in the clear water of Rock Corral Canyon, about 50 miles south of Tucson, are gone.</p>
        <p>"Copper smelting and acid rain changed the pH of the water, and they've died out completely in Arizona," Dr. Nabhan said. "They haven't been seen in seven years."</p>
        <p>But such messages from the desert haven't reached Picacho, where a thousand people are coming through the gate a day (their license plates say Manitoba, British Columbia, Maine, Florida, Ohio), most of them looking for the big bang.</p>
        <p>Pearl and Lloyd Higgins, from New Port Richey, Fla., sat on metal folding chairs at the end of a 38-foot camper that was emblazoned with a mural of endangered wild animals surrounding a pair of hands holding the earth. The white and blue camper is named Odessa, and she gets 11 miles to the gallon.</p>
        <p>"So where's the desert?" Mr. Higgins asked.</p>
        <p>Why, he was sitting in it, he was told.</p>
        <p>So listen up, wildflower lovers. The annuals are peaking right now, but the cactuses haven't even gotten revved up yet. The saguaros, those big tall cactuses that stand like giants with their arms raised to the sky, won't bloom until May.</p>
        <p>"The flowers smell like rotted cantaloupe," Dr. Dimmitt said.</p>
        <p>The desert museum's director, David Hancocks, said: "I love how big and burly they are. And when they get these big frilly flowers, they look like they're in drag."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hancocks, who grew up in Wales, said it had taken him awhile to really see the desert. First he looked for green, and there wasn't much. Then he looked for color, which comes and goes.</p>
        <p>"Then I started looking for texture, and I saw beauty," he said. He leaned over the stringy lone leaf of a desert lily that had yet to bloom. He chuckled.</p>
        <p>"Imagine coming all the way from Maine for that," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
