<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World: Japan's Nature; A People Tremble in Harmony With the Land</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="738562"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTHQUAKES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISASTERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KOBE (JAPAN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kobe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earthquakes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Disasters</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DC113FF931A15752C0A963958260" item-length="1833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World: Japan's Nature; A People Tremble in Harmony With the Land</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRISTOF, NICHOLAS D</byline>
      <dateline>KOBE, Japan</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Earth shakes, ground trembles.  With great weight of snow,  The tight rope snaps back.</p>
        <p>-- Itto Nishimoto, haiku poet, 1907-1991</p>
        <p>WITH its neon lights and heated toilet seats and cellular faxes, the great trading city of Kobe a week ago seemed a citadel of modernity and affluence and internationalism, an antipodean New York with more sushi. Then the ground opened up Tuesday and unleashed an inferno that killed more than 4,000 people and returned part of western Japan to a primeval condition that would have been recognizable to the people who lived in Japan thousands of years ago.</p>
        <p>The earthquake was a horrific reminder that prosperity and technology cannot insulate a country from its natural environment. The familiar pattern of Japanese history -- development, disaster and reconstruction -- is now being repeated in Kobe and the surrounding cities as residents search the smoldering rubble for the bodies of their friends and try to rebuild homes and businesses that took a lifetime to create.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Earth shakes, ground trembles.  With great weight of snow,  The tight rope snaps back.</p>
        <p>-- Itto Nishimoto, haiku poet, 1907-1991</p>
        <p>WITH its neon lights and heated toilet seats and cellular faxes, the great trading city of Kobe a week ago seemed a citadel of modernity and affluence and internationalism, an antipodean New York with more sushi. Then the ground opened up Tuesday and unleashed an inferno that killed more than 4,000 people and returned part of western Japan to a primeval condition that would have been recognizable to the people who lived in Japan thousands of years ago.</p>
        <p>The earthquake was a horrific reminder that prosperity and technology cannot insulate a country from its natural environment. The familiar pattern of Japanese history -- development, disaster and reconstruction -- is now being repeated in Kobe and the surrounding cities as residents search the smoldering rubble for the bodies of their friends and try to rebuild homes and businesses that took a lifetime to create.</p>
        <p>It is of course risky to generalize too much about differences in foreign cultures. A century ago one of the first Japanese to travel to the United States wrote back, "In America, unmarried women are called Jones, and married women are called Johnson."</p>
        <p>Yet differences can be real, and sometimes the way people or nations react to disasters can open a window on their souls. The catastrophe in western Japan, and its orderly aftermath, with hardly a looter to be found, may offer some insights into life and society in Japan.</p>
        <p>Asian cultures have always felt themselves to be intertwined with nature in a way that is difficult for Americans to appreciate. Earthquakes, floods, typhoons, tidal waves, monsoons and volcanoes are an essential part of the natural order, nourishing life and extinguishing it, and the risks are always in the back of people's minds.</p>
        <p>The sense of vulnerability has bred a stoicism that can be seen in the streets of Kobe today. "Shikata Ga Nai," the Japanese say, "that's just the way it is; it can't be helped." Natural disasters may just be a matter of "unmei" -- fate -- a word that, when it is written, is composed of the characters for movement and for life.</p>
        <p>While Westerners have long seen humans in confrontation with nature, and usually overcoming it, the traditional Japanese conception was different. The Japanese saw themselves as a part of nature, so much so that even the word for nature, "shizen," is a modern one, only about 100 years old. Until then there was no need for a Western concept of nature, for people were not distinct from the environment but embedded in it. Japan is, after all, the only industrial country whose head of state (Emperor Akihito) is a descendant of the Sun Goddess.</p>
        <p>Expecting Disaster</p>
        <p>Japan, in fact, has been subject to the cycle of natural disaster and renewal for thousands of years, and today the 30 million people in the Tokyo region sit atop an active fault that constantly threatens the kinds of upheaval that killed 142,000 people in the great Tokyo earthquake of 1923. The city fire authorities released a study a few days ago that another severe earthquake in Tokyo could kill or injure 68,000 people -- and that might be optimistic, since the Kobe quake produced more damage than anybody had anticipated.</p>
        <p>In one respect, it is much the same throughout Asia. In low-lying Bangladesh, flooding in 1988 left two-thirds of the country under water, and a typhoon in 1991 killed more than 100,000 people. Some were saved only when they were blown off their offshore islands and onto the mainland a dozen miles away. If global warming leads oceans to rise a few feet, much of Bangladesh may simply disappear.</p>
        <p>China is the great historical chronicler in the region, and its records go back for thousands of years in recording hundreds of thousands of people at a time killed by earthquakes or floods or changes in the courses of rivers.</p>
        <p>At the beginning of the 1960's a famine killed 30 million Chinese -- it was the worst famine in world history -- and as recently as 1976 an earthquake in the northern Chinese city of Tangshan killed 240,000 people by official count and perhaps several times that number.</p>
        <p>Yet Japan has traveled a long way from its Shinto roots as a nation of nature-worshiping rice farmers. Beginning with the Meiji Era a century ago, when Japan began its frantic and furious effort to modernize, every effort has gone into building skyscrapers and bridges and (supposedly) quake-proof freeways. Instead of keeping in harmony with the dragons of nature, engineers sought dominance.</p>
        <p>"We're exposed to a severe natural environment, and we're probably more aware of natural hazards than Americans are," said Yozo Fujino, an earthquake expert and engineering professor at Tokyo University. "So we've been paying extra to try to get more safety, but the quake shows that our procedures weren't adequate."</p>
        <p>Still, in some ways the engineers succeeded. There has been a good deal of second-guessing and recrimination about the collapse of buildings and bridges that were not supposed to collapse, but the fact remains that an exceptionally violent temblor took a region with millions of people, with enough strength to heave railroad cars on their sides, and 99.9 percent of the population survived.</p>
        <p>Japanese engineers have developed not only bullet trains that travel as fast as 170 miles an hour, but also a system whereby seismographs automatically dispatch computerized instructions to halt the bullet trains at the first sign of an earthquake. In Osaka, near the heart of the quake, the gas company has installed meters that instantly shut off the gas supply at the first seismic jolt. Japanese engineering was humiliated only because of its own exceptionally high standards.</p>
        <p>Remembering Old Boasts</p>
        <p>Still, the humiliation is there. The Japanese newspapers are full of self-mocking recollections that after the Los Angeles earthquake a year ago Japanese said that freeways here could never collapse. The nation itself has been humbled, adding to the tangle of feelings the Japanese have about precisely who they have become and just where they fit in the modern world.</p>
        <p>Sometimes Japan seems torn between two perceptions of itself. One is of the irrepressible, unstoppable powerhouse, whose secret weapon is its own special national characteristics. That vision of Japan as No. 1 was strongest in the early part of World War II, when the Japanese Army and Navy overwhelmed allied forces in the Pacific and Southeast Asia, and again in the 1980's, when the Tokyo stock market seemed filled with helium and real estate tycoons ate food coated with gold -- the better for their health -- as land prices rose so high that the Imperial Palace grounds in Tokyo were supposedly worth more than all of California.</p>
        <p>The other self-perception of Japan is of the poor island archipelago with few natural resources, one that is always living on the edge of one disaster or another. This more humble version returned a bit in the last few years following the collapse of the "bubble economy." The great earthquake seems to have again brought this image to the fore when Japan holds a mirror to itself.</p>
        <p>A Lingering Uncertainty</p>
        <p>"It's been 50 years since the war ended and we're at a watershed," said Keigo Okonogi, a professor of psychiatry at Keio University in Tokyo. "We've had our economy hollowed out, corruption in politics, and very rapid changes. This earthquake will add to the sense of uncertainty among the Japanese people.</p>
        <p>"Japan had been proud of its highways, bridges, railroads, and they were destroyed in the quake, so there's a psychological blow to the Japanese people."</p>
        <p>Yet it is striking how, here in Kobe, people are looking only ahead. They are cleaning out their homes, or clearing the rubble, and seeing how they can rebuild their lives.</p>
        <p>One of the phrases the Japanese have used in describing themselves is "gaman," a term that has no equivalent in English but that roughly means a kind of stoical perseverence.</p>
        <p>Half a century ago, Kobe was nearly destroyed by bombing in World War II, and then the local people rebuilt it into one of the great trading centers of Asia, the port through which 12 percent of Japan's exports pass. Now, large sections of Kobe again are smoldering rubble, and the rebuilding has begun once more. The resilience is breathtaking.</p>
        <p>"In 1944 I was in Tokyo when it was heavily bombed, and in one night almost one-third of the city was bombed," Hiroyoshi Ishikawa, a professor of social psychology at Seijo University, remembers. "But the next day we began to adjust to the new environment and find a way to survive. It's the gaman mindset, and it's in the national character of the Japanese people."</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is a bit self-serving when Japanese see themselves as apostles of patience and perseverence, but it is true that such values are often drilled into young people from an early age. Whereas American parents are always telling Johnny to put on his jacket before going outside, some Japanese parents send Toshi-kun to kindergartens where the kids run around outside in winter in just their shorts. It builds character.</p>
        <p>Or maybe it just gives the kids colds. Even so, it at least helps create a sense of expectation that people will endure hardship together.</p>
        <p>There was little or no looting in Kobe, even though store windows were shattered and goods were sometimes available for the picking. Perhaps people didn't steal because they are good at heart, or perhaps because each neighborhood is like a little village, or perhaps because everybody is suffering together, or perhaps because residents are too worried about the shame of getting caught.</p>
        <p>A Sense of Order</p>
        <p>It is common to describe Western society as guilt-based and Japanese as shame-based. Americans have hangups while the Japanese get embarrassed, or so the theory goes, and no doubt it can be taken too far.</p>
        <p>But this sense of personal honor and dignity, and fear of being shamed, may be one reason why the Japanese in Kobe are ideal disaster victims. Even when their lives have been torn apart by earthquake, they sometimes line up and politely offer: After you.</p>
        <p>Then, too, this part of Japan, which is known as the Kansai, is famous as an area where people are particularly pragmatic. In Osaka, the capital of the Kansai region, older folks sometimes still greet each other: "Mokari makka" -- "Have you made money today?" People of Kansai barely see pie in the sky before they're plotting to bring it down to earth.</p>
        <p>These days, this pragmatism is evident in the little ways that people are adapting. They press ahead to rebuild, accepting the week's tragedy with a measure of philosophical acceptance. As the great 17th century haiku poet Basho wrote, after finding a man's grave in a bamboo grove:</p>
        <p>The vicissitudes of life.</p>
        <p>Sad, to become finally</p>
        <p>a bamboo shoot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
