<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WINE TALK</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="813778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E6D71E39F935A35751C1A963958260" item-length="1190" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WINE TALK</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORE sparkling wine is sold in November and December than in the other 10 months combined, and that's unfortunate.</p>
        <p>Even if we accept the fact that sparkling wines are for celebrations, there have to be other times in the year when there is something worth celebrating. Weddings once made a difference; June used to be a good sparkling-wine month. But that was when everyone got married in June. Now, it's a year-round sport.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MORE sparkling wine is sold in November and December than in the other 10 months combined, and that's unfortunate.</p>
        <p>Even if we accept the fact that sparkling wines are for celebrations, there have to be other times in the year when there is something worth celebrating. Weddings once made a difference; June used to be a good sparkling-wine month. But that was when everyone got married in June. Now, it's a year-round sport.</p>
        <p>As for opening a bottle of sparkling wine just because it tastes good, forget it. A lot of people seem to feel guilty drinking a party wine when there  is no party. Too bad.</p>
        <p>We consume about 34 million gallons of sparkling wine a year in this country, and 24 million gallons of it -- about 70 percent -- is made here.</p>
        <p>Most of this is sweet innocuous stuff, made by injecting carbon dioxide into  relatively cheap wine. This kind of sparkling wine is made in enormous quantities and sells for $5 a bottle, sometimes less.</p>
        <p>When we do have something special to crow about, we have turned, almost automatically, to France and Champagne.</p>
        <p>That may be changing. It has taken 20 years, but the best of our own sparklers are finally beginning to hold their own against the best Europe has to offer, which invariably means French Champagne. Premium sparkling-wine producers both here and there use the methode champenoise, the Champagne method. In this expensive process, the wine ferments in its bottle, which must be uncorked at some point so that dead yeast cells can be removed, then topped off and recorked.</p>
        <p>Over the years, various efforts have been made to produce top-quality sparkling wine in this country. Gold Seal and Taylor in New York, the somewhat Germanic wines of Hanns Kornell in the Napa Valley and the popular line from the Korbel Champagne Cellars in Sonoma County come to mind.</p>
        <p>But the first in modern times to truly match the style and quality of the best French Champagnes is from Jack and Jamie Davies's Schramsberg Vineyards in  the Napa Valley. The Davieses have more than held their own over the years -- this is their 30th anniversary -- producing a line of excellent sparkling wines  led by their J. Schram, a blend of pinot noir and chardonnay that spends at least four years in the bottle before it is released.</p>
        <p>Schramsberg also produces a delicious medium-sweet demi-sec, which makes a perfect dessert wine.</p>
        <p>The 1970's and 80's saw a veritable invasion of California by foreign sparkling-wine producers. First and still the largest was Moet &amp; Chandon, with the Domaine Chandon in the Napa Valley. Chandon produces some 500,000 cases of sparkling wine a year, led by its luxury cuvee, Etoile. Some critics say its best is its brut, especially in magnums.</p>
        <p>Piper-Heidsieck (Piper-Sonoma), Deutz (Maison Deutz), Taittinger (Domaine Carneros), Mumm (Mumm Napa Valley) and Roederer (Roederer Estate) followed from  France, while two giants came from Spain: Codorniu (Codorniu Napa) and Freixenet (Gloria Ferrer).</p>
        <p>Among the European settlers, Roederer, which situated itself in the Anderson  Valley in Mendocino County, and Taittinger, in Carneros, Calif., are doing some  of the most interesting work. Roederer's new L'Ermitage should give serious competition to some of the wines being made back at the home office in Reims. Domaine Carneros's Brut Blanc de Blancs is less muscular than the Roederer but makes up for it in elegance and delicacy. The first release of Mumm Napa Valley's new DVX, the 1990, would be near the top of any list of fine California sparkling wines.</p>
        <p>John Scharffenberger ranks among the best of the American sparkling-wine producers, so much so that he was bought out in 1989 by the owners of Pommery and Lanson, two French Champagne concerns. They were, in turn, swallowed up by others, and now Scharffenberger Cellars is owned by LVMH, the French conglomerate whose holdings include Moet &amp; Chandon, Veuve Clicquot, Mercier, De  Venoge and, of course, Domaine Chandon.</p>
        <p>Iron Horse, in western Sonoma County, has been producing superior sparkling wines for years, the best known being its Wedding Cuvee. Its blanc de blancs occasionally has the edge in finesse. Iron Horse, too, flies two flags: it has a working relationship with Laurent-Perrier. A wine combining the talents of both  has been promised for the future.</p>
        <p>A genuine sleeper among American sparkling wines comes from Oregon. It is called Argyle and is made by Brian Croser, wine maker for and manager of Petaluma, one of Australia's most famous wineries. The Argyle sparkling-wine lineup comprises a brut, a rose and a blanc de blancs comprise, but they are not yet easy to find. The brut is fresh, medium bodied and surprisingly elegant -- no surprise to anyone familiar with the fine sparklers Mr. Croser makes in the antipodes. Argyle is a name to seek out.</p>
        <p>So, too, is a new line of sparkling wines from Artisans and Estates, a branch of the ever-growing Kendall-Jackson organization. The unfortunate name, Kristone, makes it sound like something for a car's radiator, but the wine is exceptional. A blanc de blancs, a blanc de noirs and a brut rose were released earlier this year to justified acclaim. The blanc de noirs in particular displayed the fullness and richness found in the best French Champagne.</p>
        <p>Kristone comes from Santa Barbara County, with an eye-popping $60-a-bottle price tag. The only California sparkling wine to approach that price is Schramsberg's J. Schram, which lists for $50. There is another connection: Harold Osborne, the wine maker who helped make Schramsberg's reputation in the 70's, is the wine maker for Kristone.</p>
        <p>Kendall-Jackson will introduce another sparkling wine, from Mendocino County, in a year or two, to be called Bailey &amp; Brock, and Mr. Osborne is the consulting wine maker.</p>
        <p>TASTINGS</p>
        <p>Meerlust Merlot 1989 (Stellenbosch, South Africa). About $15.</p>
        <p>The Meerlust Estate, which has been producing wine at the Western Cape in South  Africa for 300 years, has long been known for its superior reds. The winery's most famous offering is its Rubicon, a cabernet-merlot blend with the same name  as Francis Ford Coppola's good Napa Valley wine. But merlot is the first love of Giorgio Dalla Cia, Meerlust's wine maker, and it shows in this intense, elegant  wine. It has all the concentration and structure of a great Pomerol and, thanks  to 18 months in new French oak, the roundness, fruit and soft tannins of a top California merlot. The wine is beautifully balanced -- no one component predominates -- and has a remarkably long finish. Even though it's already six years old, it should improve in the bottle for another five years and drink well for another 10 after that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
