<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study of Cloud Patterns Points to Many Areas Exposed to Big Rises inUltraviolet Radiation</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="810567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA SPACE INSTITUTE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEASPACE CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUBIN, DAN (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JENSEN, ELSA H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDC1339F932A15752C1A963958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study of Cloud Patterns Points to Many Areas Exposed to Big Rises inUltraviolet Radiation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEPLETION of the earth's protective ozone layer is exposing some areas of the world, including parts of the United States, to biologically harmful doses of ultraviolet radiation, but some other areas will not become vulnerable for another 20 to 50 years, according to a new study.</p>
        <p>The reason for the variance, the authors of the study say, is that patterns of cloud cover vary from one area to another. Clouds as well as ozone block ultraviolet radiation, and the actual pattern and amount of radiation reaching the ground cannot be calculated globally unless this is taken into account.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEPLETION of the earth's protective ozone layer is exposing some areas of the world, including parts of the United States, to biologically harmful doses of ultraviolet radiation, but some other areas will not become vulnerable for another 20 to 50 years, according to a new study.</p>
        <p>The reason for the variance, the authors of the study say, is that patterns of cloud cover vary from one area to another. Clouds as well as ozone block ultraviolet radiation, and the actual pattern and amount of radiation reaching the ground cannot be calculated globally unless this is taken into account.</p>
        <p>By making the calculation in that manner, experts in California have concluded on the basis of satellite data that large parts of North America, most of central Europe, the Mediterranean, New Zealand, South Africa and the southern half of Australia, Argentina and Chile are now being subjected to significant increases in harmful radiation. In the United States, the affected areas arethe  Midwest, the Southwest including southern California, and part of the Northeast. Hawaii is also being affected, according to the study.</p>
        <p>The research was done by Dr. Dan Lubin, a research physicist at the California Space Institute at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in San Diego, and Elsa H. Jensen, an aerospace engineer with the SeaSpace Corporation,  a satellite instrument and software company in San Diego. Their report appeared  in the Oct. 26 issue of the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Ultraviolet-B from the sun, a form of radiation that can cause skin cancer and cataracts, damage the immune system and disrupt natural ecosystems, is normally blocked by a layer of ozone in the stratosphere. Industrial chemicals,  principally chlorofluorocarbons used as refrigerants, destroy stratospheric ozone.  Under an international agreement, the production of chlorofluorocarbons  is to cease at the end of this year. But because the chemicals persist so long in the atmosphere, ozone depletion is expected to continue for decades.</p>
        <p>"Whether or not you can assert that ozone depletion is an environmental problem" at any given time "depends very much on where you are," Dr. Lubin said.</p>
        <p>He and Ms. Jensen calculated that at the estimated average global rate of ozone depletion, about 2.5 percent per decade, large parts of continental Europe, North and South America, Australia and Southern Africa would be bathed in increased UV-B radiation in five years.</p>
        <p>But the British Isles and Ireland, for instance, are not expected to experience a significant increase for another 30 years, and it is not expected for 20 to 50 years in parts of central Russia, most of China, Japan, North and South Korea and the Indian subcontinent. Mexico, northern Australia, New Guinea  and areas of South America north of Sao Paulo, Brazil, are also not expected to  experience increases for decades.</p>
        <p>In the United States, the South and Pacific Northwest should not experience increases for another 20 years, according to the calculations.</p>
        <p>A major factor in determining whether biologically significant amounts reach  the earth, Dr. Lubin said, is the natural variability of cloudiness in a given area. When cloud cover varies widely from one year to the next, the ultraviolet  radiation that people and other organisms are exposed to also varies. Increases  in the radiation because of the depleted ozone layer probably do not have a biological effect until they exceed this natural variability, Dr. Lubin said.</p>
        <p>To calculate natural variability, Dr. Lubin and Ms. Jensen combined satellite data on global ozone trends from 1978 to 1993 with satellite data on solar radiation reflected from clouds from 1985 to 1990. This produced a base line of  natural variability, against which the researchers compared trends in UV expected from ozone depletion. The comparison enabled them to determine how long it takes for the expected UV trend to become significant.</p>
        <p>In determining the present amount of UV-B striking the earth, an indirect analysis of this sort would not be necessary if there were abundant UV detection instruments around the world. But the instruments are sparse, and most have not  been in position long enough, over a broad enough area, to detect any trends, especially in the temperate zones where most people live.</p>
        <p>Instruments have shown for certain that UV-B has risen significantly in Antarctica, where ozone depletion has been the most severe. A few measurements in temperate zones also indicate an increase.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
