<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spun Mercury Is Eye of Telescope</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="810564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELESCOPES AND OBSERVATORIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERCURY (METAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIRRORS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mirrors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07EFDC1339F932A15752C1A963958260" item-length="1553" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spun Mercury Is Eye of Telescope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE Sir Isaac Newton invented the reflecting telescope three centuries ago, astronomical observatories have been largely dependent on huge and increasingly  costly light-collecting mirrors made of aluminum-coated glass. But a new generation of mirrors based on silvery liquid mercury promises to drastically reduce the cost of cutting-edge astronomy.</p>
        <p>The new mirrors are little more than rotating dishes containing small quantities of liquid mercury metal. As the mirror dish at the base of a telescope rotates, centrifugal force counters the force of gravity on the heavy  fluid, pushing some of the mercury outward and upward toward the edge, curving its shiny surface into a perfect paraboloid. By adjusting the speed of rotation, and hence the curvature of the mercury's surface, the focal length of the mirror can be adjusted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE Sir Isaac Newton invented the reflecting telescope three centuries ago, astronomical observatories have been largely dependent on huge and increasingly  costly light-collecting mirrors made of aluminum-coated glass. But a new generation of mirrors based on silvery liquid mercury promises to drastically reduce the cost of cutting-edge astronomy.</p>
        <p>The new mirrors are little more than rotating dishes containing small quantities of liquid mercury metal. As the mirror dish at the base of a telescope rotates, centrifugal force counters the force of gravity on the heavy  fluid, pushing some of the mercury outward and upward toward the edge, curving its shiny surface into a perfect paraboloid. By adjusting the speed of rotation, and hence the curvature of the mercury's surface, the focal length of the mirror can be adjusted.</p>
        <p>New telescopes based on liquid-mercury mirrors must look almost straight up, a limitation for an astronomical observatory. But for many purposes, including astronomical scanning, searching for space debris and probing the chemistry of the Earth's atmosphere, a vertical view is adequate.</p>
        <p>Users of the new mercury telescopes describe the quality of their reflected images as better than those of most solid glass mirrors.</p>
        <p>"We are getting image quality from mercury mirrors comparable to that of the  glass mirror in the Hubble Space Telescope," said Dr. Ermanno F. Borra of the Universite Laval in Quebec, a leading innovator in the development of spinning liquid mirrors. Best of all, a telescope with a liquid-mercury mirror costs less than one-hundredth as much as a telescope with a conventional glass mirror, he said.</p>
        <p>In September, the University of California at Los Angeles began operating a 2.6-meter (104-inch) mercury mirror 100 miles below the Arctic Circle 30 miles east of Fairbanks, Alaska. The telescope, the 20th largest in the world, is dedicated to studying the aurora borealis and the ionosphere, the region of the  upper atmosphere where the aurora occurs. The telescope, say its builders, cost  only $50,000, a small fraction of the cost of a telescope with a glass mirror of the same size.</p>
        <p>The telescope is partly financed by the military because experiments with it  may lead to new techniques for signaling submarines and probing battlefields for secret tunnels and bunkers. Users of the telescope will study the interaction of intense pulses of radio beams with the ionosphere, which then broadcasts a signal that can be received in the deep ocean. [Page C10.]</p>
        <p>Dr. Ralph Wuerker, a U.C.L.A. development engineer, said that the instrument  will spend the forthcoming winter studying ionized nitrogen in the atmosphere about 60 miles high, where solar radiation rips away some electrons from the atoms making up gases, leaving them in an electrically charged state. A laser mounted near the telescope fires brief pulses of light upward, tuned to excite the ionized gas to emit a pulse of light of its own. This return pulse is then collected by the mercury-mirror telescope, and its light is analyzed in terms of spectral composition.</p>
        <p>Several other mercury-mirror telescopes are in operation.</p>
        <p>At Sunspot, N.M., the National Aeronautics and Space Administration has completed a three-meter-diameter (118-inch) mercury-mirror telescope designed to collect images of space debris that might hit manned spacecraft with catastrophic results. The telescope can detect orbiting objects as small as one-half inch across as they pass overhead. NASA plans to build a similar telescope at the Equator to hasten the agency's tally of dangerous space debris.</p>
        <p>For three years, the University of Western Ontario at London, Ontario, has operated a 2.7-meter (106-inch) mercury mirror in conjunction with an upward-pointing laser for atmospheric studies, which include the detection of changes in the protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>At Dr. Borra's laboratory, a 3.6-meter (142-inch) liquid mirror is under development, and Dr. Borra is collaborating with Dr. Paul Hickson of the University of British Columbia at Vancouver in the building of a gigantic five-meter mercury-mirror instrument. This telescope will have the same light-collecting power as the great 200-inch telescope at Mount Palomar, Calif., which is the third largest in the world. (Russia has a six-meter, or 236-inch, telescope; the Keck Telescope in Hawaii, 10 meters, or 393 inches, in diameter,  is the world's largest.)</p>
        <p>Mercury mirrors are so accurate, Dr. Borra said, that one of them, a59-inch reflector built in Belgium, is used as a reference standard for testing conventional glass telescope mirrors being sent into space by the European Space Agency.</p>
        <p>The idea of using a liquid mirror in an astronomical telescope is not new. Isaac Newton himself is believed to have thought of it.</p>
        <p>In 1908, Dr. Robert W. Wood of Johns Hopkins University spent his summer vacation on Long Island, building a primitive observatory with a spinning liquid mercury mirror. The mirror, a dish 20 inches in diameter, was mounted on a bearing attached to a sturdy concrete foundation at the bottom of a deep pit. The mirror was turned by a pulley connected to an electric motor. By adjusting the motor's speed he could change the curvature of the mercury and bring an image of stars directly overhead to focus on a photographic plate mounted at the top of the pit. The system produced blurred images but worked well enough to photograph the barely separated components of a double star.</p>
        <p>But two main obstacles delayed the further development of liquid-mirror telescopes. One was that such telescopes cannot track their targets. They look straight up and can only photograph stars and other celestial objects as streaks, as the earth's rotation carries them through their vertical fields of view.</p>
        <p>A second formidable problem was that the early bearings and motors used by Dr. Wood and a few other experimenters were vulnerable to even the slightest vibrations, which tended to produce waves on the mercury surface and distort images.</p>
        <p>But in recent years, astronomers have realized that even fixed telescopes that can point only upward are useful. One of the most productive astronomical instruments in the world is the great radio telescope at Arecibo, P.R., 1,000 feet across. The telescope cannot be aimed, but it scans the sky overhead as the earth's rotation moves a strip of sky across the instrument's line of sight.</p>
        <p>Technology has enhanced the abilities of fixed optical telescopes, as well as radio telescopes. The invention of the charge-couple device, a chip somewhat similar to the image chip in a television camera, endows even a fixed telescope  with limited tracking ability. As an image sweeps across the chip, a computer follows the image electronically and records it as a single point of light rather than a smeared streak.</p>
        <p>The stability of the latest mercury-mirror telescopes has been greatly improved by replacing conventional mechanical bearings with compressed-air bearings, which prevent the turning dish from coming into contact with any solid object that might cause vibrations. Another improvement has been in the quality  of drive motors and power supplies, which can now maintain almost perfect constancy of rotation speed.</p>
        <p>The latest mercury mirrors start out as shells cast in approximately paraboloid shapes from strong, rigid epoxies and Kevlar. To create an accurate starting paraboloid, the finished shell is spun on a turntable at the required speed, and liquid polyurethane is poured in. The polyurethane quickly spreads out in the shape of a paraboloid, and then hardens.</p>
        <p>To prepare the mirror for use, its rotation rate is adjusted and mercury is added. The new 2.6-meter (102-inch) mirror built by U.C.L.A. in Alaska contains  300 pounds of the heavy metal, which is spread out in the revolving dish to a thickness of about one-eighth of an inch.</p>
        <p>Builders of mercury-mirror telescopes acknowledge that mercury vapor is toxic, but once a mirror is spinning, they say, the surface of the mercury is quickly oxidized by contact with air. Although the thin oxidized layer is just as reflective as the bare metal, it forms a barrier preventing the escape of poisonous vapor, and gas masks must be used only while a mirror is being started.</p>
        <p>To start a mirror, operators must turn it by hand until it is revolving at about the rate at which the motor operates. They then sweep the pool of heavy mercury at the bottom of the dish outward, until its surface stabilizes into a parabolic curve.</p>
        <p>The great weight of even a small quantity of mercury forces telescope builders to build extremely strong mirror shells, but Dr. Borra and his associates are experimenting with lighter liquid metals requiring less dish strength. One candidate is liquid gallium.</p>
        <p>In an article last year in Scientific American, Dr. Borra said that one day astronomers may build gigantic and relatively cheap liquid-metal telescopes on the moon, using special liquid metal alloys with very low freezing points.</p>
        <p>"The point of all this work is to bring down the cost of astronomy," he said, "and we're making rapid progress."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
