<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="768370"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DB1031F932A25755C0A963958260" item-length="4512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>a opinionated giode to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. To submit items for consideration,write to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y., 10036, or send a fax to (212) 552-7219 MUSIC BEACH FEST '95 A nonstop weekend festival of free music on the Boardwalk in Atlantic City with the New Rascals, the Drifters, Shirley Alston Reeves, and Harold Melvin and the Blue Notes. Friday at 9 P.M., Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 7 P.M. Free. Atlantic City's Boardwalk. (609) 484-0920. CALDWELL COLLEGE ALUMINI THEATER The Center for Italian and Italian-American Culture presents a special Father's Day program featuring Theresa Pezzano Siegert, soprano, in "Songs My Father Taught Me and Other Arias From Great Italian Operas." Friday at 7:30 P.M. Ryerson Avenue, Caldwell. (201) 812-0433. CONGRESS HALL, CAPE MAY The Cape May Festival Pops Orchestra presents a concert today at 2 P.M. and an evening performance at 8:30. The New York Chamber Ensemble, Tuesday at 8:30 P.M. The Cape May Festival Orchestra, Thursday at 8:30 P.M. The American Boy Choir, next Sunday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. CONNECTICUT FARMS ELEMENTARY SCHOOL The Union Symphony Orchestra presents its summer concert featuring the works of Brahms, Bach and others. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $8 or $5 for students and the elderly. 711 Stuyvesant Avenue, Union. (908) 851-6476. FIRST UNITED METHODIST CHURCH "Music for Violin, Clarinet, and Piano," a concert performed by Anakay Koshka, Howard Meltzer and Christine Todd. Today at 4 P.M. Free. Burton and Division Avenues, Hasbrouck Heights. (201) 288-4636. HARDING ELEMENTARY SCHOOL The Philharmonic Orchestra of New Jersey presents its second annual "Music Gardens" concert. Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $50. Lee's Hill Road, New Vernon. (908) 356-6165. KASSACHAU MEMORIAL SHELL Trattoria Fratelli, an Italian restaurant, sponsors "Opera in the Park," featuring highlights from "Rigoletto," "La Boheme" and "Carmen." Next Sunday at 7 P.M. Free. North Maple Avenue, Ridgewood. (201) 447-9377. MEADOWLANDS ARENA Melissa Etheridge. Friday at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $35 and $50. The Grateful Dead, next Sunday at 6 P.M. and next Monday at 7 P.M. Tickets; $35 and $50. 50 Route 120, East Rutherford. (201) 935-3900. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM Sarah Partridge performs as part of the Montclair Art Museum's annual jazz concert. Next Sunday at 4 P.M. Tickets: $12. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. MONTCLAIR HIGH SCHOOL The Montclair High School Band Boosters will present a jazz concert with Oliver Lake, Reggie Workman, Steve Turre, Chris White and Steve Colson. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10 or $3 for children. 140 Park Street, Montclair. (201) 783-8344. NEWARK MUSEUM The Newark Boys Chorus presents a concert of classics, pop and ethnic music. Today at 3 P.M. Free. The Billy Johnson Auditorium. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6638. OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS The Kingston Trio. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035. RIDGEWOOD CONCERT BAND A concert with Myra Garcia-Fernandez, soprano, and Rick White, trumpeter. Today at 7 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Benjamin Franklin Middle School, Glen and Van Dien Streets. (201) 265-6174. RIDER UNIVERSITY The Westminster Community Orchestra, conducted by Barbara Barstow, presents a pops concert today at 7 P.M. Tickets: $5. Richardson Auditorium, Alexander Hall on the campus of Princeton University, Princeton. (609) 921-7104, ext. 260. SOCLAIR MUSIC FESTIVAL The 20th season begins with an anniversary celebration titled "Bach 'n' All." Today 4 P.M. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. Soclair Brooks Farm, 19 Haytown Road, Lebanon. (908) 236-6476. SUMMERFEST '95 CONCERTS The Tim Gillis Band. Today at 3 P.M. Free. Schooleys Mountain Park, West Springstown Road, Washington Township. (201) 326-7600. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER Jennie Avila and Amy Torchia will sing, play guitar and conga drums in a concert next Sunday at 7 P.M. in the last of the Center's Sunday night series this season. Tickets: $8. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF CLIFTON THe Council Contemporary Club, a group of singers and dancers, presents its annual music show, "Smile, Darn You, Smile." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $2. 199 Scoles Avenue, Clifton. (201) 799-2980. Theater BRUNDAGE PARK PLAYHOUSE "Les Liaisons Dangereuses," by Christopher Hampton. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Through June 17. Tickets: $10. Carrell Road, Randolph. (201) 989-7092. CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire," with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341. JOHN HARMS THEATER John Amos stars in "Halley's Comet." Today at 3 and 7 P.M. Tickets: $30 and $50. 30 North Van B runt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. McCARTER THEATER "Random Acts '95," the second annual festival of new plays presents "A Park in Our House," by Nilo Cruz. Today at 8 P.M., Monday through Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Saturday at 9 P.M. and next Sunday at 7:30 P.M. Staged readings of one-act plays by Wendy Wasserstein, Joyce Carol Oates, Mac Wellman and Jane Anderson will be presented today at 2 P.M., Saturday at 5 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $18. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. MODERN JEWISH REPERTORY THEATER "Two," by Ron Elisha. Today at 2 and 7 P.M. Tickets: $25. Blooming Grove Theater, 544 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 325-8154. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL Harold Pinter's "The Homecoming." Starts Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M. Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-5600. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE "The Secret Garden," a musical by Marsha Norman and Lucy Simon based on the novel by Frances Hodgson Burnett. Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 23. Tickets: $29 to $44. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. PARSIPPANY PLAYHOUSE "Run for Your Wife." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 18. Tickets: $10, or $7 for students and the elderly. 130 Knoll Road, Lake Hiawatha. (201) 263-7020. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY The Celtic Theater Company presents John B. Keane's "Sharon's Grave." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $9, or $7 for students and the elderly. 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (201) 761-9790. SMALL TOWN AND FANCY PLAYERS "The Fantasticks," presented by the Mahwah High School Drama Club. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Mahwah High School, Ridge Road. (201) 529-4909. SOMERSET VALLEY PLAYHOUSE "Inherit the Wind." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $10 on Friday and Sunday; $12 on Saturday. Route 514, Amwell Road, Hillsborough. (908) 369-7469. STRAND THEATER "Ravensbruck," a suspense drama set during World War II. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15 and $18. Fourth Street and Clifton Avenue, Lakewood. (908) 367-9595. Museums and Galleries ARTWORKS Paintings of Dante's "Inferno," by Eric Fowler. Thursday, Friday and Saturday through June 24. Thursday and Friday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. 19 Everrett Alley, Trenton. (609) 394-9436. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. Through Aug. 10. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Summer Daze," an exhibit of works by all members of the Center. Starts Thursday with an opening reception on FRiday from 7:30 to 10 P.M. Through August 20. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Tangible Insites," textural paintings and clay vessels by Susan Hogan. Opening reception today from 2 to 8 P.M. Through July 1. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CS SCHULTE GALLERIES "Duet: Dan Christensen -- 30 Years of Paintings, Elaine Grove -- Recent Sculpture." Through July 14. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 340 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 376-6900. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007. EXTENSION GALLERY "Hug the Noise," an exhibition of cast metal sculpture and drawings by Sean Poreda. Through June 29. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777. GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Through July 1. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Displacement," a collage by Peter Jacobs, and "Home," a collage done in mixed media are on display. Starts with an opening reception today, 3 to 5 P.M. Through June 28. Tuesday and Wednesday, 6 to 8 P.M., Thursday, 10 A.M. to noon and 6 to 8 P.M. Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. GUILD OF CREATIVE ART "Rhythms of Nature," a collection of landscapes, watercolors, pastels and collages by Fran McIlvain. Through July 6. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 4:30 P.M. 620 Broad Street, Route 35, Shrewsbury. (908) 741-1441. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Through June 25. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. JAZZ 88 GALLERY Paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880. J. RICHARDS GALLERY Oil paintings of faraway beaches, old Paris streets and landscapes of the French countryside by J. P. Dubord are on display. Through June 26. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 64 East Palisade Avenue, Englewood. (201) 871-1050. LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photgraphs by H. Lisa Solon. Through June 29. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "From Darkness Into Light," paintings and drawings by Howard Lerner. Through June 30. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 939-6969. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the papermaking town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through Today. Admission: $3, or $2 for the elderly. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College, 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through June 25. "Still Life Works From the Collection" offers 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found," an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimensional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through July 2. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through July 2. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through today. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through next Sunday. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Renee Foosaner Art Gallery holds its Sixth Annual Juried Exhibition of Miniature Art. Starts Wednesday. Through July 30. Opening reception on Monday, 6 to 9 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636, extension 2272. PATERSON MUSEUM "Pencilworks: The Drawings of Jerry Winick" displays pencil drawings noted for their details and photo-like realism. Through July 9. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 12:30 to 4:30 P.M. 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 881-3874. PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The Passaic County Cultural and Heritage Council presents paintings and collages by Arnold Brown. Starts Tuesday; opening reception on Friday, 6 to 8 P.M. Through July 20. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-5448. PINE SHORES ART ASSOCIATION Spring Art Show, featuring the works of members and local artists. Through June 21. Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 3:30 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 3:30 P.M. 94 Stafford Avenue, Manahawkin. (609) 597-3557. RABBET GALLERY "Five Sculptors: Clay, Wood, Metal." Through July 7. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. 120 Georges Road, New Brunswick. (908) 828-5150. SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "New Insights -- Rising Talent," an exhibition of the work of John Bingham, glass craftsman; Andrew Braitman, painter, and Lisa Gralnick, metal- smith. Through July 8. Monday through Wednesday and Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Thursday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720. SHOESTRING GALLERY "Hung Up," paintings and sculptures by Bill Barrell. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Naturescape," an exhibition of paintings by Christina Allen, Sarah Antin and Guy Ciarcia. Starts Saturday with a reception from 1:30 to 3:30 P.M. Through July 22. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592. SWAIN GALLERIES "Recent Works" in oils by Brian Townsend. Opening reception on Friday from 7 to 9 P.M. Through July 20. Tuesday through Friday, 9:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M., Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. 703 Watchung Avenue, Planfield (908) 756-1707. UNTITLED (#130), LTD "Intro Art -- Children's Art Exhibit." Through June 25. Opening reception on Saturday, 2 to 6 P.M. Gallery hours: Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WILLIAMS GALLERY "The Changing Landscape: Contemporary Interpretations of Landscape Painting and Photography" by David Scott Leibowitz, Marlene Lenker and Rena Segal. Through July 8. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 8 Chamebers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-1142. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM More than 100 prints document "Printmaking in America" from 1960 to 1990. Drawn from private collections and museums around the country, the exhibition includes works by Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Roger Brown and others. Through next Sunday. Free. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. Spoken Word BELLEVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Linda Heimall, an opera singer, will give two lectures on opera: "The French Opera" on Wednesday at 1 P.M. and "Opera Becomes Real Verismo" on June 21. Free. 221 Washington Avenue, Belleville. (201) 450-3434. DELAWARE VALLEY POETS David Felder, Patricia Celley Groth and Judah Jacobowitz will read selected works. Monday at 8 P.M. Princeton Market Fair, Route 1 South, Princeton. (609) 874-3480. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Sherrie Cleary will present excerpts from "The Belle of Amherst," which focus on Emily Dickinson's school life, family relationships and her literary contributions. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FLAT ROCK BROOK NATURE ASSOCIATION Bob Suanders will demonstrate special recipes with wild foods such as greens, mushrooms, wild teas and herbs. Today at 1:30. Fee: $6. Advance registration is required. 443 Van Nostrand Avenue, Englewood. (201) 567-1265. MORRIS COUNTY PARK SYSTEMS The "Nature Through Garden's Gate" program will describe ways to attract hummingbirds and butterflies into gardens and ways to discourage undesirable insects. The focus will be on control by natural interaction. Today, 1 to 4 P.M. at the Cooper Mill. Free. County Route 513, Chester Township. (201) 326-7645. Nancy Goodwin, the owner of Montrose, will lecture on "the Gardens of Montrose," a private garden in Hillsborough, North Carolina. Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Admission: $5. 53 East Hahover Avenue, Morris Township. (201) 326-7603. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY Michael Adonia Moscovici, the Cultural Attache at the German Embassy in Brussels, Belgium, will speak on "German-Jewish Dialogue Today." Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Free. Duffy Hall Faculty Lounge. 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (201) 378-9838. SKYLANDS ASSOCIATION Margaret Dexter, a trained herbalist, present a lecture and workshop on 6 to 10 common plants which benefit our skin. Today at 3 P.M. A free plant clinic will offer advice on what to do if your hosta leaves have holes in them, if your your hemlock is showing signs of color loss and if there are tiny white insects crawling on your shrubs. Saturday from 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. The Carriage House at the New Jersey State Botanical Garden. Morris Road off Slatsburg Road, Ringwood. (201) 962-9534. SOMERSET MEDICAL CENTER A series of lectures on health and medicine by Dorothy L. Zufall includes "Remember This -- Improving Your Memory." Monday at 7 P.M. and Tuesday at 10 A.M. "Laughing Matters," regarding arthritis support. Wednesday at 7 P.M. and "Making Your Wishes Known." Thursday at 10 A.M. Advance registration required. 110 Rehill Avenue, Somerville. (908) 685-2200. For Children MARCELLA GELTMAN GALLERY The Art Center of Northern New Jersey sponsors the Annual Children's Art Show. Monday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 250 Center Street, New Milford. (201) 599-2992. MEADOW THEATER "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe." Saturday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M. and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Gingerbread Players present "Beauty and the Beast." Saturday and next Sunday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6 and $7. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC.  ANNUAL ROCKLAND COUNTY FAIR Rockland County Futures sponsors an 11-day and night celebration of Rockland County. On Thursday a "$25 Per Carload" includes free admission, free parking and unlimited rides on the fair ground. Friday is highlighted by a "Moonlight Madness" party at 10:30 P.M. Fireworks will light up the sky on Saturday. Through June 25. Anthony Wayne State Park, off exit 17 of the Palisades Interstate Parkway. (914) 358-2272. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through Saturday. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. COMMUNITY THEATER Paula Poundstone, comedian. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $25. 100 South Street, Morristown. (201) 539-8008. COUNTY COLLEGE OF MORRIS A Mini-foreign film festival with "Cafe Au Lait," on Friday, "The Revolt of Jon" on June 23 and "Sweetie" on June 30. All show times 8 P.M. Tickets: $3. Dragonetti Auditorium in the Student Center, 214 Center Grove Road, Randolph. (201) 328-5024. DINNER AND THEATER The $42 ticket price includes a four-course meal and "Deep Space Noir," an interactive and futuristic detective story. Saturdays, 8 P.M. Il Giardino Restaurant. 41 Ridgedale Avenue, Cedar Knolls. (201) 301-0562. GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER The 1995 Spring Heritage Festivals continues with the Jewish Festival of the Arts is next Sunday, starting at 10 A.M. with a stage show at 2 P.M. with Freddie Roman, comedian, and Michael Burstyn, singer. Tickets: $5 to $21. Exit 16 on the Garden State Park Way, Holmdel. ((908) 442-9200. GUARDIAN ANGEL CATHOLIC CHURCH The Wyckoff Lions Club presents its 29th Annual carnival with games of skill and shance, rides, giant slides, food, prizes and family fun. Today, 2 to 7 P.M. 320 Franklin Turnpike, Wyckoff. (201) 445-8200. INTERNATIONAL AUCTION AND FOOD FESTIVAL Area restaurants will lend some of their best dishes to this benefit for the Paper Mill Playhouse. For a contribution of $25, guests may stroll under large tents for a sampling of foods from participating restaurants and bid on a variety of items during a silent auction. Tuesday at 6 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636. JCC ON THE PALISADES "The New Season Cabaret," benefits the Jewish Community Center on the Pallisades with performances by Merwyn Goldsmith, Amelia Gold, Don Glaser, Jill Kotler and Derwyn Holden. Tickets: $15. 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 569-7900. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Vintage Market" has all types of vintage items: toys, antiques, table lines, housewares adn more. Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M. and Saturday 9 A.M. to 4 P.M. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL "To Live," Friday, "Ladybird, Ladybird," Saturday and "Latcho Drom," June 23. All show times 7 P.M. Tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, Milledoler Hall, George Street and Seminary Place. (908) 932-8482. POW-WOW AND FESTIVAL The Nanticoke Lenni-Lenape Indians present two full days of dancing, drumming, arts and crafts, foods and cultural exhibits in this 15th annual event. Today, 10 A.M. until 4 P.M. Admission: $5, or $2 for the elderly. Salem County Fair Grounds, Route 40, Woodstown. (609) 455-6910. RIDGEWOOD GARDEN TOUR The Women Gardeners of Ridgewood sponsor a tour of nine private gardens on Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Tickets: $20 which includes light refreshments. The Stable, 259 North Maple Avenue, Ridgewood. (201) 652-8046. RIVERFAIR Sounds of music will blend with International Foods, Art Show and Antique Show and Sale on the waterfront grounds of the Island Heights Boro Complex. The Garden State Philharmonic Youth Orchestra, the Garden State Philharmonic Chorus and "Brown" a rhythm and blues band will perform through out the day. Tickets: $10. A garden tour of six gardens will also be available. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. (908) 349-6277. UNITARIAN SOCIETY The Unitarian Montessori School will dedicate a peace pole at the Unitarian Society of New Brunswick. The peace pole is a handcrafted obelisk erected to spread the message "May peace prevail on earth." The message is inscribed in English, American Sign Language, Hebrew, and paw prints. Today at 1 P.M. Free. 176 Tices Lane, East Brunswick. (908) 246-0606.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>a opinionated giode to cultural and recreational goings-on around the state this week. To submit items for consideration,write to On the Towns, Sunday New Jersey Section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y., 10036, or send a fax to (212) 552-7219 MUSIC BEACH FEST '95 A nonstop weekend festival of free music on the Boardwalk in Atlantic City with the New Rascals, the Drifters, Shirley Alston Reeves, and Harold Melvin and the Blue Notes. Friday at 9 P.M., Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 7 P.M. Free. Atlantic City's Boardwalk. (609) 484-0920. CALDWELL COLLEGE ALUMINI THEATER The Center for Italian and Italian-American Culture presents a special Father's Day program featuring Theresa Pezzano Siegert, soprano, in "Songs My Father Taught Me and Other Arias From Great Italian Operas." Friday at 7:30 P.M. Ryerson Avenue, Caldwell. (201) 812-0433. CONGRESS HALL, CAPE MAY The Cape May Festival Pops Orchestra presents a concert today at 2 P.M. and an evening performance at 8:30. The New York Chamber Ensemble, Tuesday at 8:30 P.M. The Cape May Festival Orchestra, Thursday at 8:30 P.M. The American Boy Choir, next Sunday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. CONNECTICUT FARMS ELEMENTARY SCHOOL The Union Symphony Orchestra presents its summer concert featuring the works of Brahms, Bach and others. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $8 or $5 for students and the elderly. 711 Stuyvesant Avenue, Union. (908) 851-6476. FIRST UNITED METHODIST CHURCH "Music for Violin, Clarinet, and Piano," a concert performed by Anakay Koshka, Howard Meltzer and Christine Todd. Today at 4 P.M. Free. Burton and Division Avenues, Hasbrouck Heights. (201) 288-4636. HARDING ELEMENTARY SCHOOL The Philharmonic Orchestra of New Jersey presents its second annual "Music Gardens" concert. Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $50. Lee's Hill Road, New Vernon. (908) 356-6165. KASSACHAU MEMORIAL SHELL Trattoria Fratelli, an Italian restaurant, sponsors "Opera in the Park," featuring highlights from "Rigoletto," "La Boheme" and "Carmen." Next Sunday at 7 P.M. Free. North Maple Avenue, Ridgewood. (201) 447-9377. MEADOWLANDS ARENA Melissa Etheridge. Friday at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $35 and $50. The Grateful Dead, next Sunday at 6 P.M. and next Monday at 7 P.M. Tickets; $35 and $50. 50 Route 120, East Rutherford. (201) 935-3900. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM Sarah Partridge performs as part of the Montclair Art Museum's annual jazz concert. Next Sunday at 4 P.M. Tickets: $12. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. MONTCLAIR HIGH SCHOOL The Montclair High School Band Boosters will present a jazz concert with Oliver Lake, Reggie Workman, Steve Turre, Chris White and Steve Colson. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10 or $3 for children. 140 Park Street, Montclair. (201) 783-8344. NEWARK MUSEUM The Newark Boys Chorus presents a concert of classics, pop and ethnic music. Today at 3 P.M. Free. The Billy Johnson Auditorium. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6638. OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS The Kingston Trio. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035. RIDGEWOOD CONCERT BAND A concert with Myra Garcia-Fernandez, soprano, and Rick White, trumpeter. Today at 7 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Benjamin Franklin Middle School, Glen and Van Dien Streets. (201) 265-6174. RIDER UNIVERSITY The Westminster Community Orchestra, conducted by Barbara Barstow, presents a pops concert today at 7 P.M. Tickets: $5. Richardson Auditorium, Alexander Hall on the campus of Princeton University, Princeton. (609) 921-7104, ext. 260. SOCLAIR MUSIC FESTIVAL The 20th season begins with an anniversary celebration titled "Bach 'n' All." Today 4 P.M. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. Soclair Brooks Farm, 19 Haytown Road, Lebanon. (908) 236-6476. SUMMERFEST '95 CONCERTS The Tim Gillis Band. Today at 3 P.M. Free. Schooleys Mountain Park, West Springstown Road, Washington Township. (201) 326-7600. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER Jennie Avila and Amy Torchia will sing, play guitar and conga drums in a concert next Sunday at 7 P.M. in the last of the Center's Sunday night series this season. Tickets: $8. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF CLIFTON THe Council Contemporary Club, a group of singers and dancers, presents its annual music show, "Smile, Darn You, Smile." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $2. 199 Scoles Avenue, Clifton. (201) 799-2980. Theater BRUNDAGE PARK PLAYHOUSE "Les Liaisons Dangereuses," by Christopher Hampton. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Through June 17. Tickets: $10. Carrell Road, Randolph. (201) 989-7092. CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire," with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341. JOHN HARMS THEATER John Amos stars in "Halley's Comet." Today at 3 and 7 P.M. Tickets: $30 and $50. 30 North Van B runt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. McCARTER THEATER "Random Acts '95," the second annual festival of new plays presents "A Park in Our House," by Nilo Cruz. Today at 8 P.M., Monday through Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Saturday at 9 P.M. and next Sunday at 7:30 P.M. Staged readings of one-act plays by Wendy Wasserstein, Joyce Carol Oates, Mac Wellman and Jane Anderson will be presented today at 2 P.M., Saturday at 5 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $18. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. MODERN JEWISH REPERTORY THEATER "Two," by Ron Elisha. Today at 2 and 7 P.M. Tickets: $25. Blooming Grove Theater, 544 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 325-8154. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL Harold Pinter's "The Homecoming." Starts Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M. Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-5600. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE "The Secret Garden," a musical by Marsha Norman and Lucy Simon based on the novel by Frances Hodgson Burnett. Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 23. Tickets: $29 to $44. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. PARSIPPANY PLAYHOUSE "Run for Your Wife." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 18. Tickets: $10, or $7 for students and the elderly. 130 Knoll Road, Lake Hiawatha. (201) 263-7020. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY The Celtic Theater Company presents John B. Keane's "Sharon's Grave." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $9, or $7 for students and the elderly. 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (201) 761-9790. SMALL TOWN AND FANCY PLAYERS "The Fantasticks," presented by the Mahwah High School Drama Club. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Mahwah High School, Ridge Road. (201) 529-4909. SOMERSET VALLEY PLAYHOUSE "Inherit the Wind." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $10 on Friday and Sunday; $12 on Saturday. Route 514, Amwell Road, Hillsborough. (908) 369-7469. STRAND THEATER "Ravensbruck," a suspense drama set during World War II. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15 and $18. Fourth Street and Clifton Avenue, Lakewood. (908) 367-9595. Museums and Galleries ARTWORKS Paintings of Dante's "Inferno," by Eric Fowler. Thursday, Friday and Saturday through June 24. Thursday and Friday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. 19 Everrett Alley, Trenton. (609) 394-9436. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. Through Aug. 10. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Summer Daze," an exhibit of works by all members of the Center. Starts Thursday with an opening reception on FRiday from 7:30 to 10 P.M. Through August 20. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Tangible Insites," textural paintings and clay vessels by Susan Hogan. Opening reception today from 2 to 8 P.M. Through July 1. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CS SCHULTE GALLERIES "Duet: Dan Christensen -- 30 Years of Paintings, Elaine Grove -- Recent Sculpture." Through July 14. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 340 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 376-6900. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007. EXTENSION GALLERY "Hug the Noise," an exhibition of cast metal sculpture and drawings by Sean Poreda. Through June 29. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777. GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Through July 1. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Displacement," a collage by Peter Jacobs, and "Home," a collage done in mixed media are on display. Starts with an opening reception today, 3 to 5 P.M. Through June 28. Tuesday and Wednesday, 6 to 8 P.M., Thursday, 10 A.M. to noon and 6 to 8 P.M. Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. GUILD OF CREATIVE ART "Rhythms of Nature," a collection of landscapes, watercolors, pastels and collages by Fran McIlvain. Through July 6. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 4:30 P.M. 620 Broad Street, Route 35, Shrewsbury. (908) 741-1441. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Through June 25. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. JAZZ 88 GALLERY Paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880. J. RICHARDS GALLERY Oil paintings of faraway beaches, old Paris streets and landscapes of the French countryside by J. P. Dubord are on display. Through June 26. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 64 East Palisade Avenue, Englewood. (201) 871-1050. LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photgraphs by H. Lisa Solon. Through June 29. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "From Darkness Into Light," paintings and drawings by Howard Lerner. Through June 30. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 939-6969. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the papermaking town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through Today. Admission: $3, or $2 for the elderly. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College, 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through June 25. "Still Life Works From the Collection" offers 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found," an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimensional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through July 2. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through July 2. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through today. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through next Sunday. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Renee Foosaner Art Gallery holds its Sixth Annual Juried Exhibition of Miniature Art. Starts Wednesday. Through July 30. Opening reception on Monday, 6 to 9 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636, extension 2272. PATERSON MUSEUM "Pencilworks: The Drawings of Jerry Winick" displays pencil drawings noted for their details and photo-like realism. Through July 9. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 12:30 to 4:30 P.M. 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 881-3874. PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The Passaic County Cultural and Heritage Council presents paintings and collages by Arnold Brown. Starts Tuesday; opening reception on Friday, 6 to 8 P.M. Through July 20. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-5448. PINE SHORES ART ASSOCIATION Spring Art Show, featuring the works of members and local artists. Through June 21. Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 3:30 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 3:30 P.M. 94 Stafford Avenue, Manahawkin. (609) 597-3557. RABBET GALLERY "Five Sculptors: Clay, Wood, Metal." Through July 7. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. 120 Georges Road, New Brunswick. (908) 828-5150. SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "New Insights -- Rising Talent," an exhibition of the work of John Bingham, glass craftsman; Andrew Braitman, painter, and Lisa Gralnick, metal- smith. Through July 8. Monday through Wednesday and Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Thursday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720. SHOESTRING GALLERY "Hung Up," paintings and sculptures by Bill Barrell. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Naturescape," an exhibition of paintings by Christina Allen, Sarah Antin and Guy Ciarcia. Starts Saturday with a reception from 1:30 to 3:30 P.M. Through July 22. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592. SWAIN GALLERIES "Recent Works" in oils by Brian Townsend. Opening reception on Friday from 7 to 9 P.M. Through July 20. Tuesday through Friday, 9:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M., Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. 703 Watchung Avenue, Planfield (908) 756-1707. UNTITLED (#130), LTD "Intro Art -- Children's Art Exhibit." Through June 25. Opening reception on Saturday, 2 to 6 P.M. Gallery hours: Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WILLIAMS GALLERY "The Changing Landscape: Contemporary Interpretations of Landscape Painting and Photography" by David Scott Leibowitz, Marlene Lenker and Rena Segal. Through July 8. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 8 Chamebers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-1142. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM More than 100 prints document "Printmaking in America" from 1960 to 1990. Drawn from private collections and museums around the country, the exhibition includes works by Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Roger Brown and others. Through next Sunday. Free. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. Spoken Word BELLEVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Linda Heimall, an opera singer, will give two lectures on opera: "The French Opera" on Wednesday at 1 P.M. and "Opera Becomes Real Verismo" on June 21. Free. 221 Washington Avenue, Belleville. (201) 450-3434. DELAWARE VALLEY POETS David Felder, Patricia Celley Groth and Judah Jacobowitz will read selected works. Monday at 8 P.M. Princeton Market Fair, Route 1 South, Princeton. (609) 874-3480. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Sherrie Cleary will present excerpts from "The Belle of Amherst," which focus on Emily Dickinson's school life, family relationships and her literary contributions. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FLAT ROCK BROOK NATURE ASSOCIATION Bob Suanders will demonstrate special recipes with wild foods such as greens, mushrooms, wild teas and herbs. Today at 1:30. Fee: $6. Advance registration is required. 443 Van Nostrand Avenue, Englewood. (201) 567-1265. MORRIS COUNTY PARK SYSTEMS The "Nature Through Garden's Gate" program will describe ways to attract hummingbirds and butterflies into gardens and ways to discourage undesirable insects. The focus will be on control by natural interaction. Today, 1 to 4 P.M. at the Cooper Mill. Free. County Route 513, Chester Township. (201) 326-7645. Nancy Goodwin, the owner of Montrose, will lecture on "the Gardens of Montrose," a private garden in Hillsborough, North Carolina. Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Admission: $5. 53 East Hahover Avenue, Morris Township. (201) 326-7603. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY Michael Adonia Moscovici, the Cultural Attache at the German Embassy in Brussels, Belgium, will speak on "German-Jewish Dialogue Today." Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Free. Duffy Hall Faculty Lounge. 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (201) 378-9838. SKYLANDS ASSOCIATION Margaret Dexter, a trained herbalist, present a lecture and workshop on 6 to 10 common plants which benefit our skin. Today at 3 P.M. A free plant clinic will offer advice on what to do if your hosta leaves have holes in them, if your your hemlock is showing signs of color loss and if there are tiny white insects crawling on your shrubs. Saturday from 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. The Carriage House at the New Jersey State Botanical Garden. Morris Road off Slatsburg Road, Ringwood. (201) 962-9534. SOMERSET MEDICAL CENTER A series of lectures on health and medicine by Dorothy L. Zufall includes "Remember This -- Improving Your Memory." Monday at 7 P.M. and Tuesday at 10 A.M. "Laughing Matters," regarding arthritis support. Wednesday at 7 P.M. and "Making Your Wishes Known." Thursday at 10 A.M. Advance registration required. 110 Rehill Avenue, Somerville. (908) 685-2200. For Children MARCELLA GELTMAN GALLERY The Art Center of Northern New Jersey sponsors the Annual Children's Art Show. Monday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 250 Center Street, New Milford. (201) 599-2992. MEADOW THEATER "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe." Saturday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M. and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Gingerbread Players present "Beauty and the Beast." Saturday and next Sunday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6 and $7. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC.  ANNUAL ROCKLAND COUNTY FAIR Rockland County Futures sponsors an 11-day and night celebration of Rockland County. On Thursday a "$25 Per Carload" includes free admission, free parking and unlimited rides on the fair ground. Friday is highlighted by a "Moonlight Madness" party at 10:30 P.M. Fireworks will light up the sky on Saturday. Through June 25. Anthony Wayne State Park, off exit 17 of the Palisades Interstate Parkway. (914) 358-2272. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through Saturday. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. COMMUNITY THEATER Paula Poundstone, comedian. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $25. 100 South Street, Morristown. (201) 539-8008. COUNTY COLLEGE OF MORRIS A Mini-foreign film festival with "Cafe Au Lait," on Friday, "The Revolt of Jon" on June 23 and "Sweetie" on June 30. All show times 8 P.M. Tickets: $3. Dragonetti Auditorium in the Student Center, 214 Center Grove Road, Randolph. (201) 328-5024. DINNER AND THEATER The $42 ticket price includes a four-course meal and "Deep Space Noir," an interactive and futuristic detective story. Saturdays, 8 P.M. Il Giardino Restaurant. 41 Ridgedale Avenue, Cedar Knolls. (201) 301-0562. GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER The 1995 Spring Heritage Festivals continues with the Jewish Festival of the Arts is next Sunday, starting at 10 A.M. with a stage show at 2 P.M. with Freddie Roman, comedian, and Michael Burstyn, singer. Tickets: $5 to $21. Exit 16 on the Garden State Park Way, Holmdel. ((908) 442-9200. GUARDIAN ANGEL CATHOLIC CHURCH The Wyckoff Lions Club presents its 29th Annual carnival with games of skill and shance, rides, giant slides, food, prizes and family fun. Today, 2 to 7 P.M. 320 Franklin Turnpike, Wyckoff. (201) 445-8200. INTERNATIONAL AUCTION AND FOOD FESTIVAL Area restaurants will lend some of their best dishes to this benefit for the Paper Mill Playhouse. For a contribution of $25, guests may stroll under large tents for a sampling of foods from participating restaurants and bid on a variety of items during a silent auction. Tuesday at 6 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636. JCC ON THE PALISADES "The New Season Cabaret," benefits the Jewish Community Center on the Pallisades with performances by Merwyn Goldsmith, Amelia Gold, Don Glaser, Jill Kotler and Derwyn Holden. Tickets: $15. 411 East Clinton Avenue, Tenafly. (201) 569-7900. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Vintage Market" has all types of vintage items: toys, antiques, table lines, housewares adn more. Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M. and Saturday 9 A.M. to 4 P.M. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL "To Live," Friday, "Ladybird, Ladybird," Saturday and "Latcho Drom," June 23. All show times 7 P.M. Tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, Milledoler Hall, George Street and Seminary Place. (908) 932-8482. POW-WOW AND FESTIVAL The Nanticoke Lenni-Lenape Indians present two full days of dancing, drumming, arts and crafts, foods and cultural exhibits in this 15th annual event. Today, 10 A.M. until 4 P.M. Admission: $5, or $2 for the elderly. Salem County Fair Grounds, Route 40, Woodstown. (609) 455-6910. RIDGEWOOD GARDEN TOUR The Women Gardeners of Ridgewood sponsor a tour of nine private gardens on Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Tickets: $20 which includes light refreshments. The Stable, 259 North Maple Avenue, Ridgewood. (201) 652-8046. RIVERFAIR Sounds of music will blend with International Foods, Art Show and Antique Show and Sale on the waterfront grounds of the Island Heights Boro Complex. The Garden State Philharmonic Youth Orchestra, the Garden State Philharmonic Chorus and "Brown" a rhythm and blues band will perform through out the day. Tickets: $10. A garden tour of six gardens will also be available. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. (908) 349-6277. UNITARIAN SOCIETY The Unitarian Montessori School will dedicate a peace pole at the Unitarian Society of New Brunswick. The peace pole is a handcrafted obelisk erected to spread the message "May peace prevail on earth." The message is inscribed in English, American Sign Language, Hebrew, and paw prints. Today at 1 P.M. Free. 176 Tices Lane, East Brunswick. (908) 246-0606.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
