<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Good Earth Looks Better</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="756927"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">EASTERBROOK, GREGG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF153FF932A15757C0A963958260" item-length="1104" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Good Earth Looks Better</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gregg Easterbrook;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EASTERBROOK, GREGG</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tomorrow, on the 25th anniversary of Earth Day, I'll be smiling, and so should you. Nearly every ecological trend in the United States is positive. The air and water are getting cleaner and the forests are rebounding: a natural recovery of historic proportions may be at hand. The first Earth Day, in 1970, was a time for demonstrations and expressions of rage. Earth Day 1995 is a moment for celebration.</p>
        <p>In fact, Americans could treat the anniversary as marking one of the leading social achievements of our age, were it not for an outbreak of retrograde anti-environmentalism in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tomorrow, on the 25th anniversary of Earth Day, I'll be smiling, and so should you. Nearly every ecological trend in the United States is positive. The air and water are getting cleaner and the forests are rebounding: a natural recovery of historic proportions may be at hand. The first Earth Day, in 1970, was a time for demonstrations and expressions of rage. Earth Day 1995 is a moment for celebration.</p>
        <p>In fact, Americans could treat the anniversary as marking one of the leading social achievements of our age, were it not for an outbreak of retrograde anti-environmentalism in Washington.</p>
        <p>The House, under Speaker Newt Gingrich, in February enacted a spectacularly wrong-headed bill designed to make antipollution rules close to unenforceable; now it is moving toward legislation that would dismantle the Endangered Species and Clean Water acts. In the Senate, majority leader Bob Dole has proposed anti-environmental legislation that in some ways is more callous that the House bill.</p>
        <p>Strangely, these anti-environmental initiatives have been made possible partly by fashionable environmental doomsaying on the left. If it were commonly understood that most conservation programs are effective and affordable, initiatives to gut those programs would outrage voters. But because the good news about the environment is a well-kept secret, Gingrich, Dole &amp; Company can get away with proposing to clobber programs that voters falsely believe don't work anyway.</p>
        <p>What trends are positive in the United States? Since 1970, smog is down by more than 30 percent, even as the number of cars has soared. In 1970, one-third of rivers and lakes were safe for fishing and swimming; today, two-thirds are. Most forested areas have been expanding, not contracting. Municipal wastes going to landfills peaked in 1988 and have been declining since then, as recycling has taken hold. Ocean dumping of sludge has ended; land-filling of untreated chemical wastes has ended; most emissions of chlorofluorocarbons (the chemicals that deplete the ozone layer) have ended; endangered species such as the bald eagle and gray whale have made spectacular recoveries; pesticide use is declining, relative to agricultural production.</p>
        <p>Such progress hardly means environmental challenges have been overcome. Numerous ecological emergencies exist in the developing world. In the West, problems such as overfishing and the prospect of global warming have yet to inspire much-needed reforms.</p>
        <p>But the main source of environmental trepidation ought not to be the conditions in nature but on Capitol Hill. There Mr. Gingrich, Mr. Dole, Senator Slade Gorton, Representatives Thomas DeLay and Bud Shuster and others are attempting to undermine the very laws that made possible the good news.</p>
        <p>Of course many environmental strictures are flawed. They may contain economic disincentives, regulatory overkill and other defects. Initially Mr. Gingrich and Mr. Dole and others said they wanted to inject clear thinking and free-market mechanisms into regulation of the ecology. These are excellent goals. But instead of seeking constructive revisions, Congressional conservatives, with the help of industry lobbyists and lawyers, are now attacking environmental programs indiscriminately, seeking to undo all programs whether good or bad.  Among their many faults, regulatory-reform bills passed in the House, and proposed by Mr. Dole in the Senate, suggest that every environmental issue contains a discernible scientific resolution now ignored by bureaucrats intent on red tape. It is true that environmental initiatives would benefit from more scientific inquiry, but the notion that scientists agree about environmental questions is a fantasy.</p>
        <p>For instance, the Supreme Court recently reviewed reams of differing scientific opinions about whether the ash from municipal waste incinerators is hazardous, then essentially ruled that the science was irrelevant. And the chemistry of incinerator ash is a simple, straightforward matter compared to complex questions such as the greenhouse effect and preservation of habitats.</p>
        <p>As Philip K. Howard points out in his excellent book "The Death of Common Sense," laws demanding a precise scientific answer as a basis for regulation have amounted to geysers of hot air, generating interminable lawsuits but little action. Conservatives know that and have worded the science clauses of anti-environment bills to create gridlock. This is pure cynicism, if only because it gives the valid aspects of rational environmental reform a bad name.</p>
        <p>The embrace of the anti-environment bills by business may well threaten the progress of recent years, not to mention business's hard-won environmental credibility. Until the new Congress began, all signs seemed encouraging.</p>
        <p>Since 1988, the toxic emissions of American industry have declined more than 35 percent, even as production of petrochemicals has increased. Many major companies have found pollution controls much cheaper than expected, and as a result are doing more than the law requires. As recently as January, Earnest Deavenport, chairman of the Eastman Chemical Company and of the Chemical Manufacturers Association, said the association's members "now accept that strict environmental regulation is necessary" and "do not want to turn back the clock."</p>
        <p>Yet within a month association lobbyists were warmly endorsing anti-environmental bills like the one that the House passed in February. Has all the apparent progress in the chemical industry been merely a public-relations ploy? The logging industry, whose recent record in adopting sustainable-forestry practices seems admirable, recently embraced a bill that would make a mockery of the Endangered Species Act. Suddenly, sensing blood on Capitol Hill, much of industry is turning regressive.</p>
        <p>With the exception of the mess in Washington, most news regarding the environment conveys hope -- hope for the planet and, possibly, hope for the human prospect itself.  Two centuries ago, the thinkers of the European Enlightenment dreamed that one day the study of nature would reveal messages of enduring value to society. The environmental pessimism of the postwar era seemed to give up that promise: a weak, doomed nature could hardly find much worth knowing.</p>
        <p>But perhaps if the environment is not doomed, it may be understood as a source of wisdom after all. The initial, halting attempts of Western society to create environment-protection programs suggest that mankind and nature eventually can become allies. That is the brightest and greatest hopes of this, the first happy Earth Day.  Gregg Easterbrook is author of "A Moment on the Earth: The Coming Age of Environmental Optimism."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gregg Easterbrook is author of "A Moment on the Earth: The Coming Age of Environmental Optimism."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
