<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From: The Mystic River Foundry; Where to Be an Artist, Athlete and Engineer, All at Once</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="769740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">METALS AND MINERALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MACHINERY AND EQUIPMENT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MYSTIC RIVER FOUNDRY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATTISTA, CAROLYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BORGES, PHYLLIS BROOKS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D8153EF93BA25755C0A963958260" item-length="1132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From: The Mystic River Foundry; Where to Be an Artist, Athlete and Engineer, All at Once</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BATTISTA, CAROLYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the Mystic River Foundry in Mystic, three women tackle the work of shoveling sand, making molds, melting metals, cleaning castings and smashing the occasional whisky bottle. It's a kind of work that few places do anymore, and that none of the three -- including the foundry owner, Phyllis Brooks Borges, who is 70 -- ever expected to do.</p>
        <p>"It's very much of a lost art, the way we do it here," Ms. Borges said. "Most foundries today do machine molding. We're one of the few left that can do 'loose' molding -- carving in the sand." Modern "production-type" foundries, she said, don't have the time, equipment or trained personnel to such work. She held up a piece from an old steam engine, with a little bit missing. "We put this broken piece in the sand and made a mold," she explained. "We carved out the piece that was missing; we recreated the shape of the piece."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the Mystic River Foundry in Mystic, three women tackle the work of shoveling sand, making molds, melting metals, cleaning castings and smashing the occasional whisky bottle. It's a kind of work that few places do anymore, and that none of the three -- including the foundry owner, Phyllis Brooks Borges, who is 70 -- ever expected to do.</p>
        <p>"It's very much of a lost art, the way we do it here," Ms. Borges said. "Most foundries today do machine molding. We're one of the few left that can do 'loose' molding -- carving in the sand." Modern "production-type" foundries, she said, don't have the time, equipment or trained personnel to such work. She held up a piece from an old steam engine, with a little bit missing. "We put this broken piece in the sand and made a mold," she explained. "We carved out the piece that was missing; we recreated the shape of the piece."</p>
        <p>The foundry's products include machine parts, boat fittings, decorative architectural work, plaques and pieces of sculpture in aluminum, brass and bronze. Among its customers are manufacturing companies, architects and artists; people who restore things (from old trains to old houses) and people who break things -- like one young man who took out his father's yacht, damaged the rudder and had to get it fixed before his father got home. The clock face on New Haven City Hall, sculpture at the New London Public Library and plaques on the Mystic River drawbridge all came from the foundry.</p>
        <p>Every casting starts with a pattern, either an incomplete original piece, like the steam engine part, or a complete pattern that represents exactly what the customer needs. "Every pattern deserves its own attention as to how to mold it," said Sherry Eastwood Hertzler, who does the molding, often intricate, in prepared silica sand. Each mold gets filled with molten metal; after the metal solidifies, the mold is broken, and the casting is retrieved and cleaned.</p>
        <p>Phoebe Berlepsch, a co-worker, said, "You have to be an artist, an athlete and an engineer, all in the same breath." You also need to know that "cope" and "drag" are parts of a mold, and that you should smash a whisky bottle into a crucible where you're going to melt red bronze. "The glass melts and floats to the top; it makes a cover," said Ms. Borges, explaining that the cover keeps out impurities that red bronze would pick up from the air, and that clear whisky bottles have good glass.</p>
        <p>In 1960 she didn't know such things. She'd worked as an X-ray technician, served during World War II in the Women's Land Army (which kept farms going while the men were away) and studied art. "I'd never set foot in a foundry," she said. "I was doing some sculpture, and I brought a piece here to be cast." She became enamored, she said, of the foundry's work, with different shapes and materials. "I couldn't stay away," said Ms. Borges, who began working for the owner, Eliot M. Borges, whom she married. She and her husband, who'd started the foundry in 1952, ran it together until his death in 1980. She's carried on, but she stressed that she hasn't been alone. She's had capable workers, both men and women, most of whom trained at her foundry.</p>
        <p>At 24, Ms. Hertzler needed a job; her father, who knew Ms. Borges's father, suggested she apply at the foundry. Now, she said: "I'm 43. My kids are 18, 15, 12 and 7; I worked here before I had them and in between."</p>
        <p>Ms. Berlepsch, who's 24, arrived three years ago, after listening to foundry employees who ate lunch at the shop where she made sandwiches. She felt prepared for foundry work. "I'd built stone walls, so I was used to getting sweaty and dirty," she said. Ms. Borges said that Ms. Berlepsch has learned fast -- at a place where mostly, everybody does everything, from fielding phone calls to cleaning castings.</p>
        <p>On a recent day Ms. Berlepsch shoveled sand into a muller, where big blades would mix it with clay, water and a little oil. "It comes out like this," said Ms. Borges, offering a damp clump. Next the sand would go through the riddle, a large electric sifter; then it would be ready for molding.</p>
        <p>To make a mold, Ms. Hertzler starts with the bottom half, called the drag. She puts the pattern in a molding box, then rams the sand against the pattern, using an air rammer, a hand rammer (resembling a potato masher) or both. Meanwhile she dusts parting compound onto surfaces that mustn't stick.</p>
        <p>When a drag is completed, it's time for the roll, turning the drag upside down, so Ms. Hertzler can put the cope on top of it and ram the top part of the pattern. (The pattern may have one piece or two; either way, the two parts of the mold will form one complete casting.) If the mold is big and heavy, the roll takes two people. In each mold, Ms. Hertzler must also include a pouring basin, a sprue for the metal to enter, a trough-like runner, and gates that channel the metal into the casting. Some castings require extra risers, insulated sleeves in which metal stays fluid longer. A casting can sink as it cools and the sleeves keep molten metal to feed it.</p>
        <p>Some projects,-- like a fragile, fish-shaped wall piece recently done for an artist, require sand that's mixed with sodium silicate, then gassed during molding. After ramming the fish mold, Ms. Hertzler took an ice pick from her pile of tools and poked holes in the sand. Then she injected each hole with carbon dioxide. "That's what sets the sand; it has a chemical reaction with it," she said.</p>
        <p>When the cope and drag are completed, they're separated, and the pattern is removed. Then the halves are rejoined, and the mold is clamped and weighted. It's ready for pouring. Later the snagging process, which can involve everything from the bandsaw to dental tools, will remove all extraneous items, like risers and gates. "In a minute, I'll saw off the risers," said Ms. Borges, eyeing some castings.</p>
        <p>To take molten metal out of the furnace and pour it into molds, the women don respirators and protective aprons, gloves and visors. They place giant tongs on the blazing hot crucible and, aided by the hoist on the crane, lift the metal from the fiery furnace. Taking the handles of a carrying device, two guide the crucible over to the molds, where they tilt it and pour. The third person skims off impurities and, if the crucible is extra heavy, hangs onto the back of it with a hook, so it won't tip too far, too fast.</p>
        <p>A few years ago Ms. Borges sold the foundry. "I went home to do some sculpture and painting," she said. But the buyer ran into difficulties and couldn't make payments to her, so she resumed ownership. "I came back to build it back," she said. "That was my dream, to keep it going." But she'd still like to sell the foundry. After all, she said, "The sculpture still waits to be done."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
