<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="787752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DE1E3DF933A2575AC0A963958260" item-length="678" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-12  A NEW SHIFT ON GLOBAL WARMING  In a major shift, experts advising the world's governments on climate change are saying for the first time that human activity is a likely cause of global warming.  1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-12  A NEW SHIFT ON GLOBAL WARMING  In a major shift, experts advising the world's governments on climate change are saying for the first time that human activity is a likely cause of global warming.  1</p>
        <p>ANTI-GAY CAMPAIGN IN ZIMBABWE  Life is getting more complicated for homosexuals in Zimbabwe, where President Mugabe has recently embarked on a campaign of words against those he calls "sodomists and perverts." 3  CHINA DEFENDS RECORD ON WOMEN  In an apparent response to criticism of China's human rights record by the West, Beijing asserted that women enjoy more personal safety and greater opportunities in China than in the U.S.  10  CRITICS PRESS YELTSIN ON NATO  Nationalists, Communists and some moderates in the Russian Parliament demanded that President Yeltsin suspend Russia's cooperation agreement with NATO because of its bombing in Bosnia.  12  SERBS SAY NATO KILLED CIVILIANS  Bosnian Serbs said a shell fired by U.N. troops killed 10 people and injured 22 at a hospital in a suburb of Sarajevo patrolled by Serbs.  12  Europe and the U.S. send aid to the hurricane-torn Caribbean. 4  Islamic militants in Libya clashed with Qaddafi's forces. 6  An I.R.A. leader reaffirmed he would consider disarmament. 9  National 18-44  MEDICARE PROPOSALS EXPECTED  House Republicans will unveil detailed proposals next week to slow the growth of Medicare and encourage elderly people to join health maintenance organizations.  1  A RARE LOOK INSIDE THE SENATE  The diaries and documents that drove Senator Bob Packwood from office offer a rare record of how a Senator can come to rely on lobbyists, influence peddlers and money raisers for friendship, counsel and political cash.1  THE GENERAL WRITES  In his forthcoming memoir, General Colin Powell writes on such diverse topics as the appeal of a third political party and the consideration of nuclear weapons during the Persian Gulf War.  1  'MISTAKE ON THE LAKE' NO MORE  The Cleveland Indians' division title, assuring the once-hapless team of its first post-season appearance in 41 years, is emblematic of the city's own continuing rebirth.  18  CLINTON PRODS ON WELFARE  President Clinton urged Congress not to let the debate on anti-poverty policies become a hostage to Presidential politics or a confrontation over the Federal budget.  28  A DEATH FOCUSES A DEBATE  The shooting of a homeless black man by an off-duty white police officer in Chicago has become the latest focus there of what is a national debate on justice, race, class and the police.  18  CHRISTIAN GATHERING CONCLUDES  The Christian Coalition ended its two-day conference with its leader declaring, "We have gained what we have always sought -- a place at the table" of national politics.  25  HURTING, OR HELPING, SMUGGLERS?  An effort to streamline Customs procedures at Miami International Airport is coping with concern that drug smugglers, already a fixture there, may be even more inclined to use it as a gateway.  38  Metropolitan 45-52  THE CHESS SUMMIT  Tomorrow afternoon, Gary Kasparov opens the fifth defense of his world chess title against Viswanathan Anand at the World Trade Center. It is likely to be the splashiest world championship ever.  1  HEALTH-CARE QUANDARY  As Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani embarks upon an overhaul of the municipal hospital system, the fate of uninsured and uninsurable patients presents a major quandary.  45  CRIME AGAINST IMMIGRANTS  Experts in Chinese smuggling say that a kidnapping and murder in Brooklyn may be the latest in what has become a new type of crime against Chinese immigrants.  45  DEAL SEEN ON LITTLE ITALY FEAST  Organizers of Little Italy's Feast of San Gennaro and city officials said they had all but reached an agreement for festival sponsors to open their books to an outside monitor hand-picked by Mayor Giuliani.  45  Obituaries 53  Jamie Whitten, former Democratic Congressman from Mississippi.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
