<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trying to Stem Emissions, U.S. Sees Its Goal Fading</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE AIR IN 2000 -- First of two articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSEEFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2D71039F93BA15752C1A963958260" item-length="2135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trying to Stem Emissions, U.S. Sees Its Goal Fading</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For every step the United States takes to cut emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases that scientists say are warming the earth's atmosphere, it seems to be slipping two steps back from its goal.</p>
        <p>Across the country, for instance, more than 1,100 companies have signed up to do as the American Express Company is doing at its 51-story headquarters in lower Manhattan. There, under an agreement with the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, the company has installed new energy-efficient lighting that  saves it up to 40 percent on electricity bills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For every step the United States takes to cut emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases that scientists say are warming the earth's atmosphere, it seems to be slipping two steps back from its goal.</p>
        <p>Across the country, for instance, more than 1,100 companies have signed up to do as the American Express Company is doing at its 51-story headquarters in lower Manhattan. There, under an agreement with the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, the company has installed new energy-efficient lighting that  saves it up to 40 percent on electricity bills.</p>
        <p>Using less electricity means burning less coal and oil, and therefore emitting less carbon dioxide. Through this simple expedient, American Express has cut annual emissions by about 3,300 tons all told in New York and five other cities.</p>
        <p>But a few miles away in Montclair, N.J., not long ago, vivid evidence of backsliding sat resplendently on the floor of Montclair-Bloomfield Motors: a red 1996 Ford Explorer, Eddie Bauer model, one of the gasoline-guzzling sport utility vehicles, vans, minivans and pickups made by all American car companies  whose surging popularity is reversing longtime advances in fuel efficiency. The  carbon dioxide emitted by about 700 Explorers -- less than half a day's production -- more than cancels out all of American Express's gains.</p>
        <p>Do customers ever ask about carbon dioxide emissions when shopping for an Explorer? "Not once," said Ed Goldstein, the business manager of the Ford agency. "Environment is probably last on the list."</p>
        <p>The net result of this sort of energy-use tug of war across the broader economy is that the United States is faltering in its effort to cut emissions to 1990 levels by the year 2000, as this country and other rich nations are pledged to do under a treaty signed at the 1992 United Nations conference on the environment in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration attributes the shortfall mainly to higher emissions brought about by unexpectedly strong economic growth and reduced energy prices. The Administration has promised to take stronger action if its initial actions prove insufficient, but the United States could fall even further behind if the Republican-run Congress carries out plans to cut up to 40  percent of the money used mainly to stimulate private investment in energy-saving measures.</p>
        <p>The Republicans display "great hostility" to the Administration's plan, Vice  President Al Gore, the driving force behind the policy, said in an interview. And indeed, the conservative Republican chairman of a House subcommittee that deals with environmental issues, Representative Dana Rohrabacher of California,  says concern about global warming may just be "liberal claptrap." Initial Effort Even Opening Step Is Falling Short</p>
        <p>This political byplay comes at a time when scientists around the world are more convinced than ever that emissions of carbon dioxide, the major contributor to the tons of carbon in the atmosphere, and certain other gases pose a serious  threat.</p>
        <p>A United Nations panel of scientists advising parties to the climate treaty,  in a draft report now undergoing final review, recently concluded for the first  time that human influences already have probably caused some warming of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The 2,500-member group, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, predicts that the warming will increase over the next century and beyond and that the resulting climate changes and rise in sea level are likely to cause widespread economic, social and environmental dislocation if greenhouse gas emissions are not reduced.</p>
        <p>Even before these latest findings, the 142 nations that are parties to the 1992 treaty had opened negotiations on stronger emissions-reduction measures. The aim of cutting emissions to 1990 levels by 2000 -- a nonbinding treaty goal  to which the United States and other rich countries have voluntarily subscribed  -- was never intended as anything more than a first step in a decades-long effort to deal with the risk of climate change.</p>
        <p>Going beyond the first step now appears more daunting than ever in view of the stumbling of not just the United States, but most other industrialized countries as well. Britain, Denmark, the Netherlands and Switzerland say they expect to reduce carbon dioxide emissions below 1990 levels by 2000, and Germany expects an 11 percent drop from 1990 levels by 2005. But eight other industrialized countries expect to join the United States, the world's leading emitter of carbon dioxide, in falling short of the treaty goal.</p>
        <p>It is a shaky initial example for the developing countries, which are not yet bound to any specific aims but whose emissions are expected to outstrip those of the rich nations in the decades ahead.</p>
        <p>The Administration's Climate Change Action Plan, adopted two years ago as an  executive branch policy, relies mostly on an array of voluntary measures by business, industry and homeowners to cut energy use and thereby carbon emissions. Its philosophy is exemplified by the program for stimulating investment in more efficient lighting, Green Lights, in which the Federal Government acts as catalyst, provider of reliable technical information and cheerleader.</p>
        <p>For instance, the Environmental Protection Agency recruited American Express  as a Green Lights participant. Because of the long-term savings in electricity bills, the company agreed. In another wrinkle of a sort encouraged by the Clinton plan, Consolidated Edison, the utility company, provided a one-time incentive rebate to American Express. The resulting energy savings by many such  Con Ed customers obviates the need for the utility to build new power plants, saving money and emissions.</p>
        <p>Green Lights began in the Bush Administration, and utilities in many parts of the country have been offering energy-saving incentives to businesses and consumers for some time, but both efforts are being expanded and encouraged under the Clinton plan. Companies now participating in or committed to Green Lights are expected to save 14.3 million tons of carbon dioxide a year, and the  E.P.A. projects annual savings of 44 million tons by 2000. More than $3 billion  in annual electric bill savings are also projected for 2000, along with a substantial reduction in other air pollutants.</p>
        <p>There is "really no downside," said Martin T. Warfel, an American Express vice president.</p>
        <p>Moderate Measures Indirect Approach To Emissions Cuts</p>
        <p>Many experts believe that these sort of "no regrets" measures are the way to  go in the near term: reducing carbon dioxide emissions through energy-efficiency measures that make sense for other reasons.  The experts do not agree on whether this will be enough to solve the problem in the long term.</p>
        <p>In view of scientists' uncertainty about how serious the climate problem is,  almost no one is advocating costly, Draconian action just yet, and no country has taken any.</p>
        <p>The Administration's plan outlines more than 50 measures, many patterned on the Green Lights approach. They include awarding "Energy Star" labels to energy-efficient office equipment, appliances and computers, planting more trees to absorb carbon dioxide, setting higher efficiency standards for home appliances, though Republican-sponsored legislation would place a moratorium on  them and reducing emissions of methane, the second most important greenhouse gas, from farms and leaky natural gas lines.</p>
        <p>Together the measures represent a long and varied menu of ways to reduce emissions. The plan projects a total Federal expenditure of less than $800 million from 1994 through 2000. This expenditure is designed to induce $60 billion in private investment over the same period, the fruits of which, the Administration calculates, would produce an annual reduction in total greenhouse gas emissions equivalent to nearly 440 million tons of carbon dioxide by 2000 -- and a cumulative total of nearly $286 billion in energy savings between 1994 and 2010.</p>
        <p>The emissions reduction, according to the Administration's original calculations, would bring total United States emissions back in line with the 1990 figure of something more than five billion tons of carbon-dioxide equivalent. But with faster economic growth and lower energy prices unexpectedly boosting emissions, Mr. Gore said, "we can fairly say" that the country will miss the 2000 target the way things are now going, even with no budget cuts.</p>
        <p>Tough Issue  Lack of Consensus On Motor Vehicles</p>
        <p>The glaring omission in the Administration's plan is its lack of any significant measure to rein in motor vehicle emissions, which account for a third of all the carbon dioxide spewed out and are growing faster than emissions from any other source.</p>
        <p>Perhaps made gun-shy by its early failure to secure Congressional passage of  an energy tax, the Administration included in the action plan only a few small measures to encourage less driving. It has proposed no gasoline tax or increase  in Federal gasoline mileage standards, the two measures most often advocated to  cut fuel use and emissions significantly.</p>
        <p>Instead, the Administration entered a yearlong discussion with the automotive and petroleum industries and environmentalists that broke up in September after  failing to reach a consensus. A major reason was opposition from industry to taxes or tightened gas mileage standards.</p>
        <p>The Administration is considering what to do next about motor vehicles. "We don't view it as that the problem is intractable or that solutions don't exist," Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>One possibility is to raise the mileage standard for light trucks -- pickups, sport utility vehicles, vans and minivans -- like the Explorer in Montclair. They have replaced station wagons as the big gas drinker in many driveways, wasting both power and fuel on short trips to school or supermarket.</p>
        <p>Light trucks average only 20 miles a gallon of gas, while passenger cars average 28, yet the trucks have now taken over 40 percent of the domestic market, causing overall fleet mileage to decline. At the same time, more miles are being driven. Theresult is that automotive carbon dioxide emissions continue to rise.</p>
        <p>But the prospects for raising the mileage standards are muddy at best, since  Republican-sponsored legislation would prevent any such action.</p>
        <p>The Administration is pinning many of its longer-term hopes on a collaboration between the Federal Government and the auto industry to develop, in the next decade, a prototype family-size car that would be three times as energy-efficient as today's.</p>
        <p>There is wide agreement that it is critical to invest now in research and development along a broad front, including eventual alternatives to fossil fuels, before the next long-term investment cycles lock in obsolete technology.</p>
        <p>In the case of the hoped-for "super car," some environmentalists note that the industry has not yet committed itself explicitly to producing any of the new vehicles. They say the project is an industry ploy to delay taking meaningful action on emissions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore disagreed, saying, "You can be certain that such a vehicle will be produced when the ability to make it is demonstrated." He said he had considerably more optimism about this project than about shorter-term efforts to reduce automotive emissions. The prototype should be ready within eight years, he said, "maybe before."</p>
        <p>In the meantime, political skirmishing over climate change continues. Representative Rohrabacher said last summer that he assumed global warming "at best, to be unproven and, at worst, to be liberal claptrap, trendy but soon to go out of style in our Newt Congress."</p>
        <p>In recent interviews, he said that after reading and hearing more about global warming, "I'm now even more inclined to think it's liberal claptrap," adding that "far too many people in the Government and media are far too willing to listen to and amplify any claim of doom by someone who's wearing a white coat."</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Gore said of the effort to reduce emissions that nobody "is under any illusions about how tough this is going to be."</p>
        <p>"It's at the outer boundary of what is possible in our world," he added, "but it is possible." As the evidence of climate change "inexorably accumulates," he  predicted, "the degree of difficulty in getting support for effective responses  will decline."</p>
        <p>The Air in 2000</p>
        <p>A future article will examine the looming effects on global warming posed by  China, with its vast coal reserves and rapid economic growth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
