<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE2D71039F93BA15752C1A963958260" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-19</p>
        <p>CLINTON SPEAKS ON BOSNIA President Clinton sought to build the case for sending 20,000 American troops on a peacekeeping mission to Bosnia. A1</p>
        <p>REPUBLICAN DIVISION News Analysis: A look at the prospects for action in Congress, where attitudes among Republicans range from isolationism to internationalism. A1</p>
        <p>Text of President Clinton's speech on Bosnia. A14</p>
        <p>Effects of lifting economic sanctions on Yugoslavia. A15</p>
        <p>TUSSLE OVER HAITIAN FILES After landing in Haiti last year, American troops seized more than 150,000 pages of documents from security forces. Now the new Haitian Government wants them back and Washington is stalling. A1</p>
        <p>AIDS MAKES INROADS IN CHINA The heroin plague that swept into China as the country opened its borders in the 1980's has brought with it the companion scourge of the AIDS virus. A3</p>
        <p>WINNIE MANDELA'S WOES Winnie Mandela, who has been battling creditors on several fronts lately, has narrowly escaped losing her furniture to them. A6</p>
        <p>ALGERIAN LEADER'S OVERTURE At his swearing in, Algeria's new President pointedly omitted Islamic militants in his invitation to a new "national dialogue.". A7</p>
        <p>WAYWARD FLYING OBJECT A derelict Chinese spy satellite weighing more than two tons is getting ready to plunge back to earth, which could create a hazard or an intelligence bonanza. A19</p>
        <p>ISRAELI-SYRIAN EXCHANGE Israel and Syria exchanged new signals of interest in renewing their stalled peace talks when their Foreign Ministers met at an international conference in Spain. A19</p>
        <p>Puerto Ayora Journal: Turmoil in the Galapagos Islands. A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A20-21, B8-10</p>
        <p>ELUSIVE ENVIRONMENTAL GOALS The United States pledged to cut emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases, but an energy-use tug-of-war across the economy is frustrating that efforts. A1</p>
        <p>FALLOUT FROM THE SIMPSON TRIAL The California Attorney General's office is investigating whether former Detective Mark Fuhrman committed perjury during the O. J. Simpson trial. A20</p>
        <p>NEW STRUGGLE FOR BLACK FARMERS The difficult life of black farmers may become more so as Republicans in Congress consider cutting a program that offers low-interest loans to minority farmers. A20</p>
        <p>GINGRICH RULES OUT CANDIDACY Newt Gingrich said he would neither seek the Presidency in 1996 nor soon endorse any of the Republican candidates. A21</p>
        <p>Wisconsin's Governor endorsed Sen. Bob Dole's candidacy. A21</p>
        <p>PRISONERS NO MORE A couple who had remained in prison on murder convictions even after someone else confessed to the crime were released. A21</p>
        <p>STUDENT'S APPEAL TURNED DOWN The Supreme Court turned down an appeal that argued that a teacher's refusal to accept a ninth grader's research paper on Jesus was discriminatory. B9</p>
        <p>RODNEY KING REDUX In a case similar to the notorious Rodney King beating in Los Angeles, three white police officers in suburban Pittsburgh were charged in the death of a black motorist with whom they scuffled. B10</p>
        <p>Metro Digest</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>QUESTIONS IN GIRL'S DEATH The death of Elisa Izquierdo has raised questions about whether the city made monthly visits to the girl's home, as ordered, before she died, apparently at the hands of an abusive mother. A1</p>
        <p>FUROR OVER FIREBOMBING Facing a chorus of criticism, Columbia Pictures declined to comment on whether its new picture, "The Money Train," inspired a token booth firebombing in a Brooklyn subway station. A1</p>
        <p>BALLOT RULES STRUCK DOWN A Federal judge in Brooklyn has struck down the Republican Party's strict rules for getting on the presidential ballot in New York State, handing a blow to Senator Bob Dole's political hopes. A1</p>
        <p>Science Times</p>
        <p>C1-12</p>
        <p>The Navy releases a wealth of secret environmental data. C1 A restoration project to help dams win new licenses. C1 A rare microbe survives very high doses of radiation. C1 The Doctor's World: Frustrated in trying to save doomed athlete. C3 Q&amp;A. C6 Personal Computers. C8 Peripherals. C11</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>B13-20</p>
        <p>Columns: Berkow on Reeves. B13 Rhoden on Rutgers. B15 Football: Reeves cites fans' influence. B13 Rutgers fires coach. B13 Hockey: Rangers tie Devils. B13 Marathon: Joan Benoit Samuelson's new priorities. B20 Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>C13-18</p>
        <p>Master classes. C13 Umberto Eco, word-bending wit. C13 Theater: "Golden Boy." C13 "The Warm-Up." C16 Dance: American Ballet Theater's outreach programs. C18 Books: New novel by Oscar Hijuelos. C17 Television: Teen-agers and survival on the street. C18 "New York the Way It Was: Brooklyn." C18</p>
        <p>Fashion Page</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>The power of couture photography.</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Bernard M. Oliver, founder of Hewlett-Packard Laboratories. John Craven, actor.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>Making the case on Bosnia. Training for police recruits. Susanna Rodell: The Clearwater.</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>A. M. Rosenthal: Yes, there is a Taiwan. James Webb: Remember the Nixon Doctrine. Marc Parent: For Elisa, more than the system failed.</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>C7</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>C17</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
