<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7D91339F931A25753C1A963958260" item-length="748" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>CEASE-FIRE IN THE BALKANS After many fits and false starts, the warring parties in the Balkans finally declared a cease-fire intended to end nearly four years of bloodletting in Bosnia. A1</p>
        <p>'ETHNIC CLEANSING' GOES ON A cessation of hostilities will have come too late for the victims of a new round of "ethnic cleansing" in northwestern Bosnia. A8</p>
        <p>DESPITE TALKS, AMAZON BURNS ON Three years after Brazil hosted the Earth Summit, shepherding ambitious international accords on biodiversity and climate change, burnings in the Amazon region appear to be worse than ever. A3</p>
        <p>RUSSIANS BUY FUR FOR A CHANGE Fur exports have slowed to a fraction as many Russians -- newly rich, profoundly ostentatious and hellbent on staying warm -- are buying fur as never before. A1</p>
        <p>TOKYO STIRS KOREA CONTROVERSY Tokyo raised new questions about Japanese contrition for past militarism by declaring that its annexation of Korea in 1910 was legal and was not forced on the Koreans. A5</p>
        <p>France's President is told to vacate his Paris apartment. A6</p>
        <p>Israeli troops evacuated a militant Palestinian stronghold. A7</p>
        <p>Lagos Journal: Nigerians wince at remarks by Colin Powell. A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A14-21, B6-7</p>
        <p>SIMPSON CANCELS INTERVIEW O. J. Simpson pulled out of a planned interview with NBC News, saying it posed potential problems for civil litigation he faces. A1</p>
        <p>REVERBERATIONS OF TAILHOOK The Navy officer appointed after the Tailhook scandal to head efforts to combat  sexual harassment is facing a court-martial on charges of sexually harassing two women who worked for him. A1</p>
        <p>DOCTORS WIN G.O.P. PLEDGE The American Medical Association received a commitment from House Republicans not to reduce Medicare payments to doctors, but the organization denied that the guarantee was payment for its endorsement of the measure. A1</p>
        <p>MEDICARE BILL ADVANCES The House Ways and Means Committee voted to send a disputed overhaul of the nation's Medicare system to the House floor for debate next week. A20 NOBELS FOR WORK ON OZONE Two Americans and a Dutch scientist won Nobel Prizes in chemistry for their work in explaining the processes that deplete the earth's protective ozone layer. A1</p>
        <p>Two Americans won the prize for physics. B6</p>
        <p>UNCERTAINTY ON DAMAGES The Supreme Court appeared uncertain how to proceed as it heard arguments on limiting punitive damages in civil lawsuits. A18</p>
        <p>The defendant called the killing of Selena an accident. A21</p>
        <p>Republicans defeated an attack on their immigration plan. A20</p>
        <p>Metro Digest</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>NEW CHANCELLOR ARRIVES The next Chancellor, Rudolph F. Crew, barreled into New York like a politician taking a victory lap, visiting an elementary school in Queens in a carefully choreographed tour and experiencing his first Board of Education meeting. A1 Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>C15-24</p>
        <p>Survey says business is giving more to the arts. C15 "Alternative Jazz" series. C22 Theater: Mamet's take on Priestley's "Dangerous Corner." C15 "Pomp Duck and Circumstance." C24 Film: "Cyclo." C20 "Hate." C20 Music: Mary Chapin Carpenter. C15 Australian Chamber Orchestra. C18 The Pop Life. C22 Jazz outsiders in Brooklyn. C22 Dance: Paul Taylor. C15 Murray Lewis Company. C23 Books: "Telling Time," by Austin Wright. C22</p>
        <p>The Home Section</p>
        <p>C1-13</p>
        <p>Not just for show: this house drops the act. C1</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>B8-15</p>
        <p>Baseball: Indians win Game 2. B9 Braves prevail in extras. B9 Columns: Vecsey on A.L.C.S. B9 Football: Northwestern's resurgence. B9 Giants' Miller benched. B9</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B22</p>
        <p>Charles G. Gomillion, fought for a black majority in Tuskegee, Ala.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>A hard-hearted tax bill. Britain's obligation in Hong Kong. Saving the Tarrytown riverbank. Letters</p>
        <p>William Safire: After the aftermath. Maureen Dowd: The Crisco kids. Abigail Thernstrom: Two nations, separate and hostile? Marc Miller and Donald Kennedy: Saving the Galapagos.</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>D22</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>C23</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>C23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
