<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place;A Giant of Wind Power Stumbles Badly</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="818556"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">KENETECH CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALPUKAS, AGIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7D61539F934A15751C1A963958260" item-length="1179" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place;A Giant of Wind Power Stumbles Badly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SALPUKAS, AGIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kenetech, the world's biggest maker of wind turbines and the once-proud symbol of the coming of age of wind power in the United States, is scrambling to survive.</p>
        <p>A little more than a year ago, the San Francisco company was on a roll. Impressed by its high-technology variable-speed turbines and by analysts' upbeat sales projections, investors bid Kenetech's stock to a peak of $29.50 in  March 1994 from $16.50 at its initial public offering in September 1993.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kenetech, the world's biggest maker of wind turbines and the once-proud symbol of the coming of age of wind power in the United States, is scrambling to survive.</p>
        <p>A little more than a year ago, the San Francisco company was on a roll. Impressed by its high-technology variable-speed turbines and by analysts' upbeat sales projections, investors bid Kenetech's stock to a peak of $29.50 in  March 1994 from $16.50 at its initial public offering in September 1993.</p>
        <p>Then, late last year, things started to unravel.</p>
        <p>First, Windpower Monthly, a trade publication, reported in September that there were cracked blades and damaged generators in Kenetech turbines at wind farms in Buffalo Ridge, Minn., and Palm Springs, Calif. Those defects had forced frequent shutdowns of the machines, according to the magazine.</p>
        <p>In October, Henry Hermann, an analyst in Dallas who covers the industry for W. R. Lazard, Laidlaw &amp; Mead, warned investors about the problems. "They invested tremendous amounts in a machine that did not work very well," Mr. Hermann said in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>The company's top management brushed off the reports, saying the problems were glitches, and they continued to peddle the machines aggressively. Even so,  sales slumped; analysts now estimate only 500 turbines will be sold this year, half their original projection.</p>
        <p>But problems ran deeper than customer doubts. In the spring, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission scrapped a requirement for California utility companies to buy renewable energy sources, including wind power, at prices that  had become uncompetitive to fossil fuels. The decision was a blow to Kenetech and prompted it to make a marketing push abroad.</p>
        <p>The company, however, maintained a positive attitude and convinced most analysts that things would get better. They didn't. On Aug. 9, Kenetech reported a second-quarter loss of $1.5 million, or 2 cents a share. The results surprised analysts, who had expected earnings of about 23 cents a share, and the next day, shares of Kenetech plunged $3.25, to $7.81.</p>
        <p>As more analysts turned negative on the stock and rating agencies downgraded  Kenetech's debt, the share price plunged, closing yesterday at $1.1875 in Nasdaq trading, down 6.25 cents for the day.</p>
        <p>With questions multiplying about the turbine's reliability, both the chief financial officer and chief operating officer resigned in November. This month,  they were followed by Gerald R. Alderson, the chief executive.</p>
        <p>The most humiliating setback of all came last month, when blades at 2 of the  company's 90 turbines at a farm in Spain broke and flew off. Though they landed  harmlessly, the company feared for the safety of motorists on a nearby road and  shut the project.</p>
        <p>Back on Sept. 28, Gold, Bennett &amp; Cera of San Francisco, a law firm that specializes in class-action shareholder suits, filed a complaint against Kenetech contending that its top officers had given analysts "misinformation, causing them to mislead investors."</p>
        <p>The suit asserted that some top executives and directors had falsely claimed  Kenetech's turbines could compete with coal by producing electricity for 5 cents a kilowatt hour. It also asserted that they continued to push the product even after flaws had been cited.</p>
        <p>As 1995 ends, some people wonder whether Kenetech will make it through 1996.  They fear that it might have to file for bankruptcy protection to stay afloat -- a possibility that the company's treasurer, William Klitgaard, does not rule out.</p>
        <p>Yet he and the new chief executive, Richard D. Saunders, a turnaround specialist who took over this month, do not think that will happen.  "It will take a little while, but we will get our house in order," Mr. Klitgaard said.</p>
        <p>Kenetech officials say they still believe they can correct the problems of their turbine, a three-blade machine called the KVS-33 that took four years and  $70 million to develop. Powered by two generators and mounted on a steel tower,  the KVS-33 contains an advanced electronic system that lets it operate at variable speeds and capture more energy than earlier machines could.</p>
        <p>The company stands by its claim that the KVS-33 can produce electricity for 5 cents a kilowatt hour, making it competitive with some coal-fired plants. Reducing costs to that level is crucial for the future of the wind-power industry.</p>
        <p>Kenetech blames its suppliers for some defects that have plagued the KVS-33,  adding that any new technology has kinks. Mr. Klitgaard, the treasurer, contends that the turbines have no serious flaws. The company has put 11 of the 90 machines in Spain back into operation, he says, and hopes to have the others running by next month.</p>
        <p>Kenetech has also begun a cost-cutting drive, which includes planned layoffs  for many of its 900 workers. "The challenge is to get to a size where it can survive as a business," Mr. Klitgaard said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saunders said that he is exploring all alternatives, including selling the company. He has hired Smith Barney Inc. to help in that effort. The investment bank declined to comment.</p>
        <p>The company is also reassuring skittish suppliers that it can pay its bills.  Joe Zimmer, the chief financial officer of Lindquist Machine in Green Bay, Wis., said that his company was being "very, very cautious," but was still shipping high-precision shafts to Kenetech.</p>
        <p>Meantime, Kenetech has fought back against its critics. It complained that Mr. Hermann, the analyst who came out with an unfavorable report last year, had  acted as a consultant for the New World Power Corporation, a competitor. Kenetech asked the Association for Investment Management and Research, the analysts' trade group, to investigate his conduct.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hermann said that he had disclosed his role as consultant and that it did not preclude him from evaluating Kenetech because he had long experience in the industry.</p>
        <p>This month, Kenetech and its law firm, Folger &amp; Levin of San Francisco, filed a motion in Federal court in California's Northern District to have the suit against it dismissed, saying that it had made clear the considerable risks of "attempting to introduce highly complex and new technology to an undeveloped market."</p>
        <p>But even if Kenetech can squelch the lawsuit, analysts say the company's survival remains uncertain. David W. Tice, the president of an investment and research firm in Dallas that became negative on Kenetech stock last year, said that he doubts an outside party would want to acquire such a troubled company. He also said that it was too early to tell whether the firm could be reorganized under bankruptcy law and continue operating as a much smaller company. "The company," he said, "overstated the reliability of its technology."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
