<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="817416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD91439F932A15751C1A963958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conferees Reach Accord On Telecommunications Bill House and Senate negotiators reached agreement on a sweeping bill to rewrite the nation's communications laws, clearing the way for Congress to pass a final bill before the weekend. The new agreement came after Republicans capitulated to Democrats on a wide variety of issues, and it means that the bill is virtually assured of becoming law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Conferees Reach Accord On Telecommunications Bill House and Senate negotiators reached agreement on a sweeping bill to rewrite the nation's communications laws, clearing the way for Congress to pass a final bill before the weekend. The new agreement came after Republicans capitulated to Democrats on a wide variety of issues, and it means that the bill is virtually assured of becoming law.</p>
        <p>The bill is more moderate than versions passed by the House and Senate and is likely to be less jolting for consumers. Still, the choices may bewilder consumers. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Budget Talks Snag Again  Republicans in the House scuttled an agreement to begin serious budget talks. That agreement was reached by Senator Bob Dole, Speaker Newt Gingrich and President Clinton. The House Republicans balked at approving a spending resolution before a balanced budget was agreed on. [A1.]</p>
        <p>The shutdown is taking a toll on the Government's statistical reporting on the economy. But this time, most of the monthly numbers have been obtained. [D4.]</p>
        <p>House Overrides Clinton Veto  The House voted to override President Clinton's veto of legislation to make it more difficult for stockholders to bring fraud suits. The Senate, which is more  closely divided, made plans to vote later this week. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Preparations by Goldman, Sachs  Goldman, Sachs, buoyed by its rebounding profit, is preparing itself for a possible sale next year, top executives acknowledged. [D7.] Hanson to Raise Cash Hanson P.L.C. put up for sale its Oregon lumber company and offered shares in its New Jersey propane company in an effort to raise $2.3 billion to pay down heavy debt. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Hoechst to Cut 8,000 Drug Jobs  Hoechst of Germany plans to close more than half its 77 drug-production plants and eliminate 8,000 jobs. The actions followed the company's acquisition in July of Marion Merrell Dow for $7.1 billion. [D8.]</p>
        <p>Californians May Get to Pick Utility  Californians would be the first consumers in the nation free to choose their supplier of electricity, under a vote by regulators. [D6.]</p>
        <p>California County Sues Auditor  Orange County, Calif., sued its former auditor, KPMG Peat Marwick, for $3 billion, saying it failed to warn of financial risks. [D6.]</p>
        <p>Innovative Dividend Offer  Merrill Lynch is raising money for Citicorp by promising a sweeter dividend if Congress cuts the tax deductions for dividends. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Informix to Buy Software Firm  Informix agreed to buy Illustra Information Technologies for $386 million in stock. Both make database management software. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Algeria to Develop Oilfields  Algeria is ready to sign several important deals with American, British and French companies to develop its huge oil and gas reserves. British Petroleum is  planning a $3.5 billion commitment. [A13.]</p>
        <p>Ruling Could Cost U.S. $2 Billion  The Justice Department may appeal a ruling that the Federal Government be held financially responsible for canceling contracts with General Dynamics and McDonnell Douglas for the Navy's A-12 Stealth aircraft. The ruling could cost $2 billion or more. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Historians Want Tax Records  The Government's archivist said the I.R.S. has violated laws requiring that it send historically significant documents to the National Archives. The I.R.S. maintains that legally it must keep most of its records secret to protect confidentiality; the Archives responds that the I.R.S. does not even turn over mundane documents like tax forms.  [D4.]</p>
        <p>Ozone Labeling on Refrigerators  Four refrigerator makers agreed to put labels on the machines saying they cause  damage to the ozone layer, even without using a prominent chemical. [A15.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
