<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Map Makes Ocean Floors as Knowable as Venus</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19951025T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="802812"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAVITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTINENTAL DRIFT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC &amp; ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gravitation and Gravity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D71538F937A15753C1A963958260" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Map Makes Ocean Floors as Knowable as Venus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until now, 71 percent of Earth was not as well mapped as the surface of Venus. Today the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration corrected the situation, unveiling the first good map of the ocean floor.</p>
        <p>"It's like being able to drain the oceans and look at the Earth from space," said Dr. David T. Sandwell, a geophysicist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., who helped make the new map. "We're having a data feast. It really is a time of celebration."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until now, 71 percent of Earth was not as well mapped as the surface of Venus. Today the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration corrected the situation, unveiling the first good map of the ocean floor.</p>
        <p>"It's like being able to drain the oceans and look at the Earth from space," said Dr. David T. Sandwell, a geophysicist at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., who helped make the new map. "We're having a data feast. It really is a time of celebration."</p>
        <p>At a news conference here, Dr. Sandwell and Dr. Walter H. F. Smith of the ocean agency revealed a striking multicolored map 12 feet wide and 8 feet high of the 71 percent of Earth that underlies the oceans. Scientists say the map opens a major new window on the sea and its mysteries.</p>
        <p>Previously, seabed maps were generally made with the aid of surface ships that bounced sound waves off the bottom to get a glimpse of the wilderness below. With much artistic license, such scattered readings were drawn into seabed renderings.</p>
        <p>The new map is far more accurate and is based in part on secret Navy data recently declassified in a post-cold-war peace dividend. From an orbit 500 miles high, a Navy satellite in the 1980's made gravity measurements over the world's oceans as part of a quiet effort to increase the accuracy of long-range missiles fired from submarines.</p>
        <p>With the Navy's cooperation, the ocean agency turned the gravity data from that $80 million mission, as well as recent readings from a European satellite, into a global map of the sea floor that reveals all kinds of plains, fissures, ridges, mountains, volcanoes and riddles that had been hidden until now in the sunless depths.</p>
        <p>"The improvement is dramatic," Dr. William F. Haxby, a founder of satellite mapping at the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Already, a rush to exploit the new map is under way. Fishermen want to find seamounts that produce upwellings of deep, nutrient-rich water that feed aquatic swarms. And industries want to find the kinds of rocks that overlay oilfields and the kinds of volcanic eruptions that form undersea deposits of copper, iron, silver and gold.</p>
        <p>Of great importance to scientists is that the new data are starting to revamp parts of plate tectonics. This widely accepted theory holds that the earth's surface is made up of a dozen or so plates that float on a sea of molten rock and grind past one another in earthquake spasms. The intersections of those plates that are now being found sometimes look quite different from what had been envisioned.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jian Lin, a geophysicist at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution on Cape Cod, said the new data "will almost certainly change our thinking about the active geological processes in the world's deep ocean basins."</p>
        <p>So too, the new map is seen as important for climate studies and investigations of global warming, since mountain chains and other seabed features play important but poorly understood roles in regulating currents and circulatory patterns in the deep ocean.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gregory Neumann, an earth scientist at Johns Hopkins University, said the new map "brings us one step closer to understanding the processes that drive our planet."</p>
        <p>The glimmer of a new approach to mapping ocean floors came in 1978 with the space agency's launching of Seasat, a satellite that worked three months before it unexpectedly failed. The craft had a radar altimeter that fired short pulses of microwaves at the ocean's surface and picked up reflected signals. The time of the round trip gave the satellite's altitude and a very precise reading of the sea's height down to a few inches.</p>
        <p>Close examination of such readings showed that seabed features like mountains produced swells at the surface and trenches produced dips, mimicking the topography of the seafloor. Moreover, the features were fairly big, often several feet high. What caused them was the skewing of Earth's gravitational field.</p>
        <p>In March 1985, the Navy launched an improved mapper, Geosat, and used it to measure the pull of gravity on the sea until October 1986. Its findings of sea-surface height were accurate to about one inch and were classified secret because they could be used to improve the accuracy of missiles fired from submarines.</p>
        <p>In 1990, with the cold war ending, the Navy declassified Geosat gravity data below 60 degrees south latitude, mostly around the Antarctic seas. In 1992, it publicly released all data below 30 degrees south, still a small slice of the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Finally, last July the Navy released all the remaining Geosat data. The ocean agency then combined it with readings from the European ERS-1 satellite, which had finished a similar gravity-mapping mission in April.</p>
        <p>The new map not only reveals deep secrets but is being used by airline equipment makers to improve the accuracy of navigation gear, which can be thrown off by gravitational anomalies.</p>
        <p>Geologists and geophysicists are probably most excited about the map, which reveals a mountain of rocky facts and riddles. It instantly doubled the number of known volcanoes under the sea, many of which are strangely elongated and perhaps with analysis will give insights into plate structure and mechanics. "These features suggest that the plates are not exactly rigid as predicted by the simple plate tectonic theory," Dr. Sandwell and Dr. Smith wrote in background paper handed out today.</p>
        <p>Another enigma concerns the ridges where hot rock oozes out onto the dark seabed during volcanic eruptions to form new crust and to add to the size of tectonic plates. Historically, scientists have identified two ridge types: smooth fast-spreading ones found in the Pacific Ocean and rough slow-spreading ones found in the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
        <p>But the new map shows this distinction to be false. Now that scientists can see the whole of the 30,000-mile-long ridge system that snakes across the bottom of the global seabed, they have discovered that the two types of ridges can coexist, with rough and smooth ones sitting alongside each other.</p>
        <p>A colon California by telephoning (619) 534-2752. A computer copy of the raw data is available on four CD-ROM's for $124 from the ocean agency's National Oceanographic Data Center in Washington and can be ordered by telephoning (202) 606-4549. The agency says it is integrating the gravity map into other databases, including those from acoustic mapping expeditions, and will publish updated versions in the months ahead.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 25, 1995, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday misstated the comparative accuracy of a new map of the global sea floor and maps of Venus. The ocean map remains less accurate. The surface of Venus was mapped by the Magellan spacecraft to reveal objects as small as hundreds of feet across, while the new sea floor map can make out only features that are miles in diameter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 25, 1995, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday misstated the comparative accuracy of a new map of the global sea floor and maps of Venus. The ocean map remains less accurate. The surface of Venus was mapped by the Magellan spacecraft to reveal objects as small as hundreds of feet across, while the new sea floor map can make out only features that are miles in diameter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
