<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Rain and Temperature Data, New Signs of Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="791134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDB1530F935A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Rain and Temperature Data, New Signs of Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a new study of weather trends in the United States, China, Australia and the former Soviet Union, scientists have turned up further evidence that some of the predicted effects of emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases on the world's climate are being felt.</p>
        <p>Computerized models of the climate system suggest, among other things, that as concentrations of greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide rise, a greater proportion of precipitation will be in the form of heavy rainfalls and snowfalls. They also suggest that day-to-day and week-to-week differences in temperature will be less pronounced.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a new study of weather trends in the United States, China, Australia and the former Soviet Union, scientists have turned up further evidence that some of the predicted effects of emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases on the world's climate are being felt.</p>
        <p>Computerized models of the climate system suggest, among other things, that as concentrations of greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide rise, a greater proportion of precipitation will be in the form of heavy rainfalls and snowfalls. They also suggest that day-to-day and week-to-week differences in temperature will be less pronounced.</p>
        <p>The new study, by American and Australian scientists, has found that both phenomena are occurring in some parts of the world, but not in others. It was conducted by Thomas R. Karl and Richard W. Knight of the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C., and Neil Plummer of the Australian Bureau of Meteorology and is published in the current issue of the British journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karl characterized the results as "another piece of the puzzle" of climate change that researchers are trying to assemble by investigating different climatic effects likely to be produced by increasing concentrations of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The latest research extends a study last May, also led by Mr. Karl, which concluded that from 1980 through 1994, the greenhouse effect increased the incidence of drought, above-normal temperatures, wintertime precipitation and heavy rainstorms in many areas of the United States.</p>
        <p>As revealed in a draft report recently made available on the Internet, experts advising the world's governments are saying for the first time that at least some of the climate change being observed in the world is likely to have been caused by human activity like the burning of coal, oil and wood, which produces carbon dioxide. The draft report also predicts that an increase in the incidence of extreme weather events will accompany a rise in the average global temperature of 1.44 to 6.3 degrees Fahrenheit over the next century if greenhouse gas emissions are not reduced.</p>
        <p>According to the imperfect computerized models of the climate system on which the experts largely base their expectations, a warming climate could damp down short-term variations in temperature. In temperate zones, high and low temperatures in the summer normally vary less from one day to the next than in other seasons. The models predict that as the climate warms, the swings should generally become more summerlike.</p>
        <p>This has indeed happened, Mr. Karl and his colleagues found by examining temperature records from hundreds of sites in China, the former Soviet Union and the United States over the last 30 to 80 years. In this respect, temperate regions are becoming somewhat more like the tropics, where the temperature is relatively constant year-round.</p>
        <p>Temperature records were also examined for Australia, but no clear trend was found. Different atmospheric circulation patterns in the Southern Hemisphere may account for this, Mr. Karl said.</p>
        <p>The researchers also examined precipitation records from the United States, China and the former Soviet Union. They divided daily precipitation totals into five categories ranging from very light to extremely heavy, then calculated the proportion of precipitation falling into each category. "Extreme" was defined as two or more inches of precipitation in one day.</p>
        <p>The results from the former Soviet Union were inconclusive. Because the Russians have changed their techniques for observing and measuring rainfall many times, said Mr. Karl, reliable data are available only for the last 20 to 25 years. "That's not enough to get a good notion of what's happening in the long term," he said.</p>
        <p>In China, where data exist from 1951 to 1990, no increase in the proportion of total precipitation falling in extreme events was found. One reason, Mr. Karl said, may be that China is heavily affected by monsoons; another may be that the effects of warming have not yet been felt in China, because that country's unusually heavy reliance on the burning of coal produces large emissions of sulfate aerosols that exert a cooling effect. The aerosols reflect some of the sun's energy.</p>
        <p>In the United States, however, there was a clear pattern: from 1910 to 1990, the proportion of precipitation falling as part of extreme events grew, while the proportion falling in moderate and lighter events shrank.  In 1910, about 9 percent of total annual precipitation was derived from extreme events; in 1990, about 12 percent was so derived. In the summer, the increase in rainfall derived from heavy one-day rains was especially large.</p>
        <p>The question of rainfall in Australia was not directly addressed by the Karl study, but the report cites a recent Australian analysis showing an increase in the intensity of heavy precipitation in northeastern Australia in this century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
