<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Utility to Sell Air Pollution Rights to Merck</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="766041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMOG</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RAHWAY (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PUBLIC SERVICE ELECTRIC &amp; GAS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E4DF1639F932A35755C0A963958260" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Utility to Sell Air Pollution Rights to Merck</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Public Service Electric &amp; Gas Company is trying something new to win customers' loyalty: It is selling them the right to pollute. Cheap.</p>
        <p>In the first deal likely to make it past all the regulatory hurdles, Public Service and Merck &amp; Company plan to announce an agreement today that will let boilers at Merck's plant in Rahway, N.J., emit tons more than the new limit of smog-causing chemicals this summer because it has bought the right to do so from P.S.E.&amp; G., which polluted less than expected in 1992.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Public Service Electric &amp; Gas Company is trying something new to win customers' loyalty: It is selling them the right to pollute. Cheap.</p>
        <p>In the first deal likely to make it past all the regulatory hurdles, Public Service and Merck &amp; Company plan to announce an agreement today that will let boilers at Merck's plant in Rahway, N.J., emit tons more than the new limit of smog-causing chemicals this summer because it has bought the right to do so from P.S.E.&amp; G., which polluted less than expected in 1992.</p>
        <p>Proponents of such trading foresee a growing future for it. Buying pollution credits could let factories delay or avoid installing cleanup systems and take the pressure off big office employers, who are now supposed to be pushing carpools or working by computer from home. Others speculate that entrepreneurs will buy old cars with dirty exhaust and junk them for the credits, or offer to  replace homeowners' furnaces with newer, more efficient models, at a cut rate -- and then sell the pollution credits to industrial plants in need.</p>
        <p>Companies in New Jersey, New York and Connecticut, making everything from licorice extract to nuclear attack submarines, are lining up to take the credits, and utilities are anxious to develop a market.</p>
        <p>Public Service is selling the allowances for nitrogen oxide pollutants for $1,600 a ton. That is about what it cost the company in 1992 to switch two generating stations from coal to natural gas, which earned it the credits. It is also hundreds of dollars less per ton than what Merck would spend to meet the nitrogen oxide standards itself.</p>
        <p>Public Service is not the only utility trying to increase the loyalty of customers big enough to build their own power plants or buy from independent producers. Northeast Utilities of Berlin, Conn., is discussing giving credits to several customers, including the Electric Boat division of the General Dynamics  Corporation, the submarine manufacturer, and the University of Massachusetts at  Amherst, which runs boilers for heating. William L. Stillinger, director of technology and transmission planning for Northeast, likened the credits to airlines' frequent flier miles.</p>
        <p>Northeast and Public Service announced a deal in March 1994 under which Northeast was to buy allowances from Public Service for distribution to Northeast's customers. But the trade never occurred. Northeast said yesterday that regulations on interstate trading of pollution rights had not yet been written. Public Service's manager of corporate issues, Eric B. Svenson, said that Northeast had backed out, possibly because it was sensitive about the image of buying the right to pollute.</p>
        <p>In any case, Northeast is now generating its own credits, in part by claiming credit for electricity it did not generate. It has cut demand for power by installing high-technology light bulbs and other energy-saving equipment for its customers, reducing the pollution it created.</p>
        <p>Regulators in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut say that they have several deals before them awaiting approval.</p>
        <p>Behind the trades are new rules under the Clean Air Act amendments of 1990, which take effect today. They put controls on nitrogen oxides, a class of chemicals that contribute to smog and are emitted by thousands of companies in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>Reducing pollution to a commodity can make it easier for regulators to force  compliance, said Michael J. Bradley, an air pollution consultant based in Concord, Mass. If a company had trouble installing equipment to reduce emissions, he said, "the old strategy was to go to the governor's office and raise hell," and seek an exemption. Now, he said, companies can simply pay others for the reductions they need.</p>
        <p>Public Service, of Newark, and Merck are scheduled to announce this morning that the drug company, which runs two steam boilers that produce nitrogen oxides, will buy the right to emit 10 tons above the new limit, which varies with the amount of heat the boilers produce.</p>
        <p>Merck may buy up to 75 tons this year and every year through 1998, while it decides whether to replace the boilers or buy energy from outside. A public comment period on the deal is in force until next week.</p>
        <p>Under the deal and all proposed trades, one ton of every nine traded will be  "retired" and not emitted, to reduce total pollution. In addition, trades are supposed to be "directionally correct," meaning that buyers should be downwind of sellers.</p>
        <p>It will not make any money for Public Service, but it will save money for Merck.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists do not find all trades benign. Some have complained that in another trading system, for sulfur dioxide, the chemical that makes most acid rain, sometimes the buyer is upwind of the seller. The effect is to shift pollution emissions so dirty air is over land longer before being blown out to sea.</p>
        <p>In fact, sulfur dioxide trading has been slow to begin and prices have plummeted, an indication that the problem of compliance was never as great as some utilities had said it was. But experts say they think that a bigger market will develop in the smog pollutants, because many more companies are regulated. Some said yesterday, though, that the market price is likely to be less than $1,000 a ton. If it falls low enough, Mr. Svenson said, Public Service may turn into a buyer instead of a seller.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
