<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Cuts Seen By Science Group As Very Harmful For U.S. Research</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950908T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="785507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHYSICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN ASSN FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TEICH, ALBERT W (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA1F38F93AA1575BC0A963958260" item-length="1618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Cuts Seen By Science Group As Very Harmful For U.S. Research</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEDERAL financing of nonmilitary scientific research in the United States will decline by one-third within seven years, the American Association for the Advancement of Science says in a report to be released today. It warns that "the long-term effects of dismantling a coherent scientific enterprise could be very harmful."</p>
        <p>The study projects financing trends through the year 2002, based on the budget resolution passed by Congress on June 29 and on subsequent actions by the House and Senate in drafting appropriations bills for the fiscal year 1996. Deep projected reductions in the support of research and development, in some cases 100 percent, represent "the most significant across-the-board funding cuts to the research-and-development enterprise in the post-World War II era," the authors of the report wrote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEDERAL financing of nonmilitary scientific research in the United States will decline by one-third within seven years, the American Association for the Advancement of Science says in a report to be released today. It warns that "the long-term effects of dismantling a coherent scientific enterprise could be very harmful."</p>
        <p>The study projects financing trends through the year 2002, based on the budget resolution passed by Congress on June 29 and on subsequent actions by the House and Senate in drafting appropriations bills for the fiscal year 1996. Deep projected reductions in the support of research and development, in some cases 100 percent, represent "the most significant across-the-board funding cuts to the research-and-development enterprise in the post-World War II era," the authors of the report wrote.</p>
        <p>The A.A.A.S., a professional society with more than 140,000 individual members, is the largest scientific federation in the world and tracks the financing of American science every year. Dr. Albert H. Teich, who directs the association's division of science and policy programs, said in an interview that "what we're trying to do is call people's attention to the implications of present trends."</p>
        <p>The current drive in Congress toward deficit reduction and a balanced budget by 2002 is strongly supported by new members of Congress whose election platforms called for sweeping cutbacks in Government spending.</p>
        <p>The budget cuts will affect science unevenly. Money appropriated for the National Science Foundation may decline only a few percent in 1996, and the National Institutes of Health may actually get an increase of more than 6 percent. But some major programs of NASA, the United States Geological Survey and the National Institute of Standards and Technology face extinction, and the overall trend in Federal support of science alarms many scientists.</p>
        <p>Scientific groups are worried that the era of generous treatment from Congress may be waning. "For many years," Dr. Teich said, "we had a protective umbrella of members of Congress who understood science, were sympathetic toward it and were associated with it. But now we have an awful lot of new people in Congress who don't have any connection with science. It's up to the scientific community to try to reach them."</p>
        <p>Many scientists and research administrators acknowledge that Federal belt-tightening has made cuts in research support inevitable. But they believe that Congress has been moving too hastily and without adequate consultation with experts.</p>
        <p>An important factor in the trend, besides the need to cut Federal spending across the board, has been the conclusion of the cold war, which, Dr. Teich said, had "provided a geopolitical situation in which political-military power was strongly associated with a nation's scientific and technological prowess." With a decline in the perceived need to maintain that prowess, he said, science has lost political support.</p>
        <p>Among the fields in which the association expects the sharpest reductions are research on environmental issues, fusion-energy development, atmospheric and geological problems, unmanned space programs and research assistance to industry. For 1996, research funds for Federal agencies, other than the Defense Department, have been reduced in Congressional appropriations bills by more than 5 percent. The National Institutes of Health was the only major Federal agency granted a budget increase, of 6.2 percent, but it was included in a bill that President Clinton might veto for other reasons.</p>
        <p>Some Federal departments and the research they support may not survive the next few years. The Commerce Department has been made a target for elimination by many Congressmen, leading to uncertainty about the future of two of its major research agencies, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration and the National Institute of Standards and Technology.</p>
        <p>NOAA investigates changes in global climate, like the possible greenhouse warming of the planet caused by gaseous emissions of human industry and the so-called ozone hole, a thinning of the atmosphere's protective ozone layer believed to have been caused by the release of chlorofluorocarbon compounds. NOAA faces a probable reduction in 1996 of 14.1 percent in money for its operations, research and facilities, the science association says.</p>
        <p>At the National Institute of Standards and Technology (formerly the National Bureau of Standards), Congress has already eliminated the Advanced Technology Program, a $466.5 million undertaking to assist private industry in the development of technology.</p>
        <p>In a recent speech, Dr. Arati Prabhakar, the institute's director, said that "if the current Congress has its way, it will turn the clock back 20 years and put technological innovation on the shelf."</p>
        <p>Republican leaders in Congress, however, have argued that Federal subsidies for research conducted to benefit private industry are unnecessary, and that industry should pay for its own research.</p>
        <p>The biggest expected dollar reduction in 1996 Federal support for science is the $716.5 million that the House has voted to pare from NASA's $9.5 billion budget. A major share of that reduction would come from Mission to Planet Earth, a system for using satellites to track changes in the earth's ecosystems.</p>
        <p>Another research casualty of the 1996 budget will be the Interior Department's Bureau of Mines, for which Congress has provided no money at all. The bureau, which this year is spending $102 million, studies mine safety and supervises the helium-conservation program under which some of this irreplaceable gas, separated from the natural gas with which it is mixed, is stored in underground caverns.</p>
        <p>Faced with so-called rescissions, or cuts in money previously appropriated by Congress for the present year, as well as the further cuts expected for 1996, many Federal research groups have begun dismissing scientists and other employees.</p>
        <p>For example, the United States Geological Survey, founded in 1879 as part of the Interior Department, has been forced to truncate one of its three main programs, its geology program, which was created to explore and map the nation's geological resources.</p>
        <p>"We have reached the point," said Donovan B. Kelly, spokesman for the agency, "at which there is no longer enough money after fixed expenses are paid to support field research in geology. We therefore have to make deep cuts. Nationwide, about 500 employees of the program will be separated by mid-October, and another 200 will be downgraded or transferred to other jobs. It's really hard doing this, when you know the names and faces of the people leaving -- people who were highly trained to do special jobs on behalf of the nation, and who are now being cast off."</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly said he hoped the geological survey's international earthquake network would be preserved. The network links seismographic instruments operated by about 120 countries with the survey's network, giving participating nations timely information about all earthquakes and greatly broadening the data base on which seismological research depends.</p>
        <p>High-energy physics research suffered a devastating blow last year when Congress, charging mismanagement, cut off funds for the $10 billion superconducting supercollider, a proton accelerator that would have made the United States the world's leader in the field until well into the next century. Leadership is now expected to pass to Europe after the turn of the century, as a consortium of nations completes the Large Hadron Collider near Geneva. Many American physicists hope to find work there.</p>
        <p>Another branch of physics, which holds out the hope of developing hydrogen fusion as a cheap, nonpolluting, renewable source of energy, is expected to suffer a serious reduction of financing in 1996. House action calls for a reduction of 36.4 percent in the budget for magnetic confinement fusion, whose main beneficiary is the experimental Tokamak reactor at the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ronald C. Davidson, director of the laboratory, said in an interview that if only $229 million of the requested $366 million budget for the laboratory was granted, as Congressional appropriations committees have done, it would be impossible to build a new-generation experimental reactor, the Tokamak Physics Experiment.</p>
        <p>Another major fusion experiment, in which microscopic pellets filled with hydrogen isotopes are bombarded by intense lasers, is in progress at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California, which is operated by the University of California for the Department of Energy. But this, too, faces an uncertain future.</p>
        <p>Many of Livermore's projects, including the development of nuclear weapons, are directed and paid for by the Defense Department, which provides the laboratory with a traditionally reliable financing pipeline. Defense Department research is not included in the overall research cuts that Congress has been making, and the House Appropriations Committee has set a 4.2 percent increase in military research and development for 1996, bringing financing to $36.7 billion.</p>
        <p>Officials of the A.A.A.S. said the association's gloomy new report was not a prediction, merely a projection.</p>
        <p>"Between now and 2002 a lot of things could happen," Dr. Teich said. "We could get another President and a different Congress, or we could have a war, or a recession. Lots of things could change. But what worries scientists is the Congressional resolution enacted in June, which is a broad statement of where Congress wants us to be in 2002. It's not a vision that bodes well for the health of American science."</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 8, 1995, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Aug. 29 about the expected effects of Congressional budget reductions on research misstated the role of the Defense Department in the development of nuclear weapons at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory. The Defense Department benefits from the programs, but they are directed and paid for by the defense programs division of the Energy Department.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 8, 1995, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Aug. 29 about the expected effects of Congressional budget reductions on research misstated the role of the Defense Department in the development of nuclear weapons at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory. The Defense Department benefits from the programs, but they are directed and paid for by the defense programs division of the Energy Department.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
