<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Refrigerators: Just How Friendly To Ozone Layer?</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="800143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISLEADING AND DECEPTIVE ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRPOLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E5DD1139F93AA25753C1A963958260" item-length="1289" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Refrigerators: Just How Friendly To Ozone Layer?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Turning necessity into a virtue, four big refrigerator manufacturers are crowing that they have helped save the environment by removing chlorofluorocarbons, which destroy the earth's protective ozone layer, from the  compressors in their new models.</p>
        <p>In fact, they must eliminate the chemicals, known as CFC's, because an international treaty decrees that after the end of this year, these compounds cannot be legally produced for use in this country. But the redesigned refrigerators will still damage the ozone because of another chemical the manufacturers have started using in foam insulation for the refrigerator walls,  something the companies are not advertising.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Turning necessity into a virtue, four big refrigerator manufacturers are crowing that they have helped save the environment by removing chlorofluorocarbons, which destroy the earth's protective ozone layer, from the  compressors in their new models.</p>
        <p>In fact, they must eliminate the chemicals, known as CFC's, because an international treaty decrees that after the end of this year, these compounds cannot be legally produced for use in this country. But the redesigned refrigerators will still damage the ozone because of another chemical the manufacturers have started using in foam insulation for the refrigerator walls,  something the companies are not advertising.</p>
        <p>They're saying the refrigerators are ozone safe, but they're really just ozone safer," said John Passacantando, the executive director of Ozone Action, a Washington environmental group. Ozone Action and the Environmental Law Foundation in Oakland, Calif., say they filed suit today in California against four manufacturers and marketers, Amana, General Electric, Sears, Roebuck and Whirlpool, accusing them of deceptive advertising.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Federal Trade Commission has been discussing the ads with at least some of those companies. The commission's guidelines say: "It is deceptive to misrepresent, directly or by implication, that a product is safe for or 'friendly' to the ozone layer. A claim that a product does not harm the ozone layer is deceptive if the product contains an ozone-depleting substance."</p>
        <p>But the manufacturers say that they have an environmental dilemma, because the chemical they are using in the foam, while it does do some ozone damage, is  extremely helpful in saving energy and thus in preventing other kinds of pollution. The arguments are over CFC's and two other classes of chemicals that  even engineers find hard to pronounce: hydrochlorofluorocarbons, known as HCFC's, and hydrofluorocarbons, or HFC's.</p>
        <p>Many of the ads say simply that the refrigerators have no CFC's, which is true. But they use a substitute product, an HCFC, to create the bubbles in the foam wall panels. HCFC's may be used for that purpose until 2003.</p>
        <p>The Federal Trade Commission cites HCFC's in its example of a deceptive claim. The guidelines give an example of an aerosol product that contains HCFC's, which are being used more and more widely as a substitute for CFC's because they are less damaging to the ozone. "Because the claim 'Contains no CFC's' may imply to reasonable consumers that the product does not harm the ozone layer, the claim is deceptive," the commission's guidelines say. A commission spokesman said that he could not say whether an investigation was going on.</p>
        <p>The two environmental groups filed their suit in California because it has a  "green label" statute that defines the term "ozone friendly." Hannah Bentley, a  lawyer with the Environmental Law Foundation, said that an amendment passed by the California Legislature earlier this year would make the environmentalists' case even stronger after Dec. 31, because from that date on, green-label definitions will be borrowed directly from the Federal Trade Commission guidelines.</p>
        <p>At Amana, a subsidiary of Ray theon, Ann Humbert, a spokeswoman, said today that its advertising is accurate: "We were the first in the industry to eliminate CFC's from both foam and refrigerators in our entire product line. We  did this well in advance of the deadline, and we're extremely proud of that accomplishment."</p>
        <p>The environmentalists' complaint has some irony for the manufacturers. A model the two groups are complaining about was developed under the Super Efficient Refrigerator Program, which was an environmental effort by electric utilities.  They paid a bounty to the manufacturers to come up with a model that used substantially less electricity, thereby reducing power plants' pollutants,  including those that contribute to acid rain and global warming.</p>
        <p>The superefficient refrigerator has no CFC's either but does use HCFC's in its insulation. That insulation is a higher-quality version of the foam used in  packaging, with precisely controlled bubble sizes.</p>
        <p>European manufacturers now make the bubbles with a hydrocarbon, cyclopentane. But Vincent P. Anderson, the director of environmental programs at the Whirlpool Corporation, said, "We've got a real dilemma here from an environmental point of view," because a refrigerator with cyclopentane bubbles would use 10 percent more electricity. "There's not a perfect solution out there," he added.</p>
        <p>The manufacturers are also struggling to meet Federal energy-efficiency standards, a kind of gasoline mileage rule for refrigerators, and if they had to give up the HCFC's in the foam, they would have to take other steps to regain efficiency.</p>
        <p>Another problem is that cyclopentane might leak from the foam into food in the refrigerators, manufacturers say.</p>
        <p>Experts differ on how ozone-hostile HCFC's are. The refrigerator manufacturers say that HCFC's are only 10 percent as potent as CFC's, formerly used as blowing agents. Ozone Action says that this may be so over 100 years, but in the next 20, each HCFC molecule is 20 percent as effective as a CFC molecule in breaking up the ozone. The next 20 years are more important than the following 80, Ozone Action argues, because that is when the maximum ozone depletion is expected to occur.</p>
        <p>Beyond 20 years, with global production of CFC's sharply cut, the natural formation of ozone molecules will exceed the rate of man-made destruction. In the interim, scientists say that a thinner ozone layer means that more of the sun's harmful ultraviolet rays will reach the surface of the earth, damaging plants, animals and people.</p>
        <p>Some HCFC's escape to the atmosphere during the manufacture of insulating foam. Some stay in the foam for the life of the refrigerator. But when the refrigerator's life is over, the foam will eventually break down, and the gases  will escape. Likewise, at some point the refrigerant will leak from the cooling  system and bleed out into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>There is also an irony in attacking the refrigerator as a threat to health. Refrigeration of food is one of the great aids to human health. But if the technology can be made more benign, it should be, the environmentalists argue.</p>
        <p>Another issue for the environmentalists is the manufacturers' choice of a substitute refrigerant for the compressors. They are using HFC's, which do not deplete the ozone but do add to global warming. Ozone Action favors hydrocarbons and points to Europe, where a once-faltering refrigerator manufacturer in the former East Germany switched to a butane mixture, similar to the fuel in some cigarette lighters. The company, Foron, has sold millions of these refrigerators since they were introduced in March 1993. Greenpeace paid for the first 10 prototypes in July 1992.</p>
        <p>Whirlpool also makes refrigerators in Europe that use butane, but Mr. Anderson, the company's environmental director, said that the technology was not ready for use in the United States. Few European refrigerators are frost-free, he said, but American consumers demand that feature and the blower and heater needed for frost-free models could ignite the butane if it ever leaked from the  compressor. The five ounces of refrigerant used in a full-size refrigerator could be sufficient to sustain an explosion, he said, and "the doors would come  flying open."</p>
        <p>The major contribution to global warming from a refrigerator, he said, comes  from burning fossil fuels in power plants. Make the machine more efficient, Mr.  Anderson said, and the global-warming impact will be lower, even if the refrigerant contributes to it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
