<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renewable Energy Can Be Competitive</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="755662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOTHERMAL POWER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA ENERGY CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOKOL, DAVID L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geothermal Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDD123EF935A25757C0A963958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renewable Energy Can Be Competitive</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your April 11 article on renewable energy ("70's Dreams, 90's Realities," Business Day) underscores two trends in the energy industry: utilities overcharging their customers and deflecting the blame on others, and the failure of the United States to develop a coherent energy policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your April 11 article on renewable energy ("70's Dreams, 90's Realities," Business Day) underscores two trends in the energy industry: utilities overcharging their customers and deflecting the blame on others, and the failure of the United States to develop a coherent energy policy.</p>
        <p>It is interesting to compare your chart of energy costs, showing natural gas at 3 cents per kilowatt-hour, wind at 5 cents and geothermal at 5.5 cents, with San Diego Gas &amp; Electric's 1994 annual report, showing that the three major California utilities charge their customers between 9.7 and 10.5 cents per kilowatt-hour. There's the price gap.</p>
        <p>The renewables just aren't competitive, lament the utilities. Well then, how did our company win $2 billion in contracts over the last two years in Indonesia and the Philippines, going head to head on a level playing field against all energy sources? By showing that renewables in fact are competitive, especially weighed against the long-term effects of polluting fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the entire move toward lower prices in the United States electric power industry has been due to competition since 1978 from renewables and other independent power companies, which have forced the utilities out of their monopoly position in generating power.</p>
        <p>Are renewables competitive with current spot market prices of gas? Not today. However, will a natural-gas company sign a fixed 30-year contract at today's price? No, because gas prices are at a historical low and no one knows where they will go tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Will a geothermal company sign a fixed 30-year contract? Absolutely, because geothermal steam is not a commodity subject to the same price fluctuations, market changes and Middle East politics.</p>
        <p>The utilities' rush to abandon renewables and embrace low-priced gas has an eerie sense of deja vu, as the United States demonstrates once again its inability to develop an intelligent energy policy. We ran to nuclear, which would be "too cheap to meter," according to the Atomic Energy Commission's Lewis Strauss. We ran to oil, which would last forever. Now we're running to gas. Once again, we base our strategy on the lowest available fuel source without giving any thought to diversity, security and environmental risks.</p>
        <p>Renewable energy is neither a dream nor a luxury. It is a necessity that should be encouraged by anyone in the public or private sector whose definition of long-term is more than one year.  DAVID L. SOKOL  Chairman of the Board and Chief Executive Officer California Energy Company Inc. Omaha, April 11, 1995</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
