<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Off the Grid</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="735642"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHITE SUPREMACY GROUPS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">IDAHO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISS, PHILIP</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRITZ, JAMES (BO)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEAVER, RANDALL C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Idaho</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D8123CF93BA35752C0A963958260" item-length="8360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Off the Grid</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Philip Weiss;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEISS, PHILIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A warming morning late in October, and James (Bo) Gritz stands on a mountaintop in north-central Idaho, addressing the faggot press. His words. Still, look at them: a Brit with blond hair fringing his round head -- The London Times calling; a reporter from People with long hair and a goatee; the neo-beat novelist William T. Vollmann, on assignment from Spin magazine and accompanied by a friend, a birdlike woman with bright red lipstick and purple gloves. And there are three or four others, including a photographer from this magazine who has slipped his earring into his pocket to get under the faggot radar.</p>
        <p>Gritz (rhymes with "bites") is long-winded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A warming morning late in October, and James (Bo) Gritz stands on a mountaintop in north-central Idaho, addressing the faggot press. His words. Still, look at them: a Brit with blond hair fringing his round head -- The London Times calling; a reporter from People with long hair and a goatee; the neo-beat novelist William T. Vollmann, on assignment from Spin magazine and accompanied by a friend, a birdlike woman with bright red lipstick and purple gloves. And there are three or four others, including a photographer from this magazine who has slipped his earring into his pocket to get under the faggot radar.</p>
        <p>Gritz (rhymes with "bites") is long-winded.</p>
        <p>"I don't know about you, friends, but I look at everything from my guerrilla perspective," he explains, alluding to his years as a Green Beret colonel. "The Government will do a threat analysis. They'll look and say, Jiminy Christmas, this is not Waco. We're going to have to completely encircle this whole area here if we're going to control it, and as you know there's only one road. . . . "</p>
        <p>He turns and motions over the hills to the north, toward a dirt road that winds 11 miles to the small town of Kamiah, population 1,100.</p>
        <p>"I know what they're going to say. 'Gritz is going to have a .50-caliber up here, he's going to have cannons, he's going to have explosives in the trees.' So they're going to have to try vertical envelopment." He's referring to helicopters. "Non-habit-forming. Five thousand helicopters shot down in Vietnam. No way! So I think they're going to leave us alone. So we don't have to shoot at them. We don't even have to have the capability. As long as they think that there is that threat."</p>
        <p>Gritz is talking about a place he calls Almost Heaven. It will rise right here, in northern Idaho -- 200 acres that he and his partners bought and subdivided into 30 lots that they're selling, at $3,000 an acre, to people who want to escape Government tyranny and Armageddon in the lowlands. The lots are going fast, as are those Gritz is selling on higher hilltops nearby -- he calls one Shenandoah, the other Woodland Acres. Up here, with a view of the Clearwater River and Gospel Hump Wilderness Area, buyers will form a "covenant community." They will agree to stand by one another and defend one another, and maybe not pay any taxes either. "Off the umbilical," he calls it. Off the grid.</p>
        <p>Gritz, who was briefly on the ticket with David Duke in '88 and ran for President himself in '92, is, at 55, a leader of the radical right-wing survivalist movement. He quotes Scripture, prophesying end times in the next few years, times when we shall all have to accept the mark of the beast: a bar code implant in the forehead or right hand that means the cashless society is upon us, and that every transaction an individual makes will be subject to surveillance. Just as Revelation 13 describes.</p>
        <p>"We are going to live our lives according to our ways," Gritz is saying now. "Let's say it comes down to the fact that eventually you cannot go down to the 7-Eleven and buy bread and milk and meat. Then yes, up here there's an abundance of game, and if it did come to that -- and according to biblical prophecies there are times like that ahead -- then we would be prepared. If it never comes, hallelujah. But personally I'm going to go off the grid, because every time I've lived off the grid, like Vietnam, I've been very happy."</p>
        <p>Gritz does what the photographers want him to do: he props one of his black cowboy boots on a barbed-wire fence and stares off squinting and box-headed. He hugs his wife, Claudia, and walks across the land. Claudia is nearly 20 years younger than he is -- she's wife No. 3 -- and doesn't seem like much of a survivalist. Pretty with Liz Taylor eyes, she wears two large diamonds rings on her fingers. She and Bo may be going off the grid, but Claudia is going to have a washer and dryer, a lawn.</p>
        <p>"I'm hungry," she says. "I need to go to the bathroom, so do one more shot."</p>
        <p>"There's a port-a-potty," one of Gritz's partners, Jerry Gillespie, tells her.</p>
        <p>"No way," she says.</p>
        <p>So, just one more shot. The top couple of buttons on Gritz's shirt are open, and sprigs of gray chest hair peek over his undershirt and catch the morning light, and the same sunlight takes in the valley of the Clearwater and the pale blue berries on the elderberry bushes. If you live off the grid you can make wine and pancakes with the crunchy, bittersweet elderberry.</p>
        <p>GO A HALF MILE EAST. THE SAME SUNLIGHT picks out honey-colored chinking on the log-house homestead of the first people to buy into Gritz's message and move up here: the Fullers, Dan and Barb, formerly of St. George, Utah. They are prepared for end times. They have a $20,000 solar-energy system and are storing food -- stuff that looks like dried cat food and takes a long time to get used to. T.V.P.: textured vegetable protein. Taco-flavored T.V.P. Magic Barbecue T.V.P.</p>
        <p>You get invited into their kitchen. Boy, that T.V.P. takes a while to get used to. They say Bo's got the Gospel. They say that years of study have convinced them that political collapse is a real possibility. They hand you literature from Florida that will open your eyes -- The Revelator. In which it is written that the Anti-Christ Banksters are squeezing the life out of America in preparation for the New World Order. Shrewd goldsmiths are plotting to deceive the goyim, the goy states. Mayer Amschel Rothschild. Haym Solomon. There is a long bit from the Protocols of the Elders of Zion.</p>
        <p>Dan Fuller, 68, is a retired crop-duster, and he tells you: "There are two choices. Go along with the New World Order, or change your life. They're going to decide everything about your life. Where you can work. Where you can live. Where you can go for groceries. They will tell you all of that. You're not going to be a free man, you're going to be a slave."</p>
        <p>You're skeptical. "I don't know."</p>
        <p>"Nothing would please me more than for it all not to be true." But, he continues, "Your clothes are not going to be yours. They're going to belong to the state."</p>
        <p>"Who will decide?"</p>
        <p>"World bankers."</p>
        <p>"The Queen of England," Barb says.</p>
        <p>"Rothschild," he says.</p>
        <p>You say, "How will it be in the middle of winter when you have to drive down 10 miles of snaking dirt road to get some milk?"</p>
        <p>Dan shakes his head once. "Well, let me ask you this: What are you going to do when they ask you to accept the mark of the beast?</p>
        <p>THE ANTI-GOVERNMENT MOOD THAT HAS seemingly swept the nation is nowhere more pronounced than in Idaho. This is not the state that elected Frank Church to the Senate, not any more. Idaho is sending no Democrats at all to Washington this month, and the Statehouse, which only a few years ago was roughly balanced between the two parties, now counts only 21 Democrats among its 105 members. The most powerful Democrat in the state, indeed the only Democrat holding statewide office, is J. D. Williams, the auditor. And Idaho's Republicans are not in the William Weld-Christine Whitman mold. There is Helen Chenoweth, for instance. During her successful campaign last fall to unseat Representative Larry LaRocco, a Democrat, Chenoweth declared that "white Anglo-Saxon males are an endangered species."</p>
        <p>White Anglo-Saxons are not endangered in Idaho. The state, with a population of roughly 1,100,000, is virtually all white. The 1990 census counted about 9,000 Asians and Pacific Islanders in Idaho and slightly more than 3,000 blacks. This goes some way toward explaining why Idaho is suddenly one of the most attractive destinations for whites in flight. (A third of the state's newcomers are said to be coming from California.) So far in the 90's, only Nevada's and Arizona's population growth rates are greater than Idaho's.</p>
        <p>"Our real estate is going nuts here because people are trying to get away from the real world," Clint Engledow, a real-estate agent in Kamiah, says. "Downtown Houston, downtown Denver, downtown Vallejo. You name it, they're fleeing. They say they're sick of drive-by shootings and 14-year-old orange-haired mall rats. They want to pick huckleberries and not be near any population base."</p>
        <p>The appeal of Idaho is not simply its whiteness, though. There are good jobs in Boise, and affordable homes in suburbs here that still feel like small towns. And for those looking for a last frontier, there is the terrain. Idaho has magnificent scale, its dry Western air yielding long views of rugged river breaks and serried mountains. These vistas are preserved thanks in large part to the Federal Government. Nearly two-thirds of the state is publicly owned land, mainly national forests and wilderness.</p>
        <p>Survivalists and conspiratorialists, Christian constitutionalists and New Age back-to-the-landers would seem to number in the several thousands in Idaho. Steve Willey, owner of Backwoods Solar Electric in Sandpoint, says he has 1,000 customers in northern Idaho, all off the grid.  "There's a wide variety here that come from opposite ends philosophically to the same situation physically," Willey says. Jess Walter, a reporter for The Spokesman-Review in Spokane, Wash., who has done considerable reporting on survivalists, estimates that there are more than 10,000 people living off the grid, both literally and philosophically, in the hills of eastern Washington, northern Idaho and western Montana. He has encountered a Vietnam vet who says he's hiding in the woods, a loner who shares a cabin with a grand piano, a man living in a trailer with his children and new wife, on the lam from a custody dispute, and a commune that sells food.</p>
        <p>"If you follow a dirt road anywhere in northeast Washington or Idaho, chances are you're going to find them," he says. "They're harder to count than homeless people, because they're just gone."</p>
        <p>In the 60's and 70's, hippies came to Idaho's empty spaces, and you can still find them growing garlic and tanning hides and holding barter fairs. And the promise of being left alone has drawn other kinds of free spirits. People like the novelist Denis Johnson, who lives near the Canadian border and who brings along bungee cords when he goes out with a chain saw so he can tourniquet himself in case of an accident.</p>
        <p>"You come here with a vague notion of getting away from it all," Johnson says. "Then when you get out into the woods, you see how wonderful it is to be self-sufficient to any degree, how essential it is to being human. I feel I robbed myself by living in cities. The city itself is like a big baby, being supplied from outside."</p>
        <p>Self-reliance is Idaho's byword. The landscape fosters an American romance about working out one's own fate in nature that is equal parts Thoreau and manifest destiny -- and one big part pure hatred of government. Up in the mountains of the panhandle, Idahoans bring those feelings to a high art. Local newspapers are filled with laments like the one that a husband and wife, new to the state, sent to The Clearwater Progress in Kamiah to complain about Federal policy on land use and schooling: "We eat the bitter bread of tyranny and the cake of oppression."</p>
        <p>For people like this, Idaho offers not only a landscape but a coherent politics, a world view: survivalism, tax protest, apocalypse, conspiracy theories. A woman in Kamiah urges you to investigate sightings of black helicopters, which, she has heard, are a sign that the United Nations is about to take over America's Armed Forces. At breakfast in the Lewis Clark Motel outside Kamiah, a retiree tells you, "In California they put a meter on your well and you get charged twice, once when it comes in and once when it flows out, as sewage," then gives you information about how to build a house from tires. And the publisher of The Clearwater Progress, Bill Glenn, shows you the plastic security strip they're putting into $20 bills, and says this is a step toward one world government.</p>
        <p>Out here, there's room for such thinking, room for everything. Bo Gritz tells you that Idaho County, Idaho, is ideal for Almost Heaven because, among other things, there is only one traffic light and the citizens have rejected all efforts to impose a building code. He tells you other things too. He says that as the global tide toward world government grows stronger, "we will need a pivotal state" -- Idaho as base camp.</p>
        <p>Gritz's attraction to Idaho, his sense of having found a place here, also has to do with his role in an episode that, for Idaho's survivalists, has become a legend -- one about a first taste of end times. In August 1992 a 44-year-old survivalist named Randall Weaver garrisoned himself and his family and a friend in a mountaintop cabin outside of Naples, Idaho, 30 miles from the Canadian border. Federal agents were moving in through the woods with a warrant for Weaver's arrest. (He had failed to appear at a trial on a gun charge in 1991.) During an unintended encounter, a deputy marshal was killed and Federal sharpshooters killed Weaver's 14-year-old son, Sam. The next day a sharpshooter killed Weaver's wife, Vicki, 43, as she stood in the doorway of the cabin holding her infant daughter. For eight days Randy Weaver huddled in his cabin with his three daughters a few feet from Vicki's body.</p>
        <p>A vigil gathered at the base of the mountain, known as Ruby Ridge. There were neo-Nazis, tax protesters, enraged neighbors. Children held posters saying Death to ZOG -- Zionist-Occupied Government. Skinheads shaved their heads in nearby Ruby Creek. The standoff ended when Bo Gritz showed up and forced himself on the hostage rescue team. He wore a special negotiator's outfit -- a midnight blue jacket with epaulets that he had made for him in Thailand years before, and he eventually helped convince Weaver to give up and fight the battle in court.</p>
        <p>The destruction of the Weaver family, and Randy Weaver's subsequent exoneration on Federal conspiracy charges, is today the parable by which many living off the grid in Idaho and elsewhere understand government's relationship to the American family. The story has the same resonance for survivalists today as confrontations between the Black Panthers and the police had for the radically alienated left in the 70's.</p>
        <p>WHERE ARE THESE PEOPLE COMING from that can inflict so much pain. I don't sleep at night."</p>
        <p>Leah Balint hugs herself as she recalls the death of Vicki Weaver.</p>
        <p>You're back at Almost Heaven. Two horses in a field. An apple tree. Leah's husband, Stewart, 41, in a Cochise belt buckle and a cowboy hat with a piece of polished stone, malachite or something, dangling from the band. And Leah herself walking around with just gray wool socks on her feet, a 22-year-old with a fragile piping voice and clear skin and thick Venus hair. Their two small boys play with a hammer. Solar panels lean against the trailer, charging the car battery that runs their television.</p>
        <p>They're off the grid and going further. Because Stew is engaged in the study of law. His studies began when his family lost its farm in Washington state. First he read "None Dare Call It Conspiracy," by Gary Allen, a former speech writer for George Wallace; that opened his eyes to the designs of the international bankers who, in league with the Government, fix prices arbitrarily and cripple the nation. Now Stew is renouncing all of what he regards as his contracts with government. Driver's license. Social Security. Birth certificate. Hunting license. He has torn them up.</p>
        <p>"The Government wasn't designed for people like us," Leah says.</p>
        <p>She goes to the trailer and comes back out with Birkenstocks. A bird tweets from a barbed-wire fence.</p>
        <p>"You see the magpie?"</p>
        <p>You turn and there's a magpie perched on a wire, iridescent and strange. Meriwether Lewis was enchanted by them when he traveled here 190 years ago.</p>
        <p>"Do you sleep at night?" she asks.</p>
        <p>LIKE SO MANY OTHER STANCES of the late 60's, the back-to-the-land movement was mostly talk. People on the coasts had visions of throwing off the traces of a sick imperialist society and making a homestead, but it took a special sort to act on those beliefs and go off the grid. It wasn't people who shouted about revolution till they were hoarse. That was first chakra energy, from the groin. The true back-to-the-lander was drawing on integrative energy, higher in the body, fourth or fifth chakra.</p>
        <p>Greg Sempel was confused by his football coaches at the University of Montana who screamed about winning and fed him 21 pills a day to bulk him up -- but said he was wrong to smoke pot. He felt abused. He dropped out, did some ranch work -- and eventually found himself on a remote hillside near Santa, Idaho, 80 miles north of Kamiah, with other hippies. He bought five acres (at $100 down, $50 a month), and melted snow for water. He formed a tree-planting co-op. It was grueling work, it tore at your back and your knees; men tended to be better cut out for it. That was a cruel truth about going back to the land; it might be saner, but it sorted out gender in a hurry. His wife, Leah, sewed quilts to exchange at the annual barter fair and gathered with the other women for home birthing.</p>
        <p>"Ruby was born in a tepee," Leah says now, reaching for her, a friend's 10-year-old child.</p>
        <p>"No, I was born in a bus," Ruby says.</p>
        <p>Sheryl and Larry Nims came out to Kamiah from Portland in 1970. The land they bought had a grove of locusts in a draw, and the trees made William Blake-like silhouettes against the darkening sky. They bought a tepee for $324. They had a son they named Asa, and after he broke a pitchfork trying to pole-vault, they got him a pole and built standards out of lodgepole pines and a crossbar from a piece of thornwood. (He would later be state champ.) Sheryl farmed with horses and their hippie friends up the hill ate puppies because the Indians had done that. The Nimses found they didn't like to kill pigs or cows but they could kill goats. Goats were stupid. When it came time Larry would lead the goats they'd raised to a hollow and throw out grain for the one they'd chosen to eat that winter, and then he'd balance his rifle on a fence post 15 feet away and aim for the head. Sheryl cooked the goat and canned it, and the dogs ate the bones.</p>
        <p>No chain saws. Chain saws were noisy, they smelled. To use one was to be fully implicated in the economy of fossil fuels. The metal blade of a crosscut saw going through the trunk of a cedar made a bright song that filled their hearts. Sheryl rode horseback and Larry walked over their land with a pruning saw hung around his neck, and they were the last people they knew who did physical eradication of weeds, pulling, no chemicals, and Sheryl wore nothing at all in the summer, even rode the horse naked. And when a surveyor came across the land one day and asked for a glass of water, Sheryl walked calmly back to the house with him in tow, naked as Eve before the fall, and got it for him in the house.</p>
        <p>No phone. No electricity. Their lives were harder than the lives the University of Oregon had trained them for, but they were sinewy people, they liked things hard, and they abided by the frontier ethos: tolerance and distance. Everyone is escaping something. Mind your own business. Don't crowd him. Don't come on strong. Don't drop in, don't touch. A handshake means a lot more here than it does other places. Pay attention to the No Trespassing sign.</p>
        <p>THE HIPPIES WEREN'T THE ONLY PEOPLE IN northern Idaho who were convinced that society was out of whack.</p>
        <p>There was Paul Palmer, tall and wry, who came from New Mexico in the 60's. He was an electrician by training, but now lives and farms with his family on Clear Creek, a remote spot 17 miles from Kamiah. "After the Watts riots our feeling was that things were not right," he says. "But you don't wait for a crisis and then put up a tent in the wilderness. You go early and get prepared." For a time he pulled two of his boys from the public schools in Idaho because, he says, "a full-fledged Communist and a sex pervert" were teaching there. Meanwhile, his studies of the law convinced him that the Federal Government had grossly overstepped its limits.  The income tax was voluntary, as he read the law. His refusal to file a 1040 form made it hard for him to find work.</p>
        <p>"After my difficulties with the I.R.S,, I was in the ragbag," he says. So he learned the ways of the land -- how to farm with horses and dry fruit and grow beans.</p>
        <p>Steve Majors, 41, came from Illinois and settled on a hillside not far from Palmer's place. He also began to read law books. "When I was farming, I began to have a conviction from God about not being on Social Security," he tells you. "You farm your land, when you're too old to farm it your son can farm it. That's your Social Security. The Government's Social Security program just didn't make sense to me. I inwardly felt the conviction that it's wrong for me to be in the system, and I better study the law to find out how best to protect myself. I started with the Bible, the basis of law in our country. The I.R.S. doesn't like my position."</p>
        <p>A few miles down the Clearwater River in the town of Stites, (Grandpa) John Brandt sold building supplies to the hippies and said that building codes were Communism. He hung the Governor in effigy outside his store. Grandpa John had a library of literature.</p>
        <p>You go to his store, Stites Ace Hardware. Grandpa John's having lunch. Just a minute. He finishes up and comes into his office, a big jovial man with antic eyebrows and a little mouth. Napkins his hands, talks about history.</p>
        <p>"Hitler didn't get started on the Jews," he tells you. "He was trying to build the country up. The reason Hitler had a problem with them, there was inflation, and everything kept falling down and the Jews picked it up, for pennies on the dollar. Did you hear the expression I'm going to Jew you? That expression didn't come out of thin air. I know a lot of people got killed, but they run that Holocaust thing ragged, and that's going to stop. Now the Indians are taking that over. The Germans got credit for killing, or blame for killing, more Jews than there were at the time. Many times over. Who do you think, when we go into debt -- who owns the Federal Reserve System? I've known this for at least 25 years. The first time people told me that, I thought, that's crazy. But they gave me books. I've spent a lot of time reading this. Roosevelt started socialism and ruined the country. I've heard one story that Eleanor shot him in the back of the head. He was with his mistress. The way this story goes -- he gave away so much to the Russians, he was sick. That's normal. We know that. But he was going to confess this and she shot him, because she was a card-carrying Communist. They said it was a cerebral hemmorhage."</p>
        <p>THE HIPPIES HAD THEIR PROBLEMS WITH THE Government, too. When a D.E.A. helicopter dips over the trees on the hillsides around Santa and looks into the gardens, Hari Heath runs from his tepee, giving them the finger with one hand and waving his assault rifle with the other.  Hari got to Idaho as a hippie. He still makes bows and arrows, but now he tells you how every commune he has seen fell apart because of inequities in power. Over the years he learned a lot from the right-wing survivalists and the local rednecks. He has learned that his ability to walk into a gun shop and buy anything he wants guarantees democracy.</p>
        <p>Hari says: "The World Bank 10 white guys socialist economic scam U.N. one world government? They're doing it very slowly. They know they can't pull it off if we maintain an armed population."</p>
        <p>Larry Nims has a less alienated view of politics. He sees the American Constitution as beautifully designed. Still, as self-reliant people, he and Sheryl have self-reliant fantasies of end times. They, too, imagine the crunch, a time of bank failure, riots, social collapse. What if the dispossessed swarmed up from the lowlands? What if they came for Sheryl's canned goat and canned corn and potatoes?  Would Larry be willing to shoot them?</p>
        <p>He has met a survivalist who spoke about how you could use high land to get the drop on the hordes. And there was a way to use a handkerchief to improve your accuracy with a revolver. You wrap one corner of the handkerchief around the revolver grip, then you grip it with your hand and take the opposite corner of the handkerchief and clasp it in your teeth. Now aim the gun out from your body, strain with your mouth and your arm so you have two points of support. Here, like this. . . .</p>
        <p>IN THE 1980'S IDAHO became strongly identified with right-wing apocalypticism. This was in large part because of the presence in the panhandle of Richard Butler, a neo-Nazi from California who bought 20 acres outside Coeur d'Alene, a short drive east of Spokane, Wash., and founded the Aryan Nations. He built a compound on his land, and it became an outpost of Christian Identity thinking, which generally holds that white Christians are the true Israelis; that blacks and other people of color are mud people, soulless animals; that Jews are the mongrelized descendants of Esau, hated by God, and that homosexuals should be exterminated. Conspiracies abound: notably, that the Government is controlled by a corrupt Babylonian system that includes the Jewish Defense League, the Anti-Defamation League of the B'nai B'rith, the Council of Foreign Relations and the Trilateral Commission.</p>
        <p>Today Richard Butler is 75 and in seeming decline, but he will spend an hour or two with you in his compound (even if you have identified yourself as a Jew). A fuzzy, crocheted swastika turns slowly in the window, his German shepherd, Bonn, rests nearby and Butler lays out the finer points of neo-Nazi practice.</p>
        <p>"We had a cross lighting down there----"</p>
        <p>"Most people call it a cross burning."</p>
        <p>"Well, Jesus Christ is the light of the world, he's the one who removes the darkness, so we call it a lighting. We don't burn the cross, we just light it."</p>
        <p>"Gasoline?"</p>
        <p>"No we use diesel oil. Wrap the cross in burlap. Light it, and the cross itself still stands."</p>
        <p>"So it's the same cross year after year?"</p>
        <p>"Oh yeah."</p>
        <p>Ten years ago Butler was more puissant. He reached out to prisoners and other rootless young men with terrifying warnings about the crippling of the white race. Homosexuality is financed by the Jews, he'd say. That's why you never see a poor homosexual. . . . Pregnant black women are coming by the millions to your neighborhood, he'd say. "Want to live in an all-white area?" Idaho beckons you. Butler and other Identity spokesmen envisioned the Idaho panhandle as the center of "a territorial imperative," a nation embracing portions of five Northwestern states in which blacks, Jews and Indians would have few rights and face deportation or worse. In "The Politics of Righteousness," a study of Idaho extremists, James A. Aho says Butler's training included living off the grid: "survivalist workshops, and classes in health, diet, food storage and nuclear protection."</p>
        <p>The growing prominence of the Aryan Nations in the early 1980's presented the Coeur d'Alene community with a dilemma: leave Butler alone or come out against him. Civic leaders spoke of the state's tradition of tolerance. Ignore him and his appeal will die away. Besides, in northern Idaho his anti-Government views were widely shared.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the debate were some Coeur d'Alene residents who organized as the Kootenai County Task Force on Human Relations. They came together in 1981 after a restaurant owned by a Jewish family was daubed with swastikas. The activists wanted to publicize Butler's message and decry it. At great personal risk -- one task force leader's house was bombed as he sat in his living room -- they spoke out against the Aryan Nations.  And later they supported the first prosecution of an Aryan Nations follower after the man, a devotee of Hitler's, issued biblically inflected threats to a young white man whose mother had married a black man.</p>
        <p>Inevitably Butler seeded violence. In 1984 a group linked to the Aryan Nations and calling itself the Order went on a crime spree of bank robberies and bombings and killings, notably the murder in June of that year of a Denver radio talk-show host -- an outspoken liberal, and a Jew -- named Alan Berg. The group's leader, Robert Jay Matthews, wrote: "I realized that white America, indeed my entire race, was headed for oblivion unless white men rose and turned the tide."</p>
        <p>By December 1984, when Matthews died in a fiery shootout with the police on Whidbey Island in Washington, the Kootenai County Task Force was no longer lonely. Developers and the owner of several panhandle newspapers were on its side. The Nazis in the neighborhood were now a quality-of-life issue. "We had three problems," Marshall Mend, a local real-estate developer, said in "Stand Up to Hate Crimes," a 1991 documentary celebrating the task force's first 10 years. "One, our community's image was being destroyed by the media. Two, we saw minorities being discouraged from moving to the area. Three, we saw these same articles encouraging racists, bigots and other hate groups to move into our area."</p>
        <p>Law-enforcement agencies were at first rather slow to respond. The F.B.I. was "absolutely . . . behind the ball" on the Order, recalled Wayne Manis, then the special agent in charge of the F.B.I.'s Coeur d'Alene office. But officials were far better organized when a second Order group with connections to the Aryan Nations began a crime spree in 1986, setting off several bombs in the Coeur d'Alene area and threatening greater destruction: bombs for gay discos in Portland, cyanide for the water supply of Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>"The F.B.I. did Order 1," says Tony Stewart, the current president of the Kootenai County Task Force. "Order 2 was F.B.I., A.T.F., Secret Service, the sheriff's office and the state police."</p>
        <p>Stewart grows enthused describing this phalanx. Liberals are comfortable with government. And the Kootenai County task force worked closely with the state, helping legislators in Boise, for example, to pass far-reaching state hate-crimes laws in the 1980's. Incidents of racist graffiti and harassment dropped sharply, and the hive of angry young men at the Aryan Nations began to decamp to a less sensitized region 60 miles away: the flats of Sanders County in Montana.</p>
        <p>Coeur d'Alene began to earn recognition for its achievement. Its Mayor went to New York City in 1987 to accept a civic award from the Raoul Wallenberg Committee of the United States. The F.B.I. was all over northern Idaho; they weren't going to be surprised again. The agency, Wayne Manis says, had run up against "without a doubt the best organized and most serious terrorist threat that this country has ever seen." That the F.B.I. itself was feeling a little apocalyptic might explain the Government's actions on Ruby Ridge, the bloody standoff with the Weavers.</p>
        <p>OCTOBER. BLACK HOUNDS are baying outside. The barrel stove is going. Cougar and bear skins are draped over the couch. You're in the cabin of Jackie and Tony Brown in the hills not far from Naples, 70 miles north of Coeur d'Alene, not far from Ruby Ridge. The Browns were good friends of the Weavers.</p>
        <p>"The Weavers were a curious blend of religious holy rollers and tactical soldiers of God, plus reactionaries," Tony says. "They reacted to things around them. So you're on the defensive, things aren't going the way you want them to do. Which is why I dropped out of the egomaniac-driven society in Oregon and followed a path of my own. But Weaver believes the Bible tells people of the knowledge and that they should expound that knowledge to their brothers and sisters. Form a body of true believers. Part of their life was sharing with people what they thought. They weren't pushy, but they thought a remnant or small group of people would bring about a new kingdom. Over the sheep type."</p>
        <p>"The sheeple," Jackie says.</p>
        <p>"Randy thought everyone was in for higher taxes, more restrictions, erosion of rights till you were a slave," Tony says. "One thing that sets his mental tone, he was a believer in absolute truth. I think the truth is pretty relative to what you know, two ideas can coexist. He was an idealist. The mission's right, we're going to do it."</p>
        <p>Jackie says: "He was an all-American guy to the core. An angry, orientated farmer's kid."</p>
        <p>In 1983, Randall Weaver was a machinist at the John Deere plant in Waterloo, Iowa. Vicki Weaver was an executive secretary. They studied religion but wanted no part of churches. He was a thin man with cavernous, troubled eyes and a strong jaw. He had trained as a Green Beret in demolitions. His wife was pretty and small, with dark hair and a wide face. She was more studious, she was the scripturalist. They were both intense, they both talked religion, they drew people to them. Don't believe me, Randall Weaver would say, according to later testimony at his trial. (Weaver declined to be interviewed.) Decide for yourself if this is the truth. But he knew it was the truth himself.</p>
        <p>They learned that in the Idaho panhandle, they could find a mountaintop and live off the grid. There they could weather the chaos of martial law and the downfall of democracy. They would be there when the great tribulation came. Because in Matthew 24, it says, "When you see the abomination of desolation, which was spoken of by Daniel the prophet, stand in the holy place, then let them which be Judee's flee into the mountains."</p>
        <p>They learned about the Great Illuminati that rules in Babylon, they learned about the Trilateral Commission and Council on Foreign Relations that are pushing one world government.</p>
        <p>Which is spoken of in Revelation: "I saw a beast rising out of the sea, with 10 horns and seven heads. . . .  One of its heads seemed to have a mortal wound, but its mortal wound was healed, and the whole earth followed the beast with wonder."</p>
        <p>The seven heads being the G-7. And the wounded head Germany.</p>
        <p>In the Idaho panhandle they could home-school their three children. Home schooling was illegal in Iowa. They would dehydrate food and arm themselves. Because in Luke 22:36, a man is commanded to sell his cloak and buy a sword if he have none, Randy Weaver got himself two Ruger Mini-14 semiautomatics. And a pump-action Remington shotgun. And plenty of ammo.</p>
        <p>The Weavers bought land on a knob 4,000 feet up in the Selkirk Mountains. The road up was a steep, rocky, bulldozed strip that twirled and did switchbacks. Weaver built a cabin at the top. It wasn't built to last. Did he know something? Two-by-fours and uninsulated plywood walls. Before long the 2-by-4's began to belly. A big open room with a sleeping loft, and a shed nearby where Vicki and the girls went when they were menstruating.</p>
        <p>They had a rocker on the rickety back porch, and, believing themselves to be true Israelites, they smeared the blood of a goat over their door frame to celebrate the Passover. They had a view from that porch that could make you weep for the power of God's hand. Washington and Montana you could see, and the plain of the Kootenai River Valley, and the shimmering golden white shanks of the Cabinet Mountains. Government land -- but the Weavers' private view.</p>
        <p>Vicki had visions with people's faces looming in them. She wrote a booklet called "Feed Our Sheep," setting out what she believed to be the true Hebrew names for things and explaining the way that Babylon had misnamed them. Randy told people never to say God -- God was dog spelled backward. They called God Yahweh. And Jesus was Yahshua. And the sabbath was Thursday through Friday night. Only the Judas churches had their sabbath on Sunday.</p>
        <p>When friends would listen Vicki and Randy told them of the civil war that was coming. Kevin Harris, a 15-year-old from Washington with family trouble, moved in with them, and Randy ran for sheriff of Boundary County to restore power to the locals. "The Federal income tax is the most cunning act of fraud that has been perpetrated against Americans since the introduction of paper money and the credit system," he declared.</p>
        <p>And the former executive secretary now typed letters addressed to "the Queen of Babylon."</p>
        <p>At least three times in the late 80's, the Weaver family drove south from their knob to Richard Butler's campground on Hayden Lake to attend Aryan Nations congresses. And under the dapply larches and alders and maples their children played with other children while men wandered about in Nazi regalia talking politics, and Butler gave out leaflets for "a nigger shoot" and hawked pamphlets about how the Jews were plotting to enslave the white man. There were always bikers at the congresses. Randy Weaver met a biker named Gus Magisono, 5 foot 11, 245 pounds, in a Harley T-shirt and black boots.</p>
        <p>The apocalypse came to the Weavers' mountain in the shape of a burly biker.</p>
        <p>It was the fall of 1989, and Weaver was having a hard time making it off the grid, cutting wood, doing jobs for farmers. Winter was coming on; Magisono told Weaver he could make money dealing guns. They discussed the mistakes of Order 1 and Order 2, and Magisono said he needed sawed-off shotguns. Weaver said he could get him four or five a week. He had never sold a sawed-off shotgun before in his life, but he pulled his red pickup around next to Magisono's car and got his Remington pump action from a case and pointed at the barrel.</p>
        <p>"About here." Magisono touched the barrel at 13 inches.</p>
        <p>A week later Weaver delivered two sawed-off shotguns, one of them the Remington. He said he hoped they went to street gangs. Magisono gave him $300, with $100 more to come.</p>
        <p>The Government came forward. Gus Magisono was actually one Kenneth Fadeley, whom the Feds had busted for gunrunning; Fadeley was persuaded to mount a sting on Randy Weaver. The F.B.I. wanted Weaver to do the same thing: go undercover among white supremacists. Weaver refused. So he was charged with gun peddling.</p>
        <p>Randy Weaver didn't show up for his trial. In March 1991 he became a fugitive on his mountain. Friends brought the Weavers food and gas. There came a fourth child, Elisheba, and Vicki was convinced that if Randy went down he would be killed, that they should hold the family together on top of the mountain as long as they could, come what may. The three older children carried weapons and learned to shoot them. Sam, the only boy, would shoot off his rifle in the air when strangers approached, Sam who had been home-schooled and could quote history verbatim, from the Roman era on up to the present. All the Presidents, and the Constitution too.</p>
        <p>On Aug. 21, 1992, Sam's dog ran barking after something in the woods and Sam and Randy and Kevin Harris went after him, guns drawn. Down through the thick forest, young tamarack and larch, cartridge casings and slash. At a trail crossing the dog came on three Federal marshals with twigs stuck in their bucket helmets and camouflage submachine guns in their hands.</p>
        <p>"Freeze, Randy----"</p>
        <p>Weaver cursed and ran, then the shooting began. Marshals later testified that Sam had started shooting, but another Government witness contradicted that claim. The dog was shot dead, then Sam was shot in the arm and the back. And Kevin Harris killed Deputy Marshal William Degan.</p>
        <p>That night Harris and Weaver found Sam's body. Sam, who was not five feet tall. They carried him to the menstrual shed, took his clothes off, washed him.</p>
        <p>Vicki was killed the next day. F.B.I. sharpshooters had gathered in the trees 100 yards from the cabin. Overnight, their orders had been changed. Flying out from Washington, D.C., Richard Rogers, commander of the hostage-rescue unit of the F.B.I., had ruled that any armed adult coming out of the Weavers' cabin could be shot dead. The standard rules of engagement allowed lethal force only when the target represented a threat to another person. When Randy Weaver and Kevin Harris came out to see Sam's body, an agent named Lon T. Horiuchi shot Weaver in the upper arm. Weaver and Harris rushed back to the cabin, and Horiuchi aimed again, at Harris. This round pierced a window in the cabin's open door and hit Vicki in the head as she stood holding 10-month-old Elisheba.</p>
        <p>Is this how the tribulation begins? A plywood cabin with three terrified girls, their mother lying dead in the kitchen, a bloody body covered with blankets.</p>
        <p>The next day a Government robot crawled on to the crude porch. It held a loudspeaker and microphone in one claw and a shotgun in the other. Weaver refused to acknowledge it. Not till a week later did Bo Gritz talk his way in, accompanied by Vicki's friend Jackie Brown. Weaver gave her a letter signed by the family, because he thought the whole family would die. The letter acknowledged that Kevin Harris had killed William Degan, but it said the Feds had fired first.</p>
        <p>We had run smack into a ZOG/ NEW WORLD ORDER ambush. . . .  Samuel Hanson Weaver and Vicki Jean Weaver are Martyrs for Yah-Yahshua and the White Race.</p>
        <p>Randy surrendered the following day with Gritz at his side. In the spring of 1993 at the Federal courthouse in Boise, the Government tried Weaver and Harris on charges of conspiring to kill William Degan. But for six weeks the Government was more on trial than the defendants. Lon Horiuchi said he had missed his target on both shots. The Government admitted staging photographic evidence of bullets found on Weaver's knob and was fined $10,000 by the judge for misconduct. The defense argued simply that Randall Weaver's beliefs were his own business. The jury remained out for 20 days, then acquitted Harris of everything and Weaver of everything but failing to show up for trial. Even on the gun charge, the jury concluded that the Government had set Weaver up.</p>
        <p>Later, Janet Reno ordered an investigation of the Justice Department's conduct with regard to the Weavers, top to bottom. The department has had a report in hand for some time, but has not released it. Last month, news reports based on leaks of the 542-page document say it is highly critical of Federal officials' strategy leading up to the shootings. Specifically, the report charges that the F.B.I.'s change in rules of engagement was imprecise and violated Vicki Weaver's constitutional rights.</p>
        <p>Randall Weaver has moved back to Iowa. Last fall he and his three daughters sued the Government for $52 million.</p>
        <p>IN IDAHO SURVIVALISTS TALK ABOUT WEAVER'S daughter Sara, what a good homemaker she was, what a good student. She has graduated from public high school in Grand Junction, Iowa, with honors, which, they say, demonstrates conclusively that home schooling works. Randy Weaver's supporters send Sara money, and Sara sends back a letter written on a word processor.</p>
        <p>"May our Creator bless you."</p>
        <p>What liberals there are in Idaho also talk about the Weaver children. That was the real abuse in the case, they say: the Weavers oppressed their kids, made them hostage to a feverish and paranoid ideology. Took them to an isolated mountain, made them walk around a cold knob holstered and belted with ammo. The liberals are wary of the powers of the family. To them, home schooling instills sexism -- girls do traditional homemaking activities, baking bread, making dolls from corn husks, taking care of the children. Failure to regulate home schooling has made Idaho a haven for kooks and bigots, says one big panhandle paper, The Lewiston Tribune. The Government must step in; the Government can protect children from their families.</p>
        <p>But what happens when the terrors of a paranoid, racist, anti-Semitic father are outdone by the violent abuses of a Government? What happens when the state shoots and kills a mother before her children? The liberal imagination fails, the liberal simply cannot conceive it.</p>
        <p>"The Randy Weaver incident itself was not as important as the fact that people with extremist intentions were using it to make inroads into the community," a woman in the town of Bonner's Ferry, not far from the Canadian border, tells you.</p>
        <p>"It was an aberration," Tony Stewart, the liberal activist, tells you. "He had defied a Federal court order. No one knew how the case was going to unfold. It almost had a force of its own."</p>
        <p>Stewart gives you a videotape of Bo Gritz's last news conference up at Ruby Ridge, one he held after Randy Weaver's surrender. You play it, and watch Gritz offer a stiff-armed, slant-armed salute to the skinheads at the back. "By the way, he told me to give you guys a salute," Gritz says, referring to Weaver. "He said you knew what that is."</p>
        <p>The skinheads heil him back.</p>
        <p>"THAT WAS NOT A SALUTE, THAT WAS A WAVE," Gritz is telling you. "I raised my hand like" -- he gives a little wave -- "it was a wave to them, I said, 'Hey guys,' and I got their attention, 'I really wanted to thank you.' "</p>
        <p>Late at night. A room at the Lewis Clark motel. Gritz sits in a chair wearing a leather bomber jacket. His wife, Claudia, is stretched across one of two beds.</p>
        <p>Gritz began buying land outside Kamiah early last year. He paid roughly $1,000 an acre for the 600 acres he purchased, and after putting in roads and making other improvements he offered the lots at $3,000 to $3,500 an acre for 5- to 10-acre parcels. He told followers he was trying to be Noah in the time of Lot, build an ark before it was needed. He also quoted Second Corinthians, 6:15. "Come out from them and be separate and touch not the unclean thing, and I will be your father and you will be my sons and my daughters."</p>
        <p>He promoted the venture at weekendlong survivalist workshops he hosted around the country. Called Spikes (Specially Prepared Individuals for Key Events), the workshops teach people to deal with social collapse: how to pick locks, tan hides, give birth at home. Among those who show up is a friend of Gritz's who sells literature saying the Jews intend to enslave everyone else. Pressed about this association, Gritz says he is not anti-Semitic. But he tells you that until a year and a half ago he "really wondered what the truth was" about the Holocaust -- whether the Jews died by premeditation or "by accident." Then he read what Hitler himself wrote about Jews in "Mein Kampf" and saw that it was premeditated.</p>
        <p>When Gritz's plans for Almost Heaven became known last February, they caused murmured concern in and around Kamiah, even among those living off the grid. "This has been a kind of utopia," Larry Nims says. "I worried that Kamiah will become synonymous with neo-Nazism, and who will that draw?"</p>
        <p>Seeking to allay concerns, Gritz scheduled a public meeting last August at the Kamiah High School's multipurpose room. Bill Glenn, the editor of The Clearwater Progress, collected questions ahead of time, and at the meeting Gritz answered 51. But the gathering seemed only to solidify divisions in the community. Gritz sprinkled his answers with a soldier's language -- "anal orifice," "cesspool" and "flushing your stool" cropped up in discussions of public schools, and this kind of talk bothered people. Others were upset by Gritz's comment that he hoped to work with the local members of the Nez Perce tribe, whose reservation surrounds Kamiah. The Indians, Gritz said, could teach his people how to make rope; his people could teach them how to pick locks.</p>
        <p>Two months later, reporters from around the world gathered at Almost Heaven for an impromptu press conference, and Gritz played huckster. He talked about the occasional "light snow" the hilltop gets during the "temperate" winter. (The area gets heavy snows and the road out of Kamiah is sometimes impassable, according to residents.) Gritz asserted that he probably wouldn't make money on Almost Heaven -- that his prices were well below local prices, which he said ranged from $4,500 to $10,000 an acre for raw land. This was untrue. Comparable lots of high, timbered land in the area were listed at roughly $3,200 an acre -- about what Gritz was charging -- and likely to sell for less.</p>
        <p>Gritz has his supporters in Kamiah. Bill Glenn, the Progress editor, praised Gritz in the paper as a constitutionalist and a patriot. "All I have heard him espouse are a) common sense, b) traditional values, c) fiscal responsibility, and d) limited government," he wrote.</p>
        <p>Glenn advised that people take a wait-and-see attitude, and that's what a lot of people seem to be doing. It's the way of the Idaho panhandle. A certain tolerance, a certain trust in those who distrust Government.</p>
        <p>And anyway, Bo Gritz had the myth of the Weavers on his side. He had saved Randy from almost certain self-destruction. Gritz described the scene on the mountain during the meeting at the high-school multipurpose room. He told about the girls huddled in the house, and poor Vicki Weaver's body, lying in a "puddle of blood and body fluids."</p>
        <p>THE HIPPIES WHO MOVED TO POKEY CREEK near Santa, Idaho, some time ago realized that they could never escape the system entirely. They even came to depend on it. A boy's health threatened by serious disease, girls touched inappropriately by a friendly man living in a tepee -- their families turned to state clinics for expensive cures, to the state to put the abuser in prison.</p>
        <p>Paul Palmer used to think about shooting marauders on his land on Clear Creek, but he has changed, too. He has come to believe in a kind of community. If people flee the cities, he imagines that his barrels of lentils and carrots stored in sand will be enough to feed them. Palmer's on the grid a little now. He got electricity from the Government, the Rural Electrification Administration. "That's socialism, yes," he says. "But you can't be a purist."</p>
        <p>Even on the frontier, ideas of community assert themselves. The romance of self-reliance will always summon Americans, but in the end it is still a romance. Even off the grid, people find themselves connected. Randy Weaver did run for sheriff.</p>
        <p>Sheryl and Larry Nims used to think the crunch was likely and soon. Then they got to where they felt they could handle almost any scenario, and they stopped worrying about it. Their son Asa is married now. He lives in Boise, he works in computer graphics and they're mighty proud of him.  Philip Weiss is a contributing writer to the Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Philip Weiss is a contributing writer to the Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
