<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evolution Of Humans May at Last Be Faltering</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="748727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHEOLOGY AND ANTHROPOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GENETIC ENGINEERING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D9133AF937A25750C0A963958260" item-length="1422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evolution Of Humans May at Last Be Faltering</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NATURAL evolutionary forces are losing much of their power to shape the human species, scientists say, and the realization is raising tantalizing questions about where humanity will go from here.</p>
        <p>Is human evolution ending, ushering in a long maturity in which Homo sapiens persists pretty much unchanged? Or will humankind, armed with the tools of molecular biology, seize control of its own evolution?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NATURAL evolutionary forces are losing much of their power to shape the human species, scientists say, and the realization is raising tantalizing questions about where humanity will go from here.</p>
        <p>Is human evolution ending, ushering in a long maturity in which Homo sapiens persists pretty much unchanged? Or will humankind, armed with the tools of molecular biology, seize control of its own evolution?</p>
        <p>The questions have no immediate answers, but recent work by evolutionary biologists and others is bringing into focus some of the factors likely to influence humanity's fate.</p>
        <p>A number of experts say that Homo sapiens is becoming increasingly disengaged from the forces of natural selection and speciation, the key processes that brought humankind into existence. Until quite recently on the evolutionary time scale, those processes bound humans to the confined and perilous existence of hunter-gatherers. But the explosion of human culture, already in full flower in the cave art of Europe some 35,000 years ago, has enabled the human species to liberate itself gradually from the harsh forces of natural selection.</p>
        <p>"Natural selection has to some extent been repealed" in the case of humans, says Dr. Steve Jones, a geneticist at University College London. Most social changes "seem to be conspiring to slow down human evolution," he argues in a recent book, "The Language of Genes: Solving the Mysteries of Our Genetic Past, Present and Future" (Anchor Books, 1994).</p>
        <p>Natural selection shapes species by choosing the fit over the unfit, generation after generation. Individuals born with advantageous genetic changes survive and have more progeny, while those who lose out in the genetic lottery may perish before breeding age.</p>
        <p>The human line, until the relatively recent weakening of evolutionary pressures, evolved to exploit a life as hunters and gatherers. One major selective force on its emergence was climatic change. It was a global cooling around five million years ago, many paleontologists believe, that shrank the forests of Africa and induced the forebears of the human line -- those genetically predisposed to do so -- to walk upright and forage across the savanna.</p>
        <p>Other environmental disruptions forced further adaptation, leading eventually to hunting, tool-making and language. Along the way, scientists believe, some populations became isolated by barriers of geography or habitat, and they evolved differently enough to split into new species. Many species probably arose as the human line evolved, but only one now remains.</p>
        <p>Homo sapiens, the survivor, is departing from the script of natural selection in a number of ways, experts say, and evolutionary forces on humans consequently have weakened.</p>
        <p>For instance, lions and leopards and sabre-toothed cats do not carry off the weak and unfit as they once did. "That's no longer there," notes Dr. Elisabeth S. Vrba, an evolutionist at Yale University.</p>
        <p>Since most people now survive to reproductive age, according to one view, natural selection is being robbed of its most important raw material. If everyone survives and reproduces, no selection of the fittest can take place; in evolutionary terms, everyone is fit.</p>
        <p>Humans, some evolutionists say, have wrapped themselves in such a snug cocoon, from clothing to central heating to hurricane warning systems, that populations are largely insulated from the environmental stresses that drive evolution. Technology and medicine also tend to cancel out inherited genetic defects.</p>
        <p>Colonies, emigration and travel have also blunted the shaping forces of evolution. When a population becomes isolated by geography from the rest of its species, it is most likely to evolve independently and eventually become a new species.</p>
        <p>"Homo sapiens today is in a mode of intermixing rather than of differentiation, and the conditions for significant evolutionary change simply don't exist -- and won't, short of some all-too-imaginable calamity," writes Dr. Ian Tattersall, a paleoanthropologist at the American Museum of Natural History in New York, in "The Fossil Trail" (Oxford University Press, 1995).</p>
        <p>For Dr. Tattersall, the most striking factor in the relaxation of evolutionary pressures is the mobility of humans in the modern world. "What you have is a species that is spread over a huge variety of environments. There is no barrier that humans cannot cross now."</p>
        <p>Humans are intermixing more than ever before, marrying people born in locations farther away and generally eliminating the isolation of populations that leads to speciation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stephen Jay Gould, an evolution expert at Harvard University, puts it this way, "We are not likely to speciate unless we send up some space colonies."</p>
        <p>All this suggests to some scientists that human evolution is winding down and that humankind faces a long period of evolutionary stasis. "The biology of the future will not be very different from that of the past," Dr. Jones wrote. Humans, in his judgment, will never be superhuman; no X-ray vision, Superman strength or ability to fly lies in the future.</p>
        <p>Differences in fertility rates may have become an evolutionary factor relatively recently, Dr. Jones and others say. Among urban middle-class people, birth rates have dropped in the last two centuries, while they have remained high among many poorer groups, especially the more numerous rural people of the third world. Because the rural poor on average have more children per parent, and the children are more likely to survive than was the case not so long ago, they have become more successful than their middle-class urban compatriots in passing on their genes.</p>
        <p>The evolutionary impact of these fertility factors is unclear, scientists say. One possibility, they say, is that if the global population doubles before stabilizing late in the next century as United Nations demographers predict, the more prolific groups will expand rapidly and genetically overwhelm the less prolific, who generally are more likely to be shielded from evolutionary pressures. Another possibility is that after the population explosion has run its course, the majority of humanity will gradually be shielded from natural selection -- albeit with an altered genetic profile.</p>
        <p>The fertility factors may already be weakening. United Nations demographers say third world birth rates are dropping so rapidly that on average, they will reach the "replacement level" of a little more than two births per woman of child-bearing age in all countries within the next 50 years. If so, the evolutionary importance of fertility differences would be sharply reduced. However, they would not be eliminated if, as seems certain, some individuals continue to have more children than others.</p>
        <p>Some evolutionary biologists believe humans will eventually take their future firmly into their own hands through genetic engineering. Once the 100,000 human genes are mapped in detail, "we will be in position to choose our own course of evolution," said Dr. Edward O. Wilson of Harvard University.</p>
        <p>Whether to intervene in that course deliberately is a political and moral issue, and Dr. Wilson says the decision may be to do nothing. If it is otherwise, "at that point, Darwinian natural selection will have ceased," he said, adding: "I don't think the human species will ever go extinct. I think we'll find the wisdom to put ourselves on the course of near-infinite tenancy of the earth."</p>
        <p>All but 1 percent of all species that have ever lived are now extinct, but many, in Dr. Jones's words, "stayed unchanged as living fossils" for much of their species lifetimes. He said humans would probably also become living fossils, their evolution complete, "but fossils that redesign their own environment to stay alive."</p>
        <p>While it may seem as if humans are indeed transcending natural selection, a longer view of evolution might take into account occasional but devastating events like ice ages, the movement of continents and the impacts of asteroids and comets.</p>
        <p>Some scientists fear that humans themselves may be creating a disaster of similar scale by destroying natural habitats worldwide and risking the onset of climate change set off by industrial pollutants. Natural or man-made calamities would have profound evolutionary implications for all life, including humans.</p>
        <p>For now, Dr. Tattersall writes,  given the absence of either a natural calamity or any sign that the human form is evolving further, "we shall have to learn to live with ourselves as we are. Fast."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
