<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Price of Global Warming? Debate Weighs Dollars and Cents</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY EFFICIENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDB103BF933A25753C1A963958260" item-length="1503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Price of Global Warming? Debate Weighs Dollars and Cents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF the world's climate is warming because of the burning of fossil fuels, how much will it cost to fix the problem? And is the fix worth the cost?</p>
        <p>Some economists say that reducing emissions of heat-trapping carbon dioxide by 20 percent, as has been proposed to nations that signed the the 1992 climate treaty, would crimp the economy, reducing the gross domestic product of the United States by 1 percent to 2 percent.  Others are more upbeat, saying that simply making energy production more efficient would take care of the problem -- at a net profit to the economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF the world's climate is warming because of the burning of fossil fuels, how much will it cost to fix the problem? And is the fix worth the cost?</p>
        <p>Some economists say that reducing emissions of heat-trapping carbon dioxide by 20 percent, as has been proposed to nations that signed the the 1992 climate treaty, would crimp the economy, reducing the gross domestic product of the United States by 1 percent to 2 percent.  Others are more upbeat, saying that simply making energy production more efficient would take care of the problem -- at a net profit to the economy.</p>
        <p>The debate over the costs and benefits of averting climate warming has suddenly assumed new pertinence now that the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change is concluding for the first time that at least part of the global warming of the last century was probably caused by the heat-trapping greenhouse gases emitted by the burning of fossil fuel.</p>
        <p>The panel's scientists have estimated, according to recently revealed drafts of a new report, that the world's average surface temperature will rise by 1.4 to 6.3 degrees Fahrenheit over the next century unless emissions of carbon dioxide are reduced, and that this amount of warming will probably cause widespread dislocations in the economies and environments of nations.</p>
        <p>The economic argument over how best to address these consequences will come to a boil starting tomorrow in Montreal, where a subgroup of the intergovernmental panel is to meet for three days to draw up its final report to policy makers on the costs and benefits of reducing greenhouse gases. The intergovernmental panel's mission is to advise the parties to the 1992 treaty.</p>
        <p>As the Montreal meeting convenes, there appears to be a wide measure of agreement on one major point: that the world has significant opportunities to control emissions by making its energy system more efficient, and that these opportunities should be seized. Since energy efficiency is desirable for economic reasons, many economists argue, achieving it in the interest of heading off global warming amounts to a policy of "no regrets."</p>
        <p>But there the arguments begin.</p>
        <p>One school of thought holds that by carrying out the available means of improving energy efficiency, likemore efficient automobiles, emissions could be reduced by 60 percent over the next few decades. At the same time, according to this analysis, the more efficient use of energy would increase the gross domestic product by 1 percent to 2 percent.  This gain does not include the benefits of averting the damage caused by climate change.</p>
        <p>On the other side are the economic modelers, whose simulations show that reducing emissions by 20 percent below 1990 levels by the year 2010 would reduce the gross domestic product of the United States by 1 percent to 2 percent. This calculation also does not include the benefits of reduced damage to the climate.</p>
        <p>The flaw in the modelers' analysis is that it assumes that the economy is already using energy as efficiently as possible and therefore underestimates the potential of more efficient energy practices, said Dr. Florintin Krause, an author of the intergovernmental panel's chapter covering the subject. Dr. Krause is an energy economist with the International Project for Sustainable Energy Paths, a research organization in El Cerrito, Calif.</p>
        <p>The modelers reply that these efficiencies cannot be achieved on the scale that Dr. Krause believes. "We all agree there is some free lunch out there," said Dr. Richard Richels, an economist at the Electric Power Research Institute, an organization in Palo Alto, Calif., that is supported by the power industry. "What we don't agree on is how much." Dr. Richels, an expert on modeling, is also an author of the intergovernmental panel's report. "It's somewhat of a gamble as to who's right," he said. "Over time, we'll learn who's right."</p>
        <p>Another author of the panel's report, Dr. William R. Cline of the Institute for International Economics in Washington, said that even if Dr. Krause was right, the early and relatively easy "no regrets" reductions would represent a one-time windfall whose impact would not come close to solving the emissions problem in the long term.</p>
        <p>Both Dr. Richels and Dr. Cline argue that the long-term view should prevail, and this raises perplexing issues as to the timing of emissions reductions. Too large a reduction now, Dr. Richels said, could work a financial hardship on the economy by forcing it to replace physical plant and equipment with new technologies prematurely.</p>
        <p>The intergovernmental panel, in a draft report, said there would be at least two replacement cycles over the next century. Each would offer an opportunity to adopt alternative fuels and technologies like solar and wind power, electric and hydrogen-powered vehicles, fuels made from wood or grain and nuclear power if safety concerns can be met. It makes economic sense, Dr. Richels argues, to use the cheaper fossil fuels now, while investing in the research and development that can bring down the cost of alternative fuels and technologies and make them more attractive in the next investment cycle.</p>
        <p>Another point of contention has to do with the trade-offs involved in deciding whether to take stronger action sooner rather than later.  Some economists say the only economically efficient course is to make very modest emissions reductions and to delay even those. Others say this merely delays effective action, thereby favoring the economic well-being of the present generation at the expense of future ones: today's consumers would behave like grasshoppers rather than ants.</p>
        <p>Few analyses of the costs and benefits of dealing with climate change look more than a century ahead. But Dr. Cline said this was not far enough for a true reading. He said that if no emissions reductions were made, enough fossil fuel remained to allow atmospheric carbon dioxide concentrations to rise for 300 years before mixing processes in the deep ocean started to stabilize them.</p>
        <p>Placing a dollar value on the benefits of avoiding damage from climate change is an even more difficult exercise than calculating the costs.  Some experts say that in some ways it may be impossible: what is the worth, for instance, of the culture of an ocean island destroyed by rising seas? Nevertheless, a number of attempts to calculate benefits have been made. The potential damages to be avoided include, for example, agricultural losses, damage to natural ecosystems, inundation by rising seas, higher cooling bills, human illness, displacement of populations and damages from extreme weather.</p>
        <p>Typically, studies value the benefit of avoiding damages caused in the United States by a doubling of atmospheric carbon dioxide at 1 percent to 2.5 percent of the nation's gross domestic product -- roughly the same range of the modelers' estimates of cost. The benefits are probably higher for developing countries, Dr. Cline said.</p>
        <p>But he points out that if the world pursues business as usual, atmospheric concentrations will not stop at a doubling. Concentrations three centuries from now could be eight times those of today, leading to a global average temperature about 18 degrees higher than now, he said. This would return the climate to something like that of the Cretaceous period, the heyday of the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>For this scale of warming, Dr. Cline calculates that the benefits of damage prevention in the United States would amount to at least 6 percent of the gross domestic product. The benefits of modest but increasingly stringent emissions reductions would exceed the costs at first, according to his analysis. But as soon as the early efficiency gains in fossil-fuel use have been exhausted, costs would outpace benefits for a few decades before benefits again exceeded them.</p>
        <p>This calculation excludes what some scientists consider the possibility of catastrophe brought on by climate change. Some studies have suggested that a possible quadrupling of atmospheric carbon dioxide would so change the climate that the Gulf Stream would shut down. Without the Gulf Stream's warming influence, Northern Europe's climate could become as cold as that of Hudson Bay.</p>
        <p>Many scientists also warn that there is no guarantee that warming or other climatic disruptions would be gradual; the system could suddenly shift to an unstable and highly damaging state. This possibility makes the estimate of climate damages and the benefits of preventing them even more uncertain.</p>
        <p>In the face of this, many environmentalists invoke what is called the precautionary principle: although it is necessary to reduce costs as much as possible, cost should not stand in the way of whatever action is necessary to avoid the risk of catastrophe.  A draft of the policy makers' summary of the working group about to meet in Montreal says that all told, the risk of "aggregate net damage" and the adoption of the precautionary principle "provide rationales for action beyond 'no regrets.' "</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
