<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants' Brown Settles In And Enjoys the View</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="752037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, DAVE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DF103BF932A05750C0A963958260" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants' Brown Settles In And Enjoys the View</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is munching on chicken fingers in a restaurant not far from Giants Stadium and the first thing you notice about Dave Brown is that he is relaxed. He has always been talkative, friendly, smart. But last season was the first year of the Giants P.S. -- Post Simms -- and there was sometimes a hint of tension in Brown's voice.</p>
        <p>It was understandable. First, he had to battle Kent Graham for the spot left vacant when the Giants released Phil Simms. Brown was a first-round draft pick and every throw he made in training camp was supposed to be great. Graham was an eighth-rounder and every great throw he made was unexpected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is munching on chicken fingers in a restaurant not far from Giants Stadium and the first thing you notice about Dave Brown is that he is relaxed. He has always been talkative, friendly, smart. But last season was the first year of the Giants P.S. -- Post Simms -- and there was sometimes a hint of tension in Brown's voice.</p>
        <p>It was understandable. First, he had to battle Kent Graham for the spot left vacant when the Giants released Phil Simms. Brown was a first-round draft pick and every throw he made in training camp was supposed to be great. Graham was an eighth-rounder and every great throw he made was unexpected.</p>
        <p>Then came the Simms comparisons. The Giants wouldn't have lost that game if Simms was still around. Simms would never have thrown that interception.</p>
        <p>There were times last season when Brown wouldn't slide to avoid a hit just to prove he was as tough as anyone else. As time went on and his teammates began to see that he was indeed a warrior like they were, they began to follow and believe.</p>
        <p>And slowly, oh so slowly, Brown shed the Simms comparisons. Simms is his hero, but if Brown is going to write his own story he must have the freedom to do it without the comparisons. With the Giants now meeting for their off-season workouts -- and Simms firmly planted in a television studio -- Brown enters a new era in his life and a new era for Giants football.</p>
        <p>Even though Simms didn't set foot in the Giants' locker room last season, his presence was still there.</p>
        <p>"It's funny," Brown was saying now. "Last year around this time Phil was still here. I was just trying to improve myself. Then when he left, I had to battle Kent. It was a whirlwind. This year it is a lot more relaxing.</p>
        <p>"Maybe when we beat Dallas in the last game of the season last year, that got some people off my back. I think people began to believe in me more then. I think there will be comparisons between myself and Phil Simms my whole career. I understand it. That's part of life. But I can already feel the difference between now and last year. There is less tension."</p>
        <p>Those differences are that he no longer has to fight for respect. He has earned it. The older veterans who worshiped Simms now follow Brown.</p>
        <p>"When Phil left there were guys who thought, 'Phil was the man; why was he let go?' " Brown said. "I had to constantly earn their respect."</p>
        <p>That was where the refusal to slide came in. He had to take big hits to prove himself.</p>
        <p>"The veterans had Phil; they had Jeff Hostetler, and then here comes this skinny little kid from Duke," Brown said. "I think I've shown them I can play. I think the team believes in me."</p>
        <p>Several great efforts and concussions later there is no question the Giants do. The transformation began as Brown grew into the job toward the end of the season. The Giants finished with six straight victories, second only to New England's seven as the longest winning streak in the league last season. Brown led the Giants to last-minute victories in three of their last four games. More than anything, those last-minute victories may have made the team believe in Brown.</p>
        <p>All of which accounts for why Brown is so relaxed and comfortable. Having lunch with him is like having lunch with your best friend; there is a sense of comfort and relaxation.</p>
        <p>Of course, now that he is the quarterback, Brown will be seen as the leader of the team. He hates the phrase "his team" but the reality is that it is his team. He will be asked his opinion on everything from the 3-4 defense to global warming. Is he ready? He laughed.</p>
        <p>"I found out last year what that was like," Brown said. "I already know what it's like to be a quarterback in New York."</p>
        <p>And he will soon know what it is like to make big money. Brown will be an unrestricted free agent at the end of next season but he would like to get a new contract before then.</p>
        <p>"I would like to play my entire career here," he said. "But obviously if we don't get it done before the season, I'd have to listen to other offers. I want to stay, though."</p>
        <p>Brown isn't very likely to be going anywhere. The Giants don't want to let their prize catch go, especially after how much he grew during the past year.  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
