<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Picture of Cold War: U.S. Spy Photos Go Public</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ESPIONAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AERIAL PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL SECURITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CLASSIFICATION OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT INFORMATION POLICIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECONNAISSANCE SATELLITES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Espionage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classification of Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF1739F936A15751C0A963958260" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Picture of Cold War: U.S. Spy Photos Go Public</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
      <dateline>McLEAN, Va., Feb. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Their acquisition cost billions. They number in the millions, with hundreds added every day. Thousands of people have labored in secrecy to interpret them. Hundreds of spacecraft, the most advanced ever made, were lofted over the decades to make them. More than one person landed in jail for revealing something about them, one of the cold war's top secrets.</p>
        <p>Until now. Today, American spy satellite photographs came in from the cold, at least a bit, as the Clinton Administration lifted the veil on those taken between 1960, the beginning of the space-surveillance era, and 1972. The Government has never before made public a spy satellite photograph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Their acquisition cost billions. They number in the millions, with hundreds added every day. Thousands of people have labored in secrecy to interpret them. Hundreds of spacecraft, the most advanced ever made, were lofted over the decades to make them. More than one person landed in jail for revealing something about them, one of the cold war's top secrets.</p>
        <p>Until now. Today, American spy satellite photographs came in from the cold, at least a bit, as the Clinton Administration lifted the veil on those taken between 1960, the beginning of the space-surveillance era, and 1972. The Government has never before made public a spy satellite photograph.</p>
        <p>More than 800,000 images are to be released -- for sale in photographic form and free of charge over the Internet, the global electronic computer network, at the address http:/ /edcwww.cr.usgs.gov/dclass/ dclass.html.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, who as a Senator pushed for the declassification as early as 1990 and today presided over the unveiling at the Central Intelligence Agency, said the photographs were "a gold mine of hitherto unavailable data." Beside him were poster-size blowups of spy photos and behind him an engineering model of an early reconnaissance satellite.</p>
        <p>The declassification is a milestone in the decline of cold-war secrecy and is seen as a potential boon for historians, scholars, and scientists intent on studying environmental change and such geologic riddles as volcanoes and the fault lines that produce earthquakes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said civilian study of the spy photographs would "help predict and mitigate natural disasters."</p>
        <p>Perhaps most important, the photographs open a new window on environmental change over the decades. Beginning in 1972, civilian Landsat satellites started snapping shots from space, so the spy photographs will push back the environmental database by more than a decade.</p>
        <p>"You can look at snow cover, deforestation, ground cover and those kinds of things," said Bruce D. Berkowitz, a former analyst with the Central Intelligence Agency and Senate Intelligence Committee staff member who aided a Council on Foreign Relations study of intelligence data and the environment.</p>
        <p>One image released today, taken in August 1962, shows the Aral Sea before a slow ecological catastrophe ended up draining it of more than enough water to fill Lake Erie.</p>
        <p>"These kinds of photographs," Mr. Gore said, standing by the Aral image, "are what make today's event so exciting to those who study the process of change on our earth."</p>
        <p>Another released image was of the Klyuchevskaya Volcano on Russia's Kamchatka Peninsula, taken in November 1962. A C.I.A. statement said the photo "provides insight into the evolution of volcanic activity" in the wilderness of the remote promontory.</p>
        <p>President Clinton's executive order directs the declassification of imagery from the nation's first generation of spy satellites, whose code names were Corona, Argon and Lanyard.</p>
        <p>The order also calls for the Director of Central Intelligence to review other photographs in the archive "with the objective of making available to the public as much imagery as possible consistent with the interests of national defense and foreign policy."</p>
        <p>Four sample photographs were handed out today at the declassification ceremony, which was attended by spies, scientists, former C.I.A. directors and Federal officials. Eighteen months will be needed to hand over, copy, archive and prepare the rest of the images for distribution through the National Archives and the United States Geological Survey's data center in Sioux Falls, S.D.</p>
        <p>The spy-satellite era began in August 1960 when a Corona craft succeeded in taking photographs of Soviet air and missile bases and sending its film pod hurling back through the atmosphere. The photos, one of which was made public today, were fuzzy by later standards but a stunning success from the perspective of spying on a nuclear-armed foe.</p>
        <p>The released image shows a military airfield near Mys Schmidta on the Chukchi Sea in far-northeastern Russia, including a rugged coastline and a bright runway. No planes or buildings are visible.</p>
        <p>Over the years the photographs improved dramatically in quality and became one of the most important military tools of the century, along with radar and the atom bomb. Darkly, they helped locate enemy targets for nuclear bombardment. More auspiciously, they helped diffuse crises by shedding light on military enigmas.</p>
        <p>For instance, the early satellites showed that Moscow was further behind in building nuclear-armed missiles than many American experts feared.</p>
        <p>"We've spent 35 or 40 billion dollars on the space program," President Lyndon B. Johnson remarked in 1967. "And if nothing else had come out of it except the knowledge we've gained from space photography, it would be worth 10 times what the whole program has cost."</p>
        <p>Perhaps most important, the pictures of submarines, bomber bases and missile silos paved the way for East-West treaties by giving the means of verifying compliance. Interestingly, the photographs also were, and still are, high diplomatic cards, often giving the United States leverage with allies.</p>
        <p>The high secrecy was deemed vital for keeping Moscow in the dark about exactly what the satellites were able to observe, thus making it harder to outwit the spies in the sky. The photographs released today, C.I.A. officials said, give no clue of current capabilities.</p>
        <p>One of the released images shows a bomber base near Dolon, Kazakhstan, taken in August 1966. A C.I.A. statement said the photograph "demonstrates the ability of the early imagery systems to distinguish between heavy bombers and transport aircraft." Dozens of craft are plainly visible on the airfield's main parking apron, but to the untrained eye there is no distinction between the types of aircraft.</p>
        <p>The photo archive that is being released includes images whose best resolution is 6 feet, and the worst 560 feet. These wide area shots, taken by systems like Argon, were used for area surveillance and mapping. All told, the collection includes 2.1 million feet of film.</p>
        <p>By contrast, images from current spy satellites are said to have an resolution down to inches. One from a Keyhole 11 satellite that was illegally released by Samuel L. Morison, a Navy analyst who later went to jail, has a resolution of about one foot and shows a Soviet nuclear-powered aircraft carrier under construction.</p>
        <p>"The cold war is over," Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>"Selectively declassifying information we already have gathered during this period is a common-sense way to address new threats," he added, including the depletion of "water supplies and the ozone layer, large-scale destruction of forests, and global warming linked to pollution."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
