<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="765260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D7153BF93BA15756C0A963958260" item-length="3480" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSIC BARRON ARTS CENTER Listen Up! -- a group of four jazz and blues musicians -- performs as part of the final concert in the "Let the Good Times Roll" series. Friday at 8 P.M. Admission: $5, or $4 for the elderly. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (908) 634-0413. CAPE MAY MUSIC FESTIVAL The Cape May Festival Orchestra. Wednesday at 8:30 P.M., Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. FRELINGHUYSEN ARBORETUM The Morris County Park Commission presents "Big Band Express." Next Sunday at 3 P.M. Free. 53 East Hanover Avenue, Morris Township. (201) 326-7600. JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Great Questions -- Great Answers," featuring Beethoven's Ninth Symphony, is the final performance of the Ars Musica Chorale's 10th season. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20, or $15 for students and the elderly. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. MARGATE LIBRARY The Festival Chorus, conducted by Paul McKay, performs American and patriotic music to celebrate Memorial Day. Today at 3 P.M. Free. 8100 Atlantic Avenue, Margate. (609) 822-4700. MAURICE LEVIN THEATER Barbara Cook sings a mix of pop songs and show tunes. Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M. Tickets: $25. 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. (201) 736-3200. MORRISTOWN UNITARIAN FELLOWSHIP The annual jazz picnic with the Eddie Hazell Trio. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $14. 21 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (201) 540-1177. OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS The Sammy Kaye Orchestra, conducted by Roger Thorpe, with vocals by the Kaydettes. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035. ST. JOSEPH'S CHURCH THe Morris Choral Society, conducted by R. Wayne Walters, performs Haydn's "Creation." Next Sunday at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Main Street, Mendham. (201) 895-4142. TENAFLY MIDDLE SCHOOL The North Jersey Symphony Orchestra presents its annual spring concert, featuring the works of Herold, Borodin, Handel and Dvorak. Saturday at 8:15 P.M. Tickets: $10. Jefferson and Columbus Avenues, Tenafly. (201) 384-9778. TRINITY COVENANT CHURCH Holly Weiss, soprano, and Marion Pedersen, organist, present a benefit concert of opera and oratorio favorites. Next Sunday at 5 P.M. Tickets: $10. 343 East Cedar Street, Livingston. (201) 992-4044. VILLAGERS THEATER The Garden State Opry presents a concert with old and new country songs, bluegrass, clog-dancing and gospel music with a country twist. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $7.50, or $5 for children. (908) 274-2748. WESTMINSTER CHOIR COLLEGE Conducted by Frank Abrahams, the Westminster Conservatory Chorale will perform the works of Mozart, Mendelssohn, Rachmaninoff and Stephen Sondheim. Next Sunday at 4 P.M. Free. The Playhouse on the campus of Westminster Choir College of Rider University, 101 Walnut Lane, Princeton. (609) 921-2663. THEATER BARN THEATER "Follies," a musical by Stephen Sondheim and James Goldman. Today at 3 P.M. and Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Skyline Drive, Montville. (201) 334-9320. CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire" with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341. CIRCLE PLAYHOUSE "The Final Word: The Hall-Mills Murders," written and directed by Nick Pelino Jr. Today at 2 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $10. 416 Victoria Avenue, Piscataway. (908) 968-7555. CROSSROADS THEATER COMPANY "Genesis 1995: A Celebration of New Voices in African-American Theater," a series of performances: "The Quadroon Ball," by Damon Wright, Wednesday at 8 P.M.; "A Portrait of the Artist as a Soul-Man Dead," by Jake-ann Jones, Thursday at 8 P.M.; "Originals Rags," a musical by Michael Dinwiddle, Friday at 8 P.M.; "Servant of the People, the Rise and Fall of Huey P. Newton and the Black Panther Party," by Robert Alexander, Saturday at 8 P.M., and "Blues Train, A Play With Music," by Ronald Wyche, next Sunday at 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $15. 7 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 249-5560. FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH The Aberdeen/Matawan Repertory Theater presents "Tribute," a comic drama. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M., next Sunday at 3 P.M. and June 9 and 10 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Route 34 at Franklin Street, Matawan. (908) 583-1093. GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE "Of Mice and Men." Tuesday through Thursday at 11 A.M.; Friday at 11 A.M. and 8 P.M.; Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $30, $26 and $22. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 246-7717. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The National Stage Company presents Sam Shepard's "Fool for Love" and Strindberg's "Miss Julie." Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $18, or $14 for students and the elderly. Matinees are $15 and $12. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 489-0322. MODERN JEWISH REPERTORY THEATER "Two," by Ron Elisha. Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through June 11. Tickets: $25. Blooming Grove Theater, 544 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 325-8154. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL "Love's Labour's Lost." Tuesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 10. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University. 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-3278. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Lerner and Loewe's "Brigadoon." Today at 3 and 8 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. Tickets: $29 to $44. (201) 376-4343. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY The Celtic Theater Company presents John B. Keane's "Sharon's Grave." Today at 2 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M., next Sunday at 2 P.M., June 9 and 10 at 8 P.M. and June 11 at 2 P.M. Tickets: $9, or $7 for students and the elderly. (201) 761-9790. SOMERSET VALLEY PLAYHOUSE "Inherit the Wind." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 18. Tickets: $10 on Friday and Sunday; $12 on Saturday. Route 514, Amwell Road, Hillsborough. (908) 369-7469. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART FORMS "Paintings, Works on Paper and Sculpture," with works by Richard Stout, John Kochansky, Boris Zherdin and Paul Hirsch. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Through Wednesday. 16 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (908) 530-4330. ART WORKS Paintings of Dante's "Inferno," by Eric Fowler. Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays through June 24. Opening reception today at 3 P.M. 19 Everrett Alley, Trenton. (609) 394-9436. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Wilderness of Waves," featuring the oils and watercolors of John Powers. Today, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Exposure," an exhibition of photographs by Carol Seitz. Through Friday. Tuesday through Friday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. Opening reception today, 3 to 6 P.M. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CRAFTSMAN FARM "Time of Transition: Textiles of the Arts and Crafts Movement" displays a variety of textiles, including table scarves, pillow covers, pocketbooks, bedspreads and clothing. Through next Sunday. Thursday, noon to 3 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for students and the elderly. Route 10 and Manor Lane, about three miles west of Route 287, Parsippany. (201) 540-1165. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007. EXTENSION GALLERY Cast metal sculptures will be on display in "Concavo -- Concave" through Thursday. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Johnson Atelier Building, 60 Ward Avenue Extension. Mercerville. (609) 890-7777. GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Opening reception on Saturday, 6 to 8 P.M. Through July 1. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Omaha -- An Artist's Journey: Memories of D-Day," with drawings and collages by Ugo Giannini. Through next Monday. Tuesday through Thursday, 6 P.M. to 8 P.M.; Friday, 10 A.M. to noon; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Through June 25. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. JAZZ 88 GALLERY An exhibition of paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880. KERYGMA GALLERY "A Sense of Place," works by Townsend Howe, a realist painter with an impressionistic style. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Through June 10. 38 Oak Street, Ridgewood. (201) 444-5510. LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photgraphs by H. Lisa Solon. Starts Friday; through June 29. Opening reception on Saturday, 2 to 5 P.M. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the paper-making town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through June 11. Admission: $3, or $2 for the elderly. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College, 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through June 25. "Still Life Works from the Collection" features 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission, $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found," an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimensional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through July 2. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through July 2. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through June 11. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through June 18. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. RIVERRUN GALLERY "Face -- Feelings," 40 works in oil, watercolor and mixed media by Edward Adams. Through next Monday. Noon to 5 P.M. daily. Closed on Tuesdays. 287 South Main Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-3349. SHOESTRING GALLERY "Hung Up," paintings and sculptures by Bill Barrell. Through June 17. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STEAMROLLER GALLERY Paintings by Sara Pasti. Through June 10. Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 52 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-7279. TRENTON CITY MUSEUM The Trenton Artists Workshop Association presents the mixed-media work of Katharine Bruce. Through next Sunday. "When Trenton Baseball Roared Like Thunder" and "Extra Innings." Through next Sunday. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Parkside Avenue and West State Street, Trenton. (609) 989-3632. UNTITLED (#130), LTD Paintings, sculpture and photography by Joanna Thompson, Jennifer Freid and Frank Fernicola. Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Shine On," color photographs of last year's solar eclipse. Through Tuesday. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. Free. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WYCKOFF GALLERY "Spring Rhapsody," featuring traditional and abstract works in various media. Through June 12. Tuesday through Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436. SPOKEN WORD BELLEVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Linda Heimall, an opera singer, will give four lectures on opera: "The Birth of Opera" on Wednesday at 1 P.M., "The Age of Bel Canto" on June 7, "The French Opera" on June 14 and "Opera Becomes Real Verismo" on June 21. Free. 221 Washington Avenue, Belleville. (201) 450-3434. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS Sharon Gill, curator of the center, is the featured speaker in "Just About Art," an open forum on art issues, which includes a tour of "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video" exhibition. Tuesday at 7:30 P.M. Free. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Birdwatching for Beginners," a three-part lecture series with two field trips. Wednesday and June 7 and 14, all at 7:30 P.M.  The field trips are on June 10 and 17 from 8 to 11:30 A.M. Fee: $30. Titus Mill Road, Pennington. (609) 737-3735. FOR CHILDREN ARTS MAPLEWOOD "Art in Park," an art fair for children of all ages. Local artists lead children in workshops on papermaking, origami, color pencil techniques, pottery wheels, sculpture, mural painting and pastel drawing. Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Free. De Hart Park, 120 Burnett Avenue, Maplewood. (201) 378-2133. HENRY HUDSON REGIONAL HIGH SCHOOL A Tri-District Music and Art Fair will display more than 150 multimedia works by local elementary, middle school and high school art students. Thursday at 6:30 P.M. The exhibition will be followed by a choral and band concert at 7 P.M. Both events are free. 1 Grand Tour, Highlands. (908) 872-0900. HERITAGE DAYS FESTIVAL Food, arts and crafts, dancing, music, a puppet theater and other activities for children are some of the attractions of Trenton's 17th annual Heritage Days Festival. The festival is held on the streets of downtown Trenton and in Mill Hill Park. Saturday, 1 to 9 P.M., and next Sunday, 1 to 7 P.M. Free. (609) 695-7107. MEADOW THEATER "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe." Saturday at 11 A.M. and June 10 and June 17 at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M. and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Bird Cages," for children 6 to 10. Children will make a pyramid-shaped bird cage and decorate a bird to be housed inside. Tuesday, 3:45 to 5:15 P.M. $20, with materials fee included. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. OAKES MEMORIAL OUTREACH CENTER The Stony Hill Players present "You're A Good Man, Charlie Brown" with Lucy, Snoopy and all the Peanuts gang. Today at 3 P.M. and Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: 12. 120 Morris Avenue, Summit. (908) 464-7716. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC. ART CENTER OF NORTHERN NEW JERSEY "Cartooning Illustration Forum" is a four-hour course for students 16 and up who have an interest in the basics of cartoon illustration. Next Sunday at 10 A.M. Course fee: $50. 250 Center Street, New Milford. (201) 599-2992. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through June 17. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. CAT SHOW The Tristate Cat Fanciers of New Jersey present their eighth annual judging ring championship show. Today, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $5, or $4 for the elderly. Westfield National Guard Armory, 500 Rahway Avenue, Westfield. (201) 379-2816. MOUNT HOPE HISTORICAL CONSERVANCY The Morris County Park Commission sponsors a guided walking tour of the historic Richard Mine Tract, the remains of an iron mining operation that began in the 1700's. Today, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. Free. Pre-registration is required. (201) 326-7644. GLEN ROCK HIGH SCHOOL AUDITORIUM The Glen Rock Arts Council sponsors "Revenge of the Creature," a 3-D film, along with a classic 1950's cartoon and newsreel. Saturday, 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $5 or $3 for students and the elderly. 600 Harristown Road, Glen Rock. (201) 670-3968. GREEK ORTHODOX FESTIVAL Kimisis Tis Theotokou Greek Orthodox Church sponsors the 19th Annual Greek Festival with food, folk dancing, raffles and imported jewelry and crafts. Friday, 5 P.M. to 11 P.M., Saturday 11 A.M. to midnight and next Sunday, noon to 8 P.M. Admission: $1. 20 Jillcrest Road, Holmdel. (908) 739-1515. RANKOKUS INDIAN RESERVATION The Pow hattan Lenape Nation presents its Annual Juried American Indian Arts Festival, with more than 100 artists and entertainers representing 50 tribes throughout the Americas. Today and tomorrow, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Tickets: $7, or $3 for the elderly. Rancocas Road, Westhampton Township, Burlington County. (609) 261-4747. Sounds of Summer Bonnie Raitt performs on Thursday with Ruth and Charles Brown. Seal and Des'ree perform on Friday.  GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER Shows at 8 P.M. Tickets $18 to $38.50. Exit 116 on the Garden State Parkway, Holmdel. (908) 888-5011.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSIC BARRON ARTS CENTER Listen Up! -- a group of four jazz and blues musicians -- performs as part of the final concert in the "Let the Good Times Roll" series. Friday at 8 P.M. Admission: $5, or $4 for the elderly. 582 Rahway Avenue, Woodbridge. (908) 634-0413. CAPE MAY MUSIC FESTIVAL The Cape May Festival Orchestra. Wednesday at 8:30 P.M., Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. FRELINGHUYSEN ARBORETUM The Morris County Park Commission presents "Big Band Express." Next Sunday at 3 P.M. Free. 53 East Hanover Avenue, Morris Township. (201) 326-7600. JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Great Questions -- Great Answers," featuring Beethoven's Ninth Symphony, is the final performance of the Ars Musica Chorale's 10th season. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20, or $15 for students and the elderly. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. MARGATE LIBRARY The Festival Chorus, conducted by Paul McKay, performs American and patriotic music to celebrate Memorial Day. Today at 3 P.M. Free. 8100 Atlantic Avenue, Margate. (609) 822-4700. MAURICE LEVIN THEATER Barbara Cook sings a mix of pop songs and show tunes. Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M. Tickets: $25. 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. (201) 736-3200. MORRISTOWN UNITARIAN FELLOWSHIP The annual jazz picnic with the Eddie Hazell Trio. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $14. 21 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (201) 540-1177. OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS The Sammy Kaye Orchestra, conducted by Roger Thorpe, with vocals by the Kaydettes. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035. ST. JOSEPH'S CHURCH THe Morris Choral Society, conducted by R. Wayne Walters, performs Haydn's "Creation." Next Sunday at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Main Street, Mendham. (201) 895-4142. TENAFLY MIDDLE SCHOOL The North Jersey Symphony Orchestra presents its annual spring concert, featuring the works of Herold, Borodin, Handel and Dvorak. Saturday at 8:15 P.M. Tickets: $10. Jefferson and Columbus Avenues, Tenafly. (201) 384-9778. TRINITY COVENANT CHURCH Holly Weiss, soprano, and Marion Pedersen, organist, present a benefit concert of opera and oratorio favorites. Next Sunday at 5 P.M. Tickets: $10. 343 East Cedar Street, Livingston. (201) 992-4044. VILLAGERS THEATER The Garden State Opry presents a concert with old and new country songs, bluegrass, clog-dancing and gospel music with a country twist. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $7.50, or $5 for children. (908) 274-2748. WESTMINSTER CHOIR COLLEGE Conducted by Frank Abrahams, the Westminster Conservatory Chorale will perform the works of Mozart, Mendelssohn, Rachmaninoff and Stephen Sondheim. Next Sunday at 4 P.M. Free. The Playhouse on the campus of Westminster Choir College of Rider University, 101 Walnut Lane, Princeton. (609) 921-2663. THEATER BARN THEATER "Follies," a musical by Stephen Sondheim and James Goldman. Today at 3 P.M. and Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Skyline Drive, Montville. (201) 334-9320. CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire" with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341. CIRCLE PLAYHOUSE "The Final Word: The Hall-Mills Murders," written and directed by Nick Pelino Jr. Today at 2 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $10. 416 Victoria Avenue, Piscataway. (908) 968-7555. CROSSROADS THEATER COMPANY "Genesis 1995: A Celebration of New Voices in African-American Theater," a series of performances: "The Quadroon Ball," by Damon Wright, Wednesday at 8 P.M.; "A Portrait of the Artist as a Soul-Man Dead," by Jake-ann Jones, Thursday at 8 P.M.; "Originals Rags," a musical by Michael Dinwiddle, Friday at 8 P.M.; "Servant of the People, the Rise and Fall of Huey P. Newton and the Black Panther Party," by Robert Alexander, Saturday at 8 P.M., and "Blues Train, A Play With Music," by Ronald Wyche, next Sunday at 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $15. 7 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 249-5560. FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH The Aberdeen/Matawan Repertory Theater presents "Tribute," a comic drama. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M., next Sunday at 3 P.M. and June 9 and 10 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Route 34 at Franklin Street, Matawan. (908) 583-1093. GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE "Of Mice and Men." Tuesday through Thursday at 11 A.M.; Friday at 11 A.M. and 8 P.M.; Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $30, $26 and $22. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 246-7717. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The National Stage Company presents Sam Shepard's "Fool for Love" and Strindberg's "Miss Julie." Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $18, or $14 for students and the elderly. Matinees are $15 and $12. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 489-0322. MODERN JEWISH REPERTORY THEATER "Two," by Ron Elisha. Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through June 11. Tickets: $25. Blooming Grove Theater, 544 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 325-8154. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL "Love's Labour's Lost." Tuesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 10. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University. 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-3278. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Lerner and Loewe's "Brigadoon." Today at 3 and 8 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. Tickets: $29 to $44. (201) 376-4343. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY The Celtic Theater Company presents John B. Keane's "Sharon's Grave." Today at 2 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M., next Sunday at 2 P.M., June 9 and 10 at 8 P.M. and June 11 at 2 P.M. Tickets: $9, or $7 for students and the elderly. (201) 761-9790. SOMERSET VALLEY PLAYHOUSE "Inherit the Wind." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 18. Tickets: $10 on Friday and Sunday; $12 on Saturday. Route 514, Amwell Road, Hillsborough. (908) 369-7469. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART FORMS "Paintings, Works on Paper and Sculpture," with works by Richard Stout, John Kochansky, Boris Zherdin and Paul Hirsch. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Through Wednesday. 16 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (908) 530-4330. ART WORKS Paintings of Dante's "Inferno," by Eric Fowler. Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays through June 24. Opening reception today at 3 P.M. 19 Everrett Alley, Trenton. (609) 394-9436. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Wilderness of Waves," featuring the oils and watercolors of John Powers. Today, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Exposure," an exhibition of photographs by Carol Seitz. Through Friday. Tuesday through Friday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. Opening reception today, 3 to 6 P.M. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CRAFTSMAN FARM "Time of Transition: Textiles of the Arts and Crafts Movement" displays a variety of textiles, including table scarves, pillow covers, pocketbooks, bedspreads and clothing. Through next Sunday. Thursday, noon to 3 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for students and the elderly. Route 10 and Manor Lane, about three miles west of Route 287, Parsippany. (201) 540-1165. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007. EXTENSION GALLERY Cast metal sculptures will be on display in "Concavo -- Concave" through Thursday. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Johnson Atelier Building, 60 Ward Avenue Extension. Mercerville. (609) 890-7777. GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Opening reception on Saturday, 6 to 8 P.M. Through July 1. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Omaha -- An Artist's Journey: Memories of D-Day," with drawings and collages by Ugo Giannini. Through next Monday. Tuesday through Thursday, 6 P.M. to 8 P.M.; Friday, 10 A.M. to noon; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Through June 25. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. JAZZ 88 GALLERY An exhibition of paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880. KERYGMA GALLERY "A Sense of Place," works by Townsend Howe, a realist painter with an impressionistic style. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Through June 10. 38 Oak Street, Ridgewood. (201) 444-5510. LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photgraphs by H. Lisa Solon. Starts Friday; through June 29. Opening reception on Saturday, 2 to 5 P.M. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the paper-making town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through June 11. Admission: $3, or $2 for the elderly. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College, 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through June 25. "Still Life Works from the Collection" features 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission, $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found," an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimensional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through July 2. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through July 2. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through June 11. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through June 18. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. RIVERRUN GALLERY "Face -- Feelings," 40 works in oil, watercolor and mixed media by Edward Adams. Through next Monday. Noon to 5 P.M. daily. Closed on Tuesdays. 287 South Main Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-3349. SHOESTRING GALLERY "Hung Up," paintings and sculptures by Bill Barrell. Through June 17. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STEAMROLLER GALLERY Paintings by Sara Pasti. Through June 10. Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 52 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-7279. TRENTON CITY MUSEUM The Trenton Artists Workshop Association presents the mixed-media work of Katharine Bruce. Through next Sunday. "When Trenton Baseball Roared Like Thunder" and "Extra Innings." Through next Sunday. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Parkside Avenue and West State Street, Trenton. (609) 989-3632. UNTITLED (#130), LTD Paintings, sculpture and photography by Joanna Thompson, Jennifer Freid and Frank Fernicola. Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Shine On," color photographs of last year's solar eclipse. Through Tuesday. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. Free. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WYCKOFF GALLERY "Spring Rhapsody," featuring traditional and abstract works in various media. Through June 12. Tuesday through Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436. SPOKEN WORD BELLEVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Linda Heimall, an opera singer, will give four lectures on opera: "The Birth of Opera" on Wednesday at 1 P.M., "The Age of Bel Canto" on June 7, "The French Opera" on June 14 and "Opera Becomes Real Verismo" on June 21. Free. 221 Washington Avenue, Belleville. (201) 450-3434. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS Sharon Gill, curator of the center, is the featured speaker in "Just About Art," an open forum on art issues, which includes a tour of "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video" exhibition. Tuesday at 7:30 P.M. Free. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Birdwatching for Beginners," a three-part lecture series with two field trips. Wednesday and June 7 and 14, all at 7:30 P.M.  The field trips are on June 10 and 17 from 8 to 11:30 A.M. Fee: $30. Titus Mill Road, Pennington. (609) 737-3735. FOR CHILDREN ARTS MAPLEWOOD "Art in Park," an art fair for children of all ages. Local artists lead children in workshops on papermaking, origami, color pencil techniques, pottery wheels, sculpture, mural painting and pastel drawing. Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. Free. De Hart Park, 120 Burnett Avenue, Maplewood. (201) 378-2133. HENRY HUDSON REGIONAL HIGH SCHOOL A Tri-District Music and Art Fair will display more than 150 multimedia works by local elementary, middle school and high school art students. Thursday at 6:30 P.M. The exhibition will be followed by a choral and band concert at 7 P.M. Both events are free. 1 Grand Tour, Highlands. (908) 872-0900. HERITAGE DAYS FESTIVAL Food, arts and crafts, dancing, music, a puppet theater and other activities for children are some of the attractions of Trenton's 17th annual Heritage Days Festival. The festival is held on the streets of downtown Trenton and in Mill Hill Park. Saturday, 1 to 9 P.M., and next Sunday, 1 to 7 P.M. Free. (609) 695-7107. MEADOW THEATER "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe." Saturday at 11 A.M. and June 10 and June 17 at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M. and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Bird Cages," for children 6 to 10. Children will make a pyramid-shaped bird cage and decorate a bird to be housed inside. Tuesday, 3:45 to 5:15 P.M. $20, with materials fee included. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. OAKES MEMORIAL OUTREACH CENTER The Stony Hill Players present "You're A Good Man, Charlie Brown" with Lucy, Snoopy and all the Peanuts gang. Today at 3 P.M. and Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: 12. 120 Morris Avenue, Summit. (908) 464-7716. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC. ART CENTER OF NORTHERN NEW JERSEY "Cartooning Illustration Forum" is a four-hour course for students 16 and up who have an interest in the basics of cartoon illustration. Next Sunday at 10 A.M. Course fee: $50. 250 Center Street, New Milford. (201) 599-2992. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through June 17. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. CAT SHOW The Tristate Cat Fanciers of New Jersey present their eighth annual judging ring championship show. Today, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $5, or $4 for the elderly. Westfield National Guard Armory, 500 Rahway Avenue, Westfield. (201) 379-2816. MOUNT HOPE HISTORICAL CONSERVANCY The Morris County Park Commission sponsors a guided walking tour of the historic Richard Mine Tract, the remains of an iron mining operation that began in the 1700's. Today, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. Free. Pre-registration is required. (201) 326-7644. GLEN ROCK HIGH SCHOOL AUDITORIUM The Glen Rock Arts Council sponsors "Revenge of the Creature," a 3-D film, along with a classic 1950's cartoon and newsreel. Saturday, 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $5 or $3 for students and the elderly. 600 Harristown Road, Glen Rock. (201) 670-3968. GREEK ORTHODOX FESTIVAL Kimisis Tis Theotokou Greek Orthodox Church sponsors the 19th Annual Greek Festival with food, folk dancing, raffles and imported jewelry and crafts. Friday, 5 P.M. to 11 P.M., Saturday 11 A.M. to midnight and next Sunday, noon to 8 P.M. Admission: $1. 20 Jillcrest Road, Holmdel. (908) 739-1515. RANKOKUS INDIAN RESERVATION The Pow hattan Lenape Nation presents its Annual Juried American Indian Arts Festival, with more than 100 artists and entertainers representing 50 tribes throughout the Americas. Today and tomorrow, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Tickets: $7, or $3 for the elderly. Rancocas Road, Westhampton Township, Burlington County. (609) 261-4747. Sounds of Summer Bonnie Raitt performs on Thursday with Ruth and Charles Brown. Seal and Des'ree perform on Friday.  GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER Shows at 8 P.M. Tickets $18 to $38.50. Exit 116 on the Garden State Parkway, Holmdel. (908) 888-5011.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
