<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Extra Round Will Wreck Some Arms</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="797239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD71531F931A25753C1A963958260" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Extra Round Will Wreck Some Arms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW that baseball has lurched into the extended-playoffs business, is it too late to ask what havoc the endless October may wreak upon its very best pitching arms?</p>
        <p>The war of attrition has already threatened the Mariners, who played the Indians last night in the second game of the American League championships. (I warn you: I'm going to shriek like Dick Vitale if anybody uses the phrase Final Four around me.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW that baseball has lurched into the extended-playoffs business, is it too late to ask what havoc the endless October may wreak upon its very best pitching arms?</p>
        <p>The war of attrition has already threatened the Mariners, who played the Indians last night in the second game of the American League championships. (I warn you: I'm going to shriek like Dick Vitale if anybody uses the phrase Final Four around me.)</p>
        <p>The Mariners were forced to use their superb lefty, Randy Johnson, for 19 innings -- and three victories -- in a special playoff game and a high-octane five-game round with the Yankees. They stunned Cleveland, 3-2, Tuesday, using Bob Wolcott, a rookie who had been left off Lou Piniella's first-round roster.</p>
        <p>One pitcher who has been to the land of the dangling arm is Orel Hershiser, last night's starter for the Indians. Once upon a time, Tommy Lasorda called him "Bulldog" because Hershiser's thoughtful, peaceful manner hides his combative heart.</p>
        <p>In the 1988 National League series, Hershiser pitched eight and a third innings on Oct. 4, seven innings on Oct. 8, got the last out in relief the next day, and pitched nine innings on Oct. 12.</p>
        <p>Did Hershiser have a sense of deja vu when he saw Johnson pitching so often?</p>
        <p>"That's the second time I've heard that question," Hershiser said with a smile.</p>
        <p>"It just goes to show you that when you get to this point in the season, players will sacrifice anything, and so will management," Hershiser responded. "I am sure Lou first had permission from Randy. That was kind of the way it went in '88, also. I told Tommy I was available no matter what. Fortunately, it worked out for us, and the same for the Mariners."</p>
        <p>Johnson, who pitches tomorrow in Cleveland, dominated three games with his 6-foot-10-inch frame and his brutally fast curveballs.</p>
        <p>"I was pitching on the fumes," Johnson said later. "I may have to stop for gas on the way to the ball park."</p>
        <p>In the old days, courageous pitchers like Allie Reynolds, Bob Gibson and Mickey Lolich demanded the ball as September hurtled into October. All we had in those days was a pennant race and a World Series.</p>
        <p>Could three rounds ruin some arms? When I ask the question, I get blank looks. Baseball short-sighted? How could you say that?</p>
        <p>Just look at the wonderful owners' success with labor negotiations, their machinations to use scab players last spring, and their current embarrassment of showing only one playoff game to each region of the country, thus depriving fans of the heroics in the other series. You think these owners have even considered the danger of wearing down gallant pitchers like Johnson and David Cone and Jack McDowell? They're just meat on the hoof. Office temps.</p>
        <p>Baseball is different from the three other sports with long playoffs. I can't help remembering the New York Islanders, the best team I ever covered. They won four straight Stanley Cups and then lost the 1984 finals, before the ice turned mushy. They tried blaming global warming, but then they took out their abacuses and discovered that more than one extra season was accumulated in their knees.</p>
        <p>At least hockey is democratic -- goalies, defenders and forwards all pay the price. Baseball is selectively cruel. By adding a third tier of post-season play, baseball is asking its best pitchers to perform that unnatural act 125 times or more per game -- right up to Halloween.</p>
        <p>In this expansion age, most teams have only one or two reliable starters. Star pitchers will start measuring their careers in dog years -- one equals seven. And by the way, Cone and McDowell and Johnson are highly paid stars who volunteered from their big hearts.</p>
        <p>Fans will always remember Cone firing 147 pitches on Sunday. I asked Cone afterward if his arm had any feeling in it.</p>
        <p>"Barely," he said. "I'll know more in a few days."</p>
        <p>Fans will always remember McDowell's doleful expression, like a Celtic warrior fighting for his life in a misty highland bog. He had missed two weeks with a knot in his back, pitched bravely Friday night, then came back in relief on Sunday.</p>
        <p>Will his back remember that grisly evening?</p>
        <p>At least their labors are done. Randy Johnson's could just be starting. If his arm goes, don't blame mushy ice or global warming. Blame baseball's new playoffs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
