<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Considers Toughening Its Anti-Emissions Program</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="790751"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF1431F937A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Considers Toughening Its Anti-Emissions Program</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Acknowledging that its program of largely voluntary antipollution measures is falling short of its goal, the Clinton Administration is considering tougher steps to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that cause global warming.</p>
        <p>When the Administration established the current program in 1993, it said the provisions would reduce emissions of greenhouse gases to 1990 levels by the year 2000. That would have kept the pledge made by the United States and other industrial nations when they signed the Rio de Janeiro treaty on global warming in 1992.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Acknowledging that its program of largely voluntary antipollution measures is falling short of its goal, the Clinton Administration is considering tougher steps to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that cause global warming.</p>
        <p>When the Administration established the current program in 1993, it said the provisions would reduce emissions of greenhouse gases to 1990 levels by the year 2000. That would have kept the pledge made by the United States and other industrial nations when they signed the Rio de Janeiro treaty on global warming in 1992.</p>
        <p>But with emissions rising steadily, it is becoming increasingly clear that the United States will not meet that target, especially now that Congress is moving to cut spending on energy conservation and eliminate some elements of the Administration's current efforts.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, leading scientists have said they are more certain than ever that continuing increases in emissions are warming the planet and will have major environmental consequences unless they are reined in.</p>
        <p>"We appear to be veering off the target, and a gap now exists between our goals and what current actions and funding are likely to accomplish," Stephen Seidel of the White House Council on Environmental Quality said on Friday at a hearing of the council, which is to decide by December whether to toughen its antipollution program.</p>
        <p>Groups representing oil companies, electric utilities, automobile makers and others have said that mandatory steps would be too costly and that the current program's voluntary measures need more time to work. Partly in response to that program, scores of big corporations have embarked on energy-saving measures or undertaken efforts like the planting of trees, which help clean the environment by absorbing carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>But environmental groups say the voluntary measures neglect a principal and fast-growing source of greenhouse gases: the carbon dioxide emitted by cars burning gasoline.</p>
        <p>Rather than require auto makers to increase the average efficiency of their cars, as Bill Clinton promised to do during his Presidential election campaign, the Administration last year convened a yearlong conference of environmentalists, car companies and others to seek a consensus on ways of cutting automobile pollution.</p>
        <p>But the conference broke up this week without filing a report. That development followed a refusal by the oil companies and the car makers to go along with recommendations that included tougher fuel efficiency standards and financial incentives for consumers to buy efficient cars. A group representing a majority of the conference's participants will file a report, but the consensus that the Administration sought will be lacking.</p>
        <p>At the hearing of the White House environmental council on Friday, William O'Keefe, executive vice president of the American Petroleum Institute, urged the Administration "to avoid any temptation to adopt mandatory requirements."</p>
        <p>And John Slaes, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition, a group representing industry trade associations and corporations, said, "Current voluntary programs should be given adequate time to work before any further actions are considered."</p>
        <p>But Daniel Lashoff, director of the climate program at the Natural Resources Defense Council, said these same organizations were "busily working in Congress to undermine the funding for these programs."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
