<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Ponder Causes of Breakup of Ancient Supercontinent</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="793260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTINENTAL DRIFT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURE (JOURNAL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D71339F930A35753C1A963958260" item-length="1935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Ponder Causes of Breakup of Ancient Supercontinent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE drops of water skating across a hot skillet, sometimes colliding and coalescing, sometimes splitting asunder and scattering, the earth's continents are constantly in motion.</p>
        <p>A rapidly growing body of observations has shed light on many details of the earth's continental gyrations, but a summary of conflicting theories published in the current issue of the journal Nature makes clear that many tantalizing mysteries remain to be solved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE drops of water skating across a hot skillet, sometimes colliding and coalescing, sometimes splitting asunder and scattering, the earth's continents are constantly in motion.</p>
        <p>A rapidly growing body of observations has shed light on many details of the earth's continental gyrations, but a summary of conflicting theories published in the current issue of the journal Nature makes clear that many tantalizing mysteries remain to be solved.</p>
        <p>For some 35 years scientists have known that most of the earth's activity -- the opening up of new oceans, the collision of continents and consequent raising of great mountain chains, the creation of volcanoes and islands, the accretion and splitting up of supercontinents, the destruction wrought by earthquakes and many other effects -- are traceable to the relentless movement of tectonic plates.</p>
        <p>Tectonic plates are gigantic slabs ranging from 40 to 90 miles thick, the rocky hide of the earth's lithosphere. No scientist is in doubt about the overwhelming importance for life of the movements of these vast stone slabs as they float over the planet's mantle on what is believed to be a viscous layer of molten rock.</p>
        <p>But despite growing understanding of the earth's six major tectonic plates and a host of smaller plates, scientists still must wrestle with many intractable questions about the driving forces that constantly reshape the planet's surface. Debates and disagreements have proliferated along with a flood of new data in recent years, and in the Nature article, Dr. Bryan C. Storey, a geologist at the British Antarctic Survey in Cambridge, England, presented a summary of the many divergent views concerning the role of "mantle plumes" in breaking up an ancient supercontinent called Gondwanaland.</p>
        <p>The broad question addressed by Dr. Storey was whether mantle plumes played a vital, moderate or negligible role in the disruption of Gondwanaland, an event 180 million years ago that led to the creation of today's continents. A major problem confronted by this analysis was the fact that mantle plumes themselves remain hypothetical; their existence has yet to be proved beyond doubt.</p>
        <p>The many questions about the demise of Gondwanaland remaining to be answered hinge on whether the movement of tectonic plates alone could cause the breakup of a supercontinent, or whether mantle plumes would have been needed to trigger at least some of the major rifts.</p>
        <p>Geologists presume that plate tectonics and continental drift are ultimately driven by heat generated deep within the earth from the decay of radioactive elements. But it is the visualization of a mechanism by which this heat is transformed into dynamic geological processes that sparks disagreement.</p>
        <p>A widely accepted theory is that mantle plumes are an essential part of the global heat engine. Mantle plumes, if they exist, are thought to originate at depths of about 1,800 miles beneath the earth's surface, where the liquid-metal outer core meets the lowermost part of the rocky mantle. Because of seismic sounding experiments (some of them exploiting the sound waves that penetrate the earth when underground nuclear blasts are set off), geologists know that the core is not smoothly spherical but has many irregularities, perhaps analogous to the mountain ranges on the earth's surface. It may be that core irregularities channel heat flows to produce rising plumes of molten rock capable of penetrating the thick mantle, occasionally even reaching the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>With the help of mathematical models and observations, many geologists have concluded that plumes are born just above the earth's core, and that their lower parts, some 60 miles in diameter, are shaped like the thin stems of wine glasses. As plumes approach the top of the mantle, they are believed to cool, making their molten rock so viscous that they flare out into bulbous mushroom heads some 1,200 miles in diameter.</p>
        <p>Once in a while a monster plume may break through the surface and spout an immense flood of molten basalt or other rock, many geologists believe.</p>
        <p>Such a plume or plumes may have caused the gigantic volcanic upheaval 65 million years ago that spewed lava over a 200,000-square-mile region of the Indian subcontinent known as the Deccan Traps. (Trap rock takes its name from the Swedish word trapp, a fine-grained, dark, basaltic lava. The Deccan is a region in India.)</p>
        <p>The Deccan lava flood is believed by many scientists to have caused an important geological rift, one that chopped the Seychelles Island chain away from India. Geologists have been able to trace a trail leading from the "hot spot" presumed to have caused the Deccan Traps upheaval to the present-day position of the hot spot at Reunion Island.</p>
        <p>(Some scientists, including Dr. Dewey M. McLean of Virginia Polytechnic Institute, and Dr. Charles B. Officer and Dr. Charles L. Drake of Dartmouth College in Hanover, N.H., have postulated that the Deccan Traps upheaval may have caused the mass extinctions that occurred at the end of the Cretaceous period, which included the demise of the dinosaurs. A theory proposed by Dr. McLean in 1980 was that the eruption sent such large amounts of carbon dioxide and other gases into the atmosphere that a "greenhouse" warming occurred, and the dinosaurs were unable to cope with the heat.)</p>
        <p>Dr. Asish R. Basu at the University of Rochester in New York is among the geochemists who have concluded that the lava that flooded the Deccan region originated near the boundary between the earth's core and mantle, and rose to the surface through plumes.</p>
        <p>But although the mantle plume theory of heat convection is widely accepted, "there is no direct evidence for the existence of plumes," according to Dr. Michael E. Wysession of Washington University in St. Louis, a leading geophysicist.</p>
        <p>There is strong indirect evidence for plumes, he said in an interview, but these hypothetical structures must be extremely difficult to detect with the seismic probes geologists use to try to map the earth's interior. Because plumes must be very hot, sound waves tend to be bent around them rather than being reflected to the surface as recognizable echoes, he said. "We can easily image cold objects, like the huge crustal slabs that push themselves under tectonic plates, but we can't yet see the plumes, if they're there."</p>
        <p>Not all scientists believe that plumes play roles in the transport of heat from the core to the surface.</p>
        <p>Dr. Donald Anderson of the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena, for example, theorizes that hot spots may form at relatively shallow depths when a mass of insulating rock like the Gondwanaland supercontinent blocks the normal steady flow of heat to the surface. When a shallow zone of rock is slowly heated from beneath without being able to pass its heat up to the surface, it becomes a hot spot that may finally break through the insulation above it and create a lava flood. Such a sequence of events could have initiated the breakup of the Gondwanaland supercontinent, Dr. Anderson believes.</p>
        <p>Whatever the case, geologists are at least filling in some of the details as to where and how things happened.</p>
        <p>One of the main tools scientists use to sort out chronology is the measurement of magnetic orientation in rocks. The earth's magnetic field changes constantly, sometimes even reversing itself completely, so that the north magnetic pole moves to the geographic South Pole. The orientation of the earth's global magnetic field imprints itself on certain minerals at the time they form. Geologists have determined roughly when and how the global magnetic field has changed over the eons, and can use magnetic rock data to work out the latitudes and magnetic orientation of ancient rocks at the times they formed, compared with present-day latitudes and orientation. By piecing many bits of such information together, geologist try to reconstruct the ancient reshaping of continents and supercontinents.</p>
        <p>Another method scientists use to infer geological history is to measure the ratio of a radioactive form of argon to a nonradioactive form. The rate of decay from one form to the other is known, and from this, a rough estimate can sometimes be made of the age of the rock containing argon. The decay of radioactive uranium to lead can also sometimes yield approximate ages of rock.</p>
        <p>Scientists also frequently use satellite photographs to detect the faint traces of rifting, collisions and other ancient events that have shaped the earth since its birth some 4.5 billion years ago.</p>
        <p>A sequence of sketches of earth history assembled from many sources of information suggests a succession of events in which continents crash together to form supercontinents, later splitting up into new continents, which in turn coalesce into new supercontinents.</p>
        <p>"Some people believe that these steps occur in cycles of 400 or 500 million years," Dr. Storey said.</p>
        <p>In an article published last January in Scientific American, Dr. Ian W. D. Dalziel of the University of Texas in Austin, sketched a series of transformations of a supercontinent named Rodinia that may have existed 750 million years ago, from which a normal-sized continent that would eventually be North America apparently broke loose and began wandering. All the continents drifted apart at about the same time, somehow grouping themselves 422 million years ago into two supercontinents: Laurasia (including North America, Australia, Antarctica and India) near the Equator, and Gondwanaland (including South America and Africa) in the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Up to that point, the scientific evidence is so spotty that few geologists insist on specific details.</p>
        <p>But the trail of evidence is fresher at the next stage. Scientists believe that the two supercontinents merged into a single supercontinent named Pangea around 260 million years ago, when large amphibians and reptiles ruled the land, leaving many revealing fossils.</p>
        <p>Pangea later broke up into smaller continents, but then, some 200 million years ago, the separate continents recombined in a new configuration also named Gondwanaland.</p>
        <p>In yet another transformation about 180 million years ago during the Jurassic period, east and west Gondwanaland began to part company, opening up a narrow waterway destined eventually to form the Wedell Sea in Antarctica, the Somali Basin and the Mozambique Basin.</p>
        <p>About 130 million years ago another split occurred, in which the two separated plates of Gondwanaland rearranged themselves to create a third plate, with South America separating from the African-Indian plate. Finally, about 100 million years ago, the destruction of Gondwanaland was completed when Australia and New Zealand separated from the main Antarctic land mass, and Madagascar and the Seychelle Islands separated from India.</p>
        <p>In his article, Dr. Storey concludes that "from the currently available evidence, plumes are not the ultimate driving force for continental breakup," although they may be the main cause of splitting off smaller continental blocks.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wysession said: "We've taken some big leaps in the last five years, thanks partly to the increasing power of computers, to advances in three-dimensional seismic tomography, better mineral evidence and so forth. But we still don't know why plates move as they do. We understand something about heat convection from the earth's core, but the breaking up of supercontinents is still an enigma."</p>
        <p>Dr. Storey agreed.</p>
        <p>"I don't think there's a scientific consensus on these things," he said, "but I do believe we're moving toward a resolution."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
