<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DF173EF934A15752C0A963958260" item-length="802" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A2-A10  RUSSIANS ACCUSED OF BRUTALITY  Grozny residents say Russian troops have turned increasingly brutal now that they control much of the Chechen rebels' capital.  A1  MOSCOW'S MONEY PROBLEMS GROW  Russia has dug itself into a hole with Western Governments and with the I.M.F., which is currently debating a $6 billion loan that Moscow is counting on.  A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A2-A10  RUSSIANS ACCUSED OF BRUTALITY  Grozny residents say Russian troops have turned increasingly brutal now that they control much of the Chechen rebels' capital.  A1  MOSCOW'S MONEY PROBLEMS GROW  Russia has dug itself into a hole with Western Governments and with the I.M.F., which is currently debating a $6 billion loan that Moscow is counting on.  A6</p>
        <p>AUSCHWITZ LIBERATION IS MARKED  Jewish survivors and others prayed in the memory of the million Jews who were killed by the Nazis in the Auschwitz-Birkenau death camp.  A3  German bishops say Catholics share blame for the Holocaust.  A3  NEW U.N. COMMANDER IN BOSNIA  A new U.N. commander, a Briton, arrived in Sarajevo with cool words for his predecessor and no peace to keep for the 24,000 troops he directs. A5  A RECORD LOAN FOR MEXICO  The I.M.F. tentatively agreed to lend Mexico $7.8 billion. Mexico said it hoped that would improve its chances for U.S. aid.  A10  MEXICO DENIES DEAL FOR A LOAN  Mexico denied it would agree to block illegal migrants or give the U.S. greater influence over its anti-drug efforts in return for $40 billion in proposed loan guarantees.  A10  HAITI FACES U.S. WITHDRAWAL  As the U.S. prepares to hand over its responsibilities to a U.N. force, Haitians are finding it difficult to adjust to the new military and political reality that portends.  A10  Pula Journal: On the Istrian peninsula, war seems far off.  A4  Republican Senators attack the Administration's foreign policy.  A8  National A12-19  THE RETURN OF GLOBAL WARMING  Global warming has resumed as predicted, after an interruption by the eruption of Mount Pinatubo in the Philippines in 1991.  A1  BUDGET AMENDMENT PASSES  The House approved a proposal to require the balancing of the Federal budget, without a provision to make tax increases more difficult.  A1  MORE, BUT FEWER, BASE CLOSINGS  Facing pressure from the military, the Defense Secretary said a new round of base closings would be smaller than anticipated.  A16  COMMERCE SECRETARY CRITICIZED  A House Republican asserted that the Ronald Brown had violated financial-disclosure requirements by not reporting $135,000 from a partnership in 1993.  A1  MASSACHUSETTS MIRACLE II?  Massachusetts, the state hit harder in the last recession than any other, is coming back. But this recovery is different because smaller, little-known companies are generating the jobs.  A1  HOW A SPY WAS CAUGHT  It was four months after the F.B.I. began its investigation of the C.I.A. officer-turned-Moscow-spy Aldrich H. Ames that agents got their first chance to catch Mr. Ames in the act of espionage.  A18  A FIGHT OVER FISHING RIGHTS  A Federal court ruling last month allowing Indians to take up to half the shellfish in Puget Sound has generated new animosity between Indians and non-Indians.  A12  FRUSTRATION AT SAFETY HEARINGS  The National Transportation Safety Board chairman complained that the Boeing Corporation had not told everything it knew about incidents involving its 737-type jets.  A12  A QUESTION OF EVIDENCE Judge Lance A. Ito delayed the trial of O. J. Simpson until Monday after a day of acrimony between lawyers for both sides.  A19  WHO WILL THE JURORS BELIEVE?  News Analysis: The Simpson case comes down to who made the most convincing argument.  A19  Law B7  Congress targets the civil justice system for an overhaul.  Metro Digest B1 MUSEUM EXPANSION PROPOSED  The American Museum of Natural History is planning a major expansion in an attempt to compete with the new generation of interactive science museums.  A1  Business Digest D1  Weekend C1-28 The twists and turns of yoga.  C1  Alexander defends arts endowment.  C3  For Children.  C16  Theater: On Stage, and Off.  C2  Film: "Tsahal." C1  "Miami Rhapsody." C6  "Before Sunrise."C8  Music: "Simon Bolivar." C13  Rewind and review.  C16  Dance: A Russian portrait.  C3  Restaurants.  C20 Art: The music of Kandinsky.  C1  Sports B9-17 BASEBALL GETS A WARNING  President Clinton ordered a Federal mediator to bring baseball's players and owners back to the bargaining table, and he set a Feb. 6 deadline for them to make progress toward ending the strike.  A1  Fashion B6  Obituaries A20-21  Editorials/Op-Ed A26-27 Editorials  Myopia on Mexico.  Governor Whitman's trade-offs.  Trails of blood, seeds of doubt.  An unaffordable pension boost.  Letters  Anthony Lewis: Reform or wreck?  A. M. Rosenthal: $40 billion questions.  Michael Eric Dyson: Haunted by conspiracy.  Thomas O. McGarity: Read the fine print. Neediest Cases B2  Chronicle B8 Crossword C26</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
