<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="790665"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DA143CF937A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International 3-17  POLITICAL FIGHT OVER ENVOYS  Senator Jesse helms is continuing to hold up 30 ambassadorial appointments and a series of treaties to try to force the Clinton Administration to revamp its foreign policy bureaucracy.  1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International 3-17  POLITICAL FIGHT OVER ENVOYS  Senator Jesse helms is continuing to hold up 30 ambassadorial appointments and a series of treaties to try to force the Clinton Administration to revamp its foreign policy bureaucracy.  1</p>
        <p>CUBAN EXILES LOOK HOMEWARD  There is a growing desire among some Cuban exiles to help bring democracy to their homeland and to help normalize relations, but as they go back they find the reality is not the Cuba they remember. 1  ANOTHER TRY IN ISRAEL TALKS  Negotiators for Israel and the Palestinians tried once again to resolve an impasse in their talks over expanding Palestinian self-rule, in the hope that they would finish before the Jewish New Year. 14  JEWS RETURNING TO GERMANY  In Modest numbers, Jews from the former Soviet Union are moving to Germany, a quiet footnote to German unification, and they are coming largely for economic reasons, not a spiritual mission.  3  The popularity of German's main opposition party is flagging. 4  FRONT LINE IN BOSNIA  What remains of the war in Bosnia is in the northwest, about 20 miles from the Serb stronghold of Banja Luka, and Bosnian troops are impatient that they have been halted, waiting for peace talks. 16  Serbs were reported to have retaken some territory they had lost. 16  India fears a threat at home from Sri Lankan separatists. 9  Only one former Mexican leader keeps his silence on politics. 10  A conference found third world children at risk from Western ills. 5  A militant wanted in Egypt was reported held in Croatia. 13  European leaders vowed to keep trying for a common currency. 17  A road was bringing northern Brazil closer to the ocean. 11  From the Amazon rain forest, come fruits with high nutrition. 12  National 18-42  POLITICAL FUNDS COME UP SHORT  The Federal Election Commission is expecting a shortfall of at least $15 million in the Federal matching funds that candidates are expecting to receive early next year.  1  LOOKING AT LEGISLATURES  The nation's state legislatures, on the verge of assuming greater powers from the Federal Government, are vastly different in size, professionalism and rules governing lobbying and ethics.  1  CLINTON REFLECTS ON 'BIG PICTURE'  President Clinton said he failed to convey "the big picture" during his first two years in office.  1  MEMORIAL TO A LEGENDARY ROAD  A new museum dedicated to Route 66 is the most visible sign yet of the revitalized interest in what many people in Clinton, Okla., still refer to as "the old road." 1  THE HUMBLEST OF SETTINGS  For the last four years on Sundays, a dozen or so worshipers and their 81-year-old pastor have gathered in a Chicago junkyard to hold nondenominational services.  18  CHANGING THE RULES  Changes in the law may mean that would-be immigrants who have abided by the rules might never be admitted, unlike some who came to the United States illegally and were granted amnesty.  18  NEW MEASURES TO FIGHT POLLUTION  The Government is considering tougher steps to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that cause global warming.  31  BUSINESS FIGHTS DISEASE  Employers are pressing health maintenance organizations to feed patient records into powerful computers to determine effective treatments for an array of illnesses.  32  F.A.A. ACTS ON EQUIPMENT FAILURES  The Federal Aviation Administration is taking a series of actions to prepare air traffic controllers for equipment failures, which are becoming more common.  42  Metropolitan 43-50  A MEDIATOR AS SCHOOLS CHOICE  Leon M. Goldstein, Mayor Giuliani's leading choice to be the next New York City Schools Chancellor, has paved a path of access to City Hall and Albany -- and has been criticized for offering patronage jobs at Kingsborough Community College in Brooklyn. But he has also demonstrated skills as a mediator and negotiator.  43  STILL HANGING IN THE 'HOOD  For many rap performers, stardom may mean a mansion far from their former, humble surroundings. But performers who are struggling to keep their creative edge and credibility with audiences are pulled by the communities where their talent took root.  43  TWO RABBIS, ONE HOUSEHOLD  The lead-up to the Holy Days is a busy time for many observant Jewish couples, but among the most harried these days is a two-pulpit pair in New Jersey at synagogues in Teaneck and Leonia. 43  Obituaries 51  Diana Chin Hsu, writer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
