<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>4 Refrigerator Makers Agree to Clarify Ozone-Damage Labels</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="817485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFRIGERATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HYDROCHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISLEADING AND DECEPTIVE ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABELING AND LABELS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WHIRLPOOL CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL ELECTRIC CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMANA REFRIGERATION INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEARS ROEBUCK &amp; CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAYTAG CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SANYO ELECTRIC CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2D81439F932A15751C1A963958260" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>4 Refrigerator Makers Agree to Clarify Ozone-Damage Labels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shopping for a refrigerator is about to get more informative: if not about the refrigerator itself, then about its impact on the environment.</p>
        <p>To settle a lawsuit brought by environmentalists, four big refrigerator manufacturers have agreed to re-label their appliances to clarify that their appliances will damage the earth's protective ozone layer to some extent, even though they have no chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, the most common ozone-eating  chemicals. Meanwhile, the environmental groups that brought the suit say they will file another, against two manufacturers that still use CFC's, but without,  the environmentalists say, the required labels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shopping for a refrigerator is about to get more informative: if not about the refrigerator itself, then about its impact on the environment.</p>
        <p>To settle a lawsuit brought by environmentalists, four big refrigerator manufacturers have agreed to re-label their appliances to clarify that their appliances will damage the earth's protective ozone layer to some extent, even though they have no chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, the most common ozone-eating  chemicals. Meanwhile, the environmental groups that brought the suit say they will file another, against two manufacturers that still use CFC's, but without,  the environmentalists say, the required labels.</p>
        <p>The four that settled are Amana, a subsidiary of the Raytheon Company; General Electric; Sears Roebuck, and Whirlpool. In environmental terms, all had  been leaders, moving faster than the law requires to eliminate chlorofluorocarbons. These have been used for decades in the compressors that produce cold, and in making the foam insulation for refrigerator walls. But in the 1970's the chemicals were found to damage stratospheric ozone.</p>
        <p>The four companies had gone a step further, though, advertising that their products were CFC-free. According to the Environmental Law Foundation, of Oakland, Calif., and Ozone Action, in Washington, this was deceptive, because it implied that the refrigerators would not damage the ozone. The Federal Trade Commission had also questioned the claim, but took no action.</p>
        <p>The substitute chemical used by the four, hydrochlorofluorocarbons, or HCFC's, also damage the ozone, although not as severely as CFC's.</p>
        <p>Now those models must be labeled as "significantly less ozone depleting" than models with CFC's.</p>
        <p>At Ozone Action, a nonprofit environmental group, Patrick P. Fleming, a refrigerator expert, said the new labels would help move the market toward less-damaging machines, although no refrigerator on the market in this country is completely ozone friendly. "You are stuck with fridges that will do less damage to ozone layer," Mr. Fleming said.</p>
        <p>The companies are claiming victory, too. "We don't think consumers were misled in the first place," said T. R. Reid, a spokesman for Whirlpool. But, he  said, "if anything the new labeling will probably make the genuine environmental benefits of these products, vs. the previous designs, even more clear."</p>
        <p>Mr. Reid said his company was going to re-label the machines anyway, because  the Federal Trade Commission had "re-interpreted its regulations."</p>
        <p>His company and the three others also agreed to give a total of $100,000 for  research into ozone depletion.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists are suing Maytag and Sanyo, which still make full-sized refrigerators using CFC's.</p>
        <p>By law, production of CFC's for use in the United States must end on Dec. 31, but manufacturers can keep using their stockpiles.</p>
        <p>Under the Clean Air Act, consumer products that use CFC's are supposed to carry a "clearly legible and conspicuous label" that says that the item contains the chemical, "a substance which harms public health and the environment by destroying ozone in the upper atmosphere." The environmentalists said that models in showrooms in California did not have the required tags.</p>
        <p>At the Maytag Corporation, in Newton, Iowa, Edward H. Graham, the vice president and general counsel, said: "We do put this label on. I've seen it." He said he had yet to see the suit.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Sanyo Fischer (USA) Corporation, a subsidiary of Sanyo Electric in Chatsworth, Calif., also said that his company complied.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
