<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. WILL DEPLOY ITS SPY SATELLITES ON NATURE MISSION</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811815"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D81039F934A15752C1A963958260" item-length="1601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. WILL DEPLOY ITS SPY SATELLITES ON NATURE MISSION</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the cold war a fading memory, the nation's spy satellites are beginning  to turn some of their attention to nature.</p>
        <p>In addition to peering at the usual military targets, they are monitoring such natural phenomena as clouds, glaciers, sea ice, deserts and tropical rain forests to gather clues about long-term global climatic change and ecological threats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the cold war a fading memory, the nation's spy satellites are beginning  to turn some of their attention to nature.</p>
        <p>In addition to peering at the usual military targets, they are monitoring such natural phenomena as clouds, glaciers, sea ice, deserts and tropical rain forests to gather clues about long-term global climatic change and ecological threats.</p>
        <p>At the urging of Vice President Gore, and with the support of Congress, the  new program is directing spy satellites to study about two dozen ecologically sensitive sites around the world. Ultimately, it is to monitor about 500 sites.  Scientists are programming the satellites to study diverse habitats vulnerable to environmental shifts and damage, including some that are unusually remote and forbidding.</p>
        <p>"In terms of turning swords into plowshares, this is about as good of an example as I can think of," said Dr. Jeff Dozier, dean of the school of environmental science at the University of California at Santa Barbara and a member of the program's management team.</p>
        <p>The data will be archived for future generations of scientists and will remain secret for now to conceal the abilities of the nation's reconnaissance systems, the scientists said. Intelligence experts always try to hide the exact  abilities of their surveillance systems so foes are less likely to know how to evade and counter them. And in any event, the data will be most interesting in future decades because it seeks to reveal trends over time.</p>
        <p>The program picks areas of the Earth that are thought to be particularly revealing of changes in the natural world and repeatedly photographs them on a fixed schedule, seasonally in some cases. Data are to be collected for decades,  in theory revealing subtle ecological shifts that might otherwise be missed. For example, Mount Kilimanjaro in northeast Tanzania near the Kenya border is to be  scrutinized for signs that the Earth's rising levels of carbon dioxide are changing its high forests.</p>
        <p>The monitoring effort is led by Medea, a taciturn group of about 60 scientists in academia and industry who advise the nation's intelligence agencies on the use of secret data to study the environment. Medea stands for Measurements of Earth Data for Environmental Analysis. The group was founded after the cold war to aid re-evaluations of the nation's sprawling intelligence  enterprise and has championed an environmentalist agenda.</p>
        <p>"We want to make sure that the scientist working in 2020 has available a lot  of relevant information," Dr. Gordon J. MacDonald, Medea's chairman and a geophysicist at the University of California at San Diego, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The new reconnaissance effort is run for Medea by the National Reconnaissance Office in the Pentagon and is coordinated by the Central Intelligence Agency, which is apparently pleased with the broadening of its responsibilities.</p>
        <p>"It's an exciting new issue to engage in," said a senior Federal intelligence official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity. "Modest amounts of resources  are producing interesting results. The other thing that makes it interesting is  the high-level interest. It makes any producer enthusiastic if you've got eager  customers."</p>
        <p>The program is very different from the related effort to mine old spy-satellite photos for environmental data, a process the Clinton Administration recently began. That effort, featuring photos originally taken for military reasons, is often hit or miss in terms of ecological relevance. In  contrast, the new effort directly targets nature and its subtleties.</p>
        <p>So too, the program is different from recent intelligence gathering that studies natural phenomena for clues to the deeper roots of war and focuses on such things as drought, population growth and lack of arable land.</p>
        <p>Medea scientists say spy satellites have several advantages over standard environmental studies. Coverage is wider and cheaper than that done by armies of scientists on the ground and can aid in spotting trends. Moreover, spy satellites can often assess faraway areas virtually inaccessible by other means.</p>
        <p>The scientists add that spy satellites are better than civilian remote-sensing craft, like Landsat or Spot, which orbit the earth for the United States and France, respectively. Military craft can zoom in on ground targets,</p>
        <p>letting scientists learn more. Moreover, they say, these spy images can often aid civilian analyses.</p>
        <p>"You can use the intelligence assets to make the interpretation of the civilian ones much more accurate," said Dr. Dozier of the University of California at Santa Barbara.</p>
        <p>By definition, the vision of spy satellites is far more penetrating than civilian ones, though Medea scientists are barred from discussing such differences. It is well known that spy satellites not only take color and black-and-white photos but readings in hundreds of different parts of the electromagnetic spectrum, using such instruments as space radars to see through  forest canopies and desert sands.</p>
        <p>Since the cold war's end, policy makers in Washington have heatedly debated how best to use the nation's huge investment in spy satellites, with some encouraging a broadening to include economic intelligence in aid of businesses and trade negotiations.</p>
        <p>The Republican-led Congress has been generally supportive of Medea and its environmental efforts, ignoring scattered critics who say the programs are inappropriate and wasteful and should be eliminated. For the fiscal year 1996, the Administration requested $17.6 million for the environmental work, and appropriations conferees allotted $15 million.</p>
        <p>Representative Norman D. Dicks, Democrat of Washington, and his colleagues on the House Intelligence Committee wrote in a minority report on the 1996 budget that the initiative "promises to lead to better understanding of long-term environmental change as well as better management of crisis situations involving natural and ecological disasters."</p>
        <p>Steven Aftergood, a senior researcher at the Federation of American Scientists, a private group in Washington, said the environmental reconnaissance was "potentially a watershed in the reform of intelligence," adding, "It reflects an expanding definition of national security."</p>
        <p>"There are people who will paint this as soft-headed environmentalism," Mr. Aftergood said. "But in fact environmental changes can be an important source of regional conflict, so I think it's a perfectly legitimate redirection."</p>
        <p>Marc A. Levy, a political scientist at Princeton University who studies ecological politics, said he applauded the change of focus but doubted if it had political staying power.</p>
        <p>"I'm worried that it will be vulnerable to the ebbs and flows of security politics," Dr. Levy said. "Like Star Wars and the B-1 bomber, these things come  and go."</p>
        <p>But scientists involved in the program say its overhead is so low and the potential gains so great that it is likely to exist for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>Since the nation launched its first spy satellite in 1960, it has spent $100  billion or more to acquire and use spacecraft laden with cameras, telescopes and antennas that spy on the Earth. Today each spy satellite is thought to cost roughly $1 billion and a dozen or so are believed to be constantly at work.</p>
        <p>The Medea group is conducting two dozen or so experiments to see how effectively these spy satellites can monitor natural sites. In many cases, the experimental areas are long-term ecological reserves around the country that are financed by the National Science Foundation, which provides money for basic research.</p>
        <p>In the near future, the reconnaissance effort is to expand to take on hundreds of other domestic and foreign sites, with Federal civilian agencies helping nominate areas. Dr. Dozier said that Medea had so far selected about 260 candidate sites around the world and that eventually some 500 would be targeted.</p>
        <p>These are some of the current candidates:</p>
        <p>*Clouds off the California coast between Los Angeles and San Diego;</p>
        <p>*The Mojave Desert in California;</p>
        <p>*The Luquillo experimental forest in Puerto Rico;</p>
        <p>*A mixed coniferous-deciduous forest in Pleshcheyevo, Russia;</p>
        <p>*The Konza prairie in Kansas;</p>
        <p>*A lowland tropical rain forest at La Selva, Costa Rica;</p>
        <p>*The forested slopes of the Sumava Mountains, Czechoslovakia;</p>
        <p>*The coastal zone around the Galapagos Islands, off Ecuador;</p>
        <p>*Permafrost in Fish Creek, Alaska;</p>
        <p>*Glaciers in Griegsletchner, Switzerland;</p>
        <p>*The high slopes of Mount Kilimanjaro.</p>
        <p>Dr. Herman H. Shugart, an environmental scientist at the University of Virginia, is now working on a Medea project to study Mount Kilimanjaro and other mountains in the tropics. The thesis is that the increases of carbon dioxide in  the atmosphere that are under way will first affect vegetation at high altitudes, causing it to become more verdant.</p>
        <p>"If you're looking at the first place on Earth that might show a biological change, the place would be the highest vegetation zones you can find, and those  puppies are found in tropical high forests," Dr. Shugart said.</p>
        <p>"If this archival system works," he added, "then one day people will be able  to say, 'By god, all those mountains are changing in the same way.' It gives you a chance to be creative about things that might matter."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
