<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Many Species Are Being Lost? Scientists Try New Yardstick</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="777639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D91430F936A15754C0A963958260" item-length="1376" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Many Species Are Being Lost? Scientists Try New Yardstick</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW if any conservation biologists doubt that humans are driving other living species to extinction at a growing rate, and in recent years estimates of the magnitude of the apparent extinction crisis have flooded forth: A million species gone by the year 2000. A quarter of all species by 2015. Twenty-seven thousand species a year. Three every hour. The list goes on.</p>
        <p>These global estimates have always been crude at best, heavy on theory but lighter on data, and have stimulated controversy. Many scientists, while still convinced that humans are precipitating extinctions on an epic scale, now say it is futile to try to estimate future extinctions with any exactitude.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW if any conservation biologists doubt that humans are driving other living species to extinction at a growing rate, and in recent years estimates of the magnitude of the apparent extinction crisis have flooded forth: A million species gone by the year 2000. A quarter of all species by 2015. Twenty-seven thousand species a year. Three every hour. The list goes on.</p>
        <p>These global estimates have always been crude at best, heavy on theory but lighter on data, and have stimulated controversy. Many scientists, while still convinced that humans are precipitating extinctions on an epic scale, now say it is futile to try to estimate future extinctions with any exactitude.</p>
        <p>Partly as a result, the attempt to measure the loss of species is moving beyond its early, rough phase into a new and more difficult period. In this second phase, the focus is more closely on the relatively few, small, scattered places inhabited by species that live nowhere else. These are termed endemic species by ecologists, and scientists believe they account for most of the extinctions caused by humans. Pacific and Caribbean islands, for instance, are rich in endemics. So are many American rivers, and even single mountainsides in South America. Wipe out a small piece of the landscape there, and whole species are doomed. Wipe out a like-sized piece where species are more widely distributed, as in much of North America, and they survive.</p>
        <p>In what appears to be the first study of its kind, ecologists at the University of Tennessee have calculated recent extinction rates for well-known endemic-rich "extinction centers" around the globe and found that the rates are 100 to 1,000 times as high as the prehuman "background" extinction rate. This is about one-tenth the rate of the most pessimistic global estimates.</p>
        <p>But because scientists know relatively little about the distribution of endemics, say the researchers, it is impossible to gauge the overall future of the world's wild creatures accurately -- or to direct conservation efforts to many of the most urgent targets.</p>
        <p>"The fate of those special places will decide whether we keep species or we don't," says Dr. Stuart L. Pimm, the chief author of the new study, which appears in the current issue of the journal Science. The other authors are Gareth J. Russell, Dr. John L. Gittleman and Thomas M. Brooks. As things stand now, they wrote, "our understanding of endemism is insufficient for us to know the future of biodiversity with precision."</p>
        <p>Until now calculations of extinction rates, especially in tropical forests, have often depended on a theoretical construct called the species-area curve. This theory holds that as an area of habitat is reduced by human activity, species will disappear from it at a predictable rate; for instance, when an island of habitat is reduced by 90 percent, according to a widely cited rule of thumb, half its species will eventually vanish. If one can accurately estimate the future rate of habitat destruction, say proponents of the theory, then one can estimate the future rate of species loss as well.</p>
        <p>The theory has become enshrined in textbooks, but many scientists now agree with Dr. Daniel Simberloff, an ecologist at Florida State University who has long criticized its shortcomings as a predictor, that it is only a "rough guide" and may be off by at least a factor of 10. One of the theory's developers, Dr. Edward O. Wilson of Harvard University, says it has served the purpose of "making a first rough cut" at estimating the extinction rate and alerting other scientists and the public that something out of the ordinary appears to be happening.</p>
        <p>Now, says Dr. Wilson, "we are moving into the second phase of closer analysis," a phase he says is well illustrated by the Tennessee study.</p>
        <p>In it, Dr. Pimm and his colleagues, drawing on fossil evidence, calculated the background rate of past extinctions. They determined that aside from five or six mass extinctions believed to have been caused by climate change or impacts by asteroids or comets, species in the past have typically persisted for about a million years before becoming extinct. Put another way, this means that in every group of a million species, one species should become extinct naturally each year.</p>
        <p>Then the Tennessee researchers calculated extinction rates in the last 100 years among birds on Pacific islands, mammals worldwide but especially in central Australia and the Caribbean, reptiles on islands in the Indian and Atlantic oceans and clams in the Mississippi river drainage. These are all well-known centers of endemism in which extinctions have been well documented. In these "black spots," of extinction, as Dr. Pimm calls them, the researchers found that the observed rates of extinction are 100 to 1,000 times the background rate. They also calculated that if all species in those areas now threatened with extinction do become extinct, the rate will increase about tenfold.</p>
        <p>In another calculation, Dr. Pimm and his colleagues matched data on extinct and soon-to-be-extinct bird species in various parts of Southeast Asia where deforestation has proceeded at different rates against the number of extinctions that would be predicted there by the species-area curve. "If you do that for all species present," said Dr. Pimm, "you get the wrong answer. You have to do it for only the species that are found only there." Then reality squares with the theory. Dr. Pimm believes that with this new calibration of the area-species curve, he and his team have developed a tool for predicting future species losses among endemics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Simberloff expresses skepticism about any attempt to compare recent extinction rates with background rates derived from fossils, arguing that in both cases the data are skimpy. "We're comparing fractions of what happened ages ago with fractions of what's happening now," he said. The most important point made by the Tennessee study, he said, is that "the key factor in causing these extinctions is the very limited geographical range of these species."</p>
        <p>Islands tend to be particularly rich in endemics, said Dr. Pimm, but not all islands; the British isles, for instance, are an exception. Likewise, continents contain concentrations of endemics that would disappear if their habitats were wiped out. Examples abound in the tropics, many ecologists and field investigators say. But even in North America, where many species are relatively secure because they are widely distributed, especially birds, there are many pockets of endemism. This continent, for example, is rich in species of fish and mollusks restricted to small areas. In the last century, 21 of 197 freshwater mussels and clams and 40 of about 950 species of freshwater fish have gone extinct.</p>
        <p>But many areas of endemism have not been found and delineated, nor their species inventoried, frustrating efforts to predict the magnitude and rate of extinctions globally and to attack the species conservation problem at its source. Remote sensing can help in this, said Dr. Pimm, but in the end it comes down to hard-slogging, time-consuming field work: "It is the lowest-tech work imaginable; you go out with your plant press and your binoculars and your notebook."</p>
        <p>In the meantime, biologists must continue to fall back on fragmentary evidence, and such evidence as exists convinces many biologists that although they cannot yet measure the phenomenon very well, a major wave of extinctions caused by humans is under way.</p>
        <p>"Every biologist works on particular groups" of organisms, said Dr. Simberloff, "and independently we can see the same kinds of processes occurring with our pet taxa, particularly habitat destruction. Whenever we get together at meetings, we're basically exchanging horror stories" about species in trouble.</p>
        <p>"It's happening in every taxon and every habitat," he said. "That's why we're confident in saying there is a real crisis here and that it's getting worse, not better."</p>
        <p>Furthermore, he said, "I don't know anyone who has expertise and has studied the literature and has the background to assess it who doesn't feel that extinction rates are greatly elevated over prehuman times and that they are likely to be elevated more in the future."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
