<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Laser at South Pole to Track Ozone Depletion</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LASER (LIGHT AMPLIFICATION BY STIMULATED EMISSION OF RADIATION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLORINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADAR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laser (Light Amplification by Stimulated Emission of Radiation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3D9163FF937A15752C0A963958260" item-length="1282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Laser at South Pole to Track Ozone Depletion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
      <dateline>AMUNDSEN-SCOTT SOUTH POLE STATION, Antarctica</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A POWERFUL laser beam has begun to stab the sky above the South Pole, and scientists expect that it will illuminate many vital details about the depletion of the global ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Working under uncomfortable and primitive conditions, a team of scientists from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign completed preparations this month for operating the beam during the Antarctic winter, when darkness will prevail 24 hours a day and temperatures will drop below minus 100 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A POWERFUL laser beam has begun to stab the sky above the South Pole, and scientists expect that it will illuminate many vital details about the depletion of the global ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Working under uncomfortable and primitive conditions, a team of scientists from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign completed preparations this month for operating the beam during the Antarctic winter, when darkness will prevail 24 hours a day and temperatures will drop below minus 100 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>The ozone layer is a region of the earth's upper atmosphere containing a small amount of ozone gas, a compound consisting of three atoms of oxygen. At ground level, ozone is hazardous to health, but stratospheric ozone is vital to life on earth. It blocks the most harmful ultraviolet rays from the sun, protecting plant and animal life.</p>
        <p>The quantity of ozone in the stratosphere has declined alarmingly over the last decade. During the Antarctic spring beginning in August, an ozone-depleted region the size of the entire continent has opened up for several weeks during each recent year. Although the hole later closes, the brief but virtually total depletion of ozone inside it is eventually distributed around the world, affecting even low latitudes. The extent and severity of the Antarctic depletion reached a record in 1993, when the ozone hole extended more than 9.4 million square miles.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric chemists have concluded that the main agency of this depletion is stratospheric chlorine produced by human activity. In particular, chlorofluorocarbons, which are widely used as refrigerants in air-conditioners, as plastic foaming agents and in many other applications, are believed to be responsible.</p>
        <p>These compounds, known as CFC's, linger in the lower atmosphere for many years after they are released. This gives them time to drift upward into the stratosphere, where they are exposed to such intense radiation from the sun thattheir molecules are broken apart, producing free chlorine. Chlorine breaks ozone apart to form free oxygen and chlorine monoxide, and a catalytic sequence begins that releases the chlorine after each reaction to begin its destructive effects anew.</p>
        <p>For the ozone-destroying reaction to work, scientists believe, a catalyst is needed, in the form of fine ice crystals that form only when the upper stratosphere is so cold that even nitrogen gas freezes solid. Stratospheric ice begins to form as clouds of crystals high over Antarctica in the dead of winter in June. The first crystals to form are those of nitric acid trihydrate, and these form nuclei for the crystallization of water ice. Microscopic ice crystals of various kinds are believed to provide reaction sites at which chlorine can interact with ozone. But the details of the many complex reactions involved are not well understood.</p>
        <p>Overall ozone levels in the atmosphere are routinely measured throughout the world by spectrographic Dobson instruments on the ground and by the Total Ozone Mapping Satellite. But the subtle and continuously changing structural details of the atmosphere that influence the rate and degree of ozone destruction remain obscure.</p>
        <p>For this reason, Dr. Chester S. Gardner, Dr. George C. Papen and their colleagues from the University of Illinois have just finished installing and testing a year-round laser radar, or "lidar," designed to maintain surveillance of the atmosphere above the South Pole at altitudes up to 60 miles. The instrument will allow scientists to create continuous three-dimensional maps of the chemical composition and physical details of the atmosphere throughout the year.</p>
        <p>The laser beam points straight up through an open pipe piercing the roof of the South Pole's aging and decrepit Clean Air Facility. As the beam hits molecules of air, particles of ice, droplets and trace chemicals like sodium, a small part of the beam's light is scattered back toward the earth, where a 14-inch-diameter telescope in the laboratory gathers it and pipes it to an array of detectors. Substances differ in how well they scatter different wavelengths of beam light, so multicolored laser beams probe different constituents of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Observations are expected to show how stratospheric ice crystals change in size and shape as the ozone hole is created, and how various crystal types affect ozone destruction. The laser probe will also track the chemical steps driving the process at various altitudes.</p>
        <p>Despite their efforts to automate part of the measuring processes, the team must leave behind one of its members, Paul J. Charpentier, to nurse the complex lidar throughout the long, dark winter.</p>
        <p>Although the National Science Foundation plans to build a new Clean Air Facility, for which the prefabricated components are already at the South Pole, the agency lacks funds to erect it, and conditions in the old building, which stands on stilts above the ice, are proving to be difficult. The lidar laboratory is overheated, and the scientists must leave a window open to cool the apparatus. Scientists labor in shifts to alternately fan or warm components of the laser that are so sensitive to temperature change that a variation of 1.8 degrees Fahrenheit alters results by 20 percent.</p>
        <p>The experiment has also suffered the effects of power shortages and brownouts created by growing numbers of scientists and support personnel at this crowded station. The South Pole electrical plant is operating at peak capacity, but power demands are forcing station residents to turn off washing and drying machines, curtail microwave cooking, turn off office lights and take other emergency measures.</p>
        <p>This is creating conflicts. The University of Illinois laser apparatus draws about 7,000 watts of power, but another big consumer of power has been an educational television project called "Live from Antarctica." The four-part broadcast series, sponsored by the National Science Foundation, featured live segments and direct communication between scientists here and schoolchildren in the United States.</p>
        <p>This month the producers of the program asked station officials to increase the availability of electrical power by closing down the laser lidar experiment for 48 hours. But Dr. Papen and Dr. Gardner refused, saying that critical data would be lost. The brownouts continued.</p>
        <p>The University of Illinois lidar consists of a series of lasers, beginning with a very powerful (26-watt) pulsed infrared laser. This can be projected into the sky directly or fed to a crystal lens that doubles the invisible infrared frequency to produce a green beam. This in turn can be shot into the sky directly or fed to another type of laser (a dye laser), the frequency of which can be precisely adjusted.</p>
        <p>The lidar can precisely measure the amounts of ozone at various altitudes above the observatory, but it can do much more. For example, a precisely tuned yellow beam from the laser is adjusted to energize sodium atoms in a layer near the top of the atmosphere about 60 miles high. Observation of the height and intensity of the resulting glow at the spot where the laser makes the sodium atoms glow reveals changes in the height of the atmosphere itself and the passage of "gravity waves" across the top of the atmosphere.  Gravity waves are analogous to the ripples in a pond that spread from the impact of a rock on the surface.</p>
        <p>"We don't yet know, but these atmospheric gravity waves may affect the process of ozone destruction," Dr. Gardner said. "Many, many factors are involved, and until we discover how they interact, we cannot develop a good mathematical model describing every aspect of ozone depletion."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
