<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ice Age Evidence Suggests a Mercurial Tropical Climate</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="782533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEMPERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE AGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDC1338F936A2575BC0A963958260" item-length="942" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ice Age Evidence Suggests a Mercurial Tropical Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCIENTISTS have long believed that when the ice ages froze northern and southern latitudes, the tropics remained warm and climatically stable. This suggests that the equatorial regions are less sensitive to climate change generally, and that the tropics might therefore be spared the worst of any global warming caused by human activity.</p>
        <p>Now evidence is accumulating that the tropical climate is just as vulnerable to wide, long-term swings in temperature as areas farther north and south and by one set of data may have been 10 degrees Fahrenheit cooler in the last ice age. Such a large cooling suggests that the tropics could also get much warmer in a period of global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCIENTISTS have long believed that when the ice ages froze northern and southern latitudes, the tropics remained warm and climatically stable. This suggests that the equatorial regions are less sensitive to climate change generally, and that the tropics might therefore be spared the worst of any global warming caused by human activity.</p>
        <p>Now evidence is accumulating that the tropical climate is just as vulnerable to wide, long-term swings in temperature as areas farther north and south and by one set of data may have been 10 degrees Fahrenheit cooler in the last ice age. Such a large cooling suggests that the tropics could also get much warmer in a period of global warming.</p>
        <p>The findings may force climatologists to reassess the potential impact of future climate change in the heavily populated tropics, whose residents, many of them dependent on subsistence agriculture, are especially vulnerable to the vagaries of weather and climate.</p>
        <p>Some scientists also say that the emerging evidence strengthens earlier estimates of a key property of the earth's climate system: its sensitivity, or magnitude of response to heating and cooling influences like sunlight, clouds and carbon dioxide, a gas emitted by the burning of fossil fuels that traps heat in the atmosphere. Several estimates of climate sensitivity say that the average temperature of the earth would rise by 4 to 5 degrees if levels of atmospheric carbon dioxide double, as is expected before the end of the next century at present rates of emission.</p>
        <p>In comparison, the average global temperature was an estimated 5 to 9 degrees lower in the depths of the last ice age than it is now. Conventional wisdom, however, has held that the tropics cooled hardly at all. The latest and perhaps strongest clue to the contrary, reported last month in the journal Science, comes from a chemical analysis of fresh water trapped since the last ice age in sandstone layers in the tropical lowlands of northeastern Brazil.</p>
        <p>Surface water has continuously seeped into the sandstone layers for many millenniums, carrying with it chemical indicators of temperature in the form of the noble gases argon, neon, krypton and xenon, which were in the atmosphere at the moment of seepage. Water samples from existing wells drilled into the sandstone were collected and analyzed by eight researchers from the Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University headed by Dr. Martin Stute, a geochemist.</p>
        <p>Water seeps through the sandstone very slowly, at about three feet a year, so that a noble gas record stretching back tens of thousands of years has been preserved. The researchers determined the age of the seeping liquid by radiocarbon dating. They determined its temperature by measuring the concentrations of noble gases: the higher the concentration, the lower the temperature.</p>
        <p>The measurements found that the average temperature at the research site was nearly 10 degrees lower in the last ice age than it is now.</p>
        <p>Other evidence of a tropical cooling has surfaced as well. Various studies have indicated that temperatures in the tropical Andes dropped as much as 20 degrees in the last glaciation, that snow lines advanced and vegetation retreated more than 1,000 yards down mountainsides and that the ocean near Barbados cooled by about 9 degrees.</p>
        <p>Based on all the studies, said Dr. Stute, it now looks as if temperate and tropical regions cooled off substantially, at least in America. "It appears," he and his colleagues wrote in Science, "that the tropical Americas are characterized by a temperature sensitivity comparable to that found in higher latitudes."</p>
        <p>Until the new spate of evidence, paleoclimatologists had based their belief in ice age tropical warming on an analysis of the fossilized remains of tiny marine animals called foraminifera and of oxygen isotopes preserved in ocean sediments. Certain kinds of foraminifera are associated with certain temperature ranges, and oxygen isotopes can tell scientists which foraminifera lived during the ice age.</p>
        <p>Just what explains the discrepancy between the ocean-sediment findings and the latest findings is not clear. One possibility, said Dr. Stute, is that surface winds in glacial times could have muddled the ocean record.</p>
        <p>While the discrepancy must still be explained, the finding of Dr. Stute and his team is a "convincing result" in light of the other converging evidence, said Dr. James E. Hansen, a climatologist who directs the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York. The question is of "tremendous importance," he said, in helping to determine the climate system's sensitivity to warming and cooling influences.</p>
        <p>By comparing ancient climates with today's, some scientists have calculated the climate's sensitivity as expressed by its response to a doubling of atmospheric carbon dioxide. That sensitivity, they have found, lies in the range of 4 to 5 degrees of warming on a global average. If the tropics did not cool much in the last ice age, said Dr. Hansen, the sensitivity would be lower: in the range of 3 to 4.5 degrees.</p>
        <p>As for the tropics themselves, Dr. Stute cautioned that the new finding does not necessarily mean that they would heat up along with the rest of the globe in the event of a global warming caused by rising concentrations of carbon dioxide. "It's a red light" that calls for further investigation, he said, but the mechanisms that caused the glacial cooling might be different from those involved in a warming. Scientists fear that even a few degrees of tropical warming could significantly affect living and farming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
