<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Estimates of Insurers' Costs On Environment Are Lowered</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSURANCE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESSIONAL BUDGET OFFICE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN ACADEMY OF ACTUARIES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">STANDARD &amp; POOR'S CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUINT, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DA133AF933A05753C1A963958260" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Estimates of Insurers' Costs On Environment Are Lowered</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL QUINT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">QUINT, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cost of environmental cleanups is not quite the disaster for insurance companies that was once feared, according to a growing number of studies, including one to be published today by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation, the securities rating company.</p>
        <p>"The costs have come down as more data have emerged about the actual cost of cleaning up and as companies have reached settlements on some claims," said Alan M. Levin, a managing director at S.&amp; P. He cautioned, however, that environmental claims remained a big problem for American insurers because many had not set aside enough reserves to pay for environmental and asbestos claims, which he expects to cost about $40 billion in today's dollars and $125 billion in total over the next 30 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cost of environmental cleanups is not quite the disaster for insurance companies that was once feared, according to a growing number of studies, including one to be published today by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation, the securities rating company.</p>
        <p>"The costs have come down as more data have emerged about the actual cost of cleaning up and as companies have reached settlements on some claims," said Alan M. Levin, a managing director at S.&amp; P. He cautioned, however, that environmental claims remained a big problem for American insurers because many had not set aside enough reserves to pay for environmental and asbestos claims, which he expects to cost about $40 billion in today's dollars and $125 billion in total over the next 30 years.</p>
        <p>The S.&amp; P. estimate is well below the $150 billion to $165 billion in 30-year costs estimated in studies last year by the Congressional Budget Office and the University of Tennessee, and is only slightly higher than the $100 billion estimate in 30-year costs issued in August by the American Academy of Actuaries.</p>
        <p>"The black hole is not quite so deep as feared, and some light is beginning to filter through," said Jack F. Snyder, an executive at the A. M. Best Company, an insurance- rating company in Oldwick, N.J. Last year Mr. Snyder estimated that insurers faced claims of $132 billion in current dollars, a figure he now estimates at about $50 billion. Much of the reduction came from eliminating from the calculation claims for restoration of natural resources, like lakes polluted by acid rain, because those claims have not materialized as expected.</p>
        <p>Analysts at Tillinghast, an actuarial firm whose studies of environmental claims have been used by many insurance companies, have reduced their estimate for 30-year costs to insurers to $25 billion to $55 billion, from $60 billion to $90 billion at the beginning of the year.</p>
        <p>Amy S. Bouska, a principal at Tillinghast, said the reduction reflected the success of insurers in court and in negotiating lower settlements and a cutback in the number of cleanup sites nationwide to about 2,000 from the more than 3,000 assumed earlier. She noted that Federal budget cuts would reduce the ability of the Environmental Protection Agency to investigate new sites and add them to the cleanup list.</p>
        <p>Several companies, including Aetna Life and Casualty; the Cigna Corporation, and Fireman's Fund, a subsidiary of Allianz Versicherungs A.G. of Germany, have recently bowed to pressure from regulators and investors and announced increases in their reserves to cover environmental claims. Mr. Levin said many more companies would be adding reserves soon, including one large company that he declined to identify, which will add more than $1 billion.</p>
        <p>According to the S.&amp; P. study, confidential reports by the 27 most exposed insurance companies indicate that the shortfall in their reserves, relative to their expected costs in current dollars, is equal to about a third of their capital. Over the next 30 years the need to set aside profits to increase reserves and pay for claims should reduce those companies' profits by about 18 percent, the study indicates.</p>
        <p>The status of many companies will become clearer early next year, analysts said, because end-of-year financial reports mandated by state regulators will require for the first time that the companies disclose their environmental liabilities and the reserves they have to pay them. The Securities and Exchange Commission already has such a requirement for shareholder-owned companies, but the new rule will also apply to small companies and mutual companies, which are owned by their policyholders.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
