<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth Day at 25: How Has Nature Fared?</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="755932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EARTH DAY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D71638F93BA25757C0A963958260" item-length="2102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth Day at 25: How Has Nature Fared?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A QUARTER of a century after the first Earth Day, on April 22, 1970, an emerging public perception holds that the peak of human insult to the environment has passed in the United States and that an increasingly green and healthy future lies ahead.</p>
        <p>Proponents of this sunny conviction argue that the modern age of environmental protection has drastically reduced the threat from most forms of pollution, that nature is resurgent and that environmentalists have refused to recognize their own success. Their position is reflected, for instance, in the title of a new book by the environmental writer Gregg Easterbrook, "A Moment on the Earth: The Coming Age of Environmental Optimism" (Viking). In a related article in the April 10 New Yorker, Mr. Easterbrook argued that the environmental laws of the last 25 years have been a "stunning success" and that environmental trends in the United States and Europe "are, for the most part, positive."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A QUARTER of a century after the first Earth Day, on April 22, 1970, an emerging public perception holds that the peak of human insult to the environment has passed in the United States and that an increasingly green and healthy future lies ahead.</p>
        <p>Proponents of this sunny conviction argue that the modern age of environmental protection has drastically reduced the threat from most forms of pollution, that nature is resurgent and that environmentalists have refused to recognize their own success. Their position is reflected, for instance, in the title of a new book by the environmental writer Gregg Easterbrook, "A Moment on the Earth: The Coming Age of Environmental Optimism" (Viking). In a related article in the April 10 New Yorker, Mr. Easterbrook argued that the environmental laws of the last 25 years have been a "stunning success" and that environmental trends in the United States and Europe "are, for the most part, positive."</p>
        <p>The wave of revisionism is different from the anti-environmentalist rhetoric that has lately argued not that things are getting better, but that there was no serious problem to begin with. And it comes at a time when the whole edifice of environmental regulation that is being credited with so much success is under threat of being weakened or even dismantled by Congress.</p>
        <p>Are the revisionists right?</p>
        <p>In some ways, yes, according to environmental scientists and Government statistics. Several types of air and water pollution have been sharply reduced. In the last seven years alone, the Environmental Protection Agency says, American manufacturers have cut back their releases of toxic chemicals by 43 percent. The United States' production of other industrial chemicals that erode the earth's protective ozone shield, the largest output in the world, is being phased out, and the shield is expected to recover in time.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the environment of the United States and other rich nations is far healthier than that of the developing world, which is under sometimes overwhelming assault by population growth and industrial exploitation. America's system of domestic environmental protection has in fact been widely regarded as a model.</p>
        <p>But most of the victories so far have been relatively easy ones against obvious, clear-cut threats. Tougher and more complex problems lie ahead, especially the largely unchecked destruction and biological impoverishment of the natural landscape and the uncertain but real prospect of climate change. As ecological threats go, scientists advising the Government have said, none rank higher than these, and they promise to dominate environmental politics in the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>These problems are potentially explosive because their roots lie in the everyday behavior of people: their use of the land and their consumption of the fossil-fuel energy whose byproduct, carbon dioxide, could heat the atmosphere and make the global climate more unstable and disruptive. Already, the implacable opposition of property owners threatens to weaken drastically the Endangered Species Act, which is up for reauthorization by Congress this year. And although the United States formally joined in an international agreement 11 days ago to seek reductions in carbon dioxide emissions, the nation that emits the most has hardly begun to confront the implications of that commitment.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the achievements of the last quarter-century are not complete. According to the E.P.A., two of every five Americans still live in areas where the air is unhealthful. Forty percent of the nation's rivers and lakes are not fit for drinking, fishing or swimming, the agency says. Last year, the agency issued more than 1,000 warnings against eating fish from chemically contaminated waters. Although more of the East is covered by trees now than at the beginning of the century, fragmentation of the forest landscape by development and invasion by weedy exotic species threaten the forest's biological variety and vitality.</p>
        <p>And new threats pop up, like the microbial contamination of drinking water in Milwaukee two years ago that contributed to the deaths of more than 100 people with compromised immune systems and made tens of thousands of others ill. Scientists are only beginning to understand the potential threat to human and animal reproduction posed by a wide range of hormone-disrupting chemicals that are accumulating in the environment.</p>
        <p>"Each generation has to revisit these issues and do them again," says William K. Reilly, who was the E.P.A. administrator and chief environmental voice in the Bush Administration.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Reilly and others also say that by refusing to acknowledge progress and incessantly beating the drums of doom, environmentalists are not helping. The refusal not only harms their credibility, critics say, it also plays into the hands of naysayers who might argue that if existing environmental regulations are not showing results, they are not worth the cost. Mr. Reilly warned that too negative a stance may also undercut the environmentalists' political allies: "By failing to credit success," he said at a Yale University forum on the subject a few days ago, "you reduce the rewards to politicians for the risks they take."</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists agree. Mr. Reilly's point is "definitely" valid, said Fred Krupp, the executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund. "We should celebrate progress," he said, acknowledging that "we have made a lot of progress in this country -- even if it's also true that we've got a long way to go."</p>
        <p>Carol M. Browner, the present E.P.A. Administrator, agrees, pointing out that "while we have done a lot, the challenges of tomorrow are going to be far more complicated." For instance, she said, it is much easier to stop the flow of raw sewage into waterways than to control the broad runoff of fertilizers, silt and pesticides from farm fields and urban developments, which are equally devastating to aquatic life. Among other things, she believes, this requires focusing on prevention and building political consensus at the local level, as she recently attempted to do in issuing new standards for the discharge of toxic materials into the Great Lakes.</p>
        <p>Since almost every activity on land ultimately affects adjoining rivers, lakes and streams, their health has become recognized as a particularly revealing gauge of environmental quality in general. "A clean aquatic ecosystem with a healthy biological community will be indicative of the condition of the terrestrial habitat in the watershed," says a report to be published soon by the National Biological Service, a research organization in the Interior Department.</p>
        <p>If that is so, there is some ground for encouragement. The flow of industrial waste and sewage into watercourses has been greatly reduced. But scientists say that biological quality has continued to decline anyway because of farm and urban runoff, destruction of streamside vegetation, erosion, introduction of exotic species, straightening of streams and building of dams.</p>
        <p>People commonly equate environmental protection with conquering chemical pollution. "They say we've put a lot of time and resources into reducing pollution and everything's O.K.," said Dr. James R. Karr, an aquatic ecologist who heads the University of Washington Institute for Environmental Studies in Seattle. But when the actual state of aquatic biology is added to the assessment equation, he said, it "doubles the proportion of waters that are in violation of water quality standards." In other words, he said, "the situation is not getting better."</p>
        <p>As a result, freshwater fish and invertebrates face particularly serious perils, and 362 species of freshwater fishes have been extinguished or are endangered as a result of human activity, said a broad group of scientists who met at the American Museum of Natural History in New York City recently to assess the dangers to biological diversity.</p>
        <p>"The condition of freshwater ecosystems over the last 100 years has gotten much, much worse," said Dr. Walter Reid, an ecologist with the World Resources Institute, a Washington-based research organization.</p>
        <p>A sweeping revision of the Clean Water Act approved by a House subcommittee last month not only backs away from further regulation like controlling runoff from farms but also would roll back some existing pollution-control measures.</p>
        <p>The fate of the American landscape and waters and the creatures who live there is perhaps the biggest domestic environmental problem on which the nation is not yet getting a good grip, a number of experts say. Preservation of natural habitat "is likely to be the primary ecological issue of the coming century," Mr. Easterbrook wrote in The New Yorker, while maintaining a generally optimistic posture.</p>
        <p>Dr. Thomas Lovejoy, a conservation biologist with the Smithsonian Institution, said at the Yale forum: "Biodiversity trends are negative. It is difficult to put numbers on it. But despite the imprecision, any biologist who has ever taken a look at the situation has come up with numbers to worry about. They don't always agree, but the numbers all point in the wrong direction."</p>
        <p>A study issued two months ago by the National Biological Service found that scores of natural ecosystems, amounting over all to at least half the area of the contiguous 48 states, have declined to the point of endangerment. This encompasses not just a few isolated species, but entire communities of species.</p>
        <p>The biological service's forthcoming report, "Our Living Resources," says that "if unchecked, human activities will continue to result in an upset balance of species interactions, alteration of ecosystems and extensive habitat loss."</p>
        <p>Sustained change of the American landscape by humans "continues, and continues at a substantial rate," said Dr. B. L. Turner 2d, the director of the George Perkins Marsh Institute at Clark University in Worcester, Mass. The institute is devoted to examining the relationship between people and the environment.</p>
        <p>But the signals of change can be confusing, said Dr. Turner. For instance, the long-recognized but continuing reforestation of the Eastern United States is being held up as a prime exhibit by environmental optimists. Many ecologists, however, say that although forest cover is increasing over all, the degree of fragmentation -- by development, logging or other forms of human activity -- is also increasing. Fragmentation of habitat is a main threat to biological diversity; while there may be more trees, many are in smaller, less biologically rich and more vulnerable patches. Moreover, several studies have shown that in many natural areas, a few alien plant species are taking over the ecosystem and choking out large numbers of native species. This process is clearly abetted, conservation biologists say, by the withholding of fire from the many ecosystems adapted to it.</p>
        <p>Over all, said Dr. Turner, the message about what is happening to the landscape "is a mixed message."</p>
        <p>Some kinds of ecosystems tend to recover spontaneously, to one extent or another, if humans leave them alone, though the recovery may take decades or centuries. The Eastern forests, which started coming back after farms were abandoned and the farmers moved west in the late 19th century, are one example. Similarly, millions of acres of prairie land in the Midwest, removed from cultivation under the Department of Agriculture's Conservation Reserve Program over the last decade, are beginning to recover some of their wild character.</p>
        <p>But conservation biologists say that in many cases the effects of human intervention -- the takeover by introduced species from abroad, for example, and the outright destruction of natural habitat -- may make it necessary for humans to intervene again to set things back on track, and then deliberately to manage ecosystems to keep them there.</p>
        <p>One positive sign is that a fledgling effort to restore natural ecosystems is beginning to pick up steam in several parts of the country. While some ecosystems can be partly or even largely restored, however, restorationists "are still a long way" from being able to return highly disturbed systems to a natural state in most cases, said Dr. Reid. Nevertheless, he said, "restoration is going to grow dramatically in the years ahead."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Reilly and others, eliminating pollution only to see the natural landscape steadily decay would be a disappointing achievement. "We may well get a safe environment," he said, "but it may not be a very attractive environment, or one we want to live in."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
