<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plant Plays Host to Ants, and Reaps the Benefits</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="764337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLOWERS AND PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCHIDIA MAJOR (PLANT)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MALAYSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Malaysia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Malaysia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDB1239F930A15756C0A963958260" item-length="428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plant Plays Host to Ants, and Reaps the Benefits</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESEARCHERS have shown that a rootless tropical plant shelters ants in its saclike leaves because the insects in turn supply it with key nutrients.</p>
        <p>For the first time, scientists say, they have been able to quantify the enormous benefit this sort of plant derives from playing host to ants in a mutually advantageous relationship: the plant absorbs large amounts of carbon dioxide from the ants' breath and nitrogen from their waste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESEARCHERS have shown that a rootless tropical plant shelters ants in its saclike leaves because the insects in turn supply it with key nutrients.</p>
        <p>For the first time, scientists say, they have been able to quantify the enormous benefit this sort of plant derives from playing host to ants in a mutually advantageous relationship: the plant absorbs large amounts of carbon dioxide from the ants' breath and nitrogen from their waste.</p>
        <p>By measuring the ratios of types of carbon and nitrogen derived from ants against those obtained from other sources, "we calculate that 39 percent of the carbon in the occupied host plant leaves is derived from ant-related respiration, and that 29 percent of the host nitrogen is derived from debris deposited into the leaf cavities by ants," the scientists wrote this month in the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>The tropical plant, Dischidia major, which was found in the Bako National Park in Malaysia, is an epiphyte. This is a nonparasitic plant that grows on other plants, or even nonliving objects such as fences or rocks, but depends upon the underlying structure only for support and not food. Epiphytes are sometimes called air plants because they appear to have no outside source of moisture or food other than air.</p>
        <p>Several scientists, including Dr. Camille R. Huxley of Oxford University in England, previously noted that Dischidia attracted small ants of the genus Philidris into special podlike leaves and that the insects often reared their young and left waste there. These experts suspected that the plant must be using the animals to augment their nutritional needs.</p>
        <p>In the new work, biologists at the University of Utah confirmed this nutritional relationship and measured it. Kathleen Treseder, a recent graduate who is now a doctoral student at Stanford University, working with Dr. James R. Ehleringer and Dr. Diane W. Davidson, retrieved saclike leaves from Dischidia plants growing on trees in Malaysia for the analysis.</p>
        <p>Ms. Treseder said in an interview that the large, rolled-up leaves used by ants differed markedly from ones that were not occupied. The sacs that harbored ants had interior pores, or stomates, to take up carbon dioxide more easily, she said. And after ants deposited feces and other refuse in older leaves, the plants grew roots in the leaf sacs to take up nitrogen from the debris deposits, she said.</p>
        <p>"This system allows the plants living on tree branches to obtain nitrogen where it is scarce, and to take up a lot of carbon dioxide for photosynthesis from an internal source," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
