<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Cuts Provoke Interest Groups' Fury</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="762072"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMES, STEVEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, EDWARD M (SEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DA123EF931A25756C0A963958260" item-length="989" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Cuts Provoke Interest Groups' Fury</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLMES, STEVEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The dramatic spending reductions put forward this week by House and Senate Republicans have stirred up a hornet's nest among interest groups in Washington.</p>
        <p>"I think there is no way to look at the current budget proposals and not see them as a drastic hit on environmental programs," said Gawain Kripke, director of the Friends of the Earth Appropriations Project. He was speaking of proposals to reduce financing for research on renewable energy sources and to open the Arctic Wildlife Refuge for oil and gas drilling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The dramatic spending reductions put forward this week by House and Senate Republicans have stirred up a hornet's nest among interest groups in Washington.</p>
        <p>"I think there is no way to look at the current budget proposals and not see them as a drastic hit on environmental programs," said Gawain Kripke, director of the Friends of the Earth Appropriations Project. He was speaking of proposals to reduce financing for research on renewable energy sources and to open the Arctic Wildlife Refuge for oil and gas drilling.</p>
        <p>"These cuts are so big that for a number of our hospitals, a substantial number, it's going to be very disruptive," Dick Davidson, president of the American Hospital Association said of the proposals to hold down projected increases in the Medicare and Medicaid health programs for the elderly, the disabled and the poor. "Ultimately it will affect quality, and a number of them are going to have to close."</p>
        <p>While interest groups representing veterans, the elderly, farmers, mayors, children and the poor castigated the Republicans' proposals, the budget plans received high marks from business lobbyists who believe they will lead to lower interest rates, and from the conservative Christian Coalition, which supports the House's $500-per child tax credit.</p>
        <p>"We love the overall thrust of the proposals," said Lonnie Taylor, vice president for Congressional Affairs for the United States Chamber of Commerce. "The chamber has been advocating a balanced budget for years. To have two proposals that are likely to make it to the floor of Congress is just wonderful."</p>
        <p>Veteran lobbyists in Washington say there has not been so much concern, praise or protest over a budget proposal since 1981, when President Ronald Reagan and David A. Stockman, then director of the Office of Management and the Budget, sought significant spending reductions and hefty tax cuts.</p>
        <p>But the proposals unveiled this week by House and Senate Republicans to pare in the range of $1 trillion from projected Federal spending increases over seven years, dwarf the budget cuts put forward by Mr. Reagan and Mr. Stockman.</p>
        <p>"The last time there was this same sense of threat was during the Stockman, O.M.B. years, particularly the early 80's," said a lobbyist who asked that neither he nor his organization be identified. "At that point, those cuts were considered dramatic, if not worse, because we had not experienced anything like them before. But these are much larger."</p>
        <p>As they begin to digest the scope of the Republicans' spending plans, representatives of some interest groups say that proposed reductions will play havoc with city budgets by reducing the Community Development Block Grant, will increase economic pressure on farmers by slashing farm price supports by $8 billion to $9 billion, will punish poor working families by reducing the earned income tax credit and will break a longstanding promise to the elderly not to mess with Social Security.</p>
        <p>"At the end of this process we're going to learn just how much the public hates the Federal Government," said Thomas Mann, an analyst of government at the Brookings Institution, a research center here. "The Republicans have taken the public at their word that they want a smaller government."</p>
        <p>Indeed, the National Taxpayers' Union said the wailing by many groups was in marked contrast to statements these organizations had previously made stating that they favored balancing the budget so long as the pain was spread around equitably.</p>
        <p>Pete Sepp, a spokesman for the taxpayers' union, said, "These are the very same groups, when lobbying against the balanced budget amendments, that said, 'We know there have to be cuts in spending and we know we have to balance the budget, but this amendment is not the way to do it.' Now it's time for them to put up or shut up. If they can't come up with a better package, then they shouldn't complain."</p>
        <p>Many critics of the Republicans' proposals insist that they support deficit reduction, and some even like some of the Republican cuts -- in other people's programs. "When we don't see cuts in other services such as Social Security, that has us greatly concerned," said Bill Smith, director of Public Affairs for the Veterans of Foreign Wars, who objected to reductions in funds for construction of Veterans hospitals.</p>
        <p>When it comes to programs they favor, however, these critics tend to say the reductions go too far, or break longstanding promises.</p>
        <p>Martin A. Corry, director of Federal Affairs at the American Association of Retired Persons, said his group was surprised to find that the House Republicans had recommended a change in inflation calculations that would effectively reduce Social Security and other Government benefits starting in 1999.</p>
        <p>Under the House Republicans' plan, announced on Wednesday by Representative John R. Kasich of Ohio, the chairman of the Budget Committee, the Consumer Price Index would be adjusted downward by six-tenths of 1 percent in 1999, on ground that it overstated the extent of inflation. The move would reduce the cost-of-living adjustments to Social Security payments, which are based on the index, which was already set to be adjusted downward in 1998.</p>
        <p>"What was surprising," Mr. Corry said, "was that after all of the statements by leadership on both sides of the aisle, including the President, that they would leave it alone, Mr. Kasich has reached to beyond what the Congressional Budget Office has projected."</p>
        <p>Pat Wolff, chief lobbyist for the American Farm Bureau, said agricultural subsidies had already been reduced by 50 percent from the projected spending levels since 1986. Now, she said, the Republicans were pushing for an actual reduction in price supports, rather than merely slowing their rate of growth.</p>
        <p>"We believe that if you take a look at historic spending for agriculture, that you find that these cuts are just not equitable," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
