<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Axes Land on Items Big and Small</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745061"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGISTRATION OF VOTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISASTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUREAUCRATIC RED TAPE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Voter Registration and Requirements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Disasters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bureaucratic Red Tape</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DD143AF937A15751C0A963958260" item-length="1359" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Axes Land on Items Big and Small</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Taking aim at both big ticket items like public housing and obscure programs like a voter registration project in the Western Sahara, House Republicans today outlined billions of dollars more in budget cuts.</p>
        <p>While House subcommittees continued their efforts to pare up to $15 billion from the current budget to help offset disaster relief spending, the full House took preliminary votes on measures aimed at putting a temporary freeze on most new Federal regulations. The regulatory moratorium, part of a broad effort by Republicans to rein in the Government's rule-making powers, is likely to pass the House on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Taking aim at both big ticket items like public housing and obscure programs like a voter registration project in the Western Sahara, House Republicans today outlined billions of dollars more in budget cuts.</p>
        <p>While House subcommittees continued their efforts to pare up to $15 billion from the current budget to help offset disaster relief spending, the full House took preliminary votes on measures aimed at putting a temporary freeze on most new Federal regulations. The regulatory moratorium, part of a broad effort by Republicans to rein in the Government's rule-making powers, is likely to pass the House on Friday.</p>
        <p>The most sweeping and emotionally charged of the Republicans' budget actions was a proposal to cut $9.4 billion from programs involving veterans, public housing and a host of Federal agencies dealing with everything from water installations to the Hubble Space Telescope. More than half of those savings, $5.36 billion, would be shifted to pay for natural disaster relief for California, Texas and Georgia.</p>
        <p>Programs that assist the needy would bear the brunt of the huge cut, with $5.7 billion from assisted housing alone. That category involves items like public housing development ($690.1 million), modernization projects ($1.2 billion), an incremental rental assistance program ($2.7 billion) and housing for people with AIDS ($186 million).</p>
        <p>Other programs targeted by the subcommittee on Veterans' Affairs, Health and Urban Development and Independent Agencies were the Hubble telescope ($10 million) and supercomputing research ($3 million), both under the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. The Environmental Protection Agency was marked for nearly $1.4 billion in cuts, most of them out of unspecified water installation projects ($1.3 billion).</p>
        <p>Two other panels presented their midyear budget reviews today and suggested cuts, known as rescissions: the Transportation subcommittee and the Commerce, Justice, State and Judiciary subcommittee. All told, the four subcommittees of the House Appropriations Committee outlined nearly $11 billion in cuts to the current Federal budget. But those potential savings were offset by the disaster relief request.</p>
        <p>The Administration had asked for $6.7 billion to help California bear the costs of the 1994 Northridge earthquake and for California, Texas and Georgia to pay for flood damages. But the Republicans agreed to provide only 80 percent of the request, $5.36 billion, saying that they would wait until after the fiscal year 1997 to determine if more money was needed.</p>
        <p>Even the White House failed to escape the Republicans' budget ax.  The Treasury, Postal Service subcommittee approved a modest $160.2 million in cuts that included a $171,000 reduction to the Executive Office of the President, money that normally goes for salaries.</p>
        <p>It was more a political swipe than a fiscal blow for the White House, and Democrats on the subcommittee took immediate exception, calling the proposed cut partisan pettiness.</p>
        <p>"The $171,000 is nickel-and-diming them and I don't think we should do that," said Steny H. Hoyer, the ranking Democrat on the subcommittee.</p>
        <p>The Republican-drafted rescission bills targeted $700 million in cuts to transportation.</p>
        <p>Programs that fall under the jurisdiction of the Commerce, Justice and State Departments were marked for $449.3 million in reductions.</p>
        <p>Those spending cuts would wipe out one of the pet projects of the Clinton Administration: the Violent Crime Reduction Trust Fund, a component of the President's crime package that was to have dispensed "Ounce of Prevention Grants" to local police jurisdictions. The Republicans marked for elimination the program's annual budget of $1.5 million, noting that the House had killed that program on Feb. 14 and replaced it with block grants to local law enforcement agencies.</p>
        <p>The Commerce subcommittee also eliminated the Globe Program, an international science education and climate change research project for students from kindergarten through 12th grade. The Democratic-controlled Congress last year approved $7 million for the project, an acronym for Global Learning and Observations to Benefit the Environment, and it was to begin operating next April on the 25th anniversary of Earth Day.</p>
        <p>An amendment to strike funds for Globe in the last Congress failed by one vote on the House floor.</p>
        <p>And the Republicans continued their assault against paying for international peacekeeping operations, denying the Clinton Administration's appeal for a $672 million emergency supplemental appropriation to cover estimated peacekeeping bills through the end of the current fiscal year on Sept. 30.</p>
        <p>The Republican budget cutters were able to find even more obscure foreign spending. From the State Department, they cut funds for a four-year-old operation in the Western Sahara to register 200,000 people to vote. According to the subcommittee, the project cost $100,000 a day and only 12,000 people had been registered since 1991.</p>
        <p>In beginning debate on the bill to temporarily freeze most new Federal regulations, the full House refused to permit specific health, safety and environmental rules to take effect. At the same time, it moved to free regulators to proceed with some rules favored by industry.</p>
        <p>For example, the House voted not to delay Federal Communications Commission regulations that will help open new markets for communications companies to offer cellular telephone services, but it refused to explicitly approve a proposal by the Agriculture Department to impose stricter requirements for inspecting meat.</p>
        <p>The full House almost certainly will pass the anti-regulation bill on Friday, and President Clinton has hinted that he might veto it. The regulatory moratorium is part of a broad effort led by Congressional Republicans to restrict the Government's rule-making powers.</p>
        <p>The proposed legislation, affecting most rules issued between last Nov.  20 and next Dec. 31, would temporarily shelter businesses and individuals from hundreds of new regulations. During the moratorium, Congress would debate a separate bill that would permanently change the way Federal rules are written.</p>
        <p>Republicans accused the Administration and its allies in the House of using "scare tactics" to suggest that the delay in new regulations would jeopardize public health and safety.</p>
        <p>The measure debated today would exempt regulations addressing "an imminent threat to health or safety or other emergency." It also exempted other categories, including banking regulations, tax rulings by the Internal Revenue Service and routine actions by regulatory agencies. The sponsors of the bill argued that further exemptions were unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Democrats, knowing that they do not have the votes to defeat the bill and limited by the Republican majority to just 10 hours of debate, seized on several examples of rules that would be delayed, saying the examples showed how the moratorium would endanger the public.</p>
        <p>For example, Representative Louise Slaughter of upstate New York, a former bacteriologist with a degree in public health, proposed a specific exemption to let the Agriculture Department go ahead with its recent proposal requiring the meat industry to modernize its methods of detecting the bacteria that cause food poisoning. The amendment was defeated, 177 to 249.</p>
        <p>The meat inspection rules, issued after highly publicized episodes of fatal poisoning resulting from contaminated hamburgers at fast food restaurants, are opposed by the food industry.</p>
        <p>Although thousands of people die or become ill each year because of food poisoning, Democrats warned that the regulations would not be exempted from the freeze proposal because the inspections did not address an "imminent" danger. The bill's sponsors have argued that the measure would not necessarily block the department's proposal.</p>
        <p>Next week, the House is expected to vote on a broader Republican proposal, part of the Contract With America, which would subject most major new regulations to elaborate risk-assessment procedures and require determinations that the benefits of regulations outweigh their costs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
