<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="766716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFD91E39F937A35755C0A963958260" item-length="4746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Music</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Music</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY MUSIC FESTIVAL The Cape May Festival Orchestra. Today, Tuesday and Thursday at 8:30 P.M. The Cape May Festival Pops Orchestra presents a concert for families next Sunday at 2 P.M. and an evening performance at 8:30. Tickets:  $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and  Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278.</p>
        <p>FIRST CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH, WESTFIELD James Chang, 14-year-old violinist, performs the works of Mozart and Beethoven, with Vicki Sedlacek, pianist, and Stephen Wolosonovich, guest violinist. Saturday at 7 P.M. 125 Elmer Street. (908) 232-0737.</p>
        <p>FORT LEE FREE PUBLIC LIBRARY Arlene Kachadoorian, soprano, and Mariano Vidal, tenor, sing operatic arias. Thursday at 8 P.M. Free. 320 Main Street, Fort Lee.  (201) 592-3614.</p>
        <p>MORRIS CHORAL SOCIETY The society, led by R. Wayne Walters, performs Haydn's "Creation." Today at 7:30 P.M. St. Joseph's Church, Main Street, Mendham. Friday and Saturday at 7:30 P.M, Church of the Redeemer, South Street, Morristown. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. (201) 895-4142.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY POPS Conducted by Michael Buglio, the New Jersey Pops Symphony Orchestra performs classical, Broadway, standards and patriotic music. Today at  7 P.M. Free. The Gazebo on Ridgewood Avenue, Florham Park. (201) 744-1700, extension 52.</p>
        <p>OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS "Tribute to Nat 'King' Cole," with Freddy Cole and the Freddy Cole Trio, along with the Ink Spots. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035.</p>
        <p>RIDGEWOOD CONCERT BAND A concert with Myra Garcia-Fernandez, soprano, and Rick White, trumpeter. Next Sunday at 7 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Benjamin Franklin High School, Glen and Van Dien Streets. (201) 265-6174.</p>
        <p>SHREWSBURY CHORALE A chorus of 75 singers from Monmouth, Ocean and Middlesex Counties, under the direction of Brian Aschinger, gives its first concert of the season. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for students and the elderly. First Unitarian Church, 1475 West Front Street, Lincroft. (908) 747-4582.</p>
        <p>SOCLAIR MUSIC FESTIVAL The 20th season begins with an anniversary celebration titled "Bach 'N All." Next Sunday at 4 P.M. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. Soclair Brooks Farm, 19 Haytown Road, Lebanon. (908) 236-6476.</p>
        <p>SUMMERFEST '95 CONCERTS The Morris County Park Commission presents "Big Band Express." Today at 3 P.M. Free. Frelinghuysen Arboretum, 53 East Hanover Avenue, Morris Township. The Tim Gillis Band will perform next Sunday at 3 P.M. Schooleys Mountain Park, West Springstown Road, Washington Township. (201) 326-7600. TRINITY COVENANT CHURCH, LIVINGSTON Holly Weiss, soprano, and Marion Pedersen, organist, present a benefit concert of opera and oratorio favorites. Today at 5  P.M. Tickets: $10. 343 East Cedar Street. (201) 992-4044.</p>
        <p>UNITARIAN CHURCH OF PRINCETON Anita Cervantes of the Chamber Music Co-op performs a solo piano concert. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10 or $6 for students and the elderly. Cherry Hill Road, off Route 206. (609) 448-4068.</p>
        <p>VINCENT UNITED METHODIST CHURCH, NUTLEY Mixolydian Brass and Organ Ensemble. Today at 4 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $4 for students. 100 Vincent Place. (201) 667-5440.</p>
        <p>WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER Harmonytryx, an eight-woman a cappella group, performs "Java Jive," "In the Mood," "River of Dreams" and "Zombie Jamboree." Today at 7  P.M. Tickets: $8. At 8 P.M. on Friday, Johnny Varro gives a solo piano concert.  Tickets: $10. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190.</p>
        <p>WESTMINSTER CHOIR COLLEGE The Westminster Conservatory Chorale, conducted by Frank Abrahams, will perform works of Mozart, Mendelssohn, Rachmaninoff and Stephen Sondheim. Today at 4 P.M. Free. The Playhouse on the college campus, 101 Walnut Lane, Princeton. (609) 921-2663.</p>
        <p>Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF CLIFTON THe Council Contemporary Club, a group of singers and dancers, presents its annual music show, "Smile, Darn You, Smile." Next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $2. 199 Scoles Avenue, Clifton. (201) 799-2980.</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>ABERDEEN/MATAWAN REPERTORY THEATER "Tribute," a comic drama. Today at 3 P.M. and Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly.  First Presbyterian Church, Route 34 at Franklin Street, Matawan. (908) 583-1093.</p>
        <p>BRUNDAGE PARK PLAYHOUSE "Les Liaisons Dangereuses," by Christopher Hampton. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Through June 17. Tickets: $10. Carrell Road, Randolph. (201) 989-7092.</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire," with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Through July 1. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341.</p>
        <p>CIRCLE PLAYHOUSE "The Final Word: The Hall-Mills Murders," written and directed  by Nick Pelino Jr. Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $10. 416 Victoria Avenue, Piscataway. (908) 968-7555.</p>
        <p>CROSSROADS THEATER COMPANY "Genesis 1995: A Celebration of New Voices in African-American Theater" presents "Blues Train, a Play With Music," by Ronald Wyche. Today at 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $15. 7 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 249-5560.</p>
        <p>GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE "Of Mice and Men." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $26. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 246-7717.</p>
        <p>McCARTER THEATER "Random Acts '95," the second annual two-week-long festival of  new plays presents "A Park in Our House," by Nilo Cruz. Tuesday through Friday at 8 P.M., Saturday at 4 P.M., next Sunday at 7:30 P.M., June 12, 13, 14 and 16  at 8 P.M., June 17 at 9 P.M. and June 18 at 7:30 P.M. Staged readings of one-act plays by Wendy Wasserstein, Joyce Carol Oates, Mac Wellman and Jane Anderson will be presented on Saturday at 8:30 P.M., next Sunday at 2 P.M., June 17 at 5  P.M. and June 18 at 2 P.M. Tickets: $18. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000.</p>
        <p>MODERN JEWISH REPERTORY THEATER "Two," by Ron Elisha. Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Through next Sunday.  Tickets: $25. Blooming Grove Theater, 544 Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 325-8154.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL "Love's Labour's Lost." Today at 2 and 7 P.M.; Tuesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Wednesday and Saturday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-5600.</p>
        <p>PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE "The Secret Garden," a musical by Marsha Norman and Lucy Simon based on the novel by Frances Hodgson Burnett. Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 23. Tickets: $29 to $44. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343.</p>
        <p>PARSIPPANY PLAYHOUSE "Run for Your Wife." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 18. Tickets: $10, or $7 for students and the elderly. 130 Knoll Road, Lake Hiawatha. (201) 263-7020.</p>
        <p>SETON HALL UNIVERSITY The Celtic Theater Company presents John B. Keane's "Sharon's Grave." Today at 2 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $9, or $7 for students and the elderly. 400 South Orange Avenue, South Orange. (201) 761-9790.</p>
        <p>SMALL TOWN AND FANCY PLAYERS "The Fantasticks," presented with the Mahwah High School Drama Club. Friday and Saturday and June 16 and 17 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. Mahwah High School, Ridge Road. (201) 529-4909.</p>
        <p>SOMERSET VALLEY PLAYHOUSE "Inherit the Wind." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 7 P.M. Through June 18. Tickets: $10 on Friday and Sunday; $12 on  Saturday. Route 514, Amwell Road, Hillsborough. (908) 369-7469.</p>
        <p>STRAND THEATER "Ravensbruck," a suspense drama set during World War II. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $15 and $18. Fourth Street and Clifton Avenue, Lakewood. (908) 367-9595.</p>
        <p>Museums and Galleries</p>
        <p>ARTWORKS Paintings of Dante's "Inferno," by Eric Fowler. Thursday, Friday and Saturday through June 24. Thursday and Friday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 2 P.M. 19 Everrett Alley, Trenton. (609) 394-9436. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248.</p>
        <p>BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. Through Aug. 10. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195.</p>
        <p>CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804.</p>
        <p>CRAFTSMAN FARM "Time of Transition: Textiles of the Arts and Crafts Movement" displays a variety of textiles, including table scarves, pillow covers, pocketbooks, bedspreads and clothing. Today, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for students and the elderly. Route 10 and Manor Lane, about three miles west of Route 287, Parsippany. (201) 540-1165. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007.</p>
        <p>EXTENSION GALLERY "Hug the Noise," an exhibition of cast metal sculpture and drawings by Sean Poreda. Starts Monday. Through June 29. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777.</p>
        <p>GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Through July 1. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035.</p>
        <p>GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Omaha -- an Artist's Journey: Memories of D-Day," with  drawings and collages by Ugo Giannini. Through Today, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754.</p>
        <p>GUILD OF CREATIVE ART "Rhythms of Nature," a collection of landscapes, watercolors, pastels and collages by Fran McIlvain. Starts today with a reception from 3 to 5 P.M. Through July 6. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 4:30 P.M. 620 Broad Street, Route 35, Shrewsbury. (908) 741-1441.</p>
        <p>HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Through June 25. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415.</p>
        <p>JAZZ 88 GALLERY Paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880.</p>
        <p>J. RICHARDS GALLERY Oil paintings of faraway beaches, old Paris streets and landscapes of the French countryside by J. P. Dubord are on display. Opening reception on Thursday, 6 to 9 P.M. Through June 26. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 64 East Palisade Avenue, Englewood. (201) 871-1050.</p>
        <p>KERYGMA GALLERY "A Sense of Place," works by Townsend Howe, a realist painter with an impressionistic style. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Through Saturday. 38 Oak Street, Ridgewood. (201) 444-5510.</p>
        <p>LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photgraphs by H. Lisa Solon. Through June 29. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464.</p>
        <p>MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "From Darkness Into Light," paintings and drawings by Howard Lerner. Starts Monday. Through June 30. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 1 Williams  Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 939-6969.</p>
        <p>MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the papermaking town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through next Sunday. Admission: $3, or $2 for the elderly. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College, 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266.</p>
        <p>MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through June 25. "Still Life Works From the Collection" offers 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555.</p>
        <p>NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found," an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimensional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M.  River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through July 2. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through July 2. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through next Sunday. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday,  9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton.  (609) 292-6308.</p>
        <p>NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through June  18. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly,  $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848.</p>
        <p>PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Renee Foosaner Art Gallery holds its Sixth Annual Juried Exhibition of Miniature Art. Starts Wednesday. Through July 30. Opening reception on Monday, 6 to 9 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636, extension 2272.</p>
        <p>PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The Passaic County Cultural and Heritage Council presents paintings and collages by Arnold Brown. Starts Tuesday; opening reception on Friday, 6 to 8 P.M. Through July 20. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M.  to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-5448.</p>
        <p>PINE SHORES ART ASSOCIATION Spring Art Show, featuring the works of members and  local artists. Starts today with a reception from 1 to 4 P.M. Through June 21. Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 3:30 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 3:30 P.M. 94 Stafford Avenue,  Manahawkin. (609) 597-3557.</p>
        <p>RABBET GALLERY "Five Sculptors: Clay, Wood, Metal." Starts today with areception from 3 to 5 P.M. Through July 7. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. 120 Georges Road, New Brunswick. (908) 828-5150.</p>
        <p>RIVERRUN GALLERY "Face -- Feelings," 40 works in oil, watercolor and mixed media by Edward Adams. Through Monday. Noon to 5 P.M. daily (closed on Tuesday). 287 South Main Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-3349.</p>
        <p>SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "New Insights -- Rising Talent," an exhibition of the work of John Bingham, glass craftsman; Andrew Braitman, painter, and Lisa Gralnick, metal- smith. Opening reception on Friday, 7 to 9 P.M. Through July 8. Monday through Wednesday and Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Thursday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720.</p>
        <p>SHOESTRING GALLERY "Hung Up," paintings and sculptures by Bill Barrell. Through  June 17. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018.</p>
        <p>STEAMROLLER GALLERY Paintings by Sara Pasti. Through Saturday. Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 52 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-7279.</p>
        <p>STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Naturescape," an exhibition of paintings by Christina Allen, Sarah Antin and Guy Ciarcia. Starts Saturday with  a reception from 1:30 to 3:30 P.M. Through July 22. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592.</p>
        <p>TRENTON CITY MUSEUM "When Trenton Baseball Roared Like Thunder" and "Extra Innings." Today, 2 to 4 P.M. Parkside Avenue and West State Street, Trenton. (609) 989-3632.</p>
        <p>UNTITLED (#130), LTD Paintings, sculpture and photography by Joanna Thompson, Jennifer Freid and Frank Fernicola. Today, noon to 5 P.M. "Intro Art -- Children's Art Exhibit." Starts Thursday. Through June 25. Opening reception on  Saturday, 2 to 6 P.M. Gallery hours: Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767.</p>
        <p>WYCKOFF GALLERY "Spring Rhapsody," traditional and abstract works in various media. Through next Monday. Tuesday through Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436.</p>
        <p>ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM More than 100 prints document "Printmaking in America"" from 1960 to 1990. Drawn from private collections and museums around the country, the exhibition includes works by Andy Warhol, Roy Lichtenstein, Roger Brown and others. Through June 18. Free. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237.</p>
        <p>Spoken Word</p>
        <p>BELLEVILLE PUBLIC LIBRARY Linda Heimall, an opera singer, will give three lectures on opera: "The Age of Bel Canto" on Wednesday at 1 P.M. "The French Opera" on June 14 and "Opera Becomes Real Verismo" on June 21. Free. 221 Washington Avenue, Belleville. (201) 450-3434.</p>
        <p>BERGEN COUNTY COMMUNITY SERVICES BUILDING George M. Aronson, photographer, presents "The New Jersey Highlands: Treasures at Risk," a narrated slide show, at a meeting of the North Jersey chapter of the Adirondack Mountain Club. Friday at 8 P.M. Free. 327 Ridgewood, Paramus. (201) 368-4200.</p>
        <p>BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE "The Health and Care of the Elderly" will be discussed in a symposium for people who work with older adults. Wednesday, 8:30  A.M. to 4:30 P.M. The $35 fee includes lunch and materials. 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 224-2880.</p>
        <p>ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Lorraine Matys, a travel photographer and lecturer, will give a slide presentation on "Ancient Egypt: Art and Archaeology, What Does It All Mean?" Tuesday at 7 P.M. Free. Prof. James P. Woods of Montclair State University presents a lecture on "The Vikings." Free. Wednesday at 7:30 P.M. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215.</p>
        <p>JFK MEDICAL CENTER Edward Asner is the guest speaker at "A Celebration of Life," the J.F.K. Medical Center's free program marking Cancer Survivors' Day 1995. Today, 1 P.M. 70 James Street, Edison. (908) 632-1586.</p>
        <p>MORRIS COUNTY PARK SYSTEMS The "Nature Through Garden's Gate" program will describe ways to attract hummingbirds and butterflies into gardens and ways to discourage undesirable insects. The focus will be on control by natural interaction. Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. at the Cooper Mill. Free. County Route 513, Chester Township. (201) 326-7645.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS Alfred Vitiello, a producer with Suburban Cablevision, will discuss TV production as part of "Just About Art," an open forum on art issues, which includes a tour of "The Artful Message: Contemporary  Video" exhibition. Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Free. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121.</p>
        <p>SOMERSET MEDICAL CENTER A series of lectures on health and medicine by Dorothy L. Zufall includes "The Brain at Risk," on Monday at 7 P.M.; "Stroke Club," on Tuesday at 2 P.M., and "Don't Forget -- Improving Your Memory," on Wednesday at  10 A.M. Advance registration required. 110 Rehill Avenue, Somerville. (908) 685-2200.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY THEATER Parachute Express brings its musical styles, ranging from folk to rock to R &amp; B, together for a family concert. Today at 11 A.M. and 2 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for children. 100 South Street, Morristown. (201) 539-8008.</p>
        <p>HERITAGE DAYS FESTIVAL Food, arts and crafts, dancing, music, a puppet theater and other activities for children are some of the attractions of Trenton's 17th  annual Heritage Days Festival. The festival is held on the streets of downtown Trenton and in Mill Hill Park. Today, 1 to 7 P.M. Free. (609) 695-7107.</p>
        <p>MARCELLA GELTMAN GALLERY The Art Center of Northern New Jersey sponsors the Annual Children's Art Show. Starts today with a reception from 6 to 8 P.M. Through next Monday. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 3 P.M. 250 Center Street, New Milford. (201) 599-2992.</p>
        <p>MEADOW THEATER "The Lion, the Witch and the Wardrobe." Saturday at 11 A.M. and June 17 at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099.</p>
        <p>NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M. and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Comic Books Workshop" forchildren 9 to 12. Create a character and take it through different adventures. Bring pencil and paper no smaller than 8 1/2 by 11 inches. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 12:30 P.M. Fee: $15. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308.</p>
        <p>PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE THEATER "North, South, East and Jim West," a multicultural puppet production for children 4 to 9. Monday at 9:15 and 10:45 A.M. Free, but reservations are required. Ellison Street and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-6182.</p>
        <p>RITZ THEATER "Jack and the Beanstalk." Thursday and Friday at 10 A.M. and Saturday at 10 A.M. and 1 P.M. Tickets: $4. 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609)  858-5230.</p>
        <p>ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM Children and their families are invited to participate in a  free origami workshop. Participants will learn basic origami techniques and construct an origami mobile to bring home. All materials are provided but advance registration is required. Next Sunday at 2 P.M. The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237.</p>
        <p>Etc.</p>
        <p>ART CENTER OF NORTHERN NEW JERSEY Cartooning Illustration Forum, a four-hour course for students 16 and up who have an interest in the basics of cartoon illustration. Today at 10 A.M. Course fee: $50. 250 Center Street, New Milford.  (201) 599-2992.</p>
        <p>CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through June 17. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351.</p>
        <p>COIN, STAMP AND CURRENCY SHOW Today, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Free. Birchwood Manor, 111 North Jefferson Road, Whippany. (201) 887-1414.</p>
        <p>DINNER AND THEATER The $42 ticket price includes a four-course meal and "Deep Space Noir," an interactive and futuristic detective story. Saturdays. 8 P.M. Il Giardino Restaurant. 41 Ridgedale Avenue, Cedar Knolls. (201) 301-0562.</p>
        <p>GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER The 1995 Spring Heritage Festivals begin with the Polish Festival, which will feature food, craft items, music, traditional Polish folk dancing and a Polish shopping village with dolls, jewelry, folk games, records and tapes. Today, starting at 10 A.M. The Polish-American Dancers perform at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10 to $23. The Italian Heritage Festival includes food, craft items, jewelry, cultural displays, sing-a-longs, comedy acts and dancing. Saturday, starting at 11 A.M. The "Festa Italians," a revue with music  and comedy, begins at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $7 to $25. The Jewish Festival of the Arts is next Sunday, starting at 10 A.M. with a stage show at 2 P.M. with Freddie Roman, comedian, and Michael Burstyn, singer. Tickets: $5 to $21. Exit 16 on the Garden State Park Way, Holmdel. ((908) 442-9200.</p>
        <p>GREEK ORTHODOX FESTIVAL Kimisis Tis Theotokou Greek Orthodox Church sponsors the 19th Annual Greek Festival with food, folk dancing and imported jewelry and craft items. Today, noon to 8 P.M. Admission: $1. 20 Hillcrest Road, Holmdel. (908) 739-1515.</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL "The Madness of King George," Friday; "Psycho," Saturday; "To Live," next Friday, and "Ladybird, Ladybird," next Saturday. All show times 7 P.M. Tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, Milledoler Hall, George Street and Seminary Place. (908) 932-8482.</p>
        <p>POW-WOW AND FESTIVAL The Nanticoke Lenni-Lenape Indians present two full days of dancing, drumming, arts and crafts, foods and cultural exhibits in this 15th annual event. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M., and next Sunday, 10 A.M. until 4 P.M. Admission: $5, or $2 for the elderly. Salem County Fair Grounds, Route 40,  Woodstown. (609) 455-6910.</p>
        <p>REFORMED CHURCH OF FREEHOLD The Freehold Area Branch of the American Association of University Women holds its annual book sale. Thursday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 8 P.M., and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Proceeds benefit scholarships and community service projects. 67 West Main Street, Freehold. (908) 462-1717.</p>
        <p>Song and Dance  With credits ranging from screen to stage, Ben Vereen, backed by a five-piece ensemble, performs in an evening of song and dance. CONGREGATION B'NAI JESHURUN Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $35. 1025 South Orange Avenue, Short Hills. (201) 379-1555.</p>
        <p>Fine Lines  "Pencilworks: The Drawings of Jerry Winick" displays pencil drawings noted for their details and photo-like realism. PATERSON MUSEUM Starts today. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 12:30 to 4:30 P.M. 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 881-3874.</p>
        <p>Latin Jazz  Tito Puente and his 10-piece Latin Jazz Ensemble perform in a concert to benefit the Community Theater's fund for repairs and restoration. COMMUNITY THEATER Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $25. 100 South Street, Morristown. (201) 539-8008.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
