<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDF1F38F930A35750C0A963958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A2-13  BIG GAMBLES GONE WRONG  Barings P.L.C. left itself open to trouble. Letting a rising young trader like Nicholas W. Leeson in essence police himself showed that the firm did not have effective controls to prevent the losses of $1 billion that brought it down. A1  ANDREOTTI TO STAND TRIAL  Giulio Andreotti, a former Prime Minister and symbol of Italy's now-collapsed political establishment, was ordered to stand trial on charges that he acted as a protector for the Mafia. A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A2-13  BIG GAMBLES GONE WRONG  Barings P.L.C. left itself open to trouble. Letting a rising young trader like Nicholas W. Leeson in essence police himself showed that the firm did not have effective controls to prevent the losses of $1 billion that brought it down. A1  ANDREOTTI TO STAND TRIAL  Giulio Andreotti, a former Prime Minister and symbol of Italy's now-collapsed political establishment, was ordered to stand trial on charges that he acted as a protector for the Mafia. A1</p>
        <p>TV OFFICIAL'S DEATH ROCKS RUSSIA  The killing of the head of a television network has lifted the thin veil covering the corruption that has insinuated itself into Russia's largest industries. A8  A SOMBER FAREWELL TO SOMALIA  The last American marines left Mogadishu after supervising the withdrawal of United Nations forces. The pullout ends a mission that fed Somalia's hungry but did not end the fighting there. A3  REIN IN POLICE, 12 URGE IN BEIJING  In a petition to lawmakers, 12 prominent intellectuals warned that the failure to rein in indiscriminate police powers throughout China was threatening "the lives and freedom" of 1.2 billion Chinese. A2  The arrest of a top Mexican boosted the President's standing. A5  Serbs blocked aid convoys seeking to reach a Bosnian enclave. A7  Punta Arenas Journal: Much ado about a hole in the ozone layer. A4  National A14-20, B7  AMENDMENT FAILS, FOR NOW  The Senate failed to adopt a balanced-budget amendment to the Constitution. But a parliamentary maneuver will make another vote easy to get.  A1  TWO 'HOMETOWN HEROES'  "They're paying attention now" one North Dakotan said after his state's senators voted against the balanced-budget amendment.  A1  PLANE INCIDENTS MISDIAGNOSED  Two employees of the maker of ATR turboprops testified that they had misunderstood early incidents in which their planes showed instability because of icing.  A1  THE ELUSIVE TOP QUARK  Two rival groups of physicists announced that they had found the top quark, an ephemeral building block of matter.  A1  THE ULTIMATE SACRED COW  Nine new Republican members of the House were eager to cut the size of government until low-cost electric power in the Northwest was singled out.  A14  CRIES FOR HELP BEFORE KILLINGS  A Jehovah's Witness sought help because she was afraid of her teen-age sons. Now she, her husband and another son are dead.  A14  TUBERCULOSIS DANGERS  Federal officials have documented a case of tuberculosis transmitted from one passenger to others on a commercial airline.  B7  Law B8  Maid's memory is the target of Simpson prosecutors.</p>
        <p>Metro Digest B1  INDICTMENT IN SUBWAY SHOOTING  Even as he announced an assault indictment charging a police officer with recklessly shooting a black undercover transit officer, the Manhattan District Attorney called the indicted officer "a sympathetic figure" who had acted after finding himself in a frightening and "very difficult situation." A1  Business Digest D1  Weekend C1-28  Similar passages in two books.  C3  Guide to the mini-museums.  C1  For Children C26  Theater: On Stage, and OffC2  "Smokey Joe's Cafe." C1  Film: "Man of the House." C6  "Super 8 1/2" C6  "Roommates." C10  "Exotica." C12  "The K.K.K. Boutique Ain't Just Rednecks." C14  "Hideaway." C14  "Mina Tannenbaum." C17  Music: Battle and Hampson put on a parade of hits.  C3  Recital by Alexander Korsantiya.  C5  Restaurants C22  Art: Bruce Nauman, at the Museum of Modern Art.  C1  Works by Minnie Evans.  C18  Paintings from the limbo of storage.  C18  Inside Art C24  Art in Review C21  Books: "The Last of the Duchess." C27  Television: TV Weekend D16  Home Video D16  Sports B11-18  Baseball: Negotiations are bad news.  B11  Replacement Yanks lose.  B11  Basketball: Knicks rebound.  B11  Columns: Vecsey on Giants.  B11  On Basketball.  B14  Football: Pats get Meggett.  B11  Browns, Simms not set yet. B11  Hockey: Islanders and Devils lose.  B13  Racing: Timber Country in the hunt.  B18  Sports People B14  Obituaries B9-10  Ashton Graybiel, doctor.  B10  Ferdinand Lundberg, writer.  B10  Editorials/Op-Ed A26-27  Editorials  A bad idea, buried.  Whose drug problem?  Mr. Bliley's double talk.  Close more bases -- now.  Letters  Anthony Lewis: Zelig for President?  A. M. Rosenthal: Wilson at the pool.  Po Bronson: The young and the reckless.  Stephen Sherrill and Paul Tough: What men can do.  Chronicle B4  Crossword C27</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
