<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place;Disappointment in the Lab and on Wall St.</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19951202T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="809266"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSIDER TRADING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENGELHARD CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insider Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DC1139F936A25752C1A963958260" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place;Disappointment in the Lab and on Wall St.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few companies have ever issued more expansive claims for a new technology than did the Engelhard Corporation last April when it announced a system that would "allow automobiles to reduce smog" and drastically cut the amount of ozone in the air.</p>
        <p>The announcement caused a flurry of excitement and sent the company's stock price soaring. It rose 31 percent that day and rose a total of 66 percent by the time the price peaked in July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few companies have ever issued more expansive claims for a new technology than did the Engelhard Corporation last April when it announced a system that would "allow automobiles to reduce smog" and drastically cut the amount of ozone in the air.</p>
        <p>The announcement caused a flurry of excitement and sent the company's stock price soaring. It rose 31 percent that day and rose a total of 66 percent by the time the price peaked in July.</p>
        <p>Then yesterday, after Engelhard said tests that showed the environmental benefits from its catalytic system were "less than originally projected," the stock tumbled $4.125, or 16 percent, to close at $21.125, less than $2 above its price before the April announcement. Wall Street analysts rushed to withdraw the "buy" recommendations they had issued in the wake of the original announcement.</p>
        <p>The rise and subsequent fall of Engelhard shares illustrate the risks of leaping into a stock based on forecasts of a huge new success. That is especially true if corporate insiders are themselves selling, as was the case at Engelhard.</p>
        <p>At least eight Engelhard executives, including the company's top three officers and the head of its research operations, sold about $19 million in stock. All told, the Engelhard insiders took in about $4.8 million more than they would have received had they sold their shares at yesterday's closing price. The average price they got was $28.37 a share -- a level the stock had never reached before the April announcement.</p>
        <p>"Sometimes Wall Street bids the price of a stock up, and insiders take advantage of it," said Bob Gabele, the president of CDA/Investnet of Fort Lauderdale, Fla., which monitors insider sales of stock. He said he believed that had happened at Engelhard.</p>
        <p>At Engelhard, a leading maker of catalytic converters for cars, Francis X. Vitale Jr., a vice president of strategic planning and corporate affairs, said it was normal for Engelhard officers to sell stock, which they get from exercising stock options. He said most of the compensation for top officers was  in the form of stock, and he denied that this year's selling represented a large increase from normal patterns. "If it was up in total shares, it was up by a nominal amount," he said.</p>
        <p>But records of the sales filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission indicate that there was a sharp increase in selling from April to November. In 1994, from April through November, only two insiders sold, taking in $1.4 million.</p>
        <p>In the latest period, Mr. Gabele said several officers, among them Orin R. Smith, the chairman and chief executive, and L. Donald Latorre, the president, sold more than ever before. Mr. Smith took in $7.1 million and Mr. Latorre $4.3 million from selling shares.</p>
        <p>Not all of that was profit, of course. The executives paid from $4.54 to $17.92 a share to buy the stock when exercising options, with most of the purchases at prices below $10 a share. Mr. Smith and Mr. Latorre, for example, had profits of $5.1 million and $3.1 million, respectively. Most of the options  exercised this year could have been exercised at a profit, albeit a smaller one, in earlier years. This year's stock price surge provided a strong incentive to cash in on the profits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gabele said this year's selling by insiders, which began in April and ended in September, was greater than for any full year since 1991, when the law  on insider trading was changed, generating a flurry of selling at many companies, including Engelhard. Before 1991, top corporate officers who exercised stock options were required to hold the shares for at least six months, leaving them open to the possibility that the share price would fall. Since then, it has been legal for them to exercise options and sell the shares immediately.</p>
        <p>Selling of shares by insiders is completely legal, so long as they are not acting on material information that has not been made public at the time of the sale. There is no evidence that the results of the tests on the Engelhard pollution-reduction system, which were conducted jointly with the Ford Motor Company, were known when the stock sales were made.</p>
        <p>And in many cases, insiders sell shares because they need the money, not because they think the stock is overvalued. Mr. Vitale, who took in $1.6 million, cited his need for money to build a house in Spring Lake, N.J.</p>
        <p>The news release that Engelhard issued in April to describe its system was one of the most expansive ever. It proposed placing a catalytic coating on a car's radiator and air-conditioning condenser. As air passed over the coating, ozone, a pollutant, would be converted into oxygen, while carbon monoxide, another pollutant, would be turned into carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>If the system was installed on all vehicles in Los Angeles, the company said  then, there would be a bigger reduction in ozone than from all other suggested alternatives together, including the use of electric cars, reformulated gasolines and efforts to reduce commuting by workers.</p>
        <p>In the latest announcement, released late Monday after the stock market had closed for the day, Engelhard and Ford said that the system was performing well, but that it would not do as much for the environment as had been hoped. The companies said that was because they had earlier overestimated how much ozone would come into contact with a radiator and what percentage of that ozone  could be converted.</p>
        <p>It also turns out that the original estimate assumed that cars would be designed so that the radiator fans would turn on at times of high pollution, even if the car was parked, thereby becoming air-cleaning systems. That idea has been dropped by Ford, but Mr. Vitale said Engelhard would continue to pursue it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vitale indicated that Engelhard was surprised by the extent of the stock  market reaction yesterday, and said that it might take a few days for investors  to completely understand the importance of the announcement.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 2, 1995, Saturday</p>
        <p>The Market Place column in Business Day on Nov. 15, about an announcement by  the Engelhard Corporation that a new automobile pollution-reduction system was less effective than originally projected, overstated the reaction of Wall Street analysts. Only one analyst withdrew a recommendation to buy shares of the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 2, 1995, Saturday&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;    The Market Place column in Business Day on Nov. 15, about an announcement by  the Engelhard Corporation that a new automobile pollution-reduction system was less effective than originally projected, overstated the reaction of Wall Street analysts. Only one analyst withdrew a recommendation to buy shares of the company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
