<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Hi-Tech Voyeurism For a Summer Evening</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="780262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LINCOLN CENTER FOR THE PERFORMING ARTS (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">C'EST LA VIE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DE113CF936A3575BC0A963958260" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Hi-Tech Voyeurism For a Summer Evening</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spying on strangers when they are not being observed is a temptation that is particularly ripe in a city like New York where the windows of neighboring buildings present whole fields of voyeuristic opportunity. That's one reason why "C'est la Vie," an event produced for Lincoln Center Out of Doors and billed as "an audience-as-voyeur theater piece," promised to explore and perhaps to explode conventional notions of privacy, voyeurism and urban life.</p>
        <p>That promise is unfortunately subordinated to loftier goals that are not met. In the event, which plays through Tuesday at the Fountain Plaza at Lincoln Center, the audience, equipped with binoculars and radio headphones, observes 11 different interwoven dramas, broken into 51 segments played out in the windows of the nearby Radisson Empire Hotel. A soundtrack broadcast through the headphones tuned to an FM frequency plays the dialogue spoken by characters whose actions are pantomimed by actors behind the theatrically lighted windows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spying on strangers when they are not being observed is a temptation that is particularly ripe in a city like New York where the windows of neighboring buildings present whole fields of voyeuristic opportunity. That's one reason why "C'est la Vie," an event produced for Lincoln Center Out of Doors and billed as "an audience-as-voyeur theater piece," promised to explore and perhaps to explode conventional notions of privacy, voyeurism and urban life.</p>
        <p>That promise is unfortunately subordinated to loftier goals that are not met. In the event, which plays through Tuesday at the Fountain Plaza at Lincoln Center, the audience, equipped with binoculars and radio headphones, observes 11 different interwoven dramas, broken into 51 segments played out in the windows of the nearby Radisson Empire Hotel. A soundtrack broadcast through the headphones tuned to an FM frequency plays the dialogue spoken by characters whose actions are pantomimed by actors behind the theatrically lighted windows.</p>
        <p>What the French director Veronique Guillaud has created with 4 writers, 25 body-movement actors and 32 voices is a strident, tiresome potpourri of cliched characters and heavy-handed metaphysics that gets more pretentious as it goes along. The show is also not easy to watch. At Thursday's performance, the strain of holding up the binoculars and wearing an uncomfortable headset took its toll. By the end of the 105-minute performance, the audience was about one-third depleted.</p>
        <p>Among the characters on view are a newlywed couple, an Eastern European immigrant and a local visitor, a New York Jewish family, two quarreling spinsters, a wacky disk jockey advertising a miracle powder and an artist whose wife is giving him a fancy party on the hotel's top floor. They are all watched over by an angel hovering in an upper window. Weaving through these more or less conventional dramas is a dialogue between a nurse and a terminally ill patient whom she is guiding into the next world. It is the nurse who voices the gloomy theme of the work, "Whatever we say to each other, it can only be about leaving."</p>
        <p>Several times, a spotlight is flashed on a replica of the Statue of Liberty atop a nearby building, and the statue laments that she has had to spend the last 109 years watching the Big Apple rot. "Stop looking and start living!" she scolds. Periodically the program is interrupted to bring news of a hole in the ozone layer over Paramus, N.J., and its movement toward New York, where residents are advised to stay indoors.</p>
        <p>The play has its moments of humor, but not enough. One recurrent character is a Chinese takeout deliverer who scuttles from room to room with an order that no one seems to have placed.</p>
        <p>"C'est la Vie" might have been fun had it provided an illusion of voyeuristic transgression. But with its nearly profanity-free dialogue and its insistence that the newlyweds wear body stockings as they thrash about on a bed, it is a cheat in that department. And the acting, even by the standards of old-time radio drama, is strained and brittle.</p>
        <p>Underneath its huffing and puffing, "C'est la Vie" has the germ of a terrific idea. The excitement of being able to tune into people's lives, followed by the horror of absorbing their collective pain, was distilled most memorably in John Cheever's famous story "The Enormous Radio." "C'est la Vie" suggests "The Enormous Radio" stripped of any mystery. And what is voyeurism without the sense of uncovering something secret? C'est la Vie An Outdoor Image Theater Performance. Conceived, produced and directed by Veronique Guillaud; managing producer, Jerry Van Campen; original music by Erik Walker; dialogues by Lucy Grealy, Gil Kofman, Ann Nocenti, Peter Steinfeld and Rob Singer; costumes by Agnes b; lighting by Dominique Gentil. A Mundial Sisters Production presented by Lincoln Center Out of Doors and Dancing in the Streets. Sponsored by Johnnie Walker Black Label. At Lincoln Center Fountain Plaza.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
