<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="789876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF143BF932A1575AC0A963958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-15 NATO WON'T RESUME BOMBING United Nations and NATO commanders announced that Bosnian Serb forces have removed their heavy weapons from positions around Sarajevo and that NATO planes will not resume bombing attacks against them.A1 For Croatian Serbs, a flashback to World War II.A14 EGYPT UNCOVERS MASS GRAVES Egypt said that it had discovered two mass graves in the Sinai containing the remains of Egyptian prisoners of war and unarmed civilians shot by Israeli soldiers during the 1967 war.A1 CONTINUED TENSIONS IN CHECHNYA An almost palpable hatred toward Moscow seems to pose the biggest threat to the fragile stability of Chechnya, where tensions were punctuated by an attack on the Russian President's envoy.A6 NATO OUTLINES RULES TO JOIN NATO ambassadors in Brussels approved a blueprint of membership requirements for formerly Communist European countries that want to join, overriding Russia's objections to expanding the alliance.A6 SAGGING FORTUNES IN INDIA The fortunes of India's Prime Minister, P. V. Narasimha Rao, have turned from bad to worse as newspapers now report his use of a controversial faith-healer.A3 MEXICO OPENS CORRUPTION FIGHT After months of concern that Mexico's national law enforcement agency has been infiltrated by drug traffickers, the Attorney General announced a campaign to root out corruption.A11 Lambach Journal: Art and intrigue at a Benedictine monastery.A4 National A16-20, B9-11 AT&amp;T SPLITTING UP, AGAIN The AT&amp;T Corporation announced that it would divide its business into three companies: communications services, communications equipment and computers. The breakup comes more than a decade after it broke up the Bell System to settle a Federal suit and is a tacit acknowledgment that its vast information technology empire had become too unwieldy.A1 AT&amp;T'S ILLUSORY VISION AT&amp;T's abandoning of its once-grand vision of combining communications and computers into a single corporate empire -- a union that proved to be a costly illusion -- could well be a lesson for other companies pursuing synergy.A1 STATES' OWN WELFARE PLANS In light of the bipartisan vote in the Senate, it is clear that the country's main Federal welfare program, Aid to Families with Dependent Children, is headed toward extinction. But a canvass of states indicates "welfare reform" has been taking place all across the country. A1 STUNNED IN NEW YORK The directors of New York City's 37 settlement houses, which provide charitable services to more than half a million low-income people every year, were stunned by the Senate's action. B11 MUCH IN NEW TAX BILL The $52 billion tax bill that the House Ways and Means Committee approved on Tuesday was advertised as an attempt to shut down unwarranted corporate tax breaks, but the bill include a lot more. A1 JOCKEYING ON MEDICAID Congress scrutinized Republican proposals to limit the growth of Medicaid, and Democrats complained that Republicans were trying to ram the changes through Congress. B9 MISSTEPS ON SWEATSHOPS With the raids on sweatshops in Los Angeles, state and Federal investigators have issued assurances that they are flushing out such operations. But an examination of past investigations shows a series of missteps dating to 1988.A16 POLICE CALLED SENSITIVE Prosecutors in the O. J. Simpson case argued that after the killing of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald L. Goldman, the police were sensitive toward Mr. Simpson and determined to ease his grief. A16 PLAN TO POSTPONE OZONE CURBS Conservative Republicans in Congress are moving to postpone the phasing out of chemicals that scientists say are destroying the earth's protective ozone layer in the stratosphere. A20 Metro Digest B1 CHANCELLOR SEARCH NARROWS The Board of Education narrowed its search for a new Chancellor for New York City's public schools to three candidates, including a college president from Brooklyn who has emerged as Mayor Giuliani's latest candidate.A1 Business Digest D1 Arts/Entertainment C13-22 Off Broadway theater rising on Broadway. C13 Music: By Paul Bowles. C13 Poplife C16 Dance: Compagnie Maguy Marin, at the Joyce Theater. C13 Susan Rethorst C18 Books: Essays by Milan Kundera. C19 Television: Julie Harris in "Lucifer's Child." C20 "Listening to Children." C20 The Home Section C1-11 Parent &amp; Child: Practicing safety on the Internet. C1 Obituaries B12 Sports B13-19 Baseball: Yankees are awaiting a proposal from New Jersey. B13 Yanks win to tighten race. B13 Angels in a free fall. B15 Mets win: 7 out of 8. B16 Pro Basketball: Mason is set to re-sign with the Knicks. B13 Columns: Anderson on golf B13 Pro Football: Taylor gives the slumping Giants a pep talk. B13 Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23 Editorials New York's bilingual 'prison.' Mr. Aristide's first year. Attack on low-income housing. Richard E. Mooney: Immigrants. Letters William Safire: Testiness up top. Maureen Dowd: The rise of the fallen. Lynne A. Munson: Art by committee. E. Clay Shaw Jr.: A credit that's fair.  Chronicle B24 Bridge C18 Crossword C16</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-15 NATO WON'T RESUME BOMBING United Nations and NATO commanders announced that Bosnian Serb forces have removed their heavy weapons from positions around Sarajevo and that NATO planes will not resume bombing attacks against them.A1 For Croatian Serbs, a flashback to World War II.A14 EGYPT UNCOVERS MASS GRAVES Egypt said that it had discovered two mass graves in the Sinai containing the remains of Egyptian prisoners of war and unarmed civilians shot by Israeli soldiers during the 1967 war.A1 CONTINUED TENSIONS IN CHECHNYA An almost palpable hatred toward Moscow seems to pose the biggest threat to the fragile stability of Chechnya, where tensions were punctuated by an attack on the Russian President's envoy.A6 NATO OUTLINES RULES TO JOIN NATO ambassadors in Brussels approved a blueprint of membership requirements for formerly Communist European countries that want to join, overriding Russia's objections to expanding the alliance.A6 SAGGING FORTUNES IN INDIA The fortunes of India's Prime Minister, P. V. Narasimha Rao, have turned from bad to worse as newspapers now report his use of a controversial faith-healer.A3 MEXICO OPENS CORRUPTION FIGHT After months of concern that Mexico's national law enforcement agency has been infiltrated by drug traffickers, the Attorney General announced a campaign to root out corruption.A11 Lambach Journal: Art and intrigue at a Benedictine monastery.A4 National A16-20, B9-11 AT&amp;T SPLITTING UP, AGAIN The AT&amp;T Corporation announced that it would divide its business into three companies: communications services, communications equipment and computers. The breakup comes more than a decade after it broke up the Bell System to settle a Federal suit and is a tacit acknowledgment that its vast information technology empire had become too unwieldy.A1 AT&amp;T'S ILLUSORY VISION AT&amp;T's abandoning of its once-grand vision of combining communications and computers into a single corporate empire -- a union that proved to be a costly illusion -- could well be a lesson for other companies pursuing synergy.A1 STATES' OWN WELFARE PLANS In light of the bipartisan vote in the Senate, it is clear that the country's main Federal welfare program, Aid to Families with Dependent Children, is headed toward extinction. But a canvass of states indicates "welfare reform" has been taking place all across the country. A1 STUNNED IN NEW YORK The directors of New York City's 37 settlement houses, which provide charitable services to more than half a million low-income people every year, were stunned by the Senate's action. B11 MUCH IN NEW TAX BILL The $52 billion tax bill that the House Ways and Means Committee approved on Tuesday was advertised as an attempt to shut down unwarranted corporate tax breaks, but the bill include a lot more. A1 JOCKEYING ON MEDICAID Congress scrutinized Republican proposals to limit the growth of Medicaid, and Democrats complained that Republicans were trying to ram the changes through Congress. B9 MISSTEPS ON SWEATSHOPS With the raids on sweatshops in Los Angeles, state and Federal investigators have issued assurances that they are flushing out such operations. But an examination of past investigations shows a series of missteps dating to 1988.A16 POLICE CALLED SENSITIVE Prosecutors in the O. J. Simpson case argued that after the killing of Nicole Brown Simpson and Ronald L. Goldman, the police were sensitive toward Mr. Simpson and determined to ease his grief. A16 PLAN TO POSTPONE OZONE CURBS Conservative Republicans in Congress are moving to postpone the phasing out of chemicals that scientists say are destroying the earth's protective ozone layer in the stratosphere. A20 Metro Digest B1 CHANCELLOR SEARCH NARROWS The Board of Education narrowed its search for a new Chancellor for New York City's public schools to three candidates, including a college president from Brooklyn who has emerged as Mayor Giuliani's latest candidate.A1 Business Digest D1 Arts/Entertainment C13-22 Off Broadway theater rising on Broadway. C13 Music: By Paul Bowles. C13 Poplife C16 Dance: Compagnie Maguy Marin, at the Joyce Theater. C13 Susan Rethorst C18 Books: Essays by Milan Kundera. C19 Television: Julie Harris in "Lucifer's Child." C20 "Listening to Children." C20 The Home Section C1-11 Parent &amp; Child: Practicing safety on the Internet. C1 Obituaries B12 Sports B13-19 Baseball: Yankees are awaiting a proposal from New Jersey. B13 Yanks win to tighten race. B13 Angels in a free fall. B15 Mets win: 7 out of 8. B16 Pro Basketball: Mason is set to re-sign with the Knicks. B13 Columns: Anderson on golf B13 Pro Football: Taylor gives the slumping Giants a pep talk. B13 Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23 Editorials New York's bilingual 'prison.' Mr. Aristide's first year. Attack on low-income housing. Richard E. Mooney: Immigrants. Letters William Safire: Testiness up top. Maureen Dowd: The rise of the fallen. Lynne A. Munson: Art by committee. E. Clay Shaw Jr.: A credit that's fair.  Chronicle B24 Bridge C18 Crossword C16</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
