<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trucks' Popularity Undermining Gains In U.S. Fuel Savings</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="786764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OIL (PETROLEUM) AND GASOLINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UTILITY VEHICLES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRYSLER CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORD MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D7103BF936A3575AC0A963958260" item-length="1962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trucks' Popularity Undermining Gains In U.S. Fuel Savings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans who might sneer at driving a gas-guzzling Cadillac are tickled to be seen in a Jeep, Range Rover or Chevy Suburban. But the enormous popularity of these light trucks is reversing the nation's impressive gains in fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>Because the Government sets a much looser standard for trucks -- including sport utility vehicles, mini-vans and pickups -- they use far more fuel than cars. Light trucks get only 20 miles to a gallon of gasoline, on average, while cars get 28, according to the Department of Transportation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans who might sneer at driving a gas-guzzling Cadillac are tickled to be seen in a Jeep, Range Rover or Chevy Suburban. But the enormous popularity of these light trucks is reversing the nation's impressive gains in fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>Because the Government sets a much looser standard for trucks -- including sport utility vehicles, mini-vans and pickups -- they use far more fuel than cars. Light trucks get only 20 miles to a gallon of gasoline, on average, while cars get 28, according to the Department of Transportation.</p>
        <p>And with trucks now accounting for 4 of 10 new passenger vehicles sold, the boom is dirtying the air and making the United States more dependent on oil.</p>
        <p>As a result, the Clinton Administration is weighing the first significant increase in years in the mileage standard for trucks. Any new standard would take effect by April, for trucks that reach the showrooms in late 1997.</p>
        <p>Yet an increase is by no means guaranteed. The Big Three auto companies -- General Motors, Ford and Chrysler -- are scrambling to thwart it, and they have found a powerful ally in the House of Representatives, which recently voted to block the Government from taking such action.</p>
        <p>The auto makers argue that Americans like their trucks sturdy and powerful, and that it would be too expensive to make engines for such vehicles burn less fuel. Further, the Big Three auto makers say, any stiffening in the regulations would hand a chunk of the light-truck market, which they dominate, to Japanese companies, which make more efficient truck engines.</p>
        <p>"It scares us," said Michael J. Stanton, a lobbyist for the American Automobile Manufacturers Association.  But energy-conservation groups and other critics say the auto companies have not even tried to improve the fuel efficiency of trucks. And, they point out, most Americans who drive light trucks do not use them for the kinds of activities that require Herculean shock absorbers and towing strength, even if they like to pretend they do. After all, the United States has not suddenly realized Jefferson's dream and become a nation of farmers; nor has it become a nation of off-road adventurers.</p>
        <p>Instead, the auto companies' own research shows, it has become a nation of overprepared commuters, as millions of Americans use the rugged vehicles only to drive to work and haul youngsters and groceries. Trucks Are to Blame As Fuel Rating Slips</p>
        <p>The impact of the growing popularity of light trucks has been striking. With cars and light trucks counted together, average fuel economy increased steadily among new vehicles from the 1979 model year until 1987, when it was 26.2 miles a gallon. Since then, as truck sales have surged, overall fuel economy has declined, to 24.8 miles a gallon in the 1995 model year, according to a Government estimate.</p>
        <p>"Because of trucks, we've lost fuel efficiency in the fleet," said Robert E. Larson, associate director at the Environmental Protection Agency's National Vehicle and Fuel Emissions Laboratory in Ann Arbor, Mich. "At the same time, everybody thinks we're getting better."</p>
        <p>Because of improvements like front-wheel drive and lighter-weight materials, passenger cars are much more fuel efficient than they were in 1975 (although there are more cars traveling more miles). By contrast, light trucks in total are burning twice as much fuel as they were 20 years ago. And the United States is more dependent on foreign oil than it was then.</p>
        <p>"It's utterly outrageous," said Daniel F. Becker, director of the global warming and energy program at the Sierra Club. Because of the lower standard for trucks, he said, "we have more pollution, more oil consumption and a higher trade deficit in oil."</p>
        <p>Light trucks have sold so well because buyers, tempted by the auto makers and little concerned about the cost of gasoline, are substituting them for passenger cars. "The Montero. A Luxury Car Not Designed for the Idle Rich," reads an advertisement for a Mitsubishi sport utility vehicle. An ad for the Chrysler Town &amp; Country mini-van crows, "It Has Leather in Places Luxury Cars Don't Even Have Places."</p>
        <p>As trucks have crossed over, fancy rugs have replaced rubber floor mats; coffee-mug holders, compact disk players and outlets for telephones and computers have proliferated in once-spartan cockpits; neon yellows, pinks and greens have washed over traditional duller tones; once-jouncy rides have mellowed.</p>
        <p>In a sure sign that Alan Alda has replaced Tom Joad in the driver's seat, Ford announced last month that the new model of its Ranger pickup will have not only a passenger-side air bag but also a switch to turn it off when the passenger is a child in a rear-facing child seat.</p>
        <p>Niceties like cruise control, adjustable lumbar support, a tilt steering wheel and an in-dash three-disk CD player helped persuade Scott Domingue of Patterson, La., to trade in his Honda Accord for a Toyota 4Runner sport utility vehicle.</p>
        <p>Those amenities, he said, more than made up for what he called the vehicle's only deficiency. "The mileage is horrible," he said -- averaging about 18 miles to the gallon. "I drive 100 miles a day and burn about two and a half tanks a week." Double Standards On Mileage Ratings</p>
        <p>The domestication of light trucks has prompted more than a few people to wonder why the Government maintains separate fuel economy standards for them. "A Ford Taurus station wagon and a Ford Windstar mini-van with different fuel economy norms?" the trade weekly Automotive News editorialized last week. "Ridiculous!"</p>
        <p>Mileage requirements are not the Government's only double standard on fuel economy. The so-called gas-guzzler tax, which is applied to cars with combined mileage ratings below 22.5 miles a gallon, does not affect light trucks at all.</p>
        <p>Yet in another crucial area, safety, the Government now treats light trucks the same as cars.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the fuel efficiency debate is the so-called "corporate average fuel economy" program, known as CAFE, which has its 20th anniversary this year. Congress created the program in response to the Arab oil embargo in the early 1970's, in hopes of reducing the country's dependence on foreign oil.</p>
        <p>Under the program, the fuel economy of passenger vehicles produced by an auto company must meet, on average, certain standards. Congress set the standard for cars at 18 miles a gallon in 1978, mandating that it rise to 27.5 miles a gallon by 1985. While the car standard has not risen, the actual average fuel economy of cars has continued to improve, to 28.2 miles a gallon today.</p>
        <p>In 1975, light trucks were a small fraction of the market -- burly, basic workhorses for farmers and contractors. Congress did not bother to set a mileage requirement for them, instead directing the Transportation Secretary to set the level each year.</p>
        <p>The standard climbed from 14 miles a gallon in 1980 to 20.5 later in the 1980's, but it has all but stalled since. It is set to reach 20.7 miles a gallon over the next two years.</p>
        <p>According to E.P.A. statistics, 20.7 miles a gallon was already the actual average fuel economy of light trucks in 1983. Today it is 20.4 miles a gallon. These numbers, based on laboratory tests, are likely to be higher than real-world results.</p>
        <p>Even the longest production car in the United States, the barge-like Cadillac Fleetwood, has an E.P.A. rating of 17 miles a gallon in the city and 25 on the highway. And it has an eight-cylinder engine and rear-wheel drive.</p>
        <p>By contrast, General Motors' biggest light truck, the four-wheel-drive Chevrolet Suburban, gets only 13 miles a gallon in the city and 15 on the highway, according to Chevy's estimate. Even the much smaller Chevrolet Blazer sport utility vehicle performs worse than the Cadillac, getting 16 miles a gallon in the city and 21 on the highway -- despite having a six-cylinder engine. Tougher U.S. Rules May Benefit Japanese</p>
        <p>The auto companies say that making trucks more fuel efficient would weaken their appeal. Sure, an owner may use his truck mostly for commuting, said Dick Kinsey, manager of fuel economy planning and compliance at the Ford Motor Company. But, he added, "there is that weekend that he wants to go to the lumberyard and fill it full of plywood."</p>
        <p>With gasoline costing less than Coca-Cola, Mr. Kinsey said, customers do not worry about fuel. "Our customers are demanding more performance," he said.</p>
        <p>The Big Three say that strengthening the truck mileage standard would benefit the Japanese auto makers, just as they contend that strengthening the car standard did in the late 1970's. Then, the Japanese sold a higher proportion of fuel-efficient small cars, just as they now sell a higher proportion of fuel-efficient compact trucks.</p>
        <p>As a result, as the Big Three scrambled to make more small cars in the 1980's, the Japanese were able to introduce larger cars that burned more fuel, while still meeting the Government averages. In the same way, they could now move into the full-size pickup and sport utility market -- as they have already begun to do -- while the need to meet the average could restrain Big Three truck production.</p>
        <p>"CAFE is something we're pretty good at," said Bob Thomas, president of the Nissan Motor Corporation U.S.A. "Our four-cylinder and six-cylinder engines are very efficient, so we would have no problem."</p>
        <p>Publicly, the Big Three have long favored a steep gasoline tax in place of the fuel economy standards, although their critics have never believed they are sincere.</p>
        <p>Critics say the auto companies could raise fuel efficiency at reasonable cost. Many truck engines have "1960's to 70's-vintage technology," said John M. DeCicco, a senior associate at the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy. By using turbochargers, multiple valves per cylinder and other available technology, he said, "you can meet the power needs with a smaller engine, and that improves efficiency." House Acts to Bar Increase in Standard</p>
        <p>More than a year ago, the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, which runs the fuel economy program, suggested that it would raise the fuel economy standard for trucks, setting rules several years into the future to give the auto companies time to meet them. If they are imposed by next April, such rules would affect light trucks beginning with the 1998 model year.</p>
        <p>The auto companies filed comments opposed to increases, and for months they have been nervously awaiting the agency's proposal.</p>
        <p>The agency refuses to discuss its plans. But in July, in testimony before Congress, Barry Felrice, the agency's associate administrator for safety performance standards, said, "In light of the rapid growth in fuel consumption by light trucks, we believed that we should see what could reasonably be done to improve light-truck fuel economy in the long run."</p>
        <p>Without endorsing the finding, Mr. Felrice noted that a 1992 National Academy of Sciences report projected a "technologically feasible" level of 26 to 28 miles a gallon by 2006.</p>
        <p>Now Congress has stepped into the act. As part of the appropriations bill for the Transportation Department, the House of Representatives effectively forbade the traffic safety agency to raise fuel economy standards next year.</p>
        <p>"Because the light-truck market now represents over 40 percent of total vehicle sales, and it is a segment which is dominated by domestic manufacturers, this action would be devastating to the nation's economy," Tom DeLay, a Texas Republican and the House majority whip, said in remarks submitted to the Congressional Record about raising the fuel economy standard.</p>
        <p>The Senate did not pass the same restriction. It is not clear whether the Clinton Administration will act before a House-Senate conference on the bill this month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
