<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Win Nobel Prize for Work on Threat to Ozone</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19951020T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796843"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NOBEL PRIZES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLOROFLUOROCARBONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MASSACHUSETTS INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAX PLANCK INSTITUTE FOR CHEMISTRY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOLINA, MARIO (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRUTZEN, PAUL (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROWLAND, F SHERWOOD (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D91739F931A25753C1A963958260" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Win Nobel Prize for Work on Threat to Ozone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Americans and a Dutch citizen who is based in Germany were awarded a Nobel Prize in Chemistry yesterday for their pioneering work in explaining the chemical processes that deplete the earth's ozone shield.</p>
        <p>The scientists' achievements presaged the 1985 discovery of the ozone "hole" over the Antarctic and led to a landmark environmental treaty banning the production of industrial chemicals that erode the ozone layer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two Americans and a Dutch citizen who is based in Germany were awarded a Nobel Prize in Chemistry yesterday for their pioneering work in explaining the chemical processes that deplete the earth's ozone shield.</p>
        <p>The scientists' achievements presaged the 1985 discovery of the ozone "hole" over the Antarctic and led to a landmark environmental treaty banning the production of industrial chemicals that erode the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>The winners are Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland of the University of California at Irvine, Dr. Mario Molina of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Dr. Paul Crutzen of the Max Planck Institute for Chemistry in Mainz, Germany. Their award appears to be the first Nobel Prize ever given, even though indirectly, for work in the environmental sciences.</p>
        <p>The accolade is a vindication for the two Americans, who were attacked by industry when in 1974 they first advanced their thesis that the continued use of chlorofluorocarbons as refrigerants, plastic foams and aerosol propellants would seriously damage the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Although most scientists now accept the thesis, it still has influential critics outside the scientific community. Republicans in Congress, for instance, have introduced legislation to overturn the United States' participation in the international ban on the production of chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's.</p>
        <p>Unless attenuated by the ozone layer, the sun's ultraviolet rays can cause skin cancer, cataracts and damage to the immune system, and harm natural ecosystems. Indeed, if there were no protection at all from the layer, plants and animals could not exist on land.</p>
        <p>So the scientists' work was a watershed in environmental thinking, since it showed for the first time that human activities could undermine global life support processes and that the fabric of nature was not infinitely resilient to insult.</p>
        <p>In its citation yesterday, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences said Dr. Rowland, Dr. Molina and Dr. Crutzen "have contributed to our salvation from a global environmental problem that could have catastrophic consequences." Largely because of the three researchers, the academy said, "it has been possible to make far-reaching decisions on prohibiting the release of gases that destroy ozone."</p>
        <p>The announcement of the chemistry prize, and of the physics prize, which went to two Americans yesterday, brought to eight the number of Nobel winners in science and medicine this year, six of them Americans. That result has furthered a recent trend in which Americans have dominated the science and medicine prizes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rowland, who is called Sherry, is 68 years old. He was born in Delaware, Ohio, and was awarded a doctoral degree in chemistry from the University of Chicago in 1952. He is a chemistry professor at Irvine and serves as foreign secretary of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>Dr. Molina, 52, was born in Mexico City and is now a United States citizen. He holds a doctorate in physical chemistry from the University of California at Berkeley, is a professor in the department of earth, atmospheric and planetary sciences at M.I.T., and is also a member of the National Academy.</p>
        <p>Dr. Crutzen, 62, is a native of Amsterdam. The son of a waiter, he was trained as a meteorologist but taught himself chemistry. He is known among his colleagues as a nonconformist who shows up in an open shirt and sandals at conferences where everyone else is in formal attire. Instead of delivering formal papers at scientific meetings, he fumbles a few handwritten notes, then ends up mesmerizing his audiences. He is currently a professor at the Max Planck Institute in Mainz.</p>
        <p>The work leading to discovery of the threat to the ozone layer can be traced to Dr. Crutzen's finding in 1970 that the layer, created naturally by the action of sunlight on oxygen, also has a natural means of being destroyed, by nitrogen oxides that react chemically with ozone. Although the finding was not fully accepted for a decade, it helped pave the way for the work of Dr. Rowland and Dr. Molina, which soon followed.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Molina joined Dr. Rowland's laboratory at Irvine as a postdoctoral fellow, the two were academic chemists. "We both decided that we wanted to do more applied chemistry and learn about the atmosphere," Dr. Molina recalled yesterday, "and one way to do that was to try to solve a problem that forces you to learn the field."</p>
        <p>The "nice problem" that presented itself, he said, was the one suggested by the intriguing fact that recently measured global CFC concentrations were about the same amount as had been emitted by industry.</p>
        <p>Very quickly, Dr. Molina said, the two discovered that CFC molecules could gradually waft to the ozone layer and, because of their remarkable chemical stability, persist in the stratosphere for about a century.  There the sun's ultraviolet rays would split chlorine out of the chemicals, the two scientists concluded.</p>
        <p>Next, said Dr. Rowland, they found that the liberated chlorine set off a self-sustaining chain reaction in which one chlorine atom "takes out about 100,000 ozones." After comparing the amount of CFC's in the atmosphere with the amount of nitrogen oxides, the two scientists concluded that the industrial chemicals were having a global effect on the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Their prediction that continued emissions of CFC's would greatly weaken the ozone layer, published in 1974 in the British journal Nature, created an enormous stir. Inside the scientific community, said Dr. Rowland, "right from the beginning people were saying, 'It sounds bizarre, but all the steps are plausible.' "</p>
        <p>The two Americans attracted much fire from industry, not least because they insisted on spreading the new gospel quite vocally. Also, Dr. Molina said, there was not yet enough evidence to put their hypothesis beyond doubt. The CFC industry, which in 1974 had sales of $2 billion, "rightfully demanded that you had to have more than calculations," Dr. Rowland said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some industry scientists called the hypothesis nonsense. According to The Los Angeles Times, the president of one aerosol manufacturing company suggested that criticism of CFC's was "orchestrated by the ministry of disinformation of the K.G.B."</p>
        <p>But gradually, Dr. Molina said, the evidence accumulated, in the end convincing industry "that the scientific evidence was good enough to work with us and the scientific community and the policy makers to formulate regulations." That, he said, was "very rewarding."</p>
        <p>The whole problem gained new urgency with the discovery in 1985 of a drastic depletion of the ozone layer -- it was called a hole even though the depletion was far from total -- over Antarctica. The "hole" could not be fully explained by any mechanism then known. It was Dr. Crutzen and his colleagues who identified the mechanism as chemical reactions on the surfaces of cloud particles.</p>
        <p>The urgency of this finding speeded the negotiation of a 1987 international agreement, the Montreal Protocol, to protect the ozone layer. Under 1992 amendments to the protocol, brought about by findings that ozone depletion was affecting temperate regions, industrialized countries agreed to phase out the production of CFC's by the end of this year.  The treaty was widely held up as a stellar example of international cooperation, including that of industry, on a global environmental problem.</p>
        <p>Many experts say the production phase-out has already led to a lessening of CFC emissions, and it is generally expected that concentrations of the chemical will stop building up around the turn of the century, after which a slow recovery lasting perhaps a century will begin.</p>
        <p>Conservative Republicans in the House of Representatives, citing the dissent of a tiny number of scientific critics, have introduced legislation to roll back American participation in the CFC ban, even though industry has long since acceded to it -- and in fact has moved more rapidly to ban the chemicals than legally required.  The legislation is not expected to progress very far very soon, and would most likely be vetoed by the President if it passed.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 20, 1995, Friday</p>
        <p>An article and a picture grouping on Oct. 12 about the awarding of the Nobel Prize in Chemistry to three scientists, including Dr. Paul Crutzen, misstated his age. He is 61, not 62.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 20, 1995, Friday</p>
        <p>An article and a picture grouping on Oct. 12 about the awarding of the Nobel Prize in Chemistry to three scientists, including Dr. Paul Crutzen, misstated his age. He is 61, not 62.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
