<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evolving in the Dark, Over 5.5 Million Years</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="815530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOLOGY AND BIOCHEMISTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EVOLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAVES AND CAVERNS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROMANIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOVILE CAVE (ROMANIA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF CINCINNATI</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KANE, THOMAS (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Romania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Caves and Caverns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EFD91639F931A25751C1A963958260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evolving in the Dark, Over 5.5 Million Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROWNE, MALCOLM W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the light of day is turned off for five and a half million years, creatures trapped in perpetual darkness must learn to navigate without seeing, to live in an atmosphere that could kill outsiders and to make do without the solar energy that sustains the food chain elsewhere. But survive these troglobionts do, and a pitch-dark cave in Romania has become a laboratory for biologists studying life at the precarious edge of existence.</p>
        <p>During the last three years a team of American and Romanian scientists from the University of Cincinnati in Ohio has been mining biological treasure from the Stygian darkness of Movile Cave near Mangalia, Romania, which is on the shore of the Black Sea about 10 miles north of the Bulgarian border. Dr. Thomas  Kane, a professor of biology at the University of Cincinnati, said 48 species have been identified in the cave, of which 33 were previously unknown. Movile Cave has been so scientifically productive that the National Science Foundation  recently renewed its grant to the Cincinnati team studying the cave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the light of day is turned off for five and a half million years, creatures trapped in perpetual darkness must learn to navigate without seeing, to live in an atmosphere that could kill outsiders and to make do without the solar energy that sustains the food chain elsewhere. But survive these troglobionts do, and a pitch-dark cave in Romania has become a laboratory for biologists studying life at the precarious edge of existence.</p>
        <p>During the last three years a team of American and Romanian scientists from the University of Cincinnati in Ohio has been mining biological treasure from the Stygian darkness of Movile Cave near Mangalia, Romania, which is on the shore of the Black Sea about 10 miles north of the Bulgarian border. Dr. Thomas  Kane, a professor of biology at the University of Cincinnati, said 48 species have been identified in the cave, of which 33 were previously unknown. Movile Cave has been so scientifically productive that the National Science Foundation  recently renewed its grant to the Cincinnati team studying the cave.</p>
        <p>Dr. Brian Kinkle, the microbiologist in the group, said that although other  caves have some of the characteristics of Movile, none exhibit such a diversity  of interdependent species.</p>
        <p>There are no vertebrates among the animals in the cave, and the environment in which they live is similar in some respects to the deep-ocean thermal vents studied by marine biologists. Among the previously unknown species of cave dwellers discovered by the Cincinnati group were three species of spiders, a centipede, four species of terrestrial isopods (called "pill bugs"), a leech never seen anywhere else in the world and a very unusual insect called a water scorpion.</p>
        <p>"It's related to bedbugs," Dr. Kane said. "There are several surface-dwelling species of the insect in Europe and the United States, but this aquatic version  is the first seen anywhere."</p>
        <p>Another species the scientists were surprised to find was a spider.</p>
        <p>"If you wanted to find a surface relative of this spider that belonged to the same group, the closest one is in the Canary Islands," Dr. Kane said, "and that's tropical. What we think is, that back at the end of the Miocene Epoch, about 5.5 million years ago, a big climatic change had a tremendous impact on life. We know there was a big change, because the Mediterranean Sea dried up around that time. We think that the surface-dwelling ancestors of at least some  of the species we find in the cave lived in a tropical environment. When the global climate changed, the only ones that survived were those that had adapted  to some degree to living in warm caves underground."</p>
        <p>Evolutionary change in the cave after it was sealed off from the surface world was probably rapid, Dr. Kane believes, occurring within a few tens or hundreds of thousands of years.</p>
        <p>In both Movile Cave (which is about 160 feet deep and 800 feet long) and in water near oceanic thermal vents, the absence of light precludes photosynthesis, the chemical process by which green plants draw energy from sunlight to build carbohydrates from water and carbon dioxide. Microorganisms at the bottom of the food chain in caves and the deep ocean are therefore obliged to use a different  strategy, in which energy is extracted by oxidizing hydrogen sulfide dissolved in the water. By using chemical energy from hydrogen sulfide in place of the radiant energy of sunlight, a peculiar class of bacteria called chemoautotrophs  not only survive but furnish food for higher organisms.</p>
        <p>All the animals in the cave have lost their ability to see, and their bodies  have lost all pigmentation. Some have very large antennas, and they probably navigate using tactile, chemical and electrical sensors.</p>
        <p>"The great advantage of this cave over deep-ocean vents," Dr. Kane said, "is  that it is easily accessible. We can experiment in ways that would be prohibitively expensive in the deep sea."</p>
        <p>The scientists believe Movile Cave is merely a small part of an aquifer extending over nearly 80 square miles.</p>
        <p>"People have known since the days of the Greeks and Romans that the spring water here was unusual, loaded with sulfur, and in demand at health spas," Dr. Kane said. One object of the group's research was to prove that the deep underground springs were truly isolated from the world above.</p>
        <p>"We have achieved that by comparing chemical analyses of the water above and  below, and by comparing ratios of different isotopes of carbon and nitrogen," Dr. Kane said. "These ratios are very different in the deep spring water from those of surface water."</p>
        <p>The organisms living in Movile Cave may help explain how some of the world's  greatest caves, including Carlsbad Caverns in New Mexico, were hollowed out of the rock. Dr. Kane believes that chemoautotrophic bacteria like those in Movile  Cave may have played key roles. By oxidizing hydrogen sulfide from the water, the bacteria produce not only free sulfur but also sulfuric acid, which attacks  the calcium carbonate of which limestone consists. The mixture of water and sulfuric acid produced by bacteria probably eats away the rock over the centuries, eventually hollowing out great underground chambers.</p>
        <p>If this is the case, he said, one could expect to find calcium sulfate, or gypsum, in the caves, and in fact the walls of Movile Cave are coated with gypsum.</p>
        <p>Movile Cave was discovered accidentally in 1986 during an excavation nearby,  but while the Romanian dictator Nicolae Ceausescu lived, scientists were barred  from the site. After Ceausescu was overthrown in 1989, however, Serban M. Sarbu, a political refugee studying at the University of Cincinnati, returned to Romania to begin the cave research that has continued ever since.</p>
        <p>"It's really nice to stumble on an ecosystem that's really different," Dr. Kane said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
