<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="761004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DF153EF934A35756C0A963958260" item-length="4204" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSIC ARBOR CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY Four original songs by David Sampson along with Beethoven's Sonata in A major for cello and piano and Arensky's Piano Trio in D minor. Today at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $16, or $12 for the elderly and $5 for students. Center for Visual Arts, 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 232-1116. BENJAMIN FRANKLIN AUDITORIUM The Tokyo String Quartet will perform as part of the Art Center Chamber Music Concerts, with works by Mozart, Beethoven and Debussy. Tuesday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $20. Benjamin Franklin School. Windsor Road, Teaneck. (201) 224-0285. BLOOMFIELD SPRING CONCERT The Bloomfield Mandolin Orchestra, with Gabriel Nevola, conductor, in a program of Mozart, Tchaikovsky, Strauss and Schubert. Today at 3 P.M. Bloomfield Middle School, 60 Huck Road, Bloomfield. (201) 748-0081. CENTRAL JERSEY SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA Gala Anniversary Concert, to coincide with the commemoration of the 50th anniversary of the end of World War II. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $7 for the elderly. Edward Nash Theater at Raritan Valley Community College, Route 28 and Lamington Road in Somerset County. (908) 725-3420. CHATHAM HIGH SCHOOL The Colonial Symphony performs Haydn's Sinfonia Concertante in B flat major, Brahms's Symphony No. 4 in E minor (Op. 98) and the New Jersey premiere of David Leisner's "Embrace of Peace." Friday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $29, $18, $10 and, for students, $5. 255 Lafayette Avenue, Chatham. (908) 766-7555. COLUMBIA HIGH SCHOOL Arts Maplewood and Sing Out present Pete Seeger and Friends in a benefit for the Sing Out Resource Center. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $30. 17 Parker road, Maplewood. (201) 378-2133. CONGREGATION SONS OF ISRAEL Leonia Sinfonia, a chamber orchestra with harpsichord, strings and soloists, offers the works of Bach, Tchaikovsky and Telemann. Today at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $8. $6 for students and the elderly. 150 Grand Avenue, Leonia. (201) 944-3477. CORPUS CHRISTI PARISH "Music at Corpus Christi" Spring Concert, with John Schucker, organist, and Andre Tarantiles, harpist, performing the works of Baur, Debussy and Vierne. Today at 4 P.M. Free, but donations are welcomed. 234 Southern Boulevard, Chatham Township. (201) 635-0070. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Evelyn Krog sings operatic and classical selections, accompanied by Vincent Rogers, pianist. Today at 5:30 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH The Verdi Requiem with Bradley Williams, tenor; Edward Russell, bass; Deborah Adkins Williams, soprano, and Noel Piercy, conductor. Today at 7:30 P.M. Free, but donations are welcomed. 326 Bloomfield Avenue, Caldwell. (201) 228-0310. JEWISH COMMUNITY CENTER The Metropolitan Orchestra and the Yueyue Ensemble will perform Haydn's "Creation." Sunday at 3 P.M. Free. Maurice Levin Theater, 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. (201) 736-3200. JOHN HARMS THEATER Taylor 2, a company of six dancers with a repertory of works by Paul Taylor, will perform "Aureole, Arden Court" and "Company B." Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $15, $18, $21 and $26. The Pro Arte Chorale offers a Bach program. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $22 and $19, or $18 and $15 for students, the elderly and the handicapped. Lou Rawls. Saturday at 7 and 9 P.M. Tickets: $25 and $20. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. MERCER COUNTY SPRING CONCERT The Mercer County Community Band and the Merce County Community College Jazz Band perform on Thursday at 8 P.M. Free. Kelsey Theater on the West Windsor Campus, 1200 Old Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 586-4800. PRO ARTE CHORALE "Bernstein's Broadway," a revue of selections from Leonard Bernstein's shows including "On the Town," "West Side Story" and "Candide." Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $5. Community Church, 354 Rock Road, Glen Rock. (201) 445-9052. RARITAN RIVER CONCERTS L'Ensemble with Ida Faiella, soprano, Barry Finclair, violin and viola, and Lincoln Mayorga, piano. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $9 for students. Stanton Reformed Church, Route 629, Stanton. (908) 213-1100. SOUTH ORANGE MIDDLE SCHOOL The South Orange Symphony Orchestra performs Shostakovich's Festival Overture and Mozart's Fourth Concerto for Horn Soloist. Saturday at 8:15 P.M. Free. (201) 731-5710. SUMMIT HIGH SCHOOL The Summit Sumphony performs Rachmaninoff's "Caprice Bohemien" and Chopin's Concerto No. 1 in E minor. Elyane Laussade, piano soloist, will perform Liszt's Preludes for piano and orchestra. Saturday at 8 P.M. Free. Kent Place Boulevard, Summit. (201) 763-3640. UNION CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH The New Jersey Chamber Music Society presents Benjamin Verdery, guitarist, in "Toward the Sea" and "Fandango Quartet." Friday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $18, or $6 for students. 176 Cooper Avenue, Upper Montclair. (201) 746-6068. UNITY CONCERTS Tomohiro Okumura, violinist, will make his first appearance for Unity Concerts, performing compositions by Bach, Schubert and Milstein. Today at 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $25, $20 and $15. Montclair High School Community Auditorium, Park and Chestnut Streets, Montclair. (201) 744-6770. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Classic Blues Revue," with Natalie Lamb, draws upon famous and infamous blues singers with tunes that range from somber to risque. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. THEATER ALGONQUIN ARTS THEATER The Red Oak Music Theater presents "Seesaw," a musical directed by Jerry Yoder. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20. Old Square Plaza, Manasquan. (908) 367-1515. BURGDORFF CULTURAL CENTER The Strollers present "The Royal Family," by George S. Kaufman and Edna Ferber. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. and May 19 and 20 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $6 for the elderly. 10 Durand Road, Maplewood. (201) 761-8453. CENTENARY LITTLE THEATER Three musicals presented by the Centenary Young Performers Workshop. "Company," Friday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 2 P.M. "Anything Goes," Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. "Tom Sawyer," Saturday at 11 A.M. and next Sunday at 5 P.M. Tickets: $7, or $5 for students the the elderly. Campus of Centenary College, Hackettstown. (908) 852-1400, extension 203. CHATHAM COMMUNITY PLAYERS "Nunsense." Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M.; Saturday at 3 and 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $14, or $10 for students. The Playhouse. 23 North Passaic Avenue, Chatham. (201) 635-7363. CIRCLE PLAYERS "Lettice and Lovage," a comedy by Peter Shaffer. Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $8. 416 Victoria Avenue, Piscataway. (908) 968-7555. CIVIC THEATER OF HUDSON COUNTY "Jesus Christ Superstar," directed by Brian Waggoner. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for the elderly and students. Raphael J. Cordero School, 158 Erie Street, Jersey City. (201) 823-2085. CROSSROADS THEATER COMPANY "Two Hah Hahs and a Homeboy," with Ruby Dee, Ossie Davis and their son, Guy Davis. Today and next Sunday at 7:30 P.M.; Wednesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 3 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $20, $25. 7 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 249-5560. ELIZABETH PLAYHOUSE "Kinfolks," by Karon Semones, based on the novel by Gurney Norman. Friday and Saturday at 7:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $4. 1100 East Jersey Street, Elizabeth. (908) 355-0077. GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE John Steinbeck's "Of Mice and Men." Starts Friday; through June 4. Tuesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Tickets: $30, $26 and $22. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 246-7717. GUGGENHEIM THEATER The Two River Theater Company presents George Bernard Shaw's "Misalliance." Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M.; next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $15 on Thursday, $22 on Friday and Saturday, and $18 on Sunday. Monmouth University, Cedar Avenue, West Long Branch. (908) 291-4114. IRON MOUNTAIN STAGE COMPANY "Vital Signs," by Jane Martin, a collage of contemporary women in a series of 3o monologues. Today at 4 P.M. Tickets: $9. Community Presbyterian Church of Ringwood, 145 Carletondale Road, Ringwood. (201) 962-9007. LITTLE FIREHOUSE THEATER The Bergen County Players present "A Few Good Men." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 1 and 5 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $12, or $10 for matinees. 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200. McCARTER THEATER Brian Friel's "Wonderful Tennessee." Today at 2 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M., Saturday at 4 and 8:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $26 to $30. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The National Stage Company presents Sam Shepard's "Fool for Love" and August Strindberg's "Miss Julie." Thursday through Saturday at 8 P.M.; Sunday at 3 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $18, or $14 for students and the elderly. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 489-0322. MILL HILL PLAYHOUSE The Passage Theater Company presents "Three More Gone," by Bruce Jacoby. Wednesday through Saturday at 8 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday at 3 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $25, $20 and $15. Front and Montgomery Streets, Trenton. (609) 392-0766. MOUNT HEBRON SCHOOL THEATER The Montclair Operetta Club presents "Cabaret." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $17.50. Bellevue Avenue, Montclair. (201) 669-5588. OAKHURST UNITED METHODIST CHUCH "Sweet Singer," a one-man musical based on the life of Charles Wesley. Today at 7:30 P.M. Suggest donation: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. 103 Monmouth Road, Oakhurst. (908) 531-1150. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Lerner and Loewe's "Brigadoon." Through May 28. Tickets: $29 to $44. Wednesday through Sunday at 8 P.M.; matinees Thursday at 2 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. PINE TREE PLAYERS "The Butler Did It." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Through May 20. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly. (908) 774-8833. PLAYERS GUILD "A Grand Night for Singing." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12, $11. The Little Theater at Leonia High School, Willtree Road, Leonia. (201) 947-9606. STATE THEATER "An Evening With Neil Sedaka." Saturday at 7 P.M. Proceeds will benefit the George Street Playhouse. Tickets: $20, $30, $40, $50. Tickets from the Playhouse box office: (908) 846-0825. 19 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 247-7200 ST. FRANCIS PLAYERS Rodgers and Hammerstein's "Carousel." Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10. Bergen Avenue and Park Street, Ridgefield Park. (201) 440-1829. VILLAGE PLAYERS Neil Simon's "Sunshine Boys." Today at 3 P.M.; Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for the elderly and students. Ho-Ho-Kus School Auditorium, Lloyd Road in Ho-Ho-Kus. (201) 652-6872. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART FORMS "Paintings, Works on Paper and Sculpture" with works by Richard Stout, John Kochansky, Boris Zherdin and Paul Hirsch. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M., Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Sunday 1 to 4 P.M. Through May 31. 16 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (908) 530-4330. BERGEN MUSEUM A series of photography exhibitions created by local teen-agers. Through May 21. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Opens Thursday. Through Aug. 10. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Wilderness of Waves," featuring the oils and watercolors of John Powers. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Omaha -- An Artist's Journey: Memories of D-Day," with drawings and collages by Ugo Giannini. Through June 5. Tuesday through Thursday, 6 P.M. to 8 P.M.; Friday, 10 A.M. to noon; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The John Harms Theater's Intermission Gallery presents "Sitting Pretty," an exhibition of acrylics and mixed media by Ann Hadley Lasusas. Through Thursday. Free. Monday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-5797, extension 20. MIDDLESEX COUNTY COLLEGE The Fifth Annual Alumni Art Exhibit. Starts Monday; through May 31. Daily, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. The College Center Gallery. 155 Mill Road, Edison. (908) 906-2566. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the paper-making town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through June 11. Admission: $3. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Admission, $4; the elderly and students with ID, $3. 3 South Mountain Avenue. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found" an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimenional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY AUDUBON SOCIETY Photographs of New Jersey wildlife by John Collins will be displayed and available for sale. Proceeds will benefit New Jersey Audubon's Scherman-Hoffman Sanctuaries. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Through May. Hardscrabble Road, Bernardsville. (908) 766-5787. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through June 11. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through June 18. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. RIVERRUN GALLERY "Face -- Feelings," 40 works in oil, watercolor and mixed media by Edward Adams. Through June 5. Noon to 5 P.M. daily. Closed on Tuesdays. 287 South Main Street. Lambertville. (906) 397-3349. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY An exhibition of Ukrainian folk art, showing samples of pysanky (Ukrainian Easter eggs), ceramics, wood carvings, clothing and embroidery. Through May 28. 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday through Friday. Walsh Library Gallery, South Orange. (201) 761-9476.  SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "Masters' Vision," featuring paintings by Ruth Gikow. Through May 20. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursday until 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720. STEAMROLLER GALLERY Paintings by Sara Pasti. Opens Saturday; through June 10. Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 52 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-7279. TRENTON CITY MUSEUM The Trenton Artists Workshop Association presents the mixed-media work of Katharine Bruce. Through May 28. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. (609) 989-3632. UNTITLED (#130), LTD "Member Invitational Exhibit." Paintings, sculpture and photography. Through next Sunday. Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 P.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Shine On," color photographs of last year's solar eclipse. Starts tomorrow; through May 30. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. Free. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WYCKOFF GALLERY "Spring Rhapsody," featuring traditional and abstract works in various art media. through June 12. Tuesday through Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. SPOKEN WORD BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE Gordon Lewis, director of Stoneledge Fine Arts Conservation, will give an hourlong lecture on the history and conservation of paper art. Friday at 10:30 A.M. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE Anna Quindlen, author, will lecture on "Balancing the Political and the Private" as part of the annual Spring Women's Conference. Wednesday, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Fee: $35. 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 224-2880. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Milton Meltzer, a biographer and historian, will discuss "Child Labor -- Has It Disappeared?" and "The Writer and Social Responsibility." Wednesday at 8 P.M. Free. Julio Ibarra, a photojournalist, will present a slide-lecture on Rwanda. Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY Paul Edwards and Constance Antonopoulos Webster, landscape architects, present a slide-lecture on "Preservation of Historic Gardens: An American and a British Perspective." Today at 3 P.M. Free. Lenfell Hall, 485 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 593-8661. MORRIS COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Carriages in the Industrial Age" is the topic of a slide-lecture today at 2 P.M. Free. Haggerty Educa tion Center of the Frelinghuysen Arboretum, East Hanover Avenue, Morris Township. (201) 267-3565. PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE David Ray presents a poetry workshop and reading as part of the Distinguished Poets' Series. Satuday, 10 A.M. to noon. Free. Paterson Museum, 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 684-5444. PRINCETON MARKET FAIR John Kelly, Corey Langer and Shirley Wright, Delaware Valley poets, will read selected works. Monday at 8 P.M. Free. Route 1 South, Princeton. (908) 874-3480. WOODBRIDGE MAIN LIBRARY E. W. Count, author of "Cop Talk: True Detective Stories From the NYPD," and Alfred Marini, a New York City Police Department detective, share their experiences. Wednesday at 7 P.M. Free. 1 George Frederick Plaza, Woodbridge. (908) 634-4450. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF NORTH JERSEY Benjamin Nelson, a professor at Fairleigh Dickinson University, will lecture on "The Jew as Serio-Comic Wanderer" in the context of the American Frontier. Thursday at 7 P.M. Tickets: $5. 1 Pike Drive, Wayne. (201) 595-0100. FOR CHILDREN BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "I See a Poem," a workshop that will allow children to listen to poems and then illustrate their thoughts and ideas. Saturday at 11 A.M. Fee: $4. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Suszanne Gomez will demonstrate tae kwon do, a martial arts form, for children 5 and up. Monday at 7 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FAMILY FUN FAIR The Montclair Art Museum's grounds will double as fairgrounds on Saturday from noon to 5 P.M. with arts and crafts and jewelry making. Members of the Intertribal Indians of New Jersey will perform traditional songs and dances. Admission: $3 for children and $2 for adults. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. HILLCREST COMMUNITY CENTER The West Milford Players present "Winnie the Pooh." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 3 P.M. and May 19 and 20 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $6 for children. Macopin Road, West Milford. (201) 728-0027. JEWISH COMMUNITY CENTER "From Our Children's Hands" is the culmination of a yearlong effort by children in fine art classes, on display from today through next Sunday. Monday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 9:30 P.M.; Friday, 9 A.M. to 4 P.M., and Sunday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M. 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. (201) 736-3200. MEADOW THEATER "The Frog Prince and the Princess." Saturday at 11 A.M. and Sunday at 1 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. MORRIS MUSEUM Bill Money, actor, will present "The Jersey Devil and Other Tales." Today at 11 A.M. and 1:30 P.M. Tickets: $6.25. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (201) 538-8069. MORROW MEMORIAL METHOIDST CHURCH "Give Your Faith a Voice," a festival of choral music by children's church choirs of the area. Saturday at 5 P.M. Free. 600 Ridgewood Road, Maplewood. (908) 388-9794. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M., and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. RITZ THEATER "The Ugly Duckling" and Ritzy the Wolf lead the audience on a journey to discover tolerance, kindess and compassion for others. Wednesday at 10 A.M. and 2:30, Thursday and Friday at 10 A.M. and Saturday at 10 A.M. and 1 P.M. Tickets: $4. 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609) 858-5230. ST. ANDREW'S CHURCH The Canterbury Fair is a medieval marketplace including crafts, children's games, food, madrigal singers and demonstrations of medieval life. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Free. 419 South Street, New Providence. (908) 464-4875. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER Enchanted Creations presents "Alice in Wonderland," an audience-participatory version of Lewis Carroll's classic fairy tale. Saturday at 1 P.M. Tickets: $5. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF BERGEN COUNTY "Let the Children Remember," an awareness project that exhibits art depicting subjects related to the Holocaust. Today at 2 P.M. Free. 605 Pascack Road, Washington Township. (201) 666-6610. ETC. BERGEN COUNTY ANIMAL SHELTER Bring your pets, large and small, to the Blessing of the Animals. Today at 1:15 P.M. 100 United Lane, Teterboro. (201) 646-2710. BIRCHWOOD MANOR The Garden State Coin, Stamp and Currency Show. Today, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Free. 111 North Jefferson Road, Whippany. (201) 887-1414. BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE "Follow the Drains," a walking tour of the drainage system in Red Bank for children aged 5 to 10. Saturday from 10 A.M. to noon. Registration is required for site of tour. (908) 224-2880. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through June 17. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. GARDEN CLUB OF ENGLEWOOD A spring flower show, contest and sale. Today, noon to 3 P.M. Free. Englewood Hospital's Learning Center, 350 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 894-3000. HOME AND DESIGNER SHOWCASE The Junior League of Monmouth County sponsors this exhibition featuring established and budding designers. Sunday, noon to 6 P.M.; Monday, Tuesday, Thursday and Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. Tickets: $15. National Guard Armory, Chestnut Street, Red Bank. (908) 842-2039. NATURE WALK AND FIELD TRIP The Stony Brook-Millstone Watershed Association offers a daylong field excursion on the Watershed Preserve. Saturday, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Fee: $15. A Mother's Day Walk will stroll the preserve in search of nature -- birds building nests and other signs of motherly love. Saturday, 10 A.M. to noon. Fee: $3. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-3075. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL A double feature with "Death and the Maiden" and "Mamma Roma," today. "The Life and Times of Allen Ginsberg," Friday, and "Siddhartha," Saturday. 7 P.M. Friday and Saturday tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, George Street and Seminary Place. Sunday showings are at the State Theater, 19 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. Tickets: $7. (908) 932-8482.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSIC ARBOR CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY Four original songs by David Sampson along with Beethoven's Sonata in A major for cello and piano and Arensky's Piano Trio in D minor. Today at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $16, or $12 for the elderly and $5 for students. Center for Visual Arts, 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 232-1116. BENJAMIN FRANKLIN AUDITORIUM The Tokyo String Quartet will perform as part of the Art Center Chamber Music Concerts, with works by Mozart, Beethoven and Debussy. Tuesday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $20. Benjamin Franklin School. Windsor Road, Teaneck. (201) 224-0285. BLOOMFIELD SPRING CONCERT The Bloomfield Mandolin Orchestra, with Gabriel Nevola, conductor, in a program of Mozart, Tchaikovsky, Strauss and Schubert. Today at 3 P.M. Bloomfield Middle School, 60 Huck Road, Bloomfield. (201) 748-0081. CENTRAL JERSEY SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA Gala Anniversary Concert, to coincide with the commemoration of the 50th anniversary of the end of World War II. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $7 for the elderly. Edward Nash Theater at Raritan Valley Community College, Route 28 and Lamington Road in Somerset County. (908) 725-3420. CHATHAM HIGH SCHOOL The Colonial Symphony performs Haydn's Sinfonia Concertante in B flat major, Brahms's Symphony No. 4 in E minor (Op. 98) and the New Jersey premiere of David Leisner's "Embrace of Peace." Friday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $29, $18, $10 and, for students, $5. 255 Lafayette Avenue, Chatham. (908) 766-7555. COLUMBIA HIGH SCHOOL Arts Maplewood and Sing Out present Pete Seeger and Friends in a benefit for the Sing Out Resource Center. Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $30. 17 Parker road, Maplewood. (201) 378-2133. CONGREGATION SONS OF ISRAEL Leonia Sinfonia, a chamber orchestra with harpsichord, strings and soloists, offers the works of Bach, Tchaikovsky and Telemann. Today at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $8. $6 for students and the elderly. 150 Grand Avenue, Leonia. (201) 944-3477. CORPUS CHRISTI PARISH "Music at Corpus Christi" Spring Concert, with John Schucker, organist, and Andre Tarantiles, harpist, performing the works of Baur, Debussy and Vierne. Today at 4 P.M. Free, but donations are welcomed. 234 Southern Boulevard, Chatham Township. (201) 635-0070. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Evelyn Krog sings operatic and classical selections, accompanied by Vincent Rogers, pianist. Today at 5:30 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FIRST PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH The Verdi Requiem with Bradley Williams, tenor; Edward Russell, bass; Deborah Adkins Williams, soprano, and Noel Piercy, conductor. Today at 7:30 P.M. Free, but donations are welcomed. 326 Bloomfield Avenue, Caldwell. (201) 228-0310. JEWISH COMMUNITY CENTER The Metropolitan Orchestra and the Yueyue Ensemble will perform Haydn's "Creation." Sunday at 3 P.M. Free. Maurice Levin Theater, 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. (201) 736-3200. JOHN HARMS THEATER Taylor 2, a company of six dancers with a repertory of works by Paul Taylor, will perform "Aureole, Arden Court" and "Company B." Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $15, $18, $21 and $26. The Pro Arte Chorale offers a Bach program. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $22 and $19, or $18 and $15 for students, the elderly and the handicapped. Lou Rawls. Saturday at 7 and 9 P.M. Tickets: $25 and $20. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-3600. MERCER COUNTY SPRING CONCERT The Mercer County Community Band and the Merce County Community College Jazz Band perform on Thursday at 8 P.M. Free. Kelsey Theater on the West Windsor Campus, 1200 Old Trenton Road, Trenton. (609) 586-4800. PRO ARTE CHORALE "Bernstein's Broadway," a revue of selections from Leonard Bernstein's shows including "On the Town," "West Side Story" and "Candide." Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $5. Community Church, 354 Rock Road, Glen Rock. (201) 445-9052. RARITAN RIVER CONCERTS L'Ensemble with Ida Faiella, soprano, Barry Finclair, violin and viola, and Lincoln Mayorga, piano. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $9 for students. Stanton Reformed Church, Route 629, Stanton. (908) 213-1100. SOUTH ORANGE MIDDLE SCHOOL The South Orange Symphony Orchestra performs Shostakovich's Festival Overture and Mozart's Fourth Concerto for Horn Soloist. Saturday at 8:15 P.M. Free. (201) 731-5710. SUMMIT HIGH SCHOOL The Summit Sumphony performs Rachmaninoff's "Caprice Bohemien" and Chopin's Concerto No. 1 in E minor. Elyane Laussade, piano soloist, will perform Liszt's Preludes for piano and orchestra. Saturday at 8 P.M. Free. Kent Place Boulevard, Summit. (201) 763-3640. UNION CONGREGATIONAL CHURCH The New Jersey Chamber Music Society presents Benjamin Verdery, guitarist, in "Toward the Sea" and "Fandango Quartet." Friday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $18, or $6 for students. 176 Cooper Avenue, Upper Montclair. (201) 746-6068. UNITY CONCERTS Tomohiro Okumura, violinist, will make his first appearance for Unity Concerts, performing compositions by Bach, Schubert and Milstein. Today at 3:30 P.M. Tickets: $25, $20 and $15. Montclair High School Community Auditorium, Park and Chestnut Streets, Montclair. (201) 744-6770. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Classic Blues Revue," with Natalie Lamb, draws upon famous and infamous blues singers with tunes that range from somber to risque. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $10. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. THEATER ALGONQUIN ARTS THEATER The Red Oak Music Theater presents "Seesaw," a musical directed by Jerry Yoder. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20. Old Square Plaza, Manasquan. (908) 367-1515. BURGDORFF CULTURAL CENTER The Strollers present "The Royal Family," by George S. Kaufman and Edna Ferber. Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. and May 19 and 20 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $6 for the elderly. 10 Durand Road, Maplewood. (201) 761-8453. CENTENARY LITTLE THEATER Three musicals presented by the Centenary Young Performers Workshop. "Company," Friday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 2 P.M. "Anything Goes," Saturday at 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. "Tom Sawyer," Saturday at 11 A.M. and next Sunday at 5 P.M. Tickets: $7, or $5 for students the the elderly. Campus of Centenary College, Hackettstown. (908) 852-1400, extension 203. CHATHAM COMMUNITY PLAYERS "Nunsense." Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M.; Saturday at 3 and 8 P.M. and next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $14, or $10 for students. The Playhouse. 23 North Passaic Avenue, Chatham. (201) 635-7363. CIRCLE PLAYERS "Lettice and Lovage," a comedy by Peter Shaffer. Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $8. 416 Victoria Avenue, Piscataway. (908) 968-7555. CIVIC THEATER OF HUDSON COUNTY "Jesus Christ Superstar," directed by Brian Waggoner. Today at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for the elderly and students. Raphael J. Cordero School, 158 Erie Street, Jersey City. (201) 823-2085. CROSSROADS THEATER COMPANY "Two Hah Hahs and a Homeboy," with Ruby Dee, Ossie Davis and their son, Guy Davis. Today and next Sunday at 7:30 P.M.; Wednesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 3 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $20, $25. 7 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 249-5560. ELIZABETH PLAYHOUSE "Kinfolks," by Karon Semones, based on the novel by Gurney Norman. Friday and Saturday at 7:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $4. 1100 East Jersey Street, Elizabeth. (908) 355-0077. GEORGE STREET PLAYHOUSE John Steinbeck's "Of Mice and Men." Starts Friday; through June 4. Tuesday through Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 7 P.M. Tickets: $30, $26 and $22. 9 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 246-7717. GUGGENHEIM THEATER The Two River Theater Company presents George Bernard Shaw's "Misalliance." Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M.; next Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $15 on Thursday, $22 on Friday and Saturday, and $18 on Sunday. Monmouth University, Cedar Avenue, West Long Branch. (908) 291-4114. IRON MOUNTAIN STAGE COMPANY "Vital Signs," by Jane Martin, a collage of contemporary women in a series of 3o monologues. Today at 4 P.M. Tickets: $9. Community Presbyterian Church of Ringwood, 145 Carletondale Road, Ringwood. (201) 962-9007. LITTLE FIREHOUSE THEATER The Bergen County Players present "A Few Good Men." Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and Sunday at 1 and 5 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $12, or $10 for matinees. 298 Kinderkamack Road, Oradell. (201) 261-4200. McCARTER THEATER Brian Friel's "Wonderful Tennessee." Today at 2 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M., Saturday at 4 and 8:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 2 P.M. Tickets: $26 to $30. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The National Stage Company presents Sam Shepard's "Fool for Love" and August Strindberg's "Miss Julie." Thursday through Saturday at 8 P.M.; Sunday at 3 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $18, or $14 for students and the elderly. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 489-0322. MILL HILL PLAYHOUSE The Passage Theater Company presents "Three More Gone," by Bruce Jacoby. Wednesday through Saturday at 8 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday at 3 P.M. Through May 21. Tickets: $25, $20 and $15. Front and Montgomery Streets, Trenton. (609) 392-0766. MOUNT HEBRON SCHOOL THEATER The Montclair Operetta Club presents "Cabaret." Today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $17.50. Bellevue Avenue, Montclair. (201) 669-5588. OAKHURST UNITED METHODIST CHUCH "Sweet Singer," a one-man musical based on the life of Charles Wesley. Today at 7:30 P.M. Suggest donation: $10, or $8 for students and the elderly. 103 Monmouth Road, Oakhurst. (908) 531-1150. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Lerner and Loewe's "Brigadoon." Through May 28. Tickets: $29 to $44. Wednesday through Sunday at 8 P.M.; matinees Thursday at 2 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 P.M. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. PINE TREE PLAYERS "The Butler Did It." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Through May 20. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly. (908) 774-8833. PLAYERS GUILD "A Grand Night for Singing." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $12, $11. The Little Theater at Leonia High School, Willtree Road, Leonia. (201) 947-9606. STATE THEATER "An Evening With Neil Sedaka." Saturday at 7 P.M. Proceeds will benefit the George Street Playhouse. Tickets: $20, $30, $40, $50. Tickets from the Playhouse box office: (908) 846-0825. 19 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. (908) 247-7200 ST. FRANCIS PLAYERS Rodgers and Hammerstein's "Carousel." Sunday at 3 P.M. Tickets: $10. Bergen Avenue and Park Street, Ridgefield Park. (201) 440-1829. VILLAGE PLAYERS Neil Simon's "Sunshine Boys." Today at 3 P.M.; Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $10, or $8 for the elderly and students. Ho-Ho-Kus School Auditorium, Lloyd Road in Ho-Ho-Kus. (201) 652-6872. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART FORMS "Paintings, Works on Paper and Sculpture" with works by Richard Stout, John Kochansky, Boris Zherdin and Paul Hirsch. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M., Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Sunday 1 to 4 P.M. Through May 31. 16 Monmouth Street, Red Bank. (908) 530-4330. BERGEN MUSEUM A series of photography exhibitions created by local teen-agers. Through May 21. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Opens Thursday. Through Aug. 10. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Wilderness of Waves," featuring the oils and watercolors of John Powers. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Omaha -- An Artist's Journey: Memories of D-Day," with drawings and collages by Ugo Giannini. Through June 5. Tuesday through Thursday, 6 P.M. to 8 P.M.; Friday, 10 A.M. to noon; Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. JOHN HARMS CENTER FOR THE ARTS The John Harms Theater's Intermission Gallery presents "Sitting Pretty," an exhibition of acrylics and mixed media by Ann Hadley Lasusas. Through Thursday. Free. Monday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 30 North Van Brunt Street, Englewood. (201) 567-5797, extension 20. MIDDLESEX COUNTY COLLEGE The Fifth Annual Alumni Art Exhibit. Starts Monday; through May 31. Daily, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. The College Center Gallery. 155 Mill Road, Edison. (908) 906-2566. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Japanese Expression in Paper." The upper gallery will be devoted to five sculptors from the paper-making town of Imadate in the prefecture of Fukui in Japan. Through June 11. Admission: $3. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Admission, $4; the elderly and students with ID, $3. 3 South Mountain Avenue. (201) 746-5555. NABISCO GALLERY "Lost and Found" an exhibition of 80 works of three-dimenional art using recycled objects. Through June 22. Daily and weekends, noon to 4 P.M. River Road and DeForest Avenue, East Hanover. (201) 503-3238. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through July 3. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY AUDUBON SOCIETY Photographs of New Jersey wildlife by John Collins will be displayed and available for sale. Proceeds will benefit New Jersey Audubon's Scherman-Hoffman Sanctuaries. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Through May. Hardscrabble Road, Bernardsville. (908) 766-5787. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "The Artful Message: Contemporary Video," focusing on the evolving art of video. Through June 11. Monday through Friday, noon to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Admission: $1. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NOYES MUSEUM "Messages From the Planet: Artists Work to Save the Earth," two- and three-dimensional works by artists in the mid-Atlantic region. Through June 18. "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. RIVERRUN GALLERY "Face -- Feelings," 40 works in oil, watercolor and mixed media by Edward Adams. Through June 5. Noon to 5 P.M. daily. Closed on Tuesdays. 287 South Main Street. Lambertville. (906) 397-3349. SETON HALL UNIVERSITY An exhibition of Ukrainian folk art, showing samples of pysanky (Ukrainian Easter eggs), ceramics, wood carvings, clothing and embroidery. Through May 28. 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday through Friday. Walsh Library Gallery, South Orange. (201) 761-9476.  SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "Masters' Vision," featuring paintings by Ruth Gikow. Through May 20. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Thursday until 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720. STEAMROLLER GALLERY Paintings by Sara Pasti. Opens Saturday; through June 10. Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. 52 Bridge Street, Frenchtown. (908) 996-7279. TRENTON CITY MUSEUM The Trenton Artists Workshop Association presents the mixed-media work of Katharine Bruce. Through May 28. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., and Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. (609) 989-3632. UNTITLED (#130), LTD "Member Invitational Exhibit." Paintings, sculpture and photography. Through next Sunday. Friday, 1 to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 10 P.M. to 7 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 130 Ryerson Avenue, Wayne. (201) 633-6767. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER "Shine On," color photographs of last year's solar eclipse. Starts tomorrow; through May 30. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. Free. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WYCKOFF GALLERY "Spring Rhapsody," featuring traditional and abstract works in various art media. through June 12. Tuesday through Saturday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 648 Wyckoff Avenue, Wyckoff. (201) 891-7436. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. SPOKEN WORD BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE Gordon Lewis, director of Stoneledge Fine Arts Conservation, will give an hourlong lecture on the history and conservation of paper art. Friday at 10:30 A.M. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE Anna Quindlen, author, will lecture on "Balancing the Political and the Private" as part of the annual Spring Women's Conference. Wednesday, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Fee: $35. 765 Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 224-2880. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Milton Meltzer, a biographer and historian, will discuss "Child Labor -- Has It Disappeared?" and "The Writer and Social Responsibility." Wednesday at 8 P.M. Free. Julio Ibarra, a photojournalist, will present a slide-lecture on Rwanda. Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FAIRLEIGH DICKINSON UNIVERSITY Paul Edwards and Constance Antonopoulos Webster, landscape architects, present a slide-lecture on "Preservation of Historic Gardens: An American and a British Perspective." Today at 3 P.M. Free. Lenfell Hall, 485 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 593-8661. MORRIS COUNTY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Carriages in the Industrial Age" is the topic of a slide-lecture today at 2 P.M. Free. Haggerty Educa tion Center of the Frelinghuysen Arboretum, East Hanover Avenue, Morris Township. (201) 267-3565. PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE David Ray presents a poetry workshop and reading as part of the Distinguished Poets' Series. Satuday, 10 A.M. to noon. Free. Paterson Museum, 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 684-5444. PRINCETON MARKET FAIR John Kelly, Corey Langer and Shirley Wright, Delaware Valley poets, will read selected works. Monday at 8 P.M. Free. Route 1 South, Princeton. (908) 874-3480. WOODBRIDGE MAIN LIBRARY E. W. Count, author of "Cop Talk: True Detective Stories From the NYPD," and Alfred Marini, a New York City Police Department detective, share their experiences. Wednesday at 7 P.M. Free. 1 George Frederick Plaza, Woodbridge. (908) 634-4450. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF NORTH JERSEY Benjamin Nelson, a professor at Fairleigh Dickinson University, will lecture on "The Jew as Serio-Comic Wanderer" in the context of the American Frontier. Thursday at 7 P.M. Tickets: $5. 1 Pike Drive, Wayne. (201) 595-0100. FOR CHILDREN BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "I See a Poem," a workshop that will allow children to listen to poems and then illustrate their thoughts and ideas. Saturday at 11 A.M. Fee: $4. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. ENGLEWOOD PUBLIC LIBRARY Suszanne Gomez will demonstrate tae kwon do, a martial arts form, for children 5 and up. Monday at 7 P.M. Free. 31 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 568-2215. FAMILY FUN FAIR The Montclair Art Museum's grounds will double as fairgrounds on Saturday from noon to 5 P.M. with arts and crafts and jewelry making. Members of the Intertribal Indians of New Jersey will perform traditional songs and dances. Admission: $3 for children and $2 for adults. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. HILLCREST COMMUNITY CENTER The West Milford Players present "Winnie the Pooh." Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 3 P.M. and May 19 and 20 at 8 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $6 for children. Macopin Road, West Milford. (201) 728-0027. JEWISH COMMUNITY CENTER "From Our Children's Hands" is the culmination of a yearlong effort by children in fine art classes, on display from today through next Sunday. Monday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 9:30 P.M.; Friday, 9 A.M. to 4 P.M., and Sunday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M. 760 Northfield Avenue, West Orange. (201) 736-3200. MEADOW THEATER "The Frog Prince and the Princess." Saturday at 11 A.M. and Sunday at 1 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $6. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. MORRIS MUSEUM Bill Money, actor, will present "The Jersey Devil and Other Tales." Today at 11 A.M. and 1:30 P.M. Tickets: $6.25. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (201) 538-8069. MORROW MEMORIAL METHOIDST CHURCH "Give Your Faith a Voice," a festival of choral music by children's church choirs of the area. Saturday at 5 P.M. Free. 600 Ridgewood Road, Maplewood. (908) 388-9794. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M., and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Saturday and Sunday through June 25. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through July 2. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. RITZ THEATER "The Ugly Duckling" and Ritzy the Wolf lead the audience on a journey to discover tolerance, kindess and compassion for others. Wednesday at 10 A.M. and 2:30, Thursday and Friday at 10 A.M. and Saturday at 10 A.M. and 1 P.M. Tickets: $4. 915 White Horse Pike, Oaklyn. (609) 858-5230. ST. ANDREW'S CHURCH The Canterbury Fair is a medieval marketplace including crafts, children's games, food, madrigal singers and demonstrations of medieval life. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Free. 419 South Street, New Providence. (908) 464-4875. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER Enchanted Creations presents "Alice in Wonderland," an audience-participatory version of Lewis Carroll's classic fairy tale. Saturday at 1 P.M. Tickets: $5. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. Y.M.-Y.W.H.A. OF BERGEN COUNTY "Let the Children Remember," an awareness project that exhibits art depicting subjects related to the Holocaust. Today at 2 P.M. Free. 605 Pascack Road, Washington Township. (201) 666-6610. ETC. BERGEN COUNTY ANIMAL SHELTER Bring your pets, large and small, to the Blessing of the Animals. Today at 1:15 P.M. 100 United Lane, Teterboro. (201) 646-2710. BIRCHWOOD MANOR The Garden State Coin, Stamp and Currency Show. Today, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Free. 111 North Jefferson Road, Whippany. (201) 887-1414. BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE "Follow the Drains," a walking tour of the drainage system in Red Bank for children aged 5 to 10. Saturday from 10 A.M. to noon. Registration is required for site of tour. (908) 224-2880. CAPE MAY WHALE WATCHER A sightseeing cruise around Cape May. Saturdays through June 17. Tickets: $10 and $5. Miss Chris Fishing Center, Third Avenue and Wilson. (609) 884-3351. GARDEN CLUB OF ENGLEWOOD A spring flower show, contest and sale. Today, noon to 3 P.M. Free. Englewood Hospital's Learning Center, 350 Engle Street, Englewood. (201) 894-3000. HOME AND DESIGNER SHOWCASE The Junior League of Monmouth County sponsors this exhibition featuring established and budding designers. Sunday, noon to 6 P.M.; Monday, Tuesday, Thursday and Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Wednesday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Saturday, 1 to 5 P.M. Tickets: $15. National Guard Armory, Chestnut Street, Red Bank. (908) 842-2039. NATURE WALK AND FIELD TRIP The Stony Brook-Millstone Watershed Association offers a daylong field excursion on the Watershed Preserve. Saturday, 9 A.M. to 3 P.M. Fee: $15. A Mother's Day Walk will stroll the preserve in search of nature -- birds building nests and other signs of motherly love. Saturday, 10 A.M. to noon. Fee: $3. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-3075. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL A double feature with "Death and the Maiden" and "Mamma Roma," today. "The Life and Times of Allen Ginsberg," Friday, and "Siddhartha," Saturday. 7 P.M. Friday and Saturday tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, George Street and Seminary Place. Sunday showings are at the State Theater, 19 Livingston Avenue, New Brunswick. Tickets: $7. (908) 932-8482.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
