<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ocean Study to Start After Big Changes And a Long Delay</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="807408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHALES AND WHALING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MODELS (SIMULATIONS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOUDSPEAKERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCRIPPS INSTITUTION OF OCEANOGRAPHY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EFD61739F934A35752C1A963958260" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ocean Study to Start After Big Changes And a Long Delay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER 18 months of delays and acrimonious debate over whether it would deafen whales and other marine mammals, a $35 million experiment using underwater sound to investigate the reality of global warming is scheduled to begin this week, though much modified because of protests.</p>
        <p>The experiment, run by the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., and involving seven foreign nations, was originally intended to fire sounds from underwater speakers across the Pacific Ocean at least once a day for a year. Sound travels faster in warm water than cold. In theory, changes in the  sound's speed as it crossed the Pacific could reveal temperature shifts as subtle as a few thousandths of a degree Fahrenheit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER 18 months of delays and acrimonious debate over whether it would deafen whales and other marine mammals, a $35 million experiment using underwater sound to investigate the reality of global warming is scheduled to begin this week, though much modified because of protests.</p>
        <p>The experiment, run by the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif., and involving seven foreign nations, was originally intended to fire sounds from underwater speakers across the Pacific Ocean at least once a day for a year. Sound travels faster in warm water than cold. In theory, changes in the  sound's speed as it crossed the Pacific could reveal temperature shifts as subtle as a few thousandths of a degree Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>Such work would try to verify whether computerized global climate models used to predict global warming are accurate or need to be improved.</p>
        <p>The temperature experiment is known as Acoustic Thermometry of Ocean Climate, or ATOC (pronounced A-talk). From a depth of about 3,000 feet, speakers off California and Hawaii are to rumble intermittently with low-frequency noises. Thousands of miles away, underwater microphones all over the Pacific are to pick up the faint signals.</p>
        <p>But the plan drew protests from about a dozen groups trying to protect such endangered mammals as the humpback whale, which is sometimes found near the transmission sites. The protesters contended that the project threatened to deafen whales and other marine mammals, disturbing a world where careful listening was synonymous with survival -- with finding food and avoiding becoming someone else's meal.</p>
        <p>"A deaf whale is a dead whale," said Dr. Linda S. Weilgart, a scientist who led the protests. "It's not worth the risk."</p>
        <p>The project scientists, led by Dr. Walter Munk, a leading Scripps oceanographer, vigorously denied that the experiment threatened to deafen or harm any animal. But faced with the prospect of defeat by the well-organized whale lobby, the scientists agreed to substantially redraw the plan.</p>
        <p>The new blueprint calls for fewer intermittent broadcasts from the loudspeakers -- about two days of six, instead of daily. More fundamentally, it  changes the sensitive test of global warming into an experiment that mainly measures the effects of loud noises on seagoing mammals. If signs of serious harm emerge, the experiment is to stop.</p>
        <p>From the start, the project has devoted a sizable amount to animal studies -- $2.9 million. But the revised plan, instead of combining temperature and whale tests, has the biologists taking exclusive control of the sound sources for the  experiments, and allowing investigations of possible injuries to mammals.</p>
        <p>The biologists want about four days between sound transmissions so areas around the loudspeakers can return to their normal acoustical and biological state, presumably allowing any animals that were scared away to return and allowing new animals to arrive.</p>
        <p>As important, the new plan calls for the California broadcast site to move from the sheltered waters of the Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary to Pioneer Seamount, a mass of old volcanic rock rising from the sea floor some 55  miles off San Francisco, where seas are rougher.</p>
        <p>The distance and the possibility of high waves will prevent small boats from  conducting animal studies. Instead, larger boats and planes or underwater microphones will scan the waters for signs of animal distress.</p>
        <p>A biologist at the University of California at Santa Cruz, Dr. Daniel P. Costa, who directs the California marine mammal studies, said aerial surveys of  the site had been flown once a month since June to try to understand the normal  volatility of animal behavior and demographics.</p>
        <p>Dr. Costa's team has been able to tie radio transmitters onto 14 male and 7 female elephant seals so that satellites can easily track their movements and determine if the project's transmissions cause the animals any anxiety, perhaps  as evidenced by their veering away.</p>
        <p>A similar plan to put instruments on blue whales fell through when too few of the animals could be found in the proper vicinity, even as great numbers of them were sighted much farther south near the Channel Islands. "People think of the ocean as static," Dr. Costa said. "It's just not that way."</p>
        <p>Moving the experiment out to sea added to its costs. Old power cables for the California loudspeaker had to be lifted from the seabed and new cables laid down. But project scientists say the Pioneer site is fine scientifically.</p>
        <p>"For acoustic propagation, the seamount is better" than the sanctuary site, said Dr. Andrew Forbes, the project manager.</p>
        <p>In the new plan, the gathering of any warming data will be secondary, but perhaps still significant. By definition, the best experiment for temperature studies is to take daily readings, thereby collecting as much information as possible. Yet taking readings every four days or so is still regular, though less productive.</p>
        <p>If the tests show no significant harm to the animals after about a year of transmissions, the scientists hope to operate the speakers according to their own schedule in an effort to study global warming. But they acknowledged that any further studies would require the approval of the whale lobby.</p>
        <p>Scientists are eager to press ahead because the project is so superior to any other method of detecting global warming. Buoys and instruments launched from ships at great cost can generate a finite number of readings, perhaps 100 or at  most 200 on a good voyage.</p>
        <p>By contrast, ATOC would probe the average temperature of a vast body of water, greatly increasing the reliability of the information while significantly cutting the cost.</p>
        <p>During a decade, the signature of global warming is anticipated to be the infinitesimal speedup of sound waves so that their overall travel time across the Pacific is reduced by 1.5 seconds.</p>
        <p>Another attraction for global warming studies is that water has a high "specific heat" or heat capacity, greater than that of almost any other liquid or solid. That means it absorbs heat relatively easily with a minimum rise in temperature and once warmed up holds onto the heat tenaciously. So the sea's temperature changes, compared with those of air and land, are minuscule. It absorbs and stores huge quantities of solar energy and averages out the violent swings of atmospheric weather.</p>
        <p>For these reasons, the sea is considered one of the best places to hunt for clues of a global temperature rise, especially in its dark regions, far from the vicissitudes of the surface.</p>
        <p>The project was designed to maximize warming data and to minimize animal disruptions, its architects say. The frequency of the sound, 60 to 90 cycles per second, was chosen because it appeared to be practically inaudible to seals, sea lions and toothed whales (the kind that dive deep). So too, the sound begins softly and grows louder, giving mammals time to swim away if they find it unsettling.</p>
        <p>Many project scientists seem to believe that the onset of behavioral studies  will show only that the sound system is biologically innocuous. But they stress  that they are keeping an open mind.</p>
        <p>"We're not an advocacy group," said Dr. Christopher W. Clark, a Cornell biologist who directs the project's mammal studies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
