<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Perils of Invisible Foe Are Often Tied to Heat Systems</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="743808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASPHYXIATION AND SUFFOCATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIRES AND FIREMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D7123CF934A25751C0A963958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Perils of Invisible Foe Are Often Tied to Heat Systems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Each year, about 250 people in the United States are killed by carbon monoxide and 5,000 more are injured, some permanently, according to the Consumer Product Safety Commission.</p>
        <p>Most often, the source is a heating system or water heater that has a cracked flue or a blocked chimney. While experts say equipment fueled by natural gas appears to be the most troublesome, carbon monoxide can also come from heating systems using oil, propane or coal, from cars running in attached garages, or from charcoal grills used indoors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Each year, about 250 people in the United States are killed by carbon monoxide and 5,000 more are injured, some permanently, according to the Consumer Product Safety Commission.</p>
        <p>Most often, the source is a heating system or water heater that has a cracked flue or a blocked chimney. While experts say equipment fueled by natural gas appears to be the most troublesome, carbon monoxide can also come from heating systems using oil, propane or coal, from cars running in attached garages, or from charcoal grills used indoors.</p>
        <p>In the incident yesterday in Brooklyn in which dozens of people were overcome, carbon monoxide, which is odorless and colorless, apparently was released when underground Con Edison cables caught fire. The furnace in the building was in good condition, according to Brooklyn Union Gas, which inspected it.</p>
        <p>Carbon monoxide is produced from incomplete combustion, that is, burning with limited oxygen. If there is enough oxygen for a fuel to burn completely, the gas produced is carbon dioxide, which is not toxic.</p>
        <p>In home heating systems that use forced hot air, a crack in the metal box in which the air is heated can let smoke into the box and then, through the heating ducts, into the living area. In all heating systems, a blocked chimney can let smoke back into a house. A faulty heating system was blamed for the death of Vitas Gerulaitis, the tennis star, in a cottage in Southampton, L.I., in September.</p>
        <p>When carbon monoxide enters the lungs, it latches on to hemoglobin, the component of blood that normally shuttles oxygen to the cells, and refuses to let go. With less oxygen being delivered around the body, drowsiness, headache and nausea set in, followed, at increasing levels of poisoning, by respiratory failure, convulsions and death.</p>
        <p>While carbon monoxide is invisible and odorless, often the smoke that comes with it warns people who are exposed. But because the gas makes people drowsy, many victims die as they sleep. And heating systems that run relatively cleanly, especially natural gas and propane systems, often have smoke so clean that it can go unnoticed.</p>
        <p>In October, Chicago began requiring carbon-monoxide detectors in some houses that use natural gas, but no other major American cities do. Experts say, though, that they are a good idea.</p>
        <p>"Whether you're required to, or you have the choice, if you have gas-burning appliances or a garage attached to a house, you should buy at least one carbon monoxide detector," said Tim Montgomery, a spokesman for Underwriters Laboratories, an independent, nonprofit testing organization based in Northbrook, Ill. The first one should go in a hallway near bedroom doors, he said.</p>
        <p>"If you can afford it, put another one in an area near one of the gas-burning appliances," he said. The units sell for $30 to $70 in hardware stores and resemble smoke detectors. Some have batteries and others plug in.</p>
        <p>To reduce the risk, experts also advise having fuel-burning appliances inspected annually. Underwriters Laboratories also advises watching for streaks of carbon or soot around fuel-burning appliances.</p>
        <p>New York City requires smoke detectors but has no regulations or advice concerning carbon monoxide detectors, according to George Semidey, a spokesman for the Fire Department. But New York is studying the Chicago rule, which requires such detectors in new houses and existing single-family houses when new furnaces are installed. Several smaller cities have similar requirements.</p>
        <p>Hardware stores also sell cardboard strips that change color in the presence of carbon monoxide, but Underwriters Laboratories advises against them. "It doesn't warn you if there's a problem when you're not looking at it," said Mr. Montgomery.</p>
        <p>But the models that sound an alarm are also not trouble free. In December, Chicago experienced unusually high carbon monoxide levels on the streets, from cars and other sources, and this set off thousands of new carbon monoxide detectors. Underwriters Laboratories is considering new standards for the detectors, so that they cannot be set off so easily.</p>
        <p>"If it becomes a nuisance, people are going to disregard the detector or turn it off," said Mr. Montgomery.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
