<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bedford's Struggle With the Devil</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="811489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRADING CARDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SATANISM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BEDFORD (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOMBARDI, KATE STONE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DI BARI, MARY ANN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DI NOZZI, CEIL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Occult Sciences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFDC1039F935A15752C1A963958260" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bedford's Struggle With the Devil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE STONE LOMBARDI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOMBARDI, KATE STONE</byline>
      <dateline>BEDFORD</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE way Mary Ann Di Bari and Ceil Di Nozzi see it, the Devil arrived in Bedford, liked what he saw and settled in. Now, there are signs of him everywhere, the women say, particularly in the school curriculum, where he reveals himself in science experiments that worship death, award-winning books that promote the occult and history lessons that glorify witchcraft and Satanism.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce Dennis, Superintendent of Bedford's schools, sees things differently. He refers to the women as "a coalition of two" who claim to speak for most parents but who in reality are attempting to dictate their own narrow point of view by fomenting hysteria and advocating censorship. Dr. Dennis said he believed that the women are part of a national movement that is pursuing a broad agenda of curriculum control in local schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE way Mary Ann Di Bari and Ceil Di Nozzi see it, the Devil arrived in Bedford, liked what he saw and settled in. Now, there are signs of him everywhere, the women say, particularly in the school curriculum, where he reveals himself in science experiments that worship death, award-winning books that promote the occult and history lessons that glorify witchcraft and Satanism.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce Dennis, Superintendent of Bedford's schools, sees things differently. He refers to the women as "a coalition of two" who claim to speak for most parents but who in reality are attempting to dictate their own narrow point of view by fomenting hysteria and advocating censorship. Dr. Dennis said he believed that the women are part of a national movement that is pursuing a broad agenda of curriculum control in local schools.</p>
        <p>The controversy has become so heated that the police were required to control attendance at a forum the school district held last week to address Mrs. Di Bari and Mrs. Di Nozzi's accusations. Dr. Dennis said he wanted to limit attendance to Bedford residents and news organizations. His critics suggested the district had something to hide.</p>
        <p>The conflict began last spring over a popular fantasy trading-card game called Magic: The Gathering. The game allows players to pretend they are powerful wizards who can summon enchantments, cast spells and vanquish foes. Magic, never part of the school's curriculum, was being played on school grounds at meetings of the Magic Club, which met before school at the Pound Ridge Elementary School, as well as at an after-school enrichment program at Fox Lane Middle School.</p>
        <p>Parents whose children play Magic say it is only a card game, one comparable  to chess in its strategies, which promote creative thinking. But Mrs. Di Nozzi and Mrs. Di Bari saw something dangerous in the game and contended that the cards promoted the occult and Satanism.</p>
        <p>"Magic: The Gathering is steeped in the hidden language, imagery, signs and rites of at least 30 satanic cults in this country," Mrs. Di Bari said. "Moreover, it is a codification of the beliefs, practices and perceptions of the new Satanists of today. There are inducements in Magic: The Gathering to engage  in destructive, cruel cult practices."</p>
        <p>The two women formed a group called Concerned Parents: Citizens and Professionals Against the Seduction of Children and took their complaint to Dr.  Dennis, who imposed a 30-day moratorium on Magic in the schools until he could study it. After consulting three child psychologists and conferring with the school board, Dr. Dennis determined that the game was not harmful. He lifted the moratorium and allowed Magic to be played -- under supervision and with parental consent -- on school grounds.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dennis said that when he announced that he would permit children to resume playing Magic, Mrs. Di Nozzi came to him and said that the issue was not  over and that he would soon be remembered as "the superintendent who brought Satanism to the district."</p>
        <p>Over the summer, after a lull in the protest, the anti-Magic movement gathered force. The association was host to a forum in September, in which seven people who said they were experts on Satanism and the occult criticized the district. Now, however, the accusations have expanded beyond the card game and include assertions about Satanism in Bedford's curriculum.</p>
        <p>The association has taken exception to a common science experiment in which children examine owl pellets -- which includes partial remains of their prey --  in an activity intended to teach ecological relationships. The women call the experiment part of a "death curriculum." They also object to a "bio poem" English assignment, in which a student writes about his emotions and fantasies,  and the teaching of multiculturalism. Mrs. Di Bari also singled out the sixth-grade decision-making curriculum, which includes relaxation techniques like yoga and meditation as "promoting New Age religious teachings."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Di Nozzi and Mrs. Di Bari, along with another parent, wrote to Dr. Dennis, asking that their children be excluded from various materials and practices in classrooms. Included among the subjects to which they did not wish  their children exposed were values clarification, use of moral dilemmas, discussion of moral standards, role playing, sensitivity training, keeping a diary or journal or log book, curriculums pertaining to drugs and alcohol, discussion of nuclear war, globalism, education in human sexuality and evolution.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dennis was surprised by some of the books the parents objected to, including "My Side of the Mountain" by Jean Craighead George, which won the Hans Christian Andersen International Award, and "Bridge to Terabithia" by Katherine  Paterson, a Newbery Medal Winner.</p>
        <p>" 'Bridge to Terabithia' is a horrible book," Mrs. Di Nozzi said. "It contains profanity. It is full of death, and it goes contrary to my beliefs." As to a drug and alcohol program, Mrs. Di Nozzi, who has twins in the fifth grade,  said: "I don't want my children in there. It takes 17 weeks to tell our children not to take drugs? The third week my son had to sit there and watch a movie, and there was a girl who had a drug overdose on a stretcher, screaming and yelling.  I don't want him exposed to this. My child is not going to take drugs because that's how he has been raised."</p>
        <p>One of Mrs. Di Bari and Mrs. Di Nozzi's complaints is that no alternatives are offered to the instruction that offends them. Dr. Dennis maintains that the  district is under no obligation to offer alternatives.</p>
        <p>But what has really heated up the debate is the perception that the women want to impose their views and restrictions on other parents in the district. At the forum last Monday night, residents lined up at two microphones to express their feelings. While a handful of speakers lauded Mrs. Di Bari and Mrs. Di Nozzi's courage in opposing the district, the majority of residents spoke with anger against them.</p>
        <p>"If we learned anything from Salem in 1692, from Munich in 1938 and from Washington in the early 1950's, it is that when the witch hunt begins, it is not only morally wrong but ultimately dangerous for good citizens to remain silent," said Rosa Portell, a district resident. "When the witch hunt begins, we must all come together to say: 'Nonsense,' and 'Not in this community you don't.' "</p>
        <p>Adam Green, 14, a freshman at Fox Lane High School, said, "I can not stop world hunger or save the ozone layer, but I will stand with a resistance unparalleled to the strongest blockade before my freedom of education is taken away from me."</p>
        <p>One fifth grader got up and said in a trembling voice: "I play Magic, and I don't want to sacrifice anybody or anything."</p>
        <p>Maria Pappace, a fifth-grade teacher at Pound Ridge Elementary School, defended the multiculturalism teaching that Mrs. Di Bari had attacked. "We never celebrated the Day of the Dead," she said. "We don't worship idols. The children did learn about other cultures and some of the customs the Aztecs followed. I've been told by you that my teaching is immoral and illegal. I'm proud to be a teacher, and I think it is slander what you're doing to our school." Mrs. Di Bari insisted that her association was not engaged in censorship. "We burn no books and restrict no one other than our own children from reading anything in school or out of school," she said.</p>
        <p>But others remained skeptical. Several parents suggested that the association is backed by the Christian Coalition. "There is a very well-established national agenda, and our school district is being affected by that," said Ron Rothenberg, who has two children in the district.</p>
        <p>The two women and the Christian Coalition deny any connection with each other. "These two women are acting totally on their own," said Wendy Holibaugh,  chairwoman of the Westchester chapter of the Christian Coalition. "We don't work with them, and we don't back them in any way. I did call them to tell them I think they are doing the right thing. They have exposed a lot of garbage in the  district. I do believe we share a lot of values."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
