<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1890's or 1990's, the Visions Are of an Apocalypse Soon</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="762654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ART VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, VICKI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDB1230F937A25756C0A963958260" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1890's or 1990's, the Visions Are of an Apocalypse Soon</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vicki Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, VICKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WORLD HAS BEEN ENDING for a very long time, but the approach of the year 2000 has convinced a multitude that This Is It. Doomsday has in fact loomed large at least since the atom bomb gave us the power to destroy the planet, casting a dark fallout on art, on literature like Don DeLillo's "White Noise" and Richard Adams's "Watership Down," and on films from "Godzilla" to "Bladerunner." Recently, gaping holes in the ozone layer offer new evidence of how prodigal we have been in inventing means of self-annihilation, and the appearance of seemingly invincible viruses serve as a warning that the powers of medicine and science are more limited than we had thought.</p>
        <p>Millennialism has already sent some groups to mountaintops to await the end -- and when it didn't come, some came back down. Even the corridors of power, where a single command could end it all, have rung with the trump of doom: in 1982 President Ronald Reagan, his Interior Secretary and his Secretary of Defense each declared that he believed, at least some of the time, that it would all be over soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WORLD HAS BEEN ENDING for a very long time, but the approach of the year 2000 has convinced a multitude that This Is It. Doomsday has in fact loomed large at least since the atom bomb gave us the power to destroy the planet, casting a dark fallout on art, on literature like Don DeLillo's "White Noise" and Richard Adams's "Watership Down," and on films from "Godzilla" to "Bladerunner." Recently, gaping holes in the ozone layer offer new evidence of how prodigal we have been in inventing means of self-annihilation, and the appearance of seemingly invincible viruses serve as a warning that the powers of medicine and science are more limited than we had thought.</p>
        <p>Millennialism has already sent some groups to mountaintops to await the end -- and when it didn't come, some came back down. Even the corridors of power, where a single command could end it all, have rung with the trump of doom: in 1982 President Ronald Reagan, his Interior Secretary and his Secretary of Defense each declared that he believed, at least some of the time, that it would all be over soon.</p>
        <p>The Galerie St. Etienne in midtown Manhattan has jumped the clock a bit with a show called "On the Brink 1900-2000: The Turning of Two Centuries" by comparing art at the end of this century with art at the end of the last. Although this fins de siecle survey of 93 works in various media is necessarily incomplete and more than a little scattershot, much of the material is fine indeed and proves morbid fascination a powerful artistic muse.</p>
        <p>Not that all is entirely poisonous in this precinct of last days. Among the early examples are a couple of sprightly Cubist paeans to the city, a tip of the hat to technology and a wistful hint of utopia, but they fade into irrelevance before the powerful lures of naked women, unnatural disasters and the inventive excesses of hell. In 1995 it will surprise no one that sex and violence grab the lion's share of attention; hell, on the other hand, has not had much recent commercial exposure.</p>
        <p>Yet just last year Erik Desmazieres etched a "Temptation of St. Anthony" so full of self-assured monsters and fiends on chariots made of bone that they effectively render tiny, distant St. Anthony insignificant. This vigorous etching borrows subject and form from Jacques Callot, a 17th-century printmaker who lived when Satan and his cohorts were as real and believable as bad luck. During the last 200 years, such subjects dwindled as hell was downgraded in favor of purgatory, age-long sleep and a comfortable heaven. But mortal terrors do not give way easily: in 1888 James Ensor, who was on intimate terms with dread of both the here and the hereafter, could still imagine a spiky apocalypse in which demented hybrid creatures savaged a troupe of angels.</p>
        <p>The idea that human beings rather than God might polish off life on earth is barely 100 years old and has repeatedly made itself heard through two world wars, the German death camps and the atom bomb. Artists in the last couple of decades -- Neil Jenney and Robert Morris come to mind -- have repeatedly had apocalyptic visions. Interesting, "On the Brink," which runs through May 26, locates the staple science-fiction tale of post-nuclear survival in the underground comics: Gary Panter's "Jimbo," a harshly drawn figure in an exploded landscape, first published in Raw.</p>
        <p>Three other versions of a world destroyed by human folly, hate and technology turn up in photographs of Kuwait after the gulf war by Steve McCurry -- a thoroughly blackened and blistered corpse with a gun by his side; two demolished cars abandoned in the desert where an enormous, distant plume of flame cannot light up the black sky; a view of the bare desert itself with funnels of smoke supporting a sky so inky it reduces the sun to the size and power of an auto headlight.</p>
        <p>Hell is merely a metaphor today, yet cameras can take its portrait, and often do. Not only has Armageddon been secularized but the sense of impending catastrophe has been repeatedly reinforced by visions in the newspapers: Auschwitz, Hiroshima, My Lai, Bosnia, Rwanda. The camera gives us infernos easier to substantiate than anything in Bosch -- and far more numerous, more diverse and more visible to a much wider audience.</p>
        <p>Photography also completed the transformation of death's image from its traditional functions as memorial, warning or moral instruction into a news item -- McCurry's burnt corpse, for example. When it comes to death, however, "On the Brink" leans on the side of imagination rather than reporting. Death by epidemic flies into a late-19th-century hospital on the wings of a predatory bird in Max Klinger's "Plague." The idea that the entire world might perish from a disease was first broached by Mary Shelley in a story written in 1826; it comes back in Sue Coe's trenchant 1990 drawing of a virus escaping in a lab and again in David Wojnarowicz's moving "When I Put My Hands on Your Body." This last, a text printed over a photograph of skeletons, is the plaint of a lover who envisions the dissolution of the beloved's body even as he embraces it.</p>
        <p>Redemption from death is promised by a Georges Rouault print from the 20's that is so dark, so foreboding, so concentrated on skulls ranked about a cross that redemption seems beyond reach. Artists today hold out even less hope to a culture steeped in fear and pessimism. In Luis Cruz Azaceta's 1989 "Death Goes for a Walk in the City," a skull with a lolling, spotted tongue presides over the scrawled, dripping, overpainted words Crime, Drugs, Homeless, AIDS, Cocaine, an a la carte menu of destruction written out in graffiti.</p>
        <p>AND IN A STARTLING 1993 painting by Katherine Kuharic, a bare-breasted woman is decked out in pearls; her arms are flayed, and the sockets of her skull teem with red and blue worms or entrails. The Gothic images of death triumphant and death as the triumph of decay come back to haunt the end of this century, when science, medicine, technology, and, for many, faith, seem to have reached the limits of their power to save us.</p>
        <p>When the lights threaten to go out all over the world, sex, with its unique connection to life, takes on even more than the usual urgency and anxiety. Late in the last century, this anxiety manifested itself in the figure of the femme fatale, the ultimate emblem of appetite and danger. In Edvard Munch's "Hands" (1895), a half-nude woman with extravagantly flowing hair looks back over her shoulder coquettishly while a mass of male hands avidly reaches for her. Not long after, Gustave Adolf Mossa drew a miniature man trapped, perhaps crucified, on a woman's breast in a web she has woven.</p>
        <p>Other anxieties about sex were on the loose. Egon Schiele used a scorching line to draw naked women baring their genitals for the viewer. (His erotic drawings got him into trouble more than once.) Today the femme fatale is likely to be wounded, or flayed, or shut off from life -- a mannequin, improperly put together, evidently capable of suffering life's humiliations but certainly not its joys. Quite possibly women are still dangerous; certainly they have been hurt.</p>
        <p>Photography conveys anxieties about the body with the conviction of a practiced observer. The show compares Munch's etching of a sick child to Sally Mann's photograph of a child with a black eye. The early work reminds us how high child mortality rates were; the later one inevitably calls child abuse to mind. Cindy Sherman photographs a naked female dummy with hinges and joins so prominent there is no way to consider her whole; the mannequin forlornly displays her plaster vulva and the child's doll she has temporarily cast aside.</p>
        <p>Artists and anyone else uncertain they are saved are subject to eternal nervousness. Some fix their gaze on the here and now and try not to blink. Ralph Waldo Emerson, on being warned that the Second Coming was nigh, reportedly responded, "The end of the world will not affect me; I can live without it."  ART VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
