<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E4D61F39F933A05753C1A963958260" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mexicans Reach New Pact On Wages and Prices The Mexican Government signed a new agreement with labor and business intended to control prices, limit salaries and cut public spending, in an attempt to restore stability and economic growth. The pact does not include any controls on exchange rates, an issue of concern to both foreign and domestic investors who have been hurt severely by instability in the peso-dollar exchange rate. [Page D2.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mexicans Reach New Pact On Wages and Prices The Mexican Government signed a new agreement with labor and business intended to control prices, limit salaries and cut public spending, in an attempt to restore stability and economic growth. The pact does not include any controls on exchange rates, an issue of concern to both foreign and domestic investors who have been hurt severely by instability in the peso-dollar exchange rate. [Page D2.]</p>
        <p>2 Billion Takeover Offer  Praxair, a large producer of industrial gases, offered $2.1 billion for CBI Industries, the world's largest producer of carbon dioxide. Praxair, which was spun off from Union Carbide in 1992, said it would pay $32 a share, a 59 percent premium over the $20.125 closing price of CBI shares on Friday. Praxair made public its offer after six months of unsuccessful talks with CBI, which said it  would review the offer. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Budget Conferees Gather  Republican leaders in the House and Senate said they would meet today to start ironing out differences in the budget bills passed last week. President Clinton  has said he will veto the bill, and Senator Bob Kerrey of Nebraska said the Republicans should negotiate with Congressional Democrats instead of focusing on Mr. Clinton. [A1.]</p>
        <p>Leeson to Return to Singapore  Nicholas W. Leeson, the futures trader accused of ruining Barings of London, said he would return to Singapore to face forgery and fraud charges, ending his  fight to prevent extradition from Germany, where he was arrested in March. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Good News for Insurers  The cost of environmental cleanups is not quite the disaster for insurance companies that was once feared, a number of studies have found, in part because  claims for restoration of natural resources, like lakes polluted by acid rain, have not materialized. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Cable Prices Climb  Prices for cable television service have resumed their rise, even as Congress is completing legislation that would unfetter the industry. [D7.]</p>
        <p>All the Nostalgia, All the Time  Hoping to capitalize on the success of its Nick at Nite cable channel, MTV Networks plans to offer a cable channel early next year that is devoted to nostalgic television shows. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Sybase Seeks a Turnaround  Sybase is hoping that its latest version of its SQL Server will restore its competitive edge -- and its earnings growth. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Forget the Aston Martin  BMW of North America and its new advertising agency have developed an aggressive campaign that features Pierce Brosnan, who as James Bond drives a BMW in the latest 007 film. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [D10.]</p>
        <p>Turning On the Lights  Experiments are under way to demonstrate that chunks of silicon can be used to run the nation's electrical power network much the way a computer is operated. [D5.]</p>
        <p>When Systems Crash  The Food and Drug Administration has spent $13 million on a computer system to help it identify tainted food and medicine from abroad, but the General Accounting Office said that the system doesn't work. [A13.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
