<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ON THE TOWNS</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="770887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENTERTAINMENT AND AMUSEMENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DC1139F936A15755C0A963958260" item-length="4373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ON THE TOWNS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSIC ALBERT MUSIC HALL The Pinelands Cultural Society presents "Sounds of the Jersey Pines," a series of Saturday night concerts through the end of the year. The program features live presentations of bluegrass, country and Pinelands music. Admission: $4, or $1 for children under 12. 139 Wells Mill Road (Route 532), Waretown. (609) 971-1593. CONGRESS HALL, CAPE MAY Christopher O'Reilly, pianist. Today at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. DUKE ISLAND PARK, BRIDGEWATER The Somerset County Park Commission starts its free summer concert series with a program of 60's and 70's music performed by the Sensational Soul Cruisers. Sunday at 7 P.M. (908) 722-1200, extension 221. GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER Yanni. Thursday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $22.50 to $45. Exit 116 on the Garden State Parkway, Holmdel. (908) 888-5011. GIRALDA FARMS "A Salute to the Allies" is the theme of the 12th annual Giralda Concert with the New Jersey Symphony Orchestra. Today at 6 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $3 for children under 12. Route 124, Madison. (201) 377-6622. FAIR LAWN SUMMER MUSIC FESTIVAL The 35th annual festival kicks off today at 8:30 P.M. with the Symphonic Concert Band. Next Sunday at 8:30 P.M., enjoy community dancing to the music of Tubby Tubello. Free, but bring your own chairs. Memorial Park and Berdan Avenue, Fair Lawn. (201) 796-6746. MEMORIAL PARK, MAPLEWOOD Arts Maplewood presents C. J. Chenier and the Red Hot Louisiana Band with their New Orleans zydeco music. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Free. (201) 378-2133. NEWARK MUSEUM "Noontime Jazz in the Garden" series. Thursdays at 12:30 P.M. Through Aug. 10. Free. Dreyfuss Memorial Garden, 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. OCEAN COUNTY LIBRARY The Garden State Philharmonic Orchestra and Chorus present a free concert in the courtyard celebrating American heritage by performing patriotic songs, light classics and popular tunes. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Free, but bring your own chair. 101 Washington Street, Toms River. (908) 349-6277. OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS The eighth annual "Great Sousa Concert" with the Allentown Band, conducted by Ronald Demkee. Tickets: $12. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035. PRINCETON UNIVERSITY The first annual Princeton Invitational Choir Festival concludes with a Gala Final Concert with all the participating choirs. Today at 8 P.M. Free. Richardson Auditorium of Alexander Hall, Princeton. (609) 896-9330. RAMAPO COLLEGE The Minolta Summer Music Fest presents four free Thursday night concerts spanning a spectrum of musical tastes. First up, the Hanover Wind Symphony. Thursday at 8 P.M. The Bandshell, 505 Ramapo Valley Road. Off Route 17 and 202 in Mahwah. (201) 529-7612. RUTGERS ARTS CENTER The Rutgers Summerfest continues with Marian McPartland, today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $22. Keyboard Extravaganza! Wednesday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Summerfest Chamber Players. Thursday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Red, White and Blue! with Frederick Urrey, tenor. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Music From Aston Magna, Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. George Street at Route 18, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7511. TINICUM PARK, BUCKS COUNTY The Riverside Symphonia's second annual outdoor concert, on Saturday at 8 P.M., will feature a mix of light classical music and American show tunes. Tickets: $10 or $3 for children. Route 32, 10 miles north of New Hope, Pa. (215) 862-3300. VETERANS' FIELD, EDGEWATER The New Jersey Pops Symphony Orchestra, directed by Michael Buglio, performs classical works, Broadway show tunes and patriotic music. Friday at 7:30 P.M. Free. River Road, Edgewater. (201) 744-1700, extension 52. WEST SIDE PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH, RIDGEWOOD The Metisse Piano Quartet with Carol Rodland, violist; Jennifer Kloetzel, cellist; Chul-In Park, violinist, and Priya Mayadas, pianist. Today at 7 P.M. Free. 6 South Monroe Street, Ridgewood. (201) 652-1966. THEATER BECKFORD THEATER, MORRIS MUSEUM In "Love Letters," a relationship is revealed through a lifetime of correspondence. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. and July 6-9. Tickets: $17.50. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (201) 538-0454. CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER The Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire," with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341. EAST LYNNE COMPANY "The Woman Question" features Susan Glaspell's "Supressed Desires," Marie Jenney Howe's "Anti-Suffrage Monologue" and George Middleton's "Unknown Lady." Today at 3 P.M. The Meadowlands Center for the Arts, Rutherford. Also, Wednesday through July 8 at 8:30 P.M. at Lyle Hall of the First Methodist Church, Cape May. Tickets: $14, or $12 for the elderly. (201) 863-6436. FOUNDATION THEATER "Nunsense." Wednesday and Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 8 P.M. Through July 9. Tickets: $15, or $13 for students and the elderly. Burlington County College. Route 530, Pemberton. (609) 894-2138. GUGGENHEIM SUMMER THEATER "I Hate Hamlet." Thursday through Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 7:30 P.M. Through July 9. Tickets: $17. Monmouth University, West Long Branch. (908) 571-3475. McCARTER THEATER "Family Secrets," with Sherry Glaser. Monday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20 to $30. A solo piano concert with George Winston. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $22 to $32. Sweet Honey in the Rock, a tradional African-American congregational choral quintet, performs Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $17 to $27. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL Harold Pinter's "Homecoming." Today at 2 and 7 P.M., Tuesday at 8 P.M., Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. "Julius Caesar" begins July 5. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-5600. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE "The Secret Garden," a musical by Marsha Norman and Lucy Simon, based on the novel by Frances Hodgson Burnett. Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 23. Tickets: $29 to $44. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. ROOSEVELT PARK AMPHITHEATER The Middlesex County Department of Parks and Recreation presents Plays-in-the-Park 1995. "Into the Woods." Wednesday through Saturday at 8:30 P.M. "The Sound of Music" begins on July 12. Tickets: $3. Edison. (609) 548-2884. THEATERFEST "Lost in Yonkers," with Doris Belack. Today at 2 and 8 P.M. "On Golden Pond." Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M.; Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 9. Montclair State University, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (201) 655-5112. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART MUSEUM, PRINCETON UNIVERSITY "Collaborative Landscape Photographs by Laura McPhee, Class of 1980, and Virginia Beahan," an exhibition of 20 color photographs, opens Thursday. Through Aug. 20. Free. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Princeton. (609) 258-3788. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. "John Schettino: Drawings and Paintings," through July 30. "Photographic Drawings" by David Horton. Through July 30. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. Through Aug. 10. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Summer Daze," an exhibition of works by all members of the center. Through Aug. 20. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Tangible Insites," textural paintings and clay vessels by Susan Hogan. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CS SCHULTE GALLERIES "Duet: Dan Christensen -- 30 Years of Paintings; Elaine Grove -- Recent Sculpture." Through July 14. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 340 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 376-6900. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007. EXTENSION GALLERY "Hug the Noise," an exhibition of cast metal sculpture and drawings by Sean Poreda. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777. GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Displacement," a collage by Peter Jacobs, and "Home," a collage in mixed media by Valerie Sivilli, are on display. Today, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. GALLERY AT GENERAL PUBLIC UTILITIES Color photographs by H. Lisa Solon and sculptures and paintings by David A. Angelini. Opens Saturday. Through July 30. Free. Monday through Friday, 8:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 100 Interpace Parkway, Parsippany. (201) 263-6684. GUILD OF CREATIVE ART "Rhythms of Nature," a collection of landscapes, watercolors, pastels and collages by Fran McIlvain. Through July 6. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 4:30 P.M. 620 Broad Street, Route 35, Shrewsbury. (908) 741-1441. HOUSE OF BRATA ART GALLERY "So Big, So Little," five paintings by John Krushenick. Through Saturday. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. 46A Fairfield Street, Montclair. (201) 783-7348. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Today, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. JAZZ 88 GALLERY Paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880. JERSEY CITY MUSEUM "Albizu Lives," a visual commemoration. Through Sept. 16. "The Nation Is Its People: Body and Soul of Lolita Lebron." Through Aug. 18. "Joan Fine: Wall Reliefs." Through Aug. 18. Tuesday, Thursday, Friday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Wednesday, 10:30 A.M. to 8 P.M. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514. LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photographs by H. Lisa Solon. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464. LONG BEACH ISLAND FOUNDATION OF ARTS AND SCIENCE "Choice Collection -- Crafts 1995," an exhibition and sale, and "LBI Art Foundation Faculty Exhibition." Monday and Tuesday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., 120 Long Beach Blvd., Loveladies. (609) 494-3169. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "From Darkness Into Light," paintings and drawings by Howard Lerner, through Friday. "Images, Dreams, Words and Marks," a solo show of paintings and drawings by Lisa Pressman, starts Saturday. Through Aug. 4. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 939-6969. MONMOUTH COUNTY HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION MUSEUM AND LIBRARY "Optical Delights: Stereographic Views of Monmouth County" presents images of Victorian life. Starts Tuesday. Through February 1996. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $2 for adults, $1 for children and $1.50 for the elderly. 70 Court Street, Freehold. (908) 462-1466. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Artists With Physical Disabilites" includes paintings, photography, printmaking and sculpture. Opening reception today, 3:30 to 5 P.M.; the exhibition begins Tuesday. Through Aug. 17. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College campus, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through today. "Still Life Works From the Collection" offers 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 1 P.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through next Sunday. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through next Sunday. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through next Monday. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. PALMER SQUARE, PRINCETON Strictly Art in Princeton at Palmer Square features the works of more than 75 local artists. Watercolors, pastels, oil and acrylic paintings, paper collages, sculptures, photographs and mixed-media creations will be on display and on sale. Today, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Free. Palmer Square, downtown Princeton. (908) 874-5247. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Renee Foosaner Art Gallery holds its sixth annual Juried Exhibition of Miniature Art. Through July 30. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636, extension 2272. PATERSON MUSEUM "Pencilworks: The Drawings of Jerry Winick" displays pencil drawings noted for their details and photo-like realism. Through July 9. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 12:30 to 4:30 P.M. 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 881-3874. PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The Passaic County Cultural and Heritage Council presents paintings and collages by Arnold Brown. Through July 20. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-5448. RABBET GALLERY "Five Sculptors: Clay, Wood, Metal." Through July 7. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. 120 Georges Road, New Brunswick. (908) 828-5150. RINGWOOD MANOR STATE PARK "50 Years Retrospective Art Exhibition" features the works of Arthur J. Barbour in the Barn Gallery. Through July 9. "Printmaking and Sculpture" offers the works of Barbara W. Frazier and Helene Hirmes in the West Wing Gallery. Through next Sunday. Wednesday, Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4:30 P.M., with a reception next Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Sloatsburg Road, Ringwood. (201) 962-7031. SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "New Insights -- Rising Talent," an exhibition of the work of John Bingham, glass craftsman; Andrew Braitman, painter, and Lisa Gralnick, metal- smith. Through July 8. Monday through Wednesday and Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Thursday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720. SHOE-STRING GALLERY "Presence by Absence," paintings by Peter Siegel. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. or by appointment. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Naturescape," an exhibition of paintings by Christina Allen, Sarah Antin and Guy Ciarcia. Through July 22. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592. SWAIN GALLERIES "Recent Works," oils by Brian Townsend. Through July 20. Tuesday through Friday, 9:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. 703 Watchung Avenue, Plainfield. (908) 756-1707. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER. The New Jersey Photo Forum sponsors a show photographic prints in the upstairs gallery. "Vietnam: 20 Years After the Fall" features the silkscreen photography of Richard Gerstner in the downstairs gallery. Free. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WILLIAMS GALLERY "The Changing Landscape: Contemporary Interpretations of Landscape Painting and Photography," by David Scott Leibowitz, Marlene Lenker and Rena Segal. Through July 8. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 8 Chambers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-1142. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The George Riabov Collection of Russian Art includes medieval icons, 19th-century landscapes and 20th-century costume and stage design. The Kusakabe-Griffs Japonisme Gallery showcases Western art from the late 19th and early 20th centuries, documenting the Japanese influence on Western art. Free. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. SPOKEN WORD BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE "New Jersey Politics in 1995 -- What Is Right and What Is Wrong?" with Tom Byrne, state Democratic chairman; Virginia Littell, state Republican chairwoman, and Bobbi Horowitz, president of Hands Across New Jersey. Today at 7:30 P.M. Free. Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 536-9078. REEVES-REED ARBORETUM Michael Olohan of the water resource management department of the Rutgers University Cooperative Extension Service presents "Watershed Workshop," an illustrated lecture on how individuals can improve their environment at home and in the community. Today at 3 P.M. Free. 165 Hobart Avenue, Summit. (908) 273-8787. FOR CHILDREN FLAT ROCK BROOK NATURE CENTUR "In Search of the Giant Bullfrog," a pond ecology workshop for children, invites youngsters 4 to 12 to take a closeup look at frogs, tadpoles, fish and other aquatic life. The workshop for children 6 to 12 is from 1 to 2 P.M.; children 4 to 6 attend the workshop from 2:30 to 3:30. Fee: $5, and registration is required. 443 Van Nostrand Avenue, Englewood. (201) 567-1265. MEADOWLANDS AREA The Mighty Morphin Power Rangers. Today at 1 and 4:30 P.M. Tickets: $9.50, $14, $18.50 and $30. 50 Route 120, East Rutherford. (201) 935-3900. MEADOW THEATER "Behind the Scenes" offers a hands-on tour of the theater that will allow children to try on costumes and makeup, operate sound effects and lights, and rehearse and perform a scene on stage. Today at 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. The Meadow Kids' Summer Clubhouse offers a new show every week with audience participation, songs, games, dancing, improvisations and short plays. Saturday at 11 A.M. Through Aug. 26. Tickets: $5. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M., and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Today. "The Power" and "African Skies" begin next week. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Native American Crafts" allows children ages 6 to 8 to create Indian designs on clay pitchers and in seed bead necklaces and sand paintings. Fee: $32, with all materials provided. Tuesday and Thursday, 3:30 to 5 P.M. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Gingerbread Players present "Mozart, Monsters and Matisse," a production combining puppetry and music to tell the tales of "Little Blue," "Tamino and Dorabella" and "Why the Willow Weeps." Today at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6 and $7. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. RARITAN VALLEY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The college's planetarium offers "Mystery! Who Stole the Night," a show that is part legend, fairy tale, science documentary and classic mystery yarn, for the entire family. Monday and Wednesday at 2 P.M. Through Aug. 16. Admission: $4.50. Route 28 and Lamington Road, North Branch. (908) 231-8805. WEISS ART CENTER The Summerfun Sampler Series presents Allyn Gooen, a balloon artist who offers a balloon version of "Snow White." Wednesday at 1 P.M. Tickets: $7. Lloyd Road and Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 256-0576. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC. CONGREGATION B'NAI TIKVAH It's that time of the year again: garage sale time. The public is invited to come and sift through a collection of the congregation's "treasures" and cast-offs. Today, 9 A.M. to 1 P.M. Finnegan's Lane, just west of the intersection of Route 1, North Brunswick. (98) 297-0696. COUNTY COLLEGE OF MORRIS The mini-foreign film festival concludes with "Sweetie." Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $3. Dragonetti Auditorium in the Student Center, 214 Center Grove Road, Randolph. (201) 328-5024. DINNER AND THEATER The $42 ticket price includes a four-course meal and "Deep Space Noir," an interactive and futuristic detective story. Saturdays, 8 P.M. Il Giardino Restaurant. 41 Ridgedale Avenue, Cedar Knolls. (201) 301-0562. GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER The 1995 Spring Heritage Festivals conclude with the Irish Heritage Festival today. A piping competition with 20 piping bands from the tristate area starts the day off at 9 A.M. Other activities include an Irish shopping village with sweaters, crystal, food and other imported goods. The Celtic Cross, Richie O'Shea, Willie Lynch and Mike Bryne perform in the mall at noon. Tickets: $10. Exit 16 on the Garden State Park Way, Holmdel. (908) 442-9200. GREATER NEW JERSEY STAMP EXPO A chance to learn about postal history and purchase stamps, postcards, postal supplies and other memorabilia. Today, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Admission: $2. Holiday Inn Springfield, Route 22 West, Springfield. (201) 379-3779. FLEA MARKETS The Englewood Flea Market offers food, old and new toys, clothes, crafts and a performance by the EX-ZIB-ITS Jr. Steel Band. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7:30 P.M. First and Fourth Streets parking lots, Englewood. (201) 567-5354. The Chester Lions Club Flea Market offers craft items, linens, books, children's clothing, housewares, plants and produce, makeup, jewelry, scarves, handbags and other accessories. Sundays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M, through Dec. 19. Beginning next Sunday. Free. West Blackwell Street, Morris and Sussex Streets in downtown Dover. (800) 555-6263. MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION A series of night hikes for families will have an emphasis on summer insects. "Firefly Parade," the first hike of the series, will allow participants to explore the Watershed Reserve and to observe the light show provided by several species of fireflies. Thursday, 8:30 to 10:30 P.M. Advance registration is required. Program fee: $7. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL "Exotica," July 7, and "New Jersey Media Arts Exhibition," July 8. All show times 7 P.M. Tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, Milledoler Hall, George Street and Seminary Place. (908) 932-8482. Sounds of Summer Petula Clark performs her past and present vocal hits, including "Downtown," "My Love" and "A Sign of the Times," in the ummer concert season opener.  PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Tuesday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $25 and $30. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. Spanish Dance Alan Tjaarda Jones, dancer, demonstrates "From Fencing to Fandango: Dance in Imperial Spain."  RUTGERS ARTS CENTER Saturday at 6 P.M. Free. (908) 932-7511. A Fairy Tale The Pushcart Players present "Once Upon a Time," a musical collection of children's tales with a contemporary spin for children ages 4 to 10.  MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERISTY Thursday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $7.50. Valley Road, Upper Montclair. (201) 857-1115.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSIC ALBERT MUSIC HALL The Pinelands Cultural Society presents "Sounds of the Jersey Pines," a series of Saturday night concerts through the end of the year. The program features live presentations of bluegrass, country and Pinelands music. Admission: $4, or $1 for children under 12. 139 Wells Mill Road (Route 532), Waretown. (609) 971-1593. CONGRESS HALL, CAPE MAY Christopher O'Reilly, pianist. Today at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $12, or $10 for the elderly and $6 for students. Congress Hall, Beach Drive and Perry, Cape May. (800) 275-4278. DUKE ISLAND PARK, BRIDGEWATER The Somerset County Park Commission starts its free summer concert series with a program of 60's and 70's music performed by the Sensational Soul Cruisers. Sunday at 7 P.M. (908) 722-1200, extension 221. GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER Yanni. Thursday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $22.50 to $45. Exit 116 on the Garden State Parkway, Holmdel. (908) 888-5011. GIRALDA FARMS "A Salute to the Allies" is the theme of the 12th annual Giralda Concert with the New Jersey Symphony Orchestra. Today at 6 P.M. Tickets: $8, or $3 for children under 12. Route 124, Madison. (201) 377-6622. FAIR LAWN SUMMER MUSIC FESTIVAL The 35th annual festival kicks off today at 8:30 P.M. with the Symphonic Concert Band. Next Sunday at 8:30 P.M., enjoy community dancing to the music of Tubby Tubello. Free, but bring your own chairs. Memorial Park and Berdan Avenue, Fair Lawn. (201) 796-6746. MEMORIAL PARK, MAPLEWOOD Arts Maplewood presents C. J. Chenier and the Red Hot Louisiana Band with their New Orleans zydeco music. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Free. (201) 378-2133. NEWARK MUSEUM "Noontime Jazz in the Garden" series. Thursdays at 12:30 P.M. Through Aug. 10. Free. Dreyfuss Memorial Garden, 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. OCEAN COUNTY LIBRARY The Garden State Philharmonic Orchestra and Chorus present a free concert in the courtyard celebrating American heritage by performing patriotic songs, light classics and popular tunes. Saturday at 7:30 P.M. Free, but bring your own chair. 101 Washington Street, Toms River. (908) 349-6277. OCEAN GROVE SUMMER CONCERTS The eighth annual "Great Sousa Concert" with the Allentown Band, conducted by Ronald Demkee. Tickets: $12. The Great Auditorium, Pilgrim Pathway, Ocean Grove. (908) 775-0035. PRINCETON UNIVERSITY The first annual Princeton Invitational Choir Festival concludes with a Gala Final Concert with all the participating choirs. Today at 8 P.M. Free. Richardson Auditorium of Alexander Hall, Princeton. (609) 896-9330. RAMAPO COLLEGE The Minolta Summer Music Fest presents four free Thursday night concerts spanning a spectrum of musical tastes. First up, the Hanover Wind Symphony. Thursday at 8 P.M. The Bandshell, 505 Ramapo Valley Road. Off Route 17 and 202 in Mahwah. (201) 529-7612. RUTGERS ARTS CENTER The Rutgers Summerfest continues with Marian McPartland, today at 2 P.M. Tickets: $22. Keyboard Extravaganza! Wednesday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Summerfest Chamber Players. Thursday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Red, White and Blue! with Frederick Urrey, tenor. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. Music From Aston Magna, Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $16. George Street at Route 18, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7511. TINICUM PARK, BUCKS COUNTY The Riverside Symphonia's second annual outdoor concert, on Saturday at 8 P.M., will feature a mix of light classical music and American show tunes. Tickets: $10 or $3 for children. Route 32, 10 miles north of New Hope, Pa. (215) 862-3300. VETERANS' FIELD, EDGEWATER The New Jersey Pops Symphony Orchestra, directed by Michael Buglio, performs classical works, Broadway show tunes and patriotic music. Friday at 7:30 P.M. Free. River Road, Edgewater. (201) 744-1700, extension 52. WEST SIDE PRESBYTERIAN CHURCH, RIDGEWOOD The Metisse Piano Quartet with Carol Rodland, violist; Jennifer Kloetzel, cellist; Chul-In Park, violinist, and Priya Mayadas, pianist. Today at 7 P.M. Free. 6 South Monroe Street, Ridgewood. (201) 652-1966. THEATER BECKFORD THEATER, MORRIS MUSEUM In "Love Letters," a relationship is revealed through a lifetime of correspondence. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M.; next Sunday at 2 P.M. and July 6-9. Tickets: $17.50. 6 Normandy Heights Road, Morristown. (201) 538-0454. CAPE MAY WELCOME CENTER The Cape May Stage presents "Cape May on Fire," with Eric Hissom and John Alvarez. Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8:30 P.M. Tickets: $15, or $12 for students and the elderly. 405 Lafayette Street, Cape May. (609) 884-1341. EAST LYNNE COMPANY "The Woman Question" features Susan Glaspell's "Supressed Desires," Marie Jenney Howe's "Anti-Suffrage Monologue" and George Middleton's "Unknown Lady." Today at 3 P.M. The Meadowlands Center for the Arts, Rutherford. Also, Wednesday through July 8 at 8:30 P.M. at Lyle Hall of the First Methodist Church, Cape May. Tickets: $14, or $12 for the elderly. (201) 863-6436. FOUNDATION THEATER "Nunsense." Wednesday and Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M., Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 2 and 8 P.M. Through July 9. Tickets: $15, or $13 for students and the elderly. Burlington County College. Route 530, Pemberton. (609) 894-2138. GUGGENHEIM SUMMER THEATER "I Hate Hamlet." Thursday through Saturday at 8:30 P.M. and next Sunday at 7:30 P.M. Through July 9. Tickets: $17. Monmouth University, West Long Branch. (908) 571-3475. McCARTER THEATER "Family Secrets," with Sherry Glaser. Monday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20 to $30. A solo piano concert with George Winston. Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $22 to $32. Sweet Honey in the Rock, a tradional African-American congregational choral quintet, performs Saturday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $17 to $27. 91 University Place, Princeton. (609) 683-8000. NEW JERSEY SHAKESPEARE FESTIVAL Harold Pinter's "Homecoming." Today at 2 and 7 P.M., Tuesday at 8 P.M., Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M., Thursday and Friday at 8 P.M. and Saturday at 2 and 8 P.M. "Julius Caesar" begins July 5. Tickets: $16 to $30. Bowne Theater, Drew University, 36 Madison Avenue, Madison. (201) 408-5600. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE "The Secret Garden," a musical by Marsha Norman and Lucy Simon, based on the novel by Frances Hodgson Burnett. Wednesday and Friday at 8 P.M., Thursday at 2 and 8 P.M. and Saturday and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 23. Tickets: $29 to $44. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. ROOSEVELT PARK AMPHITHEATER The Middlesex County Department of Parks and Recreation presents Plays-in-the-Park 1995. "Into the Woods." Wednesday through Saturday at 8:30 P.M. "The Sound of Music" begins on July 12. Tickets: $3. Edison. (609) 548-2884. THEATERFEST "Lost in Yonkers," with Doris Belack. Today at 2 and 8 P.M. "On Golden Pond." Wednesday at 2 and 8 P.M.; Thursday, Friday and Saturday at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 3 and 8 P.M. Through July 9. Montclair State University, Valley Road and Normal Avenue, Upper Montclair. (201) 655-5112. MUSEUMS AND GALLERIES ART MUSEUM, PRINCETON UNIVERSITY "Collaborative Landscape Photographs by Laura McPhee, Class of 1980, and Virginia Beahan," an exhibition of 20 color photographs, opens Thursday. Through Aug. 20. Free. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Princeton. (609) 258-3788. BERGEN MUSEUM OF ART AND SCIENCE "Edward Walsh Sculpture," nine abstract and traditional sculptures created from stainless steel, granite and bronze. Through July 16. "John Schettino: Drawings and Paintings," through July 30. "Photographic Drawings" by David Horton. Through July 30. Tuesday through Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Suggested admission: adults, $2.50; children, $1. 327 East Ridgewood Avenue, Paramus. (201) 265-1248. BERLEX LABORATORIES GALLERY "Moments in Time," original photographs by Janet Engeman and Dwight Hiscano. Monday and Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Tuesday through Thursday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 to 5 P.M. Through Aug. 10. 300 Fairfield Road, Wayne. (201) 540-1195. BLACKWELL STREET CENTER FOR THE ARTS "Summer Daze," an exhibition of works by all members of the center. Through Aug. 20. Thursday through Sunday, noon to 4 P.M. 32-34 West Blackwell Street, Dover. (201) 328-9628. COOPER GALLERY "Tangible Insites," textural paintings and clay vessels by Susan Hogan. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 7 P.M. 295 Grove Street, Jersey City. (201) 451-1074. CORYELL GALLERY Oil paintings by Albert Bross, watercolors and acrylics by Vincent Ceglia and watercolors by Charles Ross. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Through July 5. 8 Coryell Street, Lambertville. (609) 397-0804. CS SCHULTE GALLERIES "Duet: Dan Christensen -- 30 Years of Paintings; Elaine Grove -- Recent Sculpture." Through July 14. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. 340 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 376-6900. EVERHART GALLERY Abstract paintings by Jim Fuess. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 6 P.M. Through July 12. 117 South Maple Avenue, Basking Ridge. (908) 221-9007. EXTENSION GALLERY "Hug the Noise," an exhibition of cast metal sculpture and drawings by Sean Poreda. Monday through Thursday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 60 Ward Avenue Extension, Mercerville. (609) 890-7777. GALLERY JUPITER "Recent Works," paintings by Evelyn Leavens. Monday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 25 Church Street, Little Silver. (908) 530-8035. GALLERY OF SOUTH ORANGE "Displacement," a collage by Peter Jacobs, and "Home," a collage in mixed media by Valerie Sivilli, are on display. Today, 1 to 4 P.M. Baird Community Center, 5 Mead Street, off Ridgewood Road, South Orange. (201) 378-7754. GALLERY AT GENERAL PUBLIC UTILITIES Color photographs by H. Lisa Solon and sculptures and paintings by David A. Angelini. Opens Saturday. Through July 30. Free. Monday through Friday, 8:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 100 Interpace Parkway, Parsippany. (201) 263-6684. GUILD OF CREATIVE ART "Rhythms of Nature," a collection of landscapes, watercolors, pastels and collages by Fran McIlvain. Through July 6. Tuesday through Saturday, noon to 4:30 P.M. 620 Broad Street, Route 35, Shrewsbury. (908) 741-1441. HOUSE OF BRATA ART GALLERY "So Big, So Little," five paintings by John Krushenick. Through Saturday. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 3 P.M. 46A Fairfield Street, Montclair. (201) 783-7348. HUNTERDON ART CENTER A faculty exhibition of painting, sculpture and mixed-media collages; "Sculpture and Collage," assemblage sculptures and photo collages by Carol Rosen. Today, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 7 Lower Center Street, Clinton. (908) 735-8415. JAZZ 88 GALLERY Paintings and collages by Amy Kool and photographs by Cynthia Carris with text by Jose Luis Alonso. Monday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Through July 23. 54 Park Place, Newark. (201) 624-8880. JERSEY CITY MUSEUM "Albizu Lives," a visual commemoration. Through Sept. 16. "The Nation Is Its People: Body and Soul of Lolita Lebron." Through Aug. 18. "Joan Fine: Wall Reliefs." Through Aug. 18. Tuesday, Thursday, Friday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Wednesday, 10:30 A.M. to 8 P.M. 472 Jersey Avenue, Jersey City. (201) 547-4514. LEBANON MUSEUM "Details," color photographs by H. Lisa Solon. Tuesday and Thursday, 9:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. 57 Muscanetcong River Road, Hampton. (908) 537-6464. LONG BEACH ISLAND FOUNDATION OF ARTS AND SCIENCE "Choice Collection -- Crafts 1995," an exhibition and sale, and "LBI Art Foundation Faculty Exhibition." Monday and Tuesday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M., 120 Long Beach Blvd., Loveladies. (609) 494-3169. MEADOWLANDS CENTER FOR THE ARTS "From Darkness Into Light," paintings and drawings by Howard Lerner, through Friday. "Images, Dreams, Words and Marks," a solo show of paintings and drawings by Lisa Pressman, starts Saturday. Through Aug. 4. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 6 P.M., and Saturday and Sunday, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. 1 Williams Plaza, Rutherford. (201) 939-6969. MONMOUTH COUNTY HISTORICAL ASSOCIATION MUSEUM AND LIBRARY "Optical Delights: Stereographic Views of Monmouth County" presents images of Victorian life. Starts Tuesday. Through February 1996. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 4 P.M. Admission: $2 for adults, $1 for children and $1.50 for the elderly. 70 Court Street, Freehold. (908) 462-1466. MONMOUTH MUSEUM "Artists With Physical Disabilites" includes paintings, photography, printmaking and sculpture. Opening reception today, 3:30 to 5 P.M.; the exhibition begins Tuesday. Through Aug. 17. Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M., and Sunday, 1 to 5 P.M. Brookdale Community College campus, Lincroft. (908) 747-2266. MONTCLAIR ART MUSEUM "What Is a Print?" features the works of 60 artists and demonstrates the wide range of prints produced in America over the last 150 years. Through today. "Still Life Works From the Collection" offers 13 paintings by American artists ranging in style from 19th-century realism to 20th-century modernism. Through September. Tuesday, Wednesday, Friday and Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Sunday and Thursday, 1 P.M. to 5 P.M. Admission: $4, or $3 for the elderly and students with ID. 3 South Mountain Avenue, Montclair. (201) 746-5555. NEWARK MUSEUM "Gods and Goddesses in Indian Art" features paintings, cloth hangings and tiny brass icons dating from the 11th to 19th centuries. Through next Sunday. "The Arts of Nepal" includes sculptures and paintings of the Himalayan kingdom. Through next Sunday. "Astronauts: The Star Travelers" features photographs of the Apollo XI flight. Through Dec. 31. Wednesday through Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEWARK PUBLIC LIBRARY "Lasting Impressions: The Jewish Legacy of Greater Newark" showcases the development of neighborhoods and culture in Newark by Jewish residents. Through next Monday. Monday, Friday and Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5:30 P.M.; Tuesday, Wednesday and Thursday, 9 A.M. to 8:30 P.M. 5 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 733-7798. NEW JERSEY HISTORICAL SOCIETY "Moving Through Memory: Caribbean Folk Arts in New Jersey." Through April 1996. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. 230 Broadway, Newark. (201) 483-3939. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM "Echizen: 800 Years of Japanese Stoneware," an exhibition celebrating the history and art of potters. Through Aug. 7. "Baseball in New Jersey: The Game of History." Through Aug. 27. Tuesday through Saturday, 9 A.M. to 4:45 P.M., and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. NOYES MUSEUM "Looking Due South: Paintings of South Jersey by Glenn Rudderow." Through July 9. Wednesday through Sunday, 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission, $3; the elderly, $1.50; students and children under 18, 50 cents. Free admission on Fridays. Lily Lake Road, Oceanville. (609) 652-8848. PALMER SQUARE, PRINCETON Strictly Art in Princeton at Palmer Square features the works of more than 75 local artists. Watercolors, pastels, oil and acrylic paintings, paper collages, sculptures, photographs and mixed-media creations will be on display and on sale. Today, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Free. Palmer Square, downtown Princeton. (908) 874-5247. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Renee Foosaner Art Gallery holds its sixth annual Juried Exhibition of Miniature Art. Through July 30. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 379-3636, extension 2272. PATERSON MUSEUM "Pencilworks: The Drawings of Jerry Winick" displays pencil drawings noted for their details and photo-like realism. Through July 9. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, 12:30 to 4:30 P.M. 2 Market Street, Paterson. (201) 881-3874. PASSAIC COUNTY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The Passaic County Cultural and Heritage Council presents paintings and collages by Arnold Brown. Through July 20. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 9 P.M.; Saturday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Broadway and Memorial Drive, Paterson. (201) 684-5448. RABBET GALLERY "Five Sculptors: Clay, Wood, Metal." Through July 7. Monday through Friday, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. 120 Georges Road, New Brunswick. (908) 828-5150. RINGWOOD MANOR STATE PARK "50 Years Retrospective Art Exhibition" features the works of Arthur J. Barbour in the Barn Gallery. Through July 9. "Printmaking and Sculpture" offers the works of Barbara W. Frazier and Helene Hirmes in the West Wing Gallery. Through next Sunday. Wednesday, Saturday and Sunday, 1 to 4:30 P.M., with a reception next Sunday, 2 to 4 P.M. Sloatsburg Road, Ringwood. (201) 962-7031. SHEILA NUSSBAUM GALLERY "New Insights -- Rising Talent," an exhibition of the work of John Bingham, glass craftsman; Andrew Braitman, painter, and Lisa Gralnick, metal- smith. Through July 8. Monday through Wednesday and Friday and Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., and Thursday, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M. 341 Millburn Avenue, Millburn. (201) 467-1720. SHOE-STRING GALLERY "Presence by Absence," paintings by Peter Siegel. Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. or by appointment. 111 First Street, Jersey City. (201) 420-5018. STONY BROOK-MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION "Naturescape," an exhibition of paintings by Christina Allen, Sarah Antin and Guy Ciarcia. Through July 22. Wednesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; Saturday, 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592. SWAIN GALLERIES "Recent Works," oils by Brian Townsend. Through July 20. Tuesday through Friday, 9:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M., and Saturday, 9:30 A.M. to 4 P.M. 703 Watchung Avenue, Plainfield. (908) 756-1707. WATCHUNG ARTS CENTER. The New Jersey Photo Forum sponsors a show photographic prints in the upstairs gallery. "Vietnam: 20 Years After the Fall" features the silkscreen photography of Richard Gerstner in the downstairs gallery. Free. Monday through Saturday, 1 to 4 P.M. 18 Stirling Road, Watchung. (908) 753-0190. WILLIAMS GALLERY "The Changing Landscape: Contemporary Interpretations of Landscape Painting and Photography," by David Scott Leibowitz, Marlene Lenker and Rena Segal. Through July 8. Tuesday through Saturday, 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. 8 Chambers Street, Princeton. (609) 921-1142. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The George Riabov Collection of Russian Art includes medieval icons, 19th-century landscapes and 20th-century costume and stage design. The Kusakabe-Griffs Japonisme Gallery showcases Western art from the late 19th and early 20th centuries, documenting the Japanese influence on Western art. Free. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. SPOKEN WORD BROOKDALE COMMUNITY COLLEGE "New Jersey Politics in 1995 -- What Is Right and What Is Wrong?" with Tom Byrne, state Democratic chairman; Virginia Littell, state Republican chairwoman, and Bobbi Horowitz, president of Hands Across New Jersey. Today at 7:30 P.M. Free. Newman Springs Road, Lincroft. (908) 536-9078. REEVES-REED ARBORETUM Michael Olohan of the water resource management department of the Rutgers University Cooperative Extension Service presents "Watershed Workshop," an illustrated lecture on how individuals can improve their environment at home and in the community. Today at 3 P.M. Free. 165 Hobart Avenue, Summit. (908) 273-8787. FOR CHILDREN FLAT ROCK BROOK NATURE CENTUR "In Search of the Giant Bullfrog," a pond ecology workshop for children, invites youngsters 4 to 12 to take a closeup look at frogs, tadpoles, fish and other aquatic life. The workshop for children 6 to 12 is from 1 to 2 P.M.; children 4 to 6 attend the workshop from 2:30 to 3:30. Fee: $5, and registration is required. 443 Van Nostrand Avenue, Englewood. (201) 567-1265. MEADOWLANDS AREA The Mighty Morphin Power Rangers. Today at 1 and 4:30 P.M. Tickets: $9.50, $14, $18.50 and $30. 50 Route 120, East Rutherford. (201) 935-3900. MEADOW THEATER "Behind the Scenes" offers a hands-on tour of the theater that will allow children to try on costumes and makeup, operate sound effects and lights, and rehearse and perform a scene on stage. Today at 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. The Meadow Kids' Summer Clubhouse offers a new show every week with audience participation, songs, games, dancing, improvisations and short plays. Saturday at 11 A.M. Through Aug. 26. Tickets: $5. Galleria Atrium, Bridge Avenue and West Front, Red Bank. (908) 758-0099. NEWARK MUSEUM "Cosmic Questions," for ages 6 to 10, at 1 and 3 P.M., and "Journey Through Time and Space," for ages 9 and older, at 2 and 4 P.M. Today. "The Power" and "African Skies" begin next week. Adults, $2; children under 12, $1. 49 Washington Street, Newark. (201) 596-6550. NEW JERSEY CENTER FOR VISUAL ARTS "Native American Crafts" allows children ages 6 to 8 to create Indian designs on clay pitchers and in seed bead necklaces and sand paintings. Fee: $32, with all materials provided. Tuesday and Thursday, 3:30 to 5 P.M. 68 Elm Street, Summit. (908) 273-9121. NEW JERSEY STATE MUSEUM Take a simulated flight down the 3,000-mile-long Martian Grand Canyon in "Fantastic Sky." Saturday and Sunday at 1 and 3 P.M. Learn about the greenhouse effect and holes in the ozone layer in "Spaceship Earth." Saturday and Sunday at 2 P.M. Through next Sunday. Tickets: $1. 205 West State Street, Trenton. (609) 292-6308. PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE The Gingerbread Players present "Mozart, Monsters and Matisse," a production combining puppetry and music to tell the tales of "Little Blue," "Tamino and Dorabella" and "Why the Willow Weeps." Today at 11 A.M. Tickets: $6 and $7. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. RARITAN VALLEY COMMUNITY COLLEGE The college's planetarium offers "Mystery! Who Stole the Night," a show that is part legend, fairy tale, science documentary and classic mystery yarn, for the entire family. Monday and Wednesday at 2 P.M. Through Aug. 16. Admission: $4.50. Route 28 and Lamington Road, North Branch. (908) 231-8805. WEISS ART CENTER The Summerfun Sampler Series presents Allyn Gooen, a balloon artist who offers a balloon version of "Snow White." Wednesday at 1 P.M. Tickets: $7. Lloyd Road and Bloomfield Avenue, Montclair. (201) 256-0576. ZIMMERLI ART MUSEUM The Rutgers Collection of Original Illustrations for Children's Literature: "Riders Up! Preparing for a Pony Race," an exhibition of photographs and other materials by Barbara Beirne for her book about a young girl and her pony as they prepare for their first race. Through July 31. Tuesday through Friday, 10 A.M. to 4:30 P.M.; Saturday and Sunday, noon to 5 P.M. Free. Rutgers, corner of George and Hamilton Streets, New Brunswick. (908) 932-7237. ETC. CONGREGATION B'NAI TIKVAH It's that time of the year again: garage sale time. The public is invited to come and sift through a collection of the congregation's "treasures" and cast-offs. Today, 9 A.M. to 1 P.M. Finnegan's Lane, just west of the intersection of Route 1, North Brunswick. (98) 297-0696. COUNTY COLLEGE OF MORRIS The mini-foreign film festival concludes with "Sweetie." Friday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $3. Dragonetti Auditorium in the Student Center, 214 Center Grove Road, Randolph. (201) 328-5024. DINNER AND THEATER The $42 ticket price includes a four-course meal and "Deep Space Noir," an interactive and futuristic detective story. Saturdays, 8 P.M. Il Giardino Restaurant. 41 Ridgedale Avenue, Cedar Knolls. (201) 301-0562. GARDEN STATE ARTS CENTER The 1995 Spring Heritage Festivals conclude with the Irish Heritage Festival today. A piping competition with 20 piping bands from the tristate area starts the day off at 9 A.M. Other activities include an Irish shopping village with sweaters, crystal, food and other imported goods. The Celtic Cross, Richie O'Shea, Willie Lynch and Mike Bryne perform in the mall at noon. Tickets: $10. Exit 16 on the Garden State Park Way, Holmdel. (908) 442-9200. GREATER NEW JERSEY STAMP EXPO A chance to learn about postal history and purchase stamps, postcards, postal supplies and other memorabilia. Today, 10 A.M. to 6 P.M. Admission: $2. Holiday Inn Springfield, Route 22 West, Springfield. (201) 379-3779. FLEA MARKETS The Englewood Flea Market offers food, old and new toys, clothes, crafts and a performance by the EX-ZIB-ITS Jr. Steel Band. Saturday, 10 A.M. to 7:30 P.M. First and Fourth Streets parking lots, Englewood. (201) 567-5354. The Chester Lions Club Flea Market offers craft items, linens, books, children's clothing, housewares, plants and produce, makeup, jewelry, scarves, handbags and other accessories. Sundays, 9 A.M. to 5 P.M, through Dec. 19. Beginning next Sunday. Free. West Blackwell Street, Morris and Sussex Streets in downtown Dover. (800) 555-6263. MILLSTONE WATERSHED ASSOCIATION A series of night hikes for families will have an emphasis on summer insects. "Firefly Parade," the first hike of the series, will allow participants to explore the Watershed Reserve and to observe the light show provided by several species of fireflies. Thursday, 8:30 to 10:30 P.M. Advance registration is required. Program fee: $7. Titus Mill Road, Hopewell Township. (609) 737-7592. NEW JERSEY FILM FESTIVAL "Exotica," July 7, and "New Jersey Media Arts Exhibition," July 8. All show times 7 P.M. Tickets: $4. Rutgers University in New Brunswick, College Avenue campus, Milledoler Hall, George Street and Seminary Place. (908) 932-8482. Sounds of Summer Petula Clark performs her past and present vocal hits, including "Downtown," "My Love" and "A Sign of the Times," in the ummer concert season opener.  PAPER MILL PLAYHOUSE Tuesday at 8 P.M. Tickets: $25 and $30. Brookside Drive, Millburn. (201) 376-4343. Spanish Dance Alan Tjaarda Jones, dancer, demonstrates "From Fencing to Fandango: Dance in Imperial Spain."  RUTGERS ARTS CENTER Saturday at 6 P.M. Free. (908) 932-7511. A Fairy Tale The Pushcart Players present "Once Upon a Time," a musical collection of children's tales with a contemporary spin for children ages 4 to 10.  MONTCLAIR STATE UNIVERISTY Thursday at 11 A.M. Tickets: $7.50. Valley Road, Upper Montclair. (201) 857-1115.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
