<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>25-Year Checkup Shows Gains in Air Quality but a Decline in TrashDisposal</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="813472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATERPOLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON MONOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SULFUR DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEAD</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURAL RESOURCES DEFENSE COUNCIL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, DENNIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lead</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DA1E39F936A35751C1A963958260" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>25-Year Checkup Shows Gains in Air Quality but a Decline in TrashDisposal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEVESI, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 25 years, New York City has made significant gains in improving its air quality and the cleanliness of its waterways, but the quality of its drinking water has slipped, and disposing of the city's garbage is a persistent problem,  according to a report by a leading environmental advocacy group.</p>
        <p>The report by the Natural Resources Defense Council, "New York City's Environmental Vital Signs: A 25-Year Checkup," compiled findings from 75 governmental and independent studies to paint a broad picture of the city's environment since the first Earth Day, in April 1970.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 25 years, New York City has made significant gains in improving its air quality and the cleanliness of its waterways, but the quality of its drinking water has slipped, and disposing of the city's garbage is a persistent problem,  according to a report by a leading environmental advocacy group.</p>
        <p>The report by the Natural Resources Defense Council, "New York City's Environmental Vital Signs: A 25-Year Checkup," compiled findings from 75 governmental and independent studies to paint a broad picture of the city's environment since the first Earth Day, in April 1970.</p>
        <p>It's safe to say that since 1970, there has been gradual improvement," said Eric A. Goldstein, director of the council's urban project. "But that's different from saying that comprehensive environmental health protections are in place or that the city's ecology is in balance."</p>
        <p>The report, written by Mr. Goldstein and Mark Izeman, a lawyer with the council, found that while air and waterway quality have generally improved, progress has been little or nil in other major areas. It said, for example, that although all but one of the city's nine landfills operating in 1970 have been closed, the amount of garbage generated by New Yorkers has increased and recycling efforts have had only moderate success.</p>
        <p>The amount of sewage flowing into the city's waterways has been sharply reduced, the report also said, but toxic pollutants from past industrial discharges are a lingering problem. And local problems -- like the proliferation of industrial pollution in the Brooklyn neighborhoods of Williamsburg and Greenpoint -- persist. Lead poisoning of children, particularly in the poorest communities, remains one of the city's "most pressing" health threats.</p>
        <p>The city's Commissioner of Environmental Protection, Marilyn Gelber, called the report "a fair assessment of the environmental protection progress that we've made."</p>
        <p>"In particular," she said, "it highlights the importance of the Federal role  in regulating and funding these efforts because clean air and clean water have nothing to do with political boundaries."</p>
        <p>The report said that in the area of air quality, lead levels in the region have fallen by 95 percent since 1970, and "levels of carbon monoxide have declined from more than two and a half times national health standards in the early 1970's to just below the standard itself today." The levels of sulfur dioxide, which is considered a major cause of acid rain, have also declined significantly since 1970, the report said.</p>
        <p>Still, "it goes too far" to suggest that the city's air quality problems have been solved, the report continued. Smog and particulate matter, especially from  diesel trucks and buses, remain problems.</p>
        <p>The quality of the city's waterways has also shown some improvement since 1970, the report said. The number of beaches open during the summer has increased, and the destruction of valuable wetlands has been slowed.</p>
        <p>Only 10 years ago, at least 200 million gallons of raw sewage were discharged daily into the city's waterways. The opening of major sewage treatment plants on the Hudson River in Harlem and in Red Hook, Brooklyn, "largely stemmed these raw sewage discharges," the report said.</p>
        <p>"Despite such improvements, significant sewage-related pollution persists in  certain sections of the city," the report said. "The primary culprit is the discharge of raw sewage during wet weather periods, a result of the city's combined sewage pipes, which carry both stormwater and wastewater." And certain  waterways, like the Gowanus Canal in Brooklyn, still have significant pollution.</p>
        <p>New York City's drinking water is also considered safe, though the report said that "New York can no longer accurately boast that it has the most pristine drinking-water supply in the nation."</p>
        <p>Although the upstate reservoirs are generally free of toxic contaminants and  heavy metals, data from the city's Department of Environmental Protection indicate that 13 of the 19 reservoirs are eutrophic -- a condition that results  in algae blooms and diminished water clarity.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Gelber said the recently concluded agreement between the city, the state and eight upstate counties in the watershed would bring a new level of protection to the city's supply of drinking water. But, she added, "while it is  a solid foundation for the future, it is not meant to be the last step."</p>
        <p>About solid waste, the report noted that poorly controlled incinerators have  been shut and several problem-plagued landfills have been closed.</p>
        <p>"To be sure, the city remains overly dependent on the Fresh Kills landfill in Staten Island," the report said.</p>
        <p>As late as 1980, the report said, less than 1 percent of the city's residential trash was recycled. A shift occurred after 1989, when the City Council passed a mandatory recycling law. By 1993, recycling reached 15 percent, though it slipped to 13.5 percent in mid-1995.</p>
        <p>The report also expressed concern about hazardous waste sites. The State Department of Environmental Conservation lists 26 such sites in New York City on its 1995 Superfund registry. Of those, 19 are designated as posing "a significant threat to the public health or environment."</p>
        <p>Constantine Sidamon-Eristoff, who served as regional administrator for the Federal Environmental Protection Agency from 1989 to 1993, said the assessment by the council is "really very thoughtful and very well done."</p>
        <p>"To me," he added, "emphasis should be on the fact that we have come a long way and have a long way to go."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
