<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Taking Cautious Approach in Talks on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="08CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="894395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations (Un)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE7DC123FF93BA35751C1A960958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Taking Cautious Approach in Talks on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration takes cautious approach toward negotiations on new measures to head off global warming; US will argue in statement to be delivered at United Nations meeting in Geneva that it would be unrealistic to set new deadlines for reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases before the year 2010 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration is taking a cautious approach toward negotiations this coming week on new measures to head off global warming due to air pollution.</p>
        <p>In a statement to be delivered to other delegates at a United Nations meeting starting Monday in Geneva, American officials will argue that it would be unrealistic to set new deadlines for reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases before the year 2010. And it is too early in the negotiations to specify how big any such reductions should be, they said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration is taking a cautious approach toward negotiations this coming week on new measures to head off global warming due to air pollution.</p>
        <p>In a statement to be delivered to other delegates at a United Nations meeting starting Monday in Geneva, American officials will argue that it would be unrealistic to set new deadlines for reducing emissions of so-called greenhouse gases before the year 2010. And it is too early in the negotiations to specify how big any such reductions should be, they said.</p>
        <p>The United States, like other industrial countries, is already experiencing difficulties reducing its own emissions of carbon dioxide from burning fossil fuels. It will be very complicated persuading 153 nations to agree on how strict any new controls should be and on how they should be put into force.</p>
        <p>The countries that signed the original climate-change treaty at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janiero in 1992 have since concluded that it ought to be strengthened. The original treaty called for industrial nations, as a first step, to aim at reducing their greenhouse gas emissions by the year 2000 to the levels of 1990. But that goal was not binding, and few nations have met it.</p>
        <p>So the treaty partners are now trying to agree on expanded measures to control the growth of greenhouse gas emissions well beyond the turn of the century. The talks are aimed at reaching agreement at a meeting late next year in Japan.</p>
        <p>The Administration has been arguing that the new agreement should impose binding, medium-term targets for reducing emissions to levels that are realistic and achievable, while requiring developing countries, not just industrial nations, to control their greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>At a briefing for reporters, a State Department negotiator said that in the Geneva meetings the United States would oppose suggestions by some countries that the next set of targets take effect as early as 2005. She added that the United States also opposes requiring all nations to adopt common policies, like uniform taxes on energy, and instead wants to provide flexibility to each nation.</p>
        <p>The United States is urging the United Nation negotiating committee in Geneva to develop a plan that would allow some countries to pay others to make reductions on their behalf, since controlling pollution is cheaper in some places than in others and since from the planet's point of view it makes no difference where carbon dioxide comes from.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists said they are disappointed with the Administration's approach.</p>
        <p>''The proposal would delay the beginning of any legal requirements to reduce greenhouse pollution until at least 2010, and even then emissions could be 'borrowed' from the period after 2020,'' the Natural Resources Defense Council said in a statement.</p>
        <p>''Rather than detailing commitments to protect our children, the staff paper proposes literally borrowing pollution allowances from our children and thereby putting the burden on them,'' said Dan Lashof of the environmental group.</p>
        <p>But an industry coalition opposed to a binding treaty said it was pleased that the Administration ''highlighted the growing attention to the economic costs'' of measures to fight global warming.</p>
        <p>''It is encouraging that the Administration apparently shares our concerns regarding impacts on the U.S. economy from poorly developed or premature policies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions,'' John Shlaes, executive director of the Global Climate Coalition, said in a statement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
