<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Let Nature Rule Worries Investors and Homeowners</title>
    <meta content="24SHOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Drawing Lines in the Shore's Sand" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="885312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Drawing Lines in the Shore's Sand"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Erosion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sand and Gravel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E0D91330F937A15753C1A960958260" item-length="1421" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Let Nature Rule Worries Investors and Homeowners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>HARVEY CEDARS, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses controversy over report by scientists at Rutgers University that calls for major shift in battle against beach erosion in New Jersey; study calls for shift from defending and rebuilding coastal beaches and property in high-hazard areas to removing store-damaged buildings in those places and letting nature reclaim beach; opposition to plan from environmentalists, businessmen and politicians discussed; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Picture this scenario of life along the New Jersey coast in 50 years: The Atlantic Ocean is about eight inches higher than it is now and several yards farther inland. The storms that batter the shoreline are far more destructive. And houses now on the most vulnerable parts of the coast are flooded.</p>
        <p>That is the scenario that coastal scientists at Rutgers University projected in a report for the state, paid for with $200,000 in Federal money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Picture this scenario of life along the New Jersey coast in 50 years: The Atlantic Ocean is about eight inches higher than it is now and several yards farther inland. The storms that batter the shoreline are far more destructive. And houses now on the most vulnerable parts of the coast are flooded.</p>
        <p>That is the scenario that coastal scientists at Rutgers University projected in a report for the state, paid for with $200,000 in Federal money.</p>
        <p>The scientists draw what some call a radical conclusion, at least for New Jersey: let nature take its course.</p>
        <p>The report, which was released this fall, calls for a major shift in policy, from defending and rebuilding coastal beaches and property in high-hazard areas to removing storm-damaged buildings in those places and letting nature reclaim the beach.  Although aligned with Federal thinking prompted by the devastating Mississippi River flooding in 1993, that philosophy has been considered heresy along the shore.</p>
        <p>The study has touched off angry resolutions in town halls and in the State Legislature. Businessmen and politicians shudder at the thought of eroded beaches exposing billions of dollars in ocean-front investment -- from the gaudiest Atlantic City casinos to the tiniest beach bungalows -- to the wrath of the sea. They denounce the draft as suicidal strategy: abandonment of the shore and a ''blueprint for dismantling the great heritage'' of shore resorts.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists say that with the sea level rising, the impact of coastal storms will worsen by 2050, and oft-damaged buildings and roads should be sacrificed to nature both to improve personal safety and to reduce costs.</p>
        <p>In the uproar, the state's Department of Environmental Protection has for now scrapped public meetings on the draft report. It stresses that the draft is only a possible ingredient in their revision of the state's 1981 coastal policy.</p>
        <p>To environmentalists, the agency seems to be backpedaling. The findings in the report, by Norbert Psuty, director of the Institute of Marine and Coastal Sciences at Rutgers University, are not too far afield of goals the department outlined months ago. They include encouraging shore towns not to zone vulnerable areas for development and to consider carefully whether to rebuild structures destroyed by storms.</p>
        <p>Since the 1993 Mississippi floods, the Federal Government has promoted the idea of abandoning property. In an attempt to save millions in future Federal flood insurance payouts and disaster relief costs, the Federal Emergency Management Agency has spent $192 million, primarily in the Midwest, to buy thousands of homes and build new ones for storm victims on higher, safer ground, among other measures.</p>
        <p>Since 1978, 75 percent of the Federal flood insurance paid in New Jersey, $268 million of $360 million, has gone to property owners in the state's four coastal counties -- Monmouth, Ocean, Atlantic and Cape May -- most in towns along the Atlantic or on major bays. In Monmouth County alone, the Army Corps of Engineers is restoring 21 miles of beach at a cost of $226 million.</p>
        <p>A year ago, New Jersey created a buyout program like the Federal Government's. With $30 million in voter-approved bonds, the program, Blue Acres, is intended to buy flood-prone property or storm-damaged homes along the coast or in the flood plains of the Passaic River and its tributaries in three northern counties. The land would then be dedicated to conservation or recreation.</p>
        <p>Although the start-up money is modest and there have yet to be any transactions, the program is significant because it is the first buyout plan the state's environmental department has endorsed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Psuty's report also urges buying out property owners. His report's basic premise is that the sea level is rising about 16 inches a century. He contends that broadening beaches by pumping sand from the ocean bottom and rebuilding dunes will not provide adequate protection against intense storms in high-hazard areas.</p>
        <p>Because of the rising sea level, he said, storms like the worst ones of the last half century would produce surges at least a foot higher by 2050.  ''Water will reach into places it never reached before,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He proposes that planning in high-hazard areas include buying damaged property, moving residents out, banning new development, relocating roads, sewer lines and other components of the infrastructure, and ending beach-rebuilding projects in areas with high rates of erosion.</p>
        <p>Although the report does not pinpoint any high-hazard areas, Dr. Psuty noted that the Corps of Engineers found in 1971 that 82 percent of the 127-mile shoreline was experiencing critical erosion, 9 percent was eroding but not critically, and 9 percent was stable. Monmouth and Ocean counties have been particularly prone to storm damage.</p>
        <p>North Carolina has already adopted the kinds of regulations Dr. Psuty is proposing for New Jersey, including a 10-year-old regulation limiting reconstruction of storm-damaged coastal homes. Under the regulation, up to 800 beach houses heavily damaged by Hurricane Fran on Sept. 5 may not be able to be rebuilt.</p>
        <p>The Jersey Shore Partnership, which includes local government officials, banks and utility companies, is leading the protest against Dr. Psuty. It has condemned the draft as ''sky is falling'' philosophy and urges rejecting the idea of not rebuilding eroded beaches.</p>
        <p>''We just can't walk away,'' said S. Thomas Gagliano, a former state senator who helped form the partnership and now heads it. ''And we can't send out alarms to banks and insurance and investment companies that the shore is a high-hazard area and don't come here. We don't want to frighten people or infringe on property rights or make beachgoers feel unsafe. Rutgers's attitude is we must retreat and having beachfront property is a liability and you ought to move away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gagliano said that the report ignored quality-of-life issues and overemphasized the rising sea level. ''I don't know if that's really important to generations of people,'' he said. ''It's only inches in a century.''</p>
        <p>The partnership, he said, endorses the Blue Acres program, and agrees that owners of repeatedly damaged buildings should have the option of selling to the state. But the partnership, he said, wants individual properties pinpointed for buyouts, while the report sends out signals about a broader ''attitude against rebuilding.''</p>
        <p>In Harvey Cedars, a sliver of a resort on Long Beach Island, squeezed between the ocean and Barnegat Bay, some owners say they are not averse to selling storm-damaged homes if they can recover their investments. But Fred Rice, part owner of the Harvey Cedars Marina, said the Rutgers report was a ''little late,'' given the billions invested in the shore decades ago.</p>
        <p>The value of property here far exceeds that in the Mississippi flood plains, with many tiny lots starting at $400,000, Mr. Rice said. ''How are they going to pay market value for that?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Psuty called talk about ''retreat'' an overreaction. ''I never used the word,'' he said. He said his critics were thinking only of economics, development and property taxes, and ignoring reality.</p>
        <p>''The hazards are going to increase,'' he said. ''I don't know how you can turn your back on that. You have to come up with alternatives.''</p>
        <p>One shore community, Belmar, has done just that. After repeated poundings by hurricanes over the years, the town has responded by moving public structures out of harm's way: the southern quarter-mile of its frequently damaged 1.25-mile boardwalk can be dismantled as storms approach, and newly built bathhouses can be unhooked from sewer lines and wheeled away.</p>
        <p>Mayor Kenneth Pringle of Belmar has parted company with some of his counterparts. He said that nonshore taxpayers were wearying of Federal spending to rebuild beaches and provide disaster relief for owners of damaged shore property.</p>
        <p>''If someone wants to throw their money away, that's their prerogative,'' Mayor Pringle said. ''But I don't know if we should subsidize expenditures close to the shore and automatically bail them out if they make a bad bet.''</p>
        <p>Drawing Lines in the Shore's Sand</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
