<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Charities Debate Tactic To Limit Gifts' Life Span</title>
    <meta content="19CONT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="896487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tollerson, Ernest</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E5DB1731F93AA25751C1A960958260" item-length="1275" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Charities Debate Tactic To Limit Gifts' Life Span</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERNEST TOLLERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tollerson, Ernest</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses debate over tactic used by charities to limit life span of charitable gift; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When 1996 dies at midnight on Dec. 31, so will New York's Aaron Diamond Foundation -- on schedule and in keeping with its strategy for using up its more than $200 million within 10 years to finance ambitious projects, including a Manhattan laboratory that has been in the forefront of AIDS research.</p>
        <p>In Miami, the Lucille P. Markey Charitable Trust will dissolve next June after 14 years, its officers confident that the $506 million they have awarded to finance biomedical research at universities and to support the work of young scientists will spur advances in medicine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When 1996 dies at midnight on Dec. 31, so will New York's Aaron Diamond Foundation -- on schedule and in keeping with its strategy for using up its more than $200 million within 10 years to finance ambitious projects, including a Manhattan laboratory that has been in the forefront of AIDS research.</p>
        <p>In Miami, the Lucille P. Markey Charitable Trust will dissolve next June after 14 years, its officers confident that the $506 million they have awarded to finance biomedical research at universities and to support the work of young scientists will spur advances in medicine.</p>
        <p>In San Diego, the Jacobs Family Foundation, which will eventually be endowed with $100 million to support community and economic development in Southern California and the Middle East, plans to dismantle itself  when the last of three daughters of the founder, Joseph J. Jacobs, dies, probably in about three decades.</p>
        <p>By electing to ''spend down'' substantial chunks of their assets each year until the principal is gone, these  benefactors are spending themselves out of business. They are doing so in the belief that by disbursing their vast sums in a finite number of years, they will have a greater impact on the societal problems they were created to address.</p>
        <p>Their approach is not typical, nor has it won many converts among the nation's 38,807 grant-making foundations who, in 1994, held $195.8 billion in assets and made grants of $11.3 billion. Indeed, the strategy renounces two tenets of modern philanthropy: that a foundation should operate in perpetuity and give away only a small portion of its wealth each year.</p>
        <p>But with their against-the-grain approach, these foundations have put an area of philanthropic strategy --  once reserved for board rooms and other cloistered venues -- into public debate. The question is: How can donors insure that their money has the greatest possible impact?</p>
        <p>Setting a philanthropy's life span ought to be dictated by the donor's perspective and values as well as by the nature of the problems the donor chooses to address, said Peter Goldmark, president of the Rockefeller Foundation, an international foundation that in 1995 had $2.54 billion in assets and made grants and other awards of $94.9 million.</p>
        <p>''Suppose you were going to make your problem global warming,'' Mr. Goldmark said. ''I don't think you would pick a spend-down policy. But suppose your target were going to be to clean up the Hudson River. You would have made a lot of progress by now. You might have started 20 years ago, and you might have had a 20-year policy and you know what, you'd be just about right.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, Brooke Astor, who has given away $175 million through the Vincent Astor Foundation, decided to fold the foundation and give away its last $25 million by the end of next year. Mrs. Astor, who is 94, said she was taking this course in part because she wanted more time to travel and write poetry.</p>
        <p>For some philanthropists, the choice is more a matter of philosophy.</p>
        <p>Some conservatives, for example, are drawn to such time-limited philanthropy because they believe some major foundations, including the Ford Foundation and the Pew Charitable Trust, have evolved into liberal institutions that have strayed from the intent of the donor.</p>
        <p>''There are distinct advantages'' to a time limit, said Terrence Scanlon, president of the Capital Research Center, a conservative research group in Washington, that studies the nonprofit sector. ''Donor intent is the principal one. A donor generally leaves his or her money for said purposes and often during the course of the lifetime of a foundation, particularly when you get into the second or third generation, the donor intent goes down the tubes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Scanlon called the Ford Foundation ''the most egregious one in everybody's eyes'' and asserted that Ford's officers were straying far from the founder's conservative intent, ''putting beaucoup bucks into every politically correct project that can be devised.''</p>
        <p>The Ford Foundation, America's largest philanthropy by virtue of its $7.5-billion portfolio and $314 million in annual grants and loans in fiscal 1995, was designed by its founder, Henry Ford, with a broad mission to make ''advances in human welfare.''</p>
        <p>Susan V. Berresford, the Ford Foundation's president, said the foundation's charter reflected its donor's intent. ''The donor had total freedom as to how to write that charter,'' she said. ''And what later generations of people ascribe to that donor may or may not be correct. But what is absolutely clearly correct is what the donor said when he or she wrote the charter.''</p>
        <p>With the vast number and variety of issues that foundations take an interest in, Ms. Berresford said, it should not be surprising that some donors chose to dispose of their portfolios.</p>
        <p>But, she added, ''my hope is that all would not choose to spend down.''</p>
        <p>There is by no means a consensus among conservatives in philanthropy about the value of time-limited philanthropy. ''People on the conservative side of things see foundations as very problematic,'' said Michael S. Joyce, president of the Milwaukee-based Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation and a board member of the Philanthropy Roundtable, which perceives itself as a conservative alternative to the Council on Foundations, the major umbrella group of the foundation world. Rather, he said, conservatives see foundations ''as agents of centralization and the welfare state.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Joyce said foundations constantly evolve. Time-limited foundations, he said, will not protect donor intent. ''All it does is transfer assets from one set of stewards to another unless you require consumption'' of the grant by the recipient, he said.</p>
        <p>Some major foundations also see conservatives' focus on donor intent as something of a canard. In the case of the Pew trust, the majority of the foundation's board are family members and many have life terms, said Rebecca W. Rimel, Pew's president. ''They are very active and very involved,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Aaron Diamond, a New York real estate developer, and his wife, Irene, had planned to make their philanthropic decisions together, but he died in 1984, just as they were activating the foundation. ''We both had a feeling if we stuck with our priorities and really hit hard with money, we would probably be able to make a difference, and I think we have,'' Mrs. Diamond said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Diamond's most famous philanthropic wager involved investing $25 million to create the Aaron Diamond AIDS Research Center. In 1995, its director, Dr. David D. Ho, was one of two researchers widely credited with uncovering how the AIDS virus fights with the immune system. Had Mrs. Diamond behaved conventionally, giving away $6.5 million to $7 million a year, creation of the laboratory would have been delayed for years while it searched for other foundations to be partners, said Vincent McGee, the foundation's executive director.</p>
        <p>''Because we were spending out in a 10-year period, we have given at least $20 million a year once we got going,'' he said. ''The guiding principle was 'let's not hold this up because we have to find money somewhere else.' And you can only do that if you are biting into capital.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
