<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Landfills Could Light Up Houses</title>
    <meta content="LANDFI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="894080"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Groton (Conn)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Onsi Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northeast Utilities</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency (Epa)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Carolyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E3DC113CF93BA35751C1A960958260" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Landfills Could Light Up Houses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Carolyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Groton (Conn) landfill is international attraction, as it is only landfill in world that generates electricity; in front of mounds of garbage stands fuel cell that generates electricity from gas produced as garbage decomposes; Groton installation is designed to demonstrate and refine a process that can be used at many landfills and sewage treatment plants; Onsi Corp of South Windsor manufactured 200-kilowatt fuel cell and its clean-up system; it is joint project by town of Groton, Onsi, Northeast Utilities and Federal Environmental Protection Agency; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LATELY, the Groton landfill has had visitors from several countries, including Russia and South Africa. ''It's going to be on the tourism map soon,'' joked John C. Trocciola, who was there on a recent Sunday afternoon to welcome two officials from China.</p>
        <p>Buried under the landfill's grassy mounds are some 30 years of Groton's garbage. In front of the mounds stands the international attraction: a fuel cell that generates electricity from gas produced as the garbage decomposes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LATELY, the Groton landfill has had visitors from several countries, including Russia and South Africa. ''It's going to be on the tourism map soon,'' joked John C. Trocciola, who was there on a recent Sunday afternoon to welcome two officials from China.</p>
        <p>Buried under the landfill's grassy mounds are some 30 years of Groton's garbage. In front of the mounds stands the international attraction: a fuel cell that generates electricity from gas produced as the garbage decomposes.</p>
        <p>''This is the only fuel cell in the world operating at a landfill,'' said Mr. Trocciola. He is manager for biomass energy programs at ONSI Corporation of South Windsor, which manufactured the 200-kilowatt fuel cell and its clean-up system. The fuel cell converts methane gas from the landfill into electricity -- enough for 100 average houses -- and feeds it into a nearby power grid.</p>
        <p>The Groton installation is designed to demonstrate and refine a process that can be used at many landfills and sewage treatment plants. It's a joint project by the town, ONSI (a subsidiary of International Fuel Cells Corporation), Northeast Utilities and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, most of which sent representatives to greet the Chinese visitors.</p>
        <p>''Fuel cells are the emerging technology,'' said William L. Stillinger, Northeast Utilities' director of research and environmental planning. First used in spacecraft, fuel cells are being used increasingly as power plants for electricity. The cells, also found in experimental cars and buses, operate with few moving parts, minimal exhaust and noise emissions; they produce power and heat by combining hydrogen and oxygen electrochemically. The kind of fuel cell that's in Groton -- the only kind now in commercial use -- gets its hydrogen fuel from methane and its oxygen from the air.</p>
        <p>Like batteries, fuel cells have electrodes and an electrolyte, but unlike batteries, they don't run down. While most commercial fuel cells operate on natural gas, there's growing interest in using the methane that's released by sewage treatment plants and landfills.</p>
        <p>''The whole notion of recovering human-made methane is a good one,'' said Mr. Stillinger. Methane is considered a major contributor to global warming, and it's a useful energy resource. Mr. Trocciola noted that fuel cells (with clean-up systems) are now working in sewage treatment plants in Yonkers, N. Y., and in Boston Harbor. Similar systems are planned for a sewage plant in Meriden and for a landfill in Braintree, Mass.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Mr. Stillinger, who likes to recycle everything and waste nothing, hopes to see a hydroponic greenhouse at the Groton landfill, operating mostly with heat and lighting provided by the fuel cell and carbon dioxide provided by the landfill. ''It's just a notion at this point, but we're talking to interested parties,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Like many others, the Groton landfill no longer takes in garbage. But, Mr. Trocciola pointed out, ''A closed-off landfill will produce gas for 20 years.'' Many landfills have systems of wells and pipes, collecting gas to burn it off, and those systems can collect gas for use in a fuel cell.</p>
        <p>Until the system arrived in June, all of the landfill gas was burned off. Now 20 percent of the gas heads for the clean-up system, which, Mr. Stillinger described as ''overdesigned'' because of its experimental nature. Future ones are expected to be simpler, he said. Carefully, he made his way around the clean-up equipment -- including tanks, pipes, and more -- housed next to the fuel cell. First, hydrogen sulfide from the landfill gas is absorbed by carbon pellets. ''Then we chill the gas, liquify a lot of the impurities, and drain them off,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The fuel cell itself is housed in a tidy metal structure. ''It's a neat package of power,'' said Rick Whitaker, ONSI's president. He noted that the Groton one is a bit larger than current models, which are 10 feet wide, 10 feet high and 18 feet long. The major components are a reformer, which produces a hydrogen-rich gas from the methane; the cell stack, in which an electrochemical reaction produces direct current, and the inverter, which converts the direct current to alternating current. While some fuel cells are, like the Groton one, connected to a grid, others are independent, providing power for a particular situation.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Whitaker talked of the ease of installing an ONSI fuel cell (''You just unwrap it and hook up the pipes,'' he said), the Chinese officials arrived. With them were representatives of the W. Alton Jones Foundation, their sponsor on a trip devoted mainly to an environmental meeting in Argentina. Soon Xie Zhen Hua, administrator of his country's National Environmental Protection Agency, was firing off questions, nodding vigorously at answers, and writing a lot in a tiny notebook. Wang Zhijia, also of the agency, took photos as well as notes. Dr. Ji-Qiang Zhang, originally from China but now a program officer with the foundation, translated for all on a tour of the fuel cell and the clean-up apparatus.</p>
        <p>How much, Mr. Xie asked, does a fuel cell cost? Approximately $1 million for a landfill system requiring extensive clean-up equipment, said Mr. Trocciola. But, he added, a fuel cell using natural gas would cost about $600,000, and the United States Government pays a third of the purchase price for eligible companies and governments. ''It's part of President Clinton's climate change program,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''If I buy, does the American Government pay a third?'' asked Mr. Xie. Mr. Whitaker replied, ''If you decide to buy one, we'll help you with your application.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Xie was impressed that the fuel cell operation was pollution- free, and he noted that in his country, there are many reserves of natural gas. He could help, he said, if Mr. Whitaker would be interested in doing a fuel cell demonstration project in China.</p>
        <p>''I would be interested,'' said Mr. Whitaker, as the group got ready to head for South Windsor, to see the fuel cell factory.</p>
        <p>The Groton fuel cell demonstration is expected to run through 1997 at least. Recent visitors have included groups from Russia, which has the world's largest gas company; from South Africa, where the Mandela Government wants to electrify rural areas, and from Japan, where several fuel cells run on natural gas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
