<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Debating the Benefits and Costs Of Major Surgery for Emphysema</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Medical Science Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="850500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMPHYSEMA</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURGERY AND SURGEONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LUNGS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HEALTH CARE FINANCING ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL HEART, LUNG ANDBLOOD INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Emphysema</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lungs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emphysema</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surgery and Surgeons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1DA1239F937A25756C0A960958260" item-length="1897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Debating the Benefits and Costs Of Major Surgery for Emphysema</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An increasingly popular new surgery for emphysema that at first appears to defy logic is at the center of an intense debate among chest surgeons and health care providers concerning its effectiveness and cost.</p>
        <p>The operation, called lung volume reduction surgery, is increasingly being offered at hospitals around the country, even as doctors argue about how it should be performed, which patients are likely to benefit and if its benefits are worth the risks and cost.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An increasingly popular new surgery for emphysema that at first appears to defy logic is at the center of an intense debate among chest surgeons and health care providers concerning its effectiveness and cost.</p>
        <p>The operation, called lung volume reduction surgery, is increasingly being offered at hospitals around the country, even as doctors argue about how it should be performed, which patients are likely to benefit and if its benefits are worth the risks and cost.</p>
        <p>Experts agree that the operation is not a cure for emphysema, a common, degenerative lung disease that most often results from cigarette smoking. But while many say it offers hope for at least temporarily relieving the shortness of breath and dependence upon external oxygen of many seriously ill patients who are virtually bedridden, the question of long-term benefit and relief remains unanswered.</p>
        <p>"The procedure has shown substantial benefit to some patients, but clearly there are some others who have not benefited and may have been made worse off,"  said Dr. Leonard D. Hudson, a professor of pulmonary and critical care medicine  at the University of Washington in Seattle. He added that more data were needed.</p>
        <p>Treating emphysema with lung reduction surgery involves removing 20 percent to 30 percent of the damaged lung tissue. The operation has touched off so much  debate that the American Thoracic Society, which represents chest and lung specialists, issued a position paper today in New Orleans at its annual conference acknowledging the operation's promise, based upon preliminary studies, but urging caution in its use.</p>
        <p>"At this point in time, the operation should not be considered experimental,  although insufficient data are available to determine if lung volume reduction surgery should be considered standard therapy," said the society, the medical branch of the American Lung Association. "Since there are many questions to be answered," the statement continued, "we recommend that this operation be performed only at centers where these procedures can be more completely studied  through clinical trials and extensive physiologic evaluations."</p>
        <p>Dr. Hudson, who is president of the thoracic society, said in an interview that there was concern that the surgery was becoming too widespread too soon. "We are calling for caution," he said. "Until we know more about the surgery and what it takes for it to be successful, we think it is too early to have the procedure done at every hospital."</p>
        <p>Concern about the cost of the procedure prompted the Health Care Financing Administration, the Federal agency that regulates Medicare, to stop paying for the surgery in January, citing questions about its safety and effectiveness. But some private insurers continue to cover the surgery. Studies show the costs of the operation, not including doctors' fees, range from $35,000 to more than $70,000, depending on complications and the amount of rehabilitation required.</p>
        <p>A subsequent assessment by the Agency for Health Care Policy and Research of  more than 3,000 procedures from 27 medical centers found current data inconclusive regarding the risks and benefits of the surgery. The study, requested by the financing administration, recommended limited Medicare reimbursement only for patients who were part of a national controlled trial of  the procedure.</p>
        <p>On April 24, the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute announced that it would sponsor such a trial. The institute said it would support a seven-year randomized study of more than 2,500 patients at 10 to 15 centers to determine which of several types of lung reduction surgery worked best and which patients  were most likely to benefit. The study will also examine how much of the reported benefit is due to the procedure and how much is a result of the aggressive medical therapy and rehabilitation required at centers that get the best results.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gail G. Weinmann of the institute said: "There is a possibility that the  incremental improvement of surgery is so small that it could be negligible after a year or two. But the only way to determine that is with a trial."</p>
        <p>Emphysema, which afflicts an estimated two million Americans in varying degrees, results in irreversible tissue damage when the walls between the air sacs within the lung lose their ability to stretch and spring back. The disease, which generally spreads through both lungs, is characterized by enlargement of the air spaces and loss of the organ's elasticity, causing air to be trapped and impairing the exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Until recently, little could be done for patients with severe emphysema, many of whom cannot walk more than a few feet or do simple tasks without exertion and the need for supplemental oxygen to assist their inefficient, often overly distended lungs. Lung transplantation has become an option for some cases, with  the number of transplants for emphysema patients increasing to 688 in 1994 from  2 in 1985, said the American Lung Association. But a shortage of transplant organs and rigorous criteria for the surgery prevent it from being the primary therapy for most patients.</p>
        <p>More than four years ago, Dr. Joel D. Cooper, a leading chest surgeon at Washington University in St. Louis, noticed during lung transplant operations that the enlarged chest cavities of emphysema patients shrank after the surgery, helping to allow more efficient breathing.</p>
        <p>This led Dr. Cooper to revive a discarded procedure developed in the 1950's by Dr. Otto C. Brantigan of the University of Maryland. Dr. Brantigan removed sections of diseased but functioning lung to give the remaining tissue more room to expand and deflate properly. While surviving patients appeared to develop improved lung function, a high mortality rate of one in six patients and resistance to the idea of removing tissue to improve a disease that destroyed lung tissue to begin with doomed the procedure.</p>
        <p>In the procedure developed by Dr. Cooper and his colleagues, doctors screen prospective patients with X-ray examinations and lung scans using radioactive gas to determine areas of the lungs that are not functioning well and are candidates for removal. Surgeons then open the chest and remove areas of the worstfunctioning tissues using a stapling device that cuts off tissue as it clamps the wound shut. In his procedure, Dr. Cooper simultaneously staples in a  layer of tissue taken from the hearts of cattle that helps seal the wound and prevent dangerous air leaks in the days after surgery.</p>
        <p>In an editorial debate on lung reduction surgery published in the April issue of The American Journal of Respiratory Critical Care Medicine, Dr. Cooper said his experience with the first 120 procedures performed over two and a half years showed that the operation benefited a vast majority of patients.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cooper said that on average, six months after surgery, there was a 55 percent increase in lung function over preoperative levels, a 32 percent increase in ability to force air from the lungs and a 28 percent decrease in distended lung volume. Of patients who required supplemental oxygen at any time  before the operation, 71 percent were able to discontinue all extra oxygen, he said, and the vast majority reported significant improvement in their shortness  of breath and in quality of life.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said in the article, the total mortality rate in these patients immediately after surgery and after a year from all causes was 5 percent, and the 35 patients followed for more than a year showed sustained benefits. For a significant number of patients awaiting transplantation, he said, the lung reduction procedure should be considered a potential alternative  therapy.</p>
        <p>"When done properly, this operation works," Dr. Cooper said in an interview.  "There is no question about it. Where there have been problems, they have come from a tremendous abuse of lung reduction early on, with too many doctors doing it with little experience and trying new procedures that don't work."</p>
        <p>In an article countering Dr. Cooper's position in the journal, Dr. Barry J. Make of the University of Colorado Medical School and Dr. Alan M. Fein of the State University of New York at Stony Brook said it was too soon to recommend the surgery to patients outside of clinical trials. Questions of safety and effectiveness remain, they said, including mortality rates in some studies as high as 12.5 percent within a month after surgery and an additional 10 percent mortality from respiratory-related causes in the next five months. Also, they said, the high cost of the unproven surgery could cost the nation's medical care system billions of dollars at a time when money for proven therapies is being restricted.</p>
        <p>"The most important question is will patients benefit in a significant way that improves their quality of life for a sufficient period of time," Dr. Fein said in an interview. "And this requires careful study before committing our limited resources."</p>
        <p>Dr. Frank C. Sciurba and his colleagues at the University of Pittsburgh are using a less-invasive method of surgery than that used by Dr. Cooper, but say they are seeing short-term results that are just as good. After seeing some bedridden or homebound patients dramatically improve after surgery, Dr. Sciurba  said, "we need to consider very carefully whether it is right to withhold this therapy from a fully informed patient," adding, "There is a strong potential downside based on what we don't know about the long-term effects, but there also can be an upside that can't be ignored."</p>
        <p>Dr. Sciurba's procedure involves making three incisions in the chest through  which a camera and instruments are introduced instead of opening the entire chest. The operation uses stapling to cut away tissue and a low-energy laser to  trim hard-to-reach tissue and seal cuts.</p>
        <p>In a study published last month in The New England Journal of Medicine, the Pittsburgh group said surgery increased elastic recoil in the lungs of 16 of 20  patients, who greatly increased the distance they could walk four months after the operation.</p>
        <p>The less-invasive procedure can also be used with the laser alone to destroy  tissue and collapse it into the lung, Dr. Sciurba said, but the use of lasers by themselves has proved much less effective than other surgery in improving lung function. Several specialists attributed many of the problems and failures with  lung reduction surgery in some studies to too many inexperienced doctors performing the procedure with different kinds of lasers.</p>
        <p>Dr. John Eugene of the Western Medical Center in Anaheim, Calif., and the University of California at Irvine, said that using the low-energy laser alone could be effective if an experienced surgeon noticed during a procedure that a patient's tissues were responding to the laser. In most cases, the laser is used as an adjunct to stapling and other procedures, but it can be used by itself in  15 percent of cases, said Dr. Eugene, who has performed lung reductions on more  than 300 patients using varying methods.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
