<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bleak Serbian Mining Region May Decide Milosevic's Fate</title>
    <meta content="02SERB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="893208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yugoslavia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bor (Yugoslavia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hedges, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7D9133CF931A35751C1A960958260" item-length="1380" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bleak Serbian Mining Region May Decide Milosevic's Fate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS HEDGES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hedges, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>BOR, Serbia, Dec. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fate of Serbian Pres Slobodan Milosevic, whose Government has faced almost two weeks of street protests in major cities, may ultimately hinge on whether miners strike in bleak southeastern mining region of Bor; opposition coalition says support of workers in mining communities in south is crucial to drive to force Milosevic from power; miners, who are plagued with poor working conditions and subsequent health problems caused by toxic emissions and dangerous production procedures, have been warned they face dismissals if they join protests; opposition has campaigned on pledge to curb industrial contamination; protests have followed Government decision to nullify results of recent elections; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After almost two weeks of street protests in major Serbian cities against the Government of President Slobodan Milosevic, he appeared today to be  losing patience, hinting that he might be about to crush them. But many Serbs say his fate will ultimately be determined in this bleak southeastern mining region.</p>
        <p>The opposition coalition behind the protests says the support of workers, and especially the mining communities in the south, is crucial to its drive to force Mr. Milosevic from power.  The miners are plagued with poor working conditions, numerous respiratory and other ailments caused by toxic emissions and dangerous production procedures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After almost two weeks of street protests in major Serbian cities against the Government of President Slobodan Milosevic, he appeared today to be  losing patience, hinting that he might be about to crush them. But many Serbs say his fate will ultimately be determined in this bleak southeastern mining region.</p>
        <p>The opposition coalition behind the protests says the support of workers, and especially the mining communities in the south, is crucial to its drive to force Mr. Milosevic from power.  The miners are plagued with poor working conditions, numerous respiratory and other ailments caused by toxic emissions and dangerous production procedures.</p>
        <p>The opposition took control of Bor's city government in recent elections but the Government in Belgrade then nullified the count. The protests in Belgrade, the capital, began after Mr. Milosevic's Government took similar action there to overturn another victory by a local opposition slate.</p>
        <p>The opposition campaigned here on a pledge to curb industrial contamination. But even this issue was apparently too much for Mr. Milosevic's governing Socialist Party.</p>
        <p>''The moment the miners strike, Milosevic is finished,'' said Cedomir Pavlovic, the leader of the local opposition coalition. ''The town is flooded with secret police. If the protests can continue for another week, we have a chance. Each day the miners grow bolder as more news about what is happening in Belgrade, Nis and other cities seeps into Bor. It is a race now between us and the regime.''</p>
        <p>But it is a race the Serbian leader does not appear ready to lose.</p>
        <p>Miners who work in the huge Government-owned complex of 15,000 workers in open-air pits and shafts digging for copper and gold say they have been warned by mine officials that any protests like work stoppages or strikes will be cause for immediate dismissal.</p>
        <p>The small headquarters of the opposition is so closely watched that the miner who finally agreed to lead a foreign reporter to it pulled up his hood and bent his face down to avoid identification. Miners say that phones of suspected labor activists have been bugged and that several have been called in, told that gatherings are prohibited and and warned not to do anything provocative.</p>
        <p>Opposition leaders clandestinely published a pamphlet in Bor explaining the protests and distributed it to the miners. But an information blockade by the Government, which now includes Government jamming of the only independent news radio station in Belgrade, has made it difficult to get reports to those outside the capital.</p>
        <p>The only place where large numbers of blue collar workers have joined the daily protests -- staged largely by students, the middle class and pensioners -- has been Nis, but this is not widely known elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The Interior Ministry ominously warned tonight in Belgrade that those who took to the streets without proper permits from now on would be in violation of the law and ''would have to accept the consequences.''</p>
        <p>''The control has been very effective in places like Bor,'' said Mr. Pavlovic, a 44-year-old former miner with broad shoulders and beefy hands who moved to an administrative job because of an injury.</p>
        <p>He added that ''we need time just to explain what is going on in the rest of the country,'' even before workers could be organized for protests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic was considered to have major responsibility for encouraging Serbian nationalists in the war in Croatia and Bosnia that began after the former Yugoslavia disintegrated. But he was also instrumental in achieving the agreement a year ago to end the fighting in Bosnia. The opposition is a disparate group of intellectuals and nationalists who have often fought among themselves.</p>
        <p>The Bor Smelting and Mining Company, 150 miles southeast of Belgrade, has few rivals in Eastern Europe for its toxic emissions. The gray clouds of soot and smog, pumped out from the smokestacks of huge smelters, give off an acrid, metallic smell.</p>
        <p>The seedy, decaying apartment blocks clustered around the complex are clothed in grime and dirt. The cement sidewalks are broken and cracked. The dull brown Borska River, which emits a stench of sulfur and chemicals, is so polluted that the fish and plants have died. Miners cannot wear nylon garments because the acid in the air blotches and eats through the material. Crops near the mine complex wither and die in the acid rain.</p>
        <p>Miners say 10 percent of the work force must leave the pits and shafts each year because of respiratory diseases. Asthma and bronchitis plague many children. They say birth defects and cancer have become endemic, especially since the decision two years ago by mine officials to use abandoned shafts to store containers of waste that the miners believe is radioactive.</p>
        <p>In the mines, many ventilation systems do not work, plunging miners into dimly lit tunnels where they choke on dust and fumes and toil in extreme heat or biting cold. The few masks that are available to the miners are inadequate Communist-era contraptions with thin paper filters that do little to ward off the toxins. Most miners dig without them.</p>
        <p>''No one here has ever had a long life expectancy,'' said Dragoslav Radulovic, a 32-year-old miner. ''But now it is spiraling out of control. Men in their 30's are getting cancer and dying. My own children have blood diseases, and the mines are in a state of dangerous disrepair. The mine directors, however, are rolling in money, building nice suburban houses outside Belgrade on the fat commissions they pocket.''</p>
        <p>It is not the commissions that most infuriate the miners, they say, but what these commissions have brought to the town. The mine management has signed contracts to smelt copper from Portugal that has a dangerously high mercury content as well as copper from the Ukraine that was contaminated in the Chernobyl nuclear accident.</p>
        <p>On the days when those copper shipments are smelted, the local radio warns families to evacuate children from the town, considering any further explanation unnecessary.</p>
        <p>''Our cemetery is growing faster than our town,'' Mr. Pavlovic said.  ''When our young men get called up for the army, most don't pass the physical.''</p>
        <p>In the end, though, it is not only Government repression that is thwarting the work of the activists here. The character of the mining community itself makes opposition difficult. Bor has few of the cafes and cheap restaurants where people gather that most Serbian towns have. The town that circles the mine complex seems lonely and solitary.</p>
        <p>Miners who led strikes in the past, including a successful one for higher wages two years ago, have disappeared from the mines. Some have been bought off with better-paying jobs and apartments, and those who persisted have been put on leave or dismissed.</p>
        <p>Wages, at about $200 a month, are double what they are in other industries, making many miners wary of risking their jobs. And Belgrade passed two laws this year, one in the Serbian Parliament and one in the federal Parliament of the new Yugoslavia, that in effect make it illegal for mine workers to strike. The federal law says strikes are legal only if held inside the workplace, but a Serbian mining law makes strikes illegal inside all mining complexes.</p>
        <p>''We are a miners' colony, not really a town at all,'' said Dragoljub Janez, the opposition deputy from Bor in the federal Parliament. ''We have withdrawn increasingly into ourselves. We are fearful and distrustful. Anyone who gets educated never comes back.''</p>
        <p>''Anyone who organizes the workers gets corrupted or removed from the mine,'' he said. ''We rarely gather in groups now, even to talk. We have no soul.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
