<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Cashless Future, Robots Will Cook</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Home and Garden; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="825052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINEAND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGED</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSPORTATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARRIOTT, MICHEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DC1F39F937A15752C0A960958260" item-length="2067" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Cashless Future, Robots Will Cook</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHEL MARRIOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARRIOTT, MICHEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a typical day in the year 2006. After a hectic afternoon of negotiating  contracts with business partners in Hong Kong, London, Moscow and the Bronx, you step from your office and into your kitchen. What's for lunch? You press a hand  on your personal diagnostic machine, and quicker then you can say Michael Jackson does Sinatra, the unit checks your blood pressure, cholesterol and weight-fat ratio and reads out your nutritional requirements. Up pops suggested  menus.</p>
        <p>Kitchen robots quietly go to work moving ingredients from a "smart" refrigerator that is built into a microwave oven. A minute later, out rolls a garden salad with dill dressing and an open-face pork-roast sandwich on wheat -- no crust. After lunch, you return to your home office to finish some business in South Africa. If you're done early, maybe you can squeeze in a movie: "Gone With the Wind" you reconfigured with Bruce Willis as Rhett Butler.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a typical day in the year 2006. After a hectic afternoon of negotiating  contracts with business partners in Hong Kong, London, Moscow and the Bronx, you step from your office and into your kitchen. What's for lunch? You press a hand  on your personal diagnostic machine, and quicker then you can say Michael Jackson does Sinatra, the unit checks your blood pressure, cholesterol and weight-fat ratio and reads out your nutritional requirements. Up pops suggested  menus.</p>
        <p>Kitchen robots quietly go to work moving ingredients from a "smart" refrigerator that is built into a microwave oven. A minute later, out rolls a garden salad with dill dressing and an open-face pork-roast sandwich on wheat -- no crust. After lunch, you return to your home office to finish some business in South Africa. If you're done early, maybe you can squeeze in a movie: "Gone With the Wind" you reconfigured with Bruce Willis as Rhett Butler.</p>
        <p>For much of human history, talk of the future was relegated to the musings of self-described prophets, astrologers, dreamers and fools. But as the world lurches toward the 21st century, futurism is being taken more seriously by more  people. Experts of all stripes are studying the patterns of the past and present, trying to project tomorrow. Forecasts of what might be spill out of corporate boardrooms, government offices, magazine stands, talk shows and bookstores like a bubbly brew.</p>
        <p>Look at nonfiction books published in the last couple of years. With titles like "The Road to 2015," "Visions of the Future," "Techno Trends" and "Vital Signs 1995: The Trends That Are Shaping Our Future," they give the impression, with their trend analyses and expert judgments, that the future just might be glimpsed.</p>
        <p>"I think the whole appeal of the genre, including the science fiction genre,  has always been a wish to engineer a dramatically different kind of life, especially with the millennium approaching," said Sybil Steinberg, a senior editor at Publishers Weekly.</p>
        <p>But the truth is -- and even futurists admit -- that predicting the future is a highly educated guess.</p>
        <p>"When we make any forecasts, we know that there is no predetermined future,"  said Stephen M. Millett, head of technology intelligence and management at Battelle Memorial Institute, a nonprofit research group in Columbus, Ohio. "There is no immutable future out there. But there are highly probable possibilities."</p>
        <p>Until about 200 years ago, change was so slow that people presumed that the lives of their children and grandchildren would not be very much different from  their own. And then came the 20th century, when people went from flying in the first airplane at Kitty Hawk to planting their first footsteps on the moon -- all in the blink of a lifetime. One group of scientists has said that the rate of change in our contemporary world is running a million times faster than the rate of humans' ability to adjust to the new situations.</p>
        <p>Here is what futurists say are highly probable ways Americans may live in the opening years of the next millennium.</p>
        <p>Food and Dining</p>
        <p>Marvin J. Cetron, founder and president of Forecasting International Ltd., a  consulting company in Arlington, Va., said that with more people likely to work  at home and late into the night to match business hours around the world, takeout meals and delivery of prepared meals will be even more prevalent.</p>
        <p>The World Future Society, a nonprofit organization in Bethesda, Md., predicts that supermarkets may become hydroponic greenhouses where shoppers pick their own produce from the vine. And for those who would not care for such a hands-on  experience, groceries could be electronically ordered and automatically delivered into home refrigerators designed to open to the outside as well as to  the inside of the house.</p>
        <p>How the meals of tomorrow might be prepared include the fanciful and the fantastic. Mr. Cetron says he believes that by 2006, people will have personal diagnostic and meal preparation machines. If you eat too much, the diagnostic machine will tell you to exercise.</p>
        <p>But what would an automated kitchen helper prepare?</p>
        <p>Many experts anticipate advances in biotechnology that could lead to cows that produce low-fat milk, disease-resistant potatoes grown by crossing them with a chicken gene (would that make french fries taste like chicken?) and pork  made leaner by introducing a cow gene into the pig's genetic pool. Even fat-free frying may be possible, Mr. Cetron said.</p>
        <p>Cuisines are also more likely to be spicy, as hometown cooking gives way to more international cuisines. Already, Americans use 68 more spices than they did 10 years ago, Mr. Cetron wrote in the latest issue of The Futurist magazine.</p>
        <p>But if, as expected, the world's human population doubles in the next 40 years, the pressure to produce enough food to feed everyone is going to be immense, said Lester R. Brown, president of the Worldwatch Institute, an environmental research group in Washington. He notes in his book, "Vital Signs 1995: The Trends That Are Shaping Our Future" (W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1995), that "the pace of history is accelerating as soaring human demands collide with  the Earth's natural limits."</p>
        <p>Medicine and Aging</p>
        <p>For many people, particularly aging baby boomers, a big question in the early 21st century will be, how can you add years to your life? Many futurists say that will be possible, at least for those who can afford it.</p>
        <p>By 2020, the complete human DNA structure will be mapped, Mr. Cetron said. "Doctors will know a person's genetic characteristics right from birth, even before birth," he said. That could guide doctors to tailor life styles and treatments to help patients avoid disorders they are prone to develop. With genetic medicine, Mr. Cetron said, a child born in 2010 could expect to live 120 years.</p>
        <p>Dr. Millett at the Battelle Institute says he believes that the boomers' pressure on the market, combined with advances in genetic research, will lead to a whole new level of pharmaceutical cosmetics. "There may come a day when you have a pill that will lighten your hair," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown at the Worldwatch Institute cautioned that public health and medicine are likely to be challenged by another global trend: the rise in infectious diseases and their increased immunity to antibiotics. Modern travel enables a million people to cross national boundaries every day, he said, emphasizing, "The increasing density of world populations and closer contact among people are all leading to increases in infectious diseases, including new  ones like AIDS and Lyme disease."</p>
        <p>Transportation</p>
        <p>Despite environmental pressures to encourage the expansion of mass transportation, the automobile is expected to survive, perhaps even thrive, well into the new century.</p>
        <p>"We all love the convenience and flexibility of personal transportation," Dr. Millett said.</p>
        <p>Yet, cars may undergo radical alterations in the next decade, he said. Automobiles with more than one fuel source may become the standard. These hybrids would, for instance, use a highly efficient internal combustion engine (getting 60 to 70 miles to the gallon) to burn an oil-based fuel for high acceleration, then switch to compressed gas or electricity for cruising speeds.  The result would be a relatively low-polluting vehicle, he concluded.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cetron expects electric cars to make modest gains by 2010. "A variety of  social needs will begin to force the issue and push people toward buying the electric car," he said.</p>
        <p>Edward Cornish, president of the World Future Society and editor of its magazine, The Futurist, expects that cars in the next century will learn how to  drive. They will use computers, cameras and road sensors to create an automatic  pilot. That technology might well give rise to company cars that are traveling offices: equipped with the latest business devices, telephone, couch, exercise equipment and even a wet bar.</p>
        <p>Trains are also expected to evolve. Employing exotic technologies like magnetic levitation in trains may be more than 20 years off because of the expense, but conventional trains will probably be updated.</p>
        <p>This year, Amtrak is expected to award a $400 million contract for 18 trains  that can reach speeds of 150 miles an hour. They are scheduled to go into service in 1999 along the Northeast Corridor and would cut the trip between New  York and Washington from 2 hours and 40 minutes to 2 hours and 15 minutes, Mr. Black said.</p>
        <p>Practical concerns about dwindling fossil fuels and land may force a familiar mode of transport to the fore: the bicycle.</p>
        <p>"Cars require miles of roads, parking lots, streets," Mr. Brown of Worldwatch said. "Imagine a car in every garage in China. With the streets and parking requiring so much land, what would happen to cropland?" He noted that a desk-bound society could use the exercise of pedaling to work.</p>
        <p>Housing</p>
        <p>"Home behavior changes pretty slowly," Dr. Millett said, expecting little change in how Americans build and live in houses in the next few years. But from 2010 to 2020, he anticipates "fundamental change."</p>
        <p>"We are going to move out of single-family dwellings into community condos,"  he said, because graying baby boomers will be unable to live alone but will be unwilling to live in nursing homes.</p>
        <p>By 2010, new materials will also help build houses very quickly. Fuel cells the size of a deck of cards and an expanded use of solar cells, coupled with computers to control them all, will provide che'per power to homes, Dr. Millett  said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cornish says homes will be so comfortable and so wired to the outside world with communication and entertainment equipment that people will rarely want to leave them. What to eat in this new home? Mr. Cetron anticipates that practically everything, from chili to Chevies, will be ordered electronically and delivered to your door.</p>
        <p>Money</p>
        <p>Many futurists agree that the next 10 to 20 years may see the beginning of a  mostly cashless culture. "Smart cards," or debit cards, are expected to become popular.</p>
        <p>"I am very confident that there is going to be a terrific need for this," Dr. Millett said. "Whenever you slip it in, you pay for a fare, a cup of coffee."</p>
        <p>In The Futurist, Mr. Cornish wrote that by 2025, cash may be popular only with "thieves, tax dodgers and paranoiacs."</p>
        <p>Computing</p>
        <p>In the next decade, wireless communication should untether many portable computers as they continue to grow smaller, become more personal and further integrate their functions.</p>
        <p>Sal Suwalsky, president of Royal Consumer Business Products of Bridgewater, N.J., said that the near future is likely to unleash a flood of hand-held and highly interactive tools. Hardly larger than a credit card, these little data banks will digitally organize all sorts of personal and business information and messages and respond to the sound of a user's voice.</p>
        <p>"Eventually," Mr. Suwalsky said, "everyone will have mobile cards that they will carry and receive all their telecommunications."</p>
        <p>Mr. Cetron added that by the year 2000 "you won't be using a telephone: you'll have an information appliance." A flat screen mounted on a wall and linked to the device will pour practically everything, from office information to movies, into the home of the future.</p>
        <p>Eventually, these devices will be equipped with instant language translators, Mr. Cetron continued. "They will have two buttons," he said. "One for the language you wish to talk in and another for the language you want to hear in."</p>
        <p>With that, he said, the world will truly grow small.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
