<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Takes a Skeptic to Ignore Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LINDZEN, RICHARD S (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEL GENIO, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OPPENHEIMER, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LACIS, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E4DF1239F937A15755C0A960958260" item-length="385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Takes a Skeptic to Ignore Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your profile of Dr. Richard S. Lindzen of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (Science Times, June 18) misses some reasons he is isolated in his assessment that global warming will be of little significance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Your profile of Dr. Richard S. Lindzen of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (Science Times, June 18) misses some reasons he is isolated in his assessment that global warming will be of little significance.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lindzen says that the warming due to a doubling of carbon dioxide alone, with other factors like atmospheric water vapor held constant, would be only about 1 degree Fahrenheit, which he says would be of little consequence. In fact, this warming is known to an accuracy of about 10 percent to be 2.2 degrees Fahrenheit, a change that could produce the fastest global warming since the development of civilization.</p>
        <p>You report that this "presumed amplifying effect" of water vapor is "built into the computer models." It is not. The models "reflect the physics" of water  vapor to the best of our understanding. This physics includes Dr. Lindzen's "nullifying" processes, but these are overwhelmed by amplifying processes that he ignores.</p>
        <p>The magnitude of water vapor's effect is uncertain, but not the direction in  which it drives the climate. Precise satellite monitoring with available technology would help narrow this uncertainty.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lindzen argues that the climate response to volcanic eruptions supports his assertion of very low sensitivity of climate to the buildup of greenhouse gases. But research at the Goddard Institute of Space Studies on the climate response to the eruption in 1991 of Mount Pinatubo, the only eruption studied in detail, supports the range of climate sensitivity reported by computer models, 3 to 8 degrees Fahrenheit, rather than Dr. Lindzen's estimate.</p>
        <p>If there is little evidence to support Dr. Lindzen's scientific claims, there is even less to support his assertion that a bandwagon effect supported by a desire to obtain research grants is behind the greenhouse concern. Indeed, the National Academy of Sciences issued a report in 1992 with the following lead recommendation: "Despite the great uncertainties, greenhouse warming is a potential threat sufficient to justify action now."</p>
        <p>ANTHONY DEL GENIO ANDREW LACIS MICHAEL OPPENHEIMER New York, June 19, 1996 The writers are, respectively, physical scientists at the Goddard Institute for  Space Studies and chief scientist at the Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
