<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nuclear Byproduct Cleanses Stubborn Smokestack Pollutants</title>
    <meta content="03POLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="893269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dioxin (Chemical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uranium Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Incinerators</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Liverpool</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Nuclear Fuels (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hudson, Ian D (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hutchings, Graham J (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Wastes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E3D6133CF930A35751C1A960958260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nuclear Byproduct Cleanses Stubborn Smokestack Pollutants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stubborn stability of many of pollutants coming out of industrial smokestacks makes them hard to get out of air, but British researchers report that compounds appear to break down easily in presence of catalyst made from uranium oxide, byproduct of nuclear industry; researchers say uranium oxide catalyst can even clean up organic pollutants containing chloride, which are hardest to handle because when they are burned in incinerators they leave behind traces of more toxic compounds, like dioxins; team led by Dr Graham J Hutchings at University of Liverpool worked with Dr Ian D Hudson at British Nuclear Fuels, which financed work and holds patent; more than 1.1 billion pounds of air pollutants poured out of industrial smokestacks worldwide in 1994 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE stubborn stability of many of the pollutants coming out of industrial smokestacks makes it hard to keep them from getting into the air. But a team of British researchers reports that these volatile organic compounds appear to break down easily in the presence of a catalyst made from a byproduct of the nuclear industry: uranium oxide.</p>
        <p>The researchers say the uranium oxide catalyst can even clean up organic pollutants containing chlorine, which are the toughest to handle because when they are burned in incinerators, they leave behind traces of more toxic compounds, like dioxins. After the industrial pollutants pass over the catalyst, they break down into carbon dioxide, hydrochloric acid, which can be recycled, and trace amounts of carbon monoxide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE stubborn stability of many of the pollutants coming out of industrial smokestacks makes it hard to keep them from getting into the air. But a team of British researchers reports that these volatile organic compounds appear to break down easily in the presence of a catalyst made from a byproduct of the nuclear industry: uranium oxide.</p>
        <p>The researchers say the uranium oxide catalyst can even clean up organic pollutants containing chlorine, which are the toughest to handle because when they are burned in incinerators, they leave behind traces of more toxic compounds, like dioxins. After the industrial pollutants pass over the catalyst, they break down into carbon dioxide, hydrochloric acid, which can be recycled, and trace amounts of carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>That would be a lot easier to deal with than the dioxins and furans that are produced with incineration, said Dr. Graham J. Hutchings, a chemist who led the team doing the research at the University of Liverpool. They worked with Dr. Ian D. Hudson at British Nuclear Fuels, which financed the work and holds the patent; Dr. Hudson said he expected the company to commercialize the technology within a year.</p>
        <p>Industrial uranium oxide catalysts would be similar to the catalytic converters used to clean automobile exhaust. Dr. Bill T. Harnett, the associate director of the Air Quality Strategies and Standards Division of the Environmental Protection Agency, agreed that such a catalytic process would be good for the environment, despite the production of carbon dioxide, a gas that has been linked to global warming.</p>
        <p>The chlorine-containing organic compounds in industrial pollution pose serious problems if they get into the atmosphere, Dr. Harnett said. ''These are the kinds of compounds that people are looking at now for estrogen-mimicking effects,'' he said. ''They stay in the environment a long time and can be taken up by fish and plants and even work their way back up the food chain, magnifying their effects along the way. So a technique that could destroy them, without producing dioxins and furans, which are also persistent compounds, would be very desirable.''</p>
        <p>The common way to destroy stable organic pollutants, high-temperature incineration, is itself a source of pollutants, said Dr. Philip Gschwend, a professor of civil and environmental engineering at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Any change in the ideal conditions for the incinerator -- changes in temperature or oxygen concentrations, for example -- increases the production of toxic byproducts like dioxin, he said.</p>
        <p>He said some other technologies for handling organic pollutants were being tried -- one Boston-area company, Molten Metals, is using the high temperatures of melted metal to break down the compounds -- but  catalytic processes were ''certainly a logical choice.''</p>
        <p>The environmental burden from organic pollutants is large. In 1994, the most recent year for which data are available, more than 1.1 billion pounds of air pollutants poured out of industrial smokestacks nationwide, according to the Environmental Protection Agency's Toxic Release Inventory, and about 70 percent of that came from organic pollutants, the type the uranium oxide catalyst appears to be able to break down.</p>
        <p>While the scientists said in a paper published in the current issue of the journal Nature that their catalyst was highly efficient when pollutants were passed over it at concentrations and flow rates comparable to what would be found in industry, the experiments were run with one compound at a time. The researchers say their experience with compounds that are especially hard to break down indicates that the process would be able to handle polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, but none were tested.</p>
        <p>The researchers also need to work with combinations of chemicals to prove the method's practical value, said Dr. William J. Cooper, an environmental chemist at Florida International University. He is hopeful, however, that the process will prove feasible and could be useful in pollution problems other than smokestack emissions, like the cleaning of contaminated soil. After the soil is cleaned with a device he likened to a huge vacuum cleaner, the uranium oxide catalyst might be a good way to destroy the collected organic pollutants, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cooper said one problem confronting the technology is public antipathy to anything containing uranium. Even though the radioactive isotopes of uranium have been extracted from uranium oxide, ''radioactivity is what most people think about when they think of uranium,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hutchings said the amount of radioactivity in the uranium oxide was very small. ''If you had a jar of it and you put a Geiger counter on the outside of the glass, you wouldn't detect any radioactivity at all,'' he said. ''If you stood by the catalyst unit for one year, you would get a tenth of the background radiation received by a U.K. citizen.''</p>
        <p>Uranium oxide is of little value to the nuclear industry, and it poses the same problems of disposal as any heavy metal, so most of it is stored.</p>
        <p>British Nuclear Fuels plans to lease the uranium oxide to companies using the converters. Dr. Hudson said the uranium oxide would not contain the isotopes needed for nuclear fuel or weapons production and would need no special handling.  While catalysis can be less expensive and more efficient than incineration, the relative cost of uranium oxide catalysis is not yet known.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
