<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Vetoes Bill That Would Let Solar Panels Earn Credits on Energy Bills</title>
    <meta content="24VETO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="885356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vetoes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EED61330F937A15753C1A960958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Vetoes Bill That Would Let Solar Panels Earn Credits on Energy Bills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Oct. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Gov George Pataki vetoes legislation that would have allowed homeowners with solar panels on their roofs to send power back to their utility company and get credit on their electric bills (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Siding with the state's electricity industry, Gov. George E. Pataki has vetoed legislation that would have allowed homeowners with solar panels on their roofs to send power back to their utility company and get credit on their electric bills.</p>
        <p>In a statement today, the Governor said he supported the intent of the bill but was concerned about what he called inadequate safety standards in the measure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Siding with the state's electricity industry, Gov. George E. Pataki has vetoed legislation that would have allowed homeowners with solar panels on their roofs to send power back to their utility company and get credit on their electric bills.</p>
        <p>In a statement today, the Governor said he supported the intent of the bill but was concerned about what he called inadequate safety standards in the measure.</p>
        <p>But the veto, done on Friday and announced today, angered environmentalists, who regarded the bill as a key step toward encouraging New Yorkers to use a safer and cleaner form of energy. They dismissed Mr. Pataki's questions about safety as simply an excuse to kill a measure that utility companies had opposed for financial reasons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki ordered his staff to submit a new bill, saying that he would attempt to build consensus on the issue between the utility industry and the environmental community.</p>
        <p>''This veto should not be viewed by solar advocates as an unfavorable commentary on the solar industry,'' the Governor said. ''I believe solar power should be an important and larger component of our energy supply.''</p>
        <p>The veto illustrates the quandary the Governor faces as he tries to bolster his image as a friend of the environment without alienating powerful business organizations and his other traditional Republican supporters.</p>
        <p>He has already angered conservative anti-tax groups over his decision to add to the state's debt by lobbying on behalf of a $1.75 billion bond act to pay for environmental cleanup projects across the state.</p>
        <p>The bill vetoed by the Governor today would have allowed owners of single-family homes to install solar cells on their rooftops and run their electric meters backward to send spare electricity back to their utility companies. Thus the homeowners could have seen their electric bills drop to zero or even register a credit with their utility company.</p>
        <p>Only 30,000 homeowners would have been allowed to take advantage of the measure, which would have limited the amount of power produced by households to no more than one-tenth of one percent of New York's total power supply. Still, energy experts argued that the measure could lure a solar-cell manufacturer to the state, cut pollution and help avert blackouts during peak hours of power use.</p>
        <p>But the state's electric industry had been pressuring the Governor not to sign the bill. They argued that it would unfairly benefit wealthier homeowners who are able to invest the $10,000 to $30,000 it costs to install such a system, which typically is used to supplement power bought from a utility company.</p>
        <p>They also said it would in effect force utilities to buy solar-generated power at the same retail price that they charge their customers. As a result, they said, other customers would have to absorb the cost of buying the premium-priced power.</p>
        <p>Today, industry executives praised the Mr. Pataki's veto. ''That bill was a mistake,'' said Howard Shapiro, president of the Energy Association of New York, a lobbying group for the state's power producers. ''It would have been a Government imposed burden on ratepayer.''</p>
        <p>Still, the Governor said his main problem with the bill was that it did not provide adequate guidelines for the installation, testing and monitoring of the solar-energy systems -- an argument that was also made by the utility industry but rejected by environmentalists and other experts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki said that this posed a grave threat to utility workers who could, for example, be injured while repairing downed power lines that suddenly receive a burst of electricity from a solar cell mounted on someone's home.</p>
        <p>''I am not convinced that this bill completely addresses the paramount issue of safety for those who would be required to repair these systems after a power outage,'' he said. ''Despite this bill's admirable purpose and my support generally for renewable energy sources, I cannot sign this legislation in light of the safety concerns.''</p>
        <p>But environmentalists said the Governor had seized on this issue as a pretext to veto the legislation. They noted that the safety standards in the bill are nationally recognized and are in fact established by the National Electrical Code and the Underwriters Laboratories.</p>
        <p>''I think there was a lot of pressure from the utility industry and he bowed to that pressure,'' said Larry Shapiro, an environmental specialist with the New York Public Interest Research Group. ''The safety argument was bogus.''</p>
        <p>Still, environmentalists and one of the bill's sponsors, Steven Englebright, a Democrat from Long Island, said they would work to address the Governor's concerns and resubmit the legislation.</p>
        <p>''There's no safety issue,'' said Ashok Gupta, a Manhattan-based economist with the Natural Resources Defense Council and an author of the legislation. ''But to the extent that there is the perception of a safety issue, we will address it and get this bill passed and signed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
