<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Is It Getting Hot in Here, Or Is It an Alien Invasion?</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854251"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ARRIVAL, THE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DB1E39F932A05756C0A960958260" item-length="688" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Is It Getting Hot in Here, Or Is It an Alien Invasion?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Strip away the jargon and fancy technology in David Twohy's science-fiction thriller "The Arrival" and you have a gosh-oh-golly-gee 1950's-style adventure film about an excitable boy and his magic telescope. You also have a movie that  shoehorns a blunt warning into its silly but entertaining story of a young radio astronomer's one-man battle against sinister extraterrestrials.</p>
        <p>"If you can't tend to your own planet, maybe you don't deserve to live here," declares one glassy-eyed invader in tones so glacial he couldn't possibly be human.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Strip away the jargon and fancy technology in David Twohy's science-fiction thriller "The Arrival" and you have a gosh-oh-golly-gee 1950's-style adventure film about an excitable boy and his magic telescope. You also have a movie that  shoehorns a blunt warning into its silly but entertaining story of a young radio astronomer's one-man battle against sinister extraterrestrials.</p>
        <p>"If you can't tend to your own planet, maybe you don't deserve to live here," declares one glassy-eyed invader in tones so glacial he couldn't possibly be human.</p>
        <p>Speaking of glaciers, the tending of the planet to which the creature refers has to do with global warming. As part of their plan to take over the earth, the extraterrestrials are accelerating a destructive process that humans have already started. Taking earthly form, they have set up a network of giant power  stations in third world countries that are rapidly heating up the atmosphere. Sooner rather than later, the planet should be uninhabitable for humans and more congenial to its future occupants.</p>
        <p>Alien invaders in the movies tend to fall into two types. There are monsters  from outer space ("The War of the Worlds," the forthcoming "Independence Day") and infiltrators ("Invasion of the Body Snatchers") who slip in using human disguise. "The Arrival" belongs to the second category, although it has a few shots of the spindly creatures in their original form.</p>
        <p>The uncovering of the conspiracy begins when Zane Ziminski (Charlie Sheen), a radio astronomer whose job with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration is tuning into the heavens in search of intergalactic radio signals, receives one on his office screen. When Zane informs his boss, Gordian  (Ron Silver), of his discovery, he is shocked by his superior's disinterest and  in short order finds himself downsized out of a job. To continue his work, he rigs several local satellite dishes into a monitoring system, which eventually leads him to Mexico. There he meets Ilana Green (Lindsay Crouse), a climatologist whose research has also discovered strange pockets of atmospheric  heat in the area.</p>
        <p>"The Arrival," like so many science-fiction films, begins as a promisingly eerie mixture of pseudo-scientific exposition and chilly paranoia. But once its  plot has been bared, it turns into a muddled chase movie filled with glaring inconsistencies. Why, for instance, don't the film's evil aliens, who are capable of leaping to phenomenal heights, use their high-jump techniques when pursuing Zane across the Texan flatlands?</p>
        <p>Many of the film's special effects smack of gimcrackery. Giant, plastic scorpions are deployed to finish off one character. One of the aliens' favorite  toys is a whirling metal ball with little doors that can generate a kind of indoor tornado, sucking everything in a room into another dimension. With its luminous track lighting and sleek metal platforms, the alien underground power station Zane visits has the feel of a glowing disco inferno.</p>
        <p>To humanize the burning-eyed Zane, whom Mr. Sheen plays as a flipped-out zealot, the movie gives him an adorable sidekick in Kiki (Tony T. Johnson), a sassy little boy next door who helps him with his experiments. It also gives him a girlfriend named Char (Teri Polo), who is such a yuppie caricature she might as well be an extraterrestrial. As unsympathetic as she may be, Char has the movie's niftiest visual moment, a long-distance shot of her flailing like a wounded insect in the center of a white satellite dish.</p>
        <p>"The Arrival" is rated PG-13 (Parents strongly cautioned). It has sexual situations and mild violence.</p>
        <p>THE ARRIVAL</p>
        <p>Written and directed by David Twohy; director of photography, Hiro Narita; edited by Martin Hunter; music by Arthur Kempel; production designer, Michael Novotny; produced by Thomas G. Smith and Jim Steele; released by Live Entertainment. Running time: 109 minutes. This film is rated PG-13.</p>
        <p>WITH: Charlie Sheen (Zane Ziminski), Ron Silver (Gordian), Lindsay Crouse (Ilana Green), Tony T. Johnson (Kiki) and Teri Polo (Char).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
