<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With New Budget, Domestic Spending Is Cut $24 Million</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19960428T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="846612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGAL AID FOR THE POOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEAR, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALEXANDER, JANE WILLIAM JEFFERSON'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Aid for the Poor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EEDF1E39F934A15757C0A960958260" item-length="1455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With New Budget, Domestic Spending Is Cut $24 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PEAR, ROBERT;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The budget bill signed today by President Clinton, combined with other actions taken by Congress in the last year, will cut domestic spending by $24 billion, and most of the savings will come from housing, labor, education and Commerce Department programs.</p>
        <p>Democrats rescued a few of President Clinton's favorites, like the national service program known as Americorps. But Republicans squeezed spending across the board in a wide range of domestic programs, and many of the cuts were substantial.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The budget bill signed today by President Clinton, combined with other actions taken by Congress in the last year, will cut domestic spending by $24 billion, and most of the savings will come from housing, labor, education and Commerce Department programs.</p>
        <p>Democrats rescued a few of President Clinton's favorites, like the national service program known as Americorps. But Republicans squeezed spending across the board in a wide range of domestic programs, and many of the cuts were substantial.</p>
        <p>For example, Representative Sidney R. Yates, an Illinois Democrat who has served in the House for four decades, was exaggerating only a bit when he said that the 1996 appropriations bill "sounds the death knell for for Endowments for the Arts and the Humanities." The budget of the National Endowment for the Arts  will be cut 39 percent, to $99.5 million from $162.3 million last year. At its peak, in 1992, the endowment received $175.9 million.</p>
        <p>Jane Alexander, chairwoman of the arts endowment, said she was pleased that her agency had survived at all.</p>
        <p>"The cuts are substantial," Ms. Alexander said in an interview tonight. "But  the agency, which was once listed among the Republicans' top 10 targets for elimination, is alive." She said she believed the drive to eliminate the agency  had lost momentum. "We are on the way up," Ms. Alexander said. "It's important for artists and arts organizations not to despair."</p>
        <p>Still, Cherie L. Simon, a spokeswoman for the agency, said that museums and dance, music, theater and arts education programs would feel the effects of the  cuts.</p>
        <p>Money for the National Endowment for the Humanities, which supports a variety of scholarly and cultural programs, will be cut 36 percent, to $110 million from $172 million last year.</p>
        <p>In the vocabulary of Congress, outlays subject to annual appropriations are called discretionary spending. The Congressional Budget Office said today that domestic discretionary spending this year would be reduced 10 percent to $219.7  billion, from $243.7 billion last year. Most of the savings -- $16.2 billion of  the $24 billion -- result from Republican decisions to cancel authority to spend money that had been approved for the 1995 fiscal year. The remainder results from cuts enacted this year as part of 1996 appropriations.</p>
        <p>Military spending will rise by $1.9 billion, to $264.3 billion this year, the budget office said. Together, the two categories of discretionary spending account for less than one-third of the Federal budget, which totals $1.6 trillion this year.</p>
        <p>The agreement, which Congressional Republicans and the White House concluded  this week with immense difficulty, makes a modest contribution to the bipartisan goal of balancing the Federal budget in seven years. It does not affect interest payments on the Federal debt. Nor does it affect Medicare, Medicaid, welfare and other benefit programs whose financing is set by permanent laws, rather than by  annual appropriations. These benefit programs together account for slightly more than half of all Federal spending.</p>
        <p>Among the agencies sustaining budget cuts are the Education Department, which gets $25.2 billion this year, down from $26.8 billion last year; the Labor Department, which gets $8 billion, down from $8.4 billion, and the Department of Housing and Urban Development, which gets $19.1 billion, down from $24.7 billion. The Commerce Department, which some Republicans had sought to abolish,  receives $3.7 billion, down from $4 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Legal Services  Congress cut the budget of the Legal Services Corporation by 30.5 percent, to $278 million from $400 million, and imposed restrictions on the cases that may be handled by lawyers receiving Federal money.</p>
        <p>Alan W. Houseman, director of the Center for Law and Social Policy, a public-interest law firm that receives no money from the Government, said: "Thousands of low-income people with legal problems will no longer be able to receive legal assistance. Local legal-aid offices are being closed. Lawyers and  paralegals are being laid off."</p>
        <p>The Federal program distributes money to 323 legal service organizations with a total of 1,200 offices. Under the new law, the Legal Services Corporation may  not give money to any person or entity that "initiates or participates in a class-action suit." Such lawsuits have been used for years to enforce laws and protect the rights of people seeking Medicaid, welfare, housing, Social Security and disability benefits.</p>
        <p>The law also says that lawyers getting money from the agency may not represent prisoners or inmates; may not lobby and may not engage in litigation to "reform a Federal or state welfare system."</p>
        <p>International Aid  The new Federal budget will alleviate the financial crisis that has been gripping the United Nations and many other international organizations that depend heavily on American contributions.</p>
        <p>The budget provides $892 million for all international groups including the United Nations, up from $873 million last year. The 1996 figure is close to the  $923 million that President Clinton originally requested and much more than the  $700 million that would have been provided under a bill that he vetoed last fall.</p>
        <p>For peacekeeping operations, the Administration originally wanted $445 million. The new budget provides $359 million, but that is more than the $225 million earmarked last fall. At a news conference in Oslo, the United States representative to the United Nations, Madeleine K. Albright, expressed satisfaction with the new budget.</p>
        <p>The United States says it owes more than $1.2 billion in back dues to the United Nations, and the Administration has proposed to pay its obligations in installments over five years. But such payments depend on further action by Congress, and a State Department spokesman said today, "It will take a lot of persuading to get Congress to go along."</p>
        <p>Space and Technology  For the space agency, Congress provided $13.9 billion this year, down from $14.4 billion last year. It cut spending for the Environmental Protection Agency to $6.5 billion, from $7.2 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers cut several programs of particular interest to Vice President Al Gore. A program to encourage innovative technology that protects the environment was slashed to $10 million this year, from $72 million last year. A program to curb air pollution that contributes to global warming was cut to $80 million, from $108 million. And Congress eliminated a small program that teaches schoolchildren to observe and protect the environment by analyzing samples of water.</p>
        <p>Congress also cut one of President Clinton's favorite projects, the advanced-technology program of the Commerce Department, but did not eliminate it as many Republicans had wanted. The program will get $221 million, down from $341 million last year.</p>
        <p>The program, Mr. Clinton's biggest foray into Japanese-style industrial policy, provides grants to companies to develop high-risk technologies that seem too risky for venturecapital firms to underwrite.</p>
        <p>Health and Human Services  Overall, the appropriations for the Department of Health and Human Services will rise to $197.4 billion this year, from $179.2 billion in 1995. But the agency that finances research on mental health, drug abuse and alcoholism will get less money: $1.9 billion, down from $2.2 billion last year.</p>
        <p>Money for the Healthy Start program, which provides health care for young children, will be reduced to $93 million, from $104.2 million.</p>
        <p>Congress cut the Low-Income Home Energy Assistance Program by more than one-third. The program, which helps people pay heating bills, will get $900 million this year, down from $1.4 billion last year. The House had voted to eliminate the program, but the Senate insisted on providing $900 million. Fuel deliveries to some poor people were interrupted because of uncertainty over the  program last winter.</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Morra, a spokeswoman for the House Appropriations Committee, said the new law would eliminate the Bureau of Mines, a part of the Interior Department that received $152 million last year.</p>
        <p>Representative John R. Kasich, an Ohio Republican chairman of the House Budget Committee, said the new law made "the most significant reductions in Federal spending since World War II."</p>
        <p>"We have pried some money out of the hands of Washington bureaucrats," Mr. Kasich said.</p>
        <p>Representative David R. Obey, Democrat of Wisconsin, said it would save about the same amount as bills vetoed by Mr. Clinton, but "in a far more fair and balanced way."</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 28, 1996, Sunday</p>
        <p>A headline yesterday about the budget bill signed by the President misstated  the size of the cut in domestic government spending in some editions. The cuts total $24 billion, not $24 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 28, 1996, Sunday&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;    A headline yesterday about the budget bill signed by the President misstated  the size of the cut in domestic government spending in some editions. The cuts total $24 billion, not $24 million.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
