<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="863494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRIAL, FRANK J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Wine Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DB1139F933A25754C0A960958260" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PRIAL, FRANK J</byline>
      <dateline>VALLET, France</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE upon a time a week or two ago it sometimes seems -- the western reaches  of the Loire river were a long way from Paris. The trip took a day or two, down  through Chartres and Le Mans to meet the river, then along its banks to Ancenis  and finally Nantes, where the sky is pale and clear, the air smells of the sea and the tense, gritty capital is out of sight and mind.</p>
        <p>That was then: the TGV, the high-speed train, is now. Leave Gare Montparnasse at 7:50 A.M., read a newspaper, have coffee, watch the fields rocket by, and step out on the platform at Nantes at 9:59 A.M. I did just that last week to be  able to spend a day with Jean-Ernest Sauvion, a wine maker in this town in the vineyards 20 miles southeast of Nantes itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE upon a time a week or two ago it sometimes seems -- the western reaches  of the Loire river were a long way from Paris. The trip took a day or two, down  through Chartres and Le Mans to meet the river, then along its banks to Ancenis  and finally Nantes, where the sky is pale and clear, the air smells of the sea and the tense, gritty capital is out of sight and mind.</p>
        <p>That was then: the TGV, the high-speed train, is now. Leave Gare Montparnasse at 7:50 A.M., read a newspaper, have coffee, watch the fields rocket by, and step out on the platform at Nantes at 9:59 A.M. I did just that last week to be  able to spend a day with Jean-Ernest Sauvion, a wine maker in this town in the vineyards 20 miles southeast of Nantes itself.</p>
        <p>This is muscadet country, and Mr. Sauvion is one of the best-known producers of that pale, invigorating wine. Within minutes after arriving at his estate here, the Chateau du Cleray, I was in a laboratory confronted by 25 examples of  Sauvion wines, most of them muscadet. To someone who had been asleep in Paris a  few hours earlier, it was a formidable sight.</p>
        <p>But taste them we did, reaffirming that muscadet at its best is still one of  the most underestimated of the world's fine wines.</p>
        <p>To a generation of Americans who came to wine through full-bodied chardonnay, muscadet can seem thin and acidic. But no California chardonnay can enhance a skillfully cooked fish the way a muscadet can. Chardonnay will overwhelm a delicate fish; muscadet is an accompanist, not a rival.</p>
        <p>The Roman legions introduced vines here some 1,500 years ago. Later, Dutch traders planted folle blanche, a grape that had flourished farther south in the  Charente, where much of it was distilled into brandy. Early in the 18th century  came the melon de Bourgogne, a hearty grape with a leaf shaped like a melon. The melon de Bourgogne, now called muscadet, is the dominant varietal in the region. Of some 375,000 acres of vines in the Pays Nantais, as the area is called, 325,000 are muscadet. More than 200 million gallons of the wine are produced in  an average year.</p>
        <p>Folle blanche is still around. It's made into a rough acidic wine called gros plant, which sells well in local cafes. And truckloads of it go off to Germany,  where it's turned into third-rate sparkling wine. In a new book, "A Wine and Food Guide to the Loire" (Henry Holt, $27.50), Jacqueline Friedrich calls gros plant "a rude wine made from a rude grape."</p>
        <p>The best muscadet puts the best gros plant to shame. But muscadet has troubles of its own.</p>
        <p>"We had a string of bad years, and we had high prices at the same time," Mr.  Sauvion said. "Now we have a very good year in our cellars, 1995, and prices are more sensible. We think the good times are back."</p>
        <p>Muscadet has another problem: competition. Fresh, lively white wines with good acid are being made all over the world now, mostly from the sauvignon grape. Cloudy Bay and Stoneleigh from New Zealand, Mulderbosch from South Africa and a dozen sauvignons from Chile are all in the running. Aligote, once white Burgundies' despised cousin, has also taken on a new and glamorous life.</p>
        <p>These wines jostle for space on the shelves and in the minds of consumers who enjoy a crisp white wine with fish and all the good goat cheeses that are overwhelmed by most red wine.</p>
        <p>In fact, muscadet can compete with these wines. And when it comes to value for money, the best muscadets might just have an edge on most of them. That edge is the sur lie technique.</p>
        <p>"Sur lie" means "on its lees." In fermentation, yeast turns grape sugar into  alcohol and carbon dioxide. Then, the dead yeast cells drift to the the bottom of the barrel or tank. These dead cells are the lees. Some wines are pumped off  the lees. But in muscadet country, the best wines remain on the lees until the following spring or fall. The process adds a special richness and flavor to what is essentially a neutral wine to begin with. Some muscadet producers leave their wine on its lees for several years, even though the laws don't permit them to say so on their labels.</p>
        <p>Muscadet is not the only wine-producing region that values lees contact. Champagne has always done it. The best muscadets have always carried "sur lie" on their labels. Soon it will be embossed in raised letters on the front of each bottle.</p>
        <p>The French Government recognizes four muscadet appellations: Muscadet de Sevre-et-Maine, Muscadet des Coteaux de la Loire, Muscadet and Muscadet Cotes de Grand Lieu. The first two areas were established in 1936, the third in 1937 and  the fourth in 1994. Sevres-et-Maine is supposed to be the best.</p>
        <p>What constitutes the best in muscadet often depends on who's doing the constituting. Each year, Mr. Sauvion and some of his colleagues ask a jury of other wine makers along with sommeliers and chefs to pick out their best wines.  Mr. Sauvion calls whichever of his wines the jury picks "Cardinal Richard de Sauvion" after a prelate who once owned the Chateau de Cleray.</p>
        <p>Some producers want a system of village names as in Beaujolais, where Brouilly and Fleurie, for example, are considered superior to simple Beaujolais. Still other muscadet makers are pushing for vineyard ratings -- grand cru, premier cru -- the way it's done in Chablis.</p>
        <p>The men and women in muscadet country will be wrestling with these issues. Meanwhile, the wine is excellent; there is no reason not to go out and buy a bottle or two of what's available right now. Make sure it's sur lie. And don't forget the fish.</p>
        <p>TASTINGS</p>
        <p>Francis Coppola Family Wines Cabernet Franc 1994 (Napa Valley). About $19.</p>
        <p>This is one of a new line of wines made by Francis Ford Coppola's Niebaum-Coppola Estate at Rutherford, Calif., in the Napa Valley. The expensive  Rubicon is Niebaum-Coppola's best known wine. There has been an effort to make this line of Family Wines more approachable. The front label looks as if it were handwritten, and the back label conveys a story about how Mr. Coppola and his family originally made wines "for their own enjoyment." Cabernet franc is a component of many of the top Bordeaux wines and the most important red-wine grape in the Loire Valley. But in California it is still new. It is a bit more astringent than cabernet sauvignon, perhaps, but very much worth sampling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
