<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Three Cheers For Chicken Little</title>
    <meta content="29WINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Sky Is Falling" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="898351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="The Sky Is Falling"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DF1230F93AA15751C1A960958260" item-length="1473" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Three Cheers For Chicken Little</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on alarmism as a national obsession in United States; suggests that maybe alarms work as alarmists intended, waking up public to dangers that exist while there is still time to correct the situation; says recent history is filled with examples of Chicken Littles who have clearly had impact on their cause; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''TIME is running out,'' Peter G. Peterson, financier and former Federal servant, warns in his latest book, ''Will America Grow Up Before It Grows Old?'' Mr. Peterson is writing about the imminent bankruptcy of Medicare. No matter. It easily could have been global warming, overpopulation, declining sperm counts, drug-resistant germs, designer genes, nuclear terrorism, AIDS, the national debt, Apple Computer, Democrats, Republicans, the two-party system, wetlands, desertification, moral decline, moral zealots, killer asteroids or, for that matter, software that does not recognize the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Happy New Year? Right. Enjoy your delusion of a fresh start: the world is going to hell in a handbasket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''TIME is running out,'' Peter G. Peterson, financier and former Federal servant, warns in his latest book, ''Will America Grow Up Before It Grows Old?'' Mr. Peterson is writing about the imminent bankruptcy of Medicare. No matter. It easily could have been global warming, overpopulation, declining sperm counts, drug-resistant germs, designer genes, nuclear terrorism, AIDS, the national debt, Apple Computer, Democrats, Republicans, the two-party system, wetlands, desertification, moral decline, moral zealots, killer asteroids or, for that matter, software that does not recognize the year 2000.</p>
        <p>Happy New Year? Right. Enjoy your delusion of a fresh start: the world is going to hell in a handbasket.</p>
        <p>Or so it seems. There was a time -- the '50's -- when America was hopelessly upbeat, a place where men touted atomic bombs as friendly, if noisy, tunnel-diggers and Interstate highways as adventures in manifest destiny. Nineties America, on the precipice of a new millenium, paces anxiously and prays it doesn't trip and fall into the abyss. Alarmism is a national obsession. It is also big-time entertainment, rife with pop Cassandras hawking digitally enhanced jeremiads, egged on by a news business with a bottomless appetite for thrills.</p>
        <p>From the land of glee to the home of the grave -- are Americans getting too much of a bad thing?</p>
        <p>Of course they are. In their endless pursuit of a risk-free Utopia, Americans have developed a Texas-sized neurosis about mortal threats that never quite seem to match their advance billing.</p>
        <p>But that begs the real question: why doesn't the sky fall? And that question is a tougher one.</p>
        <p>Sure, plenty of alarms are raised over threats that are, to put it kindly, overstated. Some are undiluted hype; some may reflect the fact that Americans' threshold for a good scare has fallen as their lives have become more insulated from harm. Upton Sinclair struck terror in the hearts of carnivores 90 years ago by exposing horrendous meatpacking conditions in ''The Jungle.'' Today Scare City is bad hamburger at a Jack-in-the-Box, surely tragic and just as surely infrequent.</p>
        <p>But just as often, maybe, the sky doesn't fall because alarms work as the alarmists intended. Maybe the apocalypse never fully arrives because the alarmists' wretched excess frightens people into taking action. Maybe -- go ahead, choke on the words -- maybe the world will avoid fatal blunt asteroid trauma in 2050 because Dan Quayle urged the electorate in 1992 to watch for falling meteors.</p>
        <p>Maybe. There's no way to know for sure. The only evidence that an alarm works is in its being proved false -- which may also be evidence that the alarm was unnecessary to begin with. And from this it's hard to avoid the unsettling conclusion that a bit of windbaggery can work better than wisdom to insure the public good, at least sometimes. It's a shrill world, after all, and alarmism may be both a cause and a result of it.</p>
        <p>Recent history is filled with examples of Chicken Littles -- hype artists and otherwise -- who have clearly had an impact on their cause. The chairman of the Federal Reserve, Alan Greenspan, is an alarmist, and a good one. Mr. Greenspan is a fire bell against raging inflation. His latest tack was to imply (mostly by lifting his eyebrows) that the stock market has been taken over by lunatics and ought to fall. Other alarmists have said the same thing to no effect, but investors watch Mr. Greenspan's brows the way Filipinos watch Mount Pinatubo. The market fell, if briefly.</p>
        <p>Rachel Carson, the writer and biologist, single-handedly jump-started the environmental movement in 1962 with ''Silent Spring.'' She indulged in her share of exaggeration, devoting one heart-rending chapter to the looming extinction by pesticide poisoning of the American robin, a bird that was not a dodo then and is not now. That said, not many would deny that she had a good point, or that her book changed the world.</p>
        <p>Paul Ehrlich's 1968 jeremiad, ''The Population Bomb,'' said flatly that humankind's race against famine was over and man had lost; that starvation would sweep the world in the 1970's as the number of hungry mouths outstripped the food supply. The book altered Americans' basic concept of progress and popularized the idea of sustainable growth. It also was wrong: the 1970's ''green revolution'' eased the hunger crisis, at least for the time being. Modern famines occur because of political problems, not agricultural ones.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehrlich says his error was  scientific misjudgment, not hype, and still believes the day of reckoning has only been put off. He nevertheless agrees that ''The Population Bomb'' was a polemic, start to finish. ''It would be intellectually satisfying to say the real impact is through reasoned discourse,'' he said. ''But in my view the real impact isn't in reasoned discourse. Media attention, press coverage and, if necessary, alarmism at least set an agenda. And that way you can have a debate.''</p>
        <p>He is not exactly arguing that the end justifies the means. But as ''The Population Bomb'' shows, even the gravest alarm has a sort of credibility trip-wire. Forecast the apocalypse and at least one horseman had better show up quickly; long-term urgency is an oxymoron.</p>
        <p>The environmental movement has suffered a credibility backlash as its exponents have sounded louder alarms about the overheated, under-shielded, deforested planet while ordinary Americans gazed out their Ford windshields and saw less smog each summer than the one before.</p>
        <p>The environmentalists and the declining-America school of doomsayers have spawned their own counter-alarmist movements, squads of social and scientific bright-siders aiming to debunk the Gloomy Gusses. Some are flat-Earth types who deny the existence of obvious threats. But others like Gregg Easterbrook, who wrote a book about environmental alarmism, and Robert J. Samuelson and James Patterson, whose recent books question the basis of the national funk over jobs and living standards, are serious authors with serious points to make.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ehrlich, who has written a new book bemoaning the debunkers, argues that there is nothing less than a conspiracy to roll back environmental progress. Ben J. Wattenberg, the American Enterprise Institute scholar who may be the original counter-alarmist, says doomsayers in general are well-intended exaggerators -- he calls their tactics ''lying for truth'' -- but exaggerators nonetheless. In his view, alarmists divert people and money from real problems by raising the specter of a sky that is always about to fall, but never seems to actually start dropping.</p>
        <p>''Gomorrah, Gomorrah, I love ya, Gomorrah; you're always a day away,'' he mocks.</p>
        <p>Public-policy wise, Mr. Wattenberg is probably right. European scientists hurled half the planet into a tailspin last spring by declaring that male fertility was plummeting, perhaps due to pollution, only to have American scientists conclude six months later that males were plenty virile; it was the scientists' math that had lost its potency. Silicone breast implants terrified the other half of the planet and spawned a multibillion-dollar legal industry before other scientists began to conclude that the threat may have been artificially enhanced.</p>
        <p>But there are at least two flaws in asking alarmists to be reasonable, soft-spoken folk. For one thing, a reasonable alarmist is not an alarmist any more: he's the host of a Sunday news interview program, prattling on about the other hand. ''Will the Earth Remain Habitable?'' asked an Op-Ed article in The New York Times 10 years ago. Such a question does not deserve an answer like ''Some say yes; some say no; still others don't know.''</p>
        <p>The second is that the alarmists could be right. Dr. F. Sherwood Rowland was the butt of jokes in the 1980's when he began to suggest that spray deodorants and leaky car air conditioners posed a threat because they were eating away the Earth's shield of atmospheric ozone. Last year he won a Nobel Prize, and the world's production of chlorofluorocarbons has been cut so dramatically that the ozone layer is now expected to heal itself ahead of schedule.</p>
        <p>And though Mr. Quayle has never really recovered from his alerts about incoming meteors and Murphy Brown, many now agree that somewhere out there a rock big as Pluto probably has Earth's name on it, and that TV makes most cesspools look like Source Perrier.</p>
        <p>Alarmists can be self-promoting pains, and they are often wrong. So ignore them. How bad could life be on an Earth slow-cooking in a sauce of melted icebergs, populated by genetic experiments gone wild and fated to an eternity of Windows 95?</p>
        <p>The Sky Is Falling</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
