<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Investors Like This, Who Needs Salesmen?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="826057"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">I-STAT CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIDELITY ADVISOR STRATEGIC OPPORTUNITIES FUND</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WYATT, EDWARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANK, DANIEL R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blood</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E1DC1639F93BA15752C0A960958260" item-length="1523" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Investors Like This, Who Needs Salesmen?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WYATT, EDWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUTUAL fund managers are permitted and even expected to be big boosters of the stocks they buy. But one manager at Fidelity Investments appears to be taking the practice to a new extreme.</p>
        <p>Through his Fidelity Advisor Strategic Opportunities fund, the manager, Daniel R. Frank, has made a big bet on a little medical products company known as the I-Stat Corporation of Princeton, N.J., which has invented a faster way for hospitals to administer blood tests. Many hospitals, though, remain unconvinced that the company's single product is cost-effective.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUTUAL fund managers are permitted and even expected to be big boosters of the stocks they buy. But one manager at Fidelity Investments appears to be taking the practice to a new extreme.</p>
        <p>Through his Fidelity Advisor Strategic Opportunities fund, the manager, Daniel R. Frank, has made a big bet on a little medical products company known as the I-Stat Corporation of Princeton, N.J., which has invented a faster way for hospitals to administer blood tests. Many hospitals, though, remain unconvinced that the company's single product is cost-effective.</p>
        <p>To convince some hospitals in the Boston area, Mr. Frank personally lobbied  several of them to install the device and even donated his own money to one that agreed to give it a try.</p>
        <p>Such fervent behavior indicates how controversial the company really is. "I-Stat is a cult stock," said Carol Winslow, an analyst at Vector Securities International in Deerfield, Ill. "People either love it or hate it."</p>
        <p>The company makes a hand-held device that allows blood to be analyzed at a patient's bedside in less than two minutes, down from the 20 minutes or more it  takes a hospital to get results from a lab. Some critics, though, say the I-Stat System is more expensive than using a lab.</p>
        <p>That has left many hospitals on the sidelines, weighing the benefits of time  versus money. It has also left investors wondering whether a company that has never made a profit is really worth more than $30 a share.</p>
        <p>The debate is more than academic for investors. The company's stock jumped as high as $43.75 a share last summer after a $61 million cash infusion in a marketing deal with the Hewlett-Packard Company, which makes medical diagnostic  systems.</p>
        <p>I-Stat's stock has declined roughly 30 percent from its high, to $30.75. But  the company's total market value of $406 million is a fat seven times the $55 million in sales that some Wall Street analysts expect the company to produce this year, far more than investors typically pay for more mature companies in the industry. In addition, analysts are sharply divided over I-Stat's chances of earning a profit this year -- a feat it has never attained, even for one quarter, since going public in 1992.</p>
        <p>The stock has attracted a large number of short-sellers, who bet that a company's stock will fall. As of last month, more than 1.3 million shares had been sold short -- equivalent to about 14 days of trading.</p>
        <p>Evan Sturza, editor of Sturza's Medical Investment Letter, which has recommended shorting the stock, argues that the company's Wall Street supporters "are always looking to the next quarter or the next year, but I-Stat never lives up to expectations."</p>
        <p>But those supporters are just as adamant. "People who are shorting this stock are going to have their heads handed to them," said Michael P. DiCarlo, manager  of the John Hancock Special Equities fund, which owns more than 500,000 shares of I-Stat.</p>
        <p>William P. Moffitt, the charismatic chief executive of I-Stat, remains unbowed. "This technology, like any new, real innovation, is controversial when  it comes to market," he said.</p>
        <p>The I-Stat System includes a portable device about the size of a television remote controller, into which a disposable cartridge the size of a quarter is inserted. Drops of a patient's blood are placed in the cartridge, and in 90 seconds the I-Stat System measures the blood's level of sodium, potassium, glucose, arterial blood gases, carbon dioxide and other factors. Those blood tests are required in critical-care situations and can keep a doctor from having to wait for results from the hospital's diagnostic laboratory.</p>
        <p>In addition to the time saved, I-Stat says its system can cut costs as hospitals close down the "stat" labs that provide emergency tests. "We've had 60 or more hospitals that have closed their stat labs," Mr. Moffitt said, adding that about 400 hospitals are using the product. He estimates that, with staff and overhead included, the cost of a single blood test might be cut from $14 to  $7.</p>
        <p>Others debate that point. Without counting the expense of personnel and equipment, which a hospital already requires, the cost of doing a stat-lab blood test in the typical hospital lab is less than $1, said Dr. Petrie Rainey, associate director of clinical chemistry at Yale-New Haven Hospital.</p>
        <p>That is far less than the roughly $6 cost of each single-use cartridge for the I-Stat System, Dr. Rainey said. In addition, "laboratory testing is phenomenally regulated these days," and Yale-New Haven believed it would have had to add a staff member just to oversee use of the I-Stat. "It was a concern about those costs" that led the hospital to decide not to use the new product, Dr. Rainey said.</p>
        <p>Apart from the dispute over the value of the I-Stat System, the company has generated its own controversy. Last May, when I-Stat reported its financial results for the first quarter, the company announced that manufacturing problems had led it to "suppress demand" for two months, halting sales to new customers in January and February 1995. As a result, the quarter's sales were far below expectations. Some observers said the way the company handled the situation damaged its credibility with investors.</p>
        <p>"It is hard to believe they could withhold that kind of information," said Paul E. von Kuster, a portfolio manager at Peregrine Capital Management of Minneapolis, which held more than 100,000 shares in the company early last year.</p>
        <p>I-Stat's handling of the disclosure, together with the company's tendency to  repeatedly fall short of analysts' sales estimates and the recent departure of its chief financial officer, led Peregrine to sell its shares, Mr. von Kuster said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moffitt said that I-Stat disclosed the sales information when it was necessary and that a replacement search for a chief financial officer was under  way.</p>
        <p>Other investors remain steadfast in their support of I-Stat.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Frank, the Fidelity manager whose fund holds more than one million shares of I-Stat, donated about $5,000 to the Dana Farber Cancer Institute specifically for the purchase of an I-Stat System.</p>
        <p>Pearl Leavitt, administrative director of laboratories at Dana Farber, one of the more influential hospitals in the Northeast, said the gift enabled it to buy not only the hand-held unit, but also other equipment that she estimates would have cost the hospital close to $12,000.</p>
        <p>According to Nancy McDowell, former Northeast regional sales manager for I-Stat, the hospital was able to buy the more expensive system because I-Stat sold the unit at cost rather than at its list price. Moreover, Ms. McDowell said, Mr. Frank got in touch with other area hospitals offering to donate systems or the money to buy them.</p>
        <p>"He was acting like he was the sales manager for I-Stat," Ms. McDowell said.  "The Boston medical community reacted negatively to point-of-care testing, but I-Stat used Danny Frank to get into the hospitals."</p>
        <p>Mr. Moffitt disputed that notion and said that Ms. McDowell was dismissed from I-Stat last year for poor performance. Ms. McDowell said that she was laid  off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frank declined to be interviewed. Robyn Tice, a Fidelity spokeswoman, said the gift to Dana Farber was a "personal charitable contribution" and therefore did not present a conflict with Mr. Frank's role as fund manager. "To  suggest that a less-than-$5,000 equipment purchase would have a material effect  on the company's business is illogical," she said.</p>
        <p>It would not be unusual for a fund manager to research the market for a product like the I-Stat System by calling upon hospitals. But Mr. Frank's actions raise questions about whether he is distanced enough from the company to make objective decisions about its stock for his fund.</p>
        <p>I-Stat shares have appreciated about 140 percent since the fund bought its stake and at last tally accounted for more than 7 percent of assets -- so much that the fund cannot, under its charter, buy any more.</p>
        <p>Not all I-Stat observers remain as confident about the company's outlook. "We believe the point-of-care blood gas chemistry market will ultimately be a big business," said Ms. Winslow of Vector Securities. But because the process to manufacture the analysis cartridges is so complex and the overhead is so large,  the company will have to triple its production just to begin turning a profit, she said.</p>
        <p>Although she expects the company to do better than break even beginning in the third quarter, Ms. Winslow said, the stock "might be more interesting if it  was under $20."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
