<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends;Coal Tries for a Comeback</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekin Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19960310T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="833910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING FUEL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEINBERG, JACQUES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4D71139F930A35750C0A960958260" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends;Coal Tries for a Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACQUES STEINBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEINBERG, JACQUES</byline>
      <dateline>St. NICHOLAS VILLAGE, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STANDING against the side of a soot-streaked mountain, the cluster of rickety wooden buildings that comprise the Blaschak family coal company look as if time passed them by decades ago.</p>
        <p>So it's surprising to learn that a stream of trucks has begun to roll, once again, through the Pennsylvania countryside here, about 50 miles northwest of Allentown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STANDING against the side of a soot-streaked mountain, the cluster of rickety wooden buildings that comprise the Blaschak family coal company look as if time passed them by decades ago.</p>
        <p>So it's surprising to learn that a stream of trucks has begun to roll, once again, through the Pennsylvania countryside here, about 50 miles northwest of Allentown.</p>
        <p>But instead of bearing tons of loose coal destined for nearby steel mills and American military bases overseas -- once the 59-year-old Blaschak Coal Corporation's bread and butter -- these trucks are headed for suburban stove shops and lawn and garden centers from New Mexico to northern Maine.</p>
        <p>And the coal is packaged in easy-to-tote, white plastic bags, small enough to fit in a car trunk but big enough to keep a living room warm for days.</p>
        <p>Cheap Heating</p>
        <p>More than a half century after Americans began trading in their coal shovels for the convenience and efficiency of oil and gas, a group of coal producers and stove manufacturers are trying to persuade homeowners to take a fresh look at a fossil fuel dismissed long ago as filthy and cumbersome.</p>
        <p>But in trying to market coal as a cheaper alternative to oil and gas, and a cleaner choice than wood, the companies face hurdles: from an environmental lobby that did not exist in 1950, when more than a third of American homes still burned coal, to a collective belief, seared in the memories of many people over  40, that stoking a coal fire is too much work.</p>
        <p>The grade of coal that companies like Blaschak and the nearby Harman Stove Company are pushing for home heating is anthracite, or hard coal, not bituminous coal, its softer, smokier, better-known cousin. Bituminous coal continues to stoke power plants around the country, mostly because of its availability in huge quantities. Anthracite, which is mined almost exclusively in northeastern Pennsylvania, costs a bit more but burns more cleanly than the bituminous variety, giving off none of the smoke, smell or dust that make most grades of bituminous coal impractical for home use.</p>
        <p>The modern generation of anthracite coal stoves -- which look a lot like pot-bellied wood stoves -- are far more sophisticated than the great basement furnaces of old.  Where once coal stoves required constant vigilance and shoveling, the new models, which can cost about $2,000, are tethered to computerized thermostats and sometimes fed by automated hoppers, which can be loaded with up to 80 pounds of coal -- enough to heat several rooms, untended, for as many as three days. And the ashes are carted off, not in great cans as they once were, but in briefcase-size drawers that can be emptied into the garbage.</p>
        <p>Proponents say that an anthracite stove provides a relatively inexpensive supplement to the oil or gas that might heat the rest of the house. To generate  1 million B.T.U.'s of energy, or enough to heat an average home for about a day, a homeowner could spend roughly $4.97 on anthracite coal, $5.97 on natural gas or $5.69 on oil, saidHarold Schobert, chairman of the fuel sciences program at Pennsylvania State University. Those figures may vary in different localities.</p>
        <p>A pound of coal stacks up well against an equal quantity of wood, its biggest competitor in the supplemental heating market, producing more than twice as much energy and fewer pollutants, Mr. Schobert said.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists caution that while coal may be kinder to the air than burning logs, it poses a more dangerous environmental threat than either oil or  gas. It produces numerous contaminants, including sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, and an array of microscopic metallic particulates, and in far greater quantities. That coal stoves are not regulated by the Clean Air Act is a function only of the small number in use -- fewer than 300,000 homes nationwide  heat with coal, Federal officials said.</p>
        <p>"It sounds like a really bad idea to me," said Deborah Shprentz, an air pollution expert at the Natural Resources Defense Council, a private environmental group, "like heading back into the Dark Ages."</p>
        <p>Charles Daly, an auto technician, installed a coal stove in October to heat his three-bedroom farmhouse about 50 miles south of Buffalo. His fuel bills have been reduced by half during the past four months, he said. The major handicap, however, is bulk. When the winter is over, he will have used nearly a ton and a  half, or sixty 50-pound bags of Blaschak coal.</p>
        <p>"Whenever my boys go down to the basement," he said, "they come back up with  a bag of coal."</p>
        <p>Coal never came in immaculate white packages in Dickens's London, or, for that matter, in the American Northeast during the Depression. Then, dump trucks  poured coal into the cellars of homes and apartment houses. While bituminous coal fueled railroads and factories in the Midwest, anthracite became the dominant home-heating fuel in the Northeast and Middle Atlantic states during the early decades of this century.</p>
        <p>Coming Full Circle</p>
        <p>Since 1950, the use of the fuel with a dirty reputation has steadily waned,  supplanted by oil and, increasingly, gas, according to the United States Census  bureau. In 1991, the last year for which Census figures are available, 0.3 percent of American homes, or about 280,000, were warmed by coal.</p>
        <p>Still, there are glimmers of a revival. After slipping for six decades, the production of Pennsylvania anthracite rose to more than 8 million tons last year -- nearly double the amount mined just three years earlier, and more than in any other year since 1970, according to the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection. Driving that production, at least in part, is increased home demand, state officials said.</p>
        <p>Stove makers say they are seeing the increase, too. The Harman Stove Company, which is based about 15 miles north of Harrisburg and accounts for perhaps half the national sales in the coal stove market, said it sold 3,000 stoves last year, 50 percent more than five years ago. And Keystone Manufacturing, in nearby Schuylkill, said it sold 1,400 coal stoves last year, double the number in 1990.</p>
        <p>Although environmentalists worry that the new demand will only serve to inflict more scars on the pock-marked Appalachian mountains in Pennsylvania, Daniel R. Blaschak, 38, the company treasurer who represents the third generation of his family to mine coal here, said his company has grown more respectful of its surroundings. He said that as it continues to dig deeper for coal, it is sealing the open tunnels his ancestors drilled -- which have long polluted nearby rivers when it rains -- and has started to replant the bald surfaces of old mines with grass.</p>
        <p>"It is back around full circle," he said, a line of white bags of coal chattering down an assembly line behind him, "applying modern technology to what we had in the beginning."</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 10, 1996, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in the Week in Review on March 3, with an article about the use of coal for home heating misstated the location of the Blaschak Coal Corporation. It is in St. Nicholas Village, Pennsylvania, not Nazareth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 10, 1996, Sunday&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;    A picture caption in the Week in Review on March 3, with an article about the use of coal for home heating misstated the location of the Blaschak Coal Corporation. It is in St. Nicholas Village, Pennsylvania, not Nazareth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
