<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From Platform Adopted by Republican National Convention</title>
    <meta content="13TEXT$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE REPUBLICANS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="871261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE REPUBLICANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Diego (Calif)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Diego</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EFDF1731F930A2575BC0A960958260" item-length="2481" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From Platform Adopted by Republican National Convention</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from platform adopted by Republicans at National Convention in San Diego (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the platform adopted yesterday by the Republican National Convention.</p>
        <p>PREAMBLE</p>
        <p>We meet to nominate a candidate and pass a platform at a moment of measureless national opportunity. A new century beckons, and Americans are more than equal to its challenges. But there is a problem. The Clinton Administration has proven unequal to the heritage of our past, the promise of our times, and the character of the American people. . . .</p>
        <p>This is what we want for America: real prosperity that reaches beyond the stock market to every family, small business and worker. An economy expanding as fast as American enterprise and creativity will carry it, free from unnecessary taxes, regulation and litigation.</p>
        <p>This is what we want for America: the restoration of self-government by breaking Washington's monopoly on power. The American people want their country back. We will help them to regain it.</p>
        <p>This too we want for America: moral clarity in our culture and ethical leadership in the White House. . . .</p>
        <p>BUILDING A STRONGER AMERICA</p>
        <p>Tax Relief for Economic Growth</p>
        <p>American families are suffering from the twin burdens of stagnant incomes and near-record taxes. This is the key cause of middle-class anxiety. It is why people feel they are working harder but falling further behind; why they fear the current generation will not be as successful as the last generation; why they believe their children will be worse off; and why they feel so anxious about their own economic future.</p>
        <p>In response to this unprecedented burden confronting America, we support an across-the-board, 15-percent tax cut to marginal tax rates. Fifteen percent represents the total increase in the Federal tax burden since Bill Clinton took office. . .</p>
        <p>If the personal and dependent exemption that was $600 in 1950 had kept pace with inflation, it would be $3,800 rather than the current $2,500. That is why Republicans have made the $500-per-child family tax credit one of the primary features of our tax cut package. . . .</p>
        <p>Today's personal savings rate is less than half what it was two decades ago. Republicans support expansion of I.R.A.'s and the establishment of spousal I.R.A.'s to encourage savings and investment. . . .</p>
        <p>To remove impediments to job creation and economic growth, we support reducing the top tax rate on capital gains by 50 percent. . . .</p>
        <p>We firmly commit to a tax code for the 21st century that will raise revenue sufficient for a smaller, more effective and less wasteful government without increasing the national debt. . . .</p>
        <p>Balancing the Budget And Reducing Spending</p>
        <p>Once and for all, we declare:</p>
        <p>*The budget deficit and high taxes are two halves of the vise that is producing the Clinton middle-class squeeze;</p>
        <p>*A balanced budget and lower taxes go hand in hand, not in separate directions;</p>
        <p>*Reducing the budget deficit by shrinking government produces a fiscal dividend in stronger growth and lower interest rates;</p>
        <p>*Ending that deficit will make possible a dramatic return of resources to the American people;</p>
        <p>*Tax relief is the only way to return the economy to the growth rates our country enjoyed from World War II to the coming of Bill Clinton; and</p>
        <p>*We will not mortgage our children's future by incurring deficits.</p>
        <p>Creating Jobs for Americans</p>
        <p>. . . In addition to our overall program of lower taxes, regulatory reform, and less spending, we will:</p>
        <p>*Allow small businesses to deduct the costs of their health insurance;</p>
        <p>*Restore the fair home-office deduction so important to start-up businesses;</p>
        <p>*Assure that no one who inherits a small business or farm has to sell it to pay inheritance taxes;</p>
        <p>*Make the I.R.S. stop its discrimination against independent contractors;</p>
        <p>*Enact both legal reform and product liability legislation to shield small businesses and protect jobs from the threat of unfair litigation; and</p>
        <p>*Transfer from the public sector services that can be provided by the private sector more efficiently and cost effectively.</p>
        <p>Home Ownership</p>
        <p>. . . We affirm our commitment to open housing, without quotas or controls, and we condemn the Clinton Administration's abuse of fair housing laws to harass citizens exercising their First Amendment rights.</p>
        <p>In addition, we support transforming public housing into private housing, converting low-income families into proud homeowners. Resident management of public housing is a first step toward that goal, which includes eliminating the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). HUD's core functions will be turned over to the states. Its civil rights component will be administered by the appropriate Federal agency, while enforcement will remain with the Department of Justice. . . .</p>
        <p>Promoting Trade And International Prosperity</p>
        <p>. . . Exports already fuel our economy; their continuing expansion is essential for full employment and long-term prosperity. That is possible only within the context of expanding trade, and we can do it better without a Department of Commerce. . . .</p>
        <p>Republicans are for vigorous enforcement of the trade agreements we already have on the books, unlike the Clinton Administration that uses United States trade policy as a bargaining chip and as a vehicle for pursuing a host of other social agenda items. . . .</p>
        <p>To advance economic freedom, we insist that United States foreign aid, whether bilateral or through the World Bank and International Monetary Fund, promote market reforms, limit regulation and encourage free trade. Republicans will stop subsidizing socialism in the less developed nations. Republicans will not allow the World Trade Organization to undermine United States sovereignty and will support a World Trade Organization oversight commission. . . .</p>
        <p>Changing Washington From The Ground Up</p>
        <p>. . . As a first step in reforming government, we support elimination of the Departments of Commerce, Housing and Urban Development, Education, and Energy . . . $(Other$) agencies we seek to defund or to privatize are the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, and the Legal Services Corporation.</p>
        <p>A Citizens' Congress</p>
        <p>. . . We will eliminate made-in-Washington schemes to rig the election process under the guise of campaign reform. True reform is indeed needed: ending taxpayer subsidies for campaigns, strengthening party structures to guard against rogue operations, requiring full and immediate disclosure of all contributions, and cracking down on the indirect support, or ''soft money,'' by which special interest groups underwrite their favored candidates.</p>
        <p>Cleaning Up Government</p>
        <p>It is time to restore honor and integrity to government. We propose to:</p>
        <p>*Revoke pension rights of public officials who have been convicted of crimes;</p>
        <p>*Strengthen citizen privacy laws and reform the F.B.I. to guard against the politicization of law enforcement that we have seen by the Clinton White House;</p>
        <p>*Refuse to allow special interest groups to block innovative solutions for the poor or to block workplace or legal reforms that would help all working Americans. . . .</p>
        <p>Restoring Justice to the Courts</p>
        <p>. . . The Federal judiciary, including the U.S. Supreme Court, has overstepped its authority under the Constitution. It has usurped the right of citizen legislators and popularly elected executives to make law by declaring duly enacted laws to be ''unconstitutional'' through the misapplication of the principle of judicial review. . . .</p>
        <p>INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS AND PERSONAL SAFETY</p>
        <p>Upholding the Rights of All</p>
        <p>. . . As we strive to forge a national consensus on the divisive issues of our time, we call on all Republicans and all Americans to reject the forces of hatred and bigotry. Accordingly, we denounce all who practice or promote racism, anti-Semitism, ethnic prejudice, and religious intolerance. . . .</p>
        <p>We endorse the Defense of Marriage Act to prevent states from being forced to recognize same-sex unions. . . .</p>
        <p>We likewise endorse this year's Proposition 209, the California Civil Rights Initiative, to restore to law the original meaning of civil rights. . . .</p>
        <p>The unborn child has a fundamental individual right to life which cannot be infringed. We support a human life amendment to the Constitution and we endorse legislation to make clear that the 14th Amendment's protections apply to unborn children. . . .</p>
        <p>A Sensible Immigration Policy</p>
        <p>As a nation of immigrants, we welcome those who follow our laws. . . . At the same time, we are determined to reform the system by which we welcome them. . . .</p>
        <p>Illegal aliens should not receive public benefits other than emergency aid, and those who become parents while illegally in the United States should not be qualified to claim benefits for their offspring. . . .</p>
        <p>We support a constitutional amendment or constitutionally-valid legislation declaring that children born in the United States of parents who are not legally present in the United States or who are not long-term residents are not automatically citizens.</p>
        <p>FAMILIES AND SOCIETY</p>
        <p>Improving Education</p>
        <p>. . . Our goal is nothing less than a renaissance in American education . . .</p>
        <p>We will abolish the Department of Education, end Federal meddling in our schools, and promote family choice at all levels of learning. We therefore call for prompt repeal of the Goals 2000 program . . .</p>
        <p>Renewing Hope and Opportunity</p>
        <p>. . . Because illegitimacy is the most serious cause of child poverty, we will encourage states to stop cash payments to unmarried teens and set a family cap on payments for additional children. . . .</p>
        <p>To promote personal involvement with anti-poverty efforts, we call for a Charity Tax Credit. . . . To insure that religiously affiliated institutions can fulfill their helping mission, we endorse Republican legislation to stop discrimination against them in government programs.</p>
        <p>A CLEANER, SAFER, HEALTHIER AMERICA</p>
        <p>. . . While we have made substantial environmental progress, we must reject failed approaches created by fear-mongering and centralized control. . . .</p>
        <p>The current Endangered Species Act is seriously flawed. . . . We will improve the E.S.A. by implementing an incentive-based program in cooperation with state, local, and tribal governments and private individuals to recognize the critical relationship between a healthy environment and a healthy economy founded on private property rights . . .</p>
        <p>Improving Public Lands</p>
        <p>We support a thorough review of the lands owned by the Federal Government with a goal of transferring lands that can best be managed by State, county, or municipal governments. This review should insure that the Federal Government retains ownership to unique property worthy of national oversight. . . .</p>
        <p>Power for Progress</p>
        <p>. . . The United States should continue its commitment to addressing global climate change in a prudent and effective manner that does not punish the U.S. economy. Despite scientific uncertainty about the role of human activity in climate change, the Clinton Administration has leapfrogged over reasoned scientific inquiry and now favors misdirected measures. . . .</p>
        <p>Republicans deplore the arbitrary and premature abandonment of the previous policy of voluntary reductions of greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>RESTORING AMERICAN WORLD LEADERSHIP</p>
        <p>The Atlantic Alliance and Europe</p>
        <p>The Atlantic Alliance: Our relations with the nations of Europe must continue to be based on the NATO alliance. . . . We call for the immediate expansion of the framework for peace to include those countries of Central Europe which demonstrate the strongest commitment to the democratic ideals NATO was created to protect. . . .</p>
        <p>Bosnia: We support America's men and women in uniform who are serving in Bosnia and Herzegovina. However, we did not support the ill-conceived and inconsistent policies that led to their deployment. . . . We look forward to a timely withdrawal of U.S. forces from Bosnia. . . .</p>
        <p>We have a national interest in a security relationship with a democratic Russia. Specifically, we will encourage Russia to respect the sovereignty and independence of its neighbors; support a special security arrangement between Russia and NATO, but not Moscow's veto over NATO enlargement; support Russian entry to the G-7 after its reforms have been achieved; and link U.S. assistance to Russian adherence to international treaty obligations. . . .</p>
        <p>Defending America Against Missile Attack</p>
        <p>The Republican Party is committed to the protection of all Americans -- including our two million citizens in Alaska and Hawaii -- against missile attack. . . . We therefore endorse the Defend America Act of 1996, introduced by Senator Bob Dole, which calls for a national missile defense system for all 50 states by the year 2003. . . .</p>
        <p>To cope with the threat of the proliferation of weapons of mass destruction, the United States will have to deter the threat or use of weapons of mass destruction by rogue states. This in turn will require the continuing maintenance and development of nuclear weapons and their periodic testing. The Clinton Administration's proposed Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty is inconsistent with American security interests. . . .</p>
        <p>The Middle East</p>
        <p>. . . We reaffirm that Republican commitment to maintain Israel's qualitative military advantage over any adversary or group of adversaries. While we fully support Israel's efforts to find peace and security with its neighbors, we will judge the peace process by the security it generates both for Israel and for the United States. In that context, we support Israel's right to make its own decisions regarding security and boundaries. . . .</p>
        <p>Space</p>
        <p>The Republican Party led America into space and remains committed to its exploration and mastery. . . . We look toward our country's return to the moon and to completion of the International Space Station. . . . We will develop the Reusable Launch Vehicle, promote markets for commercial space launch services. . . .</p>
        <p>APPENDIX I: MINORITY VIEWS</p>
        <p>Amendments Considered By the Full Committee on Resolutions</p>
        <p>Individual Rights and Personal Safety</p>
        <p>. . . The Republican Party welcomes individuals on each side of the abortion issue, encourages their open discussion, solicits their active participation in the Party, and respects their positions and beliefs. . . .</p>
        <p>We are committed as a party and as individuals to significantly reducing the number of abortions. . . . We believe that the decline in abortions we seek will be far better achieved by persuasion of individuals to choose -- as a matter of individual conscience -- behavior that will not produce unwanted pregnancies, than by governmental mandate and invasion of privacy. . . .  Unlike the Democratic Party, we will not censor members of our party who hold opposing views on this issue. We are a party confident enough in our beliefs to tolerate dissent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the platform adopted yesterday by the Republican National Convention.</p>
        <p>PREAMBLE</p>
        <p>We meet to nominate a candidate and pass a platform at a moment of measureless national opportunity. A new century beckons, and Americans are more than equal to its challenges. But there is a problem. The Clinton Administration has proven unequal to the heritage of our past, the promise of our times, and the character of the American people. . . .</p>
        <p>This is what we want for America: real prosperity that reaches beyond the stock market to every family, small business and worker. An economy expanding as fast as American enterprise and creativity will carry it, free from unnecessary taxes, regulation and litigation.</p>
        <p>This is what we want for America: the restoration of self-government by breaking Washington's monopoly on power. The American people want their country back. We will help them to regain it.</p>
        <p>This too we want for America: moral clarity in our culture and ethical leadership in the White House. . . .</p>
        <p>BUILDING A STRONGER AMERICA</p>
        <p>Tax Relief for Economic Growth</p>
        <p>American families are suffering from the twin burdens of stagnant incomes and near-record taxes. This is the key cause of middle-class anxiety. It is why people feel they are working harder but falling further behind; why they fear the current generation will not be as successful as the last generation; why they believe their children will be worse off; and why they feel so anxious about their own economic future.</p>
        <p>In response to this unprecedented burden confronting America, we support an across-the-board, 15-percent tax cut to marginal tax rates. Fifteen percent represents the total increase in the Federal tax burden since Bill Clinton took office. . .</p>
        <p>If the personal and dependent exemption that was $600 in 1950 had kept pace with inflation, it would be $3,800 rather than the current $2,500. That is why Republicans have made the $500-per-child family tax credit one of the primary features of our tax cut package. . . .</p>
        <p>Today's personal savings rate is less than half what it was two decades ago. Republicans support expansion of I.R.A.'s and the establishment of spousal I.R.A.'s to encourage savings and investment. . . .</p>
        <p>To remove impediments to job creation and economic growth, we support reducing the top tax rate on capital gains by 50 percent. . . .</p>
        <p>We firmly commit to a tax code for the 21st century that will raise revenue sufficient for a smaller, more effective and less wasteful government without increasing the national debt. . . .</p>
        <p>Balancing the Budget And Reducing Spending</p>
        <p>Once and for all, we declare:</p>
        <p>*The budget deficit and high taxes are two halves of the vise that is producing the Clinton middle-class squeeze;</p>
        <p>*A balanced budget and lower taxes go hand in hand, not in separate directions;</p>
        <p>*Reducing the budget deficit by shrinking government produces a fiscal dividend in stronger growth and lower interest rates;</p>
        <p>*Ending that deficit will make possible a dramatic return of resources to the American people;</p>
        <p>*Tax relief is the only way to return the economy to the growth rates our country enjoyed from World War II to the coming of Bill Clinton; and</p>
        <p>*We will not mortgage our children's future by incurring deficits.</p>
        <p>Creating Jobs for Americans</p>
        <p>. . . In addition to our overall program of lower taxes, regulatory reform, and less spending, we will:</p>
        <p>*Allow small businesses to deduct the costs of their health insurance;</p>
        <p>*Restore the fair home-office deduction so important to start-up businesses;</p>
        <p>*Assure that no one who inherits a small business or farm has to sell it to pay inheritance taxes;</p>
        <p>*Make the I.R.S. stop its discrimination against independent contractors;</p>
        <p>*Enact both legal reform and product liability legislation to shield small businesses and protect jobs from the threat of unfair litigation; and</p>
        <p>*Transfer from the public sector services that can be provided by the private sector more efficiently and cost effectively.</p>
        <p>Home Ownership</p>
        <p>. . . We affirm our commitment to open housing, without quotas or controls, and we condemn the Clinton Administration's abuse of fair housing laws to harass citizens exercising their First Amendment rights.</p>
        <p>In addition, we support transforming public housing into private housing, converting low-income families into proud homeowners. Resident management of public housing is a first step toward that goal, which includes eliminating the Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD). HUD's core functions will be turned over to the states. Its civil rights component will be administered by the appropriate Federal agency, while enforcement will remain with the Department of Justice. . . .</p>
        <p>Promoting Trade And International Prosperity</p>
        <p>. . . Exports already fuel our economy; their continuing expansion is essential for full employment and long-term prosperity. That is possible only within the context of expanding trade, and we can do it better without a Department of Commerce. . . .</p>
        <p>Republicans are for vigorous enforcement of the trade agreements we already have on the books, unlike the Clinton Administration that uses United States trade policy as a bargaining chip and as a vehicle for pursuing a host of other social agenda items. . . .</p>
        <p>To advance economic freedom, we insist that United States foreign aid, whether bilateral or through the World Bank and International Monetary Fund, promote market reforms, limit regulation and encourage free trade. Republicans will stop subsidizing socialism in the less developed nations. Republicans will not allow the World Trade Organization to undermine United States sovereignty and will support a World Trade Organization oversight commission. . . .</p>
        <p>Changing Washington From The Ground Up</p>
        <p>. . . As a first step in reforming government, we support elimination of the Departments of Commerce, Housing and Urban Development, Education, and Energy . . . $(Other$) agencies we seek to defund or to privatize are the National Endowment for the Arts, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the Corporation for Public Broadcasting, and the Legal Services Corporation.</p>
        <p>A Citizens' Congress</p>
        <p>. . . We will eliminate made-in-Washington schemes to rig the election process under the guise of campaign reform. True reform is indeed needed: ending taxpayer subsidies for campaigns, strengthening party structures to guard against rogue operations, requiring full and immediate disclosure of all contributions, and cracking down on the indirect support, or ''soft money,'' by which special interest groups underwrite their favored candidates.</p>
        <p>Cleaning Up Government</p>
        <p>It is time to restore honor and integrity to government. We propose to:</p>
        <p>*Revoke pension rights of public officials who have been convicted of crimes;</p>
        <p>*Strengthen citizen privacy laws and reform the F.B.I. to guard against the politicization of law enforcement that we have seen by the Clinton White House;</p>
        <p>*Refuse to allow special interest groups to block innovative solutions for the poor or to block workplace or legal reforms that would help all working Americans. . . .</p>
        <p>Restoring Justice to the Courts</p>
        <p>. . . The Federal judiciary, including the U.S. Supreme Court, has overstepped its authority under the Constitution. It has usurped the right of citizen legislators and popularly elected executives to make law by declaring duly enacted laws to be ''unconstitutional'' through the misapplication of the principle of judicial review. . . .</p>
        <p>INDIVIDUAL RIGHTS AND PERSONAL SAFETY</p>
        <p>Upholding the Rights of All</p>
        <p>. . . As we strive to forge a national consensus on the divisive issues of our time, we call on all Republicans and all Americans to reject the forces of hatred and bigotry. Accordingly, we denounce all who practice or promote racism, anti-Semitism, ethnic prejudice, and religious intolerance. . . .</p>
        <p>We endorse the Defense of Marriage Act to prevent states from being forced to recognize same-sex unions. . . .</p>
        <p>We likewise endorse this year's Proposition 209, the California Civil Rights Initiative, to restore to law the original meaning of civil rights. . . .</p>
        <p>The unborn child has a fundamental individual right to life which cannot be infringed. We support a human life amendment to the Constitution and we endorse legislation to make clear that the 14th Amendment's protections apply to unborn children. . . .</p>
        <p>A Sensible Immigration Policy</p>
        <p>As a nation of immigrants, we welcome those who follow our laws. . . . At the same time, we are determined to reform the system by which we welcome them. . . .</p>
        <p>Illegal aliens should not receive public benefits other than emergency aid, and those who become parents while illegally in the United States should not be qualified to claim benefits for their offspring. . . .</p>
        <p>We support a constitutional amendment or constitutionally-valid legislation declaring that children born in the United States of parents who are not legally present in the United States or who are not long-term residents are not automatically citizens.</p>
        <p>FAMILIES AND SOCIETY</p>
        <p>Improving Education</p>
        <p>. . . Our goal is nothing less than a renaissance in American education . . .</p>
        <p>We will abolish the Department of Education, end Federal meddling in our schools, and promote family choice at all levels of learning. We therefore call for prompt repeal of the Goals 2000 program . . .</p>
        <p>Renewing Hope and Opportunity</p>
        <p>. . . Because illegitimacy is the most serious cause of child poverty, we will encourage states to stop cash payments to unmarried teens and set a family cap on payments for additional children. . . .</p>
        <p>To promote personal involvement with anti-poverty efforts, we call for a Charity Tax Credit. . . . To insure that religiously affiliated institutions can fulfill their helping mission, we endorse Republican legislation to stop discrimination against them in government programs.</p>
        <p>A CLEANER, SAFER, HEALTHIER AMERICA</p>
        <p>. . . While we have made substantial environmental progress, we must reject failed approaches created by fear-mongering and centralized control. . . .</p>
        <p>The current Endangered Species Act is seriously flawed. . . . We will improve the E.S.A. by implementing an incentive-based program in cooperation with state, local, and tribal governments and private individuals to recognize the critical relationship between a healthy environment and a healthy economy founded on private property rights . . .</p>
        <p>Improving Public Lands</p>
        <p>We support a thorough review of the lands owned by the Federal Government with a goal of transferring lands that can best be managed by State, county, or municipal governments. This review should insure that the Federal Government retains ownership to unique property worthy of national oversight. . . .</p>
        <p>Power for Progress</p>
        <p>. . . The United States should continue its commitment to addressing global climate change in a prudent and effective manner that does not punish the U.S. economy. Despite scientific uncertainty about the role of human activity in climate change, the Clinton Administration has leapfrogged over reasoned scientific inquiry and now favors misdirected measures. . . .</p>
        <p>Republicans deplore the arbitrary and premature abandonment of the previous policy of voluntary reductions of greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>RESTORING AMERICAN WORLD LEADERSHIP</p>
        <p>The Atlantic Alliance and Europe</p>
        <p>The Atlantic Alliance: Our relations with the nations of Europe must continue to be based on the NATO alliance. . . . We call for the immediate expansion of the framework for peace to include those countries of Central Europe which demonstrate the strongest commitment to the democratic ideals NATO was created to protect. . . .</p>
        <p>Bosnia: We support America's men and women in uniform who are serving in Bosnia and Herzegovina. However, we did not support the ill-conceived and inconsistent policies that led to their deployment. . . . We look forward to a timely withdrawal of U.S. forces from Bosnia. . . .</p>
        <p>We have a national interest in a security relationship with a democratic Russia. Specifically, we will encourage Russia to respect the sovereignty and independence of its neighbors; support a special security arrangement between Russia and NATO, but not Moscow's veto over NATO enlargement; support Russian entry to the G-7 after its reforms have been achieved; and link U.S. assistance to Russian adherence to international treaty obligations. . . .</p>
        <p>Defending America Against Missile Attack</p>
        <p>The Republican Party is committed to the protection of all Americans -- including our two million citizens in Alaska and Hawaii -- against missile attack. . . . We therefore endorse the Defend America Act of 1996, introduced by Senator Bob Dole, which calls for a national missile defense system for all 50 states by the year 2003. . . .</p>
        <p>To cope with the threat of the proliferation of weapons of mass destruction, the United States will have to deter the threat or use of weapons of mass destruction by rogue states. This in turn will require the continuing maintenance and development of nuclear weapons and their periodic testing. The Clinton Administration's proposed Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty is inconsistent with American security interests. . . .</p>
        <p>The Middle East</p>
        <p>. . . We reaffirm that Republican commitment to maintain Israel's qualitative military advantage over any adversary or group of adversaries. While we fully support Israel's efforts to find peace and security with its neighbors, we will judge the peace process by the security it generates both for Israel and for the United States. In that context, we support Israel's right to make its own decisions regarding security and boundaries. . . .</p>
        <p>Space</p>
        <p>The Republican Party led America into space and remains committed to its exploration and mastery. . . . We look toward our country's return to the moon and to completion of the International Space Station. . . . We will develop the Reusable Launch Vehicle, promote markets for commercial space launch services. . . .</p>
        <p>APPENDIX I: MINORITY VIEWS</p>
        <p>Amendments Considered By the Full Committee on Resolutions</p>
        <p>Individual Rights and Personal Safety</p>
        <p>. . . The Republican Party welcomes individuals on each side of the abortion issue, encourages their open discussion, solicits their active participation in the Party, and respects their positions and beliefs. . . .</p>
        <p>We are committed as a party and as individuals to significantly reducing the number of abortions. . . . We believe that the decline in abortions we seek will be far better achieved by persuasion of individuals to choose -- as a matter of individual conscience -- behavior that will not produce unwanted pregnancies, than by governmental mandate and invasion of privacy. . . .  Unlike the Democratic Party, we will not censor members of our party who hold opposing views on this issue. We are a party confident enough in our beliefs to tolerate dissent.</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
