<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="865276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDE1F39F934A25754C0A960958260" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-8</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-8</p>
        <p>COMPROMISE ON CUBA</p>
        <p>President Clinton delayed the right to sue under a new American law over Cuban seizure of land, an effort to tighten the economic noose around Cuba while defusing threats of retaliation.  A1</p>
        <p>MEXICO PEASANTS FIGHT BACK</p>
        <p>The emergence of a band of rebels in the Mexican state of Guerrero appears to be an effort of peasants in a state run like a banana republic to avenge police  killings and build a workers' republic. A3</p>
        <p>YELTSIN APPEARS BUT LOOKS WAN</p>
        <p>President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia went ahead with a meeting with Vice President Al Gore, but Mr. Yeltsin appeared wan and stiff, and the meeting failed to dispel concerns about his health. A8</p>
        <p>PACT SOUGHT ON GLOBAL WARMING</p>
        <p>The United States will take a more aggressive stance on global warming, seeking an international agreement to adopt targets for reducing the buildup of  gases that are causing climate change. A6</p>
        <p>SANCTION THREAT FOR SERBIA</p>
        <p>An American envoy will tell the Serbian leader that economic sanctions will be reimposed unless the Bosnian Serb leader, who has been indicted on war crimes charges, is removed and leaves Bosnia. A8</p>
        <p>FEAR OF REPRISALS IN BOSNIA</p>
        <p>Western officials are concerned that Bosnian Serbs may retaliate against NATO troops if the Serbs' leaders are arrested, but United Nations police monitors seem to be the most vulnerable. A8</p>
        <p>TOUGH JOB FOR ISRAEL LEADER</p>
        <p>Israel's new Prime Minister is home and facing a tough agenda, with pressures from all sides. To ease some of them, he will loosen the blockade that has kept  Palestinians from jobs in Israel. A6</p>
        <p>Maple Creek Journal: Punishment and penance, by tradition. A4</p>
        <p>National A10-17, D21</p>
        <p>CLINTON SEEKS WELFARE CHANGE</p>
        <p>The President, speaking to the nation's governors, said he was moving to require welfare recipients to promise to go to work within two years, and he said they would lose benefits if they did not.  A1</p>
        <p>MARKET CALM AFTER STORM</p>
        <p>The stock market rode out the busiest day in its 204-year history and the wildest day since the 1987 market plunge, to end basically unchanged. The Dow Jones industrial average closed with a 9.25 point gain at 5358.76. A1</p>
        <p>A GIFT FROM CHICAGO?</p>
        <p>The effective closing of the stock index futures market in Chicagoseemed to give traders time to think. Stocks on Wall Street began rising, first slowly and then with exuberance. A1</p>
        <p>16 CHARGED IN PORNOGRAPHY RING</p>
        <p>A Federal grand jury charged 16 people in the United States and abroad with joining in a pornography ring that was effectively an on-line pedophilia club. A10 NO RADON-CANCER LINK SEEN</p>
        <p>A major study has failed to connect indoor radon exposure with lung cancer, raising new uncertainty about public health warnings.  A15</p>
        <p>LITTLE OVERSIGHT IN FILES CASE</p>
        <p>The White House has paid a lack of attention in recent years to an office that has had access to private information about the lives of thousands of people.  A14</p>
        <p>CONVENTION REVAMPED</p>
        <p>Republican Party officials are trying to add excitement to their convention with techniques borrowed from television.  D21</p>
        <p>NEW DEFICIT PROJECTION</p>
        <p>The White House predicted that the Federal budget deficit this fiscal year would be $116.8 billion, $29 billion less than the Administration forecast just last spring.  D21</p>
        <p>Education B8</p>
        <p>Colleges have jazzed up career services to meet new demands.</p>
        <p>Metro Report B1-7</p>
        <p>CAUGHT IN ANTI-TERRORISM NET</p>
        <p>In the three months since a tougher new counterterrorism bill was signed into law, many immigrants who have been living legally in the United States for years have been detained by the Immigration and Naturalization Service and are facing  deportation.  A1</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C9-14</p>
        <p>Theater: "Grace and Glorie." C9</p>
        <p>Film: "Multiplicity." C9</p>
        <p>Music: "Lulu" at Glyndebourne.  C9</p>
        <p>Sports B9-16</p>
        <p>ATLANTA'S INTERNATIONAL CITY</p>
        <p>Atlanta organizers have been criticized about everything from sterile architecture to technological snafus to tacky commercialism, but they are getting rave reviews concerning the $194 million Olympic Village.  A1</p>
        <p>Baseball: Yankees top Red Sox. B9</p>
        <p>The Living Section C1-6</p>
        <p>Top places in New York for a drink and a view.  C1</p>
        <p>Health C7</p>
        <p>Heart transplants for the elderly, using rejected organs. Obituaries D23</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's health problems.</p>
        <p>Campaign reform, deformed.</p>
        <p>Those slam-dunk salaries.</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>Thomas L. Friedman: Turkey wings it.</p>
        <p>Frank Rich: Dole's Snowe job.</p>
        <p>Terry George: Lost without war in Northern Ireland.</p>
        <p>Chronicle B2</p>
        <p>Crossword C4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
