<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeing Green;The Red Menace Is Gone. But Here's Islam.</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D81339F932A15752C0A960958260" item-length="1613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeing Green;The Red Menace Is Gone. But Here's Islam.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Americans consider the safety of the world these days, many still seem conditioned to look for end-of-the-world threats that must be confronted. The end of the cold war sparked a kind of intellectual contest to identify the biggest and most credible new enemy. There was unfair trade. Global warming. Computer terrorism. The spread of weapons of mass destruction. Drugs. But none of these caught fire. Even ethnic hatred did not capture Americans' imaginations, as illustrated by the lack of enthusiasm for sending G.I.'s to Bosnia.</p>
        <p>But one threat has resonated in the public mind: Islamic holy war. Just last  week, Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman was sent to Federal prison for life in a conspiracy to follow the World Trade Center bombing with a string of bombings in New York that could have killed thousands of people. The Sheik played the role perfectly; even as he proclaimed his innocence and called himself a martyr of God, he portrayed his prosecution as part of a new cold war against Islam.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Americans consider the safety of the world these days, many still seem conditioned to look for end-of-the-world threats that must be confronted. The end of the cold war sparked a kind of intellectual contest to identify the biggest and most credible new enemy. There was unfair trade. Global warming. Computer terrorism. The spread of weapons of mass destruction. Drugs. But none of these caught fire. Even ethnic hatred did not capture Americans' imaginations, as illustrated by the lack of enthusiasm for sending G.I.'s to Bosnia.</p>
        <p>But one threat has resonated in the public mind: Islamic holy war. Just last  week, Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman was sent to Federal prison for life in a conspiracy to follow the World Trade Center bombing with a string of bombings in New York that could have killed thousands of people. The Sheik played the role perfectly; even as he proclaimed his innocence and called himself a martyr of God, he portrayed his prosecution as part of a new cold war against Islam.</p>
        <p>Exactly what does he represent, though? Is he the emissary of a global threat to America and its allies, or just another opportunist with a claim to God's truth, a band of followers and not much of a future?</p>
        <p>Certainly, powerful Islamic movements have sprung up to emulate Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's victory in Iran as they challenge Western allies in Algeria, Egypt, Kuwait, Bahrain, Pakistan. The greatest danger to peace between Israel and the Palestinians remains the Islamic radicals of Hamas. And Iran has tried repeatedly to export its revolution.</p>
        <p>So there are many respected intellectuals who see the acts of terrorism and the ubiquitous Muslim diatribes against the West as part of a deepening conflict between an aggressive Islam and a defensive Western civilization. Take Bernard Lewis, the eminent historian from Princeton University, who wrote more than five years ago: "The struggle between Islam and the West has now lasted 14 centuries. It has consisted of a long series of attacks and counterattacks, jihads and crusades, conquests and reconquests. Today much of the Muslim world is again seized by an intense -- and violent -- resentment of the West. Suddenly, America had become the archenemy, the incarnation of evil, the diabolic opponent of all  that is good, and specifically, for Muslims, of Islam."</p>
        <p>But a number of other experts on Islam think it is a big mistake to see politicized Islam as a unified threat, rather than as a way of thinking that inspires local bids for power. Their argument goes something like this: Overstating the threat, and misunderstanding the role of religion in it, risks playing into the hands of the extremists by portraying Islam itself as the enemy. Algeria's Muslims don't answer to Iran, and there are inherent divisions  between the Sunni and Shiite branches of Islam. What's more, the extremists represent only one part of Islamic theology -- those who would mobilize the religion to foment social revolutions, often against repressive, corrupt governments.</p>
        <p>"Explosive headline events and acts of violence make it tempting to view Islam through the prism of religious extremism and terrorism," said John Esposito, director of the Center for Muslim-Christian Understanding at Georgetown University and author of a book titled "The Islamic Threat: Myth or Reality?" "But the demonization of a great religious tradition because of the perverted actions of a minority of dissident voices remains the real threat."</p>
        <p>In fact, political Islam has become one of the hottest, nastiest debates in academic circles today, mirroring the old debate on how well-organized and monolithic the Communist menace was. Supporters of the notion of fundamentalism  as a global threat label their opponents simplistic and naive; opponents label the supporters simplistic and bigoted.</p>
        <p>The Council on Foreign Relations, hardly a hotbed of radical thinking, has come under fire for its new monthly newsletter, Muslim Politics Report, a forum  for a broad range of thought on Islam. "It's a front for radical Islamic extremists attempting to legitimize their agenda and to put on a friendly face in the United States," said Steven Emerson, a writer who believes the extremists represent a global Islamic conspiracy against America. The council has denied his accusations, with Leslie Gelb, its president, saying: "We consider the report a major contribution to let people know about a range of thinking by Islamic experts and leaders. It will stay. Period."</p>
        <p>In Europe, the debate is even more virulent. America's European allies have been skittish about supporting the Muslim-dominated Government in Bosnia in part because of fears about their own Muslim populations. The presence of up to 15 million Muslims in Europe, many of whom are poor and have refused to embrace the ways of the West, has fueled prejudices and fears. Some French schools prohibit  girls from wearing head scarves, and Germany has refused to give Turks citizenship.</p>
        <p>So it was not surprising that last year Willy Claes, the Belgian who was then NATO's Secretary General, said offhandedly that "Islamic fundamentalism is at least as dangerous as Communism was." The remark prompted King Hassan of Morocco, one of North Africa's most pragmatic and Western-oriented leaders, to retort: "I don't think NATO was created to fight fundamentalism, but to fight Soviet guns and missiles. Anyway, if fundamentalism has to be engaged in battle, it would not be done with tanks."</p>
        <p>Several incidents in recent weeks show just how complex the issue is.</p>
        <p>Bahrain's ruling family has put down demonstrations by the Islamic Front for  the Liberation of Bahrain, blaming them on Iran. But American intelligence has found no evidence that the opposition is anything but locally organized -- spawned by economic discontent, an uneven distribution of wealth and the absence of any political freedom.</p>
        <p>The Islamic Welfare Party won a stunning 21 percent of the vote in Turkish elections last month. But a pro-Islamic vote -- for a party that has not been associated with violence -- was the only vehicle for protesting the Government's failure to tackle poverty and inflation.</p>
        <p>A Handy Explanation</p>
        <p>Under pressure from Saudi Arabia this month, Britain ordered the expulsion of Mohammed al-Massari, an opponent of the regime, to the Caribbean island of Dominica. But the Kingdom itself is an Islamic state that rules by strict Islamic law; what Mr. Masari accuses the royal family of is corruption (which, he says, is un-Islamic).</p>
        <p>And consider this: the "green menace" (the new catch-phrase in the debate, after the color associated with Islam) is a convenient way for a leader to explain away opposition based on a country's economic, social and political inequities. In visits to Washington seeking American support last year, Prime Minister Benazir Bhutto of Pakistan, President Hosni Mubarak of Egypt and then-Prime Minister Tansu Ciller of Turkey all told President Clinton that the greatest threat to their governments came from globally linked fundamentalism. While they clearly believe that, they risked sounding like one-time American friends, such as President Ferdinand Marcos of the Philippines and Shah Mohammed Riza Pahlevi of Iran, who resisted reform to the very end, while presenting themselves as bulwarks against Communism.</p>
        <p>Israel's reconciliation with the Palestine Liberation Organization has also helped cast Islam as a larger-than-life enemy. "After the fall of Communism, fundamentalism has become the greatest danger of our time," Shimon Peres, now Israel's Prime Minister, has said. The American Jewish Congress has replaced its "Boycott Report" on the Arab economic boycott of Israel with a newsletter titled "Radical Islamic Fundamentalist Update."</p>
        <p>In the absence of other compelling threats to the United States, Islamic radicalism has also seized the imagination of some in Congress. House Speaker Newt Gingrich, who has warned about "totalitarian Islam," led Congress last month to approve $20 million in covert aid to moderate Iran's behavior. No matter that there is no viable opposition to Iran's Government; that the Central Intelligence Agency has concluded that despite severe economic problems the regime is not going to collapse any time soon, and that the policy is likely only to fuel paranoia in Teheran that the United States is determined to destroy Iran's Islamic republic. The initiative was so odd that the Administration (which calls Iran an "outlaw state") found itself in the bizarre position of weakening the covert program so its mandate did not include overthrowing Iran's  Government.</p>
        <p>In fact, Iran, the only country that has tried in a serious way to export an  Islamic revolution, provides a case study of how "global, radical Islam" can fail miserably. In 1991, the mullahs failed to respond when Saddam Hussein's army attacked two of the holiest shrines of Shiite Islam, in the Iraqi cities of Najaf and Kerbala. And this year, Iran has shown no inclination to take on Moscow by supporting the Muslim rebels of Chechnya. In its 17 years, in short, the Islamic Republic of Iran may have spread a lot of money around, armed assorted guerrillas and terrorized Salman Rushdie. But its society is far from content and its brand of revolution has simply not caught on.</p>
        <p>"The last 17 years has shown that however attractive or influential they may  be, no individual or state has enjoyed any kind of unitary leadership in the Islamic world," said Mr. Esposito. "There are religious extremist leaders and organizations, but there is no global Islamic threat."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
