<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environment Yielding to Other Worries, U.N. Talks Suggest</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="848625"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN) UNITED NATIONS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5D91439F936A35756C0A960958260" item-length="576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environment Yielding to Other Worries, U.N. Talks Suggest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, May 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four years after the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro propelled the environment to the top of the world agenda, the movement seems to have reached an impasse here at the United Nations, where a commission set up to monitor progress since  Rio ended two weeks of talks today.</p>
        <p>The Commission on Sustainable Development -- dedicated to the notion that nations can continue expanding their economies without destroying their environment -- heard success stories as it prepared for a major review next year of how far the world has come since the 1992 Earth Summit, formally called the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four years after the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro propelled the environment to the top of the world agenda, the movement seems to have reached an impasse here at the United Nations, where a commission set up to monitor progress since  Rio ended two weeks of talks today.</p>
        <p>The Commission on Sustainable Development -- dedicated to the notion that nations can continue expanding their economies without destroying their environment -- heard success stories as it prepared for a major review next year of how far the world has come since the 1992 Earth Summit, formally called the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development.</p>
        <p>A number of national governments, including that of the United States, have  prepared plans for environmental protection in the next century. Hundreds of municipalities have also written plans of action, bringing the concept of environmental protection to urban neighborhoods and the grass roots.</p>
        <p>Britain's Secretary of the Environment, John Gummer, said at a news conference today that this week's meetings had also taken an important step in bringing the world's oceans and their resources under the scrutiny of United Nations environmental bodies. "We are accepting as a world community that there  are to be world rules," he said. "Until this conference, the oceans were untouched by the Rio process."</p>
        <p>But hovering over the meeting was the sense that other issues have begun crowding out the environment, as rich and poor countries alike worry about unemployment and economic decline. And in many countries, environment ministries and private organizations say they are frustrated by their inability  to make environmental impact a major factor in economic policy-making.</p>
        <p>As recent negotiations over a Federal budget agreement in Washington demonstrated, environmental platforms are often subject to compromise, even in an Administration in which the Vice President, Al Gore, has an international reputation as a leader in the movement.</p>
        <p>"To a certain extent, after Rio other issues took over," said Nitin Desai, the United Nations' Under Secretary General for Policy Coordination and Sustainable Development. "I sometimes argue that Rio took place in a particular  window of opportunity, when, in a way, the world didn't have anything else to worry about."</p>
        <p>Mr. Desai said in an interview on Thursday that the next step for the environmental movement must be to broaden its scope to get its issues on others' agendas.</p>
        <p>"When we focus only on environmental problems we won't get very far unless we move backward and focus on agriculture policy, energy policy, transport policy -- all the economic policies that affect the environment," he said.</p>
        <p>Several speakers called attention to rapidly changing patterns of transportation and the problems these are creating: the explosion in car ownership in some regions of the world, unmanageable traffic and increased pollution in many cities already choked by industrial waste.</p>
        <p>Austria's Environment Minister, Martin Bartenstein, devoted a large part of his speech to the growth of vehicular traffic and shortages in public transportation and energy supplies. Several delegates said afterward that they found it ironic that in Washington at the same time, the two major political parties were competing for ways to lower gasoline prices in the United States, thereby effectively adding to the glut of cars burning a finite supply of fossil fuels.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
