<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Test of Underwater Sound System Showing No Harm to Animals</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOLPHINS ANDPORPOISES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEALS (ANIMALS) AND SEALING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEA LIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PACIFIC OCEAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SCRIPPS INSTITUTION OF OCEANOGRAPHY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E3D71339F932A15752C0A960958260" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Test of Underwater Sound System Showing No Harm to Animals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No spasms. No seizures. No rushing away. No indications of any discomfort whatsoever.</p>
        <p>Fifty miles off the California coast, scientists in planes and boats have watched carefully for a month and a half to see whether an underwater sound system intended to take the temperature of the Pacific Ocean is harming thousands of whales, dolphins, porpoises, elephant seals, sea lions and fur seals that live in the test area or migrate through it. Other scientists on shore have studied satellite readings to track the movements of elephant seals tagged with tiny radio transmitters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No spasms. No seizures. No rushing away. No indications of any discomfort whatsoever.</p>
        <p>Fifty miles off the California coast, scientists in planes and boats have watched carefully for a month and a half to see whether an underwater sound system intended to take the temperature of the Pacific Ocean is harming thousands of whales, dolphins, porpoises, elephant seals, sea lions and fur seals that live in the test area or migrate through it. Other scientists on shore have studied satellite readings to track the movements of elephant seals tagged with tiny radio transmitters.</p>
        <p>Last week, project scientists said in a preliminary report that they had not found any evidence that the system's underwater loudspeaker is affecting the animals, as many environmental groups had feared.</p>
        <p>"Nothing out of the ordinary has happened that makes us concerned," Dr. Daniel P. Costa, a biologist who directs the marine-mammal studies at the University of California at Santa Cruz, said in an interview. "There's no effect that blows you away."</p>
        <p>Dr. Costa cautioned that the program's scientists had only begun analyzing their information and that more testing and study would be needed before they could thoroughly assess the system's effects on mammalian sea life.</p>
        <p>The $35 million test of underwater sound transmissions began early last month after a year and a half of delays and debate over whether it would deafen whales and other marine mammals, many of which use underwater sounds for tracking prey  and foes. Protests, organized mainly by whale-preservation groups, helped change the initial focus of the test from measuring temperatures to investigating the possibility the loudspeaker would harm animals.</p>
        <p>Some 55 miles southwest of San Francisco, the loudspeaker sits in inky darkness 3,200 feet beneath the ocean surface on the side of an extinct volcano  known as Pioneer Seamount. The speaker, three feet wide and five feet tall, periodically broadcasts low-frequency rumbles.</p>
        <p>The experiment is run by the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in La Jolla, Calif. Initially, the plan was to fire sounds from the underwater speaker across the Pacific Ocean at least once a day.</p>
        <p>Sound travels faster in warm water than cold. In theory, changes in the sound's speed could reveal temperature shifts as subtle as a few thousandths of  a degree Fahrenheit -- information considered vital to investigating the reality of global warming. Over a decade, the signature of global warming is expected to be the speeding up of sound waves, reducing their overall travel time across the Pacific by 1.5 seconds.</p>
        <p>The revised testing plan devised after the protests sharply cut back the number of broadcasts.</p>
        <p>During each cycle, the deep loudspeaker rumbled for 20 minutes every four hours. The cycles lasted one to four days, depending on whether the visibility was good enough to monitor nearby sea life. By design, the experiment is to stop if signs of serious harm emerge.</p>
        <p>Scientists spotted large numbers of whales, dolphins and other animals near the sound source, whether it was on or off. The whales include dozens of sperm whales, a species of particular interest because they dive to depths of thousands of feet, which could take them near the speaker.</p>
        <p>Plans call for at least one more full-power transmission in January, two in February and then at least two per month in March and April.</p>
        <p>The study on the animals is to run at least through September. After that, the Scripps scientists hope to turn the experiment into the most sensitive test  yet devised to measure the dimensions of global warming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
