<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agency Seeks a Move Because of Air Quality</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="841372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RELOCATION OF BUSINESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEPARTMENTS AND AGENCIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRANSPORTATION DEPARTMENT (US)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2DF1339F937A35757C0A960958260" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agency Seeks a Move Because of Air Quality</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After complaints that the air in its headquarters was making workers sick, the Transportation Department said today that it would ask its landlord to spend $5 million to relocate employees and overhaul the ventilation system this summer.</p>
        <p>After a number of workers complained in recent months that the building's air had caused nausea, headaches and sore throats, high levels of hydrocarbons and slightly elevated levels of carbon dioxide were detected. The ventilation system was found to be at fault.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After complaints that the air in its headquarters was making workers sick, the Transportation Department said today that it would ask its landlord to spend $5 million to relocate employees and overhaul the ventilation system this summer.</p>
        <p>After a number of workers complained in recent months that the building's air had caused nausea, headaches and sore throats, high levels of hydrocarbons and slightly elevated levels of carbon dioxide were detected. The ventilation system was found to be at fault.</p>
        <p>We're not getting fresh air in and we're not pumping out old air," said Melissa J. Spillenkothen, Assistant Secretary of Transportation for Administration.</p>
        <p>The cost of improving the ventilation and temporarily moving 5,500 staff members was estimated at $5 million. The agency will ask the landlord, Nassif Associates, to pay for the costs, Ms. Spillenkothen said.</p>
        <p>The department assembled a team to investigate the building's indoor air quality in December, when 60 employees of the Federal Railroad Administration were relocated after many complained of headaches and nausea.</p>
        <p>About 400 workers responded to a survey by saying they had experienced some health problem related to the building during their careers, and another 140 underwent medical evaluations.</p>
        <p>The tests failed to pinpoint a cause, but the symptoms did lead officials to  conclude that there was a problem with the building.</p>
        <p>The tests showed that the ventilation system was "not working . . . according to current standards," Ms. Spillenkothen said.</p>
        <p>"We don't think we found 'the' problem," she said. "We found a significant problem. That is the ventilation system. Our consultants will be continuing to do further investigations."</p>
        <p>Hydrocarbons are found in fumes like those from paints, solvents and cleaners. A normal building generally registers about 1 milligram of hydrocarbons per cubic meter of air, Ms. Spillenkothen said.</p>
        <p>Consultants found levels as high as 13 milligrams per cubic meter in the department's building, she said, adding that high levels of carbon dioxide were  also detected, but "not at levels where you would be alarmed."</p>
        <p>The building is on Seventh Street Southwest, between the Capitol and the White House.</p>
        <p>Patricia Spirer, a policy analyst who said she had suffered from congestion and coughing fits since coming to work at the department six years ago, said that breathing the air in the building caused "a very heavy feeling, like breathing pea soup."</p>
        <p>"If you feel great when you stand outside and lousy when you're in the building, that tells you something," she said.</p>
        <p>But Barbara Lucas, a staff assistant who has worked in the building for 24 years, said she had not heard about the problems. "I've never noticed anything,  and I'm as healthy as an ox," she said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
