<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Data Point to the Ultimate Recovery of the Ozone Layer</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHLORINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEMICALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL OCEANIC &amp; ATMOSPHERIC ADMINISTRATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONTZKA, STEPHEN A (DR)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DB1E39F932A05756C0A960958260" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Data Point to the Ultimate Recovery of the Ozone Layer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quantity of ozone-destroying chemicals in the atmosphere is declining for the first time, according to researchers, who say this means that ozone destruction should peak by the end of the decade, as scientists previously forecast.</p>
        <p>"This is the very beginning of a change," said one of the researchers, Dr. Stephen A. Montzka of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. "This is the first step toward the goal of closing the ozone hole."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The quantity of ozone-destroying chemicals in the atmosphere is declining for the first time, according to researchers, who say this means that ozone destruction should peak by the end of the decade, as scientists previously forecast.</p>
        <p>"This is the very beginning of a change," said one of the researchers, Dr. Stephen A. Montzka of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. "This is the first step toward the goal of closing the ozone hole."</p>
        <p>The stratospheric ozone layer forms a natural barrier against the sun's ultraviolet radiation, excessive levels of which cause skin cancer in humans and harm many plants and animals.</p>
        <p>In 1993, Government scientists reported that for the first time, the buildup  of industrial chemicals most responsible for depleting the ozone layer had slowed substantially. The scientists said then that the worst of the ozone depletion should come around the turn of the century.</p>
        <p>In the new findings, ground-level measurements on three continents and on two Pacific islands detected an outright reduction in chlorine concentrations, the component of the industrial chemicals most responsible for ozone destruction. Consequently, the peak of ozone destruction in the stratosphere should come sometime from 1997 to 1999, according to a report on the study being published on Friday in the journal Science. And sometime after that, the researchers said, the ozone shield should begin to recover.</p>
        <p>Dr. Montzka said it would take two to three years for the air masses now at ground level to migrate to the stratosphere and change the chemistry there. Only then, he said, will destruction of the ozone layer actually diminish. Further, he said, it will take a bit longer before a statistically significant recovery trend can be discerned.</p>
        <p>"A detectable signal for ozone recovery is expected around 2005 or 2010," said Dr. Montzka, a scientist at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's laboratory in Boulder, Colo.</p>
        <p>The most common chemicals responsible for the thinning of the ozone layer include chlorofluorocarbons, halons and chlorine-based solvents. Such chemicals  have been used for more than 30 years in fire extinguishers and as refrigerants, cleaning agents, spray propellants and foams.</p>
        <p>Scientists discovered in the 1980's that the gaseous chemicals released in the ground-level atmosphere eventually migrate high above earth to the stratosphere, where they cause a chemical reaction that destroys ozone molecules.</p>
        <p>Erosion of the ozone layer has been particularly severe over the South Pole.  In recent years, measurements by satellite and ground instruments found that ozone concentrations had declined to a third or less of normal in the polar region, leaving what is called an ozone hole.</p>
        <p>In 1987, 23 nations meeting in Montreal signed an agreement to phase out manufacture and use of ozone-destroying chemicals. Amendments later added more chemicals to the list and accelerated the phase-out, and Dr. Montzka said the new tests showed that the Montreal protocol was beginning to have an effect.</p>
        <p>Dr. Richard Stolarski, an atmospheric scientist at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., said the new finding was an important one in the worldwide monitoring of industrial chemicals in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>"It is particularly significant now that they have seen a peaking and a turnaround" in the concentration of the chemicals, Dr. Stolarski said. But he cautioned that the trend would have to continue for a decade or more before the  ozone layer in the stratosphere started to recover.</p>
        <p>Dr. Montzka said his laboratory had been monitoring the chemistry of air samples collected in the continental United States, Canada, Australia, Antarctica, Samoa and Hawaii. Measurements of chlorine peaked in 1994, he said,  and a decline was noted for the first time last year. "It is down 1 to 1.5 percent from the peak," he said.</p>
        <p>Not all kinds of the industrial chemicals are declining, Dr. Montzka said, noting that CFC-12, among the most commonly used chemicals in cooling compressors, continued to edge up. He said this might continue, because many old refrigerators and air-conditioners contain CFC-12 and because that chemical has  an atmospheric lifetime of more than a century.</p>
        <p>But as a group, he said, ozone-destroying chemicals have declined since January 1994. He said this trend would probably continue as long as most countries observed the restrictions in the Montreal protocol.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
