<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marijuana Farms Are Flourishing Indoors, Producing a More Potent Drug</title>
    <meta content="24MARI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="891845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Miami (Fla)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Drug Enforcement Administration (Dea)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Navarro, Mireya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ledford, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Miami</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DB123DF937A15752C1A960958260" item-length="1564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marijuana Farms Are Flourishing Indoors, Producing a More Potent Drug</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIREYA NAVARRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Navarro, Mireya</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Nov. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Ledford of Drug Enforcement Agency says indoor marijuana growers can improve quality, speed up production and create highly potent strains that threaten to make bad pot thing of past; law enforcement agents who recently raided Miami house and seized crop with estimated street value of $2.9 million, say it was among best marijuana grown anywhere; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the outside, the house looked like any other in the inner-city neighborhood -- bars on the windows, a palm tree or two, a dog in the yard. But inside, past the kitchen, a sticky, pungent smell led to four rooms where 727 marijuana plants in various stages of maturity thrived.</p>
        <p>The crop, with an estimated street value of $2.9 million, was among the best marijuana grown anywhere, the law-enforcement agents who raided the house here one night earlier this month said. Indoor marijuana growers can improve quality, speed up production and create highly potent strains that threaten to make bad pot a thing of the past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the outside, the house looked like any other in the inner-city neighborhood -- bars on the windows, a palm tree or two, a dog in the yard. But inside, past the kitchen, a sticky, pungent smell led to four rooms where 727 marijuana plants in various stages of maturity thrived.</p>
        <p>The crop, with an estimated street value of $2.9 million, was among the best marijuana grown anywhere, the law-enforcement agents who raided the house here one night earlier this month said. Indoor marijuana growers can improve quality, speed up production and create highly potent strains that threaten to make bad pot a thing of the past.</p>
        <p>''Gone are the days of the hippies and personal use,'' said Frank Ledford, a special agent with the Drug Enforcement Administration here who has handled marijuana cases for the last five years. ''Now it's, 'I'm investing; I'm here to turn out volume and put out a superior product.' ''</p>
        <p>Potent marijuana, with high levels of the plant's primary psychoactive chemical, THC, or delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol, has been available for years. But with the expansion of domestic growing since the 1980's, and particularly the proliferation of indoor gardens specializing in the seedless bud of a female plant, known as sinsemilla, high-grade marijuana is more available now than ever before in areas like South Florida, a national leader in indoor growing along with California, Oregon and Washington.</p>
        <p>Indoor growers commonly sell only the bud, the THC-rich flowering top of the plant, discarding as garbage the leaves or ''shake'' commonly used in previous generations, law-enforcement officials say.</p>
        <p>Marijuana advocates say increased potency has the advantage of getting people high with less, reducing the health hazards associated with smoking. They say potency affects only how fast the high is achieved. But drug treatment counselors say that for those whose marijuana use tips the scale toward problematic behavior, higher potency means a faster decline into academic failure, social withdrawal and other problems of having a drug habit.</p>
        <p>''People used to be able to smoke several joints and be somewhat functional,'' said Jackie Rose, program director at Spectrum Program, a 27-year-old agency dealing in substance abuse treatment, with 17 locations in Florida. ''Today you can roll a joint, share it between many people and get really plastered.''</p>
        <p>Studies of marijuana seized by law-enforcement officers show that the average THC level of most ordinary marijuana is about 3 percent, the National Institute on Drug Abuse says. Sinsemilla has a higher THC concentration, about 7 percent on the average, and indoor growing can bring it up into double digits, the agency says.</p>
        <p>In Florida, Drug Enforcement Administration agents say it is not unusual now for indoor marijuana seized in raids to test at THC levels of 12 to 14 percent, compared with 6 percent five years ago. The National Organization for the Reform of Marijuana Laws, however, calls these ''boutique strains'' that are expensive and are not accessible to the average user.</p>
        <p>''Whoever is growing that would be in the absolute top tier of growers,'' said Allen St. Pierre, the organization's deputy director. ''I'm exposed to marijuana at a fairly high rate, and I've been exposed to marijuana that's double digits twice, once in California and once in the Netherlands.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. St. Pierre and others agree that sinsemilla strains are more prevalent in the market. And in places like Dade County, Miami's metropolitan area, they grow mostly behind the placid facade of suburbia, inside rented apartments and rented houses, in affluent and poor neighborhoods alike -- dwellings that often have been stripped of interior walls to build hydroponic, or soilless, gardens that turn out crops every 15 weeks.</p>
        <p>In the latest raid, Dade County police on Friday seized more than 1,500 plants from two houses in a rural area in the southern part of the county.</p>
        <p>In Liberty City, an area the police say is better known for street-level crack sales, the grower in the house raided earlier in the month had invested no more than $4,000 in renting the house and installing a hydroponic system equipped with timers, and he had not taken out the walls. Requiring little supervision, the system kept the risk of detection at a minimum and production at a steady clip, state and Federal agents said.</p>
        <p>The man arrested that night, a 52-year-old self-described mechanic who spoke no English, said he had rented the house for $200 a month from a friend and had not known that the plants were marijuana. The man was charged with possession and cultivation of marijuana, trafficking and possession of a firearm. Of this friend, he said, ''I don't know who he is and I don't know his name.''</p>
        <p>With the right equipment, anyone can grow marijuana indoors easily and profitably. Law-enforcement officials say growers can buy supplies at legitimate stores and get expert advice from magazines and publications on the Internet.</p>
        <p>At a residential drug treatment center for adolescents near here, in fact, many teen-agers said they bought directly from friends who grew their own. Residents at the Starting Place in Hollywood, north of here, described marijuana highs that made them talkative or giddy for a short while, as expected, but also highs that lasted two hours or longer and made them intensely sleepy and hallucinatory. A 13-year-old boy who said he smoked ''hydroponics,'' the marijuana grown in indoor hydroponic gardens, from a friend's attic said that once ''I was so tired and sleepy, I crashed my bike into a wall.''</p>
        <p>Inside the raided house in Liberty City, four air-conditioned, brightly lighted rooms contained a hothouse that included mother plants, trays of clones growing in green rock wool boxes and a crop of plants just starting to bud. Windows had been sealed with insulated wallboard, and walls were covered with reflective paper to make the light in the room more intensive. Light, water and carbon dioxide piped in through plastic tubing were on timers. ''Very good,'' said William D. Lang Jr., a special agent with the Florida Department of Law Enforcement, inspecting the crop. ''Not clean, but very good.''</p>
        <p>Although market statistics are hard to come by because of the illegal nature of the marijuana business, the National Organization for Reform of Marijuana Laws estimates that domestic marijuana accounts for about a quarter of the marijuana consumed in the United States, with the rest coming from Mexico and other countries. Federal officials say the number of seizures every year indicates that indoor domestic production is growing. The trend toward increased domestic production and THC potency, they say, is primarily the result of law enforcement, mainly eradication efforts focusing on outdoor cultivation and the interdiction of imports from abroad.</p>
        <p>In Florida, state officials say, outdoor growers seeking to avoid detection mixed marijuana plants with legitimate crops, hung them from trees and even used floating platforms placed in swamps before many of them moved their operations indoors in the late 1980's, although most marijuana in this country is still grown outdoors. Now, instead of aerial surveillance, law-enforcement authorities rely on utility bills -- indoor growing inflates the electricity bill -- and tips from neighbors to find the crops, if not always the growers.</p>
        <p>Although marijuana is still grown outdoors in the Florida Panhandle, law-enforcement officials said indoor growing had greatly increased in the last five years. The number of drug seizures from indoor sites since 1991 has averaged 150 to 250 each year, compared with 45 in 1990.</p>
        <p>A similar pattern is showing up nationwide: law-enforcement authorities seized 3,348 indoor operations in 1995, compared with 1,669 in 1990, figures from the Drug Enforcement Administration show. In March, in one of the largest indoor raids ever in the United States, Federal agents seized 11,000 sinsemilla plants from a Miami house and a trailer on the same property, a site that agents said had produced a crop worth $38 million a year. But because indoor growers face Federal mandatory minimum sentences and forfeiture of assets if they are caught, they tend to grow fewer but better plants -- the manicured indoor-grown bud sells for $3,000 to $6,000 a pound, compared with $200 to $1,000 for other kinds, depending on the market, Federal officials say.</p>
        <p>Neighbors in the upper-middle-class community in northeastern Miami where the 11,000 plants were found said they were shocked. Most said they had not known the occupants of the massive two-story house, surrounded by a high concrete wall, but that they had never suspected marijuana growers.</p>
        <p>''You never know who your neighbors are or what they do,'' said Laurie Kabbaby, 35, a neighbor with two children who now call the house ''the marijuana house.'' ''It's amazing what this world has come to.''</p>
        <p>''It's obscene,'' said another neighbor, a man who did not want to be identified. ''It's hard to believe all that was going on across the street.''</p>
        <p>''I remember feeling absolutely stupid,'' his wife said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
