<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Magellan Helmsman Cast From Peter Lynch's Mold;Robert Stansky Follows Mentor's 'Growth' Tack</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="852810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUTUAL FUNDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BROKERS AND BROKERAGE FIRMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIDELITY MAGELLAN FUND</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FIDELITY INVESTMENTS CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EATON, LESLIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VINIK, JEFFREY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYNCH, PETER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STANSKY, ROBERT E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E5D61039F937A15756C0A960958260" item-length="1464" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Magellan Helmsman Cast From Peter Lynch's Mold;Robert Stansky Follows Mentor's 'Growth' Tack</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EATON, LESLIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert E. Stansky is a man with a plan, and that is likely to mean big changes for investors in the nation's largest mutual fund, Fidelity Magellan.</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. Stansky has a blueprint of what he will buy and sell for the $56 billion fund. "I don't know what Magellan will look like," he said in an interview yesterday. That will depend on what investments appear attractive when he formally takes the reins on June 3, he said, adding, "The market could be up  100 points or down 100 points -- or 1,000."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert E. Stansky is a man with a plan, and that is likely to mean big changes for investors in the nation's largest mutual fund, Fidelity Magellan.</p>
        <p>Not that Mr. Stansky has a blueprint of what he will buy and sell for the $56 billion fund. "I don't know what Magellan will look like," he said in an interview yesterday. That will depend on what investments appear attractive when he formally takes the reins on June 3, he said, adding, "The market could be up  100 points or down 100 points -- or 1,000."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stansky does have a distinctive investing style. He is widely known  as a methodical "growth" investor. In his view, unit-sales growth leads to revenue growth, revenue growth leads to earnings growth, and earnings growth leads to higher stock prices.</p>
        <p>"That's my m.o." said the 40-year-old Mr. Stansky, who has managed the Fidelity Growth Company Fund since 1987. And that will continue to be his modus  operandi, he said, though running Magellan "does broaden the possibilities a little."</p>
        <p>What that means for investors, analysts said, is that Magellan's performance  is likely to be more predictable than it has been during the four-year tenure of Jeffrey N. Vinik, who said yesterday that he would be leaving the FMR Corporation's Fidelity family of funds to start his own money management firm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vinik has zigged and zagged across the investment landscape. Late last year, he made a big bet in bonds, a bet that has since dragged down the fund's returns. But earlier in 1995, he placed a similarly hefty wager on the stocks of technology companies -- and that paid off brilliantly.</p>
        <p>By contrast, under Mr. Stansky, the gauge of Magellan's performance should be clearer, analysts said: When growth stocks are in favor, Magellen should excel;  when growth stocks are out of favor, the fund should lag.</p>
        <p>"Stansky is not as much of a gunslinger as Vinik -- he's steady and evenhanded, and true to his style," said Jack Bowers, editor of Fidelity Monitor, a newsletter that analyzes Fidelity funds.</p>
        <p>Over all, Mr. Vinik made a name for himself by moving from sector to sector in the stock market, rather than by investigating companies from the ground up,  meeting management, testing products and scrutinizing income statements and balance sheets. The bottom-up approach was epitomized by Peter Lynch, the legendary manager of Magellan from 1977 to 1990, who was Mr. Stansky's mentor when he first came to Fidelity in 1983.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stansky's methodical approach does not mean that his investing will be safe or low risk. Indeed, under Mr. Stansky, "Magellan Fund will be more apt  to outperform or underperform" the stock market, said Stephen Savage, editor of  the Value Line Mutual Fund Survey.</p>
        <p>That is because growth investing, as a strategy, works better in some stock markets than in others. While over the long haul it has been a good way to make  money, there have been periods when growth investors have lagged behind investors with a different approach, such as trying to buy cheap stocks.</p>
        <p>For proof, look at Mr. Stansky's record managing Fidelity Growth Company. Under his management since April, 1987, the fund has soared 293 percent, while a fund mimicking the Standard &amp; Poor's index of 500 stocks has climbed about 200 percent. But in times of market turmoil, Growth Company fared far worse than the market as a whole. For example, in 1987, the year that included the October crash, Mr. Stansky's fund fell 1.7 percent, while the S.&amp; P. 500 ended the year  up 5.1 percent. And in 1994, a pretty rotten year for stocks, Growth Company lost 2.2 percent, while the market eked out a gain of 1.3 percent.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Stansky follows that pattern at Magellan, he is bound to disappoint investors who expect that the fund will always beat the market. But analysts said it would probably appeal to the bulk of the investors already in Magellan -- investors saving for retirement who may not worry about chasing after the hottest performance in the country, but who are puzzled and alarmed when their fund appears to be out of sync with the market.</p>
        <p>His style seems sure to appeal to many consultants who choose stocks for pension plans; they tend to prefer that funds stick with a particular investment style -- and they hate surprises, said John Rekenthaler, a longtime editor at Morningstar Inc., the fund research company.</p>
        <p>"Particularly with a fund with as high a profile as this, you can't sell on the basis of 'Trust me,' " Mr. Rekenthaler said.</p>
        <p>Magellan has prospered under several managers, and investment advisers generally do not think Mr. Vinik's departure or Mr. Stansky's arrival should prompt shareholders to dump the fund. "I certainly would not make any changes based on the manager," said Eric M. Kobren, who edits a newsletter that follows  Fidelity and is president of Insight Management, which manages $650 million of money through Fidelity. "Shareholders did phenomenally well by Vinik, and they will be served very well by Stansky."</p>
        <p>Not everyone thinks that Mr. Stansky will be able to institute his distinctive approach when he takes over Magellan, or even that he will want to.  "Remember, Vinik stays around until June 30 -- and he can be a very persuasive guy," said A. Michael Lipper, president of Lipper Analytical Services.</p>
        <p>And some fund watchers say that with a fund as big as Magellan -- its assets  are more than twice those of the next biggest stock fund -- it is almost impossible to succeed with a bottoms-up investment style. The fund simply has to own too many stocks -- stocks of big companies -- for analysis of individual companies to pay off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch, not surprisingly, disagrees. Though Magellan was far smaller when  he ran it, even then people said it was too big to beat the market -- yet it did, he noted. And it did so by putting half of its assets in growth stocks and  then looking around at other investments, such as companies that were recovering from problems, or utilities, or the stocks known as cyclicals, which are affected by the economic cycle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lynch, now vice chairman of Fidelity Investments, said yesterday that he  expected that Mr. Stansky would follow a similar strategy. "You look at businesses," said Mr. Lynch, who has taken an increasingly visible role speaking on behalf of Magellan as its performance has sagged this year. "You don't look at where the stock market is going or who is going to be President or the state of the ozone layer."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stansky learned his bottoms-up technique at Mr. Lynch's knee, though he had become a growth stock fan several years before when someone sold him on a stock called Valtek, which he said soared from $5 to $65. "I said, 'Wow, this could be fun!' " Mr. Stansky recalled. Already an accountant, he went to New York University to earn an M.B.A., working part time in the bond department of Kidder, Peabody.</p>
        <p>After he was graduated from N.Y.U. in 1983, Mr. Stansky went directly to Fidelity, and soon became a research associate for Mr. Lynch at Magellan. He also did a stint as manager of a fund that specialized in the stocks of companies in the military-contracting industry. In 1987, he took over Growth Company, and he has also run Fidelity's emerging-growth fund; in March, he became head of what is called the Growth Group as part of a reorganization of the company's fund managers.</p>
        <p>A family man who coaches Little League and enjoys watching and playing sports, Mr. Stansky is uniformly described by colleagues and analysts as hard-working, low key, and just plain nice. Indeed, some of them wonder how he will cope with the glaring spotlight that comes with running Magellan. To Donald R. Dion Jr., publisher of Fidelity Independent Adviser, another newsletter focusing on the company's funds, the job ranks right behind chairman of the Federal Reserve in terms of its ability to affect the stock market..</p>
        <p>Mr. Stansky points out that he is no neophyte; managing about $17 billion has made him accustomed to scrutiny. "I'll continue in the same way," he said. "And  I'll try my hardest, period."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
