<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Life in Space? 2 New Planets Raise Thoughts</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="823588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIFE, EXTRATERRESTRIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STARS AND GALAXIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLANETS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JUPITER (PLANET)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN FRANCISCO STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCY, GEOFFREY (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUTLER, PAUL (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7D71139F93BA25752C0A960958260" item-length="1658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Life in Space? 2 New Planets Raise Thoughts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <dateline>SAN ANTONIO, Jan. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a stunning discovery of new worlds far out in the universe, two California astronomers today reported the detection of two planets orbiting Sun-like stars. The temperatures of the planets appear to be warm enough for water to exist in liquid form, a condition conducive to chemical processes that could, just possibly, be producing extraterrestrial life.</p>
        <p>The two newly discovered extra-solar planets, considerably larger than Jupiter, accompany the stars 70 Virginis, in the constellation Virgo, and 47 Ursae Majoris, in the Big Dipper, or Ursa Major. They are 35 light-years away, relatively close by cosmic standards. They are too small and dim to be seen against the glare of their parent stars, but their gravitational presence has been definitely established.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a stunning discovery of new worlds far out in the universe, two California astronomers today reported the detection of two planets orbiting Sun-like stars. The temperatures of the planets appear to be warm enough for water to exist in liquid form, a condition conducive to chemical processes that could, just possibly, be producing extraterrestrial life.</p>
        <p>The two newly discovered extra-solar planets, considerably larger than Jupiter, accompany the stars 70 Virginis, in the constellation Virgo, and 47 Ursae Majoris, in the Big Dipper, or Ursa Major. They are 35 light-years away, relatively close by cosmic standards. They are too small and dim to be seen against the glare of their parent stars, but their gravitational presence has been definitely established.</p>
        <p>The discovery of the planets, together with another one found last October,  encouraged scientists in their growing belief that the solar system is anything  but unique and that other planetary systems may be fairly common. This, in turn, was seen as raising the likelihood that life exists elsewhere in the universe, perhaps even intelligent life.</p>
        <p>The announcement, made here at a meeting of the American Astronomical Society, followed two other startling findings made public this week at the gathering: an increase in the estimated number of detectable galaxies in the universe, to 50 billion from 10 billion, and evidence that burned-out stars may  account for at least half the missing mass in the universe.</p>
        <p>The latest discovery was greeted with enthusiasm and widespread endorsement by other astronomers, many of whom could hardly wait to have a look with their own telescopes and possibly find other planets. They used terms like "provocative" and "profoundly exciting" to describe the findings.</p>
        <p>"We truly are at the dawn of a new era in astronomy," said Dr. Alan P. Boss,  a theoretical astronomer at the Carnegie Institute in Washington. "We will be finding many more planets in the next decade."</p>
        <p>In a similar vein, Dr. William J. Boruchi, an astronomer at the Ames Research Center in Mountain View, Calif., who is also searching for extra-solar planets,  said: "It's almost like the second coming of Marco Polo or Columbus. We're finding new worlds."</p>
        <p>In the afterglow of this discovery, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration announced at another session of the conference that one of its highest scientific priorities over the next 25 years would be a concerted effort, using ground-based telescopes and new spacecraft systems, to search the  heavens for other planetary bodies. Some of the proposed instruments might be capable of taking pictures of other planets, even those as small as Earth, and examining their reflected light for direct evidence of their composition and potential for life.</p>
        <p>The two newly found planets were discovered by Dr. Geoffrey W. Marcy, an astronomer at San Francisco State University who is a visiting scholar at the University of California at Berkeley, and his research associate, Dr. Paul Butler, affiliated with the same universities. The findings were a culmination of eight years of work using the 120-inch telescope at Lick Observatory near San Jose, Calif.</p>
        <p>The two astronomers had previously confirmed the first discovery, announced by Swiss scientists in October, of a planet around another ordinary star, 51 Pegasi, about 40 light-years away. The Pegasi planet is only about half the mass of Jupiter, however, and is so close to its star that it is baking hot and unable to support life.</p>
        <p>"After the discovery of 51 Pegasi, everyone wondered if it was a freak, a one-in-a-million observation," Dr. Marcy said. "The answer is no. Planets aren't rare after all."</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcy and Dr. Butler made the detections by observing variations in the light from the stars. Those variations were in a pattern suggesting a slight wobble caused by the gravitational force of a massive planet in nearby orbit. The patterns were so regular, just as Kepler and Newton would have predicted, Dr. Marcy said, that there is "almost no other explanation besides a planet to produce it."</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert A. Brown, a specialist in planetary systems at the Space Telescope Science Institute in Baltimore, said the observations were the "best evidence yet for what we would call a normal-type planet around another star."</p>
        <p>Although the two stars are visible from Earth with the unaided eye, Dr. Brown said that even the Hubble Space Telescope would be unable to make pictures of their planets. With a more powerful camera expected to be installed by the end of the decade, he said, the telescope might be able to get an image of the planet around 47 Ursae Majoris, because it may be sufficiently distant from its  star that it will not be washed out by the star's bright light.</p>
        <p>Both stars are analogues of the Sun, astronomers said, with no appreciable differences in size, temperature or age. The search for other planets has so far been focused on about 120 such Sun-like stars within 100 light-years of Earth.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marcy and Dr. Butler completed their observations and calculations of the planet around 70 Virginis only three weeks ago. When he saw that the wobble in the star's motion fit precisely the orbit of a large planet, Dr. Butler said in an interview, "I was sure of what we had in three minutes, and I almost literally fell out of my chair."</p>
        <p>The planet orbits the star in an eccentric, elongated orbit once every 116 days. Its distance from the star is comparable to a distance from the Sun somewhere between Mercury and Venus, unusually close for so large a body. It has an estimated mass 8.1 times that of Jupiter, the solar system's largest planet,  whose own mass is 317.8 times as great as Earth's.</p>
        <p>By measuring the star's light and its distance from the planet, the astronomers determined how much heat the planet must be absorbing. Then, using a standard formula, they calculated its surface temperature at about 185 degrees Fahrenheit, something like the heat of lukewarm tea. The planet thus could have  water in vapor and liquid forms alike.</p>
        <p>"That's cool enough to permit complex molecules to exist, ranging from carbon dioxide to complicated organic molecules," Dr. Marcy said. "And because the temperature is below the boiling point of water, this planet could conceivably have rain or even oceans."</p>
        <p>Although the planet is presumably a gaseous body like Jupiter, the astronomers said that, also like Jupiter, it could have moons with solid surfaces, equally warm temperatures and perhaps a better prospect for harboring  life.</p>
        <p>The astronomers suspected two months ago that the other star, 47 Ursae Majoris, had a planetary companion, but they were not comfortable with the research until two weeks ago. Their observations showed that this planet is 3.5  times as massive as Jupiter. It travels a circular orbit farther out from the star, equivalent to a distance from the Sun somewhere out between Mars and Jupiter, and takes 1,100 days, slightly more than three years, to make a complete trip around its star. Its surface temperature is minus 112 degrees, but it is probably warmer in its lower atmosphere, could have liquid water and may also have more temperate moons.</p>
        <p>Because this planet lies closer to a Jupiter distance from its star, Dr. Butler said, "this system is the closest thing we've seen to anything like our own solar system."</p>
        <p>As far as scientists know, other, smaller planets may orbit these stars. But  current detection techniques may not find them.</p>
        <p>The previously detected planet around 51 Pegasi was identified by Dr. Michel  Mayor and Dr. Didier Queloz, astronomers at the Geneva Observatory in Switzerland. As soon as they learn of the new discoveries, Dr. Marcy said in an  interview, they can be expected to try to confirm the findings, just as the Californians did when they heard of the Swiss discovery.</p>
        <p>A competitive race among astronomers to find planets beyond the solar system  has developed since the discovery three years ago of two and possibly three objects orbiting a most unlikely parent star: the dense core of a dead star known as a pulsar.</p>
        <p>That discovery was made by Dr. Alexander Wolszczan, an astronomer at Pennsylvania State University, who used a radiotelescope to detect signals from  the pulsar indicating that it was perturbed by the gravity of accompanying planets. But the environment around a pulsar, with its blizzard of gamma rays and X-rays and its lack of warming starlight, would not be conducive to life.</p>
        <p>The recent discoveries of planets around normal stars will give theoreticians plenty to think about, particularly the evidence that very large planets can exist much closer to their parent star than does Jupiter.</p>
        <p>Dr. William D. Cochran, an astronomer at the University of Texas at Austin, raised some of the questions that must be addressed. "What is the diversity of planetary systems?" he asked. "Is our own solar system with Jupiter so far out typical or not?"</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Marcy said: "Theorists now have a greater challenge in front of them. They have more than the solar system to explain. Others may be more diverse and may have objects that defy normal classification."</p>
        <p>He said he would leave that to the theorists, while he continued examining other likely candidates for planetary systems and expanded the search using the  much more powerful Keck Observatory at Mauna Kea in Hawaii.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
