<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evidence Puts Date for Life's Origin Back Millions of Years</title>
    <meta content="07LIFE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5D61138F934A35752C1A960958260" item-length="1051" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evidence Puts Date for Life's Origin Back Millions of Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Team of American, British and Australian scientists uncover evidence that life may have originated on Earth at least 350 million years earlier than previously believed, at time immediately after devastating bombardment by meteors; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of American, British and Australian scientists has uncovered evidence that life may have originated on earth at least 350 million years earlier than previously believed, at a time immediately after a devastating bombardment by meteors.</p>
        <p>The discovery complicates the question of when and how terrestrial life arose. Recent studies based partly on the distribution of craters on the moon have suggested that a rain of meteors smashing into the early earth was intense enough until 3.8 billion years ago to destroy all life on the planet, if any existed at that time. The oldest objects believed to be the fossils of living organisms -- tiny mineral filaments -- are estimated to be 3.5 billion years old.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team of American, British and Australian scientists has uncovered evidence that life may have originated on earth at least 350 million years earlier than previously believed, at a time immediately after a devastating bombardment by meteors.</p>
        <p>The discovery complicates the question of when and how terrestrial life arose. Recent studies based partly on the distribution of craters on the moon have suggested that a rain of meteors smashing into the early earth was intense enough until 3.8 billion years ago to destroy all life on the planet, if any existed at that time. The oldest objects believed to be the fossils of living organisms -- tiny mineral filaments -- are estimated to be 3.5 billion years old.</p>
        <p>But findings reported today in the journal Nature imply that the window of time between the end of the lethal meteor bombardment of the young earth and the beginning of life may have been vanishingly short. The work suggests that life had already established a toehold on the infant planet 3.85 billion years ago.</p>
        <p>In a comment also published by Nature, Dr. John M. Hayes of the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution in Massachusetts, said the investigation seemed to imply that biochemical processes ''developed with breath-taking rapidity after the last large impact.''</p>
        <p>Many scientists believe that the chemical processes that gave rise to life must have taken hundreds of millions of years to develop the essential enzymes, proteins and genetic codes. Evidence of a very quick beginning might mean that there was too little time to complete the job on earth, and that life therefore must have originated elsewhere, drifting through space to the earth in the form of spores or by some other means. This is known as the ''panspermia'' theory.</p>
        <p>The discovery reported today was by a group headed by Dr. Gustaf Arrhenius of the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at San Diego. (Dr. Arrhenius is the grandson of Svante Arrhenius, the renowned 19th-century Swedish scientist whose work laid much of the basis of modern chemistry and who believed that life originated somewhere other than the earth.) The team also included Dr. Arrhenius's graduate student, Stephen J. Mojzsis, and colleagues at the University of California at Los Angeles, the Australian National University in Canberra, and Oxford Brooks University in England.</p>
        <p>The focus of their investigation was a formation known as the Isua supracrustal belt of Akilia Island in southern West Greenland. The formation had been dated by radioactive decay techniques at 3.85 billion years old, the oldest known rocks in the world.</p>
        <p>The discovery did not include any actual fossils. It is believed that no fossils could survive from such ancient times. Fossils can be preserved in sediments for hundreds of millions of years, but eventually all sediments and the fossils embedded in them are drawn under the sliding tectonic plates that make up the earth's crust, or ''subducted.'' When this happens, the sedimentary fossil record is crushed, melted and destroyed.</p>
        <p>But the scientists in Dr. Arrhenius's group hit upon another way to search for ancient life.</p>
        <p>The carbon atoms in molecules distributed around the world consist mostly of an isotope, or form, in which the carbon nucleus contains six protons and six neutrons. This is called carbon-12. But among these atoms are small numbers of another isotope, carbon-13, whose nucleus contains six protons and seven neutrons.</p>
        <p>When environmental carbon from carbon dioxide and other substances is incorporated into living organisms, a process of ''fractionation'' occurs in which the heavier isotope, carbon-13, is somewhat reduced. A reduced ratio of carbon-13 to carbon-12 is therefore a characteristic of biological activity, and Dr. Arrhenius and his group said they believed this changed ratio had been preserved even in minerals that had undergone ''pressure cooking'' by geological processes.</p>
        <p>By analyzing tiny particles of carbon embedded in some of the Greenland formation's apatite rock, a phosphate mineral chemically similar to the apatite in bone, the group found a ratio of carbon-13 to carbon-12 that the scientists believed revealed the signature of life.</p>
        <p>To study the specks of carbon, the group used a high-resolution ion microprobe, which fires a beam of atomic nuclei at the sample. The beam blasts atoms loose from the sample's surface, which are then analyzed using an instrument called a mass spectrometer. The scientists found that their samples fell into two groups: those of clearly non-biological origin, and those displaying an isotope ratio characteristic of life.</p>
        <p>Dr. Arrhenius said in an interview that ''no terrestrial process other than biological organisms has been found that fractionates carbon-12 and carbon-13 in this way.''</p>
        <p>Whether or not the premises on which this work is based are true remains controversial, however.</p>
        <p>''There are some potential processes other than life that could account for the Arrhenius isotopic results,'' Dr. Hayes of the Woods Hole institution said, ''and even though they are long shots, we cannot entirely discount them. Still, if I had to rate his paper as a whole, I'd say it boils down to good science.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stanley L. Miller of the University of California at San Diego, whose experiments beginning in the 1950's suggested that some essential components of life could have been created by the interaction of simple chemicals in ''the primordial soup,'' believes that the narrowing of the window in which life arose presents no problem.</p>
        <p>''There's nothing to rule out a quick beginning of life,'' he said in an interview. ''Life might have arisen in, say, 10 million years, or even less. Or, it may be that the first wave of life was wiped out by the late meteor bombardment, except for organisms that thrive on heat, like those we find today living around thermal vents on the ocean floor. Something like them may have been our ancestors. There are lots of possibilities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
