<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Error Inflated Estimate Of Rising Sea Levels, Researchers Report</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="868394"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARBON DIOXIDE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOPYTOFF, VERNE G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7DC1439F933A05754C0A960958260" item-length="594" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Error Inflated Estimate Of Rising Sea Levels, Researchers Report</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VERNE G. KOPYTOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOPYTOFF, VERNE G</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESEARCHERS say an error in a computer program analyzing data from a United States altimeter led them to overestimate the rise in Earth's oceans over the last three years.</p>
        <p>American scientists said their revised estimate was that sea levels had risen on average 1 millimeter to 3 millimeters annually (0.04 to 0.12 inches) from December 1992 to April 1996. Previously, their data suggested that the level had increased between 3 millimeters and 5 millimeters (0.2 inches) annually in that  period. All the estimates are based on data from altimeters aboard a joint French-American satellite, Topex/Poseidon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESEARCHERS say an error in a computer program analyzing data from a United States altimeter led them to overestimate the rise in Earth's oceans over the last three years.</p>
        <p>American scientists said their revised estimate was that sea levels had risen on average 1 millimeter to 3 millimeters annually (0.04 to 0.12 inches) from December 1992 to April 1996. Previously, their data suggested that the level had increased between 3 millimeters and 5 millimeters (0.2 inches) annually in that  period. All the estimates are based on data from altimeters aboard a joint French-American satellite, Topex/Poseidon.</p>
        <p>The results do not disprove the theory that increasing industrialization is  warming the climate and melting the icecaps, the scientists said. Scientists generally say it is too early to know whether coastal cities are in any less danger of flooding.</p>
        <p>The revised findings roughly coincide with readings taken from a French altimeter also aboard the Topex/Poseidon and from ground-based measurements. Dr. Victor Zlotnicki, a participant in the study from the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, which manages the American portion of the project for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, said it would take perhaps a century of observing the  ocean before any definitive claims can be made about ocean level trends.</p>
        <p>"Rising sea levels are not something that happens all the time," Dr. Zlotnicki said. "An ice chunk may melt, causing the water level to go up, or the weather may get warm somewhere, and the water goes down. We have a nice three-year series, but readings can be done only over a long period of time."</p>
        <p>The Jet Propulsion Laboratory here said a French researcher had found the mistake in the computer programming. The revised figures show that water levels  were rising steadily but much slower than had been estimated.</p>
        <p>George S. Hayne, one of the managers at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center who is responsible for the accuracy of the data collected by Topex/Poseidon, said it was common on such complicated missions to revise figures after a few years of operation. He said the problem, a reversal of one algorithm out of thousands, should not undermine the credibility of the satellite's readings in the future.</p>
        <p>Topex/Poseidon was launched in 1992 to map the majority of the globe's ocean  currents every 10 days with an accuracy not possible on land. Decades of data collected from the ground, using tide gauges placed along the coasts, have generally shown that ocean levels are rising. But scientists said these data reflected only local conditions and were not fully reliable.</p>
        <p>But with the measurements taken from space, scientists are now reporting dramatic changes in water levels in the middle of the Pacific Ocean, probably due to the currents that precede the buildup of El Nino, a warming of the ocean  off Peru. Dr. Zlotniki said water levels in the eastern equatorial Pacific had dropped 20 millimeters annually in the last three years. In the western equatorial Pacific, he said, sea levels increased 40 millimeters during the same period.</p>
        <p>"You have all the hot water piled up on the western side, and the cold water  on the eastern part," Mr. Zlotnicki said. He said the wind causing those currents would eventually reverse, pushing the warm water toward the coast of Peru and beginning El Nino. He would not speculate as to when such a warming would occur.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
