<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Car Owners Feel the Heat as the Price of Freon Climbs</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="867777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREON</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OZONE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALPERT, JULIE EDELSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EFD81739F93BA15754C0A960958260" item-length="710" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Car Owners Feel the Heat as the Price of Freon Climbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE EDELSON HALPERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HALPERT, JULIE EDELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If your car air-conditioner is blowing Caribbean trade winds instead of Arctic cold fronts, beware: tuning up the system may cost more than you expect.</p>
        <p>A prohibition on the manufacture of the most widely used auto coolant, R-12 -- best known by its Du Pont trade name, Freon -- has sent prices soaring. An international treaty barred new supplies of R-12, which is known to deplete the  earth's ozone layer, at the end of 1995. But the coolant can still be sold until stocks run out, in about two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If your car air-conditioner is blowing Caribbean trade winds instead of Arctic cold fronts, beware: tuning up the system may cost more than you expect.</p>
        <p>A prohibition on the manufacture of the most widely used auto coolant, R-12 -- best known by its Du Pont trade name, Freon -- has sent prices soaring. An international treaty barred new supplies of R-12, which is known to deplete the  earth's ozone layer, at the end of 1995. But the coolant can still be sold until stocks run out, in about two years.</p>
        <p>Even so, repair shops do not generally have large stockpiles, partly because  a Federal tax of $5.80 a pound makes the refrigerant costly to store.</p>
        <p>R-12 is commonly used in the air-conditioners of some 90 million vehicles built before 1993. Home air-conditioners generally use a different refrigerant,  R-22.</p>
        <p>Simon Oulouhojian, president of the Mobile Air Conditioning Society Worldwide, said American inventories of R-12 totaled 150 million pounds, which "should be more than sufficient, but everybody's panicked," contributing to a perception of scarcity and higher prices. And as the temperature rises, so does  demand. While last year consumers paid about $8 a pound to have an air-conditioner topped off with Freon, or a total of $50 including parts and labor, the cost is now $20 a pound or more, with a complete recharging and checkup costing $100 to $150. An auto air-conditioner contains two to three pounds of Freon.</p>
        <p>As a result of the price jump, some alternatives that are seen as environmentally friendly have become more attractive. One of these, R-134a, has been used on new cars for three years. But it will not work properly in older cars unless modifications are made at costs that ranged, until recently, from $300 to $1,000, depending on how many of the old parts are compatible.</p>
        <p>But the conversion cost has come down, especially for cars built just before  the changeover. Drusilla Hufford, who handles ozone issues for the Environmental Protection Agency, said many retrofittings now cost $100 to $150. She said Freon's high price was raising interest in R-134a sooner than the E.P.A. had anticipated. And converting may prove wise for people who plan to hold onto older cars, because it eliminates the need to ever use Freon again.</p>
        <p>But Ward Atkinson, a consultant to the mobile air-conditioning society and owner of a repair shop in Scottsdale, Ariz., encourages his customers to use Freon as long as it is available. Older cars "are designed to run on R-12 and have the best performance and durability" with it, he said. Consumers should consider switching to R-134a only when they have to fix a serious air-conditioner problem, he said.</p>
        <p>In addition to R-134a, consumers can choose from other refrigerants intended  as transition products. One of these, Frigc, has been on the market since 1995 and will soon be offered at 550 Jiffy Lube outlets. Replacing Freon with Frigc costs less than $100.</p>
        <p>In addition to R-134a and Frigc, the E.P.A. has found two other refrigerants, Ikon-12 and Freezone, to be environmentally safe. Ms. Hufford said the agency was likely within a few months to allow the use of several other refrigerants: R-406A, GHG-X4, GHG-HP, Hot Shot and Freeze 12.</p>
        <p>While consumers may have plenty of choices, the air-conditioning industry is  concerned about the proliferation of refrigerants. When a unit is serviced, mechanics are required to capture the Freon for recycling. But when customers bring in cars that have alternative refrigerants, the substances are often pulled into recycling machines, where they taint the supply of pure Freon. "Once you have that contaminated stock, you can't put that back into someone's car," said Gregory Dana of the Association of International Automobile Manufacturers.</p>
        <p>Though the E.P.A. requires special fittings and labels that identify refrigerants, companies are not required to install them until the agency has determined that their products are acceptable. Ms. Hufford said the E.P.A. planned an enforcement effort against mechanics who are legally required to install the fittings but do not do so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
