<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q.&amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860505"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GARDENS AND GARDENING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GALITZKI, DORA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5DA1239F934A15755C0A960958260" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q.&amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dora Galitzki</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GALITZKI, DORA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Switching Azaleas</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Switching Azaleas</p>
        <p>Q.  We are redesigning our garden to make it less formal. Can you suggest something to replace the azaleas that we have always depended on for flowering shrubs?</p>
        <p>A.  This is a chance to eat your cake and have it, too.</p>
        <p>Switch those stiff, overpowering hybrids that explode into color and then fizzle out for native, deciduous azaleas.</p>
        <p>All azaleas should not be judged by their loudmouthed relatives. Native species offer benefits that the hybrids can't match.</p>
        <p>Flowering does not have to be restricted to spring; by choosing a selection of natives you can have blooms the entire season. Long, graceful, tubular flowers range from subtle to brightly colored, with feathery stamens and spicy-sweet fragrances. The foliage of many deciduous natives turns orange-red in the fall.</p>
        <p>Their range of growth habit, color and period of bloom makes natives more useful in the natural garden than those bright but boring hybrids planted next to every house since the 1920's.</p>
        <p>Of course many natives also flower in April and May. But in summer, when the  hybrids are just a memory, there are natives that will flower in every month.</p>
        <p>June and early July bring Rhododendron arborescens (sweet azalea, 6 to 8 feet), with very fragrant, bright white flowers with long red stamens and glossy green foliage.</p>
        <p>R. viscosum (swamp azalea or swamp honeysuckle, 5 to 6 feet) blooms later in  June and July, with fragrant white flowers.</p>
        <p>In late July or August you can be enjoying R. prunifolium (plumleaf azalea, 10 to 12 feet), with showy orange-red flowers. The flowers are bright, but against the foliage they become more subtle.</p>
        <p>As late as September or October, R. serrulatum (Florida hammocksweet azalea,  5 to 6 feet) provides lovely white flowers for the breakfast table. All are reliably hardy to Zone 6.</p>
        <p>Remember, azaleas are classified botanically as rhododendrons and are usually found listed under rhododendron in catalogues. Mail order sources include Eastern Plant Specialties, Box 226, Georgetown, Me. 04548, (207) 371-2888, catalogue $3; and Woodlanders, 1128 Colleton, Aiken, S.C. 29801, (803) 648-7522, catalogue $2.</p>
        <p>Cultivar or Variety?</p>
        <p>Q.  I am confused about the difference between cultivars and varieties. Can you address these terms?</p>
        <p>A.  Genus and species names are those two Latin words we glance at and promptly forget. They are actually the most common two in a series that places living things in a variety of pigeonholes, including kingdom, class, order and phylum; they show what is related to what, and how close or distant the relationship is.</p>
        <p>In the 18th century, when Linnaeus invented the naming system that is still used in biology and botany today, he expected that every plant would have a unique and universally recognized two-word name by using just genus and species, one capitalized and one not. Campanula cochleariifolia refers to the same plant  the world over.</p>
        <p>But sometimes differences arise as a result of natural mutation and uncontrolled cross-pollination in the wild. These differences may be important,  but not large enough to justify a new species name, and the plants need to be accommodated. They are called varieties, and their differences are likely (but not guaranteed) to reproduce well from seed. Variety names, in Latin, are not capitalized and simply follow the species name, sometimes set off by "var." Campanula glomerata acaulis is a dwarf form of its popular parent, Campanula glomerata.</p>
        <p>Cultivars (a contraction of cultivated and variety) are plants that have been bred or selected for desirable characteristics. They are propagated vegetatively, from cuttings rather than seeds, because their seedlings generally do not reproduce the parent. Cultivar names are capitalized, are set in single quotes in botanical usage, are not italicized, are frequently not Latin and are  more marketing-oriented. Campanula cochleariifolia Miranda is a stronger grower  than C. cochleariifolia.</p>
        <p>All this helps to avoid the confusion of common names, which change from place to place and generation to generation. All thanks to Carl von Linne, more  commonly known by his Latin name, Linnaeus. You would think that he would know better.</p>
        <p>Foliar Fertilizers</p>
        <p>Q.  I understand that I can provide my plants with nutrients by spraying the  leaves rather than using traditional fertilizers applied to the soil. If this is so, how should I go about it?</p>
        <p>A.  In the category Greatest Thing Since Sliced Bread, Horticulture Division, the hands-down winner would appear to be foliar feeding products that claim to help increase growth and disease resistance with a simple spray. If only it were so.</p>
        <p>Plant leaves are designed for transpiration -- allowing oxygen and carbon dioxide to pass in and out -- but not much else.</p>
        <p>Some nutrients can be absorbed in small amounts, and foliar spraying can be valuable for quickly correcting deficiencies in micronutrients like boron, iron, calcium or manganese, which are needed in extremely small quantities.</p>
        <p>Leaves can't absorb the larger quantities of the major nutrients (nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium), so applying them through the soil is best.</p>
        <p>It is harder to get a plant to change its feeding habits than it is a teen-ager, so why try? Let the roots do what they are built for, absorbing nutrients, and let the leaves do what they were developed for, collecting sunshine and making food.</p>
        <p>Dora Galitzki, a specialist on woody plants, runsthe plant information service at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dora Galitzki, a specialist on woody plants, runsthe plant information service at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
