<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Town-House Renovation Becomes a Family Affair</title>
    <meta content="15HABI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Habitats/347 East 52d Street" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats/347 East 52d Street"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Randi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reich, Jeffrey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DD163AF936A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Town-House Renovation Becomes a Family Affair</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Town house on East 52d Street in Manhattan that had seven rent-stabilized apartments is being converted into two units for its new owners, Barbara and Jeffrey Reich and Randi Kahn, Jeffrey's sister, and her husband, Alan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AROUND the corner on First Avenue, an old neighborhood institution, Billy's 1870 steak house, survives. But across the street, a fancy bakery now lists ''eggs en cocotte'' on its breakfast menu and lets its clientele admire its patisseries from rattan armchairs.</p>
        <p>In this changing neighborhood in the East 50's, a young brother and sister, Jeffrey Reich and Randi Kahn -- joined in the deal by their respective spouses -- have bought an impressive town house with a black marble-veneered facade, and are proceeding to rip everything out and build themselves comfortable quarters for two couples.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AROUND the corner on First Avenue, an old neighborhood institution, Billy's 1870 steak house, survives. But across the street, a fancy bakery now lists ''eggs en cocotte'' on its breakfast menu and lets its clientele admire its patisseries from rattan armchairs.</p>
        <p>In this changing neighborhood in the East 50's, a young brother and sister, Jeffrey Reich and Randi Kahn -- joined in the deal by their respective spouses -- have bought an impressive town house with a black marble-veneered facade, and are proceeding to rip everything out and build themselves comfortable quarters for two couples.</p>
        <p>At 347 East 52d Street, they have made it a family affair, working together to move out a group of rent-stabilized tenants in seven months. That Herculean task accomplished, they continue to divide to conquer, with each assigned an area on which to focus.</p>
        <p>''We kind of divided it up, with our taking the area that interested us most,'' Ms. Kahn explained. Mr. Reich, 28, a lawyer, took the facade. Alan Kahn, Ms. Kahn's husband, took the plumbing and heating; the two women worked with an architect on their respective floor plans.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kahn, at 32 the oldest, runs a small systems-management company. He talks the least, and jokes about it, deferring to his more voluble wife and brother-in-law. But Mr. Kahn is, in a way, the most boyish in his delight over the house.</p>
        <p>Downstairs, in the ground floor he and his wife have recaptured from a huge boiler and a lot of trash -- they're taking the bottom two floors of the five-story house -- Mr. Kahn jumped from one level of the two-tiered floor to the other, full of enthusiasm for their plans.</p>
        <p>''I can have a little wet bar here,'' he said, gesturing to a spot a little more than halfway to the back of the ground floor on the left side. ''And this is where we'll put the television, and my friends'll drop by and we'll watch football.'' Crossing to the series of steel casement windows across the back, leading out to an unusual dug-out terrace with steep stairs leading up to a walled garden, he said, ''And if there's any money left, we may put in a little rock garden with a fountain.''</p>
        <p>The partners don't know much about the history of the town house, but they expect to learn more. One of the former tenants returns to Manhattan from Europe this fall and has promised to tell them of the parties once held in the basement apartment.</p>
        <p>''We don't know,'' said Barbara Reich, 28, ''but we hear there was once a piano, and Judy Garland came down and sang here once or twice.''</p>
        <p>The Kahns are expecting their first child in early January, which was one of the reasons they chose the downstairs space -- to make it easier for mother and toddler to run in and out of the house. They also liked the garden, and Mr. Kahn thought the darkest space, the room toward the front of the house on the ground floor, would make an ideal home office for his business.</p>
        <p>''We're going to get a nice fake window and put some light behind it,'' said Mrs. Kahn, pointing to the east wall, currently stripped down to bare brick like the rest of the interior walls.</p>
        <p>When they chose floors, the Reichs chose the top two -- ''Luckily, there was an elevator,'' said Mr. Reich with a laugh -- and hope to make their own outdoor space on the 1,250-square-foot roof. (The third floor will be used by both families for guests.)</p>
        <p>The Reichs plan to put a 15-foot wall of glass windows across the back on the top floor -- which will contain their living room, kitchen and dining room -- and remove three feet back across the roof for a skylight, or greenhouse effect. The Reichs found an elaborate limestone Tudor fireplace mantel on the second floor and, with their relatives' permission, reinstalled it on the top floor. They will put their three bedrooms on the fourth floor.</p>
        <p>The mantel is about the only architectural detail left inside; the house is gutted now. The duct work will be finished in two weeks, ''and then we'll really fly,'' said Mr. Kahn.</p>
        <p>ONLY a few months ago, the house was packed with people. When the two couples saw it, only two floors -- the first and second -- were vacant. Altogether, there were seven rent-stabilized tenants.</p>
        <p>To most people intent on changing a town house to two-family use, the situation might have seemed hopeless. But as Mr. Reich explained it, because the tenants were rent-stabilized and not rent-controlled, the would-be buyers felt they had a good chance, since New York's rent-stabilization rules allow a property with rent-stabilized tenants to be converted to the new owners' personal use after the tenants' leases run out.</p>
        <p>And one of the good things about the property, as far as the Reichs were concerned, was that all the tenants' leases were set to run out on the same day: Jan. 1, 1996.</p>
        <p>They looked at the house in August 1995, and they knew -- they had been looking at houses for almost a year -- that they would have to give three months' notice before those leases ran out.</p>
        <p>They saw the house on Aug. 1; they negotiated and agreed on the $650,000 price in the next few days, and eventually, the notices were sent out on time, by Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>And even though they believed that they could win any court case brought by the tenants after they notified them their leases would not be renewed, the Reichs say they thought the best strategy was to try to settle with as many of them as possible anyway.</p>
        <p>''Altogether, we paid less than $100,000,'' said Ms. Kahn. ''With the renovation costs, we'll end up spending less than $200 per square foot. Given what we'll end up with -- versus some cookie-cutter condo or co-op -- it's a bargain.''</p>
        <p>''We're happy,'' said her brother.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kahn and Ms. Reich, the more silent ones, nodded in agreement.</p>
        <p>Habitats/347 East 52d Street</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
