<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Only Shakespeare Had Been in the House</title>
    <meta content="24GLOB$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="873042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Globe Theater (London)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shakespeare, William (1564-1616)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Two Gentlemen of Verona (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/William Shakespeare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D81639F937A1575BC0A960958260" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Only Shakespeare Had Been in the House</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN RIDING</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two Gentlemen of Verona is first play staged in newly finished replica of Shakespeare's Globe theater, London; cast and 900 members of audience who were sitting on wooden benches in three galleries around protruding stage were able for first time to enjoy Shakespeare's play more or less as author himself would have seen it four centuries ago; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>England being England, the main topic of conversation was the weather. So when years of dreaming, fund-raising and construction climaxed in the first staged play at the replica of Shakespeare's Globe Theater here this week, it seemed almost as significant that ''The Two Gentlemen of Verona'' was performed on a warm evening under clear skies.</p>
        <p>Naturally, there are no illusions that even global warming can banish wet and chilly summers from London. But for a theater project that has lived under clouds of skepticism, it was a reassuring sign from on high that Wednesday's first night at the open-air playhouse did not include the drenching of the 500 ''groundlings'' standing in the ''bear pit'' before the stage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>England being England, the main topic of conversation was the weather. So when years of dreaming, fund-raising and construction climaxed in the first staged play at the replica of Shakespeare's Globe Theater here this week, it seemed almost as significant that ''The Two Gentlemen of Verona'' was performed on a warm evening under clear skies.</p>
        <p>Naturally, there are no illusions that even global warming can banish wet and chilly summers from London. But for a theater project that has lived under clouds of skepticism, it was a reassuring sign from on high that Wednesday's first night at the open-air playhouse did not include the drenching of the 500 ''groundlings'' standing in the ''bear pit'' before the stage.</p>
        <p>Instead they and the 900 members of the audience who were sitting on wooden benches in three galleries around the protruding stage were able for the first time to enjoy a Shakespeare play more or less as the author himself would have seen it four centuries ago. And their hearty laughter and loud applause suggested that this latest Globe -- the first was destroyed by fire in 1613, the second was closed by the Puritans in 1642 -- had gotten off to a rousing start.</p>
        <p>Some London critics complained that, by treating ''The Two Gentlemen of Verona'' as a comedy set in modern dress, Jack Shepherd's production veered toward pantomime. But if the director was after audience participation, he was not disappointed. When the love-struck Julia asked for ''a holy kiss'' from the departing Proteus and he offered only a handshake, a voice in the crowd interceded, ''Go on, give her a kiss.''</p>
        <p>Certainly, while the production chose to play down the darker side of the work -- notably Proteus's double betrayal of Julia and his best friend, Valentine, the other gentleman from Verona -- it proved to be a highly successful housewarming. And Shakespeare, who never shied from playing to the crowd, would presumably have approved. After all, there is ample time ahead for tragedy.</p>
        <p>Shakespeare's words were first tested in the new ''wooden O'' during a series of workshops last summer. And even now, with 29 performances of ''The Two Gentlemen of Verona'' scheduled through Sept. 15, the Globe is still only in what it calls a ''prologue season.'' Next year its first full mid-May to mid-September season will include four Shakespeare plays. (The program, a mix of comedy, tragedy and royal dramas, will be announced in November.)</p>
        <p>Even then visitors may have to dodge scaffolding and cranes. But by the time the entire $45 million Shakespeare Globe Center is completed in 1999, it will comprise a 300-seat indoor theater modeled after a 1617 design by Inigo Jones, a restaurant and shopping area, an education center, a library and offices. A Shakespeare exhibition will eventually be housed in a large basement below the complex.</p>
        <p>The jewel, of course, is the theater. Constructed in the traditional manner, with Norfolk reeds providing the thatched roof, oak trees turned into beams and pillars and lime plaster covering the walls, most of its public area is now ready. But a final decision on the shape of the stage awaits the results of this summer's experience. By next spring, a permanent stage will be in place.</p>
        <p>Still, with this week's performances it is apparent that Sam Wanamaker's dream of turning back the clock to 1599 will now come true. The American actor, who came to London in 1949 expecting to find a Globe Theater, established the Globe Playhouse Trust in 1970 to raise funds to rebuild the Globe. Soon the local Southwark council offered a 1.2-acre plot of land on the south bank of the Thames, some 200 yards from the site of the original Globe.</p>
        <p>Finally, with research completed and enough money in the till to break ground (most of the early donations came from the United States), construction began in 1987. And by the time Mr. Wanamaker died in December 1993, the theater was taking shape. An $18.6 million grant from the profits of Britain's new National Lottery last year enabled work to proceed on the rest of the center. But Mr. Wanamaker remains the project's spiritual father. ''It's a great tragedy that Sam is not here,'' Mark Rylance, the Globe's artistic director, said this week.</p>
        <p>Now the challenge is to make the theater work. ''You don't want this thing to be like Madame Tussaud's -- you come, you see, you go,'' said Marina Blodget, the theater's director of international liaison and Mr. Wanamaker's former assistant. ''You want people to come to the theater. We know there is a fine line between theater and tourism and it will all depend on the content.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rylance, a Royal Shakespeare Company-trained actor who plays Proteus in this first production, said he chose to start with ''The Two Gentlemen of Verona'' because it was ''a sort of prologue play,'' written around 1594 before Shakespeare took over the Globe. By picking a work rarely performed and not widely read, Mr. Rylance also hoped the audience would have few preconceptions about how it should be done.</p>
        <p>In reality, the peculiarities of the theater tend to impose themselves. Plays are to be performed in natural light or, when lights are needed in the late summer, the bear pit and the stage are to be illuminated in such a way that performers are never spotlighted. With no wing spaces, all the actors must enter from three doors to the rear, immediately below a gallery for musicians and ''lords.'' There are also two pillars to contend with onstage.</p>
        <p>Further, the players can see and, in some cases, are even close enough to touch their public. In trying to recapture the mood of the original Globe, where the groundlings felt free to wander in and out, eat and drink and cheer or heckle, much is  now being made of interaction between actors and audience. Reverential silence before Shakespeare, it seems, was not a thing of the past.</p>
        <p>Even without audience participation, however, the theater's acoustics may provide the stiffest test for performers. They face occasional competition from aircraft passing overhead and motorboats on the Thames,  and they must make themselves heard by a public on three sides of the stage. ''Any line that is muttered disappears,'' Mr. Shepherd explained. ''The key is to keep the language alive without allowing it to become declamatory.''</p>
        <p>For its ''prologue season,'' then, the Globe Theater views itself as very much a work in progress, in a learning process that may go on for  years. ''The aim is to make this Globe as authentic as possible,'' Mr. Rylance said before the final dress rehearsal. ''We do not claim that this is it, but it's our best effort in 1996.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
