<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Run for Your Lives! The Dams Have Burst!</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="825893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="OUT OF ORDER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOUCHIER, DAVID</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFDE1639F93BA15752C0A960958260" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Run for Your Lives! The Dams Have Burst!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BOUCHIER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOUCHIER, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MARK TWAIN said that everybody complains about the weather, but nobody does anything about it. Our neighbors do something about it: they go to Florida. We get cards saying "The temperature today was 76 degrees, we keep the pool at 87.  We heard you had some snow up there." I suspect that they only go to Florida so  they can send these annoying messages.</p>
        <p>The moment the temperature in the Sunshine State touches 80, our neighbors will be heading back north toward the temperate zone. The purpose of this extravagant migration is never to allow the outside air temperature to get high  enough or low enough to make an impression on their nerve endings. In other words, never to feel the heat, and never, ever, on any account, to feel the cold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MARK TWAIN said that everybody complains about the weather, but nobody does anything about it. Our neighbors do something about it: they go to Florida. We get cards saying "The temperature today was 76 degrees, we keep the pool at 87.  We heard you had some snow up there." I suspect that they only go to Florida so  they can send these annoying messages.</p>
        <p>The moment the temperature in the Sunshine State touches 80, our neighbors will be heading back north toward the temperate zone. The purpose of this extravagant migration is never to allow the outside air temperature to get high  enough or low enough to make an impression on their nerve endings. In other words, never to feel the heat, and never, ever, on any account, to feel the cold.</p>
        <p>What these metereological migrants have failed to notice is that Long Island has a temperate climate. The only really bad weather happens on television. Last summer, for example, July was slightly hotter than normal. Then we had a drought through most of August and September. Commonplace weather in many other parts of the globe. But watching the TV weather reports, you might have imagined that the end of the world was at hand. The screens were filled with images of cracked and empty reservoirs, stories of heat exhaustion, power outages and the imminent dehydration of the whole planet. My wife spent half the summer dragging hoses around the garden trying to defeat nature, like King Canute in reverse. For my part, I entirely gave up drinking water, as the great W. C. Fields recommended.</p>
        <p>Normal weather is a statistical myth. If the average rainfall on Long Island  in August is 4.01 inches, it doesn't mean that we will get 0.13 inches every day. It is just as likely to mean 30 days with no rain at all ("The drought of the century") and one enormous downpour that will immediately be labelled "The deluge of the century." An average snowfall, an average profit ratio, an average intelligence, an average child, an average hangover, are all part of a complicated bluff, designed to make life more exciting for journalists.</p>
        <p>No sooner had we survived the annual drought of the century than we were buried by the annual snowstorm of the century, which brought Long Island to a temporary standstill three weeks ago. The media went into their disaster frenzy: roofs had fallen in, schools had been closed, retail trade collapsed (except for snowblowers, which couldn't be bought at any price), there was no mail, the Long Island Rail Road ran even slower than usual and snow removal costs threatened to break the budget. When the snow began to melt, we were warned to watch out for devastating floods and potholes the size of moon craters.</p>
        <p>Alarmed by these messages of doom, everybody on the Island began buying all the food in the supermarkets as if famine was predicted, and mobbing the video stores and libraries in case they might actually have to talk to their families  during the emergency. Travel agents and airlines were overwhelmed by people trying to avoid the cool air. When the snow arrived some people in our neighborhood (the few not already in Florida) were so mad to get out, even before the snow plows came around, that that the streets were littered with abandoned cars, some stuck only half a block from home.</p>
        <p>Television weather reports make cowards of us all. Hundreds of thousands of people are driven to migrate by mystical, pseudo-scientic predictions about El Nino and Global Warming. It seems essential to keep on the move, at any cost, to avoid the imaginary deadly heat and deadly cold, to stay within the zone of no sensation whatsoever, to be comfortable.</p>
        <p>But comfort is a nonevent. A comfortable chair has no bumps or sharp edges. A comfortable hotel has no character or surprises. A comfortable sermon doesn't mention any of our favorite vices. The ultimate comfortable place is an isolation tank, specifically designed to eliminate every physical and mental sensation. When people use the awful phrase "Are you comfortable with that?" they are just asking to be reassured that we don't care.</p>
        <p>The Puritans would have been ashamed of us. They believed that a bit of discomfort helped to build character. Consider Capt. Robert Scott, the Antarctic explorer. After one of his wretched expeditions through the frozen continent in  1904, Captain Scott commented in a letter: "How much better this ordeal has been than lounging in too great comfort at home."</p>
        <p>I like to compare myself with Captain Scott as I scrape the ice off the windshield: Scott of the suburban Antarctic, going somewhere, doing something, feeling not at all comfortable with that. It is the kind of fortitude that built empires and allowed our ancestors to colonize even the most inhospitable corners of the world, likeLong Island.</p>
        <p>Now it's almost the end of January, only 52 days until the first day of spring. The weather has been calm since the big story. But February and March may test our fortitude again. We leave for Florida next week.</p>
        <p>OUT OF ORDER David Bouchier of Wading River is an essayist andcommentator heard regularly on public radio.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Bouchier of Wading River is an essayist andcommentator heard regularly on public radio.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
