<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth's Dominant Life Form Is Also Its Smallest: the Microbe</title>
    <meta content="15MICR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="883449"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE4DC1631F936A25753C1A960958260" item-length="2371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth's Dominant Life Form Is Also Its Smallest: the Microbe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Revolution is sweeping the earth sciences; scientists are discovering that microbes dwelling up to miles deep in planetary crust are responsible for creating and arranging rocks, seas, oils, soils, gases, metals and minerals that make up earth's surface; implication--considered likely but so far unproved--is that this hidden biosphere of trillions of microbes and their ancestors has played a dominant role, perhaps the dominant role, in forming planetary skin; photos of bacteria on cell surfaces of iron oxide and pure gold (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEEP in the heart of the Amazon jungle is a famous gold field known as Serra Pelada that lies far from the usual regions where the rare metal is mined. Discovered in the early 1980's, the find prompted many thousands of poor Brazilians to rush into the wilderness and, often digging by hand or with crude tools, to extract more than 100 tons of the precious metal. The episode is often referred to as history's biggest gold rush.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, scientists who later studied the site concluded that the rich lode was produced not by the accepted mechanisms of ore formation but by swarms of microbes that over millions of years concentrated the gold from jungle soils and rivers and rocks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEEP in the heart of the Amazon jungle is a famous gold field known as Serra Pelada that lies far from the usual regions where the rare metal is mined. Discovered in the early 1980's, the find prompted many thousands of poor Brazilians to rush into the wilderness and, often digging by hand or with crude tools, to extract more than 100 tons of the precious metal. The episode is often referred to as history's biggest gold rush.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, scientists who later studied the site concluded that the rich lode was produced not by the accepted mechanisms of ore formation but by swarms of microbes that over millions of years concentrated the gold from jungle soils and rivers and rocks.</p>
        <p>''There's lots of evidence that microbes played a critical role,'' Dr. William A. Fyfe, a leading environmental geochemist, based at the University of Western Ontario in London, Ontario, said in an interview. ''You find fossil bacteria and organic compounds all over the place.''</p>
        <p>Today Serra Pelada is seen as an example of a revolution that is quietly sweeping the earth sciences.</p>
        <p>In hundreds and perhaps thousands of cases, scientists are discovering that microbes dwelling up to miles deep in the planetary crust are responsible for creating and arranging the rocks, seas, oils, soils, gases, metals and minerals that make up the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>The implication -- considered likely but so far unproved -- is that this hidden biosphere of trillions of microbes and their ancestors has played a dominant role, perhaps the dominant role, in forming the planetary skin over the ages. Put irreverently, it is the rise of the shower scum.</p>
        <p>''We're still at the very beginning'' stages of understanding how microbes shaped the planet, said Dr. Henry L. Ehrlich, a biologist at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute in Troy, N.Y., who is the author of ''Geomicrobiology,'' a college text published by Marcel Dekker in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>This new view of how the earth's surface was shaped, which stresses the importance of subtle biological processes over the more overt ones of chemistry and physics, is supported by a growing body of evidence and is  shaking up the traditional disciplines of geology and microbiology. The hottest earth sciences today are exotic hybrids of the two, with names like geomicrobiology, microbial geology and environmental geochemistry.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of scientists in these fields are producing a wave of new findings and clues about how microbes do things like generating fossil fuels, catalyzing geochemical reactions and concentrating valuable metals like iron and gold.</p>
        <p>''It's becoming a flood,'' Dr. Fyfe of the University of Western Ontario said of the recent discoveries. ''The main conclusion is that if you don't understand the biosphere, you don't understand our environment.''</p>
        <p>As an example of the field's growth, Dr. Fyfe said that two decades ago scientists knew of 30 or 40 compounds and minerals that were made or amassed by microbes, often as excreta or body parts, much as humans concentrate calcium to make teeth and bones. ''Today the number is hundreds,'' he said. ''Every time we look harder, we find more.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Grant F. Ferris, a microbiologist at the University of Toronto, said swarms of tiny microbes had proved to be adept at forming ''an enormous variety of minerals -- carbonates, phosphates, oxides, sulfides and silicates as well as silver and gold.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Debra S. Stakes, a geochemist at the Monterey Bay Aquarium Research Institute in Moss Landing, Calif., said the microbial revolution was often hard for physical scientists to accept and fathom because it undercut so many old beliefs and tenets.</p>
        <p>''This is a huge challenge for geochemists,'' she said. ''What it says is that most geological processes at their more fundamental stages could be biologically mediated, which challenges our models for inorganic thermodynamics, for driving reactions.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Stakes added, ''It undermines our capability to predict what minerals should precipitate under what conditions because biological mediation changes the conditions.''</p>
        <p>On the positive side, the microbial revolution is seen as giving scientists not only new insights into the workings of the earth's environment, both today and in the past, but powerful agents of influence as well.</p>
        <p>For instance, studies are under way to see whether carbon dioxide from the burning of fossil fuels could be pumped underground into rocky formations where microbes would turn it into carbonates, which occur naturally and widely as limestone. And microbes injected into wells might clean up polluted water and stimulate the production of natural gas. Mining with microbes is also under study, including the tapping of gold ores normally too dilute for recovery.</p>
        <p>Another use attracting wide interest is studying the earth's microbial ecology as a tool for understanding faraway places like Mars, which was recently in the headlines with a report by scientists that the planet may have once harbored primitive microbes. Insights into terrestrial microbes and their effects, scientists say, can only aid Martian explorations that seek to find extraterrestrial life or evidence of its workings long ago.</p>
        <p>''To read the fossil record more intelligently on Mars, you have to understand it here,'' Dr. Fyfe said.</p>
        <p>In general, scientists say, the microbial revolution is a key to understanding the universe and the earth's place in it.</p>
        <p>''It's a hot field,'' said Richard J. Leveille, a graduate student studying with Dr. Fyfe. ''The discovery of microorganisms in the earth's crust is very recent. Their influence has been overlooked.''</p>
        <p>Although individual microbes are largely invisible to the eye, in general they are the oldest, most numerous and most diverse forms of life on the planet. Some of their habitats and effects are obvious, like microbial rusts that speed the weathering of rocks and microbial slimes that form mineral precipitates around ponds.</p>
        <p>But in the last decade or so scientists around the globe have discovered that microbes thrive in an even wider range of habitats. In essence, scientists are discovering them wherever there is water at temperatures from about 20 degrees to 250 degrees Fahrenheit, including the icy poles, the deep sea, hot springs, volcanic fissures and, most recently, deep underground, in some cases miles down.</p>
        <p>Experts say the enormous range of microbial life was often overlooked in the past because the tiny creatures -- so small that up to millions can inhabit a drop of water -- are easy to miss and hard to investigate, especially when found deep in the earth's rocky pores and cracks.</p>
        <p>Much of the recent discovery of deep microbes has been done by governments exploring the practicality of storing nuclear wastes underground and trying to understand what effects microbes could have on metallic waste canisters and their contents. So far, the world depth record for the finding of microbes appears to be 2.6 miles, where diverse colonies thrived at a temperature of 230 degrees Fahrenheit.</p>
        <p>So great is the aggregate bulk of these microbial organisms throughout the earth's crust that over the billions of years of geologic time, their cumulative biological mass is now seen as probably exceeding that of the planet as a whole -- all 6 sextillion, 588 quintillion tons of it.</p>
        <p>''It could be several times the mass of the earth,'' Dr. Fyfe said, cautioning that such estimates were extremely crude given the current state of microbial knowledge.</p>
        <p>A gripping example of microbial handiwork is Serra Pelada, which Dr. Fyfe and his colleagues have carefully investigated, concluding that the rich lode was produced by microbes. Among the bits of evidence, he said, were not only fossil bacteria and organic compounds in the field but careful demonstrations in the laboratory of how microbes can concentrate gold.</p>
        <p>Such work was pioneered by Dr. Terence J. Beveridge of the University of Guelph, in Ontario, one of Dr. Fyfe's former students. Working with microscopes and chemical enrichments in a laboratory, he found that microbes easily crystallized a variety of metals on their cellular surfaces in pure form, including iron, magnesium, copper, sodium, potassium, manganese, zinc, calcium and gold.</p>
        <p>''Tiny crystals of pure gold,'' Dr. Fyfe emphasized. ''So we know they do these things.'' Photomicrographs published in The Journal of Bacteriology by Dr. Beveridge show microbes encircled by dense, growing crystals of gold.</p>
        <p>The range of natural deposits tied to gold-microbe interplay is on the rise, said Dr. Gordon Southam, a geomicrobiologist at Northern Arizona University in Flagstaff, Ariz. His research links the life factor to gold placers, deposits found around the globe that are traditionally seen as formed by weathering and the separation of rocks of differing densities in places like swift-running rivers.</p>
        <p>But his studies of placer nodules suggest that the process of gold concentration is catalyzed by microscopic miners. ''The transformation is organic,'' he said. ''It's mediated by microbes.''</p>
        <p>Scientists say that this generic process, which is known as biomineralization, can be passive or active. In the former case, the cell walls of microbes simply bind dissolved minerals, speeding precipitation and often completely encrusting cells.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ehrlich of Rensselaer Polytechnic noted that such crystallization, once started biologically, can often continue on its own. ''It can act as a seed or a nucleus for crystal formation,'' he said, much as salt crystallizes out of sea water.</p>
        <p>In the active case, a microbe's metabolism prompts the making of minerals inside or outside its cellular walls, often by something as simple as excretions that change the acidity of surrounding solutions. For instance, blue-green bacteria living in naturally alkaline waters produce even higher alkalinity, precipitating carbonate minerals like calcite, the basic ingredient of limestone, chalk and marble.</p>
        <p>Microbes can also seek out metals and chemically process them to release energy for their growth, often concentrating the metals in the process, for instance, diverse oxides of iron and manganese.</p>
        <p>In many cases, scientists say, the physiological role of the metals, minerals and compounds processed by microbes is poorly understood and represents a research frontier.</p>
        <p>In addition, the ties between the living and the nonliving realms are often fuzzy and represent areas of intense study.</p>
        <p>''There are times when the biological connections are obvious, as with the great sedimentary carbonate or phosphate deposits,'' said Dr. Fyfe. These include the White Cliffs of Dover in the former case and an important ingredient of fertilizers in the latter case.</p>
        <p>''But in other cases the connections are more tenuous,'' he added, ''as with uranium in phosphate deposits or molybdenum in coal.''</p>
        <p>Beyond minerals, scientists are studying realms like microbial influence in the formation of gases. An example of such work appears in the Sept. 12 issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>Scientists from the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor and the Chevron Petroleum Technology Company in La Habra, Calif., studied a big natural gas field in Michigan that was thought to have been made as the earth's heat cooked rich organic remains in a bed of shale about 370 million years old. Shale is a fine-grained rock made of ancient silt and clay.</p>
        <p>But it turned out that the gas was actively produced by billions of microbes, as revealed in part by high concentrations in industrial gas wells of carbon-13, a kind of microbial excreta and a sign of active life. Carbon at the earth's surface occurs in a variety of isotopes, or forms, including carbon-13 and carbon-12, which most plants and animals prefer.</p>
        <p>The finding is ''economically important and unexpected,'' said Anna M. Martini, an author of the Nature paper at the University of Michigan, adding that it pointed to new sources of natural gas globally.</p>
        <p>Another area of microbial studies centers on fossils. In an article in the September issue of Geology, published by the Geological Society of America, British and French scientists suggest that microbes are responsible for the preservation of ancient soft tissues, their powers of mineralizing turning them into rock.</p>
        <p>Microbes found in the earth's crust, while studied mainly to elucidate their hidden natural roles, are also increasingly being put to work on a host of projects. The Newmont Mining Corporation of Denver is studying whether microbial miners can eat the sulfur and iron out of gold ore, releasing the gold from its mineral bonds and making it easier to leach out.</p>
        <p>And Dr. Fyfe of the University of Western Ontario is working closely with the Chinese to investigate the possibility of pumping microbes and carbon dioxide from the burning of coal into China's exhausted oil fields, forming mineral precipitates.</p>
        <p>''We've had numerous discussions,'' he said. ''They're very interested because they know they have a problem'' with rising releases of carbon dioxide from burning coal, which many scientists believe is helping trap heat in the earth's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In preparation for Mars explorations, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration is studying earth microbes and their mineralogical effects as possible models for Martian ones. The studies are taking place at Mono Lake in California, a highly alkaline body of water whose floor is covered with hot volcanic vents and microbial communities. It is considered an alien environment much like what existed on early Mars.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stakes of the Monterey Bay institute and her colleagues at NASA, Stanford University and the Naval Postgraduate School explored the lake last year with a robot and plan to do so again next year.</p>
        <p>Reflecting on the recent explosion of microbe studies, Dr. Stakes said the belated understanding of the wide influence of the tiny organisms was a lesson in scientific modesty.</p>
        <p>''These processes have gone on for billions of years and we just didn't know about them,'' she said. ''And there are probably other processes -- the earth's primary regulating processes -- that we haven't discovered yet. It's pretty amazing and humbling.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
