<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spring Is Earlier Than 20 Years Ago</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="864963"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFD71E39F935A25754C0A960958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spring Is Earlier Than 20 Years Ago</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RESEARCHERS say they have evidence that spring is arriving a week earlier in  the Northern Hemisphere than it did 20 years ago, perhaps because of a gradual rise in global temperatures.</p>
        <p>The scientists, who monitor the fluctuating amounts of carbon dioxide in the  atmosphere, say this is the first time such a general increase in the length of  the growing season has been reported. The seasonal variations in the uptake of carbon dioxide by plants in the Northern Hemisphere have become more pronounced  since the 1970's, the scientists say, and these changes seem to correspond to a  rise in temperatures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RESEARCHERS say they have evidence that spring is arriving a week earlier in  the Northern Hemisphere than it did 20 years ago, perhaps because of a gradual rise in global temperatures.</p>
        <p>The scientists, who monitor the fluctuating amounts of carbon dioxide in the  atmosphere, say this is the first time such a general increase in the length of  the growing season has been reported. The seasonal variations in the uptake of carbon dioxide by plants in the Northern Hemisphere have become more pronounced  since the 1970's, the scientists say, and these changes seem to correspond to a  rise in temperatures.</p>
        <p>Dr. Charles D. Keeling, an authority on atmospheric carbon dioxide from the  Scripps Institution of Oceanography at the University of California at San Diego, is the principal investigator in the new studies. He said the findings were not extensive enough to prove conclusively that the longer growing season and increases in the seasonal swings of atmospheric carbon dioxide attributed to plants were due to global warming caused by human activity.</p>
        <p>"But our measurements of the increase in seasonal changes of carbon dioxide levels conform very well with temperature measurements going back to the late 1950's showing that surface temperatures are getting warmer," he said.</p>
        <p>Measurements of average global temperatures indicate that the surface of Earth has warmed by as much as 1 degree Celsius, or about 2 degrees Fahrenheit,  in the last century. Experts say this warming is most pronounced in the winter and in the upper latitudes, or arctic regions.</p>
        <p>"Small changes in temperature -- averaging only a fraction of a degree Celsius a year -- are nevertheless causing fairly large changes in plant growth," Dr. Keeling said.</p>
        <p>In a report published in the current issue of the journal Nature, Dr. Keeling and his colleagues said measurements of atmospheric carbon dioxide taken at Mauna Loa, Hawaii, and Point Barrow, Alaska, for almost 40 years show changing patterns of plant growth in the Northern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Each year, the level of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere drops during the growing season, then rises again as plants die and decay or become dormant.</p>
        <p>Dr. Keeling and his colleagues, including Timothy P. Whorf of Scripps and John F.S. Chin of the Mauna Loa Observatory, monitor these changes at Mauna Loa  and at Port Barrow. They say that since the 1960's, the difference between the atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide in summer and winter has risen by 20 percent in Hawaii and by 40 percent in the Arctic and that the oscillation started becoming greater in the mid-1970's. It was also around 1975 that spring  started coming slightly earlier each year.</p>
        <p>Dr. Keeling said the data from each station applied to a large area of the Northern Hemisphere. But he added, "We infer that the region most affected by change is fairly far north."</p>
        <p>Dr. Tom M. L. Wigley, a climatologist at the National Center for Atmospheric  Research in Boulder, Colo., said: "It seems entirely plausible that there can be variations in the time spring begins or fall ends." Dr. Wigley said the new research could not prove a human influence on climate, but he said he personally thought that global warming stemmed from human activity.</p>
        <p>Dr. John M. Wallace, a professor of atmospheric sciences at the University of Washington in Seattle who has expressed doubts about some assertions that human  activity is affecting the climate, said the new report was based on solid work.  "However, I find it hard to believe that the warming we've had so far can advance the growing season by as much as a week. There are other possible explanations for more carbon dioxide being taken up earlier, such as changes in  land use in the last 20 years."</p>
        <p>Dr. Keeling said different land-use patterns would not account for changing carbon dioxide patterns. He pointed out that the change was especially large at  high latitudes.</p>
        <p>Some scientists attribute much of global warming to the burning of fossil fuels, which add carbon dioxide, methane and other so-called greenhouse gases to the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
