<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>90degrees? Only in May. But Summer Brings The Missing Spring.</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="868683"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDS AND ACHIEVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEINFIELD, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D91439F932A05754C0A960958260" item-length="1424" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>90degrees? Only in May. But Summer Brings The Missing Spring.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEINFIELD, N R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some summer.</p>
        <p>It's been cloudy. It's been cool. It's been windy. It's been rainy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some summer.</p>
        <p>It's been cloudy. It's been cool. It's been windy. It's been rainy.</p>
        <p>But where's the heat?</p>
        <p>Good question. For the first time since meteorologists started keeping reliable records in 1876, there has not been a single day in either June or July in which the temperature in Central Park has reached 90 degrees. Last June and July saw 14 90-degree days. And not since 1889 has a July come and gone without  benefit of a 90-degree day. It's as if some gigantic fan has been trained on the region, and no one can turn it off.</p>
        <p>"This is an extraordinary year," said Lee Grenci, a meteorologist with the Penn State Weather Communications Group. "That's a no-brainer."</p>
        <p>Yesterday's high was only 73 degrees, and more coolness -- along with more rain -- is likely today.</p>
        <p>Perhaps this has been splendid for sweater manufacturers, but it has been relentless misery for air-conditioner salesmen and beachgoers waking up to yet another day of brisk temperatures and a chance of thundershowers. Yet a surprising number of people said they are much merrier about this weather than about the sweltering, humidity-dripping days of the last few summers.</p>
        <p>"I think this cool weather is fantastic," said Sandra Ferdman, a literature professor who lives on the Upper East Side of Manhattan. "I don't feel the least bit jealous of the people in the Hamptons who went there to escape the heat."</p>
        <p>But where did this brisk weather come from?</p>
        <p>"The weather works in waves," Mr. Grenci said. "There has been a warm ridge of high pressure in the West and that has favored a trough of low pressure in the East. A trough is associated with cloudiness and precipitation. If you block out the sun, it doesn't get very hot. That's basic science."</p>
        <p>But why is that warm ridge ensconced in the West?</p>
        <p>"That's an existential question," Mr. Grenci said. "The atmosphere can just get locked into certain patterns. We are currently locked into a certain pattern favoring warm weather in the West and cooler weather in the East. Such are the vagaries of the weather."</p>
        <p>Indeed, anyone who may think that warm weather has simply gone out of fashion need only ponder the fact that Portland, Ore., has had 12 days of 90-degree weather this month, the most ever for the city. That, of course, is small consolation to families vacationing on the Jersey Shore with six kids and no board games.</p>
        <p>This whole year has been berserk as far as the weather is concerned. It did nothing but snow all winter. Spring never happened; it was either too cold or too hot. The only 90-degree days in New York were on May 20 and May 21. Back then, New Yorkers were denouncing global warming and fearing a summer of 200-degree weather.</p>
        <p>Meteorologists, though, do not believe that the summer's coolness necessarily has anything to do with the snowy winter and weird spring.</p>
        <p>"The atmosphere is just too complex and chaotic to draw a correlation between one season and the next," Mr. Grenci said. But he said that a study of the weather in State College, Pa., since the late 1880's found that cool springs tended to be followed by cool summers.</p>
        <p>Aside from the lack of sun and heat, nearly half the days of June and July -- 26, to be precise -- have also produced measurable precipitation. Thanks to the  remnants of Hurricane Bertha, 1.77 inches of rain drenched the city on July 13 alone. The average rainfall over the last 30 years for June and July has been 8.02 inches; this year, 10.45 inches have fallen.</p>
        <p>The weather has made people testy. Ruth Finn, who is 75 and lives in Rye, N.Y., said that when she peeks outside and spies yet another dreary day of gray  skies, "I get claustrophobic, restless, disgusted.</p>
        <p>"Everything in me says, 'This is beach time,' " she said. "I look at the calendar and I think, 'Oh Lord, it's already August. Where has July gone, where  has the summer gone?' "</p>
        <p>But not everyone has found the foul weather something to lament. Julie Schonfeld, a rabbi for the Society for the Advancement of Judaism on the Upper West Side of Manhattan, said that she finds the weather "spiritually uplifting."</p>
        <p>Blake Myers, a 22-year-old New Yorker, said this has been the best summer for riding the subway. "By the time I get out, it doesn't look like I just ran a marathon," he said.</p>
        <p>Jaime Hait, an international fashion executive who lives in Chelsea, said, "I finally bought an air-conditioner this year, and I'm happy that the expense of buying it has been balanced out by not having the expense of running it."</p>
        <p>Enterprises that thrive on balmy weather feel otherwise. Lai Cauery, who sells hot dogs outside Carl Schurz Park in Manhattan, said, "We didn't make enough to cover our monthly rent to the Parks Department."</p>
        <p>Farmington River Tubing in New Hartford, Conn., runs tubing trips down the Farmington River, an activity that loses its appeal during thunderstorms and overcoat weather. "It's a very dreary time for us," said Sandee Harraden, an owner, who said business has been off by 20 percent.</p>
        <p>In Sag Harbor, L.I., Jod Lourie, a sculptor, was spending her first summer renting in the Hamptons. "It's been horrid, horrid, horrid," she grumbled as she sought refuge in Espresso, an Italian cafe.</p>
        <p>While the need for hand-warmers has curbed attendance at beaches, it has bolstered interest in shore alternatives like tours of lighthouses. "The park is packed today," said Rebecca Martin, a staff member at Barnegat Lighthouse State  Park on the Jersey Shore, where it was -- naturally -- cool and cloudy yesterday. "We're always really busy when it rains or it's cloudy."</p>
        <p>The unusual summer has meant that the reservoirs upstate have plenty of water, allowing homeowners to water their lawns any time they can find a dry day. And it has meant low energy use. One of the key barometers that Con Edison  tracks is days during which demand exceeds 10,000 megawatts. Last summer, there  were 13 of those days,including Aug. 2, when the utility set a record of 10,805  megawatts. This summer, there have been zero.</p>
        <p>The cool weather could not have come at a more welcome time for Northeast Utilities, which provides power for much of Connecticut. All four of its nuclear power plants are shut down, leaving it in a precarious position if power demand  were to reach high levels.</p>
        <p>"This summer has been absolutely wonderful for us in terms of meeting our demand for energy," said Myra Humphries, a spokeswoman for the utility.</p>
        <p>Air-conditioner salesmen, however, have been somber. "It's been bad for business," said Milton Borger, the manager of Borger's Air Conditioning in Manhattan. "If it's hot, muggy and sticky, people use the air-conditioner. If not, they open a window for fresh air." He said that sales have plunged 20 percent over last summer and that he has had to lay off half of his six employees.</p>
        <p>Demand for cold sweets has also slackened. "The rainy and dreary days and the cool nights don't bring people out for ice cream," said Al Angelini, a Carvel store owner in Thornwood, N.Y. In June alone, he said, he ordered 19 percent less ice cream than he did last year. To boost his sales, he is thinking of offering a buy-one-get-one-free special.</p>
        <p>Enough about June and July. What does this bode for August?</p>
        <p>All Mr. Grenci would say is, "The pattern could persist into August, but it's unlikely to persist through all of August."</p>
        <p>If you think it's impossible for the dog days of August to come without sweltering, oven-hot weather, consider: since record-keeping began, there have actually been 18 Augusts without a solitary 90-degree day. The last one was as recent as 1986.</p>
        <p>Don't put the sweaters away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
