<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Variety of Styles and Techniques Underscores Recent Shows</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="824552"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SPOKE, B J, GALLERY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PORT WASHINGTON PUBLIC LIBRARY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GRAPHIC EYEGALLERY (PORT WASHINGTON, LI)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRISON, HELEN A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E2D61339F932A15752C0A960958260" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Variety of Styles and Techniques Underscores Recent Shows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HELEN A. HARRISON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARRISON, HELEN A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Visions" B. J. Spoke Gallery, 299 Main St., Huntington. To next Sunday. 549-5106.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Visions" B. J. Spoke Gallery, 299 Main St., Huntington. To next Sunday. 549-5106.</p>
        <p>This is a large show of small pieces by members of the Huntington Township Art League. More than 140 artists are represented. Although there was no jury of selection, award winners have been chosen by Nesa Karakaplan, director of Gallery Authentique in Roslyn, which will be host of a show later in the year</p>
        <p>As a catchall title, "Visions" covers everything from straightforward representation to pure invention. A few of the artists have taken the theme literally, however, using the concept of sight, contemplation or imagination as  a starting point.</p>
        <p>Take, for example, Roz Udow's sensitive etching "The Eye," in which the organ of sight symbolizes the process by which images are communicated to the brain, linking visual sensations directly to the ideas they stimulate. Similarly, Barbara Berkowitz suggests both the eye and its connecting nerves in "Sphere IV," an award-winning abstraction with strong physiological references.</p>
        <p>In general the abstract works are the most appealing. Andrew Geller's tiny watercolor "Awakenings" nicely evokes the reviving effects of sunshine as a stimulus to natural growth, while Rhoda Needlman uses velvety pastels for a patchwork effect of flat colors in a schematic treatment of a lush "Landscape With Six Trees," another award winner.</p>
        <p>Vision as defined by reflected light is the subject of Randy Weisbin's monotype "Long Island Wetlands," in which translucent water shimmers under a hazy sky. The pall of a chilly overcast shadows the snowbanks in Edward McEvoy's "Wintercolor," a lovely watercolor that exploits the medium's capacity to render atmospheric nuances.</p>
        <p>Several of the more representational pieces also deserve notice, among them David A. Paulsen's oil study of "Tiska's Farm," a panoramic view over East End fields and hedgerows. "Red Beach," Mary Vitelli Berti's pastel of a seaside vignette, blends snapshot-style observation with a personalized approach to modeling and texture.</p>
        <p>Among the sculptures Arthur Bernhang's "Adornments" stands out for its balanced use of stone and steel, playing off curving loops of metal against the  angled surfaces of roughly carved rock.</p>
        <p>"Navigation and Mythology"  Port Washington Public Library, 1 Library Dr., Port Washington. To Jan. 30. 883-4400.</p>
        <p>Inspired by visits to ancient burial sites and the study of classical mythology, Irene Young has created a series of mixed-media works that take us on an imaginary journey. Its purpose seems to be to reconcile the spiritual and the concrete by unifying the observable with the metaphysical.</p>
        <p>That is a tall order, and sometimes Ms. Young's conflation of several cultural traditions seems forced. The variety of mythological characters invoked can become confusing, distracting attention from the search for coherent meaning. But when a specific story is interpreted or a general concept is defined, Ms. Young succeeds in creating provocative imagery.</p>
        <p>In "Crossroads" a circle formed by four trees leads the eye beneath the Earth's surface while simultaneously opening the vista to a view of a distant burial mound. The notion of exploration as a pathway to revelation is forcefully conveyed, with the Earth as a repository of mystical wisdom.</p>
        <p>"Phaeton's Folly" pictures the legend of the fiery chariot as if Zeus had not intervened to prevent Helios's son from burning the Earth.  Two horses, one light and one dark, do battle in the sky, while the charred landscape below testifies to the consequences of ungoverned ambition. Considering the prospects  of global warming and the destruction of the ozone layer, Ms. Young may well be using the myth as a cautionary tale with modern implications.</p>
        <p>Several of Ms. Young's pieces use doorways, portals, gates and entrances to divide and define the inner and outer realms. One of the most evocative is "Ladyshibet's Last Journey to the Unknown," in which a ring of standing stones radiates from an interior shrouded in occult significance. The core of energy at its center seems at once protected and accessible, emphasizing the links between the outside world and the inner source of power that continues to glow with the  subdued yet unquenchable force of an eternal flame.</p>
        <p>"So Many Possibilities"  Graphic Eye Gallery, 301 Main St., Port Washington. To Feb. 4. 883-9668.</p>
        <p>The year's first show highlights the variety of styles and graphic techniques used by the members of the cooperative gallery.</p>
        <p>Shellie Schneider's "Geo Series" of collages features shreds of painted paper that are combined to suggest landscape details. Earth, sky and water are jumbled together in seemingly interchangeable arrangements, yet the qualities of the elements, however abstracted, are still tangible.</p>
        <p>"Ice Floats and Ice House," Marion Klein's oil on paper, renders the landscape in bold strokes reminiscent of Marsden Hartley's forceful treatment of scenic terrain. A winter sun casts a welcome glow on the snow-covered hillside but cannot penetrate the frigid lake below.</p>
        <p>In her monotype "House Finch," Barbara Fishman uses feathered shapes in an abstracted treatment of the bird perched on a tree. Warm earthy tones herald the return of spring and with it the creatures that delight us with their saucy antics.</p>
        <p>Monotypes by Babs Kent imitate the glowing colors of stained glass windows, with their religious symbols illuminated by an inner radiance. Set against a dark background, the shapes appear to shimmer with an almost spiritual light. Susan Kornblum conveys a more cryptic message in her untitled drawing, a heavily textured sheet covered in deeply incised text that looks like graffiti on an ancient wall.</p>
        <p>Numerals bear the message in Francis Ing's "Incognito," a series of nine panels made of whitened Polaroid prints. The photographs have been replaced by winning lottery numbers and the dates on which they were drawn, a reference to the fact that, in the artist's view, our lives are dominated by numbers.</p>
        <p>Betty Gimbel turns a witty eye on the details of personal adornment in "3 + 1," a three-panel homage to lipstick and toenail polish. Behind the makeup, the  wearer is just a fashion-conscious cipher. The figures in Kent Jorgensen Czarow's "Cirque de Fous" are also acting out roles, parading across their shallow stage like anonymous heiroglyphs.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
