<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Appearances];The Seaweed Factor</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="66" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="838654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COSMETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEAWEED</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLANKTON</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TANNEN, MARY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DD1439F937A15750C0A960958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Appearances];The Seaweed Factor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary Tannen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TANNEN, MARY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEAWEED IS ALGAE, A HUMBLE PLANT WITH NO TRUE root, stem or leaf. Plankton -- microscopic plant and animal life drifting in the water -- is humbler still. But in these herb-euphoric times, low on the food chain means high on virtue. Devotees graze not only on sea plants like hungry manatees, but also slather the stuff over their bodies. They comb cosmetics counters for thermal plankton creams and kelp cleansing gels. I am both attracted and repelled. The stories about the benefits of these plants are seductive, but seem too precisely tailored to hook into receptor sites of current assumptions, expectations and fears.</p>
        <p>The history of Creme de la Mer, for example, has a mythic quality -- the triumph of good natural science over the evil petrochemical kind. According to legend, a rocket scientist named Max Huber, experimenting with fuels for NASA, suffered chemical burns on his face. No available treatments would help. But after working in his garage for 12 years, Huber developed a cream from fresh Pacific kelp that delivered nutrients into his skin to heal his scars. Since Huber's recent death, Estee Lauder has taken over manufacture of the cream, which fans swear cures blemishes, retards aging and is great for diaper rash, among other things.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEAWEED IS ALGAE, A HUMBLE PLANT WITH NO TRUE root, stem or leaf. Plankton -- microscopic plant and animal life drifting in the water -- is humbler still. But in these herb-euphoric times, low on the food chain means high on virtue. Devotees graze not only on sea plants like hungry manatees, but also slather the stuff over their bodies. They comb cosmetics counters for thermal plankton creams and kelp cleansing gels. I am both attracted and repelled. The stories about the benefits of these plants are seductive, but seem too precisely tailored to hook into receptor sites of current assumptions, expectations and fears.</p>
        <p>The history of Creme de la Mer, for example, has a mythic quality -- the triumph of good natural science over the evil petrochemical kind. According to legend, a rocket scientist named Max Huber, experimenting with fuels for NASA, suffered chemical burns on his face. No available treatments would help. But after working in his garage for 12 years, Huber developed a cream from fresh Pacific kelp that delivered nutrients into his skin to heal his scars. Since Huber's recent death, Estee Lauder has taken over manufacture of the cream, which fans swear cures blemishes, retards aging and is great for diaper rash, among other things.</p>
        <p>Thalassotherapy -- holistic healing with sea baths and salt air -- is a venerable European tradition, championed here by the algae lovers who disparage  the American practice of treating disease without regard to body and soul. Susan Ciminelli offers seaweed wraps at her day spa in Manhattan, as well as a finely  powdered seaweed for bathing at home. She says that when seaweed is in contact with the body for some time, it will "remineralize" the blood and "detoxify" the body, encouraging it to "let go of impurities." I appreciate the metaphor of the sea washing away impurities and restoring primal goodness. But I'm hypersensitive to New Age words like detoxify. And I'm dubious about the ability of minerals to penetrate the skin.</p>
        <p>Dan Fryda, president of Spa Technologies International, which develops products for spas like Canyon Ranch, maintains that the minerals in seaweed can  penetrate the skin and cites studies conducted at the University of Rennes, in France, in which rats immersed in seaweed baths for 20 minutes had the mineral ions traced to their bloodstream, liver and kidneys with radioactive isotopes. Fryda says there are about 3,000 varieties of seaweed and only a handful are being used. "The potential is vast," he says. Properties of seaweed vary with the plant: white algae, for instance, is calcium-rich, while red algae has wound-healing properties.</p>
        <p>In this era of biogenetic tinkering, we feel menaced by mutant microbes invading our cells. Plants, on the other hand, especially those from water, are  a comfort because we believe life originated in the primordial soup. For 40 years, Biotherm France has made skin cream with a microorganism isolated from plankton and concentrated in the laboratory. This enzyme, Biotherm says, has a close resemblance to the structure of the skin and stimulates cell renewal, which, in turn, helps the skin retain a youthful suppleness and tone.</p>
        <p>The idea that a simple, benign sea creature could protect us from the havoc we have wrought in our environment -- principally, the depletion of the ozone layer -- makes the attraction of sun-care products enriched with plankton especially powerful. Cindy Melk -- sleek as a seal with her slicked-back hair -- is the founder and creative director of H2 O+, which has recently reformulated a line of sea-derived skin and bath products and packaged them in frosted tubes and jars that look like beach glass. The company's Marine Enzyme Serum contains  a plankton-derived enzyme that, Melk says, helps reduce and reverse damage from  UV rays. This enzyme, according Daniel Yarosh of Applied Genetics, who developed it, has been shown to use solar energy to speed up repair of UV damage in human-skin cell cultures. (Applied Genetics puts out its own skin repair formulas called Ocean Secret: Daytime, SPF 15, and Nightime, with marine extracts that work in the dark.)</p>
        <p>I'm beginning to think there might be more to marine therapy than a load of colorful yarns. Dr. Joseph Michael Pober, a Manhattan plastic surgeon, refers patients to the Repechage day spa for seaweed applications after surgery or liposuction to restore the skin's texture and color and reduce swelling. I ask him what is in seaweed that works such wonders. He laughs. "If I knew that, I'd  be selling it."</p>
        <p>In the interest of science, I donate my body to Repechage, at Third Avenue and 62d Street. The very beautiful Melinda Angiuli paints me with a warmed-up seaweed paste, then wraps me like a giant sushi in Mylar, towels and a blanket.  She leaves me, smelling strongly but not unpleasantly, to stew in a vegetative state and listen to New Age music. After a shower and massage, my scaly skin now feels like a newborn babe's, and the seaweed facial leaves my complexion bright  and plumped. (Later, over seaweed salad, my husband says I look years younger.)</p>
        <p>Walking home through a cool, misty evening, I experience an oceanic sense of  well-being. I see that my attempt to winnow science from myth has been misguided. Thalassotherapy works best if you swallow the story whole. It's a mind-body thing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
