<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China's Endless Task to Stem Centuries of Floods</title>
    <meta content="15CHIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1DE123AF936A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="1895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China's Endless Task to Stem Centuries of Floods</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>GAOHUANG, China</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two months after parts of central China suffered some of worst flooding in two centuries, millions of Chinese are still digging out--still waiting for local governments to help them rebuild their homes, their farms and their lives; as they wait, a sober reckoning is under way among flood-control engineers: even as they race to build more dams, dikes and reservoirs, risk of catastrophic flood is increasing in many areas as riverbeds and catchment lakes fill up with sediment and shifting Asian weather patterns deliver more frequent and more intense summer monsoons; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the summer of 1996 began, the endless landscape of the Yangtze River valley here was a symphony of labor, where legions of Chinese, buried to the waist in the rich greenery of China's grain belt, were bringing in the summer harvest.</p>
        <p>But today this landscape, for as far as the eye can see, is a dismal palette of inundation: dead and rotting crops wilting above an ocean of mud and a sheen of flood water that lies like a pestilence across the land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the summer of 1996 began, the endless landscape of the Yangtze River valley here was a symphony of labor, where legions of Chinese, buried to the waist in the rich greenery of China's grain belt, were bringing in the summer harvest.</p>
        <p>But today this landscape, for as far as the eye can see, is a dismal palette of inundation: dead and rotting crops wilting above an ocean of mud and a sheen of flood water that lies like a pestilence across the land.</p>
        <p>Two months after parts of central China suffered some of the worst flooding in two centuries, millions of Chinese are still digging out -- still waiting for local governments to help them rebuild their homes, their farms and their lives.</p>
        <p>As they wait, a sober reckoning is under way among flood-control engineers. Even as they race to build more dams, dikes and reservoirs, the risk of catastrophic flood is increasing in many areas as riverbeds and catchment lakes fill up with sediment and shifting Asian weather patterns deliver more frequent and more intense summer monsoons.</p>
        <p>This year in northern China, where the rain was not so intense, the Yellow River crested at the highest level in history, raising new fear that a big flood on the north China plain could breach the main dikes and kill an estimated one million to three million Chinese.</p>
        <p>For those lucky enough to escape this year's flood, a long and bitter recovery lies ahead.</p>
        <p>Wu Kaimin, 68, is one of the survivors and one of the victims. He lost his house, his farm and all his possessions on July 23 at 9:50 A.M., when the main dike holding back the Yangtze gave way here and a 30-foot wall of water wiped clean the slate of his life.</p>
        <p>More than half of this village of two dozen houses disappeared as people scampered up undamaged parts of the dike and watched in horror as the brown flood did its awesome work.</p>
        <p>''First the tree collapsed and smashed the house, and then the house began to wash away,'' Mr. Wu said earlier this month in an interview as he stood with mud-caked feet outside the tent where he now lives with many members of his extended family. Their firewood piles and clotheslines were strewn pitifully along the canted remnant of the dike.</p>
        <p>''This is the property of a lifetime that we lost,'' he said. ''I can't farm. I have no money. I have no house and winter is coming. Please tell the Government. We want some support.''</p>
        <p>A few dozen miles away, Liu Yueyi sat among a pile of bricks that was once her home, scraping mortar off the reusable ones. ''Look at me,'' she said. ''Here I am, over 70 years old, and I no longer have a home.''</p>
        <p>She and her husband had been fish farmers at Longkou, where town officials opened a dike on Aug. 18 to relieve the pressure of the surging Yangtze River. ''All of our income came from the fish farm,'' she said, ''but all the fish swam away in the flood. Now we are living one day to the next.''</p>
        <p>It has been this way throughout China's history. First comes the deluge, then the long, grinding recovery, which far outlives the world's passing notice of China's relentless -- and increasingly frequent -- natural disasters.</p>
        <p>A huge population only magnifies the devastation, as millions of Chinese are forced to live and farm in the shadow of high earthen dikes holding back the country's major rivers. The strength and integrity of the dikes can only be tested when the torrent arrives. And where disaster strikes, for years afterward it saps the energy of the Chinese countryside and, over the centuries, has prevented Chinese in flood-prone regions from climbing out of poverty.</p>
        <p>Under Communist rule since 1949, the Government has put about $27 billion, or 4 percent of all public spending, into water-control projects, including the construction of 120,000 miles of dikes. But that has still not been enough.</p>
        <p>Even the vaunted Three Gorges Dam, which is to be the world's largest flood-control and hydroelectric project, will only help when the summer monsoons drench the Yangtze River basin upstream from the dam site at Yichang in central China. That leaves more than 100 million people in the flood-prone regions of Hunan, Hubei, Anhui and Jiangsu provinces vulnerable to the kind of drenching that struck this summer.</p>
        <p>More than 2,700 Chinese have died this year in floods, and more than 4.4 million were left homeless by flood waters that also left at least eight million acres of cropland unproductive for the balance of the year, according to United Nations estimates. In 1995, more than 2,000 died in floods; in 1994 more than 5,000, and in 1991, 5,000 lost their lives in the largest flood of the decade. That disaster left eight million homeless and damaged 35 million acres of cropland. With the decade scarcely half over, the death toll is more than 20,000, and the number of houses washed away or damaged exceeds five million.</p>
        <p>By comparison, the flood that struck the American Midwest in 1993 killed 50 people and left 70,000 homeless.</p>
        <p>The most devastating floods in this century have all taken place in China. In 1931, the Yangtze and Huai Rivers roared out of their banks and killed an estimated 225,000 people. Two years later, a Yellow River flood killed 18,300. In 1954, the Yangtze surged again and killed 34,000 in a disaster that inspired Mao Zedong to promote huge waterworks that could control the nation's floods.</p>
        <p>The most lethal flood of the century, however, was man-made. In 1938, China's Nationalist leader, Chiang Kai-shek, blew up the Yellow River dike at Huayuankou to stop the invading Japanese Army. The flood killed an estimated 890,000 Chinese, but gained only three months.</p>
        <p>But over geological time, nature has conspired powerfully against what would become China. The collision of tectonic plates in Asia has heaved the Tibetan-Qinghai Plateau to such heights over the last 40 million years that it has created a topographic flood machine where giant rivers crash down from altitudes of 20,000 feet to heavily populated alluvial plains.</p>
        <p>And now, changing weather patterns in the Pacific Ocean, perhaps caused by global warming, have added to China's woes. Studies at the National Meteorological Center blame the more frequent appearance of the mysterious El Nino current in the Pacific on more intense monsoons that wash central and southern China, including the Yangtze River drainage area, where 350 million people live.</p>
        <p>''Forest cutting in the upper reaches of the Yangtze River is also a factor in the increasing frequency of flooding,'' says Arthur N. Holcombe, the United Nations Development Fund director in Beijing. ''There is far more runoff today, and the absorptive capacity of the land is less. This has implications for repeated flooding in the future.''</p>
        <p>While the Yangtze region was the scene of this summer's worst floods, the condition of the Yellow River diking system in northern China has entered a period of even greater danger, as the summer rains pushed the river to its highest recorded level.</p>
        <p>The Yellow River's crest of 94.73 meters -- more than 310 feet -- at Huayuankou in Henan province occurred even though the volume of water was only a third the volume of a much greater Yellow River flood in 1958.</p>
        <p>This means that the Yellow River is now so choked with mud that its bed has risen to a dangerous new height above the plain. In effect, the river flows ''suspended'' between high dike walls at an elevation as much as 30 feet higher than the plain. Any major flood in northern China now holds the potential to breach the main dikes that contain the river, with disastrous consequences. Once the river breaks through the dikes, the water cannot flow back into the suspended channel and must find a new path to the sea.</p>
        <p>Although China has made prodigious efforts to contain the torrent of its major rivers, the task of lifting its flood victims out of their misery often proves overwhelming and, in the end, millions of Chinese are left destitute, relying on the charity of relatives or friends to survive.</p>
        <p>For Westerners, often moved by the plight of China's flood-stricken poor, there is no certainty that donated aid reaches those who need it most. Under Communist rule, the Ministry of Civil Affairs in Beijing has year after year mobilized immediate flood-relief efforts to rescue and evacuate flood victims, and to provide temporary shelter and modest portions of food. But extended flood recovery remains the responsibility of local governments.</p>
        <p>Statistics issued by the United Nations Department of Humanitarian Affairs tell the story. Although more than four million Chinese were left homeless by the flood, the Chinese Government reported distributing only 3,000 tents for temporary shelter.</p>
        <p>In many flood zones, local governments tend to channel funds toward rebuilding state-owned and township enterprises that provide the tax and employment base of the affected region.</p>
        <p>The peasants are often told to rely on themselves, to resurrect a livelihood from their ruined fields without any assistance in replacing all that has been washed away. In Longkou, Liu Xiangdao and his family saved only those belongings that could be carried to the second floor of the house before the dike was opened on Aug. 18.</p>
        <p>''We have no work unit,'' said Mr. Liu, referring to state-run urban workplaces through which housing and other social-welfare benefits are distributed. ''So no one has taken care of us. People who worked for the brick factory or the fish farm got a little rice, but we got nothing.''</p>
        <p>A Longkou official said the province authorities had promised $36,000 for rebuilding the hardest-hit section of the city, but added that only two-thirds of the money had arrived and that it was being used to rebuild a brick factory.</p>
        <p>Here in Gaohuang, it is the same. In this village, no help has arrived beyond the half-dozen tents distributed in the days after the dike broke. Local governments also distributed a small bag of rice for each family member and, in some cases, the equivalent of $10 to $15 for clothes or vegetables.</p>
        <p>In the month that has followed, though, nothing more has come.</p>
        <p>''We hear that the government has received some donations, but nothing has reached our hands,'' said Mr. Wu. ''The government says it is going to use the supplies for the next flood, so the donated material is frozen.''</p>
        <p>Shaking his head, he said, ''It should reach the victims.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
