<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heat of Lotus Attracts Insects And Scientists</title>
    <meta content="01LOTU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lotus (Flower)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4D7113CF932A35753C1A960958260" item-length="1222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heat of Lotus Attracts Insects And Scientists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers report that lotus flower, long revered by both Buddhists and Hindus, has remarkable ability to regulate temperature of its flowers to within narrow range just as humans and other warmblooded animals do; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE sacred lotus, which gracefully raises its elegant flower above the murky waters where  it grows, has long been revered by both Buddhists and Hindus. Now a study has recruited biologists as well as the flower's devotees. Researchers report that the lotus has the remarkable ability to  regulate the temperature of its flowers to within a narrow range just as humans and other warmblooded animals do.</p>
        <p>Dr. Roger S. Seymour and Dr. Paul Schultze-Motel, physiologists at the University of Adelaide in Australia, found that lotus flowers blooming in the Adelaide Botanic Gardens maintained a temperature of 86 to 95 degrees Fahrenheit, even when the air temperature dropped to 50 degrees. They suspect the flowers may be turning up the heat for the benefit of their coldblooded insect pollinators.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE sacred lotus, which gracefully raises its elegant flower above the murky waters where  it grows, has long been revered by both Buddhists and Hindus. Now a study has recruited biologists as well as the flower's devotees. Researchers report that the lotus has the remarkable ability to  regulate the temperature of its flowers to within a narrow range just as humans and other warmblooded animals do.</p>
        <p>Dr. Roger S. Seymour and Dr. Paul Schultze-Motel, physiologists at the University of Adelaide in Australia, found that lotus flowers blooming in the Adelaide Botanic Gardens maintained a temperature of 86 to 95 degrees Fahrenheit, even when the air temperature dropped to 50 degrees. They suspect the flowers may be turning up the heat for the benefit of their coldblooded insect pollinators.</p>
        <p>''We had no idea that they'd be doing this,'' said Dr. Schultze-Motel.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ken Nagy, a physiological ecologist at University of California at Los Angeles, said: ''To suddenly bump into a flower that's hot -- that's astounding. Warmblooded animals have a very sophisticated nervous system for sensing temperature and controlling heating and cooling. Now here's a plant that's doing exactly the same thing.''</p>
        <p>The study, published in the current issue of the journal Nature, is the latest discovery in the esoteric field of heat-producing plants. Only two other species have so far been found to be able to regulate their temperature, both in the arum-lily family: the skunk cabbage and a Philodendron known as elephant ear.</p>
        <p>The addition of a lotus, or Nelumbo nucifera as the sacred lotus is known to botanists, has come as a surprise. Since the lotus lily family is only distantly related to the arum lilies, there may turn out to be other examples of temperature regulation in plants once biologists start looking.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jane-Marie Law, a historian of religions at Cornell University, notes that the opened lotus blossom, on which the Buddha is often depicted seated, is the symbol of enlightenment. The sacred lotus's natural range is in Asia and it was probably taken to Australia by humans.</p>
        <p>For their study in the Adelaide Botanic Gardens, the researchers wired up the lotuses so as to record their temperature and monitor their metabolism. They also rigged up umbrellas to shield the blossoms from  sunlight, whose heat might confound the experiment. Dr. Schultze-Motel said the setup was so striking that  passersby asked whether it was an art project.</p>
        <p>The sacred lotus begins heating as its flowers start to bloom. As the night air cools the petals, the flower takes in more oxygen and gives off more carbon dioxide, converting more carbohydrates to energy just as would a shivering animal to try to stay warm. Heat production tapers off after dawn as the sun takes over, maintaining the same toasty heat around the clock.</p>
        <p>Warmblooded animals have an elaborate nervous and hormonal system to regulate their temperatures.  How the lotus manages the same trick without this apparatus is unknown.</p>
        <p>Researchers were also impressed by the lotus's sheer output of energy. A heating lotus flower can crank away at one watt, with 40 lotus blossoms churning out the same amount of heat as a living room light bulb. Seventy such flowers produce the heat of a human being at rest reading a newspaper.</p>
        <p>''This is a lot of energy,'' said Dr. Todd Dawson, plant physiological ecologist at Cornell University.  ''This is going to be expensive for a plant to do. It's burning up carbohydrate. So there's a cost involved here, and then the question is, what's the benefit?''</p>
        <p>Researchers have begun to answer that question for a few of the thermogenic plants. When skunk cabbage blooms in early spring, its  heat can melt away ice and snow around it, apparently protecting the flower from damaging cold. When the voodoo lily, another flower that can produce heat but does not regulate its temperature, heats up, its intensely putrid perfumes are more quickly turned to vapor and dispersed, helping to draw in pollinators. The effect is similar to that of putting a droplet of perfume on the warm human skin.</p>
        <p>But why should a lotus flower keep on at a steady 85 to 96 degrees?</p>
        <p>The authors of the new paper suggest that lotus flowers may be luring in heat-hungry pollinators, most likely beetles, with an attractively warm environment, providing an energetic reward for those that come to visit.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bernd Heinrich, a physiological ecologist at the University of Vermont in Burlington, said such an environment might also be important for keeping beetles active in a flower during a cold night. An active beetle could rummage about and be fully coated in pollen by morning. In fact, a previous study found that beetles that lingered in lotus flowers and were trapped when the petals on these bowl-shaped blooms closed up for the night were indeed very active, spending the night mating and feeding.</p>
        <p>Dr. Schultze-Motel suggests that the next morning these well-dusted beetles could quickly complete their job as pollinators. Rather than having to wait for the sun to warm them, the beetles, warmed by the flower, could take off to deposit pollen on the next lotus flower.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Heinrich notes that warming may serve other purposes, including speeding flower development, and that there may be more than one explanation for the heat production.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hanna Skubatz, a plant biochemist at the University of Washington in Seattle, said many plant species, like the voodoo lily, were being found to produce heat even though they did not appear to regulate their temperature, including species of cycad, water lily and palm. In each case it is the flower or flower-like structures that warm up. The heating usually lasts only until the last grain of pollen has been released. When the flower's job of producing pollen is done, the blossom begins to cool.</p>
        <p>Dr. Skubatz said heat-production might, in fact, be widespread, just difficult to detect. The voodoo lily uses the energy-producing organelles in its cells, known as mitochondria, to produce heat. And it does so through a chemical pathway that most plants have the ability to use.</p>
        <p>The big difference, she said, is that heat-producing plants have many more mitochondria than other  plants. Less than an ounce of the heat-producing tissue of a voodoo lily yields the same number of mitochondria as more than two pounds of corn seedlings. So it could be that heat production is widespread in the plant kingdom, but that in most plants it is  so minuscule as to be undetectable.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
