<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Connecticut Q&amp;A: Aris Crist;Can Buildings Harmonize With Nature?</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARCHITECTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENVIRONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CRIST, ARIS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREENWICH (CONN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKOWITZ, BOBBI P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6D71E39F931A35755C0A960958260" item-length="1419" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Connecticut Q&amp;A: Aris Crist;Can Buildings Harmonize With Nature?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOBBI P. MARKOWITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKOWITZ, BOBBI P</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GOOD architecture has always been based on providing good environments, both  inside and outside. These days, the terms "green" and "sustainable" architecture are interchangeable for a quiet revolution worldwide that is defined as improving the quality of living and working environments without diminishing the earth for future generations.</p>
        <p>Aris Crist, an architect in Greenwich who earned a bachelor's degree with a concentration in environmental science from the University of Vermont and a master's in architecture from Syracuse University, is a proponent of the green way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GOOD architecture has always been based on providing good environments, both  inside and outside. These days, the terms "green" and "sustainable" architecture are interchangeable for a quiet revolution worldwide that is defined as improving the quality of living and working environments without diminishing the earth for future generations.</p>
        <p>Aris Crist, an architect in Greenwich who earned a bachelor's degree with a concentration in environmental science from the University of Vermont and a master's in architecture from Syracuse University, is a proponent of the green way.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mr. Crist elaborated on the reasons for its growth. Following are some excerpts from that discussion.</p>
        <p>Q. What are the elements of green or sustainable architecture?</p>
        <p>A. Essentially, green architecture is based on a heightened awareness of conserving natural resources. It employs strategies for energy-efficient designs, improving energy performance. It deals with indoor air quality issues,  the use of sustainable wood products, the thoughtful selection of materials and  recycled products as well as the conscientious recycling of construction waste.</p>
        <p>Q. How old is the movement?</p>
        <p>A. While good architects have been incorporating and building with regard toward nature for thousands of years, there's been a growing effort since the 70's when a new awareness about pollution became acknowledged. The movement in the past has been about identifying the problems, but the next step is to spread the word, to gather and disseminate information.</p>
        <p>Q. How have we created the problem?</p>
        <p>A. We have been frivolous and wasteful with our natural resources.  We act as if we have all the trees in the world to cut down and fossil fuels to burn. We forget that the byproduct of our rapid, unplanned and overdeveloped high-technology building industry is a tremendous amount of pollution.</p>
        <p>Toxic materials, from P.C.B.'s to lead to asbestos, are polluting our earth,  potentially making us sick.  We've forgotten about the oil crisis that just took place a short 20 years ago. We lack long-term vision.</p>
        <p>We can learn from the Europeans.  Energy has always been a precious and expensive commodity in Europe so they've been conserving more for a longer time. If we don't educate ourselves, what will we be leaving for the next generation?</p>
        <p>Q. What can we do to reverse the "use it up" mentality?</p>
        <p>A. We need to create a proper balance between a building and its byproducts.  Then we can enter a sustainable equilibrium.</p>
        <p>Conserving energy is among the primary elements to consider. We use building  procedures and techniques that are concerned with keeping the house properly insulated and ventilated so that the energy used inside stays there.</p>
        <p>Solar energy, for example, can be gathered in an active way to collect heat and produce electricity. Passively, we can try to place a house in an orientation to face and gather sunlight in the winter and use shading techniques in the summer to keep the heat out. We place windows to achieve maximum warmth and cooling ventilation.</p>
        <p>Natural lighting is another source of energy savings. If you use insulated glass to brighten dim rooms, you'll cut down on electrical use. Most new buildings can use daylight to meet up to 50 percent of their lighting needs. For nighttime use, there are new low-voltage disconnect sensors which sense when people leave a room and automatically turn off lights -- another energy saver.</p>
        <p>Q. Can you give some examples of resource conservation and material recycling and selection?</p>
        <p>A. We need to select materials that have lower energy usage to produce. By buying local products, we cut down on transportation costs and through the utilization of recycling material, people can conserve half of our natural resources right off the bat. When renovating, we like to use as much of the existing structure as possible. We can use gypsum wallboard that is made of recycled paper. We can use engineered wood products that are made up of smaller  pieces of recycled wood to create beams and joists. This way we use 80 percent of the tree rather than select solid timbers.</p>
        <p>Q. How does the issue of indoor air quality correlate with the term "sick-building syndrome"?</p>
        <p>A. We've been putting a lot of toxic materials in the buildings where we work and live. We've created a lot of health problems -- headaches, dizziness, nausea, loss of appetite and fatigue.</p>
        <p>When furnishing the inside of our spaces, we should select natural products instead of ones that are laden with toxic glues, formaldehyde and adhesives. Tacking carpet down rather than gluing is less harmful. We can use paints that are much less detrimental to the ozone layer. There are new ventilation systems  that recycle the heat or cooling energy at the same time fresh air is mixed in.</p>
        <p>Q. How can you incorporate sustainable design into your practice?</p>
        <p>A. I recently completed the design for a shore-front estate, an opportunity to build in harmony with nature. We tried to minimize disturbing the land. We considered environmental issues with respect to the sun, wind and natural features which positively affected the performance of the building. To take advantage of the spectacular view and site, a lot of glass was needed. I selected Super Glass which was the highest rated insulated glass at the time. Because of the dramatic high ceilings, an in-floor heating system was used to provide warmth and comfort in the space that people occupy.</p>
        <p>While it is not always possible to position a house on a site that will enhance the ability to conserve energy, there are many creative things that can  be done on any site. We use tile and solid masonry products to capture and store the heat for later use. Wherever possible, I suggest over-insulating, as a very  easy way to reduce energy usage and cost.</p>
        <p>Q. What are some examples of using green in the public domain?</p>
        <p>A. The Audubon headquarters in New York City, an environmental renovation versus the construction of a new building. In Washington, D.C., "The Greening of the White House" brought together a group of architects to do a design study that recommended how the White House could be brought up to current standards of energy conservation and incorporated the use of recycled materials.</p>
        <p>Q. How is the movement developing?</p>
        <p>A. Presently, there is a systematic approach to bring a diverse group of people together -- not only architects but policy makers, universities, professionals, manufacturers and end users -- to form a collaboration that could start to address our problems.  There are environmental symposiums, which further the movement by trying to reduce the negative impact we have made on the planet.  Lastly and most importantly we need to educate our children.</p>
        <p>Q. Is sustainable architecture a costly proposition?</p>
        <p>A. Our objectives are first and foremost to create healthy working and living environments in our homes and offices. While constructing energy-efficient buildings may be somewhat costlier now, we need to show that incorporating sustainability can be done economically, with long-term benefits. By educating people, we can create more demand for the products so that the prices become more competitive. A great part of our objective is to develop a whole new industry, both service and in manufacturing, which will create new jobs, new businesses and new products, which will afford us new possibilities.</p>
        <p>Q. How can sustainable design influence our future?</p>
        <p>A. We want people to continue to prosper but at the same time we want to reduce the negative impact.  The more pollution we make, more money and energy will be wasted on fighting pollution. The more trees we cut down, the less forests we'll have left. The more erosion we create, the less land will be left. There are many solutions to sustainable design issues, we just have to embrace them.  We want the future generations to regain a harmonious and balanced relationship with the earth.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
