<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ice Shelves Melting as Forecast, but Disaster Script Is in Doubt</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="826410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GREENHOUSE EFFECT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OCEANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING(COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MODELS (SIMULATIONS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANTARCTIC REGIONS</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH ANTARCTIC SURVEY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D81639F933A05752C0A960958260" item-length="1397" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ice Shelves Melting as Forecast, but Disaster Script Is in Doubt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SCIENTISTS have long feared that global warming might eventually cause the vast West Antarctic Ice Sheet to melt, raising the worldwide sea level by a catastrophic 20 feet or so. The first warning sign, the experts said, would be the retreat of ice shelves that extend off the Antarctic coast into the ocean.</p>
        <p>That sign has appeared, but the experts are no longer sure what it portends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SCIENTISTS have long feared that global warming might eventually cause the vast West Antarctic Ice Sheet to melt, raising the worldwide sea level by a catastrophic 20 feet or so. The first warning sign, the experts said, would be the retreat of ice shelves that extend off the Antarctic coast into the ocean.</p>
        <p>That sign has appeared, but the experts are no longer sure what it portends.</p>
        <p>Glaciologists with the British Antarctic Survey, a government organization based in Cambridge, England, report in the current issue of the journal Nature that atmospheric warming has caused five floating ice shelves attached to the Antarctic Peninsula to shrink dramatically over the last 50 years. The most recent example of the ice retreat came early last year, when a 500-square-mile chunk of the Larsen Ice Shelf disintegrated in 50 days, launching a 125-mile-long parade of icebergs into the Weddell Sea.</p>
        <p>This ice has no effect on sea level because it has already been floating on the ocean; melting makes no difference. But the British scientists say that if the warming continues, as scientists advising the United Nations have predicted, the frontier of melting will move farther south. In time this could expose inland ice sheets to shrinkage that would add to the ocean's volume. A large enough warming could even melt the Filcher-Ronne and Ross ice shelves closer to  the South Pole, each as big as Spain. Scientists have thought that if these "dams" were removed, they would allow West Antarctica's glaciers to flow more easily into the sea, where they would melt and raise the water level catastrophically.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, according to the new study, the retreat of the ice shelves appears to have accelerated in the final stages of disintegration, leading to an unexpectedly rapid collapse. To some scientists, this raises the possibility  that inland ice sheets might behave likewise, causing sea level to rise more rapidly than scientists have anticipated.</p>
        <p>The United Nations panel of scientists recently predicted that if emissions of heat-trapping waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide are not reduced, the average global temperature will rise by a "best estimate" of 3.6 degrees Fahrenheit by 2100. The resultant melting of glaciers and thermal expansion of the ocean, the panel said, would cause the average global sea level to rise by a best estimate of 20 inches. The group said further warming and sea-level rise would take place after 2100.  It also concluded for the first time that emissions of the heat-trapping gases, produced by the burning of coal, petroleum and wood, are probably responsible for at least part of a one-degree global warming observed over the last century.</p>
        <p>While the new evidence of ice-shelf disintegration is provocative, scientists are uncertain whether it presages the destruction of the West Antarctic sheet. The quest to make sense of Antarctica's important but ill-understood climatic role has proved uncommonly frustrating.  "It's a bundle of laughs, I'll tell you," said David G. Vaughan, a glaciologist, who with his colleague Dr. C. S. M. Doake conducted the new study in Nature. "All the time, there are things that confound you."</p>
        <p>For one thing, climatologists say that one effect of global warming is likely to be heavier precipitation. In Antarctica, this means a heavier accumulation of snow that does not melt, but rather compresses under its own weight into more ice. So a thickening of the ice may be the initial response of some ice sheets and shelves, say Mr. Vaughan and Dr. Doake.</p>
        <p>For another thing, Antarctica is not warming uniformly. On the Antarctic Peninsula where the five ice shelves have retreated, the British researchers report, the climate has warmed by about 4.5 degrees Fahrenheit in the last 50 years. But for Antarctica as a whole, the warming has been only about 1.5 degrees. This is still about twice the warming measured for the earth as a whole.</p>
        <p>The computer models on which climatologists mostly depend for their predictions give different answers when asked how much Antarctica would warm in  the future. Some but not all say the warming there will be the most rapid on the globe.  Observations of Antarctic temperatures over the next few years may well  be one of the best tests of the models' accuracy, said Dr. James E. Hansen, a climatologist who directs the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York. But even that poses special difficulties, he said, since temperature measurements in Antarctica are the sparsest in the world, and natural temperature variability is largest.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert Balling, a climatologist at Arizona State University who describes himself as a "healthy skeptic" on the question of global warming, puts it this way: "Antarctica seems to be on its own planet. The temperature records down there don't seem to jibe with anything."</p>
        <p>Even if global warming causes the Filcher-Ronne and Ross ice shelves to break up eventually, glaciologists are not as confident as they once were that this would lead to a collapse of the West Antarctic ice sheet.  That possibility was  raised in the 1970's by John Mercer, an American geologist who predicted that a  disintegration of smaller ice sheets, as has just been reported, would be an early warning sign.</p>
        <p>The Filcher-Ronne and Ross shelves have been thought critical to the stability of the West Antarctic sheet, which rests on an archipelago and lies mostly below sea level. Take away the shelves, scientists have believed, and the broad ice streams that make up much of the West Antarctic sheet would flow more  easily into the ocean, there to melt and raise the global sea level.</p>
        <p>Now, said Mr. Vaughan, an accumulation of evidence, mainly from computer modeling of ice sheet behavior, has raised serious questions about whether the big ice streams would in fact flow faster if the Filcher-Ronne and Ross sheets were to melt. That calls Mr. Mercer's prediction of nearly two decades ago into  sharper question. "Half of it has happened," said Mr. Vaughan, "but we're no longer sure the rest of it is going to come true."</p>
        <p>The hypothesis may not really be tested unless the warming becomes truly catastrophic some time in the dimly perceived future. A further rise in the average global temperature of 18 degrees Fahrenheit would be necessary for the Filcher-Ronne and Ross shelves to melt, said Mr. Vaughan, and no one knows if or when that might happen.</p>
        <p>If temperatures did rise that high, they would create a climate as warm as that of the Cretaceous period, 65 million to 135 million years ago.  Then, polar ice totally melted. But if the temperature rises by 18 degrees, said Mr. Vaughan, "we're not going to be worried about ice sheets; we're going to be worried about growing food."</p>
        <p>On a more foreseeable time scale, Dr. Hansen says, the Vaughan-Doake paper raises the question of whether land-based ice sheets might begin to break up with only a little warming, raising sea level more rapidly over the next century than the United Nations panel of scientists predicts.  Mr. Vaughan and Dr. Doake say it is uncertain what mechanisms cause the floating ice shelves to break up rapidly once a certain point is reached. But they say it might happen when melted water on the ice surface, created by warming, percolates deep into the ice shelf, weakening it to the point of disintegration.</p>
        <p>If that is true, says Dr. Hansen, it might cause land-based glaciers around the world to disintegrate faster than expected. "I think he's right to raise that as an issue," said Mr. Vaughan. "It's something worth thinking about."</p>
        <p>Mr. Vaughan and Dr. Doake offer no prediction about whether global warming will continue. But at the very least, they wrote in Nature, the extent of Antarctic ice shelves "may well be a sensitive indicator of regional climate change."</p>
        <p>In terms of the broader search for answers about Antarctica and climate, Dr.  Balling called their study "another piece of evidence in a very complex and fascinating puzzle."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
