<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Better or Worse, The Car Turns 100</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="856424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCEWEN, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURYEA, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DURYEA, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D91639F93AA35755C0A960958260" item-length="986" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Better or Worse, The Car Turns 100</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES McEWEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCEWEN, CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1896, two brothers, Charles and Frank Duryea, built 13 two-passenger, two-cylinder runabouts in Springfield, Mass. From this humble beginning, the American automotive industry was born.</p>
        <p>"It was the first time that an automobile company was organized and produced  more than one car from a single design," said Prof. Richard P. Scharchburg, the  author of "Carriages Without Horses" (Society of Automotive Engineers, 1993).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1896, two brothers, Charles and Frank Duryea, built 13 two-passenger, two-cylinder runabouts in Springfield, Mass. From this humble beginning, the American automotive industry was born.</p>
        <p>"It was the first time that an automobile company was organized and produced  more than one car from a single design," said Prof. Richard P. Scharchburg, the  author of "Carriages Without Horses" (Society of Automotive Engineers, 1993).</p>
        <p>The Duryeas were just two of the scores of inventors and backyard tinkerers  who were working on primitive horseless carriages powered by gasoline, steam and batteries. In Germany, Karl Benz patented his single-cylinder Motorwagen in 1886, and he is generally credited with the earliest automobile powered by an internal-combustion engine. In the United States, the Duryeas produced their first runabout in 1893; Henry Ford completed his first horseless carriage, the Quadricycle, in 1896.</p>
        <p>But it is the Duryea brothers' effort at serial production that is being celebrated this year by the American Automobile Centennial Commission, sponsored by the Chrysler Corporation, the Ford Motor Company, the General Motors Corporation and the United Automobile Workers union. Although Detroit is the focus of several centennial events, others are national, chief among them "America on Wheels," a three-part PBS documentary that is to begin tomorrow night.</p>
        <p>The series, financed by the Corporation for Public Broadcasting through a grant from the commission, is a clear-eyed look at the car, warts and all. "We're trying to tell a comprehensive history of America as seen through the lens of the automobile," said William R. Grant, the executive producer.</p>
        <p>Certainly, few inventions have had as sweeping an influence as the automobile. "Quite simply, it changed the way we live," said Beverly Rae Kimes,  a former president of the Society of Automotive Historians. "There has been no other invention of modern times that so dramatically altered the social aspect of this country. Everything came in its wake. And for Americans, who have always had a hankering for freedom, it gave it to them in spades."</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview, Robert A. Lutz, president of Chrysler, talked about some of the changes wrought by the automobile. "It has permitted the move to the suburbs and the decentralization of the city," he said. "It has created a great  deal of job mobility. People don't feel locked in to whatever employer they happen to be with."</p>
        <p>There's a downside, too, of course. As highways became more congested, accidents increased and pollution worsened. Ralph Nader, one of the auto industry's harshest critics for three decades, remains unbowed. "What we're not  seeing is a golden age of auto safety," he said. "The White House is taking orders from Detroit."</p>
        <p>Part of the problem is that the car has become almost too popular, often to the detriment of public transportation. In Part 2 of "America on Wheels," Virginia Scharff, an associate professor of history at the University of New Mexico, says: "Now that the automobile is fouling the air, now that we're all struck in traffic jams all the time, now that we realize fossil fuels are running out, we want to be able to blame it on somebody else. I personally would rather blame some greedy corporate capitalist than my own propensity for getting in a car and driving wherever I want to go."</p>
        <p>Overcoming that propensity is one of the great challenges facing public transportation. Mr. Lutz envisions combined methods of transit within 50 years.  "Who knows?" he said. "We may have a situation in which motor vehicles come in standard sizes so that for long-distance driving they can be agglomerated onto high-speed rail cars."</p>
        <p>Michael Lamm, an author and book publisher who is completing, with Dave Holls, "A Century of Automotive Style," sees a similar future for automobiles. "If we look 100 years ahead -- and that's very dangerous -- but they will not be anything like we know them today," he said. "The car will not be a personal conveyance. It will be much more like public transportation. And taking away the personal aspects of transportation, you will gain things like speed, comfort and safety."</p>
        <p>Happy motoring -- in whatever form it may take.</p>
        <p>Blowing Out the Candles</p>
        <p>Here are some highlights of the centennial celebration of the American automobile:</p>
        <p>PBS is presenting a three-part documentary, "America on Wheels," produced by Thirteen/WNET. In the New York City area, it will be telecast on three consecutive Monday nights -- June 10, 17 and 24 -- at 9 P.M. on Channel 13.</p>
        <p>The American Automobile Centennial Week is June 16-23. The celebration is national, but many of the events will take place in Detroit, including the Great American Cruise-In on June 22 at the Michigan State Fairgrounds. The sponsors are hoping that this will be largest ever gathering of antique and classic cars.</p>
        <p>In addition, a black-tie Centennial Gala Dinner on June 22, at Cobo Center in Detroit, will honor the people who built the auto industry.</p>
        <p>And the National Auto 100 Parade, beginning at 1 P.M. on June 23, will feature antique, classic, special-interest and concept cars wending their way through Macomb, Oakland and Wayne counties in Michigan, ending at the state fairgrounds. After that, at about 3 P.M., the official national birthday party for the automobile will begin and the parade cars will be displayed.</p>
        <p>Many car shows this year are official centennial events, including the Antique Automobile Club of America's June 17-22 meet in Dearborn, Mich. Closer to New York, the Concours d'Elegance of the eastern United states is set for June 30 at Lehigh University in Bethlehem, Pa.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
