<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Death in the Forest</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="837088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOWRY, BEVERLY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EKMAN, KERSTIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BLACKWATER (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960317T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E0D91639F934A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1588" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Death in the Forest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Beverly Lowry</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOWRY, BEVERLY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BLACKWATER By Kerstin Ekman. Translated by Joan Tate. 434 pp. New York: Doubleday. $23.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BLACKWATER By Kerstin Ekman. Translated by Joan Tate. 434 pp. New York: Doubleday. $23.95.</p>
        <p>The unknown dead make a lasting impression, in literature as well as in life. Recently, there was a picture on the front page of a great many newspapers of a  dead man lying in a street in Sarajevo. The focus of the photograph, however, was not the body but the people who stood in a kind of formal, almost dancerly half-circle around it, looking down. They seemed dispassionate, not so much gaping as mesmerized, trapped inside a bubble of their own curiosity and dread.</p>
        <p>For readers of crime novels, the unidentified corpse has a similar effect. Once the victim has been described, we become stunned, horrified gawkers until the end of the book, when the dead are identified and the murderer discovered. Who can forget the three faceless people lying murdered and frozen in Gorky Park? Or Roseanna, of Maj Sjowall and Per Wahloo's novel of the same name, found strangled and naked in a lake with no clue to her identity except her first name?</p>
        <p>In "Blackwater," by the Swedish writer Kerstin Ekman, there are two unknown dead people, a young man and woman who have been found slashed to death while on a Midsummer's Eve camping trip in a remote and marshy area in the north of Sweden. The identity of the young woman is established quickly enough, but nobody can figure out why she was killed or who did it or who her murdered companion was. The mystery lasts for almost 18 years, during which time the event makes the nearby dying village of Blackwater famous. "Yes," one of Ms. Ekman's narrators tells us, "it was here. Or, rather, four kilometers up from the village, by the water called the river Lobber."</p>
        <p>The unsolved murders so unhinge the community of Blackwater that its residents can't bring themselves to refer to the event except indirectly. They don't speak the word "murder"; they talk about the thing that happened "down by  the Lobber." The murderer, they assume, must have been a maniac on the loose, or one of the longhairs from Starhill, a nearby commune. When questioned by the police, people often lie, clam up or skirt the truth, and for no good reason. "We didn't want to expose our confusion," one character tells herself, "not even to each other."</p>
        <p>"Blackwater" is being marketed as a thriller, and that it is -- but of the longer, denser and more erotic variety, the kind that comes along once every few years and usually attracts a big audience. "Smilla's Sense of Snow" was one, also "Gorky Park" and "The Little Drummer Girl." Time, place and politics play significant roles in these books. And while crime -- usually murder -- certainly serves to move the plot, murder is only a start. The dark deed resonates outward, serving to illuminate whatever larger perceptions, issues and possibilities engage the author's interests and imagination -- in this case, the effect of two grisly murders on a small, remote community.</p>
        <p>The story starts off creepily enough. It is 4 o'clock in the morning. A woman is awakened by the sound of a car driving up in front of her home. The engine shuts off, two people get out, the woman reaches for her shotgun. At the window, Annie Raft looks out and discovers her daughter, 23-year-old Mia, outside, locked in passionate embrace with a man Annie recognizes. "The same face. Firmer and coarser after 18 years, but it was him." Annie makes a phone call to her friend and lover, Birger Torbjornsson. "I've seen him," she whispers. "The one I saw that night." Birger does not ask who she means or which night, even after all these years. The boy Annie Raft saw on that night 18 years before is now a man of 34; his name, Mia tells her mother the next morning, is Johan Brandberg.</p>
        <p>Through the voices of Annie Raft, Birger Torbjornsson and Johan Brandberg, Kerstin Ekman then takes us back to the time of the murders, to 1974, when Annie and her daughter, then 6 years old, came to Blackwater to move into the Starhill commune with Annie's new lover, Dan Ulander. Through the bus window, Annie and Mia survey the landscape. They are traveling "upward along a system of lakes extending right up to the high mountains in Norway, where it ran out of marshlands and mountain streams. In the felled clearings the great network of water had been cut off and the ground had dried to dead flesh in the body of the landscape." Beyond the bus route are areas of even more extensive clear-cutting, where acid rain runs straight down into the earth to do its work  unhampered.</p>
        <p>Throughout the novel, Ms. Ekman's descriptions of the countryside are lush and lovingly rendered. Landscape -- what we've come to call the environment -- becomes a character here, as fully developed and as important to the plot as human beings. Not that "Blackwater" is a message book and, luckily, Ms. Ekman doesn't fall for "I Am the Walrus" clichs. Still, this may be one of the first environment-driven thrillers we've seen. Clear-cutting is a vital issue in the novel, and so is uranium mining. Even the international underground trade in peregrine falcons plays a major role in the unraveling of the two murders.</p>
        <p>"Blackwater" has a low steady pulse and an eerily quiet tone. The effect is to make us feel, really, more worried than afraid. Ms. Ekman sees no need to fill up the story with narrow escapes and more corpses; instead, patient as a jigsaw puzzler, she takes her time, threading her way through a plot as complicated as the lives of the people who live in and about the town itself.</p>
        <p>Dan Ulander leaves Annie and little Mia stranded at the Blackwater bus stop,  forcing Annie to try to make her own way to the commune, in the process of which she takes a path that leads to the dead bodies beside the Lobber. The reason Dan fails to meet her is that he is spending the weekend with the wife of another man, a character important to the story. After Annie discovers the bodies, she happens by a locked cabin. Peeking in the window, she sees a bare ankle, half-covered by a sheet -- her lover's, she wildly assumes. But the ankle turns out to have been somebody else's.</p>
        <p>People glance off one another, then come back years later and realize, "Oh, that was you." But then nobody lives alone in a small town. Stories web, weave and lock, particularly in a place this isolated, where there's not much to do and people reach to one another for trouble and fun.</p>
        <p>It is Mia Raft who eventually comes up with the identity of the murdered young man. Even though she was only a child at the time, she has known who he was the whole time. "I had a Barbie boy doll called Ken originally," she says. "But we rechristened him, the other kids and I. . . . And in some way I have always known that it was the name of the guy in the tent. Us kids knew that."</p>
        <p>The identity of the slasher is something of a surprise, although there are hints all along. The motivation for the killings connects the murderer to Kerstin Ekman's concerns about the environment, but the murders actually have little to do with felled trees or peregrine falcons. "The event -- 10, 20 savage knifings -- came out of nothing. Out of the darkness that follows us."</p>
        <p>The novel suffers from a few lapses. The police never figure out that it's Johan Brandberg Annie Raft saw running by her on the night of the murders, even  though he left home that night and never returned to the village. Birger Torbjornsson's wife, a very interesting and sympathetic character, simply -- conveniently -- disappears from the book, and so does his son. There are over-long scenes between Johan and a sexually voracious woman who gives him a lift just after he passes Annie and Mia in the marsh. These scenes are satisfyingly juicy, but they seem to belong in another book. Also, in what may be a translation error, the peregrine falcon is referred to in a couple of places in the English fashion, as a buzzard, awfully confusing to the American reader who knows the difference.</p>
        <p>But all in all, Ms. Ekman provides us with a rich adventure, the kind of long, lush, thoughtful page-turner many of us crave but rarely get our hands on. (One interesting tidbit of literary cross-referencing: the event we have come simply to call "Chappaquiddick" gets a sidelong mention in "Blackwater" when, in an outdoor privy, Johan Brandberg uses a magazine story about Teddy Kennedy and  his experience that night for purposes other than reading. For those of us who admired "Black Water," Joyce Carol Oates's similarly titled novel, written from  the point of view of the dead girl who drowned in a car at that other remote, then famous village, the scene fairly jumps off the page.)</p>
        <p>Beverly Lowry's most recent novel is "The Track ofReal Desires."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Beverly Lowry's most recent novel is "The Track ofReal Desires."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
