<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's the Buzz? G.M.'s Electric Car Is Headed to Showrooms</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="835517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="SPENDING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC VEHICLES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SATURN DIVISION OF GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E7DE1639F933A25750C0A960958260" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's the Buzz? G.M.'s Electric Car Is Headed to Showrooms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ELECTRIC cars produced by a brand-name auto company, complete with warranty and dealer service, are just a few months away. But the EV1, the two-seater from the General Motors Corporation, will cost roughly $35,000, almost as much as a Corvette and a little more than two Saturns. At that price, who is going to want one?</p>
        <p>Probably not someone who is comparing it to the Corvette or the Saturns, according to G.M.'s Saturn division, which will sell them. There is no car to compare it to, contended John J. Orth, director of consumer marketing at Saturn. "It's just a totally new category," he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ELECTRIC cars produced by a brand-name auto company, complete with warranty and dealer service, are just a few months away. But the EV1, the two-seater from the General Motors Corporation, will cost roughly $35,000, almost as much as a Corvette and a little more than two Saturns. At that price, who is going to want one?</p>
        <p>Probably not someone who is comparing it to the Corvette or the Saturns, according to G.M.'s Saturn division, which will sell them. There is no car to compare it to, contended John J. Orth, director of consumer marketing at Saturn. "It's just a totally new category," he said.</p>
        <p>In fact, people who would consider buying an electric car may want the EV1,  which stands for Electric Vehicle 1, not so much because they want a car but because they want to try something new, he said. The buyers will be "the same people who bought the first Macintosh" or, for that matter, the Model T.</p>
        <p>When the Apple Macintosh computer was introduced, hardly any buyers could claim they really needed it. But it was one of the first successful entries in a new industry, and G.M. hopes the EV1 will be the same.</p>
        <p>G.M. plans to offer the car only in Southern California and Arizona. The company says the energy requirements of heating, which would reduce the range of the car, make the EV1 impractical in colder climates, at least as it is currently designed. Ford and Chrysler have also promised to sell electrics, but  those vehicles will most likely end up in companies' fleets, not homeowners' driveways.</p>
        <p>So what do buyers get in the $35,000 EV1, beyond a vehicle that carries only  two people and must stop and recharge for two hours or more after driving 70 to  90 miles?</p>
        <p>Ownership gives the right to feel good about helping to clean up the air, although the car is not pollution free. The electricity used to charge the battery will mean some additional contribution to smog and global warming, although not as great as from the carbon dioxide emitted from a Saturn or Corvette. Still, a hard-core clean-air fan would do better to use a bus, a car pool or a bicycle.</p>
        <p>But the EV1 also gives a different driving sensation: swift, silent and vibration free. It is almost as different from an internal-combustion car as a computer is from a typewriter.</p>
        <p>If feel isn't enough, there are more quantifiable benefits, like the maintenance schedule: there isn't one.</p>
        <p>The EV1 has no oil to change, or air filters, spark plugs or fan belts. As owners of older, conventional cars could come to appreciate, the EV1 also has no timing belt to replace, no muffler to rust, no fuel injector to clean, no clutch or transmission linkage to wear out and no fuel line to freeze (although  cold can limit range). There are brakes, but it would be hard to wear them out because much of the deceleration is provided by the electric motor, which can also function as a generator, turning unwanted momentum back into electric power for the batteries.</p>
        <p>Maintenance expenses for the first three years, during which the average person would drive 36,000 miles, are expected to be $80, mostly for odds and ends like windshield-washer fluid, wiper blades and power-steering fluid.</p>
        <p>The big expense waiting for the owners is replacing the batteries, which at some point -- no one knows when, although likely within 36,000 miles -- will no  longer hold a charge. Replacements could cost about $2,000. In contrast, maintaining a conventional car over three years would cost about $1,000.</p>
        <p>Range may not be much of a problem because buyers are unlikely to use the two-seat EV1 as a family car. According to census data, 20 percent of all households have three or more cars, meaning that they already have a family car. And even in households with only two adults -- 53.4 million in 1990 -- one in five also has three or more cars, so there may be a market among people who would like to choose a different car to drive every time they step into the driveway.</p>
        <p>And there are no visits to the gas station, only overnight rechargings, probably in the garage or carport. The energy cost for 36,000 miles is $736 at 6.5 cents a kilowatt-hour. Going that far on gasoline at $1.15 a gallon in a car that gets 27.5 miles a gallon, the national average, would cost $1,500.</p>
        <p>But offset against this is the cost of a charger. The car comes with a 110-volt model, about the size and heft of a five-gallon gasoline can, but most  buyers will want the 220-volt kind that charges the car faster and mounts on the garage wall or sits on the floor. As with the car, the price has not been set but will probably be around $2,000.</p>
        <p>When G.M. set about to develop the car, California was planning to require that 2 percent of the company's sales in that state be electric. Meeting that quota would have required a more popularly priced car. But California has withdrawn the quota and G.M. is free to offer the car at a price that maximizes  its profits. It is also doing so in Arizona, a state that had never planned to require electric cars, but where G.M. evidently believes it can make money.</p>
        <p>How much will consumers pay? The Ecoelectric Corporation, a company in Tucson, Ariz., that converts Chevrolet S-10 pickups to electricity, charges about $30,000 for its truck, a $17,000 premium over the gasoline-powered version. G.M. arrived at its price after lending prototypes of the EV1 to 500 families for two to four weeks each, accumulating a total of 370,000 miles. G.M. then tested the families' reaction to the car at a variety of different "price points." In the mid $30,000's, Mr. Orth said, "people thought you got a good value."</p>
        <p>Some states offer tax benefits that may lower the cost a bit. The Federal Government offers a 10 percent tax credit, and in Los Angeles, the South Coast Air Quality Management District plans to offer a $5,000 rebate to the first 1,200 buyers of electric cars. Some other states also offer incentives.</p>
        <p>If $35,000 seems a little rich, or the product a little too exotic to buy, G.M. says it is considering offering leases, at $450 to $600 a month (again, not much different from two Saturns). Leasing takes the long-term risk out of the driver's hands and is an easy way to get a toe in the water, said Robert R. Tripolsky, a spokesman for Saturn.</p>
        <p>He pointed out that leasing was not unusual. In 1995, about 29 percent of all cars, vans and light trucks sold in this country were leased, and the proportion rose with the price of the car, he said.</p>
        <p>If the sales price seems too steep, waiting might be a good strategy. As with the Macintosh, mass production and technical advances may lower the price. And as with camcorders and other modern electronic devices, competition and invention may lead to lower prices and more features.</p>
        <p>SPENDING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
