<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Government Will Offer Seal For Energy-Efficient Products</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="855287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENERGY AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC APPLIANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDING (CONSTRUCTION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY(EPA) ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALD, MATTHEW L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0DB1F39F937A35755C0A960958260" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Government Will Offer Seal For Energy-Efficient Products</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALD, MATTHEW L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Energy Department and the Environmental Protection Agency said today that they would offer manufacturers of appliances and building materials the right to use a Government seal of approval, the Energy Star, if their products meet Federal efficiency standards. The program is an effort to lower energy consumption, save money for consumers and cut pollution.</p>
        <p>The two agencies want to make the logo available to the manufacturers of the  most energy-efficient refrigerators, water heaters, air-conditioners, thermostats and exit signs, and to makers of building materials like insulation. The agencies are working with builders on standards that will allow them to award the seal to an entire house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Energy Department and the Environmental Protection Agency said today that they would offer manufacturers of appliances and building materials the right to use a Government seal of approval, the Energy Star, if their products meet Federal efficiency standards. The program is an effort to lower energy consumption, save money for consumers and cut pollution.</p>
        <p>The two agencies want to make the logo available to the manufacturers of the  most energy-efficient refrigerators, water heaters, air-conditioners, thermostats and exit signs, and to makers of building materials like insulation. The agencies are working with builders on standards that will allow them to award the seal to an entire house.</p>
        <p>The move is a major expansion of the Energy Star program. The logo was developed a few years ago by the Environmental Protection Agency for computers.  Manufacturers rushed to qualify for it, especially for personal-computer monitors and other office products.</p>
        <p>The first such endorsement program was Green Lights, which began in 1991 and  was intended to point building owners to more efficient lighting choices.</p>
        <p>David Nemtzow, the president of the Alliance to Save Energy, a nonprofit group that worked with the Federal agencies to expand the Energy Star program beyond computers, said the public was already familiar with certifications, like the recycling triangle, Underwriters Laboratories' "UL" for safety and the kosher "K" on various products.</p>
        <p>"Within a year or two, the Energy Star label will be as commonplace and sought-after as those other labels," Mr. Nemtzow said at a news briefing this morning.</p>
        <p>The standards will differ from product to product, but the two agencies said  they would rank all competing brands of a product and offer the Energy Star to those in the top 25 percent, said Christine A. Ervin, the Energy Department's assistant secretary for energy efficiency and renewable energy. But once the standards have been set and more companies qualify, Ms. Ervin said, at some point the Government may raise the standards, especially if technological advances allow manufacturers to improve their products.</p>
        <p>The Energy Star program will focus on products used in buildings, which account for one-third of the nation's energy consumption and two-thirds of its electricity use. The logo, a green and blue globe, appears over the motto: Saving the Earth. Saving Your Money.</p>
        <p>The agencies pointed out that Congress had been hostile to mandatory standards for energy efficiency.</p>
        <p>Congress has blocked the Department of Energy from developing energy-consumption standards for home appliances, and this year cut in half the  Environmental Protection Agency's budget for energy-related programs, to $40 million, said Mary D. Nichols, the assistant E.P.A. administrator for air and radiation.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ervin, of the Energy Department, said the expanded Energy Star project was part of a search for "some smarter ways" of getting energy-efficient products to consumers.</p>
        <p>By Federal law, some products already carry stickers describing their energy  use and comparing them to competing products. But Ms. Nichols said that when she shopped for an appliance, "I'm not standing there with my little kilowatt guidebook in hand, I'm looking for something that will do the job."</p>
        <p>A seal of approval would be easier for consumers to understand than a complicated guide, she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nichols added: "The idea that buying equipment can make a difference to the environment is not something that necessarily resonates with the individual  consumer." The expanded Energy Star program will try to make that connection, with public-service announcements and other steps, she said.</p>
        <p>Officials have been testing various seal-of-approval strategies over the last few months. They plan to begin the program in San Francisco, Tampa, Milwaukee and Washington and then have it spread nationwide.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
