<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ms. Workaholic's Mr. Right</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="825482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BED OF ROSES (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2D81F39F935A15752C0A960958260" item-length="577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ms. Workaholic's Mr. Right</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the wistful romance "Bed of Roses," Lisa (Mary Stuart Masterson) has an enviable problem. Though she spends her working days as a vice president talking about things like cost-benefit analysis, she has developed a secret admirer. The admirer sends her flowers out of the blue, as if to acknowledge that he understands her essential loneliness. Even better, when it comes to flowers, the secret admirer has sensationally good taste.</p>
        <p>One look at either the credits or the delivery man and it's not difficult to  guess who has been appreciating Lisa from afar. Christian Slater plays Lewis, who very soon emerges as a walking, talking antidote to Lisa's workaholism. He is sweet, thoughtful and conveniently unencumbered. And he has given up an important job at Goldman, Sachs to make flowers his life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the wistful romance "Bed of Roses," Lisa (Mary Stuart Masterson) has an enviable problem. Though she spends her working days as a vice president talking about things like cost-benefit analysis, she has developed a secret admirer. The admirer sends her flowers out of the blue, as if to acknowledge that he understands her essential loneliness. Even better, when it comes to flowers, the secret admirer has sensationally good taste.</p>
        <p>One look at either the credits or the delivery man and it's not difficult to  guess who has been appreciating Lisa from afar. Christian Slater plays Lewis, who very soon emerges as a walking, talking antidote to Lisa's workaholism. He is sweet, thoughtful and conveniently unencumbered. And he has given up an important job at Goldman, Sachs to make flowers his life.</p>
        <p>As that may suggest, "Bed of Roses" enjoys its own special greenhouse effect. Among its more memorable floral epiphanies are a look at Lewis's roof garden (a Manhattan oasis, created by the film makers atop the Chelsea Hotel) and his decision to woo her with enough pale lavender roses for the Rose Bowl Parade. The effect of such thoughtful and therapeutic gestures is to make Lisa calm down and start enjoying life. "I didn't get anything done to'ay," she says  with amazement at one point in the story.</p>
        <p>"Bed of Roses" enjoys watching Lisa slow down to share Lewis's gentler pace.  They wander picturesquely through Manhattan and even deliver flowers together. As Lewis points out, delivering flowers "has to be the best job in the world, you know? Everyone's always happy to see you." In the too-good-to-be-true department, Lewis also owns the flower shop and is very eager to cook Lisa's breakfast.</p>
        <p>As written and directed by Michael Goldenberg, "Bed of Roses" has all these soothing charms without much of a second act. Two lonely souls connect, so what  can be wrong with this picture? Mr. Goldenberg tries hard to create enough trepidation between the characters to keep them slightly apart, and even writes  Lewis's role to make the character faintly smothering and scary. But Mr. Slater  plays him as a benign, ingratiating suitor, so the latter part of the film mostly spins its wheels.</p>
        <p>What makes "Bed of Roses" worth watching, beyond the desire to look at tulips in late January, is Ms. Masterson's quietly affecting performance as a woman struggling to break through her own self-imposed loneliness. This actress, who so easily conveys both cool intelligence and desperate yearning, does a lovely job of expressing the tensions in Lisa's life. If those tensions aren't terribly dramatic, Ms. Masterson does make them touching and real. Though the film backs  her up with a broadly wisecracking girlfriend (Pamela Segall) and dread family secrets, Ms. Masterson is impressive enough to hold it together on her own.</p>
        <p>"Bed of Roses" is rated PG (Parental guidance suggested). It includes mild profanity and sexual situations.</p>
        <p>BED OF ROSES Written and directed by Michael Goldenberg; director of photography, Adam Kimmel; edited by Jane Kurson; music by Michael Convertino; production designer, Stephen McCabe; produced by Allan Mindel and Denise Shaw; released by Turner BroadcastingNew Line Cinema. Running time: 87 minutes. This film is rated PG.</p>
        <p>WITH: Christian Slater (Lewis), Mary Stuart Masterson (Lisa) and Pamela Segall (Kim).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
