<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Moon May Have Water, And Many New Possibilities</title>
    <meta content="04MOON$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="893471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Moon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clementine (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DA1E3CF937A35751C1A960958260" item-length="1505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Moon May Have Water, And Many New Possibilities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists report two years of careful analysis of radar signatures of moon transmitted by small Defense Department spacecraft suggests presence of water ice in permanently cold shadows of deep basin near lunar south pole; say survey by Clementine spacececraft seems to reveal vast landscape of approximately 3,000 square miles in which ice crystals are mixed with dirt in kind of permafrost that is presumably residue of moisture from comets striking moon over last three billion years; photos; diagrams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists think they have detected water on the Moon, and suddenly visions of people living in lunar colonies and stopping off there to refuel on the way to Mars seem a little less farfetched.</p>
        <p>After two years of careful analysis, scientists said yesterday that radar signals from an American spacecraft indicated the Moon was not as bone-dry as is usually thought. The peculiar radar signatures suggested the presence of water ice in the permanently cold shadows of a deep basin near the lunar south pole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists think they have detected water on the Moon, and suddenly visions of people living in lunar colonies and stopping off there to refuel on the way to Mars seem a little less farfetched.</p>
        <p>After two years of careful analysis, scientists said yesterday that radar signals from an American spacecraft indicated the Moon was not as bone-dry as is usually thought. The peculiar radar signatures suggested the presence of water ice in the permanently cold shadows of a deep basin near the lunar south pole.</p>
        <p>The ice deposit is not at all like a frozen lake where astronauts might try skating in one-sixth gravity. Instead, the scientists said, the survey seemed to reveal a vast landscape of some 3,000 square miles in which ice crystals are mixed with dirt, a kind of permafrost that is presumably the residue of moisture from comets striking the Moon over the last three billion years.</p>
        <p>''We think we have found ice,'' said Dr. Paul D. Spudis, a geologist at the Lunar and Planetary Institute in Houston. ''We are not positive. But we see signals consistent with ice, and we think it's there.''</p>
        <p>But Dr. Spudis and other scientists reporting the findings by Clementine, a small Defense Department spacecraft, acknowledged that the discovery needed to be confirmed by an independent investigation. That could come a year from now when another spacecraft, Lunar Prospector, is to orbit the Moon with instruments with even greater precision for determining the presence of lunar water.</p>
        <p>A detailed report on the findings has been published in the current issue of the journal Science. The principal scientists, Dr. Spudis and Dr. Stewart Nozette of the Air Force Phillips Laboratory in Alexandria, Va., described the results at a news conference yesterday at the Pentagon.</p>
        <p>Other scientists reacted to the report with a mixture of caution and enthusiasm. They wanted to believe, because of the important implications for future exploration and colonization of the Moon. But they noted that the radar results were particularly difficult to interpret.</p>
        <p>''I'd be delighted if it's true,'' said Dr. Bruce C. Murray, a planetary scientist at the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena, who in 1961 predicted that water ice would be found in polar shadows. ''But we need to look very carefully at the interpretation and wait for confirmation.''</p>
        <p>In the journal article, the discovery team was also extremely cautious. ''There are several possible explanations for these observations,'' the scientists wrote, ''including the possibility'' that the signals do not result from ice deposits.</p>
        <p>But no one was ignoring the implications, if the ice proves to be real.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, Dr. Wesley T. Huntress Jr., the agency's associate administrator for science, said the likely existence of water ice on the Moon ''could be a key ingredient in the support of future human lunar exploration, due to its potential value as a source of the components of rocket fuel.''</p>
        <p>The discovery has ''changed a desert to an oasis,'' said John E. Pike, a space policy analyst at the Federation of American Scientists in Washington. ''The Moon used to be dry; now it's wet. Now it could become a gas station.''</p>
        <p>Ever since Dr. Murray's prediction in 1961, the possibility of ice on the Moon has inspired speculation about using the resource for people living in permanent outposts and as rocket fuel for interplanetary travel. Using solar or nuclear power, the water ice could be converted into its components, hydrogen and oxygen, which are valuable rocket fuels.</p>
        <p>But Dr. John M. Logsdon, director of the Space Policy Institute at George Washington University, said it was still not clear how practical a resource the polar ice would be. He questioned the economic feasibility of using the water for colonies or rocket fuel in the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>As the Clementine spacecraft discovered, the dominant topographic feature in the south polar region of the Moon is a huge depression called the South Pole-Aitken basin. Gouged out by a massive asteroid nearly four billion years ago, the basin stretches 1,500 miles and in places is as deep as eight miles, deeper than Mount Everest is high.</p>
        <p>It is in the shadow of these deep walls that the cometary ice has apparently accumulated as a mixture of dirt and rock. Temperatures in the shadows are estimated to be as low as minus 387 degrees Fahrenheit. Any ice in parts of the basin exposed to sunlight would have evaporated and escaped into space. As it is, Dr. Spudis said, the ice in shadows is not a solid sheet like that found at a skating rink, but instead constitutes probably no more than 10 percent of the material in the region, which is mostly dirt.</p>
        <p>The ice's being near the south pole is another reason some scientists gave for expressing reservations about its utility any time soon.</p>
        <p>In the book ''Mining the Sky,'' published last month by Addison Wesley, Dr. John S. Lewis, a geologist at the Space Engineering Research Center of the University of Arizona, wrote that in many respects ''the lunar poles are not an attractive site for the lunar base.'' They are harder to reach by spacecraft from Earth and require more rocket energy. And it would be a difficult engineering feat to transport the ice to a base closer to the equator.</p>
        <p>Dr. Spudis noted that there was a high point in the basin, near the actual pole, that is almost permanently in sunlight. This would be an excellent site, he said, for a lunar installation with solar power panels to run equipment to melt the ice for water or convert it to breathing oxygen or rocket fuel.</p>
        <p>But he conceded: ''We have a long way to go before we have people living on the Moon. What this is, is an indication that living on the Moon might be possible.''</p>
        <p>From an astronaut on the space shuttle Columbia came an even more optimistic response. Told of the new findings by Mission Control, Dr. Story Musgrave said, ''Clearly if there is ice and there is water out there, that is a natural resource which is extraordinarily important to establishing a permanent thing such as an observatory on the Moon, or some kind of colony.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Nozette said the scientists were almost certain the radar was detecting water ice, though there could be small amounts of other substances like methane or carbon dioxide mixed in. Some 90 percent of a comet is composed of ice and most of that is water ice.</p>
        <p>About one-third of the south polar region appeared to be in permanent shadow, the Clementine scientists said, but very little of the north pole is in shadow.</p>
        <p>The $80 million Clementine spacecraft was developed and launched by the Defense Department's Ballistic Missile Defense Organization to test sensing instruments for anti-missile defenses. Since the craft would be heading near the Moon, where some of the tests could be made, scientists got permission to put Clementine into a lunar orbit and remap in greater detail much of the surface.</p>
        <p>Clementine was launched in January 1994 and operated in lunar orbit for four months. It was the first American craft to explore the Moon since the final Apollo landing in December 1972 and the last visit by any craft since the unmanned Russian Luna 24 landed there in 1976, picked up rock samples and returned them to Earth.</p>
        <p>The next mission to the Moon is Lunar Prospector, a small, unmanned craft being developed for NASA by the Ames Research Center in Mountain View, Calif., and built by Lockheed-Martin Corporation in Denver. Scheduled for launching next September, the spacecraft is to go into an orbit of the Moon that repeatedly crosses both poles. Its five remote-sensing instruments are designed to map the composition of the lunar surface and observe its magnetic and gravity fields.</p>
        <p>Dr. Huntress of NASA said that Lunar Prospector's two neutron spectrometers should be able to measure the amount of hydrogen on the lunar surface to an accuracy of 50 parts per million. ''This will permit scientists to infer the presence or absence of ice with greater precision than possible via the innovative but indirect method used by the Clementine team,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
