<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Island Q&amp;A: Diane Romm;Toward a Definition of the Internet's Role in Education</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="854682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4D71E39F931A35755C0A960958260" item-length="1867" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Island Q&amp;A: Diane Romm;Toward a Definition of the Internet's Role in Education</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAHEL MUSLEAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DIANE ROMM met the Internet four years ago in a pilot project among Hofstra University, the Nassau School Library System and Nassau Boces. As library chairwoman in the Uniondale school district, overseeing nine libraries, Ms. Romm was trained to use the Internet with five other librarians.</p>
        <p>Hofstra has since extended its access to the Internet to all Nassau districts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DIANE ROMM met the Internet four years ago in a pilot project among Hofstra University, the Nassau School Library System and Nassau Boces. As library chairwoman in the Uniondale school district, overseeing nine libraries, Ms. Romm was trained to use the Internet with five other librarians.</p>
        <p>Hofstra has since extended its access to the Internet to all Nassau districts.</p>
        <p>Ms. Romm conducts Internet workshops for teachers. She has a M.L.S. from Columbia University, a certificate in computers in education from the New York Institute of Technology and a professional diploma in educational administration from C. W. Post.</p>
        <p>Ms. Romm lives in Bellmore, is married to Rabbi Leonard Romm and has two sons, Gadi and Zvi. She is the author of a new book, "The Jewish Guide to the Internet" (Jason Aronson).</p>
        <p>Q.  What is the importance of the Internet for students?</p>
        <p>A.  Learning about the Internet is a critical component of education today. First, the Internet levels the playing field. Before, students in wealthier schools might have had access to different kinds of resources like expensive library materials that other schools couldn't afford. By opening up the world through the Internet schools are making sure that everybody has access to the same kinds of information.</p>
        <p>When students use the Internet it expands their horizons beyond the classroom walls. It allows them to meet people they might otherwise never meet, like scientists or specialists in a particular area. Hook a kid up with a mentor through the Internet and you introduce a child to a career possibility they might never have thought of before. That could change their lives.</p>
        <p>Collaborative projects can show students what scientific inquiry is all about. In one project on acid rain students all over the country actually measured the pH of the rain in their area and shared the data.</p>
        <p>On a more local basis we're trying to match up college kids who have graduated from Uniondale High School in the last year or two with kids who are interested in attending those colleges. In that way they can ask questions of a  peer, and if they choose to attend that college they will know at least one person already.</p>
        <p>Q.  Can the Internet make a child a better student, even a better person?</p>
        <p>A.  Yes. Students develop sophisticated skills as to how to search, sift and  evaluate information in an intelligent manner. These are skills that will make them life-long learners and life-long intelligent consumers.</p>
        <p>The Internet has the potential to raise students' sensitivity. Because it is  international in its communication, people have to become more sensitive to the  way what they say may be interpreted by people who come from different cultural  backgrounds.</p>
        <p>Q.What effects does the Internet have on teachers?</p>
        <p>A.  It can break down the isolation of teaching. The hardest thing about teaching is that you never get to see how other people do the same thing you do, because when you close the door you're in the classroom by yourself. The only opportunity you get to share is if you go to conferences or professional meetings, which means you're out of the classroom or have to take time after work. You can participate in Internet dialogues on an ongoing basis.</p>
        <p>Teachers can use the Internet as an enriching and exciting resource in their  curricula. For a unit on "Huckleberry Finn" teachers can search for information  on Tom Sawyer or Mark Twain and bookmark those sites. It's almost like putting books on reserve in a library, except you have a lot more material to choose from. Students can look up the bookmarks in the library or from home.</p>
        <p>There are discussion groups for teachers in every grade level and every subject. Teachers trade ideas, lesson plans, projects, and make arrangements for mutual projects.</p>
        <p>Q.  Could a hard-working student find the same information?</p>
        <p>A.  No, they really couldn't. No library is kept as up to date as material is on the Internet. The Internet is global in its origin. We don't have global resources in libraries. We have local resources. We have American resources. We  can't afford to buy and physically house the vast array of information that's present on the Internet and that grows and changes at the rate of 20 percent a month.</p>
        <p>Books and computers aren't mutually exclusive. When people come to a library  looking for information, you help them find it in the best and easiest way possible. Sometimes that means using a book. Sometimes it means using a computer.</p>
        <p>Q.  What are the challenges of using the Internet?</p>
        <p>A.  One of the most difficult aspects is finding information, especially particular pieces of information. It's almost like someone taking the card catalog of the Library of Congress, dumping it on the floor and telling you: "The stuff's here someplace. Go find it."</p>
        <p>Students have to master the art of searching. Teaching students to define exactly what they're looking for can also be difficult. A student might come in  and say, "Where's your information on cars?" You have to help them refine the question. Do they want a picture of a car to draw for a class? Do they want information about the history of cars? Is their Volkswagen stuck outside, and they want to repair it?</p>
        <p>Another skill we teach is how to be discriminating about looking at sources of information. When you take information off the Internet you don't have any idea about the qualifications of the person who's put it up there. Kids also have to learn how to successfully sift through a barrage of information. We teach kids the process of discerning what's important and how to hone in on the  essence of the topic.</p>
        <p>Q.  Is there a danger that as with television the Internet can become addictive?</p>
        <p>A.  Yes. As in anything, I'd rather have the Golden Mean. But there is a difference between TV and the Internet. TV is passive. You sit back and watch pictures flash on it. The Internet is interactive. You have to read what's on the screen and respond to it. Whatever happens on it is what you make happen. You control it. Given a choice, kids will stay on the Internet longer than they'll watch TV.</p>
        <p>A lot of kids are writing their own home pages on the Internet. They figure out what they want to say, storyboard it attractively and compose the page. They have to learn HTML language, which makes the page appear in a particular way. So there are a lot of skills they acquire in the process.</p>
        <p>Q.  What are the practical aspects of using computers in schools?</p>
        <p>A.  In most schools access to the Internet starts off in the library or computer lab. Some school districts like Seaford and Lynbrook are nodes on the Internet. That means they are connected directly to the Internet and can access  it on a need-to-know basis from any computer in the school. The teacher doesn't  have to pick up the class and trot them to the library.</p>
        <p>We and other schools have an "acceptable usage" policy, which outlines the students' responsibilities. The students and their parents have to sign off on the policy, agreeing not to use the Internet as an abusive tool, not to use it to give offense or steal from other people.</p>
        <p>Q.  What are examples of unusual sites for school work?</p>
        <p>A.  The Internet Public Library from the University of Michigan is a simulation of going to the library. You can go to the reference desk and the young adult section and access real live books like Bartlett's Quotations, dictionaries and atlases. For younger kids Uncle Bob's Kid's Page has links to all kinds of fun things like how to make origami. In a book about origami you might look at the picture and ask, what does that dotted line mean? Here you can actually see the motion of folding.</p>
        <p>Q.  What do you advise parents who have difficulty keeping up?</p>
        <p>A.  Turn it into an opportunity for your child to show off to you. Kids love  to teach, and they respond favorably when you say: "Can you show me how to do that? How did you make that happen?" It makes them feel great about themselves.</p>
        <p>Q.  Why did you write "The Jewish Guide to the Internet" in print format?</p>
        <p>A.  Someone who has never been on the Internet may wonder what all the hoopla is all about. Despite the built-in obsolescence of a print title about the Internet, a book can give them an idea of the enormity of Jewish resources and highlights the more significant sites in 53 subject areas. They don't have to sift through the hundreds of hits they might get by using a keyword search on the Internet.</p>
        <p>The book also brings the order of the library world to the chaos of the Internet by helping people find answers to questions like, "Where can I find an  Israeli high school with E-mail access?" and, "Where can I get a bibliography of the Holocaust?"</p>
        <p>Q.  What are some sites of Jewish interest?</p>
        <p>A.  They run the gamut from scholarly to frivolous. You can participate in a  discussion group called Ioudaios, which means Jew in Greek and is about first-century Judaism and its development. Of course, it presupposes you can read Greek. You can take a course in Jewish art or history through the Jewish University in Cyberspace, which is sponsored by the World Zionist Organization. You can look up the entire texts of the Bible and Talmud.</p>
        <p>At the other end of the spectrum, there are humor repositories where you can  find out why God never received tenure at Hebrew University. You can download a  manual for obtaining an Israeli driver's license or access the Israeli Yellow Pages.  You can take bar-mitzvah lessons or learn the steps to Israeli dances. Kids can participate in a quiz called "Where in the World is Sadie Miami Beach?"</p>
        <p>The Jewish community has embraced this medium and made it its own. The Internet is a Godsend for observant Jews who live in isolated areas. They can interact with other people and create their own virtual community. The People of the Book have become the People of the Net.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
