<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="830200"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6D91239F936A25751C0A960958260" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>A MEXICAN SUCCESS STORY The conquest of Mexico's tortilla king demonstrates the cronyism and unfair business practices that prevail in Mexico even as the Government touts a commitment to an open economy. A1</p>
        <p>ZAIRE SEALS OFF REFUGEE CAMP Zairian soldiers sealed off trade from 190,000 refugees in the Kibumba camp, the latest effort by the United Nations to force the refugees to return to Rwanda. A3</p>
        <p>CABINET TALKS COLLAPSE IN ITALY Hopes for a reform of Italy's political system collapsed after Prime Minister-designate Antonio Maccanico abandoned his two-week effort to form a Government. A4</p>
        <p>BOSNIAN SERBS DETAIN MUSLIMS Bosnian Serbs said they had detained several Muslims who wandered into areas under their control, and a sniper believed to be a Bosnian Serb opened fire on a bus outside Sarajevo, wounding two people. A7</p>
        <p>MIXED SIGNALS FROM SUDAN Sudan has shown some cooperation with Western demands that it not allow terrorists to operate in the country, even as it has threatened retaliation. A6</p>
        <p>SAMPER CHARGED IN COLOMBIA Colombia's chief prosecutor formally charged President Ernesto Samper before the Congress with the crimes of illegal enrichment, electoral fraud and coverup. A12</p>
        <p>PEACE PROSPECT IN MEXICO Leaders of a rebel movement in southern Mexico said they will sign an agreement  with the Government expanding the rights of Indians, clearing the way for a peace accord in the two-year-old conflict. A12</p>
        <p>Versailles Journal: Stripping the great chateaus of France. A4</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>A14-24, B12-15</p>
        <p>BLEAK DAYS IN COAL COUNTRY Coal mines are closing in Appalachia and other parts of the East, casualties of  a provision of the Clean Air Act of 1990 that seeks to lessen acid rain. A1</p>
        <p>THE BATTLE FOR THE HOUSE A House seat held by a Nebraska Republican is just one of many that Democrats are focusing on in a campaign to regain the majority they lost in '94. A1</p>
        <p>HYBRID ORATORY SCORES POINTS Patrick J. Buchanan has combined elements of his 1992 campaign speech, which centered on social conservatism, with economic populism. The result is proving popular with Republican voters. A1</p>
        <p>NEW STRATEGIES ON THE STUMP On the campaign trail in New Hampshire, Republican Presidential candidates shifted tactics, seeking an edge as the primary election approaches. B15</p>
        <p>The wheels come off the Gramm bandwagon. B14</p>
        <p>AN OLYMPIC-SIZED DISPUTE A world-class sailor's dreams of competing in the Olympics is in doubt because he takes the hormone testosterone, a result of his battle with cancer. A14</p>
        <p>LAWYER'S PLEA AT TRIAL A lawyer for a man accused of killing two abortion-clinic workers in suburban Boston urged the jury to find him not guilty by reason of mental illness. A14</p>
        <p>SIGNS OF PSYCHOTHERAPY A study of patients with obsessive-compulsive disorder has found that psychotherapy can produce biological effects in the brain, similar to those seen with medication. B12 Metro Report</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>GIULIANI VS. THE POLICE UNION Angry that the police union pushed its arbitration bill through the state legislature, the Giuliani Administration warned that to offset the new law's costs it was considering several steps that many police officers will undoubtedly view as punitive -- including ordering the use of one-person patrol  cars. A1</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>C19-28</p>
        <p>NETWORKS' RATINGS SYSTEM After years of resisting as censorship any attempt to regulate the content of television programs, the four broadcast networks are seeking to establish their  own ratings system, similar to the Motion Picture Association of America's code  for movies. A1</p>
        <p>Resuscitating forgotten musicals. C19 "60 Minutes" makes format changes. C26 Music: Recycled oldies aren't always golden. C19 Lenny Kravitz at Roseland. C24 The Pop Life C25 Dance: Hawkins troupe. C19 Books: "Auden," a biography by Richard Davenport-Hines. C25 Television: "Inspector Morse: Twilight of the Gods." C25</p>
        <p>The Home Section</p>
        <p>C1-16</p>
        <p>Mr. Fisk's green house. C1 At home with Elmore Leonard. C1 New-old couples: vows 2. C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>B17-24</p>
        <p>Baseball: Yankees' Wetteland faces the past. B17 Basketball: Knicks lose to Hornets. B17 Nets surprise Pacers again. B17 Boxing: New York commission announces H.I.V. testing. B17 Columns: Anderson on Charlie Conerly. B17 Football: Giants face free-agent choices. B19</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>B16</p>
        <p>Lady Caroline Blackwood, novelist.</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>New Hampshire passion play. The divorce debate. Save the Harlem Fairway.</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>William Safire: Cap over the wall. Maureen Dowd: Playing Holly Gocheaply. Chas. Freeman: The end of Taiwan? Douglas Shenson: 30 days or else.</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>C17</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>C23</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
