<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene;If the U.S. doesn't follow trade rules, why should others?</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860581"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CRAY RESEARCH INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEC CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EEDA1239F934A15755C0A960958260" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene;If the U.S. doesn't follow trade rules, why should others?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF at first you don't succeed, try, try again. Cray Research, the Minneapolis-based maker of supercomputers, seems to have taken that homily to heart. After failing to convince the National Science Foundation that it could build a better machine to simulate global warming than the NEC Corporation of Japan, Cray is attempting to nullify the foundation's decision through the back  door. Friends of Cray in Congress have slipped a provision into the foundation's proposed budget that would effectively bar completion of the deal with the Japanese.</p>
        <p>More is at stake here than the $35 million contract announced last month. "Since the late 1970's, America has been pressuring Japan to play fair on government procurement," said Gary Saxonhouse, an economist at the University of Michigan. By changing the rules when it suits American interests, Washington is  risking hard-won progress in opening up the Japanese market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF at first you don't succeed, try, try again. Cray Research, the Minneapolis-based maker of supercomputers, seems to have taken that homily to heart. After failing to convince the National Science Foundation that it could build a better machine to simulate global warming than the NEC Corporation of Japan, Cray is attempting to nullify the foundation's decision through the back  door. Friends of Cray in Congress have slipped a provision into the foundation's proposed budget that would effectively bar completion of the deal with the Japanese.</p>
        <p>More is at stake here than the $35 million contract announced last month. "Since the late 1970's, America has been pressuring Japan to play fair on government procurement," said Gary Saxonhouse, an economist at the University of Michigan. By changing the rules when it suits American interests, Washington is  risking hard-won progress in opening up the Japanese market.</p>
        <p>Supercomputers -- machines that can crunch numbers at multiples of the speeds of the giant mainframes that dominated the computer market in the 1970's  -- were once thought to be the key to the future of the data processing industry. It didn't work out that way, though. Supercomputers now dominate niches in electronic eavesdropping, nuclear weapons design, high-energy physics, weather forecasting and oil exploration -- important and prestigious uses, certainly, but ones unlikely to deliver a big technological or commercial payoff to the manufacturers.</p>
        <p>That hasn't stopped NEC, Fujitsu or Hitachi, which all invested heavily in supercomputers in the 1980's, from fighting for sales. Indeed, Cray won equal consideration in bidding on Japanese Government contracts only after President George Bush threatened trade sanctions in 1989.</p>
        <p>But the supercomputer market, long dominated by American brands, is now up for grabs. Hitachi currently owns bragging rights as the maker of the fastest supercomputer in the world. More important from Cray's perspective, recent sales in Canada and Europe suggest that NEC and Fujitsu machines are now highly competitive in weather forecasting. So it was no great shock to computer gurus when the Government's top science research agency chose a computer from NEC, despite Cray's none-too-subtle contentions that American jobs and security were  at risk.</p>
        <p>Ailing Cray, which was recently bought by Silicon Graphics after prodding from the Defense Department, has lots of friends in high places. Three days after the NEC award, the acting head of the Commerce Department's Import Administration wrote to the National Science Foundation to warn that the Japanese bid was "substantially" below the manufacturer's cost and thus potentially subject to antidumping penalties.</p>
        <p>Greg Rushford, the publisher of the Rushford Report, a Washington-based newsletter on trade politics, said the warning was unusual for a variety of reasons. One Federal agency rarely interferes with procurements by another unless it is invited. More striking yet, the Commerce Department issued the warning before it had begun an independent inquiry or even given NEC a chance to defend itself.</p>
        <p>But the surprises were just beginning. Two weeks ago, Representative David R. Obey, a Wisconsin Democrat with close ties to Cray, amended a draft of the science foundation's appropriations bill to deny funds for the salaries of personnel "who approve a contract for the purchase, lease or acquisition in any  manner of supercomputing equipment" after a "preliminary determination" by the Commerce Department that the offering was "at any other than fair value."</p>
        <p>This stealth attack was bipartisan: An effort by Representative Jim Kolbe, an Arizona Republican, to scratch the Obey amendment was brushed aside by fellow committee members. That suggests it has a good chance of surviving in the 1997 appropriations bill, which is supposed to be completed by Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>The White House has yet to take a position on the Obey amendment. And for the moment Tokyo is apparently hoping the conflict can be resolved privately before  it becomes a high-profile political issue back home. So far, the only reaction -- from Hajime Ito, a senior trade official at the Japanese Embassy in Washington -- is a mild expression of "serious concern." But Mr. Ito suggests that the initiative violates World Trade Organization rules. If true, that could lead to another embarrassing defeat for America in the new trade body.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kolbe remains publicly optimistic that Congress will discard the Obey amendment. "This is such a flagrant violation of the spirit of our laws that I think it will come out," he said. But he does not hide his frustration that it has gotten this far. "We make a big point of telling other nations they must live by the rule of law," he notes, "and then we turn around and pull this kind  of stunt."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
