<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Da Going Out Guide</title>
    <meta content="IVES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="191" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ives, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E4DC153CF93AA1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1339" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Da Going Out Guide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID IVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ives, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Ives article in form of guide to 2096 entertainment and cultural events (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sept. 29 - Oct. 5, 2096</p>
        <p>(This guide covers events only in the New York City area. For events you can teletransport yourself to, click ''What's On in the World.'' For this week's virtual reality listings, click ''What's On in Your Head.'' For a list of who's going to be famous for 15 minutes this week, and when, click ''Who's On and Off in Your Head.'' To receive this guide internally on your implanted cerebrocortical computer web, click your fingers, press the electrode in your left temple and say the word ''pablum.'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sept. 29 - Oct. 5, 2096</p>
        <p>(This guide covers events only in the New York City area. For events you can teletransport yourself to, click ''What's On in the World.'' For this week's virtual reality listings, click ''What's On in Your Head.'' For a list of who's going to be famous for 15 minutes this week, and when, click ''Who's On and Off in Your Head.'' To receive this guide internally on your implanted cerebrocortical computer web, click your fingers, press the electrode in your left temple and say the word ''pablum.'')</p>
        <p>Museums</p>
        <p>Da Mitsubishi (formerly Da Metropolitan) Museum. ''Mo Mo Monet.'' The ultimate blockbuster: all</p>
        <p>18 floors of the museum are filled with Monet's paintings, drawings and pencil shavings, as well as every object the</p>
        <p>artist ever used, owned, sat on or blew his nose in. In the Gift Shop: Claude Monet himself, reconstituted from the DNA in a strand of his beard, painting haystacks</p>
        <p>and singing dirty French songs. Suggested daily admission: $350 or 18 yen.</p>
        <p>Da Museum of Modern Art.</p>
        <p>Tourists call this 20th-century ''modernist'' collection the Temple of the Quaint, and</p>
        <p>you have to see some of this kitsch from</p>
        <p>our planet's dullest century to believe</p>
        <p>it. The Picassos, which we now know were painted by his cook, are a hoot. Through October: ''Cuban Cubism,'' a small exhibit (there was no Cuban Cubism) welcoming our country's 63d state.</p>
        <p>Da Whitney Museum. ''Works on Velvet.'' Everybody's painting on velvet these days, but no one has the touch of the old and often anonymous masters. The full-figured gypsy girl from circa March 1973, by the</p>
        <p>artist known as the Master of the Rosy Nipple, will knock your eyeballs out. Starting Oct. 15: ''Heterosexual Painting, 2066-79.''</p>
        <p>Galleries</p>
        <p>''Ode to Emily Dickinson. The traditional artist Suzi Generous will have her spleen removed and painted chartreuse,</p>
        <p>then reimplanted, and her entire body laminated. This is stodgy Clintonian Age</p>
        <p>stuff, but Suzi has her fans. Wednesday at Wildenstein. Funeral Friday at Knoedler.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Schwa. These 3,767</p>
        <p>self-portraits depict Schwa in every known medium, including tapioca, phorkograph, shplit, phtung and watercolor, as part</p>
        <p>of his ''Series'' series. Our critic Azimuth</p>
        <p>Drool hailed Schwa as ''irrelevant.'' At Williams/Sonoma/Schnabel.</p>
        <p>Sounds Around Town</p>
        <p>Da Village Vanguard, Citibank Building. Netsuhiro Fishscale, the hotshot Japanese-Inuit alto zmygdophone specialist, had a bright idea after his last album went plutonium: he hooked his horn up to a nuclear reactor, and now he really wails. When we saw him last weekend, Fishscale blew 4,000 choruses of ''Body and Soul'' before his lungs melted, 16 octaves above middle C. A radiant artist. Dining, drinks, protective clothing.</p>
        <p>Lincoln Center. Da New York Philharmonic and Da Mormon Tabernacle Choir. A program of warhorses by Snoop Doggy Dogg, Boyz II Men, Willie Colon and the Sex Pistols.</p>
        <p>Da Knitting Factory. Da Guarneri Quartet plays the complete Beethoven cycle. Of course. Will they ever stop?</p>
        <p>Theater</p>
        <p>Jackie Mason: Still Alive,</p>
        <p>Still Jewish, Still on Broadway. New jokes about Jews and gentiles</p>
        <p>(wuzzat?) by the 163-year-old comedian</p>
        <p>and Nobel Peace Prize winner. Mason's</p>
        <p>not exactly on Broadway, playing the</p>
        <p>cafe in the Hotel Mitsubishi Edison, but</p>
        <p>he's close enough. Besides, the last Broadway house closed down in '68 and became the New Amsterdam Funeral Parlor. Surtitles. Chicken noodle soup.</p>
        <p>''Da Vida.'' Margo Sanchez-Chang's sequel to ''Da Nada'' and ''Da Dada,'' a period piece about life in 2061. A young woman tragically discovers that she is not Hispanic-Chinese and tall, but Chinese-Hispanic and short. Our critic Bram</p>
        <p>Bentley called the play ''ovoid.'' With</p>
        <p>Juliet Gonzalez-Fang. At the George C. Wolfe/William Shakespeare Public Theater.</p>
        <p>Lincoln Center Theater. Downstairs, in repertory, a festival of plays by America's greatest 20th-century playwrights: Maxwell Anderson, Lillian Hellman, William Inge, Joseph Kesselring and Steve Silver of ''Beach Blanket Babylon'' fame. Upstairs:</p>
        <p>the immortal, sublime ''Moose Murders,'' which is sold out through October 2108.</p>
        <p>Other theater around New York City: aintnone.</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>Da SONY (formerly New York City) Ballet. The artistic director Rupert Wuppertal faced a crisis last</p>
        <p>year when he couldn't find anyone in</p>
        <p>the hemisphere willing to shut off his porno-virtual reality web and dance,</p>
        <p>so subscribers may notice a difference</p>
        <p>in the fall season's all-Balanchine program. Tuesday: ''Agon,'' with penguins. Wednesday: ''Apollo,'' with sponges. Thursday: ''Concerto Barocco,'' with masses of warm, moist air as the corps de ballet and fruit flies and paramecia as the soloists.</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Tennis Doubles. Whoever decided to go back to wooden racquets with catgut strings was brilliant. Whoever added tackling was a genius. At Madison Square Garden, 168th and Broadway. Financed by RJReynoldsBank.</p>
        <p>Connecticut Open. These fancy new nuclear clubs have sure put some oomph into the old game. The first hole in this championship is a par 5, 368-mile dogleg with Bridgeport as its sand trap.</p>
        <p>Da Teaneck Giants vs. Da Lake Tahoe 49ers. The slippage at the coast that turned the Sierra Nevada into beachfront cliffs hasn't dampened California spirits on the gridiron. And the new armor-piercing missiles players can deploy on third downs ought to keep their ''minds'' on the game. At Giants Stadium, Hackensack, N.J.</p>
        <p>For Kids: When the major leagues closed up shop in 2093, a lot of outfielders found themselves out of work. Beisbol Commissioner George Ivana-Trump Steinbrenner 8th had the smart idea of taking up the slack with an interleague spelling bee. This week you can see the Yankees face off against the Mets in a battle to spell ''hairnet'' and ''washroom.'' The winning team gets high-school diplomas. The losing team will be executed. Surtitles. Dining. At Shea Stadium, Fifth Avenue and 23d Street.</p>
        <p>Outdoors</p>
        <p>Central ''Park.'' Leasing the park to strip-mining interests has scarred Olmsted's classic landscape a bit, but it has brought the city some much-needed revenue. Wednesday at 6 P.M., Mayor Grafton Barry will kick off the clear-cutting of the park's last remaining trees. This event oddly coincides with last week's final transformation of the Brazilian ''rain forest'' into a lawn.</p>
        <p>E.T.R.S.V.P. Now scientists claim to</p>
        <p>have decoded those mysterious signals from the region of Alpha Centauri but disagree on what they mean. The Oxford team says the signals spell out the words ''Little Nell -- is she dead then?'' The Patagonian team claims the signals ask, ''What is good for athlete's foot?'' The French team says the signals are in quite good French and spell out an advertisement for something called Velveeta. The contending teams will</p>
        <p>debate the matter Roman-style with spear, net, trident and pinking shears in Columbia's main quad, Thursday at 8.</p>
        <p>Acid rain date, Friday.</p>
        <p>Air On The G Spot</p>
        <p>The string specialist Wanda</p>
        <p>Semicolon Hyphen Forcucci has been playing the boites in Mongolia for the past year. ''Forget Mongo Disney,'' Wanda says. ''Ulan Bator is still a tough room.'' The upside of Wanda's trip</p>
        <p>was that she discovered the Himalayan qa'ma'qak, a 6-foot-tall, 49-string wooden instrument whose vibrations induce immediate orgasm in anyone who listens. Wanda married</p>
        <p>the qa'ma'qak here at City Hall last week, then took a few days' honeymoon at Niagara Hydroelectric Dam. Now the happy pair is back and romancing it up for some highly appreciative listeners at the Rainbow Room, the top of the Bulgarian-</p>
        <p>owned storage space known to your grandfolks as Rockefeller Center. Dining, showers.</p>
        <p>Take Me to Your Reader.</p>
        <p>'What Was Literacy?'</p>
        <p>A panel discussion by three of our last intellectuals who can read, sponsored</p>
        <p>by prestigious, old-world Madonna Ciccone University. Also: ''How Does Language Change?'' A panel discussion dilka flink omzivorsky blekhpis horrashow.</p>
        <p>Tuesday and Wednesday at Verb-Um, the</p>
        <p>last shop in town where you can</p>
        <p>still buy ''books.'' Try one sometime. They taste a lot like chicken.</p>
        <p>David Ives is the author of the play ''All in the Timing.'' His play ''The Red Address'' will be presented at Second Stage this fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Ives is the author of the play ''All in the Timing.'' His play ''The Red Address'' will be presented at Second Stage this fall.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
