<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Coverage Less Prominent in News Magazines</title>
    <meta content="23MAGS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19960926T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="879082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">US News &amp; World Report (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Newsweek (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E1DA103DF930A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Coverage Less Prominent in News Magazines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time, Newsweek and US News &amp; World Report are giving less coverage to foreign news, primarily because there has been a gradual but significant lessening of interest in matters overseas since Vietnam and even more so since the end of cold war; editors say Americans have become more concerned about other issues, like the economy, technology and culture; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you solely depended on the three news magazines for information and just happened to glance at the covers of those magazines when they came out on Sept. 9, chances are you might not have realized that the United States had launched a cruise missile attack on Iraq the week before.</p>
        <p>Time featured an article on the Microsoft Corporation; Newsweek on testosterone, and U.S. News &amp; World Report on the best colleges in America, with coverage inside of Saddam Hussein's most significant military campaign since the Persian Gulf war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you solely depended on the three news magazines for information and just happened to glance at the covers of those magazines when they came out on Sept. 9, chances are you might not have realized that the United States had launched a cruise missile attack on Iraq the week before.</p>
        <p>Time featured an article on the Microsoft Corporation; Newsweek on testosterone, and U.S. News &amp; World Report on the best colleges in America, with coverage inside of Saddam Hussein's most significant military campaign since the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>If international news has been noticeably lacking from the recent covers of the news magazines, part of that has to do with the proliferation of domestic news, such as the T.W.A. crash, the Olympic Games, the bombing in Atlanta during the Olympics and the Presidential race.</p>
        <p>But editors at the news magazines and foreign policy experts say there is something deeper at work, that since Vietnam and even more so since the cold war, there has been a gradual but significant lessening of interest in matters overseas.</p>
        <p>''With the end of the cold war and the vast reduction in the overall threat to the United States, we no longer have enemies, we have dangers,'' Mortimer B. Zuckerman, chairman and editor in chief of U.S. News, said. ''And that obviously has less attraction to a large audience than what existed before 1990. So, yes, there is a diminution of coverage, simply because the issues are less relevant.''</p>
        <p>So far this year, Time has run 5 international covers, after running 11 in 1995, including 2 on the British royal family and not counting one on French cave paintings and one on a tomb discovered in Egypt.</p>
        <p>Newsweek has run four such covers this year -- including one on global warming and not including the one on Mount Everest and two on the Olympics. It ran 11 in 1995.</p>
        <p>U.S. News has run no international covers this year and ran six in 1995.</p>
        <p>Time and Newsweek featured the Russian elections on their covers -- Time twice and Newsweek once.</p>
        <p>In 1995, Time devoted 385 pages to international news, or 14 percent of the magazine, according to Hall's Magazine Editorial Reports, which analyzes the editorial content of most consumer magazines. Newsweek used 338 pages, or 12 percent of its coverage, and U.S. News had 386, or 14 percent. This is a significant decline. In 1985, Time had 670 pages, or 24 percent, Newsweek had 590, or 22 percent, and U.S. News had 588, or 20 percent.</p>
        <p>To judge from publications like The Economist and The New York Review of Books, there are international subjects that Americans could be paying more attention to, such as the riots in Jakarta, Indonesia; the ousting of Domingo Cavallo, Argentina's Finance Minister, or the continuing mass killings in Burundi.</p>
        <p>But editors say they are simply responding to their readers, who care most about international news  that directly affects them, a criterion that is increasingly difficult to meet. ''The American news weeklies are thinking very much of international stories as being an extension of domestic,'' said Bill Hammett, editor of The Economist, based in London, which covers international news extensively in each weekly issue. ''How does this directly affect the U.S.?''</p>
        <p>Similarly, Americans seem to care about places like Bosnia most when an American pilot like Capt. Scott F. O'Grady is shot down there. And they care about Asia in so far as they have economic interests there. ''The Government and the business community are very interested in U.S.-Japan relations and U.S.-China relations,'' said Edward N. Luttwak, a senior fellow at the Center for Strategic and International Studies in Washington. ''There is no attention being put on Japan's relations with China, and yet what's happening between the East Asians is much more important and will eventually define the economic world in ways that will have a big impact on the United States.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, except for the Middle East, the world has been relatively quiet lately. ''Week in and week out, international news has been a bit less urgent,'' said Walter Isaacson, managing editor of Time magazine.</p>
        <p>To a great extent, editors say other issues have become more important to Americans, including the economy, technology and cultural concerns. Americans seem more curious about matters closer to home -- although a recent Newsweek cover  featured an article on Mars.</p>
        <p>''We have not diminished our interest but just focused on where we think the more important and more relevant issues are, which is more in the realm of culture and ideas,'' Mr. Zuckerman said.</p>
        <p>James F. Hoge Jr., editor of Foreign Affairs, said Americans were also following the example of their elected leaders. ''The media, to a great extent, takes its lead from public officials as to whether foreign policy is worthy of coverage,'' Mr. Hoge said. ''And we have a virtual blackout in both parties.''</p>
        <p>President Clinton himself is seen in his Presidential campaign as focusing on domestic concerns, editors say. ''You have a President who basically signaled to the American people they didn't have to worry about foreign affairs, that the bear in the Kremlin was dead,'' Maynard Parker, the editor of Newsweek, said. ''He wasn't going to spend that much time worrying about foreign affairs and they shouldn't either.''</p>
        <p>But some journalists caution against catering to a national self-interest that can lead to an unhealthy, ill-informed isolationism.</p>
        <p>''In a very interlocked world, to be one of the major players -- indeed the major player -- and not sustain more interest than we do is risky,'' Mr. Hoge said. ''What happens when we do need the public to understand and support -- however grudgingly -- some policies that don't have immediate benefits in the way of jobs or more security?''</p>
        <p>While the news magazines' international editions tend to feature more world news, Mr. Hammett of The Economist said the American editions must answer to a different set of demands. ''I think they feel they need to compete for American readers with more life-style and consumer interest stories,'' Mr. Hammett said. ''Low-cholesterol diets, science, the dinosaurs, life on Mars -- the competition between them has become such that they haven't felt that international stories really sell their magazines.''</p>
        <p>Editors say magazines with international subjects on the cover barely sell. ''The poorest-selling covers of the year are always those on international news,'' Mr. Zuckerman said.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, editors occasionally go ahead and do it anyway. ''I put the Russian elections on the cover, even though I knew it wasn't going to sell,'' Mr. Parker of Newsweek said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parker did not, however, put Benjamin Netanyahu, now Israel's Prime Minister, on the cover after his surprising upset in the Israeli elections, running a cover-length story inside instead. ''While people may be interested in the drama of it, I don't see it as an event that's going to spill way beyond its borders,'' Mr. Parker said. (Time did put Mr. Netanyahu on the cover.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Parker said his decision was based in part on the poor response to Newsweek's cover on the assassination of Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin of Israel. ''It was in the bottom 20 percent of newsstand sales for last year,'' Mr. Parker said.</p>
        <p>All of this being said, magazine editors insist they remain committed to foreign news. While correspondents may have been deployed to different areas, their numbers have been basically consistent, editors say. And while some foreign bureaus have been closed, others have been opened. Newsweek, for example, is opening a New Delhi bureau this month, though it may close its Nairobi, Kenya, bureau as a result.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zuckerman said U.S. News had scaled back its staff coverage somewhat in favor of a more extensive network of freelancers. ''Given everything that's happened, including CNN, where you can get direct coverage, you don't need as many bureaus as you used to,'' Mr. Zuckerman said. He said this was true domestically, as well.</p>
        <p>But James Fallows, the new editor of U.S. News, has extensive experience in Asia and is expected to beef up foreign coverage. ''In an age where information in general is getting cheaper, the cost of foreign bureaus is going up,'' Mr. Fallows said. ''So I think there is a long-term inevitable decline in the foreign bureau presence, and our challenge is to find ways to more shrewdly interpret and explain the impact of foreign events on our readers lives.''</p>
        <p>Michael Elliot, the editor of Newsweek's international editions, said: ''Increasingly, what I say to all my writers and editors is, the ties that bind the international community are economics and business, science and technology and culture and life style. You can't just kind of wave your magic wand and pretend that the striped-pants diplomats' news is as interesting as it was during the cold war because it plainly isn't.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 26, 1996, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Monday about international coverage by news magazines misspelled the surname of the editor of The Economist. He is Bill Emmott, not Hammett.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 26, 1996, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Monday about international coverage by news magazines misspelled the surname of the editor of The Economist. He is Bill Emmott, not Hammett.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
