<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Traverse City Journal;Utility Customers Put a Premium on Wind Energy</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="864167"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINDMILLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIND</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TRAVERSE CITY (MICH)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRAVERSE CITY LIGHT AND POWER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAUTNER, TERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DE1E39F930A25754C0A960958260" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Traverse City Journal;Utility Customers Put a Premium on Wind Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH SCHNEIDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHNEIDER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>TRAVERSE CITY, Mich., July 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This time of year, the fields on the high bluff west of Traverse City begin to yield all sorts of crops: cherries, peaches, cucumbers and corn. Seven weeks  ago, though, Terry Lautner's alfalfa field sprouted something the neighbors are  still talking about: a giant windmill to generate electricity.</p>
        <p>But it is not just the windmill's enormous spinning blades or its prodigious  size -- it is the nation's largest -- that has people in this upper Great Lakes  community buzzing. It is also how it was financed. Traverse City Light and Power, a city-owned utility, readily persuaded 145 families and 20 businesses to agree to pay 20 percent more for their electricity -- an average of $7.58 a month -- to gain a clean source of energy. It is the first time, energy industry experts say, that an electric windmill has been built in the United States by charging utility customers a premium, or green, rate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This time of year, the fields on the high bluff west of Traverse City begin to yield all sorts of crops: cherries, peaches, cucumbers and corn. Seven weeks  ago, though, Terry Lautner's alfalfa field sprouted something the neighbors are  still talking about: a giant windmill to generate electricity.</p>
        <p>But it is not just the windmill's enormous spinning blades or its prodigious  size -- it is the nation's largest -- that has people in this upper Great Lakes  community buzzing. It is also how it was financed. Traverse City Light and Power, a city-owned utility, readily persuaded 145 families and 20 businesses to agree to pay 20 percent more for their electricity -- an average of $7.58 a month -- to gain a clean source of energy. It is the first time, energy industry experts say, that an electric windmill has been built in the United States by charging utility customers a premium, or green, rate.</p>
        <p>I've always been interested in tapping the wind energy in that field," said Mr. Lautner, a 39-year-old dairy farmer whose family has tilled the fields here  since 1865. "It's real neat. I became so interested I killed a day watching them put it up when I should have been planting corn."</p>
        <p>If there is a place where some people would gladly pay a little more for a cleaner source of power, it is here in northwestern Michigan. While the Traverse region is politically conservative, it is also developing a reputation as one of the most innovative areas in the Great Lakes basin for trying ideas that join environmental and economic goals.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, for example, residents of nearby Old Mission Peninsula voted to increase their property taxes to raise at least $2.6 million. That extra revenue, generated in the teeth of national anti-tax sentiment, is being used to protect thousands of acres of scenic orchards and cultivated fields by paying farmers not to develop their land.</p>
        <p>"It really wasn't hard to attract customers to the program," said Steven B. Smiley, an energy economist here who guided the windmill project. "We wrote a letter to all of Traverse City Light and Power's customers in June 1994 and told them it would cost a little more each month to put up a windmill. Within a few weeks, we had more customers than we ended up needing."</p>
        <p>There was a brief period, in the late 1970's and early 80's, when wind power  seemed to be a promising alternative to conventional power sources like oil. Under the Carter Administration, tax credits were established to encourage innovators. The Reagan Administration ended the Federal tax credit in 1985, and  the domestic industry began to decline.</p>
        <p>The snow-white machine here, erected at a cost of $670,000, is a Danish-built Vestas V-44 600. Its rotors are 144 feet long and spin at 28 revolutions per minute, fast enough for the blades to slice through the air at 145 m.p.h.</p>
        <p>The bluff where the machine stands is buffeted by winds from Lake Michigan that average 14.5 m.p.h. The utility expects that its windmill will generate 1.2 million kilowatt hours of electricity a year, roughly what is needed to supply 200 homes in Traverse City.</p>
        <p>The windmill, which turns with a gentle whoosh like the sound of the summer breeze in a screen, is a monument to the vision and perseverance of Mr. Smiley,  who first introduced the idea to local utility executives in 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smiley said that at a cost of 7 cents a kilowatt hour, the windmill produces the lowest-priced electricity of just about any new power source. But it cannot compete with coal-fired power plants whose costs have been amortized over decades.</p>
        <p>As a result, Traverse City Light and Power produces and buys electricity for  less than 3 cents a kilowatt hour. The utility's executives assured Mr. Smiley that they would support a windmill if he could come up with a means for making up the difference. So he did.</p>
        <p>As part of its energy policy, the Bush Administration enacted a tax credit in the early 1990's that is now worth 1.6 cents a kilowatt hour. At Mr. Smiley's urging, the Michigan Public Utility Commission awarded Traverse City Light and Power a $50,000 grant. Mr. Smiley calculated that customers interested in supporting the windmill would have to pay 1.58 cents more per kilowatt hour. Some 263 of the utility's more than 8,000 customers signed green rate contracts; 80 are on a waiting list.</p>
        <p>Ever since the windmill went up over Memorial Day weekend, the utility and Mr. Smiley have been receiving fan mail from across the country. Randy Udall, director of the Community Office for Resource Efficiency, a nonprofit advocacy group in Aspen, Colo., sent one of Mr. Smiley's favorites.</p>
        <p>"Traverse City, we salute you," Mr. Udall wrote. "Taking energy decisions into your own hands. Putting money where your heart is. Cleaning the air. Saving fossil fuels for our grandkids. Why, that's almost un-American."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
