<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Climate Report Was Improperly Altered, Overplaying Human Role,Critics Say</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="858507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960617T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DC1439F934A25755C0A960958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Climate Report Was Improperly Altered, Overplaying Human Role,Critics Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former president of the National Academy of Sciences has joined an industry lobbying group in contending that unauthorized alterations were made in a crucial chapter of a recently published United Nations scientific report on climate change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former president of the National Academy of Sciences has joined an industry lobbying group in contending that unauthorized alterations were made in a crucial chapter of a recently published United Nations scientific report on climate change.</p>
        <p>The chapter dealt with the detection of human impact on the climate and was the basis for the United Nations scientific panel's conclusion, stated for the first time, that "the balance of evidence suggests that there is a discernible human influence on global climate."</p>
        <p>The critics contend that by making changes in the chapter after it was accepted last November by representatives of 96 countries meeting in Madrid, important members of the panel acted improperly. Those responsible for the report acknowledge that changes were made. But they say that far from being unauthorized, the changes were made in response to comments by scientists at the Madrid meeting and before then and that the chapter in question was accepted by  the meeting's 177 delegates on the condition that the changes be made.</p>
        <p>The critics say the revision removed several passages, including this one: "None of the studies cited above has shown clear evidence that we can attribute  the observed changes to the specific cause of increases in greenhouse gases."</p>
        <p>The defenders of the process say that the omitted sentences involved nuances  about the degree of certainty that could be expressed and that none of them affected the report's basic conclusion about the human role in climate change. The conclusion was included in a summary for governmental policy makers that was approved line by line in Madrid. The summary remains unchanged, as does a similar conclusion in the underlying scientific chapter.</p>
        <p>But the critics say that the alterations nevertheless underplay scientific uncertainties, and they call into question the integrity of the panel.</p>
        <p>"I have never witnessed a more disturbing corruption of the peer review process," Dr. Frederick Seitz, who was president of the National Academy of Sciences in the 1960's, wrote in an op-ed article addressing the deletions, which was published on Wednesday in The Wall Street Journal. Dr. Seitz, president emeritus of Rockefeller University, is the chairman of the George C. Marshall Institute, a privately financed research group based in Washington that has criticized the view that humans are causing the climate to change significantly. Peer review is the process scientists use to test and critique one another's work.</p>
        <p>The Global Climate Coalition, a Washington-based lobbying group that represents the fossil-fuel industry, contends in a monograph that has been widely circulated in political and scientific circles that the changes constitute a "scientific cleansing" aimed at suppressing evidence that would support those skeptical of the greenhouse theory.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile,, an opposing view of Dr. Seitz's article held that it "just hasn't any basis in fact at all." And the lobbying group's contentions are "just rubbish," said Dr. John Houghton, a Briton who is a co-chairman of the working group that prepared the scientific report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, which is being published by Cambridge University Press.</p>
        <p>All the accusations, Dr. Houghton said, are based on a draft, dated last Oct. 9, of the report's chapter on the detection of human-induced climate change. Before and during the Madrid meeting in late November, he said, many comments on the draft and many suggestions for changes were received by the chapter's designated leading author, Dr. Benjamin D. Santer of the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California. In effect, Dr. Houghton said that these exchanges constituted the final stage of peer review for the chapter.</p>
        <p>Dr. Santer said he had revised the chapter immediately after the Madrid meeting to take account of all the comments received, and Dr. Houghton said the  final version was "entirely faithful to what the group asked for."</p>
        <p>Both Dr. Santer and Dr. Houghton said they had never been approached by either Dr. Seitz or the Global Climate Coalition for an explanation.</p>
        <p>When Dr. Seitz was told of Dr. Houghton's explanation for the changes in the  controversial chapter, he said in an interview that he did not accept it -- "heavens, no" -- and said he suspected that the chapter had been "arbitrarily modified" for "public purposes." Both Dr. Seitz and the Global Climate Coalition argue that the net effect of the changes works in the direction of blunting skepticism about global warming.</p>
        <p>Dr. Santer sharply disputes these points. "None of the changes were politically motivated," he said. In fact, he said, he had long argued for a more extensive treatment of uncertainties in the chapter. He noted that more than four pages of the revised chapter were devoted entirely to uncertainties, while  other references to uncertainties pepper the rest of the chapter.</p>
        <p>The purpose of the disputed chapter was to summarize and assess the state of  knowledge about the detection of the role of people in climate change through an examination of the scientific literature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
