<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deep Jet-Stream Shifts Made the Blizzard Possible</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="821333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE BLIZZARD OF 1996: THE CAUSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SNOW AND SNOWSTORMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDB1339F93BA35752C0A960958260" item-length="463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deep Jet-Stream Shifts Made the Blizzard Possible</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENS, WILLIAM K</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The stage for yesterday's blizzard was set, in part, by large-scale changes in atmospheric circulation that have made it easier for masses of Arctic air to  burst out of Canada and invade the eastern United States.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, the pool of cold air that covers the northern polar regions has expanded abnormally, pushing the transcontinental jet stream farther south. The jet stream, a high-altitude, eastward-flowing river of air that girdles the Northern Hemisphere, is the boundary between the Arctic air and warmer southern air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The stage for yesterday's blizzard was set, in part, by large-scale changes in atmospheric circulation that have made it easier for masses of Arctic air to  burst out of Canada and invade the eastern United States.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, the pool of cold air that covers the northern polar regions has expanded abnormally, pushing the transcontinental jet stream farther south. The jet stream, a high-altitude, eastward-flowing river of air that girdles the Northern Hemisphere, is the boundary between the Arctic air and warmer southern air.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the predominant wintertime course of the jet stream across North  America has shifted from a relatively straight west-to-east path. Now, its course is curvier, often dipping far down into the Southeast, then turning northward into the Middle Atlantic states and Northeast, creating a southward bulge that fills with frigid air.</p>
        <p>The combined effect of these two shifts has made it more likely that Arctic cold will invade the Northeast, as it has the last few days, said Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist with the Pennsylvania State University Weather Communications Group.</p>
        <p>Any precipitation encountering such cold air is certain to fall as snow rather than rain, as it did this weekend in the Middle Atlantic and Northeastern states. "These storms are essentially a tussle between very cold Arctic air and  a storm system driving warm, moist air into it," Mr. Gadomski said.</p>
        <p>Government scientists say they have found that more precipitation is falling  in extremely heavy one-day events than was true 20 years ago, and they are 90 to 95 percent sure that the change has resulted from the effects of the heat-trapping gases released by the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's heavy snowfall qualified as one such extreme event and was "not totally unexpected," said Thomas R. Karl of the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C., the chief author of the Government study.</p>
        <p>Last year, the average surface temperature of the earth reached a record high, and scientists say it is likely that the emissions of heat-trapping gases  are at least partly responsible. The amount of warming so far is not enough to override the generation of extreme Arctic cold, Mr. Karl said. But some scientists say it may be enough to infuse the atmosphere with more moisture and  energy, contributing to more extreme weather.</p>
        <p>Yesterday's storm was unusual in that the heaviest snow fell squarely along the densely populated Washington-New York axis rather than farther inland. Why?  The luck of the draw oriented the edge of the Arctic air mass in a southwest-to-northeast position "right over the megalopolis," Mr. Gadomski said.</p>
        <p>THE BLIZZARD OF 1996: THE CAUSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
