<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harnessing the Sun And Selling It Abroad;U.S. Solar Industry in Export Boom</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="855484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOLAR ENERGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRODUCTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDONESIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRAZIL</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ENERGY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HALPERT, JULIE EDELSON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E0D91F39F936A35755C0A960958260" item-length="1765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harnessing the Sun And Selling It Abroad;U.S. Solar Industry in Export Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE EDELSON HALPERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HALPERT, JULIE EDELSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jolted by the oil embargoes of the 1970's, the Federal Government has been awarding research grants to develop solar power ever since. Twenty years and $1.4 billion in taxpayer money later, solar power is still not much more than a  dim light bulb in the nation's energy constellation.</p>
        <p>But the investment is paying off anyway -- in a thriving export business that is proving, as solar proponents insisted all along, that "small is beautiful."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jolted by the oil embargoes of the 1970's, the Federal Government has been awarding research grants to develop solar power ever since. Twenty years and $1.4 billion in taxpayer money later, solar power is still not much more than a  dim light bulb in the nation's energy constellation.</p>
        <p>But the investment is paying off anyway -- in a thriving export business that is proving, as solar proponents insisted all along, that "small is beautiful."</p>
        <p>From India and Indonesia to Mexico and Brazil, solar panels made in America  are sprouting on thousands of rooftops, lighting up jungles, deserts and other hard-to-wire areas of the developing world that have never been connected to conventional power grids -- and are not likely to be any time soon. The panels are also bringing communication links, powering up cellular phones as a wireless substitute for an installed infrastructure.</p>
        <p>Mostly, these solar investments are indeed small, at $400 to $600 a house. But they add up quickly because the projects can encompass whole villages at a time. What's more, in areas that have transmission grids, huge solar plants are  being designed by American companies to provide supplemental power to thousands  of homes at a time, and without adding to pollution.</p>
        <p>All this means big business at last for the dozens of small and mid-sized companies that make solar equipment in the United States. The companies, including Astro Power, Solec International and Solarex, are pulling in $300 million a year, or 30 percent of the worldwide market, making the United States  the biggest center of solar manufacturing, eclipsing Japan, Britain, Italy and other major players.</p>
        <p>To meet the growing demand -- the Energy Department predicts global sales will jump by 70 percent over the next five years -- companies here are adding plants and workers in a mad scramble that is expected to double their manufacturing capacity by the end of next year, from 1995 levels. They now export 70 percent of their products, up from 50 percent three years ago.</p>
        <p>"It's a bullish market and there's a lot of money to be made," said Christine Ervin, who runs the Energy Department's renewable energy program.</p>
        <p>The export market is strong enough now that it is drawing the interest of American utilities, which see solar demand abroad as a new source of revenue, with them serving as suppliers and consultants.</p>
        <p>And as manufacturing costs continue to come down, some energy experts expect  solar power to show new signs of life even at home.</p>
        <p>The cost to the consumer has already been cut in half in the last 10 years, the experts say, with the typical residential installation in the United States  now running between $18,000 and $20,000. When the price gets down to about $6,000, the initial outlay and financing expenses will become competitive with the monthly cost of traditional sources of power, according to Lisa Frantzis, a  senior consultant for renewable energy technologies at Arthur D. Little in Cambridge, Mass. That could happen in about 10 years, she added.</p>
        <p>To be sure, no one expects solar to fully replace any mainstream source of power in the United States -- for one thing, there just isn't enough sun to go around in many parts of the country. Solar now accounts for less than one tenth  of 1 percent of energy use nationally. And if all the solar panels made last year in American factories were somehow wired together, they would produce just  35 megawatts of power, only enough to meet the needs of a community of 35,000 people.</p>
        <p>Still, with the growing interest worldwide, the activity here is getting feverish.</p>
        <p>"We have more demand than we can handle," said Allen Barnett, president of Astro Power Inc. Based in Newark, Del., the company was a tiny start-up 10 years ago. Now it has 145 employees and annual revenues exceeding $10 million, 80 percent from exports.</p>
        <p>What is driving the solar boom is the sheer size of the potential foreign market: about one-third of the world's population, or two billion people, live without electricity.</p>
        <p>Interest in solar energy has surged because of the growing realization that this huge gap can not be closed with conventional power sources, said Charles Feinstein, a senior environmental specialist at the World Bank.</p>
        <p>Diesel generators, once considered the leading contender, often break down and fuel supplies are limited. Many people rely instead on smoky kerosene lamps  or car batteries that frequently need recharging.</p>
        <p>Power from the sun, an abundant resource in much of the developing world, is  an attractive alternative because one solar panel installed on a house can power two light bulbs, a television and a radio. The panels contain photovoltaic "cells," made from semiconductor materials, that convert light to electricity.</p>
        <p>"While the electric company would need to arrive with a lot of equipment, our company can arrive on a motorcycle or a donkey with a solar panel and other components very easily," said Ramon Soto, who runs an energy services company in the Dominican Republic. What's more, a solar system is virtually maintenance free.</p>
        <p>These days, India is the biggest foreign market, having committed $400 million to solar power over a five-year period ending in 1997. In addition, the  World Bank is providing $55 million in loans to bring solar power to 50,000 homes and many commercial buildings in the country.</p>
        <p>Harish H. Hande, who manages the Solar Electric Light Company in Mangalore, India, says up to 40 percent of the people in rural areas have the means to buy  the $500 systems themselves. That is a potential market of 240 million people, "a huge number, equal to the population of Europe," Mr. Hande said.</p>
        <p>Other big foreign markets are Mexico, Kenya, Indonesia and Brazil. Those with big potential are China, Vietnam and South Africa, industry experts say.</p>
        <p>In cranking up their export production, solar companies in the United States  are hoping to achieve new economies of scale to drive prices down significantly. The panels they make, which range in size from less than 1 watt of generating capacity to 300 or more watts, now cost about $4.50 a watt at the retail level.</p>
        <p>Stan Ovshinsky, president and chief executive of Energy Conversion Devices, has developed a manufacturing process at his new factory in Troy, Mich., that he said could send the price for his panels down to $1 a watt in three years.</p>
        <p>That price "will drive explosive demand, not just in the developing world, but everywhere," said Eric Ingersoll, a managing partner with Environmental Advantage, a consulting firm in New York that studies the renewable-energy industries.</p>
        <p>The existing demand has not exactly been lackluster.</p>
        <p>Solec International Inc., the country's third-largest solar manufacturer, has more than doubled its work force, to 130, over the last three years.</p>
        <p>"We don't even advertise and people visit us every day from foreign countries," said Joel Davidson, director of systems engineering for the company, which is based in Hawthorne, Calif., and is controlled by two large Japanese shareholders, the Sanyo Electric Company and the Sumitomo Corporation. Like Astro Power, Solec's revenues last year exceeded $10 million, and Mr. Davidson expects they will increase by 30 percent this year, with much of the gain coming from India.</p>
        <p>The world's largest solar company is Siemens Solar, owned by the German company Siemens A.G. but with much of its operation in the United States. It produces half of this country's panel supply, exporting 70 percent of the output from its factories in Camarillo, Calif., and Vancouver, Wash.</p>
        <p>Some of the larger manufacturers are planning enormous full-scale solar plants. The largest American-owned player is Solarex, a joint venture of two conventional energy giants -- the Amoco Corporation and the Enron Corporation. Solarex has set its sights on becoming the world's fastest-growing solar company by proposing full-scale plants. In the planning stages is a $100 million, 50-megawatt plant in Rajasthan, India, that could power 200,000 homes.</p>
        <p>"There will be a big field in the desert full of these modules," the industry term for solar panels, said Bob Kelly, chief executive of Amoco/ Enron Solar Power Development, the sister company of Solarex that handles marketing.</p>
        <p>Solarex is scheduled to open a $25 million factory outside Williamsburg, Va., next year and, by 1999, triple its capacity in its existing factory in Frederick, Md., where the company is based.</p>
        <p>Tom Cross, director of First National Battery in Johannesburg, said his company had already spent $1.5 million this year on Solarex panels for rural electrification. "It's quite remarkable the rate at which U.S. companies are coming in," he said.</p>
        <p>As domestic companies invest to meet foreign demand, niche applications of solar power are growing at home.</p>
        <p>One domestic showcase will be at the Olympics this summer in Atlanta, where the swimming and diving competitions will be held under the world's largest solar rooftop, which will provide power for the 10,000-seat arena. Solarex is supplying the panels for the $6 million project.</p>
        <p>More typically, though, solar is used to avoid digging up the ground to install electrical lines. It now powers everything from billboards and highway emergency phones to homes far from the electric grid.</p>
        <p>As utilities gear up for a big solar role abroad, they are using their domestic markets to gain experience.  Southern California Edison, a unit of SCEcorp for example, has a local program that allows residents without conventional electricity to pay the $500 up-front cost plus a monthly charge to have the company install a solar system. At the end of 15 years, the customer owns the system outright.</p>
        <p>With all the new demand, solar companies are trying not to overestimate the surge in their market. While in an expansion mode, Solarex, for one, is being cautious, said its president, Harvey Forest.</p>
        <p>"We don't want projects," he said, "that will be here today and gone tomorrow."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
