<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Track Trials Raise a Host of Questions</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="858792"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ATLANTA 1996: 30 DAYS TO GO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1996)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTA (GA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTA, GA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LONGMAN, JERE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAYNE, BILLY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1D81439F93AA25755C0A960958260" item-length="1027" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Track Trials Raise a Host of Questions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LONGMAN, JERE</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Summer Olympics begin a month from Wednesday, but the anticipation and excitement are tempered by continuing questions about Atlanta's preparedness to  host the centennial Games.</p>
        <p>While major construction is completed, and the chief organizer, Billy Payne,  continues to insist that preparations are "on time and on budget," the ongoing United States track and field trials have raised important concerns about the heat, drug testing, transportation and technology.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Summer Olympics begin a month from Wednesday, but the anticipation and excitement are tempered by continuing questions about Atlanta's preparedness to  host the centennial Games.</p>
        <p>While major construction is completed, and the chief organizer, Billy Payne,  continues to insist that preparations are "on time and on budget," the ongoing United States track and field trials have raised important concerns about the heat, drug testing, transportation and technology.</p>
        <p>And despite the $1.7 billion price tag these Olympics carry, visitors may be struck by a curious lack of grandeur. Compared with previous Olympics, there is  a distinct bargain-basement feel to the Olympic Stadium and the entire Games, a  sense of impermanence that a coat of paint, the hanging of bunting and the planting of trees and shrubs may not be able to camouflage.</p>
        <p>For his part, Payne, who turned an improbable dream into the reality of Atlanta's playing host to the Olympics, continues with unflagging optimism to say that the Games will be the most successful ever.</p>
        <p>While acknowledging that downtown streets must be paved, sidewalks must be cemented and some $150 million must be raised, Payne said today at a news conference, "We're sitting where we want to be."</p>
        <p>"It's gone from nervousness and fatigue to excitement," Payne said.</p>
        <p>Still, there are more than a few kinks to be worked out.</p>
        <p>Some athletes have complained that while other stadiums have an adjacent warm-up track, the Olympic Stadium warm-up track is a half-mile away. Athletes must leave the heat of the warm-up track, spend 10 minutes in an air-conditioned bus to the stadium, then return to the heat. Some have said they feel this climate change is partly responsible for the number of muscle cramps that have occurred during the trials.</p>
        <p>"Since they built the stadium from the ground up and they were tearing down houses all over the place, you'd think they would find a few more to tear down and build a practice track," said Carl Lewis, the winner of eight Olympic gold medals.</p>
        <p>Payne said that organizers thought it was inappropriate to displace families  living near the stadium or on land that had been set aside for redevelopment to  build a practice track.</p>
        <p>"We're dealing with issues of choice," Payne said, adding that neither "Mr. Lewis nor any of the athletes live in, grew up in or have equity in" the neighborhoods surrounding the stadium.</p>
        <p>Bob Kersee, the coach and husband of the three-time Olympic champion Jackie Joyner-Kersee, said that it was "ridiculous" for athletes to be spending long periods exposed to the sun and 100-plus-degree temperatures on the track in the  Olympic Stadium without any protective shelter. Payne and other Olympic organizers said that shelters for both athletes and spectators would be made available during the Games, along with an increased number of misting devices that will be placed at outdoor arenas such as track and field and field hockey.</p>
        <p>"No athlete will be denied the ability to hydrate himself immediately," Payne said.</p>
        <p>The awkward bus system at the track trials raises questions about the vast transportation plan designed to accommodate 2 million visitors for the Games.</p>
        <p>During the Olympics, traffic will essentially be banned downtown. Spectators  will park at perimeter lots and be bused to the various competitions.</p>
        <p>Track athletes said that a 5- or 10-minute taxi ride between a downtown hotel and the Olympic Stadium is taking 20 minutes to an hour on a bus during the Olympic trials.</p>
        <p>Payne said the routing from the athletes' village will be more direct during  the Games.</p>
        <p>Transportation is a huge concern of organizers because it is the one system that cannot be simulated before the Olympics begin.</p>
        <p>"The transportation key is the extent to which our own residents will comply  with the plan," Payne said.</p>
        <p>Other areas still to be worked out include technological bugs in the results  system at the Olympic Stadium. Glitches in the Swatch timing, I.B.M. computers and Xerox copying systems have held up the distribution of results at the track  trials for up to an hour and a half for some events.</p>
        <p>"They have to get it right sometime, and it might as well be now," said Pete  Cava, a spokesman for the United States track and field federation.</p>
        <p>The Olympic drug testing lab has not yet been accredited by the International Olympic Committee, so tests at the track trials are being conducted by the lab at U.C.L.A. Accreditation is expected later this month. However, some officials  wonder whether the lab's inexperience will leave it vulnerable to arbitration appeals by athletes who test positive during the Games.</p>
        <p>"We believe the lab will be tested and up and running and will be supportable legally and otherwise," Payne said.</p>
        <p>Organizers are also faced with trying to demonstrate that a privately financed Olympics does not mean these Games must have a bargain-basement feel. The $230 million Olympic Stadium will be converted into a smaller baseball stadium after the Games. However, designers spent so much effort trying to reproduce ball parks of old that the Olympic Stadium has no distinguishing features of its own. The Olympic cauldron is so unremarkable that it appears to  be the Olympic thimble.</p>
        <p>And the temporary structures being erected downtown as gathering places for business clients and spectators, with their gaudily displayed corporate logos, may give visitors the feeling that Atlanta is playing host to a trade show instead of the Summer Olympics.</p>
        <p>"You ain't seen nothing yet," said Payne, who added that the city will undergo a dramatic face lift in the coming weeks that will "take it forever out  of the classification as, quote, ordinary."</p>
        <p>ATLANTA 1996: 30 DAYS TO GO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
