<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Research Yields Underused Source of Food in Africa: Grains</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Environment Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="845634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRAIN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AGRICULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SORGHUM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEF (GRAIN)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILLET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FONIO(GRAIN)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARKETING AND MERCHANDISING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL RESEARCH COUNCIL</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2DA1F39F930A15757C0A960958260" item-length="1276" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Research Yields Underused Source of Food in Africa: Grains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUB-SAHARAN Africa often evokes images of famine, drought, starvation and malnutrition. Yet, researchers say, this area is the home of more than 2,000 grains, vegetables, roots, fruits and other foods that potentially could feed the continent and even other parts of the world.</p>
        <p>Africa, which seems to face a perpetual food crisis, is full of overlooked and underdeveloped food plants that are not being fully exploited in the fight against hunger, according to a recent report by the National Research Council, an arm of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUB-SAHARAN Africa often evokes images of famine, drought, starvation and malnutrition. Yet, researchers say, this area is the home of more than 2,000 grains, vegetables, roots, fruits and other foods that potentially could feed the continent and even other parts of the world.</p>
        <p>Africa, which seems to face a perpetual food crisis, is full of overlooked and underdeveloped food plants that are not being fully exploited in the fight against hunger, according to a recent report by the National Research Council, an arm of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>In the first of a planned series of reports titled "Lost Crops of Africa," an expert panel examining grains said Africa has more indigenous varieties of cereals than any other continent, including its own species of rice, millet, sorghum and several dozen more. Forthcoming studies are expected to focus on the promise of native fruits, vegetables, legumes and other foods.</p>
        <p>"This is a good heritage that has fed people for generation after generation  stretching back to the origins of mankind," the report said. "But, strangely, it has largely been bypassed in modern times."</p>
        <p>Even though local grains nourish millions of Africans, they have lost out in  popularity to such imports as wheat, rice and maize, the report said, and only a few receive concerted research, development and marketing support to improve their quality and expand their use.</p>
        <p>These grains and other native foods are considered "lost" not because they are unknown, the report said, but because they are given little or no attention  by the mainstream of international agricultural science and are often even ignored by Africans outside certain regions where they are native.</p>
        <p>During Africa's colonial era, European authorities, missionaries and researchers judged unfamiliar native grains inferior to foreign cereals such as  wheat and corn, experts said. The imported grains, made convenient and attractive by modern milling, processing and packaging, also became the favorites of Africans. Over time, they said, the old grains languished and took  on the stigma of being second-rate food for the poor or subsistence rations for  hard times.</p>
        <p>"Africa is called 'the hungry continent,' yet it is a cornucopia of food plants people are not taking advantage of," said Dr. Noel D. Vietmeyer, the staff director for the report.</p>
        <p>Studying and improving Africa's native grains should become an international  priority, the report said. Not only would this open up a new front in battling Africa's food shortages, it said, but it could provide the world with new sources of food amid concerns about global warming and climate change, and the Earth's rapidly growing population.</p>
        <p>African grains tend to be hardy, less dependent upon large amounts of water or irrigation, and more heat and drought tolerant than other major cereals, experts says.</p>
        <p>"For the future, such resilient crops will be vital for extending cereal production onto the ever-more-marginal lands that will have to be pressed into service to feed the several billion new arrivals," the report said.</p>
        <p>The report spotlighted a half dozen African grains that are likely to become  crucial in feeding the more than 40 nations of that continent and others elsewhere. While a couple of the cereals have already registered some success through development, it said, the potential of others is virtually untapped.</p>
        <p>Among the grains highlighted in the report were these:</p>
        <p>Pearl millet. Domesticated from a wild grass of the southern Sahara 4,000 years ago, pearl millet tolerates heat and drought better than other major cereals. The tall, top-heavy plants are relatively low yielding compared to some other grains, but are disease-resistant and grow in sandy soils under arid conditions. The world's sixth-largest cereal crop, pearl millet's use in the United States as an animal feed has been growing, and researchers in Georgia, Nebraska and Kansas have developed short varieties that can be harvested by machines designed to bring in wheat and other crops.</p>
        <p>Fonio. This West African grain is probably the world's fastest maturing cereal, but is grown primarily on small farms for home consumption. The plant, which does well in poor, sandy soils, is unusually high in several amino acids and nutrients and has a reputation as one of the world's best-tasting grains. Despite its potential, fonio has drawn little attention from agricultural researchers.</p>
        <p>African rice. Although many people think of rice as an exclusively Asian crop, farmers have grown this native variety in West Africa for at least 1,500 years. The grain comes in several types, some of which mature very quickly for multiple plantings, and some researchers believe its genetic characteristics might be transferred to other rice to benefit production worldwide. The grain is much like common rice in flavor, but most varieties have a red husk.</p>
        <p>Sorghum. Although this grain has spread from Africa to become a staple of more than 500 million people in 30 nations, it is relatively undeveloped. Sorghum thrives on marginal sites where other grains fail and has become a principal animal feed in the United States. Researchers say they have produced new varieties that make high-quality white flour.</p>
        <p>Tef. This staple cereal of Ethiopia is ground into flour and used to make the flat, fermented bread called injera that sustains millions of people. The grain  is rich in protein and iron, and well-balanced in amino acids, but research on it has been scant.</p>
        <p>The potential of tef outside Africa can already be seen in the United States, said Wayne Carlson of Caldwell, Idaho. Mr. Carlson became aware of the grain while working as a biologist in Ethiopia 20 years ago and returned to start growing tef in a harsh, dry valley on the Idaho-Oregon border. Now he has hundreds of acres under cultivation with several varieties of tef, which he sells to a growing market of natural-food markets and Ethiopian restaurants nationwide. His operation, now called the Tef Company, began by marketing the grain to the tens of thousands of Ethiopian immigrants in this country, he said.</p>
        <p>"We are trying to develop tef into a real commodity that people pay real money for," Mr. Carlson said. "I see it as a valuable crop even for areas outside of Africa, and the best way to perpetuate it outside its home territory is to establish new markets so it can pay its own way."</p>
        <p>Dr. John M. Yohe of the University of Nebraska at Lincoln said pearl millet could become the next African grain to find widespread success in this country.  A program sponsored by the United States Agency for International Development that teams researchers at American universities with counterparts in Africa has  led to improved varieties of sorghum and millet, he said.</p>
        <p>As underground water supplies used for irrigation in the Midwest are depleted, Dr. Yohe said, millions of acres of sandy soils in western Kansas and  Nebraska may remain productive only by using crops, such as pearl millet, that can grow on rainfall alone. "Pearl millet is naturally a high-value crop, higher in protein and oil content even than corn, but a lot of research hasn't been done on it," he said. "Its initial potential here is for chicken feed, but as we learn more about it, it could end up finding a role in human food products in this country."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
