<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tucson</title>
    <meta content="WDTUCSON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="WHAT'S DOING IN" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="WHAT'S DOING IN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tucson (Ariz)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Judith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Tucson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EEDD1E30F930A35752C1A960958260" item-length="2015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tucson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Judith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judith Anderson What's Doing In article on Tucson, Ariz; table; map; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For many Tucsonans, fall is the best season, the period when they again start referring to sun-drenched days as luminous rather than blistering or lethal. It's especially welcome this year, after temperatures hovered near 100 degrees well into October. Fall is a season of clarity here, a good time to be outdoors really looking at the city and its surroundings. Oddity strikes the eye. Even the natural icons of the region -- such as the unlikely-looking saguaro cactus or the dumpy, spindly legged javalina -- could have been designed by Dr. Seuss.</p>
        <p>But odd is good in Tucson. One of the oldest continuously inhabited settlements in the New World, the city is a palimpsest. It is in the old neighborhoods, the barrios clustered in the south and west quarters of town, that random bits of Indian, Hispanic and early black and Anglo cultures bleed through. It's worth spending some time in those areas, not as a tourist but just going about the course of daily life -- shopping or eating or just moving along.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For many Tucsonans, fall is the best season, the period when they again start referring to sun-drenched days as luminous rather than blistering or lethal. It's especially welcome this year, after temperatures hovered near 100 degrees well into October. Fall is a season of clarity here, a good time to be outdoors really looking at the city and its surroundings. Oddity strikes the eye. Even the natural icons of the region -- such as the unlikely-looking saguaro cactus or the dumpy, spindly legged javalina -- could have been designed by Dr. Seuss.</p>
        <p>But odd is good in Tucson. One of the oldest continuously inhabited settlements in the New World, the city is a palimpsest. It is in the old neighborhoods, the barrios clustered in the south and west quarters of town, that random bits of Indian, Hispanic and early black and Anglo cultures bleed through. It's worth spending some time in those areas, not as a tourist but just going about the course of daily life -- shopping or eating or just moving along.</p>
        <p>Lately, sunset at Gates Pass is becoming a local happening. This is not Key West -- no one actually applauds the sun as it disappears -- but at the scenic overlook off Gates Pass Road, senior citizens jockey to get the two shaded picnic tables as bicyclists, hikers, trail runners and residents with out-of-town guests gather to gaze at the views: the Tucson Mountains, Avra Valley, the Sonoran Desert and, of course, the sunset, which is frequently stupendous. Gates Pass is about eight miles west of Interstate 10 via Speedway, which turns into Gates Pass Road.</p>
        <p>Events</p>
        <p>Tucson is host to some world-class sporting events every fall, such as the El Tour de Tucson cycling event on Nov. 23, one of the country's top 10 ''centuries,'' or courses of 100 miles or more. It begins at 7 A.M. at Congress Street and Granada Avenue, and the winner should cross the finish line at the same spot about four hours later. It costs nothing to watch.  Information: (520) 745-2033.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 27, two major college football teams meet in the Copper Bowl at Arizona Stadium on the University of Arizona campus, after a parade and innumerable tailgate parties. Tickets are $15 to $32. Call (800) 549-2695.</p>
        <p>Other attractions are less predictable On Nov. 24, this year's version of El Nacimiento will be unveiled at Casa Cordova, an old territorial house on the property of the Tucson Museum of Art, 140 North Main Street, (520) 624-2333. Since 1975, Maria Luisa Tena has been arranging intricate little tableaux into a wild Mexican Nativity scene that fills one side of the house. She uses more than 200 hand-painted miniatures, mixing herald angels with Day of the Dead devils and skeletons and little ducks and perfect tiny hats and vegetables. Even by folk art standards, it's offbeat. El Nacimiento will be open Monday through Saturday from 10 A.M. to 4 P.M. and Sunday from noon to 4 P.M. until March 23. There is no admission fee.</p>
        <p>Two holiday musical events capture Tucson's diversity. At 7 P.M. on Dec. 12 and 13, the Arizona Repertory Singers will perform sacred Renaissance music at Mission San Xavier del Bac. The fund-raising concert for the mission's restoration will be held under its newly refurbished silver-gilt frescoes. Suggested donation: $5. San Xavier is on the  the Tohono O'Odham reservation, 10 miles south of Tucson on I-19. Call (520) 294-2624.</p>
        <p>Fiesta Navidad, a Mexican mariachi Christmas celebration, takes place Dec. 14 at 2 and 8 P.M. at Centennial Hall, 1020 East University Boulevard; (520) 621-3341. Tickets are $8 to $23.</p>
        <p>Sightseeing</p>
        <p>Just as the world was forgetting Biosphere 2, Columbia University took over. In September 1991, eight people were air-locked into the soaring glass-and-steel geodesic structure with 38,000 other species. They supported themselves for two years on seven separate ecological zones (or biomes), including a desert and a savanna, a million-gallon ocean with living coral reefs and a rain forest with a mountain and a 90-foot waterfall. Starting Nov. 25, visitors will be able to enter Biosphere 2 themselves, at least as far as the tower that was the home for the Biosphereans. Columbia is using the biomes for research on global climate change and for public education. Kids seem to love it. Biosphere 2 is about 35 miles northeast of Tucson,  on Route 77. Open daily 9 A.M. to 5 P.M. Admission is $12.95, $10.95 for senior citizens, $6 for children 6 to 17.  Guided tours last about two and a half hours. Information: (800) 828-2462.</p>
        <p>The desert without any glass cover is on view at the Arizona-Sonora Desert Museum, 2021 North Kinney Road 14 miles west of downtown beyond Gates Pass. One of the most popular attractions in southern Arizona, it has 15 acres of desert habitat with hundreds of trees, flowers and cactuses and all the native fauna from gila monsters to hummingbirds. Open 8:30 A.M. to 5 P.M. daily; admission $8.95, ages 6 to 12 $1.75. Call (520) 883-2702.</p>
        <p>Rillito Park, 4502 North First Avenue, at River Road, (520) 293-5011, is the oldest race track in the Southwest. The first parimutuel quarter horse race was run here in 1942. A race starts every 15 minutes, on the screen or on the track under the Catalina foothills. The first race at this nonprofit track is at 1 P.M. every Saturday and Sunday through March 9 except Dec. 21 to 28. General admission is $2, clubhouse admission $3, table $20 and a TV table $30. The Center for Creative Photography, part of the University of Arizona on Olive Road just south of Speedway, (520) 621-7968, houses  70,000 original prints by 1,800 artists, including the archives of Ansel Adams, Edward Weston and W. Eugene Smith. The center's current exhibit, ''Crimes and Splendors: The Desert Cantos of Richard Misrach,'' is on view through Dec. 1. Open 11 A.M. to 5 P.M. Monday through Friday and noon to 5 P.M. on Sunday; closed on Saturday; free admission.</p>
        <p>Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Hacienda del Sol Guest Ranch, 5601 North Hacienda del Sol Road, (800) 728-6514, fax (520) 299-1501, was out in the country in the days when Clark Gable and Spencer Tracy were guests. Now it is hemmed in by pricey suburban houses, but the adobe ranch buildings have a peaceable Old West air that pervades the pool, tennis courts and nearby stables. Thirty double rooms and casitas furnished like Sonoran haciendas of the 1930's range from $125 to $150.</p>
        <p>Elysian Grove Market Bed and Breakfast Inn, 400 West Simpson Street, (520) 628-1522, used to be a grocery. In the barrio called El Hoyo (The Hole), the old adobe complex has been renovated in such a way that it can be booked as two suites ($150 a night) or four double rooms ($75). The suites have two bedrooms, private bath, living area with fireplace, kitchen and access to a shade-dappled Southwestern garden. Renting an individual room is like staying in a Tuscan pensione -- you share the bath and have the run of all the common areas. Breakfast for all guests is coffee, Mexican empanadas and fresh fruit in lime juice.</p>
        <p>Budget: The Inn at Biosphere 2, Post Office Box 689, Oracle, Ariz. b85623, (520) 896-6222, fax (520) 896-6471, is about 35 miles northeast of Tucson, on the grounds of the ecological research center. Built into a hillside, each of the 36 suites has a living area with a mini-bar and refrigerator, a private terrace and a wall of glass commanding a view of the glittering Biosphere 2 and the Catalinas and Canyon del Oro beyond. Guests have access to tennis courts, swimming pool, spa and exercise facilities. Winter rates start at $80 for a suite.</p>
        <p>At the University Inn, 950 North Stone Avenue, (520) 791-7503, fax (520) 622-5951, a double runs $39 even in the winter high season. The two-story motel and pool have little landscaping, but the 40 generic rooms are clean and convenient to downtown, the university and major access roads. Coffee and doughnuts each morning are included.</p>
        <p>Luxury: The Sheraton El Conquistador Resort, 10,000 North Oracle Road, (800) 325-3535 or (520) 544-5000, fax (520) 544-1228, occupies a spectacular site in the foothills of the Catalina Mountains. Swimming pools, tennis courts, golf courses and mountain-bike and horseback trails are set against high desert peaks. Decor in all 434 rooms is Santa Fe deluxe. A double costs $206 to $310. Most activities are extra.</p>
        <p>In Tucson, luxury doesn't always mean the most expensive. At the elegant old Arizona Inn, 2200 East Elm Street, (800) 933-1093, fax (520) 881-5830, ''Grand Hotel'' lives on. Guests still arrive with steamer trunks, and they're still greeted by a staff that is formal and attentive without being stuffy. In the 14 acres of lawns and gardens, there is nothing too showy or vulgar. In the coral-pink cottages, no two of the 84 rooms and suites are decorated alike. Doubles range from $134 to $175.</p>
        <p>Where to Eat</p>
        <p>Cafe Poca Cosa, 88 East Broadway, (520) 622-6400, is one of the most creative restaurants in town, in the decor and in the kitchen. Blazing red, green and purple walls set the mood. There is no regular menu. Choices chalked on the board always include the daily Plato Poca Cosa ($15) built around any three items of the chef's choosing, perhaps some shredded beef in red chile, a tortilla of fresh spinach and cheese topped with crushed pistachio and pumpkin seed tomatillo, and strips of grilled beef with prickly pear cactus and smoked jalapenos. With margaritas or wine and dessert, dinner for two averages about $40.</p>
        <p>The Olive Tree, 7000 East Tanque Verde Road, (520) 298-1845, looks utterly Southwestern but serves Greek and Mediterranean dishes. Some have been happily localized by regional ingredients, notably the inky purple black bean hummus, the pasta Mediterraneo with mushrooms and pine nuts, or the classic slow-cooked cinnamon chicken. Shade trees and blooming flowers grace the attractive outdoor dining area. A three-course dinner for two with wine runs about $60.</p>
        <p>Good, inexpensive Mexican food is everywhere. ''No lard, no can openers, no microwaves, no freezers'' boasts La Salsa Fresh Mexican Grill, 4861 East Grant Road at Swan, (520) 325-2200, a franchise knock-off of the street taquerias of Mexico City. The most expensive a la carte item is a Baja-style fish taco for $2.45: grilled mahi, cabbage, avocado and cheese on double corn tortillas with lime and Baja sauce. Combination plates add black beans, rice, salad and chips to the main dish, and most are less than $5. Selections at the spice-it-yourself salsa bar range from mild (deliciosa) to volcanic (fuego). Two can have a quick lunch for $12.</p>
        <p>Much more authentic is Tania's, 614 North Grande, (520) 622-0685, across the Santa Cruz River in Barrio Hollywood. Open at 5:30 every morning of the week, this lively eat-in or take-out storefront caters to a different Mexican tradition. After a hard night out, nothing quells dyspepsia like an old-fashioned bowl (or bucket) of menudo, a hearty hominy and tripe soup that used to be cooked in a pig's head. You can get it at Tania's by the individual serving ($2.25) or by the quart ($3.25), along with eight other soups, hot handmade flour tortillas ($2 a dozen) and various combination platters.</p>
        <p>WHAT'S DOING IN  JUDITH ANDERSON lives in Tucson.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">JUDITH ANDERSON lives in Tucson.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
