<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giant Black Diamonds Of Mysterious Origin May Hail From Space</title>
    <meta content="17DIAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diamonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Brazil</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Central African Republic</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Geophysical Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Central African Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Central African Republic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Brazil</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diamonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDC133AF934A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="1985" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giant Black Diamonds Of Mysterious Origin May Hail From Space</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some scientists suggest that carbonadoes, large black diamonds that follow none of normal rules of diamond mineralogy, originated in heat from natural radiation, asteroid impacts and exploding stars; American Geophysical Union recently held meeting on impact diamonds and carbonadoes, sharpening debate; carbonadoes, used industrially, are found mainly in Brazil and Central African Republic and are mined from stream beds; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE source of the world's largest diamonds -- black stones known as carbonadoes -- has long been a geological puzzle. Found mostly in Brazil and central Africa, the big stones follow none of the normal rules of diamond mineralogy and inhabit none of the usual haunts. For decades, their formation has baffled scientists, even as geologists have come to understand the origin of the regular diamonds that adorn rings and jewelry.</p>
        <p>Now, however, debate over the origin of carbonadoes is heating up, and some scientific sleuths say they may have solved the mystery. Among other factors, the birth of the big diamonds is laid to heat from natural radiation, asteroid impacts and exploding stars, with the factors sometimes said to work in unison to achieve the alchemy that turns plain old carbon into huge chunks of the hardest substance known.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE source of the world's largest diamonds -- black stones known as carbonadoes -- has long been a geological puzzle. Found mostly in Brazil and central Africa, the big stones follow none of the normal rules of diamond mineralogy and inhabit none of the usual haunts. For decades, their formation has baffled scientists, even as geologists have come to understand the origin of the regular diamonds that adorn rings and jewelry.</p>
        <p>Now, however, debate over the origin of carbonadoes is heating up, and some scientific sleuths say they may have solved the mystery. Among other factors, the birth of the big diamonds is laid to heat from natural radiation, asteroid impacts and exploding stars, with the factors sometimes said to work in unison to achieve the alchemy that turns plain old carbon into huge chunks of the hardest substance known.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, just perhaps, some experts say, the swarms of rocky asteroids that zip through the solar system hide carbonadoes the size of giant boulders or mountains, wholly undiscovered yet nonetheless rock-hard diamonds on an incomprehensible scale.</p>
        <p>''It's like plate tectonics before it all came together,'' Dr. Stephen E. Haggerty, a geologist at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, said in an interview, referring to the intellectual ferment. ''It's fascinating.''</p>
        <p>The American Geophysical Union, based in Washington, recently held a meeting on impact diamonds and carbonadoes, sharpening debate on the origin of the black diamonds. The organization is the world's largest professional group devoted to earth studies.</p>
        <p>Carbonadoes have been discovered up to the size of baseballs, tipping the scales in terms of superlatives.</p>
        <p>The world's largest diamond is a carbonado, said Dr. Haggerty, an expert on the black diamonds. Found in Brazil and known as Sergio, the behemoth weighs 3,167 carats, 61 carats heavier than the largest single clear diamond ever discovered, the Cullinan, which was found in 1905 in South Africa. A carat is a unit of weight, with one ounce equaling approximately 140 carats. So Sergio weighs about 1.4 pounds.</p>
        <p>The next-largest diamonds ever found in Brazil are also carbonadoes, weighing 2,000 carats, 932 carats and 828 carats.</p>
        <p>The lumps of blackish diamond are used primarily in industry for making abrasives and drill bits that tear through rock as if it were butter, often boring miles into Earth.</p>
        <p>''They're better than regular diamonds because they don't cleave,'' said Dr. Paul S. DeCarli, a carbonado expert at SRI International, in Menlo Park, Calif. ''They sheer off at the edge and only sharpen.''</p>
        <p>Unlike their cousins, which are cut into gemstones, carbonadoes are opaque and usually have a slightly porous structure that often contains various other minerals. The blackness arises mainly because the diamonds are made up of dense aggregations of individual crystals rather than the kind of single crystal that usually characterizes the translucent diamonds cut into gemstones.</p>
        <p>Carbonadoes are found chiefly in Bahia, Brazil, and in the Ubangi region of the Central African Republic. They have also been reported in lesser amounts in Australia, Russia, South Africa, Ukraine, Venezuela and Zaire.</p>
        <p>The black diamonds are usually mined from stream beds. Geologists and mineralogists usually have no idea of the exact bedrock from which they eroded, or when.</p>
        <p>Carbonadoes are usually judged to be very old, however. Rivers rich in them often cut through geological strata and sediments that are anywhere from one billion to more than two billion years old. Moreover, recent atomic measurements of the black diamonds put their genesis at up to almost four billion years ago, a time when the early Earth and Moon were hit by intense bombardments of speeding rocks from space.</p>
        <p>Carbonadoes were first recognized around 1840 in Brazil, and they got their name from the Portuguese word for burned or carbonized. A mining rush occurred from about 1850 to 1870. Starting in 1925, the black diamonds were also gathered in the Central African Republic.</p>
        <p>In the 20th century, the mining slowly ebbed as new sources of natural diamonds were found and as scientists learned how to synthesize small diamonds for industrial cutting and drilling.</p>
        <p>At first, geologists assumed that carbonadoes had been formed in a process similar to that suspected for regular diamonds. Deep in Earth's interior, roughly 100 to 300 miles down, crushing pressure and blistering heat work in unison on carbon, squeezing its atoms into the very close proximity of a crystalline lattice. After the diamonds form, they  are carried to the surface later by volcanic eruptions.</p>
        <p>This picture of carbonado formation was discredited in the 1960's and 1970's as scientists studied the mineral inclusions and carbon isotopes of the black diamonds. Isotopes are forms of the same chemical element that have differing numbers of neutrons in their atomic nuclei and thus different atomic weights.</p>
        <p>In Earth's crust, carbon comes in two main isotopes, carbon-12 and carbon-13, with the former isotope predominating by a wide margin. Regular diamonds from deep within Earth show an even stronger bias in the direction of carbon-12, with only tiny quantities of carbon-13 in evidence.</p>
        <p>The analysis of carbonadoes, however, showed that their ratios of carbon isotopes were similar to those of surface carbons, rather than ones from Earth's depths.</p>
        <p>The main stimulus to the new thinking about carbonadoes came in 1980 as Luis W. Alvarez, a Nobel laureate at the University of California, and a team of researchers proposed that a killer rock from space had hit Earth 65 million years ago, producing a global pall of dust that blocked sunlight, disrupted the climate and did in such creatures as the dinosaurs.</p>
        <p>The ensuing debate prompted many new studies that sought to dispute, modify and extend the role of cosmic collisions in the evolution of the planet's life and landscape.</p>
        <p>In 1985, Dr. Joseph V. Smith of the University of Chicago and Dr. J. Barry Dawson of the University of Sheffield in England focused the debate surrounding the impact theory on the black diamonds. ''We propose that carbonadoes were formed from carbon-rich materials by large impacts on Earth's crust in the Precambrian era,'' they wrote in the journal Geology, referring to the age, more than 570 million years ago, when life was in its first stirrings and was mainly made up of microbial plants and animals.</p>
        <p>The team pointed in particular to the isotope evidence that suggested a crustal origin for the black diamonds.</p>
        <p>Separately, other scientists around that time began to show that craters from cosmic impacts were often riddled with translucent diamonds, trillions of them, apparently made by the great heat and pressure of impact. Most of the impact diamonds were microscopic, however, with the biggest being the size of match heads or peanuts.</p>
        <p>Nothing as big as a carbonado was found in or around the impact craters that were known to dot Earth's face.</p>
        <p>The next step came in 1992. A team of three scientists, including Dr. Patrick T. Taylor, a geophysicist at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Goddard center in Greenbelt, Md., proposed that the Ubangi region of central Africa, near the Carbonado deposits there, hid the world's largest impact crater, a colossus buried deep over the eons by geological processes like erosion and sedimentation.</p>
        <p>As evidence, the team pointed to a huge magnetic anomaly in the region suggestive of a convulsive upheaval of deep rock as well as subtle elevation clues in the area's surface topography that suggested a huge crater. But many scientists were skeptical of the evidence and the interpretation.</p>
        <p>Later, other scientists noted that Africa and South America had been joined ages ago, before being cut in two by continental drift, and that a single fiery collision might account for the carbonadoes of both Brazil and the Central African Republic.</p>
        <p>In 1995, a team of five British scientists reported at a meeting of the Lunar and Planetary Institute in Houston that Brazilian and African carbonadoes have similar signatures of carbon and nitrogen isotopes, indicating a common origin. Moreover, the team said, some of the carbonadoes had a surface rind suggestive of ''very high temperature processing consistent with an impact origin.''</p>
        <p>A dissident element in this debate had long suggested that natural Earth radiation, which was much stronger billions of years ago, might have formed the carbonadoes.</p>
        <p>Last March, Dr. Tyrone L. Daulton and Dr. Minoru Ozima of Washington University in St. Louis dealt that idea a blow. Writing in the journal Science, they reported finding microscopic diamonds in uranium-rich carbonaceous rocks dating from Precambrian times. But they also calculated that radiation alone would pack insufficient punch to produce the big carbonadoes.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, other scientists speculated, the mechanisms worked in tandem, with areas of Earth already rich in radioactively produced diamonds being fused by a hot collision to produce carbonadoes.</p>
        <p>In April, the American Geophysical Union, working with the Mineralogical Society of America, held its meeting in Baltimore on impact diamonds and carbonadoes, bringing together many of the world's top experts.</p>
        <p>Dr. Peter J. Heaney, a geologist at Princeton University, reported on a microscopic study of African carbonadoes that revealed signs of shock and diamond-grain dislocation. It showed, he said, that the black diamonds might have been produced in a fiery impact.</p>
        <p>Dr. DeCarli, from SRI International, presented some preliminary calculations showing that carbonadoes might have been produced, in theory, by the great heat and pressure surrounding a collision fireball, especially if it was accompanied by high-pressure shock waves.</p>
        <p>And Dr. Haggerty, of the University of Massachusetts, stunned the experts by proposing an entirely new mechanism for the formation of carbonadoes. They were born, he said, in dying stars and later fell to Earth.</p>
        <p>Scientists have known since 1987 that meteorites can be riddled with tiny diamonds that were apparently formed by distant stellar explosions billions of years ago. These extra-solar diamonds are different from ones sometimes found in meteorites that are made by collisions within the solar system or at Earth's surface.</p>
        <p>Dr. Haggerty took this discovery one giant step further, suggesting that the shock waves of exploding stars rich in carbon had produced dense aggregations of diamonds that were annealed into carbonado-like blocks and boulders. Over the eons, he said, some of these rocky aggregations of black diamond were captured by the Sun's gravitational pull and eventually fell to Earth, blasting apart during the blistering descent through the atmosphere to rain down across wide regions.</p>
        <p>In Precambrian times, he noted, the atmosphere had little or no oxygen to impede such a journey. But today, a giant black diamond raining down from the sky would burn up during descent in a gargantuan fireball that left little but carbon dioxide and carbon monoxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Haggerty said in an interview that all the evidence -- the lack of unambiguous craters tied to carbonadoes and the signs on the diamonds themselves of great heating and shock -- were suggestive of their formation as part of a new class of meteorites.</p>
        <p>He also noted that extra-solar diamonds found in meteorites appeared to have isotope signatures quite like those of carbonadoes.</p>
        <p>The dying-star hypothesis, Dr. Haggerty conceded, might be proved only by space explorers of some future age who hunt for huge diamonds speeding through the dim reaches of the solar system.</p>
        <p>He called the diamonds ''boulders of star dust.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
