<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home;Less Is More</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827087"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FLATTAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FORBES, STEVE ROBERT DOLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MALCOLM S 'STEVE' FORBES JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DB1739F931A35751C0A960958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home;Less Is More</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY;</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rich man campaigns for President on a one-plank platform: "Vote for me to cut my taxes drastically and make many of you pay more." The voters respond with enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>It sounds like fiction, a parody of the American political process. But judging by what is happening in New Hampshire, it is reality. Three weeks before the primary there polls show Steve Forbes, the flat-tax candidate, in the lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A rich man campaigns for President on a one-plank platform: "Vote for me to cut my taxes drastically and make many of you pay more." The voters respond with enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>It sounds like fiction, a parody of the American political process. But judging by what is happening in New Hampshire, it is reality. Three weeks before the primary there polls show Steve Forbes, the flat-tax candidate, in the lead.</p>
        <p>A survey just taken by The Boston Globe and WJZ-TV finds 31 percent of likely voters favoring Mr. Forbes. Senator Bob Dole, who has dominated the figures for a year, is second with 22 percent. Just three weeks ago the same pollsters gave Senator Dole 33 percent, Mr. Forbes 17.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes has poured millions from his personal fortune into television advertising in New Hampshire. In the new poll 85 percent of the respondents said they had seen his ads. Most of them are negative, principally attacks on Senator Dole. Just about the only affirmative argument he offers is for the flat tax.</p>
        <p>The Forbes tax proposal would exclude the first $36,000 in income for a family of four, then tax all earnings above that amount at a rate of 17 percent. Income from investments would not be taxed at all.</p>
        <p>A change of that kind would be a boon for Mr. Forbes and other wealthy Americans, who now are taxed on investment income and pay a marginal rate of 39.6 percent on income over $256,500 a year. To produce the same revenue as the present system, the flat tax would have to make the middle class pay more.</p>
        <p>The Treasury Department analyzed a flat tax that would keep government revenue steady, one with a rate of 20.8 percent and excluding the first $31,400. A family of four earning $50,000 a year would pay $1,604 more in taxes, one earning $100,000 an additional $2,683. But a $200,000 family would save $3,469.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Forbes formula as drafted would cut Federal revenue by $186 billion a year. That would mean an enormous increase in the deficit or severe cuts in Social Security, Medicare and the defense budget. There is not enough discretionary civilian spending to absorb more than a small part of that amount.</p>
        <p>Why would New Hampshire voters want to inflict such misery on themselves in order to give Steve Forbes and others in his bracket big tax cuts? Many may simply not understand the consequences.</p>
        <p>Detailed findings of the new poll suggest that the meaning of the Forbes flat tax has not quite sunk in -- but is beginning to. Asked whether they supported the Forbes tax plan, 37 percent said yes -- down from 54 percent three weeks ago.</p>
        <p>And of those who said they favored the flat tax, 45 percent said they would not be for it if it exempted investment income so the wealthy could live tax-free. Others in varying numbers dropped out of the group favoring a flat tax if it eliminated deductions for home mortgage interest or local property taxes -- as the Forbes plan would.</p>
        <p>The more attention the 17 percent flat tax gets, the less likely voters are to support it. But that need not be the end of Steve Forbes. When New Hampshire  supporters were asked why they liked him, the largest category of responses (37  percent) was that he was not a Washington insider.  In short, angry Americans -- and there are a lot of them -- can work off their feelings by voting for Mr. Forbes.</p>
        <p>The loser in all this is Bob Dole, and that is reason for regret. Even those  who disagree with him on this issue or that must recognize that he is a responsible political leader and a serious man.</p>
        <p>It is hard to take the other Republican candidates seriously. The party has lurched far to the right, but I doubt that it has become suicidal enough to nominate Phil Gramm or Pat Buchanan.</p>
        <p>As for Steve Forbes, my guess is that he will look increasingly flaky. He told a Boston Globe interviewer this week that much of acid rain "is created by  nature, not by smokestacks." Mr. Forbes's real contribution should be to make us think of ways to overcome the Supreme Court's misguided 1976 decision that limiting how much political candidates can spend on themselves violates their freedom of speech.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
