<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Don't Give Me Fahrenheit; Tell Me How It Feels</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="830886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THERMOMETERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEMPERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDWESTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOHR, STEVE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5DC1339F93BA25751C0A960958260" item-length="786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Don't Give Me Fahrenheit; Tell Me How It Feels</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LOHR, STEVE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I spent most of my childhood just north of Oshkosh, Wis., a city we saw as a  center of cosmopolitan sophistication, in a town called Neenah, where winter was winter. Deep snows and sub-zero temperatures were a routine part of life. And when the weatherman reported that it was 20 or 30 degrees below zero, we suited  up like astronauts and put on ski masks like bank robbers -- no skin exposed, period.</p>
        <p>Yet today, when a winter worthy of the name arrives, the coldness numbers are way off my childhood charts. In the New York area, there are reports of 20 degrees or so below zero, while from the Midwest and Plains states come declarations of 50, 60, even 90 degrees below zero. Is this America or Antarctica?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I spent most of my childhood just north of Oshkosh, Wis., a city we saw as a  center of cosmopolitan sophistication, in a town called Neenah, where winter was winter. Deep snows and sub-zero temperatures were a routine part of life. And when the weatherman reported that it was 20 or 30 degrees below zero, we suited  up like astronauts and put on ski masks like bank robbers -- no skin exposed, period.</p>
        <p>Yet today, when a winter worthy of the name arrives, the coldness numbers are way off my childhood charts. In the New York area, there are reports of 20 degrees or so below zero, while from the Midwest and Plains states come declarations of 50, 60, even 90 degrees below zero. Is this America or Antarctica?</p>
        <p>The temperatures haven't dropped because of global cooling or global warming. The reason, of course, is the rise of the "wind-chill factor," an inflationary number that is used so often these days that the actual temperature is just an afterthought. How did the wind-chill factor come to upstage mercury itself?</p>
        <p>The notion that the wind can make the cold feel colder is merely common sense.</p>
        <p>But the idea for a wind-chill index was first proposed in 1939 by Paul Siple, an Antarctic explorer. In 1945, after watching water freeze in plastic containers, he and a colleague, P. F. Passel, published an empirical formula for calculating the heat loss due to wind chill, using measurements of air temperature and wind speed.</p>
        <p>The formula states, for example, that at a temperature of 20 degrees Fahrenheit and a wind speed of 20 miles an hour, the wind-chill reading is 9 degrees below. At zero degrees and a wind speed of 25 miles an hour, the wind-chill becomes 45 below.</p>
        <p>Even though the formula has been around since the end of World War II, the wind-chill factor did not enter the vernacular until 15 years ago. The explanation, it seems, is a combination of meteorology and the media.</p>
        <p>The National Weather Service began reporting wind-chill numbers in the mid-1970's, after the agency received inquiries. But things really took off in the 1980's as weather announcers became fixtures on television screens across the country.</p>
        <p>"Wind-chill caught the public's imagination, and the notion was spread by the rising popularity of television weather reports," said Michael Glantz, head of the environmental and societal impacts group at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo. "And wind-chill is a very appealing concept to people. Temperature just exists, but the wind-chill tells you something that weather does. How it makes you feel."</p>
        <p>So reporting the wind-chill factor was justified in the name of weather relevancy. In addition, as more television weather people were trained in meteorology, they felt more confident in not merely reporting the weather but interpreting it, amplifying it. They understood the wind-chill formula, and they began doing the calculations themselves.</p>
        <p>Besides, as Todd Miner, a meteorologist at Penn State University, noted, the  wind-chill version "is more dramatic."</p>
        <p>Some meteorologists have questioned just how accurately the Siple wind-chill  index captures the combined cooling impact of wind and cold on humans. "It's a leap to go from water in cylinders to how quickly your skin cools," said Thomas  Schlatter, a meteorologist for the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
        <p>Using only temperature and wind speed, the Siple index is simply understood,  but it leaves out factors like sunlight, activity and clothing. Other formulas have been proposed. In 1971, R. J. Steadman devised a formula for heat loss for  what he memorably described as "an average clothed mobile human."</p>
        <p>The Steadman formula results in more moderate wind-chill ratings than the Siple index, according to a recent issue of Weatherwise magazine. At a temperature of 20 degrees and wind speed of 20 miles an hour, the Steadman wind-chill is 5 degrees, roughly 15 degrees higher than the Siple index.</p>
        <p>Some meteorologists believe that the Steadman approach is more accurate. Still, the Siple index seems assured of remaining the wind-chill standard, at least until Mr. Steadman finds a cooler name to quantify how that "average clothed mobile human" feels.</p>
        <p>Shrewd phrasing is required for any aspiring weather term. "Wind-chill" is so bluntly descriptive that one feels colder just hearing it. Meanwhile, its ungainly hot-weather counterpart -- "apparent temperature," the combined effect  of heat and humidity -- has not caught on. Small wonder.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
