<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cosmic Shiver</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="838960"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMETS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMET HYAKUTAKE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">OVERBYE, DENNIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDA1439F937A15750C0A960958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cosmic Shiver</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dennis Overbye</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">OVERBYE, DENNIS</byline>
      <dateline>STONE RIDGE, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I write this with trembling hands, because I haven't yet seen Comet Hyakutake -- the great spring comet that silently invaded our skies last week.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow will be the Night of the Comet, when it will be a mere 10 million miles from Earth and appear fat as a full moon, although much dimmer. An amateur astronomer who saw its tail last week reported on the Great Canadian Hairy Star  Party (one of the dozens of World Wide Web sites that have sprung up to celebrate the apparition) that it literally sent a shiver down his spine. "Now I know why comets used to frighten people," he wrote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I write this with trembling hands, because I haven't yet seen Comet Hyakutake -- the great spring comet that silently invaded our skies last week.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow will be the Night of the Comet, when it will be a mere 10 million miles from Earth and appear fat as a full moon, although much dimmer. An amateur astronomer who saw its tail last week reported on the Great Canadian Hairy Star  Party (one of the dozens of World Wide Web sites that have sprung up to celebrate the apparition) that it literally sent a shiver down his spine. "Now I know why comets used to frighten people," he wrote.</p>
        <p>That's a different kind of shiver than one gets from watching the stock market drop 171 points on news of rising employment. I want to experience that shiver, that primordial tingle -- and I'm not the only one. Around the Northern  Hemisphere, amateur astronomers are succumbing to comet fever, staying up all night in the still freezing darkness, straggling into work bleary-eyed with cosmic visions.</p>
        <p>Beauty, the poet Rainer Maria Rilke said, is dimly perceived terror. And the  fairy glow of comets has a long history of producing a delicious shiver in human psyches. A fourth-century B.C. Chinese booklet listed 27 different forms of comets and the disasters they presaged, from wars to famines.  The Stoic philosopher Seneca attributed comets' power to their airy contravention of the established order -- appearing without warning. Shakespeare, following Augustus  Caesar himself, linked the assassination of Julius Caesar with the great comet of 44 B.C. Milton imagined pestilence and war raining from the comet's tail as if from Satan's hair. In 1910, people took pills to protect against poison gas in the tail of Halley's Comet.</p>
        <p>Of course we know now from spacecraft photos that comets are just blackened snowballs volatilizing in the sunlight. Save being locked in a room with Patrick Buchanan, a good case of Old Testament cosmic dread is hard to come by in this age of machines. Any of us can download images taken from the Hubble Space Telescope of galaxies billions of light-years away. Some can even explain how those images are procured. But none of us can really comprehend the immensity of the gulfs of space and time they portray. Who can measure his stride against a light year?</p>
        <p>Ten years ago this week, I was standing in the Australian outback with several thousand other astronomical tourists waiting for Halley's Comet, looking forward to a dose of Rilkean terror. Halley was long on science -- it spawned the launch of a half dozen spacecraft -- but short on pyrotechnics. The lesson being that the universe is a big place, and the show's not always going to be for you.</p>
        <p>Astronomers had been touting Comet Hale-Bopp, due a year from now, as the next Great Comet. Then in January a Japanese amateur, Yuji Hyakutake, saw through his binoculars a smudgy patch of light near the constellation Libra. A Great Comet was already on our doorstep.</p>
        <p>Comet Hyakutake is a gift at the end of the worst winter on record in the East. If it means anything, let it mean spring. It could be a vision for the ages, a pearly smoosh staring down over Central Park like the eye of God. Or it  could fizzle. I'm trembling because I don't want to be fooled again.</p>
        <p>Surprise is the signature of cometary astronomy. We are hostages of the universe. But not all news that arrives in the middle of the night is bad. More  than we like to admit it, things happen and we don't know why.  The space shuttle tether snaps, the stock market goes up, the ozone layer goes down, the Einstein manuscript doesn't sell.</p>
        <p>Later, of course, we always manage to come up with an explanation. Just as in hindsight we can find a catastrophe for every comet: Halley's feeble appearance  was bracketed by the Challenger explosion and the Chernobyl accident. We will find reasons. But for a moment we're clueless, like children reduced to staring.</p>
        <p>This time, the show really is for us. Later this week, we will reconvince ourselves that we are masters of the universe with our ever more clever Web browsers, our genome maps and our hedge funds. But tomorrow it will be O.K. to feel that old primordial tingle on the hairs on the back of your neck. Pray for  clear skies.</p>
        <p>Dennis Overbye is the author of "Lonely Hearts of the Cosmos."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dennis Overbye is the author of "Lonely Hearts of the Cosmos."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
