<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Believer Finds Himself At Center of Hot Debate</title>
    <meta content="01BELI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="GLOBAL WARMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santer, Benjamin D (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0D9143AF932A35751C1A961958260" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Believer Finds Himself At Center of Hot Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <dateline>LIVERMORE, CALIF., Aug. 5, 1996</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Benjamin D Santer, climatologist who is chief author of report by United Nations-sponsored panel warning that human activity is probably causing global warming; he is at forefront of rapidly unfolding effort to determine extent of human impact on climate; photo (M)y</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DR. BENJAMIN D. SANTER, a shy, even-spoken, 41-year-old American climatologist who climbs mountains, runs marathons and enjoys a reputation for careful and scrupulous work, is the chief author of what may be the most important finding of the decade in atmospheric science: that human activity is probably causing some measure of global climate change, as environmentalists have long assumed and skeptics have long denied.</p>
        <p>The finding, issued for the first time in December 1995 by a panel of scientists meeting under United Nations sponsorship in Madrid, left open the question of just how large the human impact on climate is. The question is perhaps the hottest and most urgent in climatology today. Dr. Santer is in the forefront of a rapidly unfolding effort to answer it..</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DR. BENJAMIN D. SANTER, a shy, even-spoken, 41-year-old American climatologist who climbs mountains, runs marathons and enjoys a reputation for careful and scrupulous work, is the chief author of what may be the most important finding of the decade in atmospheric science: that human activity is probably causing some measure of global climate change, as environmentalists have long assumed and skeptics have long denied.</p>
        <p>The finding, issued for the first time in December 1995 by a panel of scientists meeting under United Nations sponsorship in Madrid, left open the question of just how large the human impact on climate is. The question is perhaps the hottest and most urgent in climatology today. Dr. Santer is in the forefront of a rapidly unfolding effort to answer it..</p>
        <p>Dr. Santer graduated with top honors in 1976 from the University of East Anglia in Britain with a degree in environmental sciences.</p>
        <p>To his dismay, his British education availed him little in the job market when he returned to his parents' home, then in the Baltimore area. He bounced around for the next few years, working at various times as a soccer teacher, a German teacher for Berlitz and an assembler in a zipper factory, at which point, he says, he found himself ''down and out in Seattle.'' He made two stabs at a doctorate at East Anglia, abandoning both.</p>
        <p>He soon made a third attempt to earn a doctorate at East Anglia, which boasts one of the world's top climatology departments, and this time he succeeded.</p>
        <p>''I found it fascinating,'' he said, ''the idea that humans could have a potentially large impact on climate.'' In his dissertation, Dr. Santer used statistical techniques to investigate the accuracy with which computerized models of the climate system simulated regional climates.</p>
        <p>He soon moved to another leading climatological laboratory, the Max Planck Institute for Meteorology in Hamburg, where he worked for the first time on the problem of detecting the signal of human-caused climate change, especially global warming -- the ''greenhouse fingerprint.'' He also met his wife, Heike, in Hamburg, and they now have a 3-year-old son, Nicholas.</p>
        <p>Since moving to Livermore in 1992, Dr. Santer has grappled with the related problems of testing the validity of climate models and searching for the greenhouse fingerprint.</p>
        <p>His strategy is to examine observed patterns of temperature change to see whether they matched the unique patterns expected to result from the combination of growing industrial emissions of heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide, on one hand, and sulfate aerosols that cool some parts of the planet, on the other. According to this reasoning, the pattern produced by the combination of greenhouse gases and aerosols would be markedly different from that produced by any natural cause.</p>
        <p>Climate models have been widely criticized for, among other things, failing to adequately represent natural variability. One critic, Dr. Richard S. Lindzen of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, says the models are so flawed as to be no more reliable than a Ouija board.</p>
        <p>''I think that's garbage,'' said Dr. Santer, part of whose job is to assess how good the models are. ''I think models are credible tools and the only tools we have to define what sort of greenhouse signal to look for. It's clear that the ability of models to simulate important features of present-day climate has improved enormously.'' He says that if the models are right -- still a big if -- the human imprint on the climate should emerge more clearly in the next few years. All in all, he says, he expects ''very rapid'' progress in the search for the greenhouse fingerprint.</p>
        <p>When might it become clear enough to be widely convincing?</p>
        <p>''Even if New York were under six feet of water, there would be people who would still say, 'Well, this is a natural event,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
