<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Adjournment Fever in Congress</title>
    <meta content="07FRI11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="971120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E1D81639F934A35752C1A961958260" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Adjournment Fever in Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial scores Congress for focusing on early adjournment, almost three weeks before Thanksgiving, instead of on governing; says its members apparently believe more they stay at work, less voters like them (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It says a lot about the vacuous state of national politics that the overriding focus of Congress right now is adjourning rather than legislating. The current target for escaping Washington is this weekend. Lawmakers usually hang around the capital past Thanksgiving. No one wants to admit it, but most in Congress believe that the more they stay at work, the less the voters like them.</p>
        <p>This is a startling state of affairs. The last several years have been filled with partisan battles over welfare, health, taxes and budgets. Now both parties are probing for sound bites rather than leading. The Republican leaders, for example, trolled for something to restore their reputation as defenders of the taxpayer, now that archconservatives have accused them of selling out on the budget. They finally settled on a proposal to defang the Internal Revenue Service. Then President Clinton outflanked them by dropping his opposition to their plan. It was welfare reform all over again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It says a lot about the vacuous state of national politics that the overriding focus of Congress right now is adjourning rather than legislating. The current target for escaping Washington is this weekend. Lawmakers usually hang around the capital past Thanksgiving. No one wants to admit it, but most in Congress believe that the more they stay at work, the less the voters like them.</p>
        <p>This is a startling state of affairs. The last several years have been filled with partisan battles over welfare, health, taxes and budgets. Now both parties are probing for sound bites rather than leading. The Republican leaders, for example, trolled for something to restore their reputation as defenders of the taxpayer, now that archconservatives have accused them of selling out on the budget. They finally settled on a proposal to defang the Internal Revenue Service. Then President Clinton outflanked them by dropping his opposition to their plan. It was welfare reform all over again.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, on the other hand, is pushing for national education standards, which might be useful but is really a gambit for blocking Republicans on vouchers and school choice. He and his wife are spending a lot of time on child care, but where is the legislative agenda? A major issue he faces is global warming, but Mr. Clinton has yet to start any kind of tough sell in Congress. Another Administration initiative, the proposed expansion of NATO, was supposed to really get the emotions going in Washington this year. But the debate has proved disappointing as all sides seek cover in a fuzzy consensus.</p>
        <p>The Republicans, of course, have always said they had a more limited agenda than the Democrats. They are, after all, the party of less government, and the initial hope of some in the House was to adjourn as early as October. Given the leaders' opposition to campaign finance reform, just being in Washington was unpleasant and risky. Finally, to speed adjournment and avoid being seen as abusers of their power, both Trent Lott, the Senate majority leader, and House Speaker Newt Gingrich agreed to take up campaign finance reform next spring.</p>
        <p>The one major piece of business that might get trampled in the rush to adjourn is the fast-track legislation enabling Mr. Clinton to negotiate new trade agreements. Here both the White House and the Republican leadership are trying to corral votes in their own parties, with Mr. Clinton struggling against a mass defection among Democrats.</p>
        <p>But perhaps the most telling spectacle is Mr. Gingrich's difficulty restraining conservatives from attaching riders on abortion and other subjects certain to provoke a Presidential veto. Skirmishing with a restive right wing has not been his favorite idea of fun, ever since the dissidents tried to oust him in a coup earlier this year. It's a good time,  in other words, to get out of town.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
