<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Than 20 Years After Viking, Craft Is to Land, and Bounce, on Mars</title>
    <meta content="01MARS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970702T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="940784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Pathfinder (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Viking Project</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Global Surveyor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mars (Planet)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Meteors and Meteorites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE0D61F31F932A35754C0A961958260" item-length="1890" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Than 20 Years After Viking, Craft Is to Land, and Bounce, on Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif., June 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States robot spacecraft Mars Pathfinder is set to land on Mars, in what would be first successful attempt to explore planet since two 1976 Viking landings; recent finding of meteorite evidence suggesting life may have existed on Mars in past has spurred excitement over plans for 10-year systematic Mars exploration, beginning with Mars Pathfinder and Mars Global Surveyor, set to orbit Mars in Sept; neither craft is designed to look for signs of past life, but two could provide data on where to look on future missions; diagrams; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flat, desolate and dry as red dust, the flood plain of Ares Vallis hardly seems an inviting place to visit on Mars, but scientists think it may well be a reservoir of the planet's early history. So the American robot spacecraft Mars Pathfinder is headed there for a landing on Friday, the Fourth of July.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft, launched last December, would be the first to reach the surface of Mars since the two Viking landings in the summer of 1976. Its success would somewhat compensate for the dismal record of several unsuccessful American and Russian attempts to explore Mars in the intervening years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flat, desolate and dry as red dust, the flood plain of Ares Vallis hardly seems an inviting place to visit on Mars, but scientists think it may well be a reservoir of the planet's early history. So the American robot spacecraft Mars Pathfinder is headed there for a landing on Friday, the Fourth of July.</p>
        <p>The spacecraft, launched last December, would be the first to reach the surface of Mars since the two Viking landings in the summer of 1976. Its success would somewhat compensate for the dismal record of several unsuccessful American and Russian attempts to explore Mars in the intervening years.</p>
        <p>The new mission carries the added burden and promise of being the first to investigate the planet since the announcement last August of evidence in a meteorite suggesting that life may have existed on Mars sometime in its first billion years. Though inconclusive and much debated, the findings kindled public and scientific excitement over existing plans for a 10-year program of systematic Mars exploration, beginning with Mars Pathfinder and its companion, Mars Global Surveyor, scheduled to orbit the planet in September.</p>
        <p>Neither spacecraft was designed -- or is expected -- to answer life-on-Mars questions. But the two could produce critical geochemical, climatic and mapping information on where to look for answers on future missions. Definitive evidence will probably come only with the return of Mars rock samples. The first such mission is planned for 2005.</p>
        <p>So far, the landing prospects for Pathfinder look good. Its flight has been virtually trouble-free, and now the one-ton craft is within one million miles of the planet, closing in at 12,000 miles an hour. After a minor course correction last week, its aim appears to be true.</p>
        <p>''Mars Pathfinder is very, very healthy,'' said Brian Muirhead, deputy project manager at the mission control center here at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory. ''From launch on, she's done everything we've asked her to do.''</p>
        <p>Over the last week or so, ground controllers completed final checks on the condition of the spacecraft and its main cargo, a 22-pound, six-wheel roving vehicle the size of a microwave oven. After touchdown, the rover, named Sojourner, is to roll out and begin at least a week of remotely controlled excursions to take close-up pictures of rocks and analyze their chemical composition.</p>
        <p>It will be the first time a roving vehicle has explored the surface of another planet. In the first days, the rover will probably not wander more than 30 or 40 feet from the lander, picking its way carefully at a rate of two feet a minute. Later, it may be sent off on excursions several hundred feet from the lander.</p>
        <p>''All systems looked fine,'' Mr. Muirhead said after the tests. ''We turned on the rover and asked, 'How are you?' and the rover told us, 'I'm fine. Can't wait to get down to the surface of Mars.' ''</p>
        <p>While Sojourner is crawling about, the landing craft is to snap color stereo photographs of the landscape and gather data on wind speeds and directions; the pressure, temperature and density of the thin atmosphere, which is mainly carbon dioxide, and other weather conditions. Engineers expect the rover to operate for at least a week and the lander for a month, though they are hoping for much longer performances.</p>
        <p>But first, Pathfinder must land, and that involves a technique never before tried by American engineers. Instead of going into orbit around Mars and then descending to the surface, Pathfinder is to plunge directly toward the landing site, speeding in at about twice the velocity of the Viking landers. With little time to make adjustments, navigation must be especially precise.</p>
        <p>The craft's descent will be slowed first by atmospheric drag, then by parachute and finally by retrorocket firings. The craft will not so much touch down as bounce and roll to a stop.</p>
        <p>Pathfinder will be enclosed in a giant cocoon of air bags, inflated seconds before landing to cushion the impact of hitting the surface at about 55 miles an hour. Pity there are no Martians to witness the spectacle of a kind of 15-foot beach ball suddenly falling out of the sky and bouncing all about. On the first couple of bounces, the craft could spring as high as 100 feet, skipping forward with each succeeding and lesser bounce before all impact energy dissipates and it comes to rest.</p>
        <p>Officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration decided on the direct descent and landing to simplify the spacecraft design, reduce its weight and lower costs. More fuel and duplicate systems would have been required to maneuver into orbit first, then release a smaller craft for landing.</p>
        <p>Controlling costs, project officials said, has been a rule strictly enforced in producing the Pathfinder spacecraft. They were under orders to develop and build the craft for no more than $150 million, in 1992 dollars, and get the mission off the ground in three years. In a time of austere budgets, NASA has all but abandoned expensive, multipurpose science missions in favor of similar low-cost, rapidly developed and highly focused flights.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muirhead said the Pathfinder spacecraft was produced within budget, at $171 million, when the amount is adjusted for inflation. With the added cost of the launching rocket and operating expenses, the entire mission is estimated to cost $266 million. By comparison, the cost of the more ambitious and complex Viking missions to Mars exceeded $1 billion at the time, or $3 billion in today's dollars.</p>
        <p>When the Pathfinder project was started in 1993, its main objective was to test new technologies for delivering small spacecraft and rovers to the Martian surface. But scientists, wanting to make the most of the opportunity, chose a landing site that promised scientific dividends. The site on Ares Vallis is a rocky plain at the mouth of a wide channel cutting through ancient highlands. It lies 525 miles southeast of the place where Viking 1 landed in the plain known as Chryse Planitia.</p>
        <p>After two years of studying Viking photographs and maps, scientists settled on the Ares Vallis site last year as meeting the criteria of engineers seeking a relatively safe place to land and planetary geologists wanting to examine a wide variety of rock samples.</p>
        <p>Engineers insisted that the site's elevation be low, said Anthony Spear, the project manager, so the parachute has sufficient time to open and slow the craft's descent. Also, the area should be clear of huge boulders, steep slopes, deep gullies or other hazards; to allow for uncertainties in navigation, the smooth area should extend over an ellipse about 120 miles by 60 miles. Finally, the site should be fairly near the Mars Equator to insure maximum sunshine at this time of the Martian year for generating electricity to run the spacecraft and rover.</p>
        <p>Scientists considered and rejected several sites that did not pass engineering standards. ''If you don't land safely, you don't get any science,'' said Dr. Matthew Golombek, a planetary geologist and the project's chief scientist. ''We're fairly confident that 99 percent of the area is safe.''</p>
        <p>What scientists like about the Ares Vallis area, Dr. Golombek said, is that it is a ''grab-bag site.'' From their analysis of pictures, scientists think rampaging flood waters carved out the Ares Vallis channel in a matter of weeks.</p>
        <p>''Imagine taking all the water in the Great Lakes and flushing it out to the Gulf of Mexico in a two-week period,'' Dr. Golombek said. ''That is the kind of catastrophe that must have swept over Mars perhaps 1 billion to 2.5 billion years ago.''</p>
        <p>At Ares Vallis, the torrent washed tons of rock from the highlands down to the mouth of the channel, littering the basin with samples of rock from a time and place where water once existed in abundance. Now, of course, Mars is dry as a bone, except for some permafrost and polar ice.</p>
        <p>Since the highlands appear to be extremely old, rocks from there could attest to environmental conditions on the planet 3.5 billion to 4.5 billion years ago, back almost to its beginning. Of special interest, the rocks could be the same age and from the same type of terrain as the Martian meteorite ALH84001, which is suspected of carrying mineral and possibly microfossil traces of former Martian microbial life.</p>
        <p>The alpha proton X-ray spectrometer on the rover was designed by scientists at the University of Chicago to press against rock outcroppings and quickly provide the first-ever chemical analysis of what Mars is made of. The two Viking landers concentrated on biology, scooping soil and testing it for signs of life; the test results were negative.</p>
        <p>''Down the line we want to be able to find out if life on Mars developed along the same lines as life on Earth,'' said Dr. Thanasis Economou, a designer of the spectrometer at the University of Chicago. ''Before that can happen, we have to learn as much as we can about Mars and figure out what kinds of samples we should bring back.''</p>
        <p>Although the evidence for a warmer and wetter Mars in the past is substantial, some scientists still question the assumption that the many dry channels were eroded by tremendous water floods. The terrain, they suggest, could have been shaped by volcanoes.</p>
        <p>Dr. Raymond Arvidson, a planetary scientist at Washington University in St. Louis, said the mission geologists were convinced that the spacecraft would be landing on a plain where there once was water. ''The onus is on the team to prove that idea as opposed to others -- for example, that the site is really an ancient volcanic deposit,'' he said. ''Either way, the data to come back will be invaluable.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 2, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Science Times yesterday about the landing site for the Mars Pathfinder misstated in some editions the World Wide Web site where the image is available. It is http://mpfwww.arc.nasa.gov/mpf/ellipse.html</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 2, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Science Times yesterday about the landing site for the Mars Pathfinder misstated in some editions the World Wide Web site where the image is available. It is http://mpfwww.arc.nasa.gov/mpf/ellipse.html</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
