<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Ecstasy to Gravel, in a Blur</title>
    <meta content="10SHAP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="DANCE REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="900644"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Complexions (Dance Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rhoden, Dwight</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6DE1638F933A25752C0A961958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Ecstasy to Gravel, in a Blur</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jack Anderson reviews performance by troupe Complexions--A Concept in Dance at Joyce Theater, featuring dance works of choreographer Dwight Rhoden (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dwight Rhoden appeared to enjoy going to choreographic extremes in the works he created for the troupe Complexions -- A Concept in Dance. The company, which he directs with Desmond Richardson, opened the Altogether Different series at the Joyce Theater on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The series focuses on up-and-coming companies and choreographers, and Complexions got it going with an eye-catching program. Mr. Richardson and Mr. Rhoden, both former members of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, have assembled an ensemble capable of giving expert performances in many styles. The dances featured taped collages in which scores by Antonio Carlos Scott, the group's resident composer, were combined with pieces by other composers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dwight Rhoden appeared to enjoy going to choreographic extremes in the works he created for the troupe Complexions -- A Concept in Dance. The company, which he directs with Desmond Richardson, opened the Altogether Different series at the Joyce Theater on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>The series focuses on up-and-coming companies and choreographers, and Complexions got it going with an eye-catching program. Mr. Richardson and Mr. Rhoden, both former members of the Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, have assembled an ensemble capable of giving expert performances in many styles. The dances featured taped collages in which scores by Antonio Carlos Scott, the group's resident composer, were combined with pieces by other composers.</p>
        <p>There is nothing timid about Mr. Rhoden's choreography. He was forceful in two different ways. The dances before intermission were stern, often extremely so. In contrast, all that came later was unabashedly flamboyant. The contrasts between the program's parts helped account for some of the evening's strengths and weaknesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rhoden was at his most flamboyant in his new ''Cake,'' an almost dizzyingly kaleidoscopic piece in which dancers never stopped swirling. It began with a sinuous balletic pas de deux for Adrianna Suarez and Mr. Richardson in which Ms. Suarez was on point. Other balletic steps were used throughout the five-part composition. Yet most sequences emphasized an extremely fluid modern-dance technique.</p>
        <p>At times, the performers recited a text by Aubrey Lynch and Mr. Rhoden that in one section proclaimed that a good recipe for life must include a warm, loving couple who know how to raise children. Although the sentiments were honorable, the tone of the statement was much more coy than the constantly churning choreography.</p>
        <p>Indeed, dancers kept rushing in and out so ferociously that ''Cake'' might well have been titled ''Volcano.'' Like volcanic eruptions, Mr. Rhoden's choreography sometimes looked chaotic. But, like a lava flow, it had undeniable power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rhoden was also balletically flamboyant in ''Ave Maria,'' a pas de deux for Christina Johnson and Donald Williams from a longer work called ''The Grapes of Wrath.'' Mr. Rhoden attempted to make acrobatics serve as a symbol of religious exaltation. Although there were moments in which virtuosity seemed more important than spirituality, Ms. Johnson and Mr. Williams danced with the ease of angels throughout the duet.</p>
        <p>Nothing in the first part of the program prepared one for the rip-roaring energy of ''Cake'' and ''Ave Maria.''</p>
        <p>The lighting by Betsy Herst, Tricia Toliver and Mr. Rhoden indicated the tone of the three opening works. In all of them, people at one time or another were trapped in pools of light.</p>
        <p>''Gravel,'' a premiere, found Mr. Rhoden and Mr. Richardson sometimes looking lost in isolation and at other times struggling to escape their confines and draw near.</p>
        <p>''Fractal Boundaries,'' an excerpt from a work called ''Global Warming,'' showed dancers imprisoned in circles of light who kept tossing silver balls at one another in a competitive manner. Light also confined the cast of ''Diction,'' a series of erotic power struggles in which some performers danced feverishly while others babbled into microphones about the problems of love affairs.</p>
        <p>The impact of ''Gravel'' was enhanced by the stage presence of Mr. Rhoden and Mr. Richardson. And ''Fractal Boundaries'' and ''Diction'' had considerable tension. Yet one stern dance after another led to a sameness of theatrical texture. Mr. Rhoden does like going to choreographic extremes, and his creations would profit by judicious editing. Nevertheless, if he sometimes goes too far, he is admirable for being bold enough to take risks. Artistically, it may be better to go too far than to have nowhere to go at all.</p>
        <p>Complexions can be seen again tonight. Other Altogether Different attractions will be on view through Jan. 26 at the Joyce, 175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
