<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Californian Wins Middle Market and Ruffles His Rivals</title>
    <meta content="04WINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Brash Prince of Wine Country" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="899262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="The Brash Prince of Wine Country"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kendall-Jackson Vineyards</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jess</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2D61739F937A35752C0A961958260" item-length="2003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Californian Wins Middle Market and Ruffles His Rivals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK J. PRIAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <dateline>SONOMA, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Jess Jackson, who owns fastest-growing and most successful wine-making business to appear in California in 20 years; says from few acres of grapes in early 1970's, Jackson now controls more than a dozen wineries--including his flagship, Kendall-Jackson--stretching from all the choice growing regions of California to Europe and South America; Jackson's empire is now among top 10 wine businesses in the country, with sales of about $200 million in 1996 from Kendall-Jackson alone; tables; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A rooster tail of dust billowing out behind it, the gold Lexus climbed into the rugged Mayacamas Mountains. ''Don't be nervous,'' said Jess Jackson, pulling deftly through another hairpin turn. ''I know this country.''</p>
        <p>He should; it's the Gauer Ranch, some 75 miles north of San Francisco, one of the last great land holdings in Sonoma County, more than 5,000 acres of mountains, meadows and, yes, vineyards. And Jess Jackson owns it all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A rooster tail of dust billowing out behind it, the gold Lexus climbed into the rugged Mayacamas Mountains. ''Don't be nervous,'' said Jess Jackson, pulling deftly through another hairpin turn. ''I know this country.''</p>
        <p>He should; it's the Gauer Ranch, some 75 miles north of San Francisco, one of the last great land holdings in Sonoma County, more than 5,000 acres of mountains, meadows and, yes, vineyards. And Jess Jackson owns it all.</p>
        <p>''I often read about the Gallos,'' he said as he drove along, ignoring a 3,000-foot drop just inches from the car. ''Everyone talks about how much land they own up here. Well, we own a lot more than they do.''</p>
        <p>What Mr. Jackson owns is nothing less than the fastest-growing and arguably most successful wine-making business to appear in California in 20 years. From a few acres of grapes in the early 1970's, he now controls more than a dozen wineries -- including his flagship, Kendall-Jackson -- stretching from all the choice growing regions of California to Europe and South America. Though still dwarfed by the E.&amp; J. Gallo Company, the industry giant, Mr. Jackson's empire is now among the top 10 wine businesses in the country, with sales of about $200 million in 1996 from Kendall-Jackson alone, according to Jon Fredrikson, an industry economist. The smaller wineries produced another $30 million, Mr. Jackson said.</p>
        <p>In the process, he has managed to change the way fine wine is made and marketed in the United States, leaving many in the business to marvel at his highly lean, efficient and integrated operation, which includes a barrel-making business and a distribution company. At the same time, the pugnacious Mr. Jackson, an experienced lawyer, has become the object of envy as well as admiration, and has generated a bumper crop of speculation and controversy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson's story combines the good fortune of a novice who has stumbled onto something new with the calculating eye of a master marketer who has found his magic niche.</p>
        <p>An early mistake in the fermentation process of his Vintner's Reserve chardonnay created a surprise hit whose slight sweetness has inspired others to offer similar products. The competition also followed in his footsteps when Mr. Jackson carved out a new middle market for fine wines after carefully analyzing the existing price structure.</p>
        <p>He has been largely alone, however, in bringing a lawyer's hardball style to the traditionally genteel wine business. Mr. Jackson took advantage of an industry downturn in the late 80's to snap up unprofitable vineyards and hire away well-regarded wine makers. And he has been involved in several high-profile legal battles, even taking on Gallo.</p>
        <p>Now, as his business is poised for still more growth, the 66-year-old Mr. Jackson is clearly a major force to be reckoned with, even though, as he proudly says, he is still not part of ''the old boy system.''</p>
        <p>''Jess came into the business as a real estate lawyer, and he still thinks like a lawyer,'' said one winery owner who has known Mr. Jackson for 20 years. ''That's why wine people can't figure him out; they're not lawyers.''</p>
        <p>Rodney Strong, the founder of another Sonoma winery, Rodney Strong Vineyards, added, ''He's not an insider in the wine business, but he's taught the insiders some valuable lessons about making and selling wine.''</p>
        <p>The original Jackson vineyard was a weekend hobby. By the late 1970's, Mr. Jackson, then a San Francisco lawyer, was selling grapes to several wineries.</p>
        <p>''I never planned to get into the wine business,'' he said recently, ''but there was a grape glut around 1978 and I couldn't sell what I had grown. So I had it made into wine.''</p>
        <p>His first vintages were called Chateau du Lac. By 1982, the name had been changed to Kendall-Jackson -- Kendall is the surname of Mr. Jackson's first wife -- and a winery was under construction.</p>
        <p>While making his 1982 chardonnay, Mr. Jackson ran into a problem. At a crucial point, the fermentation stopped before all the sugar in the grapes was converted into alcohol and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Efforts to restart the process failed, and the wine was bottled with the unfermented sugar -- just a touch -- still in it. Vintner's Reserve was an instant success, and it has stayed that way. The reason, experts say, is that the new product legitimized the sweet taste of jug wine, attracting an army of drinkers willing to pay a few dollars more for the status of a better label.</p>
        <p>From 18,000 cases that year, total Kendall-Jackson shipments rose to an estimated 2.6 million cases in 1996, with Vintner's Reserve accounting for 64 percent. No threat to Gallo, which produced an estimated 55 million cases in 1996, but impressive for a 14-year-old upstart.</p>
        <p>''Jess is a genius at calculating price points,'' one of his competitors said. ''In his early days, wineries like Sebastiani were going for the low end; $3, $4 a bottle. Others, like Chateau St. Jean, were developing the $9 category. Jess saw a space between the two and filled it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson concurred. ''We sold out the '82 vintage in six months and price was certainly part of it. We started just under $5, then we raised it 12 times in 12 years.'' Vintner's Reserve now retails for around $12.</p>
        <p>Besides Kendall-Jackson, now based in Santa Rosa here in Sonoma County, Mr. Jackson's holdings include 11 wineries in California, a winery and vineyards in Italy, a leased winery in Chile and two square miles of vines in Argentina. The wineries other than Kendall-Jackson are grouped under the name Artisans and Estates and produce small batches of higher-priced wines. $(Mr. Jackson's operations were not affected by this week's flooding in some parts of California's wine country.$)</p>
        <p>Still to come are five new wineries in California.</p>
        <p>''We are always looking for good properties,'' Mr. Jackson said.</p>
        <p>Tall and rangy, with a shock of silver-white hair tumbling into his eyes, Jess Jackson bears a resemblance to Charlton Heston. Invariably dressed in jeans and boots, his face tanned from long exposure to the California sun, he looks every inch a man of the soil.</p>
        <p>In fact, he is a city person, born in Los Angeles and raised in San Francisco. As a boy, wine was a part of his life. ''San Francisco had a rich wine culture,'' he said. ''I had an Italian uncle who made wine, and we drank it regularly. During the war, when they needed people in the vineyards, I picked grapes.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson went to law school at the University of California at Berkeley, paying his way by working on the San Francisco docks and as a Berkeley policeman. While still a student, he did research for the late Pat Brown, then California's Attorney General and later Governor.</p>
        <p>As a young lawyer, Mr. Jackson worked for the state, specializing in real estate law, invaluable training for a man who would become the state's busiest vineyard buyer.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in California's wine business, which nurtures its laid-back image, Jess Jackson's drive and combativeness stand out.</p>
        <p>He garnered considerable attention five years ago, for example, in a legal battle with Jedidiah T. Steele, his longtime wine maker.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the dispute was the accusation by Mr. Jackson that Mr. Steele had revealed ''trade secrets'' about the process for making Vintner's Reserve shortly after leaving to start his own business. When Mr. Jackson stopped making severance payments to him, Mr. Steele sued, and Mr. Jackson countersued.</p>
        <p>The fracas further separated Mr. Jackson from the wine establishment. Robert Mondavi and other prominent wine makers testified on Mr. Steele's behalf, saying that there was nothing really secret about the process. A ruling against Mr. Steele, they said, could stifle the cooperation that they maintained had enabled the California wine industry to make great strides in a relatively short time. The court ordered Mr. Jackson to pay Mr. Steele the balance of the severance agreement, but also found that Mr. Jackson's winery was entitled to keep the process to itself.</p>
        <p>As his business expanded, Mr. Jackson roiled the industry's seemingly placid surface here by hiring away some of the competition's best people, then roiled it again when he announced that the Federal Government's labeling regulations, accepted by the rest of the industry, needed to be tightened -- a grandstanding move, critics said. (The Government is still reviewing his petition.)</p>
        <p>Currently, Mr. Jackson is locked in a legal battle with Gallo over trademark infringement, accusing Gallo of copying a Kendall-Jackson label for its Turning Leaf line.</p>
        <p>This is his second courtroom tussle with the Gallos. In 1986, in his previous life as a lawyer, Mr. Jackson represented Joseph Gallo Jr. in his unsuccessful attempt to wrest a share of the company from his older brothers, Ernest and the late Julio.</p>
        <p>Kendall-Jackson's dramatic expansion at a time when other wineries were experiencing serious economic problems gave rise to some equally dramatic talk about the company's financial circumstances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson brushed off his critics with an impatient wave of the hand. ''We are in excellent financial condition,'' he said, ''and it gets better all the time. Why, we are the Bank of America's favorite winery.''</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mr. Jackson's hiring of a Los Angeles financial public relations firm gave rise to talk that he was about to take the company public.</p>
        <p>''We reserve that option,'' Mr. Jackson said, ''but we have absolutely no plans to do it now.''</p>
        <p>Jean-Michel Vallette, who watches the wine industry as a partner in Hambrecht &amp; Quist, a San Francisco investment bank, agrees with the upbeat assessment.</p>
        <p>''In the early days, Jess clearly needed outside help and was certainly highly leveraged,'' Mr. Vallette said. ''But today he can attract the highest-quality lenders and get the most attractive financing terms. People have always underestimated just how profitable Kendall-Jackson is.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson releases no precise figures but doesn't argue with an industry estimate that Kendall-Jackson has profits of about $40 million a year just from Vintner's Reserve.</p>
        <p>At last count, at least 14 members of Mr. Jackson's family were working in the business. His second wife, Barbara Banke, also a lawyer, is president of one of the wineries.</p>
        <p>The Jacksons live in a small frame house that stands in stark contrast to the palaces owned by some of his competitors. The house is just across the road from the winery where he keeps his office. His Lexus is six years old.</p>
        <p>''I prefer to put my money in the business,'' Mr. Jackson said, sounding something like a man on a mission.</p>
        <p>''I want to broaden the consumption base'' of wine, he said, ''and that means educating people. Wine is made out to be foreign, as opposed to beer, which is made to be American. We've got to make it more American. It's not going to blossom in American culture until we take the mystique out of it.''</p>
        <p>The Brash Prince of Wine Country</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
