<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schedule Leaves Cadets Marching in Place</title>
    <meta content="CHOCK16Z" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES: HOCKEY NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, William N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E0D9153FF935A25751C1A961958260" item-length="674" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schedule Leaves Cadets Marching in Place</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wallace, William N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>College hockey notes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cadets took a break for the holidays with a .500 record: seven victories, seven defeats over almost half the schedule for this Division I independent team.</p>
        <p>Was that good enough?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Cadets took a break for the holidays with a .500 record: seven victories, seven defeats over almost half the schedule for this Division I independent team.</p>
        <p>Was that good enough?</p>
        <p>Army is playing its usual mix of teams from all three divisions. Among its Division I opponents, Army has won only two of nine matches, both against Nebraska-Omaha, a new team this season. Army's last loss was typical, by 4-3 to Merrimack, one of four one-goal defeats.</p>
        <p>Up next for Army is the Rensselaer holiday tournament at Troy, N.Y., Dec. 29 and 30.</p>
        <p>On the first night, after Yale plays Lake Superior State, the Cadets will take on the host Engineers, to whom they lost, 4-1, on Nov. 1.</p>
        <p>Daryl Chamberlain, a senior from Livonia, Mich., has been in goal for Army in 82 games and holds several school records. He is getting some relief this season from the sophomore Corey Winer of Rockaway, N.J.</p>
        <p>The team's top scorer has been a freshman, John Toftey of Duluth, Minn. Toftey, Greg Buckmeier and Andy Lindbohm have scored 25 of the team's 54 goals.</p>
        <p>W.C.H.A.</p>
        <p>St. Cloud State, the West's surprise team this season, clings to first place thanks to goalie Brian Leitza, who stopped 62 of 66 shots by North Dakota in the weekend series. St. Cloud managed to split the two games, winning, 5-2, after losing by 2-1 to the defending national champions.</p>
        <p>Leitza is a senior who has been drafted by the Pittsburgh Penguins. He has a 9-1-1 record in Western Collegiate Hockey Association play this season.</p>
        <p>St. Cloud's Peter Torsson, a freshman right wing from Sweden, scored one goal and had an assist to be named the W.C.H.A.'s rookie of the week.</p>
        <p>NORTHEASTERN</p>
        <p>The Huskies, along with Yale the East's surprise teams this season, are in first in Hockey East for the third straight week. Boston University's two ties last week, against Boston College and New Hampshire, kept the Terriers from reaching the top.</p>
        <p>The Huskies have no one among Hockey East's top 20 scorers and the only statistical reflection of their 6-3-2 league record is in goaltending. Marc Robitaille, the sophomore who has played without relief, has a .917 save percentage. Coming up Thursday is a non-league match with Harvard at home in Matthews Arena.</p>
        <p>PRINCETON</p>
        <p>The Tigers are on an eight-day tour of Austria and Slovakia, during which the team will play two games and scrimmage twice. They are apt to come home with stronger legs after skating on those large European ice sheets.</p>
        <p>Coach Don Cahoon hopes to improve offensive production. The Tigers have the ECAC's leading scorer in Jeff Halpern and his teammates on the first line, Casson Masters and Scott Bertoli. Each have 12 points. But there has been little scoring punch from the other lines.</p>
        <p>In reference to ''a great cultural opportunity,'' Cahoon said, ''This is something we will do every four years, make it a part of the hockey experience at Princeton.''</p>
        <p>A good recruiting tool, too.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Cornell and Northeastern, each with 7-1 records in league play, are tied for first place in the ECAC Women's League. New Hampshire (6-0-0) is third. Laurie Belliveau of Yale (1-6-1) once again is the most shot-at target in the league. She has made 353 saves in eight games and has a .917 save percentage ... Top men's teams? WMEB, the student radio station at Maine, has Boston University, Michigan State, North Dakota and New Hampshire as the top four in its poll. Boston University and New Hampshire are 1-1-1 after their three regular-season Hockey East games, the Wildcats coming from two goals down last Friday to tie at 4-4. Their next meeting will most likely be March 21 at Boston's Fleet Center in Hockey East's tournament championship game. ... Of the ECAC's 53 league games to date, a total of 26 were decided by one goal or ended in a tie.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES: HOCKEY NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
