<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Coming Battle Over Kyoto</title>
    <meta content="12FRI1$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979784"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kyoto (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7D8113CF931A25751C1A961958260" item-length="478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Coming Battle Over Kyoto</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial contends that Kyoto agreement on greenhouse gases was test of Pres Clinton's political will; maintains that Clinton passed that test, but he must bring same creativity and passion to Senate struggle; asserts that winning Senate approval means defeating treaty's well-financed opponents in business and labor, and that will require extraordinary level of Presidential energy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are two salient facts about Wednesday's agreement on global warming in Kyoto. The first is that it could lead to an environmental undertaking of historic scale. If the industrialized countries carry out in practice what they promised on paper, making sustained cuts in the use of fossil fuels, they will forever alter the way the world produces and consumes energy.</p>
        <p>The second fact is that Kyoto was merely the beginning of what is sure to be a brutal battle. Winning Senate approval means defeating the treaty's well-financed opponents in business and labor, and that in turn will require an extraordinary level of Presidential energy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are two salient facts about Wednesday's agreement on global warming in Kyoto. The first is that it could lead to an environmental undertaking of historic scale. If the industrialized countries carry out in practice what they promised on paper, making sustained cuts in the use of fossil fuels, they will forever alter the way the world produces and consumes energy.</p>
        <p>The second fact is that Kyoto was merely the beginning of what is sure to be a brutal battle. Winning Senate approval means defeating the treaty's well-financed opponents in business and labor, and that in turn will require an extraordinary level of Presidential energy.</p>
        <p>Kyoto was the first test of President Clinton's political will. He passed it. When an agreement seemed to be slipping away, he and Vice President Gore instructed their negotiators to agree to deeper cuts in American emissions of carbon dioxide and five other heat-trapping gases than Washington had originally proposed. That concession enabled the Administration to win support, in principle, for innovative financial mechanisms that it regards as essential to the success of the entire enterprise.</p>
        <p>The President must now bring that same creativity and passion to the Senate struggle. It will be complicated by the fact that the industrialized nations failed to achieve the one thing the Senate most wanted, a commitment by developing nations like China to set targets and timetables of their own. The deadline for signing the treaty and sending it to the Senate is more than a year away, and Mr. Clinton says he will not do so until the developing countries come on board. He can also use that time to spell out in greater detail how he intends to reach the treaty's targets without provoking the huge economic dislocations forecast by its opponents.</p>
        <p>The treaty has two important features that will help him sell it. One provides in principle -- details will be worked out later -- for a system of ''emissions trading,'' under which a country or individual company would be able to meet its reduction target by buying reductions from another country or company that has reduced emissions below its targets, and thus has credits to sell. The second provision sets up a new multilateral organization that is intended to encourage companies in rich countries to invest in emissions-reduction projects in poorer countries. Both provisions could encourage cost-saving technologies and provide a ready source of capital to developing nations.</p>
        <p>There are already rumblings that Senate opponents will push quickly for a resolution declaring their opposition to the treaty. That would be outrageously irresponsible. The world has worked for more than two years to produce a serious answer to a potentially calamitous problem. For that reason alone, it deserves a measured, mature hearing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
