<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1DA123CF933A25753C1A961958260" item-length="1398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Scores Dead in Mexico As Hurricane Hits Acapulco  Scores of residents were killed in the workers' districts of Acapulco when a hurricane of unusual strength raked Mexico's Pacific Coast.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Scores Dead in Mexico As Hurricane Hits Acapulco  Scores of residents were killed in the workers' districts of Acapulco when a hurricane of unusual strength raked Mexico's Pacific Coast.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Italy's Government Falls  Prime Minister Romano Prodi resigned after a small party, Communist Refoundation, refused to support further cuts in the country's pension and unemployment programs. The left-leaning coalition, in power for 17 months, had adhered to stringent fiscal plans in order to qualify for the euro, the European common currency, which is due in 1999.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Muslim Win in Bosnia Vote  With absentee ballots, candidates of the Bosnian Muslim Party won 24 of 46 seats on the town council governing the city of Srebrenica, where thousands of Muslims died in mass executions in July 1995. Muslims were once the majority in the town, but were expelled by the Bosnian Serb Army. Only Serbs now live there.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Critics Warn of NATO Costs  On the second day of hearings by the Senate Committee on Foreign Relations, critics of plans to expand NATO to three eastern European countries charged that such an enlargement would cost the United States far more than the $2 billion the Administration has estimated. Any changes in the alliance treaty have to be ratified by the Senate.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Vintage Castro Talks, and Talks  Fidel Castro extemporized for 6 hours and 43 minutes to open the first Cuban Communist Party congress in six years, putting to rest a spate of rumors that he was in precarious health. Mr. Castro dwelled on the tribulations Cuba has experienced since the collapse of the Soviet Union, blaming the United States for most of them.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Anger at Failed Assassination  In the aftermath of a bungled Israeli attempt to assassinate a Hamas leader in Jordan, Foreign Minister David Levy of Israel said he had considered resigning, and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat complained that King Hussein was meddling in Israeli-Palestinian affairs. Still, a joint Israeli-Palestinian committee on economic cooperation held its first meeting in seven months, and there were unconfirmed reports that Benjamin Netanyahu was prepared to release $50 million in funds owed to the Palestinian Authority.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Chinese Dissident Emigrates  A Chinese dissident has left the country and flown to New York, a rights group in Hong Kong said. The dissident, Zhang Lin, was able to leave under a change in policy that now allows people considered ''troublemakers'' to emigrate, according to the Hong Kong group. Mr. Zhang, 34, was freed in June after spending three years in a labor camp, where he was sent for trying to set up an independent trade union.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-21</p>
        <p>Clinton's Advisers Urge Delay in Climate Goals  To the dismay of environmentalists seeking swift action to toughen the international treaty on climate change, President Clinton's senior economic and environmental advisers are urging him to delay for decades the time when the United States and other industrial nations must achieve deep reductions in the pollution that causes global warming.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Reno Defends Campaign Inquiry  Attorney General Janet Reno, challenged for months over the Justice Department's handling of the campaign finance investigation, offered an unusually aggressive defense of her agency's conduct and said she was mad at the White House for failing to inform her of videotapes of President Clinton with wealthy supporters.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Campaign Bill Fails Again  The Senate defeated a last-ditch effort to advance a campaign-finance bill, leaving the issue deadlocked. Senators repeated the same two procedural votes they took on Tuesday, and came up with the same results: a stalemate and no up-or-down decision on the legislation itself. The Senate majority leader, Trent Lott of Mississippi, has declared the bill dead, at least for this year.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Clinton to Unveil I.R.S. Plan  Responding to intense pressure from Congress to take stronger action to rein in the Internal Revenue Service, President Clinton will unveil proposals on Friday to overhaul management of the tax-collection agency, including establishment of an oversight board made up largely of private citizens.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Lead Found in Consumer Items  A wide variety of household objects, from children's raincoats and Barbie toys to telephone cords, have dangerously high levels of lead, Greenpeace said, citing tests it commissioned by an independent laboratory that frequently works for Government agencies.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Capital's Budget Is Passed  The House, with Speaker Newt Gingrich providing the deciding vote, narrowly approved a spending bill for the District of Columbia that includes a controversial Republican-drafted provision to give public school students vouchers to help pay tuition at private schools.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Findings on Jupiter's Moons  The discovery of organic compounds on two of Jupiter's moons increases the possibility that all of the elements for life are present on another of the planet's moons, Europa. The finding, from instruments on the Galileo spacecraft orbiting Jupiter, suggests that Europa may have all three of the ingredients scientists consider essential for life: an energy source, liquid water and organic molecules, a planetary scientist at the University of Hawaii said.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>McKinney Removed From Post  The Army said it had removed Gene C. McKinney from his post as the Army's top enlisted soldier, a day after the announcement that he would be court-martialed on charges of sexual misconduct involving six women.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>New York City Bars Swiss Bank From Offer  New York City has administered a major sanction against the Union Bank of Switzerland by barring it from participating in a billion-dollar bond offering, a move meant to underline disapproval of the way the bank has responded to the investigations into dealings with Nazi Germany, city officials said. The action was criticized by the State Department, which is attempting to coax Swiss banks to make larger contributions to humanitarian funds for Holocaust survivors and their heirs.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mayoral Candidates Debate  During a 90-minute debate marked by harsh exchanges, Mayor Giuliani and Ruth W. Messinger battled over where New York City has been in the last decade, its current condition,  and where the next Mayor should lead it.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Thruway Crash Snarls Traffic  A gasoline tanker exploded in flames after colliding with a car beneath the Governor Thomas E. Dewey Thruway in Yonkers, leaving one person dead, destroying a bridge supporting an essential thoroughfare and creating traffic chaos in the region that reverberated as far south as Maryland and as far north as Albany.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-30; E31-46</p>
        <p>Fo Wins Literature Nobel  Dario Fo, an iconoclastic Italian playwright-performer known for mixing wacky social farce with sharp political satire, was awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature, to the guarded amazement of Italy's literary establishment and the outright dismay of the Vatican, which he has often satirized. Critics have praised Mr. Fo's rare abilities as both writer and performer.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-17</p>
        <p>Germany Raises Key Rate  Germany's central bank raised a key interest rate for the first time in five years, a move that deflated stock markets across Europe and knocked down the value of the American dollar. Because many Western European countries have locked their currencies and monetary policies to those of the German mark, the change quickly led to rate increases in France, the Netherlands and Belgium. The move was made in part to insure that inflation did not emerge as the economy improved.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A22-23</p>
        <p>Editorials: New York's mayoral debate; Mr. Lott's arrogance; dynastic politics in North Korea.</p>
        <p>Columns: A. M. Rosenthal, Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>D19</p>
        <p>Bertrand Goldberg  An architect who literally changed the shape of the Chicago skyline in the 1960's with a pair of cylindrical apartment towers known as Marina City, he was 84.</p>
        <p>D19</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E43</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D18</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>D20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
