<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="946224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1D7173AF935A15754C0A961958260" item-length="1378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>U.S. Ambassador Is an Heir Right Under Swiss Eyes  Madeleine Kunin, the Swiss-born American ambassador to Switzerland, was surprised to discover her mother's name on the list of dormant accounts she herself had cajoled Swiss bankers to publish.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A complex set of schisms has developed between parties interested in the list of dormant World War II-era accounts published by Swiss banks. Paul Volcker, head of an independent investigative commission, warned that a class action suit that claims the assets of Holocaust victims are languishing in Swiss bank vaults could impede his team's progress and snuff out vital Swiss collaboration.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>U.S. Sees Bosnian Serb Scheme  Attacks on NATO troops are being orchestrated by some Bosnian Serb leaders, senior officials have concluded. The United States and NATO vowed to be resolute if ''even one more such action'' occurred. An American soldier's car was firebombed in Vlasenica, a village in the Serb-controlled part of Bosnia. No one was injured.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Untouchable to Lead India  K.R. Narayanan became India's first ''untouchable'' President. He told Parliament and the nation that his election to the post symbolized the long-awaited arrival of an era when ''the concerns of the common man'' had taken precedence in the nation's affairs.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>New Use for Cambodian Guns  Heavily armed troops were deployed around Phnom Penh, briefed to prevent high school students from cheating on their final exams. Photocopy shops were also guarded. Teachers in Cambodia are paid around $20 a month and bribery is widespread. The Government's crackdown follows its coup weeks ago.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Housing Angers East Jerusalem  The decision by the city government of Jerusalem to allow an American Jewish financier to build Jewish housing in an Arab neighborhood of East Jerusalem caught Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu off guard. He vowed to block the plan, which enraged Palestinians.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>Albright Attends Asean Talks  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright arrived in Malaysia for meetings with the Association of Southeast Asian Nations on how Hun Sen might be persuaded to hold legitimate elections after the coup in Cambodia. Washington has suspended its aid to Cambodia for 30 days.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Strike Talks Resume in Israel  Israel's skies were quiet as flights were stopped and telephone communications were often cut by workers striking against plans to privatize Bezek, the country's telephone monopoly. After Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu called the leaders of the Histadrut labor federation ''Bolshevik dinosaurs'' and they accused him of acting like a ''Bolshevik regime,'' the strike was called off and negotiations resumed.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>6-9</p>
        <p>Ex-G.O.P. Chairmen Offer Differing Accounts of Loan  One former Republican National chairman contradicted another as Richard Richards told the Senate campaign finance inquiry that Haley Barbour had stressed an urgent need for a $2.1-million foreign loan guarantee to ''free up'' funds for Republican candidates in their 1994 campaign to take control of Congress.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Congress Adds Disability Aid  Congressional Republicans bowed to President Clinton's demands and tentatively agreed to restore disability benefits to more than half a million legal immigrants, as budget negotiators broke a week-long impasse. Republicans also agreed to extend Medicaid coverage to tens of thousands of children who will lose their disability benefits under the welfare law that President Clinton signed last August.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Caretaker Seeks Reward  The caretaker who stumbled on the hideout of Andrew P. Cunanan has filed a lawsuit in Dade County Circuit Court to claim a total of $65,000 in reward money that had been offered for the apprehension of Mr. Cunanan. Mr. Cunanan, who had been sought in the murder of five men, including the fashion designer, Gianni Versace, fatally shot himself on a houseboat in Miami Beach after the police were called by the caretaker.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Notoriety Follows Ex-Suspect  It has been almost a year since Richard A. Jewell was first identified by The Atlanta Journal as the focus of the Federal investigation into the July 27 bombing at Centennial Olympic Park. It has been almost nine months since the Justice Department cleared him of any involvement in the deadly attack. And yet, Mr. Jewell, 34, lives with his unwanted notoriety every day and his bitterness remains strikingly raw.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>An internal Justice Department investigation into the bombing in Atlanta has concluded that a F.B.I. interview of Mr. Jewell was seriously flawed and resulted from a breakdown of communications within the law enforcement agency, Government officials said.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>G.M. and Union Reach Accord  General Motors and the United Automobile Workers reached a tentative pact to end a strike at a transmission factory that had forced the company to idle six other plants.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Chrysler Seats Scrutinized  The Chrysler Corporation sent instructional videos last week to about 135,000 customers after receiving complaints that child seats built into its mini-vans malfunctioned. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration is investigating the matter. No injuries or deaths have been attributed to the seats, Chrysler and the Federal safety agency said.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Senate Backs Treaty Change  The Senate unanimously urged the Clinton Administration not to pursue a treaty that would limit the industrial world's emissions of greenhouse gases unless the agreement requires developing countries to control their rapidly growing emissions at the same time.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>23-27</p>
        <p>Jury Finds Gigante Guilty On Racketeering Charges  Vincent Gigante, the enigmatic figure known for wearing a bathrobe and pajamas in public, was convicted of being a powerful Mafia kingpin who conspired in plots to kill other gangland figures and who ran lucrative rackets in New York. At the same time, though, the jury in Federal District Court in Brooklyn acquitted him of ordering three gangland killings and could not agree on charges that he ordered four other murders.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials said Mr. Gigante's racketeering conviction was unlikely to immediately weaken the Genovese crime family's powerful underworld position, since his active role as boss of the gang was reduced in recent years by intense law-enforcement pressure and a heart ailment.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Conviction in Cosby Trial  A Federal jury in Manhattan convicted Autumn Jackson of trying to extort $40 million from Bill Cosby, the man she claimed was her father. When she is sentenced on Oct. 22, she could receive a prison term of up to 12 years for her convictions on extortion and two other charges, conspiracy and traveling across state lines to commit the offenses. Her attorney said he planned to appeal the verdict and that Ms. Jackson is also considering a paternity suit against the actor.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Forced Labor Inquiry Expands  Federal agents raided two houses in a small North Carolina city and found more than a dozen illegal Mexican immigrants, most of them deaf, who officials believe were coerced into peddling trinkets at local shopping centers and giving most of the proceeds to ''bosses'' who oversaw the operation. The United States Attorney in Greensboro, N.C., said prosecutors were exploring whether the operation in Sanford was linked to the people charged last week in New York City with holding dozens of deaf Mexican peddlers in virtual slavery.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Crime Falls in New Jersey  Overall violent crime dropped 11 percent across New Jersey last year. The decline was far greater than the 7 percent decrease in violent crimes across the nation.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>33-47</p>
        <p>Columbia Chairman Resigns  The top executive of the world's largest health care company, the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation, resigned amid a growing criminal investigation of the company's business practices. Richard L. Scott, a man once celebrated as a visionary reformer of the American hospital industry, stepped down as chairman and chief executive, as did his handpicked lieutenant, David Vandewater.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>28-32</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>11-22</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>9-10</p>
        <p>Ben Hogan  The golfer, who won nine major championships from 1946 to 1953, was 84.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Bambi the pest; resuscitating the Mideast peace talks; Mr. Murdoch's payoff; Gail Collins on tired politicians.</p>
        <p>Column: Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>18</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>2-5</p>
        <p>U.S. Ambassador Is an Heir Right Under Swiss Eyes  Madeleine Kunin, the Swiss-born American ambassador to Switzerland, was surprised to discover her mother's name on the list of dormant accounts she herself had cajoled Swiss bankers to publish.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A complex set of schisms has developed between parties interested in the list of dormant World War II-era accounts published by Swiss banks. Paul Volcker, head of an independent investigative commission, warned that a class action suit that claims the assets of Holocaust victims are languishing in Swiss bank vaults could impede his team's progress and snuff out vital Swiss collaboration.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>U.S. Sees Bosnian Serb Scheme  Attacks on NATO troops are being orchestrated by some Bosnian Serb leaders, senior officials have concluded. The United States and NATO vowed to be resolute if ''even one more such action'' occurred. An American soldier's car was firebombed in Vlasenica, a village in the Serb-controlled part of Bosnia. No one was injured.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Untouchable to Lead India  K.R. Narayanan became India's first ''untouchable'' President. He told Parliament and the nation that his election to the post symbolized the long-awaited arrival of an era when ''the concerns of the common man'' had taken precedence in the nation's affairs.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>New Use for Cambodian Guns  Heavily armed troops were deployed around Phnom Penh, briefed to prevent high school students from cheating on their final exams. Photocopy shops were also guarded. Teachers in Cambodia are paid around $20 a month and bribery is widespread. The Government's crackdown follows its coup weeks ago.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Housing Angers East Jerusalem  The decision by the city government of Jerusalem to allow an American Jewish financier to build Jewish housing in an Arab neighborhood of East Jerusalem caught Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu off guard. He vowed to block the plan, which enraged Palestinians.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>Albright Attends Asean Talks  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright arrived in Malaysia for meetings with the Association of Southeast Asian Nations on how Hun Sen might be persuaded to hold legitimate elections after the coup in Cambodia. Washington has suspended its aid to Cambodia for 30 days.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Strike Talks Resume in Israel  Israel's skies were quiet as flights were stopped and telephone communications were often cut by workers striking against plans to privatize Bezek, the country's telephone monopoly. After Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu called the leaders of the Histadrut labor federation ''Bolshevik dinosaurs'' and they accused him of acting like a ''Bolshevik regime,'' the strike was called off and negotiations resumed.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>6-9</p>
        <p>Ex-G.O.P. Chairmen Offer Differing Accounts of Loan  One former Republican National chairman contradicted another as Richard Richards told the Senate campaign finance inquiry that Haley Barbour had stressed an urgent need for a $2.1-million foreign loan guarantee to ''free up'' funds for Republican candidates in their 1994 campaign to take control of Congress.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Congress Adds Disability Aid  Congressional Republicans bowed to President Clinton's demands and tentatively agreed to restore disability benefits to more than half a million legal immigrants, as budget negotiators broke a week-long impasse. Republicans also agreed to extend Medicaid coverage to tens of thousands of children who will lose their disability benefits under the welfare law that President Clinton signed last August.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Caretaker Seeks Reward  The caretaker who stumbled on the hideout of Andrew P. Cunanan has filed a lawsuit in Dade County Circuit Court to claim a total of $65,000 in reward money that had been offered for the apprehension of Mr. Cunanan. Mr. Cunanan, who had been sought in the murder of five men, including the fashion designer, Gianni Versace, fatally shot himself on a houseboat in Miami Beach after the police were called by the caretaker.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Notoriety Follows Ex-Suspect  It has been almost a year since Richard A. Jewell was first identified by The Atlanta Journal as the focus of the Federal investigation into the July 27 bombing at Centennial Olympic Park. It has been almost nine months since the Justice Department cleared him of any involvement in the deadly attack. And yet, Mr. Jewell, 34, lives with his unwanted notoriety every day and his bitterness remains strikingly raw.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>An internal Justice Department investigation into the bombing in Atlanta has concluded that a F.B.I. interview of Mr. Jewell was seriously flawed and resulted from a breakdown of communications within the law enforcement agency, Government officials said.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>G.M. and Union Reach Accord  General Motors and the United Automobile Workers reached a tentative pact to end a strike at a transmission factory that had forced the company to idle six other plants.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Chrysler Seats Scrutinized  The Chrysler Corporation sent instructional videos last week to about 135,000 customers after receiving complaints that child seats built into its mini-vans malfunctioned. The National Highway Traffic Safety Administration is investigating the matter. No injuries or deaths have been attributed to the seats, Chrysler and the Federal safety agency said.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Senate Backs Treaty Change  The Senate unanimously urged the Clinton Administration not to pursue a treaty that would limit the industrial world's emissions of greenhouse gases unless the agreement requires developing countries to control their rapidly growing emissions at the same time.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>23-27</p>
        <p>Jury Finds Gigante Guilty On Racketeering Charges  Vincent Gigante, the enigmatic figure known for wearing a bathrobe and pajamas in public, was convicted of being a powerful Mafia kingpin who conspired in plots to kill other gangland figures and who ran lucrative rackets in New York. At the same time, though, the jury in Federal District Court in Brooklyn acquitted him of ordering three gangland killings and could not agree on charges that he ordered four other murders.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials said Mr. Gigante's racketeering conviction was unlikely to immediately weaken the Genovese crime family's powerful underworld position, since his active role as boss of the gang was reduced in recent years by intense law-enforcement pressure and a heart ailment.</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Conviction in Cosby Trial  A Federal jury in Manhattan convicted Autumn Jackson of trying to extort $40 million from Bill Cosby, the man she claimed was her father. When she is sentenced on Oct. 22, she could receive a prison term of up to 12 years for her convictions on extortion and two other charges, conspiracy and traveling across state lines to commit the offenses. Her attorney said he planned to appeal the verdict and that Ms. Jackson is also considering a paternity suit against the actor.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Forced Labor Inquiry Expands  Federal agents raided two houses in a small North Carolina city and found more than a dozen illegal Mexican immigrants, most of them deaf, who officials believe were coerced into peddling trinkets at local shopping centers and giving most of the proceeds to ''bosses'' who oversaw the operation. The United States Attorney in Greensboro, N.C., said prosecutors were exploring whether the operation in Sanford was linked to the people charged last week in New York City with holding dozens of deaf Mexican peddlers in virtual slavery.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Crime Falls in New Jersey  Overall violent crime dropped 11 percent across New Jersey last year. The decline was far greater than the 7 percent decrease in violent crimes across the nation.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>33-47</p>
        <p>Columbia Chairman Resigns  The top executive of the world's largest health care company, the Columbia/HCA Healthcare Corporation, resigned amid a growing criminal investigation of the company's business practices. Richard L. Scott, a man once celebrated as a visionary reformer of the American hospital industry, stepped down as chairman and chief executive, as did his handpicked lieutenant, David Vandewater.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>28-32</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>11-22</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>9-10</p>
        <p>Ben Hogan  The golfer, who won nine major championships from 1946 to 1953, was 84.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Bambi the pest; resuscitating the Mideast peace talks; Mr. Murdoch's payoff; Gail Collins on tired politicians.</p>
        <p>Column: Maureen Dowd.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>18</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
