<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="19DIAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="966413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DA113FF93AA25753C1A961958260" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN M. ROSEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MERGERS  Another Suitor for MCI  Joining America's richest corporate takeover battle ever, the once-stodgy GTE, the nation's third-largest local telephone company, made an unsolicited $28 billion offer for MCI Communications. That's $2 billion less and two weeks later than a bid in stock from upstart Worldcom. The original suitor, British Telecommunications, with three board seats and 20 percent of MCI's shares, may now emerge as kingmaker.... An Italian insurer, Generali, made a hostile $9 billion bid for AGF of France, and the Zurich Group agreed to take over B.A.T. Industries' insurance business, creating one of the world's biggest financial services companies....Is accounting's Big Six (only a few years ago it was Big Eight) about to become Big Four? Ernst &amp; Young and KPMG Peat Marwick are expected to announce a merger, although neither would confirm it on Friday. Coopers &amp; Lybrand and Price Waterhouse have already agreed to merge.</p>
        <p>MARKETS  Earnings or Expectations?  It has become a mantra on Wall Street: the market is earnings-driven. Actually, it's greed-driven. Or, to put the matter more sophistically, is the existential question reality (earnings) or illusion (expectations thereof)? Compaq Computer reported a 41.6 percent profit increase on Thursday, topping the consensus forecast by 3 cents a share, but the market slashed 6 percent from its share price. The Street wanted more. Ford reached a 52-week high of $50.25 on Monday, beat forecasts with a 64 percent profit gain on Wednesday and saw its share price nibbled; G.M.also had solid earnings but slipped in price. Merck had a 19 percent increase but was a penny below estimates. Traders pushed its shares down 4.5 percent, and it helped grease the skids under the Dow, which finished the week at 7,847.03, off 198.17. Intel reported earnings of 88 cents a share, 3 cents below forecasts, and its shares, too, were pounded, despite news of an ultrafast microprocessor chip that it is developing with Hewlett-Packard. The Nasdaq composite lost 77.18 TK for the week, closing at 1,666.85. But the houses behind all this trading did well. Big profit gains were reported by Merrill Lynch, J. P. Morgan, Travelers, Bear Stearns and other Wall Street firms.</p>
        <p>GOLDMAN, SACHS  Teachers for a Day  To be fair, some on Wall Street are taking time off from doing well to do good. Some 2,000 employees of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, from secretaries through investment bankers, are serving as teachers for a day in New York City public schools. Besides giving lessons on basic business concepts, they hope to demonstrate to students that successful business people are not that different from them. Andy Derrow, above, skips rope in Inwood. ''In a lot of these neighborhoods the most successful business person is the local drug dealer,'' said Peter Mertens, executive vice president of Junior Achievement of New York, which coordinates the volunteers.</p>
        <p>NOBEL LAUREATES  A $1 Million Formula  Since the Bank of Sweden began awarding the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science in 1969, Americans have dominated the list of winners the way the Yankees once dominated the American League. This year Robert C. Merton, right, of the Harvard Business School and Myron S. Scholes, left, a Canadian-born professor emeritus at the Stanford Business School, will share the $1 million award for helping to devise a mathematical formula published in 1973 to answer a simple but seemingly insurmountable problem confronting Wall Street: how to measure the worth of an option? Their solution served as a foundation for today's vast global marketplace.</p>
        <p>AUTOS  A Clean, Lean Machine  Toyota beat its rivals -- not only Nissan and Honda, but also Detroit's Big Three and Volkswagen -- in unveiling the world's first gasoline-electric hybrid car. Hiroshi Okuda, Toyota's president, climbs into the car, the Prius, which the company said got as much as 66 miles a gallon during test drives while emitting only half the carbon dioxide of a regular gasoline engine. It will sell for $17,700 in Japan -- a loss leader, since analysts estimate it costs $41,000 to produce each one. Consider the difference an advertising expenditure, they said, as Toyota cloaks itself in the mantle of environmental leader. It may be sold in the United States in about six months, Toyata said.</p>
        <p>NEW ORLEANS  The House Goes Bust  New Orleans, whose unofficial motto is ''let the good times roll,'' has rolled snake eyes. Casino gambling, legalized by the Louisiana Legislature in the early 1990's, was to sweeten the city's allure to tourists and challenge Las Vegas and Atlantic City for a piece of the action. But over the last three years, all three downtown riverboat casinos, including the Flamingo, above, have foundered on economic, regulatory and legal difficulties. The city's only land-based casino has folded, too. Analysts cited high taxes on the take -- 18.5 percent, compared with an average of 7 percent elsewhere -- as a chief problem. Hillary Crain, chairman of the State Gaming Control Board, called for ''some creative financing.''</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY  The Taming of Inflation  Retail sales rose three-tenths of 1 percent in September and were revised upward for July and August. That pushed down bond prices on Wednesday, but analysts contended that the gain masked an economy that was actually decelerating. Indeed, the Consumer Price Index for September edged up a less-than-expected two-tenths of 1 percent. Because of inflation's slowdown, Americans who receive Social Security and other Federal benefits will receive an increase of only 2.1 percent in January, the second-smallest since automatic cost-of-living adjustments began in 1975.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MERGERS  Another Suitor for MCI  Joining America's richest corporate takeover battle ever, the once-stodgy GTE, the nation's third-largest local telephone company, made an unsolicited $28 billion offer for MCI Communications. That's $2 billion less and two weeks later than a bid in stock from upstart Worldcom. The original suitor, British Telecommunications, with three board seats and 20 percent of MCI's shares, may now emerge as kingmaker.... An Italian insurer, Generali, made a hostile $9 billion bid for AGF of France, and the Zurich Group agreed to take over B.A.T. Industries' insurance business, creating one of the world's biggest financial services companies....Is accounting's Big Six (only a few years ago it was Big Eight) about to become Big Four? Ernst &amp; Young and KPMG Peat Marwick are expected to announce a merger, although neither would confirm it on Friday. Coopers &amp; Lybrand and Price Waterhouse have already agreed to merge.</p>
        <p>MARKETS  Earnings or Expectations?  It has become a mantra on Wall Street: the market is earnings-driven. Actually, it's greed-driven. Or, to put the matter more sophistically, is the existential question reality (earnings) or illusion (expectations thereof)? Compaq Computer reported a 41.6 percent profit increase on Thursday, topping the consensus forecast by 3 cents a share, but the market slashed 6 percent from its share price. The Street wanted more. Ford reached a 52-week high of $50.25 on Monday, beat forecasts with a 64 percent profit gain on Wednesday and saw its share price nibbled; G.M.also had solid earnings but slipped in price. Merck had a 19 percent increase but was a penny below estimates. Traders pushed its shares down 4.5 percent, and it helped grease the skids under the Dow, which finished the week at 7,847.03, off 198.17. Intel reported earnings of 88 cents a share, 3 cents below forecasts, and its shares, too, were pounded, despite news of an ultrafast microprocessor chip that it is developing with Hewlett-Packard. The Nasdaq composite lost 77.18 TK for the week, closing at 1,666.85. But the houses behind all this trading did well. Big profit gains were reported by Merrill Lynch, J. P. Morgan, Travelers, Bear Stearns and other Wall Street firms.</p>
        <p>GOLDMAN, SACHS  Teachers for a Day  To be fair, some on Wall Street are taking time off from doing well to do good. Some 2,000 employees of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, from secretaries through investment bankers, are serving as teachers for a day in New York City public schools. Besides giving lessons on basic business concepts, they hope to demonstrate to students that successful business people are not that different from them. Andy Derrow, above, skips rope in Inwood. ''In a lot of these neighborhoods the most successful business person is the local drug dealer,'' said Peter Mertens, executive vice president of Junior Achievement of New York, which coordinates the volunteers.</p>
        <p>NOBEL LAUREATES  A $1 Million Formula  Since the Bank of Sweden began awarding the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Science in 1969, Americans have dominated the list of winners the way the Yankees once dominated the American League. This year Robert C. Merton, right, of the Harvard Business School and Myron S. Scholes, left, a Canadian-born professor emeritus at the Stanford Business School, will share the $1 million award for helping to devise a mathematical formula published in 1973 to answer a simple but seemingly insurmountable problem confronting Wall Street: how to measure the worth of an option? Their solution served as a foundation for today's vast global marketplace.</p>
        <p>AUTOS  A Clean, Lean Machine  Toyota beat its rivals -- not only Nissan and Honda, but also Detroit's Big Three and Volkswagen -- in unveiling the world's first gasoline-electric hybrid car. Hiroshi Okuda, Toyota's president, climbs into the car, the Prius, which the company said got as much as 66 miles a gallon during test drives while emitting only half the carbon dioxide of a regular gasoline engine. It will sell for $17,700 in Japan -- a loss leader, since analysts estimate it costs $41,000 to produce each one. Consider the difference an advertising expenditure, they said, as Toyota cloaks itself in the mantle of environmental leader. It may be sold in the United States in about six months, Toyata said.</p>
        <p>NEW ORLEANS  The House Goes Bust  New Orleans, whose unofficial motto is ''let the good times roll,'' has rolled snake eyes. Casino gambling, legalized by the Louisiana Legislature in the early 1990's, was to sweeten the city's allure to tourists and challenge Las Vegas and Atlantic City for a piece of the action. But over the last three years, all three downtown riverboat casinos, including the Flamingo, above, have foundered on economic, regulatory and legal difficulties. The city's only land-based casino has folded, too. Analysts cited high taxes on the take -- 18.5 percent, compared with an average of 7 percent elsewhere -- as a chief problem. Hillary Crain, chairman of the State Gaming Control Board, called for ''some creative financing.''</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY  The Taming of Inflation  Retail sales rose three-tenths of 1 percent in September and were revised upward for July and August. That pushed down bond prices on Wednesday, but analysts contended that the gain masked an economy that was actually decelerating. Indeed, the Consumer Price Index for September edged up a less-than-expected two-tenths of 1 percent. Because of inflation's slowdown, Americans who receive Social Security and other Federal benefits will receive an increase of only 2.1 percent in January, the second-smallest since automatic cost-of-living adjustments began in 1975.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
