<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bound by Suspicion</title>
    <meta content="CULT19X" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CULTURE ZONE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="CULTURE ZONE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paranoia</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Paranoia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D71039F93AA25752C0A961958260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bound by Suspicion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michiko Kakutani</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani Culture Zone column explores paranoid style that has invaded realm of culture; notes that conspiracy thinking has been used as narrative model by everyone from novelists to makers of blockbuster movies and television programs; says paranoia is remarkably efficient narrative device, and art of paranoia is a profoundly traditional form; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT DO ''THE X-FILES,'' ''INDEpendence Day'' and Joan Didion's latest novel have in common? What outlook do Louis Farrakhan and Pat Robertson share? What mind-set lumps together the C.I.A., space aliens, Communists, the Mafia and the United Nations as evil threats to our well being?</p>
        <p>The answer, of course, is paranoia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT DO ''THE X-FILES,'' ''INDEpendence Day'' and Joan Didion's latest novel have in common? What outlook do Louis Farrakhan and Pat Robertson share? What mind-set lumps together the C.I.A., space aliens, Communists, the Mafia and the United Nations as evil threats to our well being?</p>
        <p>The answer, of course, is paranoia.</p>
        <p>Back in the 70's, Henry Kissinger observed that ''even a paranoid can have enemies,'' and in recent years his observation seems to have become a kind of watchword in American politics, embraced by everyone from right-wing radicals who believe that the Federal Government planned the Oklahoma City bombing to black militants who believe that the AIDS virus was deliberately created in a laboratory to infect blacks.</p>
        <p>Although millennial anxieties seem to have fanned the flames of conspiracy thinking, paranoia itself in nothing new in American politics. (Remember the Communist plot to fluoridate American water?) What is new is the domino effect that this paranoid style is beginning to have in the realm of culture. In the last year or so, conspiracy thinking has been used as a narrative model by everyone from novelists to the makers of blockbuster movies. Paranoia is the motor that drives the cult TV show ''The X-Files'' as well as such new shows as ''Millennium,'' ''Dark Skies,'' ''The Pretender'' and ''Profiler.'' It's also the premise behind Mel Gibson's next movie,  ''Conspiracy Theory,'' which is about a paranoid cabdriver whose outlandish fears start coming true. The new card game Netrunner is set in a ''dark techno-future'' in which ''ruthless corporations scheme to accomplish secret agendas.'' And even the popular cult game that suggests that the actor Kevin Bacon is linked to every other actor in the world by no more than six degrees of separation conjures a universe of hidden connections.</p>
        <p>Why, it's almost enough to make Oliver Stone sound like a sensible human being.</p>
        <p>No doubt the new paranoid style in American arts reflects the national mood: Watergate taught us to be suspicious, and later investigations (from Iran-contra to Whitewater) further fueled those suspicions. As for the demise of the Communist threat, it left us not with a new sense of security but with a flurry of free-floating suspicions.</p>
        <p>At the same time, however, the art of paranoia is also a reflection of that oldest of human instincts -- the narrative impulse. In Didion's new novel, ''The Last Thing He Wanted,'' which pivots around an elaborate assassination plot, she describes storytellers as ''weavers of conspiracy'' who appreciate how every act has ''logical if obscure consequences.'' And in the work of Thomas Pynchon, vast conspiratorial networks metastasize, symbols of either the overwhelming nature of reality in our information-mad world or simply the yearning for meaning, experienced by poor delusional human beings.</p>
        <p>Add to this the fact that paranoia is a remarkably efficient narrative device. It enables its practitioners to build suspense, to indulge in portentous foreshadowing and to tie together incongruous loose ends into something that can be called a story. It can be used to create thrill-a-minute action films in which every offhand remark has a frightening payoff and huge, sprawling epics in which plausible resolutions exist only as projections in the paranoid audience's mind. After all, as every ''X-Files'' fan knows, the corollary to ''Trust No One'' is ''The Truth Is Out There'' -- somewhere.</p>
        <p>And yet the very notion that an explanation exists, that life is not random, is an old-fashioned, conservative view. Indeed, the last response to fin-de-siecle tensions -- that is, the modernism forged in the upheavals of turn-of-the-century Europe and galvanized by World War I -- produced not paranoia but an age (and art) of anxiety. A reaction against Enlightenment rationalism, modernism posited a world in which truth is, at best, subjective and logical explanations are suspect. Its esthetic lessons were the very opposite of those advanced by today's purveyors of paranoia. Instead of connecting events into conspiratorial plots, modernism gave us an esthetic of irony, ambiguity and fragmentation. (Think Kafka, think T. S. Eliot.) Instead of a world of secret cabals, it gave us a shadowy realm of radical discontinuity. Instead of omnipotent fixers like Cancer Man -- the ''X-Files'' figure, supposedly involved in everything from J.F.K.'s assassination to the rigging of Buffalo Bills games -- it gave us alienated loners acting on whim and impulse.</p>
        <p>We are once again on the brink of a new century, faced with mind-boggling changes like the breakdown of cold-war politics, the proliferation of new technologies and growing tensions among the races and sexes. One reaction -- apparent in rap music and avant-garde fiction -- has been to push discontinuity further, to celebrate incoherence. Another reaction, the paranoid reaction, has been to embrace an esthetic that does not mirror indeterminacy but defies it.</p>
        <p>Shows like ''The X-Files,'' ''Dark Skies'' (which suggests that many recent historical events, including the assassination of J.F.K., are connected to a secret alien invasion) and ''Millennium'' (which suggests that ''all of this violence you read about in the paper these days may not be random'') supposedly play to our worst neurotic fears. In reality, they actually help contain those worries by offering pat, systematic answers and a rationalistic (if ultimately irrational) view of the world.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the art of paranoia turns out to be a profoundly traditional form, as reassuring, in its twisted way, as the old-fashioned detective story, which offers a similar Manichaean realm of clearly defined villains and innocents, victims and victimizers and readily decodable patterns.</p>
        <p>A Government cover-up of pyramids discovered on Mars? An alien conspiracy to accelerate the greenhouse effect and wreak havoc on Earth? The mark of the beast in the Universal Product Code? However upsetting such beliefs may be, they also imply an orderly cosmos in which causality still obtains, human (or alien) will is paramount and inefficiency and accidents are unknown. Nothing is unexplained in the paranoid's universe; nothing is incoherent.</p>
        <p>No wonder a poster in Mulder's ''X-Files'' office reads, ''I Want to Believe.''</p>
        <p>CULTURE ZONE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
