<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greetings Seasoned With Partisan Wit</title>
    <meta content="T23HOLI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greeting Cards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas Trees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capitol (Washington, DC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">White House (Washington, DC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Lanny J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">White House (Washington, DC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paper and Pulp</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0D6153EF930A15751C1A961958260" item-length="963" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greetings Seasoned With Partisan Wit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christmas cards sent out in Washington reflect spirit of partisanship, as jingle of fund-raising and issue promotion continues through the season; departing White House counsel Lanny Davis says he will not miss ugly level of nastiness and hatred toward Bill Clinton; Speaker Gingrich, lighting Capitol tree, gives television viewers 'gift' of moment of silence from him, Supreme Court has usual party in camera, while White House reporters slake themselves at annual trough (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Call it residual meanness or the Ghost of Government Shutdowns Past. But there is little sense of truce this holiday season in the partisan energies that fuel the city's hammering, steaming work world of politics.</p>
        <p>Wary as Bob Cratchit on his clerk's stool, Lanny J. Davis, the White House counsel who specializes in defending President Clinton from scandal attacks in the news media, fetched up a worrisome lump of coal last week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Call it residual meanness or the Ghost of Government Shutdowns Past. But there is little sense of truce this holiday season in the partisan energies that fuel the city's hammering, steaming work world of politics.</p>
        <p>Wary as Bob Cratchit on his clerk's stool, Lanny J. Davis, the White House counsel who specializes in defending President Clinton from scandal attacks in the news media, fetched up a worrisome lump of coal last week.</p>
        <p>''It seems to get angrier and nastier,'' Mr. Davis said, after finding amid his holiday mail another dark note from another American citizen who was threatening enough to require the forwarding of the missive to the Secret Service.</p>
        <p>Usually, Mr. Davis enjoys his role as a kind of strategic Santa in making public the White House's campaign finance ''document dumps'' by the sackful near midnight, or customizing another ''deep-background private placement'' -- a pre-emptive scoop for a reporter who has been good, not bad.</p>
        <p>But he will not miss the hate-mail wassail that goes with the job when he quits next month after a grinding year's service.</p>
        <p>''The level of nastiness and hatred'' toward Mr. Clinton generated by his critics is the single deepest impression Mr. Davis says he will take with him.</p>
        <p>''Christmas or non-Christmas, it's there and it's ugly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Cheerier in intent, if no less disapproving of the President, is the Coals for Clinton's Christmas card being sent about town by John M. Snyder, a lobbyist for the Citizens Committee for the Right to Keep and Bear Arms. The card's verse (''Campaign funds in desperate need/So what if principles he must concede?'') extends holiday wishes for the impeachment of the President. Oh, and for a Happy New Year ''free from Government infringement on the right to legitimate self-defense.''</p>
        <p>All manner of special-interest wishes festoon the holiday cards. ''Choice On Earth'' is the greeting of the Planned Parenthood Federation of America. And Public Campaign, the political reform lobby, offered a 12-stanza adaptation of ''A Visit From St. Nicholas'' to excoriate endless big-money solicitations:</p>
        <p>To the tip of corruption!</p>
        <p>To the edge of the law!</p>
        <p>Now dash away! Dash away!</p>
        <p>Dash away all!</p>
        <p>The season's sleeper card is from Representative Howard Coble, Republican of North Carolina. It is a celebration of Christmas 1990. ''I know, I know,'' begins the greeting from Mr. Coble, explaining the whole thing. Like so much of Vice President Al Gore's message lately, the simple Gore Christmas card has caused controversy because the $150,000 mailing was financed by the Democratic National Committee, leaving party rivals suspecting electioneering humbug over the next Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The jingle of fund-raising continues apace through the season and so do the fund-raising scandal investigations, although the Justice Department's special grand jury on the subject can be hard to convene these days, one prosecutor said, as members go off gift shopping.</p>
        <p>''Holiday spirit?'' one inquiry-shy Democrat responded furiously to a question. ''The holiday spirit of the House committee is to send U.S. marshals out flashing badges and guns to serve subpoenas on people, including a friend of mine who just got a new job in the private sector,'' he continued, finding the Republican-run inquiry by the Government Reform and Oversight Committee to be  an instrument of the season's you-better-watch-out dictum.</p>
        <p>Committee Republicans reply that marshal service is standard procedure. But the Democrat, self-protectively anonymous in his complaint, insists the spirit at work, despite the holidays, is intimidation.</p>
        <p>This is flatly denied by David Bossie, the committee's most feared and openly anti-Clinton staff investigator, who these evenings seems far from formidable. He is happy as an elf as he rides out with Santa on the big red engine from the Volunteer Fire Department in Burtonsville, Md., where Mr. Bossie lives in Spartan dedication in the firehouse. Far from doling subpoenas, he is distributing candy canes to suburban children who have been good for goodness' sake, or at least for the sake of any controlling legal authority.</p>
        <p>At the Capitol, Speaker Newt Gingrich thought of an unusual gift as he turned on the lights of the lawmakers' tree. ''We'll let C-Span watch a brief period of silence by Newt Gingrich, which will be a historic moment,'' he said, becoming quiet.</p>
        <p>If it is any comfort to Speaker Gingrich or President Clinton, a Fox News poll has found that most Americans think Santa Claus, fearless proponent of institutionalized giveaway, would enroll Democratic, if he could, while the Grinch Who Stole Christmas would register Republican.</p>
        <p>With or without such information, the work-place parties go forward, including the ''Thank God Kyoto's Over!'' gala at the Ozone Action lobbying offices, where celebrators just back from the environmental conference in Japan savored some personalized global warming.</p>
        <p>At the Justice Department, Attorney General Janet Reno stepped out from her party for a moment and could be seen alone gently swaying to the Christmas music in the corridor.  The holiday heavy-lifting award may go to Gen. Henry H. Shelton, the new Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, who scheduled three hourlong cocktail parties on Saturday. ''Civilian Informal'' the invitation ordered. Move out.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court, ever judicious, held its traditional judges-and-staff-only party in camera. The sound of caroling echoed through the hall of justice to the press room where uninvited reporters sat like urchins outside the jolly consensus.</p>
        <p>In contrast, reporters at a White House Christmas party slaked themselves in depth at the annual trough. The lamb chops were history early as journalists ate free, then got in the free-photograph line. There, the Clintons smiled patiently, serially, for each photo-op, while some of their severest critics approached with fawning grin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
