<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; Holiday gifts with U.S. identification numbers: baggy pants, suspenders, a vest to aid exercising.</title>
    <meta content="15PATE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chartrand, Sabra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E6DF173FF936A25751C1A961958260" item-length="1038" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; Holiday gifts with U.S. identification numbers: baggy pants, suspenders, a vest to aid exercising.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sabra Chartrand</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chartrand, Sabra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Items patented this year discussed as possible holiday gifts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the holidays approaching, shoppers clutching wish lists are mobbing stores, determined to find the perfect gifts. Here are some possibilities from inventors who won patents this year for their ideas:</p>
        <p>A teen-ager might want a pair of double baggy jeans patented by James Head of Hayward, Calif. The pants look like ordinary, oversized jeans with long, loose legs -- the style pioneered by rap singers. The jeans have two seat panels, though. The first is integral to the baggy pants; the second is overlaid on the first and is even baggier -- attached at the side seams and at the knees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the holidays approaching, shoppers clutching wish lists are mobbing stores, determined to find the perfect gifts. Here are some possibilities from inventors who won patents this year for their ideas:</p>
        <p>A teen-ager might want a pair of double baggy jeans patented by James Head of Hayward, Calif. The pants look like ordinary, oversized jeans with long, loose legs -- the style pioneered by rap singers. The jeans have two seat panels, though. The first is integral to the baggy pants; the second is overlaid on the first and is even baggier -- attached at the side seams and at the knees.</p>
        <p>So while the pants themselves appear several sizes too big for the average teen-ager and are designed to drip loosely from a wearer's hips, the second rear panel gives the impression of even greater sag and volume. The waistband of the pants is visible at the lower edge of the wearer's hips, but above the second panel. Its waistband hangs somewhere near the middle of the seat.</p>
        <p>For his contribution to fashion, Mr. Head won patent 5,689,832.</p>
        <p>A working woman might appreciate a pair of the ''suit-spenders'' named and patented by David Griffin of New York City. The accessory item looks like a pair of suspenders fashioned out of a suit or shirt collar. Or like a suit front with the jacket panels and arms missing, and only the collar remaining.</p>
        <p>At the waistband, the suit-spender attaches to trousers like conventional suspenders. Its collar can be notched like that of a man's suit jacket, straight-edged like many women's jackets, or have short tabs like a shirt collar. It might have a pocket embedded in one side of the front panel. Mr. Griffin imagines that his suit-spender, which can be made of fabric, leather or even fur, will allow women to spruce up casual clothes on dress-down Fridays at work, or jazz up an evening outfit.</p>
        <p>He received patent 5,682,619.</p>
        <p>A newly patented vest might please those who work or exercise outdoors. Vernon Jackman of Little Ferry, N.J., has designed a battery-powered vest that can flash messages to warn drivers and others that the wearer is about to start moving, or is continuing to move, turn left or right, cross a road or stop. Mr. Jackman thinks the vest would be useful for runners, bicyclists, skaters, road workers, school patrol members or traffic officers.</p>
        <p>The vest's wearer would activate the signals with a small switch panel, which could be removed to hang from bicycle handlebars. Mr. Jackman holds patent 5,690,411.</p>
        <p>If walking is the exercise of choice, then Juan Quinones of Pembroke Pines, Fla., has an invention that will add an upper body workout. He has patented a belt with O-rings sewn to its sides and several latex bands attached to the rings. Weights are attached to the ends of the bands. In one design, heavier or lighter weights can be used. The bands can be adjusted in length. While walking, the person swings the weights forward and backward to exercise his back, chest, shoulders and arms. Mr. Quinones received patent 5,690,595.</p>
        <p>For children bored with Barbie dolls and train sets, there is a simulated erupting volcano. Caleb Crowell of Montclair, N.J.; George Hom of New York City and Laura Patterson of Port Washington, N.Y., have patented a toy that when squeezed, expels a gaseous material through a nozzle in a device shaped like a volcano with a crater. The toy has two inner chambers holding chemicals. Squeezing forces chemicals from the first chamber through a tube into the second, where the reaction of the two creates gases that are expelled upward through another tube to the crater. The inventors received patent 5,692,945.</p>
        <p>For those whose cars lack air-conditioning or who like to sit in the backyard on hot days, Ling Chih-Hung of Taiwan offers a seat cushion with a built-in fan. The pillow has air outlets scattered across its surface. Inside, the cushion is supported by cylinders with air spaces between them. An attached bag holds a blower with a filter that connects to an inlet on the cushion. An electric power source must be hooked to the blower, which, when turned on, forces air into the cushion through the passages around the cylinders and expels it through the outlets on the seat.</p>
        <p>Anyone seated on the cushion would be cooled by the device with patent 5,692,952.</p>
        <p>Lovers of risotto or polenta might also love the self-stirring cooking attachment invented by Jeffrey LaVelle of Edmonds, Wash., and Paul Shemeta of Seattle. The stirring mechanism sits over a pot and functions like an electric mixer. A bracket connects the attachment to the pot handle, and the cook is free to add ingredients.</p>
        <p>A motor extends over the pot's opening, and a shaft in the pot ends with a paddle. The paddle, which is set at an angle and has holes drilled through it, rests on the bottom of the pot. The inventors received patent 5,617,774.</p>
        <p>Gifts appropriate for New Year's Eve could be streamers that hold confetti or confetti launchers that fire colored bits of paper. Both were invented by James Watkins of Poolesville, Md.</p>
        <p>The streamers are made of a slick plastic film rolled into spirals. As the streamers are rolled up, confetti is placed among the layers. The confetti is made of similar plastic and some tissue paper. When thrown, the streamer unwinds in midair and the confetti is released. That device received patent 5,620,354.</p>
        <p>The confetti launcher is a tube filled with confetti or streamers, connected to a carbon dioxide cartridge or similar source of compressed gas. The launcher sprays confetti through the air. It received patent 5,620,355.</p>
        <p>Patents are available by number for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
