<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982399"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7D8143EF931A15751C1A961958260" item-length="1394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Voters in Okinawa Oppose New U.S. Military Base  Okinawans voted against construction of an offshore American military base that Japan and the United States had been planning for more than a year.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Koreans Pressure President  President Kim Young Sam of South Korea, left, faced growing pressure to yield some authority to his rival, President-elect Kim Dae Jung, before the formal transfer of power on Feb. 25.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Voters in Okinawa Oppose New U.S. Military Base  Okinawans voted against construction of an offshore American military base that Japan and the United States had been planning for more than a year.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Koreans Pressure President  President Kim Young Sam of South Korea, left, faced growing pressure to yield some authority to his rival, President-elect Kim Dae Jung, before the formal transfer of power on Feb. 25.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Turkey Buys Boeing Planes  The chairman of Turkish Airlines sealed a deal in Washington on Friday to buy up to 49 Boeing airliners. Under normal circumstances, it would have taken several months for the Turkish State Planning Office and the Cabinet to approve the choice, but with Turkey's objection to the European Union's decision to defer action on its application for membership, and Turkey's desire for stronger ties with the United States, the Government expedited the approvals.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Israel Claims Land in West Bank  Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu asserted Israel's claims to the West Bank up to the Jordan River. He also asserted that any final peace agreement must maintain security zones and Jewish settlements there. Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, described the territorial claim as a ''flagrant violation'' of signed agreements.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Turnout Light in Serb Election  Light voter turnout in Serbia's fourth presidential election in three months raised the possibility that a fifth election would have to be called. The race has Vojislav Seselj, an extreme nationalist, facing Milan Milutinovic, the Yugoslav Foreign Minister and a protege of President Slobodan Milosevic, who is constitutionally barred from seeking a third term.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Not Guilty Pleas in Egypt  Two Egyptian police generals accused of negligence and facing court martial in the killings of 58 foreign tourists and 4 Egyptians in Luxor pleaded not guilty at an Interior Ministry hearing, police officials said. The officers were dismissed from their jobs after Muslim militants attacked the tourists at an archeological site last month.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Press)</p>
        <p>In Mexico, a Daunting Year  In his first year as Mexico's Attorney General, Jorge Madrazo Cuellar investigated his predecessor's role in a scheme to rig a murder trial, put the country's drug czar on trial on charges of collaborating with drug traffickers and dismissed all 2,300 anti-narcotics officers, requiring them to take polygraph exams before they could be rehired. ''This is like trying to fix a car that's going 120 miles an hour,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-25</p>
        <p>Snowboarders Go From Pests to Saviors  Snowboarders, the bane of ski areas a decade ago, now represent the industry's salvation. The National Ski Areas Association estimates that 4.5 million snowboarders will hit the slopes of America this winter -- three times the number in 1990. With snowboarders expected to buy 20 percent of the nation's lift tickets this winter, the sport is injecting new life into the industry. At the same time, the number of skiers has gradually declined during the 1990's, from slightly over 11 million to an expected 10.5 million this season.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Challenging Extradition Policy  A Federal appeals court in San Francisco has heard arguments in a case that could force the Government to renegotiate most of its international extradition treaties and abandon its century-old practices for arresting and detaining fugitives found in the United States. At issue in the case, Parretti v. United States, is a distinctive feature of extradition law: the Government's ability to obtain an arrest warrant for a fugitive found in the United States without showing ''probable cause'' to believe the fugitive committed a crime abroad.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Anonymity for Jurors  Lawyers are expected to complete jury selection in the Unabom murder trial of Theodore J. Kaczynski today. Although jury selection has been held in open court since Nov. 12, much information will not be publicly disclosed about the 12 jurors and 6 alternates, such as their names, and in most cases, their ages, the communities where they live, how much education they have, whether they have children, whether they are married, and where or whether they work. News organizations are challenging the judge's decision, and First Amendment experts say the case is one of the first to test a growing trend across the country in which judges are increasingly trying to shield the identities of jurors.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>A Study in Intrigue  Jeffrey Sonnenfeld of Emory University, an adviser to top chief executives and a frequent commentator on corporate intrigue, is at the center of a bizarre swirl of events that could be written up as a case study in one of his own classes.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Celebrated Chef Departs  The chef Jean-Pierre Goyenvalle, who came to work in Washington in 1960, is hanging up his toque, at least for now. Saturday was the last night at his third Washington restaurant, Le Lion d'Or.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>For Manhattan Traffic, Worst May Be Yet to Come  Traffic congestion in Manhattan is greater than ever, city officials said, and it will probably get worse. Even before the holiday season, which has brought about 90,000 more vehicles into Manhattan each day, the daily influx was higher than ever -- more than 900,000 cars, trucks and buses. Many arteries leading to the heart of the city are congested as never before. Experts say that there are not only more cars, but also bigger cars -- limousines and sport utility vehicles -- and that traffic is clotting longer during the rush hours.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Police Under Surveillance  The Police Department is reviewing the actions of a former commander of the 111th Precinct in Queens who set up hidden surveillance equipment inside a station house during an investigation of complaints of racial harassment among officers.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-10  Sanders Ends Jets' Season  Barry Sanders scored the winning touchdown and became the third player in N.F.L. history to run for more than 2,000 yards in a season as Detroit ended the Jets' playoff hopes by beating New York, 13-10.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B6-7</p>
        <p>Dawn Steel  The first woman to head a major movie studio and who played a prominent role in advancing other women to top jobs in Hollywood was 51.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>Juzo Itami  A film director who gained acclaim for his satirical portraits of Japanese society, he was 64.</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>David N. Schramm  An astrophysicist who was an eminent authority on the Big Bang theory of how the universe was born, he was 52.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-16</p>
        <p>Health Plans Change Rules  Managed-care companies nationwide are starting to cut some of the generous benefits that millions of elderly Americans on Medicare counted on when they signed up with health maintenance organizations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Florida Faults Prudential  A two-year investigation of the Prudential Insurance Company of America, the nation's largest insurer, led officials in Florida to conclude that the company had deliberately set out to cheat its customers for more than a decade. ''Prudential trained its agents to mislead, misrepresent and defraud policyholders,'' an internal report on the investigation said.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Dow Jones Unit Ailing  A confidential sales document indicates that rising costs and slumping revenue are likely to result in a $69 million operating loss this year for Dow Jones Markets.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>'Titanic' on Top  ''Titanic,'' the most expensive movie ever made, was No. 1 at the box office in its first weekend. By some estimates, ''Titanic'' will have to gross $350 million to break even.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Facing up to global warming; glimmerings in the Middle East; the adoption of common sense; Amtrak's survival wager.  Columns: Anthony Lewis, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>C9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
