<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yawn. A global-warming alert. But this one has solutions.</title>
    <meta content="13SCEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Economic Scene" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="908517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Economic Scene"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Redefining Progress (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3DE163FF930A25751C0A961958260" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yawn. A global-warming alert. But this one has solutions.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Passell discusses proposal by Redefining Progress, group of academic economists, for creation of international emissions trading system to combat global warming, in which already rich economies would pay emerging economies to use less energy and less carbon intensive fuels as they develop (Market Place) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STERNLY worded petitions and ringing screeds of principle are as much a part of campus life as grade inflation -- which is why Washington rarely takes them seriously. But the nation's movers and shakers would do well to pay attention to a statement on global warming by some 2,000 mostly academic economists.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the signatures collected by Redefining Progress, a group of policy-minded social scientists based in San Francisco, range from the newish left (Duncan Foley of Barnard College) to the skeptical center (James Heckman of the University of Chicago) to the libertarian right (Gordon Tullock of the University of Arizona). ''Market-based approaches to coping with climate change generate as much consensus among economists as free trade,'' explains Paul Krugman of M.I.T., one of the organizers of the statement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STERNLY worded petitions and ringing screeds of principle are as much a part of campus life as grade inflation -- which is why Washington rarely takes them seriously. But the nation's movers and shakers would do well to pay attention to a statement on global warming by some 2,000 mostly academic economists.</p>
        <p>For one thing, the signatures collected by Redefining Progress, a group of policy-minded social scientists based in San Francisco, range from the newish left (Duncan Foley of Barnard College) to the skeptical center (James Heckman of the University of Chicago) to the libertarian right (Gordon Tullock of the University of Arizona). ''Market-based approaches to coping with climate change generate as much consensus among economists as free trade,'' explains Paul Krugman of M.I.T., one of the organizers of the statement.</p>
        <p>More important, the statement focuses on what is now regarded by insiders as a make-it-or-break-it issue in slowing atmospheric warming: designing an international system that permits rich economies to contribute cash in lieu of emissions reductions. ''Allowing some to pay others to reduce greenhouse emissions could reduce the total cost by 80 to 90 percent,'' estimates William Nordhaus, an economist at Yale and another organizer of the statement.</p>
        <p>Like any committee looking for consensus, the drafters of the climate statement cast their net widely. ''We believe that global climate change carries with it significant environmental, economic, social and geopolitical risks, and that preventive steps are justified,'' the unshocking introduction reads.</p>
        <p>Those who read on, however, will discover there is meat on these bones: ''Sound economic analysis,'' the authors argue, ''shows that there are policy options that would slow climate change without harming American living standards.''</p>
        <p>And what might these policy options be? Here, the drafters stake out a position that seems almost obvious to economists, but has barely entered the consciousness of environmental policy makers. ''A cooperative approach among nations is required -- such as an international emissions trading agreement,'' the statement asserts.</p>
        <p>To understand where the economists really want the diplomats to go, consider where we are now. Current rates of deforestation and combustion of carbon-based fuels -- coal, oil, gas -- are adding carbon dioxide into the atmosphere faster than the oceans can absorb it. The higher carbon dioxide concentrations trap solar energy. Rising temperatures will likely change weather patterns radically and raise the level of the oceans.</p>
        <p>Governments of all the major economies are vaguely committed to containing greenhouse gas emissions before once-a-century hurricanes become an annual event in the Caribbean, Kansas turns into a dust bowl and the Bay of Bengal doubles in size at the expense of Bangladesh. But the emphasis is on the vague: the process of setting emissions targets or creating political institutions to enforce the targets is in the talking stage.</p>
        <p>That's where the economists' statement fits in. ''We wanted to be there early,'' said Stephen DeCanio of the University of California at Santa Barbara, ''before governments and politicians were locked into positions.'' Specifically, the statement is intended to give the Clinton Administration some help in pressing the idea of creating an international market in emissions permits at the next global meeting on climate change, set for Kyoto, Japan, in December.</p>
        <p>The idea is simple. If and when world leaders start to deal with the practical issues, they are apt to set national targets for containing emissions that will be very expensive to meet in the rich industrial economies, and probably won't be honored in the large emerging economies like China, Russia, India and Indonesia.</p>
        <p>Creating an emissions trading system that allows already rich economies to pay the emerging economies to use less energy and less carbon-intensive fuels as they develop offers a double dividend. It reduces the cost for developed countries, in turn reducing the chances their legislatures will balk. And it creates a pool of capital to be used as an incentive to push emerging economies toward environmentally benign growth.</p>
        <p>Translation: Getting, say, China or India to switch from coal to natural gas, or to encourage energy conservation by charging world market prices at home would be a lot easier if they were paid billions of dollars each year to do it.</p>
        <p>Not every economist who favors emissions trading signed the statement. ''I'm worried it will be used at Kyoto to commit America to useless, expensive unilateral actions in reducing emissions,'' says Robert Hahn, an economist at the American Enterprise Institute.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Nordhaus has very different worries. ''Economists haven't been important players in environmental policy over the last 30 years,'' he said. ''This time we could make a difference.''</p>
        <p>Economic Scene</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
