<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sealing Mount Garbage; Closing Staten Island's Fresh Kills Dump Is an Operation of Staggering Complexity</title>
    <meta content="21DUMP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Fresh Kills (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">santation department (nyc)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toy, Vivian S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Landfill</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6D9173EF932A15751C1A961958260" item-length="2434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sealing Mount Garbage; Closing Staten Island's Fresh Kills Dump Is an Operation of Staggering Complexity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toy, Vivian S</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Covering and sealing Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island will be an enormous undertaking for New York City, costing more than $1 billion and taking five years; intricate network of wells, pipes, underground walls and treatment stations must be constructed to protect surrounding neighborhoods from foul gases and water emanating from rotting refuse; city will have to monitor and maintain site for 30 years; only a skeleton crew will remain of the 600 sanitation workers now at Fresh Kills, whose work always carried a certain cachet on the force and who consider it a well-oiled and carefully orchestrated operation; most likely use for site will be as parkland, with nature walks and possibly ball fields; photos; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Ray Maggi casts his gaze across the mounds of trash at the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island, he feels a certain sense of ownership that might puzzle most New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''I remember when the place was flat,'' said Mr. Maggi, a crane operator who has worked at Fresh Kills for 24 years. Then, pointing to the mountains of garbage that rise as high as a 17-story building, he declared like a proud parent, ''Everything you see here, I had something to do with.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Ray Maggi casts his gaze across the mounds of trash at the Fresh Kills landfill on Staten Island, he feels a certain sense of ownership that might puzzle most New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''I remember when the place was flat,'' said Mr. Maggi, a crane operator who has worked at Fresh Kills for 24 years. Then, pointing to the mountains of garbage that rise as high as a 17-story building, he declared like a proud parent, ''Everything you see here, I had something to do with.''</p>
        <p>For him, the city's plan to close Fresh Kills by Dec. 31, 2001, elicits a jumble of emotions that begins with sadness and ends with awe. Since Mr. Maggi knows precisely what it took to build Fresh Kills into the world's largest dump, he can imagine what it will take to shut it down.</p>
        <p>You don't just latch the gate and walk away. Closing the 3,000-acre landfill -- a property three and a half times the size of Central Park -- will cost the city more than $1 billion. Covering and sealing the vast trash heaps will take about five years. An intricate network of wells, pipes, underground walls and treatment stations must be constructed to protect surrounding neighborhoods from the foul gases and water emanating from the rotting refuse.</p>
        <p>And under Federal law, the city must continue to monitor and maintain the shuttered landfill for 30 years after the last truckful of apple cores, diapers and plastic sandwich bags is dumped there.</p>
        <p>Even as Mr. Maggi and the 600 other people who work at Fresh Kills continue to move nearly 11,000 tons of garbage each day from barges to trash heaps, a few dozen engineers and outside consultants pore over maps and charts at Sanitation Department offices in lower Manhattan to plot the landfill's demise. Hundreds of workers for private contractors have already started capping parts of the landfill and building the maintenance systems.</p>
        <p>The methods that will be used to cover the trash and control emissions are well established. But because of its size and age -- Fresh Kills opened in 1948, when environmental controls were almost unheard of -- the effort to close the dump safely and efficiently will tax the limits of modern landfill technology.</p>
        <p>''I can't think of anything that would come close to being as massive as closing Fresh Kills,'' said Ed Repa, a spokesman for Environmental Industry Associations, a waste management trade group. ''Building the Pyramid of Khufu would be miniature compared to what they're going to do at Fresh Kills.''</p>
        <p>The Questions</p>
        <p>Size of Project Leads to Doubts</p>
        <p>Given the scope of the project, some wonder whether the city will be able to meet the deadline set by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and Gov. George E. Pataki, who acted under intense political pressure from Staten Islanders, an important Republican constituency.</p>
        <p>''When you have such magnitude of garbage, it makes you wonder if this plan to close the place is really going to work,'' Mr. Maggi said one day recently after finishing a shift behind the gears of a 400-ton crane, a colossal machine that lifts 4 tons of garbage each time it sinks its giant maw into a garbage-filled barge.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration contends that it is not only possible but that work is well under way. ''We're ahead of schedule,'' said Randy M. Mastro, Deputy Mayor for Operations. ''And when Fresh Kills is finally closed, we will have put the city on a much sounder environmental course.''</p>
        <p>But environmentalists and neighborhood activists worry that the city and state, which have reneged on countless promises since Fresh Kills opened, will make decisions without getting sufficient public input.</p>
        <p>''How are we going to grapple with the legacy of nearly 50 years of virtually unregulated dumping of everything on Staten Island?'' said Larry Shapiro, an attorney with the New York Public Interest Research Group. ''Closing this landfill has got to be one of the most complicated engineering feats probably in the history of the United States, and some of the choices made ought to be subject to public review and discussion.''</p>
        <p>City officials maintain that planning for the closing began long before the Mayor set a date last year and has always been readily shared with local residents. While pieces of the blueprint have since been redrafted to accommodate the 2001 deadline, actual work to close the dump began as early as 1992.</p>
        <p>The demise of Fresh Kills will also mark a major turning point in the way New York City deals with its garbage. For the first time, the city will not be burying or burning even an ounce of its own trash, instead paying to dispose of it elsewhere. The city started exporting the Bronx's garbage to a landfill in Virginia last July. Sending household trash from all five boroughs out of the city will double, possibly even triple, the roughly $100 million a year it costs the city to bury it at Fresh Kills.</p>
        <p>The Challenge</p>
        <p>Daunting Amount Of Liquid and Gas</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and residents  began fighting to shut the dump even before it opened in 1948. Complaints reached a fever pitch in recent years when the stench from the landfill started to overwhelm residents even in the winter. Over the years, the city has closed dozens of landfills and incinerators, and Fresh Kills has been the sole recipient of the city's garbage since 1991.</p>
        <p>Despite the daunting costs, officials insist they will find the money to close the landfill on schedule.</p>
        <p>The city has already spent about $115 million of a budgeted $350 million to close the landfill. Most of that money has been used to cover two of the four mountains that make up Fresh Kills and to start building an underground wall and the wells and pipes needed to control landfill emissions. Treatment plants to convert the gases and liquids into less offensive, if not exactly palatable, forms have also been built but will have to be expanded in coming years.</p>
        <p>An additional $700 million will be spent to maintain the landfill, with the city expecting to spend about $24 million a year until 2031. By then, the emissions are expected to have diminished significantly.</p>
        <p>For now, though, the liquids and gases produced by Fresh Kills seem limitless. About 30 million cubic feet of landfill gas now goes into the air each day. And each day, surrounding waterways absorb about a million gallons of leachate -- a technical term for rainwater that has turned into a dark brown ooze after running through the garbage and percolating in the mound. Together, the gases and liquids give Fresh Kills -- and depending on how hard the wind is blowing, nearby communities -- its distinctive and nose-pinching odor.</p>
        <p>Sanitation officials say studies have shown that as unappealing as garbage may be, the landfill does not pose any health hazards to nearby residents, though environmentalists and Staten Islanders remain skeptical. They also fear that leachate from the landfill could be hazardous to fish, birds and other wildlife.</p>
        <p>The Plan</p>
        <p>Likely Future Use Is as Parkland</p>
        <p>No detailed plans have been worked out for what to do with the Fresh Kills real estate, though there is little likelihood of significant development. Most likely, the area will become parkland, with nature walks and possibly ball fields.</p>
        <p>But first, three major tasks must be accomplished. First, the active dumping slopes must be covered and sealed. Second, the landfill gas must be captured and piped to a treatment plant to be cleaned and either sold as energy or ''flared'' in a controlled burning. And third, the leachate must be captured and channeled to a treatment plant to be purified.</p>
        <p>Whenever garbage is dumped at the landfill, a series of trucks rolls in to cover it with about a foot of soil and to sprinkle pine oil deodorant to try to reduce the stench. Covering and sealing a landfill section requires many more layers of soil between a plastic membrane and a plastic screen, each layer carefully planned by engineers to maximize the stability of the garbage mountain and minimize the amount of water that gets into the mound. Finally, grass and plants are grown on top for an esthetic touch. The entire process costs the city about $225,000 an acre.</p>
        <p>Dave Hendrickson, a Department of Sanitation supervisor, held up a piece of the heavy plastic membrane during a recent tour of Fresh Kills and said, ''This stuff is guaranteed for 30 years, but a regular garbage bag takes about 100 years to decompose, so you can just imagine how long this will really last.''</p>
        <p>From afar, the two mounds that are already covered could be mistaken for natural hills. But within nose-shot, the essence of garbage is overwhelming. Sanitation officials say the system of gas wells and pipes under construction would control about 90 percent of the landfill's gases, significantly decreasing the odor.</p>
        <p>About 400 wells have been dug into the landfill to help capture the gas, which is formed as garbage decomposes and is composed mainly of methane and carbon dioxide. About 150 of the wells are connected to pipes that run directly to a treatment plant that now converts 10 million cubic feet of landfill gas every day into about 5 million cubic feet of a natural gas product. The gas is sold to Brooklyn Union Gas, which uses it to heat 14,000 Staten Island homes.</p>
        <p>The gas collected in the remaining 250 wells now is released into the air. But when the gas system is completed within two years, there will be 700 wells across the landfill connected to the existing plant or to a second one that has yet to be built. The city is negotiating to sell the currently unprocessed landfill gas and is also seeking a state permit to flare any unsold gas.</p>
        <p>Handling the leachate poses even greater difficulties. While new landfills since 1991 have been required to have an impermeable liner to stop leachate from seeping into groundwater, Fresh Kills has just a layer of natural clay at the bottom.</p>
        <p>To control leakage, the city started building two underground clay walls last year that will extend about eight miles and nearly surround the landfill. The walls, which descend 10 to 55 feet, will stop most of the leachate from flowing out. Miles of pipe also will be laid below ground within the wall to collect and transport the leachate to the treatment plant.</p>
        <p>That plant, built in 1994, now treats about 200,000 gallons of leachate a day with aerobic organisms that eat up the ammonia and organic materials that give leachate its odor and unappealing brown color.</p>
        <p>The leachate and gas treatment plants will operate well into the 21st century, but after 2001, the $100 million worth of trash-moving equipment at Fresh Kills will be sold, probably to third world nations and anyone else in the market for massive bulldozers, cranes and compactors.</p>
        <p>The People</p>
        <p>Crew of WorkersTo Shrink Sharply</p>
        <p>There is a human dimension to the task as well. After the landfill is officially closed, the ranks of city workers who now attack the garbage with cranes, trucks and even boats will largely disappear. A skeletal crew of security people will remain, along with a few dozen workers at the privately run treatment plants being built to purify the landfill's gases and liquids.</p>
        <p>Despite its drawbacks as a malodorous garbage heap, Fresh Kills has long maintained a certain cachet for the city's sanitation workers. Those who work there proudly proclaim it a well-oiled and carefully orchestrated operation.</p>
        <p>''When I first got here, there were no paved roads here -- we just drove on top of the garbage,'' said Richard Dieck, a tractor operator who has worked at Fresh Kills for 17 years. ''Now it's clean compared to what it was.''</p>
        <p>Steve Violetta, a supervisor at the landfill for the last decade, said that he waited three years to get his job there and that there was a time when only people with 15 years of seniority could even dream of working at Fresh Kills. ''Believe it or not, it's a really a nice place to work,'' Mr. Violetta said. ''It's like a close neighborhood and you make a lot of friends when you're here.''</p>
        <p>Many of the workers will be reassigned. But people like Mr. Maggi, who is 58, will either retire or be laid off.</p>
        <p>''There's no place else in the city that uses a 400-ton crane,'' Mr. Maggi said. ''So I'm looking to retire.</p>
        <p>''You don't like to see people lose their jobs. But I guess it has to be because it's the right thing for the environment.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
