<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Alters His Approach Over Warming</title>
    <meta content="22CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E3DC153EF931A15753C1A961958260" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Alters His Approach Over Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration, stung by complaints that it moves too slowly against global warming, will propose set of rewards for companies that cut emissions of heat-trapping gases faster than Government would require under pending international treaty; seeks to mollify environmental groups and European nations that have been demanding deep, early emissions cuts; tests plan's appeal among business and environmental groups (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stung by complaints that it is moving too slowly against global warming, the Clinton Administration has devised a set of rewards for companies that  cut emissions of heat-trapping gases  faster than the Government would require under a pending international treaty.</p>
        <p>The approach, to be outlined in a speech by President Clinton on Wednesday, is meant to mollify environmental groups and European nations that have been demanding deep, early cuts in emissions. The  Administration has resisted those calls out of fear that aggressive action might cause too much economic pain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stung by complaints that it is moving too slowly against global warming, the Clinton Administration has devised a set of rewards for companies that  cut emissions of heat-trapping gases  faster than the Government would require under a pending international treaty.</p>
        <p>The approach, to be outlined in a speech by President Clinton on Wednesday, is meant to mollify environmental groups and European nations that have been demanding deep, early cuts in emissions. The  Administration has resisted those calls out of fear that aggressive action might cause too much economic pain.</p>
        <p>Even as the White House wrestled with the details of its latest plan today, aides were testing its appeal among business and environmental groups whose support could be crucial to its success. Administration officials and people who had been briefed described the plan's outlines, but cautioned that important elements had still not been decided by Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>The United States is under pressure to explain its approach this week, as negotiations resume in Bonn on a treaty to reduce the world's emissions of pollutants that are building up in the atmosphere and threatening to disrupt the planet's climate during the coming century.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide, the main heat-trapping gas, comes primarily from the burning of fossil fuels. With the economy booming and energy cheap, United States emissions have been accelerating.</p>
        <p>The Administration's new approach has several elements, which include these:</p>
        <p>*Energy producers and consumers that reduce emissions quickly would get credits, so that those moving fastest would benefit the most when, as the Administration envisions, the Government issues pollution permits that companies can buy and sell. This trading of pollution permits is the Administration's favored approach for letting the marketplace choose how to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>*Instead of a fixed deadline for  reducing emissions, the United States would try to achieve its target within a few years on either side of a deadline. That would help to encourage companies to comply earlier.</p>
        <p>*Tax incentives and subsidies, requiring Congressional approval,  would also prompt companies to move more quickly.</p>
        <p>The new approach would not substantially change the Administration's basic goal: to require in the new treaty that industrial nations emit no more of the gases in 2010 than they did in 1990.</p>
        <p>The Administration is expected to  propose at the talks in Bonn that industrial nations meet that target, as an average, during a multiyear period falling around 2010, probably during the period from 2008 to 2012. The Administration will also suggest that deeper reductions occur in later periods, perhaps a 5 percent cut below 1990's levels as 2020 approaches.</p>
        <p>A White House official cautioned tonight that although President Clinton was attracted to the multiyear-average approach, he was concerned that the plan was too complicated and might have to be simplified.</p>
        <p>By giving extra credit to those companies that lowered emissions fastest, the new approach would seek to put the United States, whose steadily growing emissions currently account for nearly a quarter of the world's output of greenhouse gases, on a downward slope as early in the 21st century as possible.</p>
        <p>The initial reductions would be modest, but they would come soon. To meet the targets envisioned by the Administration, the United States would, as a practical matter, have to cut emissions by about 1 percent a year on average beginning in 1998.</p>
        <p>To help reverse the current trend of growing emissions, the Administration would seek from Congress a package of about $5 billion in research spending, tax credits and other incentives for companies. This package would be in addition to the plan for pollution permit credits.</p>
        <p>The Administration also wants to make sure that the deregulation of the electric utility industry does not lead to growing emissions of carbon dioxide from power plants that burn coal and other dirty fuels. Mr. Clinton is expected to address this issue as well in his new plan.</p>
        <p>In drafting the speech that he is to deliver on Wednesday, at the National Geographic Society here, the President drew upon a set of options presented by senior economic and environmental aides last week. He basically took the most aggressive approach offered -- one that environmental groups had criticized as too weak -- and tried to strengthen it by providing more incentives for early action.</p>
        <p>With the details still incomplete tonight, business and environmental groups that were told of the plan were reluctant to pledge their support.</p>
        <p>''It could be viewed as a good minimum ante to put on the table in the negotiations'' at Bonn, said Howard Ris, executive director of the Union of Concerned Scientists, which favors deep cuts in emissions. ''The President has clearly rejected the do-nothing approach.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
