<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Hones Sales Pitch On Global Warming Pact</title>
    <meta content="T04CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="962384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georgetown University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E4DC123DF937A35753C1A961958260" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Hones Sales Pitch On Global Warming Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration seeks to broaden support for its global warming pact before its negotiators present specific targets and timetables for greenhouse gas emissions; toward that end, carefully selected greenhouse experts will assemble for daylong conference at Georgetown University (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As it seeks a new treaty to fight the threat of global warming, the Clinton Administration has turned marketing on its head: first comes the sales pitch, and later the product will be unveiled.</p>
        <p>Call it publicity or call it education, the results of the campaign that is now reaching full boil could profoundly affect the proposal for controlling climate change that the Administration takes to Kyoto, Japan, in December. There, the nations will try to agree on a binding treaty to limit emissions of heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide, which comes mostly from burning fossil fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As it seeks a new treaty to fight the threat of global warming, the Clinton Administration has turned marketing on its head: first comes the sales pitch, and later the product will be unveiled.</p>
        <p>Call it publicity or call it education, the results of the campaign that is now reaching full boil could profoundly affect the proposal for controlling climate change that the Administration takes to Kyoto, Japan, in December. There, the nations will try to agree on a binding treaty to limit emissions of heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide, which comes mostly from burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>The Administration wants to broaden its public support before its negotiators present specific targets and timetables for greenhouse gas emissions. The proposals will probably not be the steep and urgent cuts supported by American environmentalists and some foreign nations, but at least a meaningful first step toward someday stabilizing the levels of greenhouse gases that have been relentlessly building up in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>It's a tough sell.</p>
        <p>''If anybody tells you this is not a tough issue, they are lying,'' said Todd Stern, a senior White House aide who is coordinating climate policy. ''We have to put together options for the President that are economically viable, that are environmentally viable, and that are politically viable -- both in the international and domestic context.''</p>
        <p>''We have to stand on the rooftops and scream, because there are those who have a vested interest in not seeing action on climate change,'' said Kathleen A. McGinty, the chairwoman of the Council on Environmental Quality, referring to powerful opposition to a treaty, led by energy-intensive industries and their labor unions.</p>
        <p>Ms. McGinty said the Administration hoped to present details of the United States proposal when international negotiators next met in Bonn later this month.</p>
        <p>But even before those details are known, the campaign to build support for it comes to a climax of sorts on Monday when carefully selected greenhouse experts assemble at Georgetown University for a daylong conference.</p>
        <p>The meeting is half a conventional policy seminar where ecologists, economists and lobbyists can have their say. But it also resembles a political convention, a chance to put Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore in the best possible light as they take on a knotty political problem.</p>
        <p>''What I want to do is to deal with the central political problem here,'' Mr. Clinton told a group of television weather forecasters on Wednesday. ''I don't mean political in terms of party politics, I mean political in how the body politic, how our society responds to this.''</p>
        <p>He also said: ''Right now, while the scientists see the train coming through the tunnel, most Americans haven't heard the whistle blowing. They don't sense that it's out there as a big issue. And I really believe as President, you know, one of my most important jobs is to tell the American people what the big issues are that we have to deal with.''</p>
        <p>To counter the Administration, its critics have mounted a $13 million advertising campaign contending that a treaty binding industrial nations to deep cuts in energy use would be unfair because it would not make the same demands on developing countries. And, they argue, such a treaty would damage the United States economy by imposing energy taxes or other punitive costs on companies that burn fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>For its own sales pitch, the White House is deploying many tools of a classic political campaign: stump speeches and photo opportunities,  the carefully staged meetings, alliances with advocacy groups, and the nearly daily events, like the meeting with the meteorologists, aimed at reaping free media coverage.</p>
        <p>The campaign began shortly after President Clinton, under pressure from environmentalists and European nations to act more aggressively, told the United Nations in June that he would marshal American public support for a treaty.</p>
        <p>He assigned Mr. Stern, an experienced White House aide, as a temporary climate ''czar'' to coordinate the Administration's efforts. Mr. Stern brought additional staff from other agencies to help out, and began laying the groundwork for Monday's high-profile public meeting.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore also met with small groups of sympathetic business leaders, scientists and environmental advocates.</p>
        <p>Cabinet members hit the hustings, giving dozens of speeches to push the Administration's cause.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, for example, Interior Secretary Bruce Babbitt told the Union of Concerned Scientists, which supports controls on greenhouse gas emissions, that success in the cause ''depends on all of us, together, taking up the burden of advocacy.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, environmental advocacy groups have been working strenuously to influence the press and the public, to mobilize their millions of members, and to persuade the Clinton Administration to call for deeper, faster cuts in greenhouse gas emissions. The scientists' group issued a call by about 1,500 scientists, including 102 Nobel laureates, more than half of all the living laureates in the sciences, urging significant cuts by industrial nations in the next few years, followed eventually by limits on the developing world. The statement called global warming ''one of the most serious threats to the planet and to future generations.''</p>
        <p>In a poll conducted in August, before the industry's ad campaign began to air, about three-quarters of registered voters surveyed said they believe that global warming is a serious problem and that a treaty with deep cuts in emissions is needed. The Mellman Group Inc. conducted the poll for the World Wildlife Fund.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
