<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pioneer in the Nuclear Age, and in Its Steep Decline</title>
    <meta content="NUKE.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="962643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E2DF1F3AF936A35753C1A961958260" item-length="1503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pioneer in the Nuclear Age, and in Its Steep Decline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article traces rise and fall of Connecticut's nuclear power industry over past two decades; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEREVER America is going, Connecticut often seems to get there first, and that includes nuclear technology. The state was one of the first to jump in, and now  seems on its way to being one of the first out.</p>
        <p>The technology once seemed a natural fit for the state, which has only two traditional energy resources: the little bit of hydropower that nurtured its earliest industries, and the technological sophistication of its work force, from engineers to technicians to mechanics. It also has a thirst for energy for its high-tech factories, offices and homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEREVER America is going, Connecticut often seems to get there first, and that includes nuclear technology. The state was one of the first to jump in, and now  seems on its way to being one of the first out.</p>
        <p>The technology once seemed a natural fit for the state, which has only two traditional energy resources: the little bit of hydropower that nurtured its earliest industries, and the technological sophistication of its work force, from engineers to technicians to mechanics. It also has a thirst for energy for its high-tech factories, offices and homes.</p>
        <p>But the idea that nuclear power is dependable and economical has come and gone over the past 20 years, and the idea that power can be cleanly, cheaply supplied by fossil fuels imported from far away has gone and then come back.</p>
        <p>The changes are stunning. Twenty years ago, Connecticut Yankee was on its way to earning the record as the largest single nuclear producer of electricity in the world, in the vanguard of a wave of reactors that were supposed to total 1,000 by the turn of the century. Millstone 1 and 2 were helping to minimize the impact of oil price shocks, and Millstone 3,  under construction, promised to further loosen the treacherous noose of oil dependency.</p>
        <p>But that was not all. Stamford was headquarters to Combustion Engineering, which built nuclear reactors  and in Uncasville, another firm built nuclear fuel. Electric Boat, in Groton, turned out a steady stream of nuclear-powered submarines and the United States Navy ran a landlocked submarine reactor in Windsor Locks, for training.</p>
        <p>Almost all of that has gone away.</p>
        <p>''We wouldn't have predicted it,'' said Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, of the industry's withering. ''Ultimately, I think it's bad.'' Nuclear reactors can run well, he said, even if Northeast Utilities' reactors don't. ''In Connecticut the problem is basically a screw-up in the management,'' he said. Someday, he said, more will be built. ''Not tomorrow, but probably in a decade or more -- more like two or three decades -- we will come back to nuclear power because we'll be concerned about the impact of fossil fuels on the economy,'' he said. In the very long term, he said, ''people will start to realize we're running out of fossil fuels.''</p>
        <p>Maybe so, but Northeast, which often got more than half its electricity from reactors, got just 28 percent last and this year it will be less.</p>
        <p>Amazingly, the system still works.  Everyone can see that, because the lights stay on and because a web page (http://www.cvx.com/) gives an up-to-the-hour picture of the balance between supply and demand.</p>
        <p>But as a technology, nuclear power seems to be withering. Combustion Engineering was swallowed by a European conglomerate, Asea Brown Boveri, in 1990, and there are no nuclear reactors to build in this country; only a few around the world. The site of the nuclear fuel plant is prospering as a casino. Of the 259 power reactors ever ordered in this country, more than half were canceled.  The Navy closed its training reactor, because it sends fewer crews to sea now. That has also cut most work at Electric Boat, which is building one last big attack submarine.</p>
        <p>And Connecticut Yankee, reliable though it was for most of its life, turned out to be not worth running. Last month the state even argued that it has been poorly run, in a way that increased contamination and the decommissioning cost.</p>
        <p>More stunning yet, though, is Millstone 3, a multibillion-dollar miscalculation. When ground was broken it was supposed to cost $400 million. By the mid 80's the price had risen to over $3.5 billion, but Northeast Utilities said its power would be cheaper than oil-fired power as early as 1989.</p>
        <p>The utility hired a forecasting company, then called Data Resources Inc., which said that not only would oil be expensive, but that low-sulfur fuel, the kind Northeast burned, would reach $181 a barrel by the year 2000. If that seemed outrageous, Data Resources had company; the United States Department of Energy's Energy Information Administration predicted a world oil price of nearly $300 per barrel by then, assuming continuing high inflation. There seemed no alternative to pressing on.</p>
        <p>But for the last few years oil has sold for about $20 a barrel. And most electricity comes from something even cheaper: natural gas. Twenty years ago, Connecticut was at the end of a very long natural gas pipeline from the Gulf Coast, meaning shortages for the state; now, it is in the middle, served by a pipeline from Canada as well, the Iroquois. ''The Iroquois was a signpost of things to come,'' said James R. Shuckerow, the director of wholesale power contracts at Northeast. ''No longer will New England be at the end of the pipeline. In many respects, we are at the beginning.'' Gas coming over the Iroquois is mostly from western Canada, but Mr. Shuckerow and others say that newly discovered gas in the Canadian Maritimes may put New England even nearer the beginning of the distribution system.</p>
        <p>Joel M. Rinebold, the executive director of the Connecticut Siting Council, a state agency that passes judgment on each proposed new power plant, said that today, ''There are more options and alternatives, as simple as that.'' These include conservation and new technologies that are just becoming competitive or are expected to be soon: solar cells, wind turbines and fuel cells, the latter manufactured in the state.</p>
        <p>Those alternatives have had a profound effect on the value of Millstone 1 and 2, because they determine the value of a kilowatt-hour, and thus the value of the plants' output and therefore of the plants themselves. The Department of Public Utilities Control asked Northeast to recalculate reactor value on that basis, and in July the company said that the value to its customers of operating Millstone 1, as opposed to closing it, was a scant $68.9 million. Millstone 2 was $488 million.</p>
        <p>People with long experience in the energy field, nuclear and otherwise, are stunned by the changes. Paul Blanch, for example, moved to Connecticut in 1966, as an instructor at the submarine reactor in Windsor Locks, and went on to become a nuclear engineer at Northeast Utilities. He, like the state, has made a long journey since then; he found technical flaws with nuclear reactors and said the company harassed him as a result; eventually the Nuclear Regulatory Commission agreed. He quit four years ago but was rehired in February, to help fix the company's nuclear problems.</p>
        <p>Two years ago the four reactors represented about one-sixth of the capacity the state would need on a peak day, and to Mr. Blanch and many others, the idea of the state doing without all of them was impossible. ''I didn't think we could possibly survive,'' he said. ''It's all economics right now,'' said Mr. Blanch. ''The Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the nuclear industry is well aware of the non-competitive or borderline competitive situation nuclear is in.'' Companies have been scrimping, he said, and the government is ignoring safety problems because ''they have to not impose anything significant that's going to cause economic hardship on these utilities.''</p>
        <p>At the Connecticut Siting Council, Mortimer A. Gelston, the chairman, said that in the next year and a half the state as likely to see 1,500 megawatts of new natural gas-powered electric generating capacity. That is almost half as big as the shut-down nuclear capacity.</p>
        <p>''We're going to be pretty dependent on gas, which bothers me,'' said Mr. Gelston. That fuel, he said, is ''nothing but a stop gap measure to get us out of this hole we're in.'' He and others point out that at the time Millstone 3 was being built, natural gas was in such short supply that a Federal law barred construction of new plants using it. He, too, is surprised that the state has done well with no reactors. Of Northeast's executives, he said, ''they all must have gone to church every Sunday to get through this year.''</p>
        <p>The constant factor is that nothing has been constant. Mr. Rinebold, of the siting council, also teaches a course in environmental issues at Central Connecticut State University in New Britain. As teaching materials he keeps the old Data Resources projections ''as an example of the dynamics of our fuel supply,'' he said. ''Even with the best projections, the best forecasts, things change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
