<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hot and Bothered</title>
    <meta content="19QUAMMET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Quammen, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schneider, Stephen H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Laboratory Earth (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DF1738F93AA25752C0A961958260" item-length="1368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hot and Bothered</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Quammen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Quammen, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Quammen reviews book Laboratory Earth: The Planetary Gamble We Can't Afford to Lose by Stephen H Schneider; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LABORATORY EARTH</p>
        <p>The Planetary Gamble</p>
        <p>We Can't Afford to Lose.</p>
        <p>By Stephen H. Schneider.</p>
        <p>174 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LABORATORY EARTH</p>
        <p>The Planetary Gamble</p>
        <p>We Can't Afford to Lose.</p>
        <p>By Stephen H. Schneider.</p>
        <p>174 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Basic Books. $20.</p>
        <p>The question of global climate change stands high among the most important of all those boring science-and-policy issues that we citizens read about with a sense more of duty than curiosity. To say not quite the same thing in almost the same language, it also stands high among the most boring of the important ones. Unless you're the sort of person who can spend hours engrossed by the Weather Channel, chances are that you find no drama in being informed, say, that automobiles and power plants and giant herds of flatulent cattle and other artifacts of human civilization may raise the temperature of our planet by a few degrees centigrade over the next hundred years. Chances are that descriptions of the role played by carbon dioxide and methane, and of the countervailing role played by something called sulfate aerosols, don't move you -- not even to fits of gloom. The abstractness and complexity of the subject are like a great groaning flywheel, ever steady against the prospect of a lurch into narrative excitement.</p>
        <p>This may be why the greenhouse effect (to be precise: the heat-trapping properties of the earth's natural atmospheric gases, an ancient and undisputed phenomenon that may or may not come to be catastrophically increased by industrial-age emissions) has become befogged, over the past several decades, by two forms of vaporous excess: an excess of simplified doomsaying and an excess of belligerently agnostic complacency. Stephen H. Schneider, a highly respected (on one side of the barricades, anyway) expert on global climate dynamics, seems to have written his new book with a resolute intent to avoid excess. Although his opponents would call him a doomsayer, ''Laboratory Earth'' doesn't justify that label. It's a concise, sensible, even-tempered discussion that reflects both the subject's scientific and sociopolitical intricacy and, unfortunately, its tendency to seem heart-squashingly dull.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schneider, a climatologist at Stanford University and a frequent expert witness before Congressional committees, has written or co-written several earlier books, including ''The Genesis Strategy'' (1976), ''The Coevolution of Climate and Life'' (1984) and ''Global Warming'' (1989). Each of them, published while the computational tools of climatology were rapidly improving, dealt in part with the scientific evidence that human activities might be forcing our planet's climate toward some sort of disastrous shift. ''Are we entering the greenhouse century?'' he asked in the subtitle of ''Global Warming,'' and his answer -- controversial back then -- was that we already had.</p>
        <p>Against this background, it's fair to ask what ''Laboratory Earth'' offers that Mr. Schneider's other books didn't. New scientific data? New analytical results derived from vastly better computer modeling? Fresh insights into the sociopolitical dimension? A more persuasive literary package? Sorry to say, the book itself seems confused on that question. Almost the only thing recommending it to a wider audience than the earlier books addressed is that it has fewer pages. In his preface, Mr. Schneider thanks the entrepreneurial agent and thinker John Brockman for ''reminding me that such an exercise in brevity increases the reach of one's ideas,'' but is that necessarily so? Ineffectively organized and indifferently written, possibly because Mr. Schneider has been over this material too many times, ''Laboratory Earth'' is a short book that seems long.</p>
        <p>In the early chapters, he lays a groundwork for intelligent discussion but declines to present any forceful thesis. His subject, he says, will be ''climate change and its ecological and societal implications.'' He gives a bullet-point list of big issues in the field of earth systems science that he means to explore, including ''How long did it take for the climate and life to evolve this far?''; ''How does the earth work as a coupled set of subsystems that includes living and nonliving parts?''; and ''How are people disturbing the earth system?'' But bullet points are a shorthand substitute for strong prose, not a form of it. Likewise, he mentions teasingly that one of the most serious global concerns is ''the combined or synergistic effects of habitat fragmentation and climate change,'' postponing elaboration until later. I suppose that this much might have satisfied me, swept me along with a sense of foreboding; it didn't. When the subject of human-caused climate change finally makes its full entrance, on page 50, bringing a certain menacing energy into a droopy tale, it seems as welcome as Milton's Satan.</p>
        <p>There have been some notable developments in this field since Mr. Schneider's last book, but he saves them for later chapters. One is the convergence of climate change studies with studies of species extinctions in fragmented landscapes, leading both climatologists and ecologists to recognize that ecosystem disruptions and losses of biological diversity may be -- as Mr. Schneider rightly noted in his comment about synergistic effects -- among the worst consequences of abrupt climate change. Many species can't migrate toward higher latitudes, since they live marooned in islandlike fragments of habitat, and they may not survive global warming if they can't migrate. Mr. Schneider's treatment of this is clear and useful.</p>
        <p>Another timely subject is what ecologists call ''ecosystem services,'' those crucial natural functions performed by richly diverse ecosystems and depended upon by humans and other life-forms. Such services (creating soil, providing oxygen, filtering wastes, maintaining precipitation cycles and much more) can be jeopardized by the destructive synergy of fragmentation, climate change and extinction -- and there aren't likely to be any practicable technological substitutes at the global scale. ''Therefore, society shouldn't just bank on the stereotypical faith of economists that we'll somehow find an affordable substitute for each crisis and buy our way out,'' Mr. Schneider warns.</p>
        <p>Still another development, more newsy, occurred in December 1995, when the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (a multinational and multi-scientist body under the joint aegis of the United Nations Environmental Program and the World Meteorological Organization) completed its Second Assessment Report, which incorporated the cautious but epochal statement that ''the balance of evidence suggests that there is a discernible human influence on climate.'' In plainer words: Stephen Schneider was right, and the greenhouse century has in fact begun. Mr. Schneider himself recounts this on page 88, at the end of a rambling paragraph about recent improvements in computer models, where the significance of the 1995 declaration seems lost. A newspaper editor would have told him, ''Steve, you buried your lead.''</p>
        <p>His assessment of the ''climatic fingerprint pattern'' emerging from those modeling results is judicious, hampered only by a dizzying mix of metaphors: ''Whether this new fingerprint evidence qualifies as a smoking gun or is simply an improbable coincidence will spawn debate for years. In the meantime, Laboratory Earth continues to grind out the answer -- experimentally.''</p>
        <p>Should we care whether our scientists mix a few metaphors when they try to present their results and their ideas to a popular audience? Should we care whether they can shape a book or produce an engaging blend of exposition and argument? Maybe not. In general we should give them thanks, not cavils. But we can still hold them to standards of effective communication -- especially so if they profess strong concern, as Mr. Schneider repeatedly has, for heightened public awareness and understanding. Readers have a right to expect enticement and persuasion from a book of popularized science, not just graceless instruction.</p>
        <p>In an area so complicated, so crucial and so fraught with controversy as global climate change, nonexperts like you and me can probably never bone up enough to make our own independent prognoses based on sheer data. We rely on experts to help us see what the numbers, the models, the inputs and parameters actually mean -- and, since the experts disagree, we rely on our own decisions about which of them we should trust. Among the scientists I trust is Stephen Schneider. But that doesn't make him a good writer.  David Quammen's most recent book is ''The Song of the Dodo: Island Biogeography in an Age of Extinctions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Quammen's most recent book is ''The Song of the Dodo: Island Biogeography in an Age of Extinctions.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
