<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mir Astronauts Now Facing Uncharted Territory</title>
    <meta content="30ORBI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="940660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mir (Space Station)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tsibliyev, Vasily</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0D61E31F933A05755C0A961958260" item-length="1544" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mir Astronauts Now Facing Uncharted Territory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Astronauts aboard trouble-plagued Mir space station are entering uncharted territory in efforts to repair damage caused by collision with supply vehicle that has caused severe loss of electrical power; Russian commander, Vasily Tsibliyev, veteran cosmonaut who has had five spacewalks and has spent long periods in space, bluntly warns he has no training in repair techniques, and that performing mission successfully will be impossible; apart from lack of training, crew must also use special equipment only now being built; job will require unusual dexterity, including maneuvering through narrow portal to damaged module while wearing bulky space suit; photo; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vasily Tsibliyev, the commander of the Mir space station, has had his brushes with danger. The veteran Russian Air Force pilot, 43, has made five space walks and spent long periods in space. He had endured a dangerous fire, which filled Mir with smoke and splattered chucks of molten metal around the space station.</p>
        <p>But the commander, who carries a plastic rabbit from his daughter as a good luck charm, has his worries about his new assignment: repairing the stricken Mir, which was severely damaged last week when a supply vehicle crashed into it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vasily Tsibliyev, the commander of the Mir space station, has had his brushes with danger. The veteran Russian Air Force pilot, 43, has made five space walks and spent long periods in space. He had endured a dangerous fire, which filled Mir with smoke and splattered chucks of molten metal around the space station.</p>
        <p>But the commander, who carries a plastic rabbit from his daughter as a good luck charm, has his worries about his new assignment: repairing the stricken Mir, which was severely damaged last week when a supply vehicle crashed into it.</p>
        <p>''I have never done this kind of work,'' he bluntly warned officials at Russia's ground control center.  ''Without training, it will not be possible to do this job.''</p>
        <p>By all accounts, restoring Mir to a functioning space station is a tricky venture into uncharted territory. Not only has the crew never trained for the mission, but they will also use special equipment that is only now being built.</p>
        <p>The job will also require unusual dexterity, including maneuvering through a narrow portal to the damaged module while wearing a bulky space suit.</p>
        <p>To choreograph the intricate maneuvers, earth-based Russian astronauts will experiment on an underwater mockup at Star City, the astronaut training center outside Moscow. Their results will be transmitted to Mir so the crew can practice before putting them to the test. If the Mir crew fails, it may even be necessary to abandon ship.</p>
        <p>Michael Foale, the American member of the team of three astronauts in it, will be waiting in the Soyuz spacecraft docked alongside while the repairs are attempted in case the crew has to make a quick getaway and blast off to earth.</p>
        <p>Life on Mir has never been glamorous. Mr. Foale has likened it to camping out in a dirty, old car. Others have not been so kind. Launched by the Soviet Union in 1986, Mir was originally intended to stay in space for only five years. After 11 years, it has had more than its share of problems.</p>
        <p>In February, an oxygen canister caught fire, filling the station with smoke. In March, oxygen generators failed. In April, the cooling system began leaking antifreeze.</p>
        <p>But Russia has powerful political and economic incentives to keep Mir in operation. The space station is not only a symbol of Russia's prowess in space, but is also a source of income for its fiscally strapped space agency. The United States is paying the Russians $470 million to train astronauts on Mir as part of a program to develop a new international space station.</p>
        <p>NASA officials insist that the training and scientific experiments make the Mir missions worthwhile. But that assumes that the major problem on Mir caused by the collision last week -- the lack of adequate power to carry out scientific experiments -- can be remedied.</p>
        <p>The crisis erupted on Wednesday when an unmanned Progress supply craft crunched into the 140-ton Mir while Mr. Tsibliyev was practicing a docking maneuver. The collision  punctured Spektr, one of the station's seven modules and the module that housed medical experiments.</p>
        <p>''I heard the big thump and a thud,'' Mr. Foale later recounted. ''Almost immediately, we heard a hiss and felt pressure falling.''</p>
        <p>The crew rushed to seal off the damaged module, disconnecting cables that carry power from Spektr's three undamaged solar arrays to the rest of the station and closing the hatch.</p>
        <p>''Since that exciting moment, we've been dealing with all the problems that resulted from that,'' Mr. Foale said. The main problem has been a power shortfall, as Spektr's solar arrays accounted for much of Mir's energy supply.</p>
        <p>As the crew shut down air conditioning and other units to conserve energy, the space station grew hotter, humid and dark. Mir had trouble maintaining its orientation in orbit when the computer that fired the station's jets lost power. So the crew fired the rockets on the Soyuz to stabilize their position.</p>
        <p>By today, life was getting back to normal -- or as normal as things can be on the aging Mir.</p>
        <p>By turning the space station, the crew was able to point the solar arrays more directly at the sun, and recharge the station's batteries. The temperature and humidity dropped, and the crew was able to turn on the system that removes carbon dioxide from Mir's atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Ground controllers also sent a signal activating Mir's gyroscopes to improve control of the space station. Some power was even used to run a greenhouse, an experiment to see how seeds grow in space.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mir has only 50 to 60 percent of its power supply, which is not enough for most of the scientific experiments NASA and the Russians have planned, a NASA official said. The future of the space station depends on fixing the power problem.</p>
        <p>The trick is to reconnect the cables from the Spektr module to the rest of Mir without letting the air escape from the space station. That was a problem that bedeviled the Russian and NASA scientists as they struggled to develop a plan.</p>
        <p>The final plan is to launch a new Progress supply vessel about July 5 from the Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakstan. The Progress will transport equipment including a new laptop computer for Mr. Foale, lights and bolt cutters.</p>
        <p>It will also carry a special plate to which the electric cables in Spektr can be connected. That piece of equipment was to be completed today at a factory near Moscow and flown to Baikonur on Monday.</p>
        <p>Another key piece of equipment is already on board Mir. It is a cone-shaped device used for docking, Viktor D. Blagov, the deputy Mir mission controller, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The idea is for Russian astronauts to conduct an internal space walk. After donning their space suits, they will enter the section of Mir next to Spektr. The rest of the space station will be sealed off.</p>
        <p>The Russian astronauts will then remove the hatch to Spektr, and at least one of them will maneuver through the tight portal and enter Spektr.</p>
        <p>The astronauts will take the cables in Spektr and run them through the center of the cone-like device, which is open at the top. The cone will be inserted in the portal between Spektr and the rest of Mir.</p>
        <p>The special plate will be used to seal the top of the cone. Cables from Spektr will be attached to one side of the plate. Cables to carry power to the rest of Mir will be attached to the other, Mr. Blagov said. That will enable the power to pass through while maintaining an airtight seal.</p>
        <p>The section next to Spektr will then be repressurized. Once it is determined that air is not leaking, the section will be opened up to the rest of the space station.</p>
        <p>During the difficult repairs, Mr. Foale will be zippered up in his space suit and waiting in the Soyuz space craft. That way the entire crew can make a quick evacuation if an emergency develops.</p>
        <p>Today, the crew appeared relaxed in a Russian television broadcast. Commander Tsibliyev said his wife was not unduly worried. His flight engineer, Aleksandr Lazutkin, praised the training he has received. Mr. Foale said he would be prepared to go up in space again.</p>
        <p>But the crew seemed less sure of itself when it was first informed about the repair mission during an off-camera session.</p>
        <p>After the crew was informed of the plan, reporters in the Russian command center heard one of the Russian astronauts mutter, ''It's very problematic.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
