<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing the Peril of Earth's Cauldrons</title>
    <meta content="26VOLC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970903T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953104"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tacoma (Wash)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Rainier (Washington)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Assn of Volcanology and Chemistry</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blakeslee, Sandra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Tacoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFDD1F3EF935A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="2345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing the Peril of Earth's Cauldrons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SANDRA BLAKESLEE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Blakeslee, Sandra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists say at least 500 million people live dangerously close to earth's 1,500 active volcanoes, any one of which could erupt at any time; in United States, people of Seattle and Tacoma live in shadow of Mount Rainier; scientists under auspices of International Assn of Volcanology and Chemistry of the Earth's Interior made video that depicts what volcanoes can do to people and property, to show to mayors and other public officials in charge of getting people to evacuate when volcanoes threaten to explode; scientists picked 15 volcanoes around world to study intensely, and they have made effort to make better predictions of when volcanoes will erupt; volcanologists face sheer perversity of volcanoes and tendency for people to deny danger even when it is obvious; in 1985, 26,000 people died in Colombia because they ignored warning that large volcanic mudflow was headed for their villages; photos; diagrams; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PLANET Earth is planning some spectacular volcanic fireworks and millions of people worldwide are going to have ringside seats.</p>
        <p>The next show could start anytime, almost anywhere. It might be Mexico City, where a 17,000-foot volcano named Popocatepetl is spewing ash and poisonous gases toward 20 million homes; it conceivably could explode with the force of 10,000 atomic bombs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PLANET Earth is planning some spectacular volcanic fireworks and millions of people worldwide are going to have ringside seats.</p>
        <p>The next show could start anytime, almost anywhere. It might be Mexico City, where a 17,000-foot volcano named Popocatepetl is spewing ash and poisonous gases toward 20 million homes; it conceivably could explode with the force of 10,000 atomic bombs.</p>
        <p>Or it might be Vesuvius, the famed volcano that looms over Naples and surrounding Italian towns, home to 11 million people. A small volcano called Soufriere Hills is erupting now on the lush Caribbean island of Montserrat, and has already driven most of the island's people from their homes.</p>
        <p>There are about 1,500 active volcanoes, not counting hundreds more under the oceans, and any of them could erupt at any time, said Dr. Tom Casadevall, western regional director of the United States Geological Survey in Menlo Park, Calif. Of the 1,500, 583 have exploded within the last 400 years, making them particularly dangerous. Each year, scientists observe 50 to 60 volcanoes in various stages of eruption, some gently extruding lava like red hot toothpaste down hillsides, others heaving molten rock particles and noxious gases many miles up into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The number of people living on the sides of volcanoes and in the valleys below has skyrocketed, said Dr. Stanley Williams, a volcanologist at Arizona State University in Tempe. At least 500 million people live dangerously close to volcanoes, he said. Many dwell in megacities in Asia and Latin America -- Tokyo, Manila, Jakarta, Mexico City, Quito -- or in cities of at least a million people. Here in the United States, the people of Seattle and Tacoma live in the shadow of Mount Rainier, a 13,000-foot volcano whose mudflows have swept through the places where the cities are situated.</p>
        <p>People have been drawn to volcanoes for centuries because the surrounding soils are rich and old volcanic mudflows make nice flat areas for settlement, Dr. Williams said. As population rises and land gets scarcer, the problem is getting worse.</p>
        <p>Most of the time, the people who colonize danger areas do not know any better. And the people who do know better, scientists and civil disaster officials, ''are not always listened to,'' said Dr. Grant Heiken, a volcanologist at the Los Alamos National Laboratory in New Mexico.</p>
        <p>For example, scientists issued a warning when a high volcano, capped with ice, began rumbling in the mountains of Colombia in 1985. On Nov. 13, the icecap exploded above the town of Novado del Ruiz. The eruption melted snow fields that picked up debris and went roaring down the side of the volcano toward the villages 30 to 40 miles away. The residents were warned that night that a large volcanic mudflow was on the way, Dr. Heiken said. ''But it was raining,'' he said. ''People said, 'Why worry, the volcano is far away.' They had only to walk 100 yards to a hill to be safe. That night, 26,000 people died.''</p>
        <p>Scientists were horrified, said Dr. Chris Newhall, a volcanologist at the United States Geological Survey at the University of Washington in Seattle. This episode and other natural disasters prompted the United Nations to declare the 1990's the International Decade of Natural Hazard Reduction, he said. ''The notion was, look, the world population is growing, the hazards are not getting any less,'' he said. ''People are moving into marginal lands that are more prone to disasters -- volcanoes, floods, earthquakes and hurricanes. The basic idea was to encourage countries to take a hard look at the hazards that their populations were facing and to undertake projects to try and reduce risks.''</p>
        <p>But the United Nations did not have money for the program, Dr. Newhall said. The International Decade of Hazard Reduction has existed in name only.</p>
        <p>So the scientists began taking action on their own. Under the auspices of the International Association of Volcanology and Chemistry of the Earth's Interior, ''we volcanologists got together and scratched our heads for ideas,'' Dr. Newhall said. ''We came up with three.''</p>
        <p>First, they made a video that depicts what volcanoes can do to people and property, with such horrifying accuracy that it is not recommended for children under 15. It is being shown to mayors and other public officials in charge of getting people to evacuate when volcanoes threaten to explode.</p>
        <p>Second, the scientists picked 15 volcanoes around the world to study intensely. These so-called decade volcanoes are near large population centers and could erupt any time.  Workshops have been held at most of them, bringing together scientists and disaster relief officials from the local regions.</p>
        <p>Third, there has been an effort to make better predictions of when volcanoes will erupt, using new scientific instruments and insights.</p>
        <p>Although real progress has been made, volcanologists face a couple of intractable problems, Dr. Williams said. One is the tendency for people to deny danger even when it is obvious. Also, once a threat is passed, they tend to dismiss it. ''They forget that grandma once told a story about how her grandmother was killed by a volcano,'' he said. And second is the sheer perversity of volcanoes. They may show all the signs and symptoms of erupting and then quiet down, leading the public to accuse scientists of ''crying wolf.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Williams himself nearly lost his life in the Galeras volcano in Colombia while surveying it for the decade project a few years ago.</p>
        <p>Volcanoes arise from the forces of plate tectonics, and usually occur where great slabs of the Earth's crust are shoved deep into the interior and melted. This molten rock is buoyant, Dr. Williams said, and makes its way back to the surface where it finds a weak spot and explodes to the surface in a volcano.</p>
        <p>Most volcanoes live for tens of thousands of years and can remain dormant for centuries between eruptions. The varying amounts of ash, lava and other particles they emit are measured in cubic kilometers,  cubes a quarter of a mile on each side. The 1980 Mount St. Helen's eruption in Washington State, which devastated the countryside, was a small event by volcanic standards, producing only one cubic kilometer, Dr. Williams said.</p>
        <p>By contrast, a volcano in Yellowstone, Wyo., has over the last two million years spewed out 3,800 cubic kilometers of ash and pumice. If Yellowstone produced another huge eruption, it could shut down the country, he said. Airplanes could not fly, trucks could not deliver food and farmers could not grow crops.</p>
        <p>The 15 decade volcanoes are being studied, Dr. Newhall said, ''to arrive at a synopsis of what was and was not understood about how each volcano works. Also, what questions need to be addressed to make future forecasts more accurate in terms of the size and timing of eruptions.''</p>
        <p>First, geologists look all around each volcano, mapping ash deposits and mud flows to determine the nature of each past eruption, how far it went and, with carbon dating, how long ago it happened, said Dr. Richard Fisher, a professor emeritus of geology at the University of California at Santa Barbara. Then they map out hazard zones. If a volcano produced serious damage in one place, it can do so again, he said.</p>
        <p>Next, the scientists study the low-frequency earthquakes that these volcanoes tend to produce. Such earthquakes make a special noise that is related to growing magma domes, the ominous bulges formed by molten rock making its way to the surface. With almost every volcano, people in the area begin feeling quakes, hearing noises and smelling gases for days, weeks or months before an eruption, Dr. Williams said. They often sense it is coming.</p>
        <p>Using a variety of instruments, the scientists are measuring the size and growth of magma domes at decade volcanoes and the gases they emit.  Steam and carbon dioxide indicate that high pressures are building up.  Sulfur dioxide emissions ''tell you that the magma is in communication with the atmosphere,'' Dr. Fisher said. It is a definite danger sign.</p>
        <p>A few things send volcanologists running for the hills, Dr. Newhall said. If a volcano starts to produce low harmonic tremors, a steady hum of seismic waves, for tens of minutes or hours, it is time to flee. It means magma is rising up the conduit and building gas pressure. Recent studies on decade volcanoes also point to another forewarning: sulfur dioxide levels sometimes drop right before the big blast.</p>
        <p>The trouble is, other volcanoes do not give these warning signs before they explode. ''You do the best you can,'' Dr. Newhall said. ''You look at spatial and temporal changes and you plot them for weeks, months and then you make your best shot at interpreting what is going on.''</p>
        <p>The major cause of death in volcanoes is not hot lava or rivers of mud, but rather glowing clouds of superhot gas and ash particles that silently sweep down the volcano's flank and across the countryside at 60 miles an hour, vaporizing everything in their path. These pyroclastic flows can knock down stone walls 10 feet thick and have killed thousands of people in less than two minutes, he said.</p>
        <p>In the movies, people outrun the flows, but in real life, the flows desiccate the flesh and fry the lungs of  everyone in their path. Ninety-eight percent of the people in Guatemala  live on the surface of a pyroclastic flow that raced over the countryside 75,000 years ago, Dr. Williams said.</p>
        <p>From watching volcano movies and films of the rather gentle and atypical volcanoes in Hawaii, people think they can walk away from danger, Dr. Heiken said. The volcanologists' video shows otherwise. It is very blunt and shows dead bodies, he said. ''When people see it, they gulp and say, 'Could that really happen here? How far did you say the town was from that volcano?' ''</p>
        <p>In 1991, a rough cut of the newly made video was rushed to the Philippines, where Mount Pinatubo was threatening to erupt. The day after it was shown on television, 50,000 people evacuated voluntarily. A few days later, the volcano erupted, spewing 12 cubic kilometers of material. ''We are convinced that the video saved tens of thousands of lives,'' Dr. Heiken said.</p>
        <p>Getting the word out and convincing people to evacuate is a huge challenge, Dr. Williams said. Ultimately, whether people live or die depends as much on communication as on science. ''We try to teach people how not to freak out,'' he said.  ''They think falling ash is lethal, but it's not. The problem is that the ash is three times heavier than water so their roof can collapse in hours. We teach people to get under the strongest table in the room, near the corner. The air is full of static electricity, so radios and traffic lights go haywire and they get scared.''</p>
        <p>Such public education saves lives, Dr. Heiken said. In September 1994, a volcano at Rabaul in Papua New Guinea destroyed 75 percent of the homes in the city. But because the citizens had been trained in evacuation procedures, they did not panic and got away safely. Only five people died.</p>
        <p>It is a different story in the United States ''where any form of government message is taken as a challenge to people's rights to do whatever they want,'' Dr. Casadevall said. At Mount St. Helens, some people refused to evacuate and died as a result. Around Mount Rainier, 250,000 people live on the surface of volcanic mudflows that are less than 500 years old. Some older flows reached Seattle. These people are being told they should be ready to move to high ground if Mount Rainier shows signs of erupting, he said. The problem is that with some towns, there is one narrow road out over a single bridge. ''We try to make sure people have this information,'' Dr. Casadevall said, ''but if they refuse to leave, they're on their own.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 3, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Aug. 26 about volcanic hazards misidentified a town in Colombia devastated by an eruption in 1985. It was Armero; Novado del Ruiz was the name of the volcano.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 3, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Aug. 26 about volcanic hazards misidentified a town in Colombia devastated by an eruption in 1985. It was Armero; Novado del Ruiz was the name of the volcano.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
