<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Lifts Off on Mission to Explore Lack of Gravity</title>
    <meta content="05SHUT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="920530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halsell, James D (Lieut Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Still, Susan L (Lieut Comdr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E7DB103DF936A35757C0A961958260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Lifts Off on Mission to Explore Lack of Gravity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., April 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Space shuttle Columbia lifts off from Cape Canaveral, carrying crew of seven on 16-day mission to explore subtleties of lack of gravity; mission, third of year, focuses on effect of minimum gravity in space on fire and combustion, and on physics of making new materials and growing protein crystals for medical research; Columbia is under command of Lieut Col James D Halsell of Air Force; pilot is Lieut Comdr Susan L Still; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space shuttle Columbia rose on yellow blasts of flame today into a deep blue sky, carrying a crew of seven on a 16-day mission to explore the subtleties of a lack of gravity.</p>
        <p>The shuttle liftoff, witnessed by tens of thousands of people who crammed the roads and beaches around the Kennedy Space Center during the spring break from school, was about 20 minutes behind schedule because of a problem with a small seal in a cabin door.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space shuttle Columbia rose on yellow blasts of flame today into a deep blue sky, carrying a crew of seven on a 16-day mission to explore the subtleties of a lack of gravity.</p>
        <p>The shuttle liftoff, witnessed by tens of thousands of people who crammed the roads and beaches around the Kennedy Space Center during the spring break from school, was about 20 minutes behind schedule because of a problem with a small seal in a cabin door.</p>
        <p>Officials at the space center were forced to turn cars away when official viewing sites filled up two hours before the blastoff, and gates were closed early as traffic clogged roads for miles around the base.</p>
        <p>The Columbia lifted off at 2:20 P.M., streaking past scattered, wispy clouds as it climbed away from cheering, waving crowds below.</p>
        <p>''Enjoy your on-orbit spring break,'' a launching controller told the crew just before liftoff.</p>
        <p>Loren Shriver, a shuttle launching manager, told a news conference afterward that the liftoff would have been ''almost on time, except for the misbehaving of a perhaps 70 cent O-ring at the end of our oxygen probe.'' A small, rubber O-ring seal through which technicians insert a probe to check pressure in the crew cabin popped loose during a final check and had to be replaced, officials said.</p>
        <p>Engineers added extra oxygen to the cabin to compensate for leaking when the seal was replaced, and later this extra oxygen was vented into the cargo bay. This additional oxygen, in turn, set off hazardous gas detectors in the bay, and mission controllers had to wait about 20 minutes for the oxygen to drop to acceptable levels before proceeding with the flight, officials said.</p>
        <p>The Columbia, the oldest of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's four shuttles, was two hours into its 22d flight when astronauts activated the pressurized laboratory in its cargo bay and moved inside shortly afterward to begin round-the-clock operations. The crew of five men and two women was divided into two teams, allowing one to work while the other slept or attended to other duties.</p>
        <p>The mission, the third of the year, focuses on the effect of minimum gravity in space on fire and combustion, and on the physics of making new materials and growing protein crystals for medical research. The shuttle is also carrying equipment, like a new experiment rack that can be moved from place to place on the ship, that is intended for the planned international space station.</p>
        <p>Of the 33 major experiments on the mission, all studying phenomena without the influence of gravity, the major ones involve fire research. The astronauts are to set as many as 200 small fires inside special, insulated chambers designed to contain any dangers.</p>
        <p>Researchers want to know how fire behaves in weightlessness, both to address safety questions for future spacecraft and to get a better understanding of how fire and heat work on Earth, as in engines and furnaces. Space agency officials said the 90-second fire aboard the Russian space station Mir last month, which filled the orbital laboratory with smoke and polluted the air, showed the importance of having a better understanding of fire in space.</p>
        <p>The largest combustion chamber aboard the shuttle Discovery is a 1,600-pound unit containing seven cameras and myriad sensors to allow scientists on Earth to observe the results. The astronauts will study fire dynamics that are difficult to observe on the ground, like flame balls, spheres of fire that can break away from regular flame under certain circumstances.</p>
        <p>Also aboard are an assortment of fossil fuels and alcohols, like heptane and ethanol, to be burned under controlled conditions to see how smoke and soot spread and influence the dynamics of a fire. The astronauts will also ignite droplets of different fuels commonly used on Earth to see how they burn and isolate the role each plays in pollution.</p>
        <p>For safety's sake, there are built-in extinguishers and five hand-held extinguishers on board. In the unlikely event of an out-of-control blaze, the astronauts could evacuate the laboratory and release the air inside,  creating a vacuum to extinguish the flames, officials said.</p>
        <p>In addition to the combustion experiments, the Columbia carries furnaces to help melt and solidify samples of metals and other materials to study chemical and structural changes that occur as they move from solid to liquid and back again.</p>
        <p>The flight also includes some plant science. To investigate how plants adapt to space flight, the Columbia is carrying a greenhouse unit containing some 50 spinach, clover, sage and periwinkle plants, as well as pine seedlings.</p>
        <p>The Columbia is under the command of Lieut. Col. James D. Halsell of the Air Force, a veteran of two previous shuttle flights. The pilot is Lieut. Comdr. Susan L. Still, making her first flight; she is the second woman to serve as a shuttle pilot.</p>
        <p>Also aboard are Dr. Janice Voss, the payload commander overseeing the mission's research program, who is a veteran of two previous flights, and two mission specialists, Dr. Michael L. Gernhardt, who flew once before, and Dr. Donald A. Thomas, who is on his third mission.</p>
        <p>Joining the NASA astronauts are two scientists who have not flown in space before, Dr. Roger K. Crouch, a physicist, and Dr. Gregory T. Linteris, a chemical and mechanical engineer who is a combustion specialist.</p>
        <p>The Columbia is scheduled to return to Earth on April 20.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
