<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Praise for the Global Warming Initiative</title>
    <meta content="12GLOB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979766"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BRIEFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kyoto (Japan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Petroleum Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibrahim, Youssef M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E0DA113CF931A25751C1A961958260" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Praise for the Global Warming Initiative</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ibrahim, Youssef M</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Dec. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>British Petroleum Co chief executive John Browne has won grudging approval from some environmentalists, many of whom place his company at forefront of multinationals willing to tackle problem of global warming; Browne praises what he describes as limited progress achieved at Kyoto climate conference; says he hopes future agreements will go further; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he graduated from Cambridge in the mid-60's, John Browne did not want to become an academic, a civil servant or a diplomat, proper careers for a member of Britain's intellectual elite.</p>
        <p>Three decades later, Mr. Browne, 49, still recalls the reaction of one of his teachers to the career he did choose. It was ''amusing,'' the don remarked loudly, that young Browne wanted to become ''a captain of industry.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he graduated from Cambridge in the mid-60's, John Browne did not want to become an academic, a civil servant or a diplomat, proper careers for a member of Britain's intellectual elite.</p>
        <p>Three decades later, Mr. Browne, 49, still recalls the reaction of one of his teachers to the career he did choose. It was ''amusing,'' the don remarked loudly, that young Browne wanted to become ''a captain of industry.''</p>
        <p>As chief executive of the British Petroleum Company Mr. Browne has indeed become a captain of industry and within the rarefied circles in which he travels, he is still a maverick of sorts.</p>
        <p>Under his leadership, British Petroleum, one of the world's biggest energy companies, has won grudging approval from some environmentalists, many of whom place his company at the forefront of multinationals willing to tackle the problem of global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Browne today was quick to praise what he described as the limited progress achieved at the Kyoto climate conference. In a statement issued at his London headquarters, he said he hoped that future agreements would go further.</p>
        <p>''We don't underestimate the amount of work which still needs to be done,'' he said, ''and we believe business has a constructive role to play in the process.''</p>
        <p>In a series of speeches, and in an interview earlier this week, he said that corporations needed to restrain emissions of carbon dioxide -- and he has taken concrete action to support his views, setting strict standards for B.P. refineries and factories, and investing $160 million in solar energy. He hopes solar power will generate a trillion dollars for the company in a decade.</p>
        <p>This has won Mr. Browne recognition in unlikely quarters. ''Compared to other oil companies, B.P. was the first major to come out in favor of policies to reduce CO2  emissions,'' said Chris Rose, deputy executive director of the environmental activist organization Greenpeace, in Britain. ''I guess you can say on a scale of good to bad, they, and the Shell Oil Company, are the good guys in this industry.''</p>
        <p>''I believe we've now come to an important moment in our consideration of the environment,'' he said in an interview in the company's stately board room in the financial district of London.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Browne's view, it is time for the business world to accept the realities of global warming, which he described as facts backed by ''effective consensus among the world's leading scientists and serious and well-informed people.''</p>
        <p>Rather than fight environmentalists, companies can save and eventually earn money if they begin to  make this ''investment in the future.''</p>
        <p>Contrast that with the Exxon Corporation, the world's No. 2 oil company behind Royal Dutch/Shell. In the 1980's it cleared out its portfolio of renewable energy projects, selling its solar unit in 1984.</p>
        <p>In Beijing earlier his month, Lee Raymond, Exxon's chairman, asserted that the link between burning of hydrocarbons and harm to the climate remained unproved. ''Many people, politicians and the public alike, believe global warming is a rock-solid certainty,'' Mr. Raymond said. ''But it's not.''</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Browne said: ''No one knows precisely what's going on, but its doesn't mean you do nothing. Our position is to continue to provide energy to the world but do it better.''</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Browne, B.P.'s market capitalization has increased from $35 billion in November 1994 to $81 billion today. Profits have increased from $2.3 billion to $ 4.1 billion in the same period.</p>
        <p>An engineer who has become a wizard in the art of finance, Mr. Browne is an opera buff. He compares a successful corporation to a well-performed opera. ''You have got to have a well-trained orchestra, a conductor who is sympathetic to the meaning of the music, a director who is sympathetic to the conductor and singers able to both sing and act,'' he said. ''So when it all comes together it is fantastic.''</p>
        <p>Puffing on a slim cigar (he says he is cutting down) and sipping coffee, Mr. Browne said B.P.'s foray into the business of pollution control was engaging the entire company.</p>
        <p>''We have an action plan in which 50,000 people participate,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The plan includes setting targets for each refinery, factory and outfit of the company around the world to use less energy, with fixed targets reviewed periodically.</p>
        <p>Special training in energy conservation has been set up for employees in scores of countries in which B.P. operates. The company has set a goal of eliminating the flaring of natural gas by repackaging it. Above all, B.P. has gone further than any other energy company in developing solar energy as a nonpolluting substitute, with factories producing solar panels in Spain, Australia and Saudi Arabia -- a dozen more factories are under consideration. ''We already have 10 percent of the market in solar energy,'' Mr. Browne said.</p>
        <p>Companies had better take action before someone else does it for them, he said, contending that he wanted to lead no one. It was simply, he said, that ''we in B.P. have reached that point.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BRIEFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
