<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore in China: Still No Break in the Political Wall</title>
    <meta content="27CHIN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="918507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyler, Patrick E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jiang Zemin (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970327T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D7163AF934A15750C0A961958260" item-length="1299" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore in China: Still No Break in the Political Wall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tyler, Patrick E</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, March 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patrick E Tyler analysis contends that while Vice Pres Gore's first visit to China provided impetus for Chinese officials to close large commercial transactions with Boeing and General Motors, political breakthroughs that had seemed possible only few months ago did not materialize, just as they failed to materialize last Nov when Pres Clinton met with Pres Jiang Zemin in Manila; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After two days of talks with China's Communist Party leaders, Vice President Al Gore said tonight that despite domestic political pressures that are vexing Chinese-American relations, the Clinton Administration is determined to ''strengthen and broaden'' its bonds with the People's Republic.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news conference here, he said planning would now go forward for President Jiang Zemin to visit Washington this fall and asserted that ''a strong consensus in the center of the American political system'' supports continued dialogue and engagement with China.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After two days of talks with China's Communist Party leaders, Vice President Al Gore said tonight that despite domestic political pressures that are vexing Chinese-American relations, the Clinton Administration is determined to ''strengthen and broaden'' its bonds with the People's Republic.</p>
        <p>Speaking at a news conference here, he said planning would now go forward for President Jiang Zemin to visit Washington this fall and asserted that ''a strong consensus in the center of the American political system'' supports continued dialogue and engagement with China.</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Gore's first visit to China provided the impetus for Chinese officials to close large commercial transactions with Boeing and General Motors, the political breakthroughs that had seemed possible only a few months ago did not materialize, just as they failed to materialize last November when President Clinton met with Mr. Jiang in Manila.</p>
        <p>Political prisoners, like Wang Dan, a student leader of the 1989 Tiananmen Square demonstrations, whose cases had been mentioned by Chinese officials this winter as possible candidates for medical parole, remain in custody. Chinese officials refused to say when, or if, they will sign two United Nations covenants on human rights, something they had been saying for months they were considering.</p>
        <p>There was no substantive progress to be claimed on ending China's weapons sales to Iran or to Pakistan. Nor did Mr. Gore make headway on persuading China to narrow its yawning trade deficit with the United States or drop the extensive trade barriers that are keeping many American companies out of the China market and Beijing out of the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>''Given the enormous importance that we attach to the U.S.-China relationship,'' Mr. Gore said at a news conference this evening, ''there was naturally a very long list of issues'' on the table.</p>
        <p>That is where they remain as Mr. Gore leaves the Chinese capital on Thursday for a day of sightseeing with his family in the ancient city of Xian and in Shanghai.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore received about as cordial a treatment as any visiting dignitary, but the tangible gains he might have hoped to pocket during this high-profile opportunity to strut his foreign policy skills for the voters of election year 2000 eluded him. If anything, those gains appear to have been undermined by the onslaught of investigations and publicity surrounding China's possible role in funneling illicit contributions to members of Congress.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Mr. Gore called those allegations a speculative matter that is under investigation.</p>
        <p>He also sought to clarify his remarks to Prime Minister Li Peng on Tuesday regarding American concerns that China may have sought to covertly buy influence in Congress.</p>
        <p>''Li Peng raised it first, and he repeated the strong denials by China,'' Mr. Gore said. ''I then said that the United States views these allegations as very serious. However, they are the subject of an ongoing criminal investigation within our Justice Department, and it is premature to speculate on what the outcome of that investigation is.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''The discussion of the controversy, pending the completion of the investigation, should not affect the relationship between China and the United States,'' and then said, ''should the allegations prove to be true, then, of course, that would be a different matter, and I made it clear that that would be serious indeed.''</p>
        <p>The fact that Mr. Gore's news conference was dominated by questions about a possible Chinese role in illicit political financing only contributed to the sense of deadlock in Chinese-American relations that has permeated Mr. Gore's visit, and that raises the question of how long a high-level dialogue can be sustained without substantive progress on human rights, trade and the proliferation of powerful weapons and technology.</p>
        <p>In rejecting the notion that paralysis has set in, Mr. Gore seemed slightly equivocal. When asked whether the ''shadow'' of the investigations was making it more difficult to make progress with China, he said: ''I understand why you would ask the question, but I really don't think so. It shouldn't, and I don't think it has to at all.''</p>
        <p>Later, he added, ''I really believe there is a strong consensus in the  center of the American political system that supports what is clearly in America's national interest, and that is furthering our dialogue with the largest nation on earth, and engaging with China in a constructive way that allows us to communicate effectively, not only on these commercial issues, but on issues like human rights as well.''</p>
        <p>At times, Mr. Gore seemed to be reaching for signs of positive political evolution in China, as if to validate the Clinton policy. He asserted at one point that ''village elections'' might soon be expanded to China's 2,500 county governments, representing ''a significant advance in the process of democracy here.''</p>
        <p>Few Western or Chinese legal scholars would argue today that in China's heavily policed one-party state, ''democracy'' is a valid description of the village chief selection process, or that the Communist Party leadership is inclined to allow democratic rule in any locality for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the debate among scholars is whether village elections represent a progressive step at all or simply a substitute method of Communist Party control that co-opts local opposition to party rule while providing a potent propaganda tool for Chinese leaders. They have recently begun to claim that up to 900 million Chinese tale part in ''free elections.''</p>
        <p>If domestic politics were afflicting Mr. Gore, they were also preoccupying his Chinese hosts.</p>
        <p>With the death of the paramount leader, Deng Xiaoping, on Feb. 19, the collective Communist Party leadership of President Jiang must demonstrate its legitimacy and competence to lead the nation, Chinese and Western officials say. To do so it must show it can command American respect without making concessions. That is why it was important for Prime Minister Li to stage a surprise champagne toast with Mr. Gore in the Great Hall of the People on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Every Chinese who saw the clinking glasses on state-run television got the message that the hard-line Prime Minister commands great respect from the United States despite Mr. Li's association with the 1989 Tiananmen massacre. The subtext was that China has emerged from the long shadow of Tiananmen and that Washington, like Paris, Bonn and Moscow, is more interested in scoring big business contracts in China than in dragging on with recriminations over the crushed democracy movement.</p>
        <p>That message is all-important in a year in which Mr. Li is angling to hold on to a commensurate measure of power after his second five-year term as Prime Minister ends next year and he is forced to relinquish the job.</p>
        <p>At times, Mr. Gore seemed just as pained to make any concessions to the Chinese.</p>
        <p>He brought no commitment from President Clinton to set a definite date for President Jiang's first state visit to Washington, though the agreement to exchange visits was announced last November. Mr. Gore said, ''President Jiang is expected in Washington this autumn, and planning will now begin in earnest in both capitals to develop specific dates and work programs.''</p>
        <p>Even in the area of environmental protection, Mr. Gore's policy forte, there was no meeting of the minds on how China could realistically reduce its emission of greenhouse gases, whose output will surpass that of the United States in the next century.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also gave little satisfaction to Chinese officials who resent the sale of advanced American weapons to Taiwan, which Beijing sees as a violation of commitments made during the Reagan Administration to end such sales.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
