<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Facing Up to Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="22MON1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDA143EF931A15751C1A961958260" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Facing Up to Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on need for Senate ratification of global warming accord (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The global warming accord was barely signed in Kyoto, Japan, earlier this month when critics pronounced its chances of Senate ratification to be nil. If that is true, then the Senate has clearly misread the American public, which in every survey has expressed an appetite for decisive action. The Senate's attitude also defines what could be President Clinton's biggest challenge in the new year -- leading the Senate where the public wants it to go.</p>
        <p>Few scientists doubt that the warming of the earth's atmosphere, caused by carbon dioxide and other greenhouse-gas emissions, poses a gigantic threat. But even before Kyoto, the Senate had voted 95 to 0 to reject any treaty that damaged the American economy or did not require developing countries to have their own energy conservation programs. The Kyoto agreement seems not to have satisfied many senators on either count. Mr. Clinton must therefore spend the next year enlisting the participation of developing countries and persuading Congress that the market incentives, tax credits and other strategies he has in mind will dramatically improve energy efficiency nationwide and allow America to meet its emissions targets without throttling the economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The global warming accord was barely signed in Kyoto, Japan, earlier this month when critics pronounced its chances of Senate ratification to be nil. If that is true, then the Senate has clearly misread the American public, which in every survey has expressed an appetite for decisive action. The Senate's attitude also defines what could be President Clinton's biggest challenge in the new year -- leading the Senate where the public wants it to go.</p>
        <p>Few scientists doubt that the warming of the earth's atmosphere, caused by carbon dioxide and other greenhouse-gas emissions, poses a gigantic threat. But even before Kyoto, the Senate had voted 95 to 0 to reject any treaty that damaged the American economy or did not require developing countries to have their own energy conservation programs. The Kyoto agreement seems not to have satisfied many senators on either count. Mr. Clinton must therefore spend the next year enlisting the participation of developing countries and persuading Congress that the market incentives, tax credits and other strategies he has in mind will dramatically improve energy efficiency nationwide and allow America to meet its emissions targets without throttling the economy.</p>
        <p>Getting the developing countries to sign up will not by itself carry the day in the Senate. At least 20 senators are unlikely to vote for the treaty under any circumstances, viewing the science as dubious or any kind of environmental regulation as offensive. The key to ratification will be the stance of such pro-environmental Republicans as John Chafee of Rhode Island, James Jeffords of Vermont and Olympia Snowe of Maine. In addition, Senators John McCain of Arizona and Richard Lugar of Indiana, both conservatives, have a record of sensitivity to American international obligations and down the road may well be persuaded to support the treaty, and bring others along.</p>
        <p>American attitudes toward energy have changed since the 1970's, when gasoline lines and high prices gave sacrifice a bad name. Americans have also coalesced politically around supporting the environment. Senate and House Republican leaders learned that lesson painfully in 1995, when they tried and failed in their assaults on the Clean Air and Clean Water Acts. In addition, as Mr. Clinton pointed out, every major environmental advance of recent years has been described as a potential economic disaster only to prove more doable than previously thought.</p>
        <p>A two-thirds vote in the Senate is required for ratification. Millions of dollars will be spent by energy companies, agribusiness and labor unions to portray the Administration as bent on destroying the economy. Some Republicans are hoping to demonize the global warming treaty as they demonized Mr. Clinton's health care proposals in 1994. But it is also interesting that some Republicans have begun saying that they do not want to help Vice President Gore ride the environmental issue to the White House in 2000. That means they might be willing to support a treaty and share in the credit.</p>
        <p>Any serious American effort to reduce greenhouse gases will require sacrifice. Even economists sympathetic to the environment warn against voluntarily bringing a repeat of the 1970's oil shock. The environmental movement would be making a mistake to belittle the anxiety Americans feel about such warnings. But critics of the treaty will make an even greater mistake if they underestimate the public's anxieties about global warming -- and their resolve to address it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
