<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INDUSTRIES REVISIT GLOBAL WARMING</title>
    <meta content="05WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="948604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Petroleum Co Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E7DD113DF936A3575BC0A961958260" item-length="1630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INDUSTRIES REVISIT GLOBAL WARMING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <dateline>BONN, Aug. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fossil fuel producers, who previously denied link between greenhouse gases and climate change and staunchly opposed binding agreements obligating countries to control their emissions, are now expressing widespread willingness to accept view of mainstream scientists that problem is real and that some action is needed to solve it; industry delegates attending meeting on climate change in Bonn, Germany, are surprised to hear British Petroleum, world's third-largest oil company, admit that concern about burning of fossil fuels is scientifically warranted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early in this decade, as the nations of the world negotiated a treaty to head off man-made global warming, industry lobbyists spoke with virtually one voice on the issue of climate change. They just said no -- no to any binding agreement obligating countries to control emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide, and no to the very idea that there was serious cause for concern.</p>
        <p>But times have changed, and the industry stance has changed as well. Though hard-liners still see no need to force anyone to limit emissions of greenhouse gases, a whole new spectrum of industry voices has joined the policy debate as businesses have examined more closely how they might win or lose.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early in this decade, as the nations of the world negotiated a treaty to head off man-made global warming, industry lobbyists spoke with virtually one voice on the issue of climate change. They just said no -- no to any binding agreement obligating countries to control emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide, and no to the very idea that there was serious cause for concern.</p>
        <p>But times have changed, and the industry stance has changed as well. Though hard-liners still see no need to force anyone to limit emissions of greenhouse gases, a whole new spectrum of industry voices has joined the policy debate as businesses have examined more closely how they might win or lose.</p>
        <p>At least one big crack has developed in the once-monolithic front presented by the producers of fossil fuels, like coal and oil, the very people who might be expected to hold out most strongly against any change.</p>
        <p>At meetings here, where delegates from around the globe have gathered  under the five-year-old treaty, these changes have surfaced as a more widespread willingness to accept the view of mainstream scientists that the problem is real and to take at least some action to solve it.</p>
        <p>The heads of several large corporations met with President Clinton in Washington today to discuss the problem. The President has promised a strong American proposal for specific levels of greenhouse gas reductions that is still being drawn up.</p>
        <p>In what may be the most telling change, British Petroleum, the world's third-largest oil company, broke ranks with other fossil fuel producers recently and announced that it believes that there is now enough scientific evidence to warrant concern about whether human activity -- primarily the burning of fossil fuels like coal, oil and natural gas -- is changing Earth's climate.</p>
        <p>The time to contemplate action ''is not when the link between greenhouse gases and climate change is conclusively proven, but when the possibility cannot be discounted and is taken seriously,'' John Browne, the company's chairman, said in a recent speech. British Petroleum, he said, ''has reached that point.''</p>
        <p>Delegates to the meeting here are negotiating reductions in emissions of greenhouse gases. The most important of these is carbon dioxide, which is produced by burning fossil fuels. The negotiations will conclude in Kyoto, Japan, in December.</p>
        <p>In the conference rooms, corridors and coffee bars of the Bonn Maritim Hotel, where the talks are taking place, the spectrum of industry opinion runs from hard-liners in the coal and oil industries who want no agreement in Kyoto to companies that produce alternatives to fossil fuels and want strong action immediately. In the middle is a broad group with a range of positions.</p>
        <p>The dominant scientific view is that greenhouse gas emissions are probably responsible for at least part of a rise of 1 degree Fahrenheit in the average global temperature over the last century. Mainstream scientists predict that if emissions are not reduced, there will be a further rise of perhaps 3.5 degrees in the next century and more after that, with accompanying disruptions in climate. These include, for instance, more frequent and severe floods and droughts and a rise in the sea level. By comparison, the world has warmed by 5 to 9 degrees since the last ice age.</p>
        <p>There is considerable uncertainty in these estimates. Nevertheless, Mr. Browne said in a telephone interview, ''it seems to us it's time we should do something'' about greenhouse gas emissions. ''Just because there are uncertainties,'' he said, ''it doesn't mean you just stand still and do nothing.''</p>
        <p>In that spirit, the company is formally collaborating with the Environmental Defense Fund, a private group, to test practical, market-based approaches to emission reduction. It is taking steps to control its own emissions and to develop alternative fuels and energy technologies. It is undertaking cooperative efforts to reduce emissions in developing countries. And it has assumed the rotating leadership of a broad Washington-based coalition of industry moderates on climate, many of them multinational companies.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration is looking to the moderates for support as part of a campaign to win public acceptance of Mr. Clinton's pledge at the United Nations in June to seek strong action in Kyoto. Mr. Browne was one of the chief executives who discussed the subject with the President today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's United Nations speech appears to have infused the climate debate with new zest -- and to have increased the lobbying from all points on the industry spectrum.</p>
        <p>''The status of industry has dramatically changed,'' said Dan Esty, who directs the Yale University Center for Environmental Law and Policy, alluding to the period since the climate treaty was negotiated in 1992, when he was a member of the American negotiating team. ''There was only one position in '92; today there is a flowering of industry positions.'' And back then, he said, ''you didn't have a major industrial powerhouse like B.P. coming in and saying the time for action is now.''</p>
        <p>As views have proliferated, so have industry lobbyists. Connie Holmes, a lobbyist for the National Mining Association who opposes any but voluntary action to reduce greenhouse gases, said that when she began lobbying in 1988, there were ''maybe three or four people'' from industry doing the same. Here in Bonn, there are scores. Mrs. Holmes acknowledges that they consist of ''a much broader range of people, a wide spectrum of opinion.''</p>
        <p>The shift in outlook should not be overstated, though. Mr. Browne, for instance, does not see climate change as a crisis and argues that there is time to head off the problem in a deliberate, step-by-step fashion that balances economic growth and environmental protection. Any targets and timetables for emission reduction, he says, should be realistic and achievable.</p>
        <p>Further, industry is virtually unanimous in insisting that developing countries share in emission reductions. Otherwise, it fears, companies in industrialized countries will be at a competitive disadvantage. As of now, the richer countries are obligated under the treaty and subsequent international policy decisions to take the first steps.</p>
        <p>Developing countries say those first steps have not been taken, since most of the richer countries have not even been able to fulfill a voluntary pledge under the treaty to stabilize emissions at 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>Most companies and industry groups do not go as far in the direction of strong action as does an American organization called the Business Council for Sustainable Energy. Its members include several utilities -- whose leaders have found it in their interest to promote energy conservation, which reduces fossil-fuel burning and greenhouse gas emissions -- as well producers of solar power, wind power and natural gas. The last, while it is a fossil fuel, is viewed as a preferred alternative in the near term because it produces less carbon dioxide than coal or oil.</p>
        <p>This group as a whole stands to benefit from controls on greenhouse emissions since its members put a premium on the more efficient use of energy. Michael Marvin, the group's executive director. said ''we've got the technology right now'' to produce energy more efficiently. Not surprisingly, his organization favors an early stabilization of greenhouse gas emissions, by 2005, followed by progressive reductions beginning in 2010.</p>
        <p>A larger group, the Washington-based International Climate Change Partnership, now under the chairmanship of British Petroleum and including a wide range of industries, accepts the existence of a scientific consensus that some measure of man-made global warming is likely. ''We think that appears to be relatively strong,'' said Kevin J. Fay, the group's executive director.</p>
        <p>But, he said, climate change is a highly complex, long-term problem that need not necessarily be attacked with immediate targets and timetables for emission reductions. The Kyoto deadline is an artificial one, he said, adding that it is more important to achieve a lasting solution that allows both environmental protection and economic growth rather than a quick ''feel good'' result. There are probably many pathways by which the objective of heading off dangerous climatic change can be achieved, he said.</p>
        <p>Still another group, consisting of electric utilities and represented by the Edison Electric Institute, is collaborating with the Administration to reduce greenhouse emissions by promoting more efficient use of electricity. This program, the institute says, has already brought significant reductions. All of this is voluntary, and the group favors that approach in any Kyoto agreement. It also is determined to get credit for reductions already achieved as part of such an agreement.</p>
        <p>The hard-liners have not changed their position. Several of them are to be found in the Global Climate Coalition, a Washington-based lobbying group representing core energy and manufacturing industries. Gail McDonald, the new president of the coalition, formed zeros with her fingers when asked what her group would like to see happen in Kyoto.</p>
        <p>The coalition continues to question the science of global warming. It argues that the impact of climate change is too uncertain and that the risk of economic damage is still too high to justify stronger, mandatory action.</p>
        <p>The Administration's present course toward mandatory targets and timetables is ''an unjustified rush to judgment,'' the coalition's chairman, William F. O'Keefe, told Congress recently. He likened it to driving too fast in a thick fog. This, he said, ''risks a fatal crash.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
