<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Clinton may soon tackle the devilish Social Security issue.</title>
    <meta content="Y23SCE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEFD8123EF930A15753C1A961958260" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Clinton may soon tackle the devilish Social Security issue.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Passell Economic Scene column says Pres Clinton may soon add Social Security to his agenda; notes that experts on whom Washington is depending for answers are deeply divided on how to eliminate $8 trillion in unfunded pension liabilities; says all sides agree that safety net must remain intact, and that reforms cannot be built around permanent increases in payroll tax; expects Clinton to name advisory commission that will include many senior Congressional leaders, to provide nonpartisan cover; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH trade liberalization and global warming already on the menu, one might expect President Clinton to take a break before heaping another difficult-to-digest economic issue on his plate. In fact, the White House is close to making a decision on whether to add Social Security to his agenda. There is reason for the haste: while the President has three years left in office, the political window of opportunity for tackling this most sensitive of issues is narrow.</p>
        <p>Creating the bipartisan will to cut benefits or force workers to set aside more of their incomes for retirement is only the first step. Actually designing the plan to eliminate $8 trillion in unfunded pension liabilities could prove far more difficult. For while there is wide agreement that the problem is technically manageable, the experts on whom Washington is depending for answers are deeply -- perhaps fatally -- divided on how to get from here to there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH trade liberalization and global warming already on the menu, one might expect President Clinton to take a break before heaping another difficult-to-digest economic issue on his plate. In fact, the White House is close to making a decision on whether to add Social Security to his agenda. There is reason for the haste: while the President has three years left in office, the political window of opportunity for tackling this most sensitive of issues is narrow.</p>
        <p>Creating the bipartisan will to cut benefits or force workers to set aside more of their incomes for retirement is only the first step. Actually designing the plan to eliminate $8 trillion in unfunded pension liabilities could prove far more difficult. For while there is wide agreement that the problem is technically manageable, the experts on whom Washington is depending for answers are deeply -- perhaps fatally -- divided on how to get from here to there.</p>
        <p>After this summer's budget accord, a triumphant President Clinton allowed that the respite from fiscal crisis ''gives us a rare opportunity to take steps for the long-term well-being of our country.'' If that is to include major changes in Social Security before the millennium, the White House is convinced the campaign must begin soon.</p>
        <p>The most likely scenario goes like this. Over the next few months the President will sound out Congressional Republicans -- in particular the Senate leadership, which is more inclined to pragmatism -- on whether they are prepared to take on Social Security. If the response is positive, Mr. Clinton will probably propose an advisory commission in his State of the Union address in January.</p>
        <p>The group, modeled after the Greenspan commission that provided the nonpartisan cover to put Social Security back on track in 1983, would be top-heavy with senior Congressional leaders. The idea is to draft legislation early in 1999, after the 1998 elections. That would give Congress a chance to vote before the Presidential campaign overwhelms bipartisanship.</p>
        <p>Administration sources emphasize that the commission would have to be buttressed by a campaign to build public support. That may not be easy since, unlike 1983 when Congress could argue that the cupboard was bare, failure to act would have no immediately visible consequences. Payroll taxes will more than cover promised pensions for at least 15 more years, when the vanguard of the baby boomers heads for Sun City.</p>
        <p>It may be even more difficult to cobble together a consensus plan than to convince taxpayers of the need for one. For while pension experts generally agree that changes are needed, they are all over the place on substance.</p>
        <p>At one end of the spectrum are remnants of the New Deal coalition, led by former Social Security Commissioner Robert Ball, who want to limit reforms to tucks and trims that would delay the day of reckoning for perhaps an extra decade. At the other, conservative intellectuals ranging from a former Reagan adviser, Martin Feldstein, to the staff at the Cato Institute want full privatization of the system, perhaps along the lines of Chile's celebrated makeover.</p>
        <p>In fact, the White House and the Republican leadership are both prepared to discount these extremes.</p>
        <p>The serious players agree that the safety net, Social Security's minimum pension benefit combined with means-tested welfare for the elderly and disabled, must remain intact. They are in accord that reforms cannot be built around permanent increases in the payroll tax. But the divisions are still fundamental.</p>
        <p>The center-right, notably the economists Carolyn Weaver of the American Enterprise Institute, Lawrence Kotlikoff of Boston University and Sylvester Schieber at Watson Wyatt Worldwide pension consultants, want to redirect a big chunk of the existing payroll tax into I.R.A.-style instruments. They want to finance the transition costs -- money needed to cover current retirees' pensions -- from temporary taxes or from substantial cuts in future benefits to those not yet retired.</p>
        <p>The center-left, including Edward Gramlich of the University of Michigan and Henry Aaron of the Brookings Institution, may be willing to create personally owned retirement accounts on top of the existing Social Security structure. But their goal is to make additional compulsory retirement savings palatable to a younger generation unwilling to pay more taxes for what has already been promised them. If the center-left had its way, individuals would have little discretion over where the money was invested, or when earnings from personal accounts could be converted to spendable cash.</p>
        <p>Social Security reform is not impossible. Hardly anyone, after all, predicted that Congress would pass radical tax reform in 1986. But, for the moment, optimism depends on faith in the wisdom of policy makers and the virtue of politicians.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
