<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study of Ocean Currents Offers Clues to Global Climate Shifts</title>
    <meta content="18OCEA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970325T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="916426"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Akkadian Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mesopotamia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E6D91238F93BA25750C0A961958260" item-length="2358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study of Ocean Currents Offers Clues to Global Climate Shifts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists studying ocean currents find clues to how and why the earth's climate is changing, the role of human activity in global warming and even how ancient civilizations of Mesopotamia vanished thousands of years ago; say that since 1970's the oscillation of water temperature in North Atlantic and similar oscillation in Pacific have made continents of Northern Hemisphere unusually warm in winter and spring, a major reason for an especially sharp rise in average global surface temperature from 1970's to 1990's; new evidence is also emerging that implicates North Atlantic oscillation in long drought that archeologists believe caused collapse, starting about 4,200 years ago, of ancient Akkadian civilization of Mesopotamia (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As scientists struggle to understand how and why the earth's climate is changing, they are increasingly looking deep into the oceans, where oscillations in water temperature that travel on stately currents from one continent to another may cause weather trends to change from decade to decade.</p>
        <p>These flip-flops in climate, which scientists suspect owe their slow decadal pacing to the sluggish movement of ocean currents and the sea's prodigious ability to retain heat and move it around, determine whether winter in Northern Europe, Asia and parts of North America will be generally mild or severe -- for 20 to 30 years at a time. They control long-term rainfall patterns over wide areas. They help determine where ocean fish can thrive and where they cannot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As scientists struggle to understand how and why the earth's climate is changing, they are increasingly looking deep into the oceans, where oscillations in water temperature that travel on stately currents from one continent to another may cause weather trends to change from decade to decade.</p>
        <p>These flip-flops in climate, which scientists suspect owe their slow decadal pacing to the sluggish movement of ocean currents and the sea's prodigious ability to retain heat and move it around, determine whether winter in Northern Europe, Asia and parts of North America will be generally mild or severe -- for 20 to 30 years at a time. They control long-term rainfall patterns over wide areas. They help determine where ocean fish can thrive and where they cannot.</p>
        <p>And now, scientists are studying them for clues to whether the earth's climate will be warmer in the future than it is now, and to why the ancient civilizations of Mesopotamia vanished thousands of years ago.</p>
        <p>One of the major oscillations, in the North Atlantic, may be in the process of switching to a new state, one with far-reaching implications for the study of global warming.</p>
        <p>Since the 1970's, scientists say, the North Atlantic oscillation and a similar oscillation in the Pacific have made the continents of the Northern Hemisphere unusually warm, on the average, in winter and spring. This natural heating is believed to be a major reason for an especially sharp rise in the average global surface temperature from the 1970's to the 1990's.  Mainstream scientists say emissions of heat-trapping waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide are also partly responsible, but they do not know which effect is more important.</p>
        <p>The change in the North Atlantic oscillation may tell them. Last year it made its sharpest reversal on record, cooling off Eurasia and casting Northern Europe into two harsh winters in a row. North America cooled as well, though the mechanism is less clear. If the overall rise in global temperatures continues in the face of continental cooling, it would offer strong support to the theory that human activity -- particularly the emission of heat-trapping gases into the atmosphere -- is disrupting the global climate system.</p>
        <p>Just as important, climatologists would have a better idea of the magnitude of any human impact. The last cool period linked to ocean oscillations, in the 1950's and 1960's, interrupted a century-long global warming trend that resumed only when the oscillation switched again in the 1970's. This time, though, average global temperature remained at a near-record level last year despite the cooler continents. But two winters' data do not establish a trend, so scientists will be watching intently to see what happens in the years just ahead.</p>
        <p>''If we decide the system has flipped, and if then the global warming were to continue, that would be kind of disconcerting,'' said Dr. Michael S. McCartney, a physical oceanographer at the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution at Woods Hole, Mass.</p>
        <p>Climate oscillates on seasonal, annual, decadal and century-long time scales, with smaller swings imposed on larger ones. But it is the decade-to-century scale that is most relevant to the question of human-induced climate change, since that is the shortest span over which it can be reliably detected.</p>
        <p>On this scale, the oceans provide the heartbeat of climate: their inertia determines the pace of natural change. Climatic oscillations in the atmosphere, many scientists believe,  would play out rapidly if they were stripped of their contact with the seas. But because the ocean and the atmosphere are linked by the mutual transfer of heat, moisture and motion, the atmosphere to a great extent must dance to the tempo of the seas.</p>
        <p>So far, scientists studying oscillations on the decade-to-century scale have concentrated on the Northern Hemisphere, where both the Pacific and Atlantic climatic seesaws affect mainly the winter and spring seasons. In one phase of the Pacific oscillation, sea-surface temperatures in the western three-quarters of the North Pacific are cooler than normal, while the tropics are warmer. In this state, the tropical sea warmth extends northward along the North American coast to west of the Gulf of Alaska. This creates an atmospheric pattern in which winters tend to be milder and drier in Alaska, Canada and the Pacific Northwest, cooler in the Southeastern United States and wetter in the Southwest.</p>
        <p>This pattern has been entrenched since the mid-1970's; before that, starting about 1945, sea-surface temperature relationships were reversed, and so were the atmospheric consequences. Temperature patterns recorded by tree rings show that these flip-flops have come every 20 to 30 years for the last 200 years, suggesting that a new flip might now be due. But it is too soon to tell whether that is happening, said Dr. John M. Wallace, an atmospheric scientist at the University of Washington in Seattle. ''It's very difficult to know where you are in real time,'' he said. ''It's easy with hindsight to go back and see when it flipped.''</p>
        <p>A number of ideas have been proposed about what drives the Pacific oscillation. One says that subsurface ocean machinations outside the tropics are responsible. Another holds that interactions between the tropical and mid-latitude oceans are the cause. Some scientists suggest that El Nino, the vast pool of unusually warm surface water that comes and goes every few years in the eastern tropical Pacific, may in some fashion trip the trigger for decade-to-decade oscillations.</p>
        <p>Strikingly different forces appear to be at work in the Atlantic. There, Dr. McCartney and other scientists are focusing on a huge, powerful current that carries warm water from the vicinity of Florida to the coast of Ireland before turning westward, cooling, sinking and curling back south near Labrador. The existence of this oceanic pipeline, which begins as the Gulf Stream and becomes the North Atlantic Current as it heads east across the ocean, has long been known. But Dr. McCartney believes, based on observations at sea, that it is linked with the atmosphere to produce the North Atlantic oscillation's interdecadal rhythm.</p>
        <p>His analysis and that of others has found that deep-lying parcels of unusually warm water move continually through the pipeline, alternating with cooler ones. Each parcel takes about 20 years to travel from the tropics, around the North Atlantic circuit to Labrador. Observations indicate that sea-surface temperatures rise and fall in concert with the movement of these parcels and with the speed of the pipeline current -- and atmospheric pressure above the sea appears to rise and fall in concert with all the other factors.</p>
        <p>When these factors are in one phase of the oscillation, characterized by lower sea-surface temperatures, powerful west-to-east winds across the Atlantic are on average stronger. This carries more oceanic warmth to Northern Europe and Asia, making for milder winters there (though cooler, the ocean is still warmer than the land). An analysis by Dr. James Hurrell of the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., has shown that in this phase, Northern Europe has more precipitation than normal, while Southern Europe and the Middle East have less.</p>
        <p>When the system flips, the opposite is true: the westerlies weaken and shift southward, making Northern Europe much colder and drier but bringing more warmth and precipitation to Mediterranean Europe, Africa and the Middle East. Eastern Canada and Greenland are warmer.</p>
        <p>While the system's elements do indeed appear to work in concert as Dr. McCartney says, not all aspects of his explanation of the oscillation's workings are nailed down, said Dr. Hugo Bezdek, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Atlantic Oceanographic and Meteorological Laboratory in Miami. ''I wouldn't call it an airtight case yet,'' he said. For one thing, he said, the origin of the warm-water parcels that move through the pipeline is unknown; for another, evidence of the ocean's connection to the atmosphere ''is suggestive, but I wouldn't call it robust.''</p>
        <p>Nor has anyone yet figured out exactly how the oscillation functions.  Some still say the atmosphere may be driving the system, but others say that given the oscillation's stately pace, it is more likely that either the ocean is driving the atmosphere or that the two are locked in a perpetual feedback loop.</p>
        <p>''If Mike's right, this is a dynamite idea,'' Dr. Bezdek said. ''Then you have a scheme to make some predictions,'' something of enormous economic value. It would be possible, for instance, to forecast rainfall trends in Europe and probably the Middle East and North Africa years ahead.</p>
        <p>It might also be possible to predict the abundance of oceanic fish like cod, which depend ultimately on tiny marine animals for their subsistence. A recent study has found that the abundance of one such animal, a copepod called Calanus finmarchicus, rises and falls in close concert with the North Atlantic oscillation.  Other studies have found that populations of Alaskan salmon and Japanese sardines similarly vary with the North Pacific oscillation.</p>
        <p>New evidence is also emerging that implicates the North Atlantic oscillation as the cause of a long drought that archeologists believe caused the collapse, starting about  4,200 years ago, of the ancient Akkadian civilization of Mesopotamia.</p>
        <p>Two paleoclimatologists at the Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory of Columbia University, Heidi Cullen and Dr. Peter deMenocal, extracted a sediment core from the bottom of the Persian Gulf that, they say, shows that huge amounts of dust blew off the Mesopotamian landscape about 4,200 years ago, just as the Akkadian drought was beginning.  Another Lamont researcher, Dr. Gerard Bond, produced evidence from ice cores of a North Atlantic cooling at the same time.</p>
        <p>Building on Dr. Hurrell's work showing that precipitation in Istanbul, near the headwaters of the life-giving Tigris and Euphrates Rivers, has varied in phase with the North Atlantic oscillation, Ms. Cullen analyzed Turkish precipitation records in detail and concluded that when the North Atlantic was cold, the headwaters region was cooler and drier and water flows dropped in the streams that supplied Mesopotamia's water.</p>
        <p>Whether the North Atlantic oscillation could operate over time scales of a century or more, where even larger climate swings have taken place in the last few thousand years, is unclear. ''There's no evidence that it couldn't happen, and no evidence that it did,'' Dr. Bond said. Even so, he said, the ocean could well play some major role in the large, centuries-long climatic fluctuations; variations in the sun's output are another possible cause.</p>
        <p>The two biggest of these fluctuations in recent millenniums were the Medieval warm period, when northern climes were so balmy that the Vikings colonized Greenland and vineyards grew in Britain; and the Little Ice Age, when much of Europe starved in the cold. An especially clear record of these swings, as well as shorter recent ones, has emerged from ocean sediments on the Bermuda Rise, a hump in the ocean floor on which Bermuda sits.</p>
        <p>There, Dr. Lloyd D. Keigwin, a paleoclimatologist at the Woods Hole institution, has tracked the swings for the last 3,000 years by analyzing the fossilized carbonate shells of tiny animals called foraminifera, in this case a species named Globigerinoides ruber, which lives year-round on the surface of the Sargasso Sea.  The shells' chemical content changes according to how cold the climate was at a given time, and Dr. Keigwin has found in them evidence of the larger swings. The shells clearly reflect, for instance, two periods of Medieval warmth, 500 and 1,000 years ago, as well as an even more pronounced warming about 2,500 years ago. The shells show the depths of the Little Ice Age about 300 years ago.</p>
        <p>''The evidence of natural oscillations is clear,'' Dr. Keigwin said.  ''They have been going on as long as we can look back in time.'' According to the shells, a recovery from the Little Ice Age is still going on. The big message from the Bermuda Rise, Dr. Keigwin says, is that to whatever extent humans are warming the climate, that warming is coming on top of a natural post-Little Ice Age warming. ''It could be,'' he said, ''that whatever is driving these oscillations in the ocean may overwhelm what we're doing to the atmosphere -- or it could be that we're making a bad situation worse.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 25, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Science Times last Tuesday with an article about the effects of ocean currents on the global climate misstated deviations from the average high air temperatures at the Kodiak, King Salmon and Cold Bay weather stations in Alaska since 1900. A corrected chart appears today on page C7.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 25, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Science Times last Tuesday with an article about the effects of ocean currents on the global climate misstated deviations from the average high air temperatures at the Kodiak, King Salmon and Cold Bay weather stations in Alaska since 1900. A corrected chart appears today on page C7.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
