<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents</title>
    <meta content="24PATE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOC Gases (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nova-Tech Engineering Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Riordan, Teresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halawani, Mohamed El (Prof)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morocco, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Innovation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Patents</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poultry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5D8113BF937A15752C1A961958260" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Teresa Riordan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Riordan, Teresa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several recent patents offer new ways to raise and slaughter turkeys; patents are issued separately to BOC Gases, to Prof Mohamed El Halawani, to Nova-Tech Engineering Inc and to Steven Morocco (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FEW of the turkeys sitting on American dinner tables this Thanksgiving will have been shot in the wild in the same way that the Pilgrims, at least according to legend, hunted their birds. Instead, turkeys of today are produced commercially.</p>
        <p>Several recent patents offer new ways to go about raising and slaughtering turkeys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FEW of the turkeys sitting on American dinner tables this Thanksgiving will have been shot in the wild in the same way that the Pilgrims, at least according to legend, hunted their birds. Instead, turkeys of today are produced commercially.</p>
        <p>Several recent patents offer new ways to go about raising and slaughtering turkeys.</p>
        <p>BOC Gases, for example, recently received a patent for the ''humane slaughter of poultry.'' The idea is to send turkeys (or chickens) through a chamber containing carbon dioxide and argon but very little oxygen. The turkeys suffocate after one to two minutes inside the chamber.</p>
        <p>This technique has several advantages over the standard way that birds are killed today, according to Bill Baker, director of food marketing at the company's American headquarters in Murray Hill, N.J.</p>
        <p>Normally, a poultry worker has to shackle the bird's legs and hang it upside down so that its head is immersed in water. An electrical current then passes through the water, stunning the bird so that it feels less pain when its neck is slit.</p>
        <p>''Hanging a chicken or turkey is one of the worst jobs in a plant,'' Mr. Baker said. ''Their wings are flapping and they're very unhappy.'' Although the BOC chamber kills the birds, they still have to be hung upside down and have their throats slit to drain the blood. ''But picking up a turkey that's already dead is a much easier job,'' Mr. Baker said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker also said that electrically stunning the birds damaged some meat. ''It can cause broken bones and hemorrhaging which can give blood spots to the meat,'' he said. ''This is particularly a problem in Europe, which is more animal-welfare-oriented and requires a more intense electrical stun.''</p>
        <p>Poultry processed using the BOC chamber can be carved up many hours earlier than electrically stunned birds, according to Mr. Baker, because ''the gas sting accelerates rigor mortis.''</p>
        <p>Antony Roger Spencer Audsley, Neville George Gregory and Ambur Balakrishnan Mohan Raj received patent 5,653,629, which was assigned to BOC.</p>
        <p>Solving Problem Of 'Broody' Turkeys</p>
        <p>Turkey hens like to lay a clutch of eggs and then sit on them until they hatch. But a turkey farmer takes the eggs away and hatches them elsewhere so that the hen will keep laying more eggs. Often these hens, unhappy over the absence of their progeny, go ''broody.''</p>
        <p>''These broody hens are upset,'' said Mohamed El Halawani, a professor of reproductive physiology at the University of Minnesota in St. Paul. ''They'll try to bite the farmer. And they stop laying eggs.''</p>
        <p>Prof. Halawani discovered that broody hens secrete elevated levels of vasoactive intestinal peptide, which, as it circulates in the blood, signals the pituitary gland that it should release prolactin, a hormone. High levels of this hormone cause ovulation to cease.</p>
        <p>So Professor Halawani created antibodies that thwart the activity of the peptide, keeping it from turning on the prolactin, he said.</p>
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration has just authorized field studies using the antibodies, according to Professor Halawani, who received patent 5,557,033.</p>
        <p>Helping Reduce Pain and Shock</p>
        <p>Commercially bred turkeys and chickens are raised in close proximity. So the tips of beaks often are either cut off or cauterized to prevent the birds from injuring one another.</p>
        <p>These procedures, however, produce ''a substantial amount of pain and shock in the bird,'' according to a patent recently granted to Marc Gorans and Scott Johnson.</p>
        <p>Their patent covers a device that exposes the top beak of a bird to high-frequency radiation, while shielding the bird's tongue and lower beak. The radiation results in the top beak falling off after a couple of weeks, according to the patent. The bottom beak, which is not a very effective weapon, remains and can be used for eating and drinking.</p>
        <p>Patent 5,651,731 was assigned to Nova-Tech Engineering Inc. of Willmar, Minn.</p>
        <p>Turkey Call Mounted on Gun</p>
        <p>For those who still hunt turkeys in the wild, Steven Morocco of Somerset, Pa., has invented a way to mount a turkey call on a shotgun.</p>
        <p>Many hunters use a mouth-diaphragm turkey call, which fits into the mouth. ''But a lot of people can't use them because they have a gag reflex or they just don't have time to practice to get the right sound,'' Mr. Morocco said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morocco's mount, which is U-shaped and made to hold a push-button turkey call, clips onto the barrel of the gun. ''There's a lanyard that you pull with whatever hand that you're not using to shoot the gun,'' Mr. Morocco said. ''It activates the call.''</p>
        <p>Turkeys have never been known for their intelligence, but they do have excellent eyesight. ''This way you can use the call with minimal movement so you don't frighten the turkey,'' said Mr. Morocco, who sells the walnut mounts through Penns Woods in Delmont, Pa. He received the design patent D377,383.</p>
        <p>Patents are available by number for $3 from the Patent and Trademark Office, Washington, D.C. 20231.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
