<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Congress, the Kibbitzer at the Climate Table, Waits for Its Turn</title>
    <meta content="01CONG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="GLOBAL WARMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor Role in Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Business Role in Politics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor Role In Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Business Role In Politics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE1DA143AF932A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Congress, the Kibbitzer at the Climate Table, Waits for Its Turn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Skeptical and suspicious Congress will be watching closely as Clinton Administration negotiates international treaty to curb global warming; coping with climate change is shaping up as another thorny intergenerational issue that forces lawmakers to make painful political choices now that will probably not yield tangible benefits for years or decades; few in Congress have studied issue in depth, but many are staking out stands consistent with those of their labor, business or environmental allies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN President Clinton's negotiators sit down in Japan on Dec. 1 with their international counterparts to hammer out a treaty to fight global warming, a skeptical and suspicious Congress will be watching closely over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>A growing body of scientific evidence supports the idea that emissions of heat-trapping gases are disrupting normal weather patterns. Opinion polls show that the theory is gaining public credibility.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN President Clinton's negotiators sit down in Japan on Dec. 1 with their international counterparts to hammer out a treaty to fight global warming, a skeptical and suspicious Congress will be watching closely over their shoulders.</p>
        <p>A growing body of scientific evidence supports the idea that emissions of heat-trapping gases are disrupting normal weather patterns. Opinion polls show that the theory is gaining public credibility.</p>
        <p>But Congress is wary. Coping with climate change is shaping up as another thorny intergenerational issue, like overhauling Social Security or Medicare, that forces lawmakers to make painful political choices now that will probably not yield tangible benefits for years or even decades.</p>
        <p>At a spirited hearing earlier this month, House members groped with how to deal with the problem. They bombarded Timothy E. Wirth, an Undersecretary of State who has been the Administration's lead negotiator on global warming, with detailed questions that he could not answer about a treaty's economic consequences. In exasperation, Representative Dan Schaefer, a Colorado Republican who heads the House Commerce energy and power subcommittee, warned Mr. Wirth, ''If you do it dumb, it could cost a lot of money.''</p>
        <p>The politics of global warming on Capitol Hill is still very much unformed. Only a handful of lawmakers have studied the complicated issue in depth. But that has not stopped many others from staking out positions consistent with those of their traditional allies in labor, business or the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>Even after President Clinton's vow last month that the United States would not sign any climate treaty that hurt the American economy or failed to win commitments from developing nations to reduce their carbon dioxide emissions, Congress is still dubious.</p>
        <p>CONGRESS plays a pivotal role in the issue. Any treaty will require approval from two-thirds of the Senate. The House has no formal role in ratifying treaties, but every step needed to carry out an accord, from policy changes to spending on programs, would have to go through that chamber.</p>
        <p>The lawmakers' underlying fear is that the United States will end up shouldering an unfair share of the emissions reductions. That, they say,  would lead to some kind of energy tax to curb consumption, which would chill the economy, which would cost jobs. Legislators also express concern that binding limits on emissions might be deferred for large developing countries like China and Mexico, projected as the fastest-growing polluters of the future.</p>
        <p>Republicans are already promising to make tax cuts a major issue in the 1998 Congressional elections, so they say any accord that even hints at a tax increase will be dead on arrival.</p>
        <p>''Protecting our environment is an honorable goal,'' Representative Bill Paxon, a fast-rising Republican star from New York, said earlier this fall.  ''But we must ask ourselves an equally important question: 'Can we afford to destroy our children's economic future in the process?' ''</p>
        <p>Of course, unyielding opposition to action would be a tricky proposition for even the most free-market Republicans. President Clinton and the Democrats have used environmental issues -- and the perceived disdain Republicans have for them -- as an effective political cudgel in the past two years. But in the current political climate, economic concerns trump most environmental worries.</p>
        <p>The science of global warming is still a contentious issue among lawmakers. A solid core of members of Congress -- most of them Republicans, but some Democrats -- insist that the proposed emissions changes are based on inconclusive evidence. That position is supported by the major foes of a climate treaty: the oil, coal and automobile industries and major electric utilities.</p>
        <p>''The science doesn't fit into neat little boxes,'' said Senator Chuck Hagel, a Nebraska Republican who is leading a Senate observer group to the final negotiations in Kyoto, Japan. ''Many climatologists will tell you this is nonsense. We just don't know enough about it.''</p>
        <p>But other lawmakers are leery of the Administration's plan to reduce emissions to 1990 levels by 2012 even though they agree that there is an impending crisis. Senator Robert C. Byrd, a West Virginia Democrat who is a powerful defender of the nation's coal industry, said, ''The problem is global and can only be solved on a global basis.''</p>
        <p>Democrats and Republicans are divided within their own ranks. Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority leader, and Representative John D. Dingell, a Michigan Democrat who staunchly defends Detroit's automobile industry, criticize the Administration for going too far.</p>
        <p>An avid environmentalist, Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California, says President Clinton must make a stronger case for a global agreement. ''There is no consensus on the Hill, and there won't be until the President explains the issue better to the American people,'' Mr. Waxman said.</p>
        <p>CONGRESS has already influenced the Administration's negotiating position. On a vote of 95 to 0 in July, the Senate passed a resolution urging the Administration not to pursue a treaty unless the agreement requires developing nations to control their emissions.</p>
        <p>This nonbinding resolution forced the Administration to harden its stance toward developing countries.  The measure also urged Mr. Clinton to avoid any treaty that would cause ''serious harm'' to the American economy, a provision that helped move the Administration away from considering direct energy taxes and toward a series of tax credits and research subsidies to encourage energy conservation.</p>
        <p>''Our challenge,'' said Senator John F. Kerry, Democrat of Massachusetts, ''is to shape an agreement which sets tough, realistic global-emission reduction goals while harnessing market forces to lower costs, foster technological development and insure economic growth.''</p>
        <p>Treaties are complex documents that, even after they are signed, take years of preparation before they can be ratified. ''Assuming a fully acceptable treaty is reached in Kyoto,'' said Todd Stern, a senior adviser to Mr. Clinton on climate change, ''you could be well into 1999 by the time you're talking about ratification.''</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
