<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 1/2-Week Delay in Fixing Mir Seems Likely, Russians Say</title>
    <meta content="19ORBI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mir (Space Station)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE7D6163BF93AA25754C0A961958260" item-length="983" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 1/2-Week Delay in Fixing Mir Seems Likely, Russians Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>KOROLYOV, Russia, July 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian space officials say they will probably wait for new crew to arrrive at damaged Mir space station before undertaking space walk to repair it; Mir's string of misfortunes made last few weeks emotionally draining for current crew and ground controllers; new crew would not face same stress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Russian space officials said today that they would probably wait for a new crew to arrive at the damaged Mir space station before undertaking a space walk to repair it.</p>
        <p>The word came just one day after NASA announced it would allow an American astronaut, Michael Foale, to be trained to perform the complex repair mission, which involves a lengthy space walk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Russian space officials said today that they would probably wait for a new crew to arrive at the damaged Mir space station before undertaking a space walk to repair it.</p>
        <p>The word came just one day after NASA announced it would allow an American astronaut, Michael Foale, to be trained to perform the complex repair mission, which involves a lengthy space walk.</p>
        <p>It also followed a largely successful effort to bring the battered Mir back to life after one of the crew accidentally caused a major power loss on Thursday. The station had already lost half its power on June 25 as a result of a collision with an unmanned cargo craft.</p>
        <p>Even given the vagaries of life in space, Mir's misfortunes have made the last few weeks emotionally draining for the crew and ground controllers at the center here near Moscow.</p>
        <p>Within the span of a week, the Russian commander was declared unfit for a space walk, Mr. Foale emerged as a candidate to take part in the repair and a crucial cable was mistakenly disconnected.</p>
        <p>These events finally led ground control officials to say Mir's crew may be too fatigued and tense to conduct the complex repair mission. Vladimir Solovyov, the mission director said, ''Maybe it is better done by the crew which is now preparing at the ground training center and which will be fresh when it comes to the station.'' This crew is to be launched on Aug. 5.</p>
        <p>That assessment was seconded by Igor B. Goncharov, the deputy flight chief for medical affairs. ''The doctors think this crew needs some rest,'' Mr. Goncharov said. ''Probably the decision will be made that this is the next crew's job.''</p>
        <p>A final decision will not be made before Monday, when top Russian space designers gather to review what is required.</p>
        <p>Sergei Krikalyov, the deputy mission director and a veteran cosmonaut, said the delay was likely to be demoralizing to the crew, which has already endured a dangerous fire, the collision and this week's emergency power shortage. ''If I was on the flight, I would be kind of upset,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said today that the latest crisis occurred as the crew was preparing for the repair mission. One astronaut -- Russian officials say they do not know which one and have not asked -- disconnected a cable that transmits power and data to the computer that controls Mir's position in orbit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krikalyov said the cable was to be disconnected before the repair space walk, but not before adjustments had been made to Mir's computer systems. ''The particular cable was the last in a sequence,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The loss of power caused the space station to drift and turned its solar arrays away from the Sun. As a result, the batteries on board were seriously drained, forcing the astronauts to turn off life-control systems, communications systems and lights to conserve power.</p>
        <p>Leroy Chiao, an American astronaut who has been overseeing the repair plans, said the mistake may have occurred because of the crew's eagerness to prepare for the space walk. ''The speculation is that they were trying to get ahead'' for the space walk, Mr. Chiao said.</p>
        <p>It is still not clear how long it took the crew to realize the seriousness of the error.</p>
        <p>Mr. Krikalyov said alarms on Mir should have told the crew immediately that they had blundered. But Mr. Chiao said hours went by before the crew or the ground controllers reacted.</p>
        <p>''It took the whole night for the batteries to run down,'' Mr. Chiao said in an interview. ''Nobody really understood the problem -- either on the ground or on board.''</p>
        <p>Despite the crisis atmosphere on Thursday, the Russians have already managed to largely rectify the mistake. By firing Mir's thrusters, the space station has stabilized its position and redirected its solar arrays toward the Sun.</p>
        <p>''We regained attitude control and have started to recharge the batteries,'' Mr. Kirkalyov said.</p>
        <p>As the batteries are being recharged, Mir's systems have gradually been brought back to life. Electricity has been restored to the core module and the carbon dioxide removal system has been activated. The gyrodynes, used to maintain Mir's position in orbit, are to be turned on Saturday.</p>
        <p>After the latest crisis, the crew was ordered to get three days' rest.</p>
        <p>The success in restoring Mir does not mean that the longer-term repair effort is back on schedule. The aim of those repairs is to restore power that was lost as a result of the June collision. This involves donning space suits, opening the Spektr module, reconnecting power cables and installing a special hatch.</p>
        <p>The new crew to be launched toward Mir on Aug. 5 includes two cosmonauts, Anatoly Solovyov and Pavel Vinogradov, who have been training in a water tank at the Star City space center outside Moscow for a space walk within Mir and are now likely to carry it out.</p>
        <p>A French scientist has been scheduled to fly with the two Russians. But Paris says that he needs power from the Spektr module to conduct his experiments and that his tour on Mir is now expected to be delayed until next year.</p>
        <p>The longer-term task is to repair the hole in the Spektr module and repressurize it, but Mr. Krikalyov said Russian specialists are still trying to figure out how to do this.</p>
        <p>''It will be a very interesting experiment to see if it is possible to seal the module,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
