<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Backs Tough Steps For a Treaty On Warming</title>
    <meta content="T26POLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="976297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Poll</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6DF133AF93BA15752C1A961958260" item-length="1418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Backs Tough Steps For a Treaty On Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Times Poll finds American people are far more willing than their Government to take early, unilateral steps to counter threat of global warming; they appear to be unimpressed by industry arguments that cutting United States' emissions of heat-trapping gases into atmosphere might cause undue economic harm; 65 percent of those polled say US, which releases more such greenhouse gases than any other country, should take steps now to cut its own emissions 'regardless of what other countries do'; delegates from 166 nations will assemble in Kyoto, Japan, to try to negotiate tougher, binding treaty on controlling emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases; Clinton Administration has proposed binding treaty, but not until another 10 or 15 years have passed; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the world's nations gather in Japan to discuss how best to counter the threat of global warming, the American people are far more willing than their Government to take early, unilateral steps, a New York Times Poll has found.</p>
        <p>They appear to be unimpressed by arguments that cutting the United States' emissions of heat-trapping gases into the atmosphere might cause undue economic harm, as industry groups opposing a treaty have contended.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the world's nations gather in Japan to discuss how best to counter the threat of global warming, the American people are far more willing than their Government to take early, unilateral steps, a New York Times Poll has found.</p>
        <p>They appear to be unimpressed by arguments that cutting the United States' emissions of heat-trapping gases into the atmosphere might cause undue economic harm, as industry groups opposing a treaty have contended.</p>
        <p>Sixty-five percent of those polled said that the United States, which releases more such greenhouse gases than any other country, should take steps now to cut its own emissions ''regardless of what other countries do.'' The poll had a margin of sampling error of plus or minus three percentage points.</p>
        <p>Only 15 percent of the 953 people polled by telephone on Sunday and Monday said the United States should delay acting until many countries agree how to address the problem together.</p>
        <p>Better-educated people are most likely to favor early action by the United States. Fully three-quarters of college graduates favor acting even without a binding treaty, as do 59 percent of high school graduates. Men and women are equally likely to favor unilateral action.</p>
        <p>Delegates from 166 nations are assembling Monday in Kyoto to try to negotiate a tougher, binding treaty on controlling emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases that trap the Sun's heat in the Earth's atmosphere and threaten to change the planet's climate. The treaty would supplant the voluntary pact that was adopted five years ago at the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration's position going into the talks has been criticized by European nations who say it would delay action for too long, and many Third World nations have been resisting the Administration's insistence that developing countries join the industrial nations in pledging to cut emissions.</p>
        <p>American emissions of greenhouse gases have been increasing ever since the world's industrial nations agreed five years ago to try to reduce them by the turn of the century. The Administration has proposed a binding treaty stabilizing emissions at the 1990 levels, but not until another 10 or 15 years have passed.</p>
        <p>The poll suggests that the public rejects the main arguments against such a treaty that have been voiced by industry groups, some unions and their allies in Congress. Rather, most Americans tend to agree with the position on the talks taken by major environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Still, just 1 percent of all respondents offered the environment when asked what was the most important problem facing the country; crime topped the list. When asked what environmental problem was most important, people were more likely to name air and water pollution than global warming. Twenty-seven percent said they had heard or read a lot about global warming and 38 percent said they had heard or read ''some'' about it. About a third said they knew ''not much'' or ''nothing'' about it.</p>
        <p>Generally, Americans strongly favor environmental protection despite its costs, the poll showed. Sixty-one percent of respondents favor protecting the environment even it it costs jobs in their community; 57 percent said environmental improvements must be made regardless of costs. Majorities have taken that view for 15 years.</p>
        <p>Major industries, including companies that produce and consume large amounts of fossil fuels, have criticized the Administration for moving too quickly on global warming, saying that the science of global warming remains uncertain and that limiting energy use or raising energy prices could needlessly harm the American economy.</p>
        <p>But neither of these arguments appear to carry much weight with the public.</p>
        <p>Fifty-seven percent of those surveyed agreed that the American economy would become more competitive if the nation controlled greenhouse gas emissions ''because these efforts will result in more efficient energy use, saving money in the long run.'' Only 17 percent agreed that cutting emissions ''will cost too much money and hurt the U.S. economy.''</p>
        <p>Only 16 percent said that they believed global warming results from normal fluctuations in climate rather than from emissions released when people burn fossil fuels like coal, oil and gasoline.</p>
        <p>Asked when serious effects from global warming might be expected, an even smaller minority, 13 percent, said they believed global warming would have no serious effect.</p>
        <p>In contrast, 23 percent said they believed global warming's impact was already serious.</p>
        <p>Another 43 percent said global warming's effects would not be felt until the future. Despite that belief, 6 out of 7 people in this group said steps were needed right away to counter global warming.</p>
        <p>Younger adults, especially those less than 30 years old, were more likely than older ones to believe that the effects of global warming are already being felt. And older people, especially those older than 65, are more likely to believe it will not have a serious impact at all.</p>
        <p>Most people said they would be willing to spend money on efficient appliances, insulation and other energy-saving investments to cut emissions of greenhouse gases and save money on gas and electric bills. Only 20 percent said they would not be willing to do so.</p>
        <p>Forty-one percent of the people in the sample said they would be willing to spend money to cut energy use even if it took as much as five years of reduced gas and electric bills to cover the cost of the investment.</p>
        <p>Far and away the most popular approach to cutting emissions was for the Government to impose energy efficiency standards on manufacturers of cars, appliances and so on.</p>
        <p>Fifty percent said they would favor this approach, while 20 percent said they favored tax breaks for nonpolluting energy like solar and wind power. Only 2 percent said they favored extra taxes on gasoline or other fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>It appeared that people were not ready to endorse the Administration's proposed approach to reducing emissions of greenhouse gases, which would involve a complicated system of trading pollution permits.</p>
        <p>When this system was described and people were told that it ''would give companies a financial reason to reduce their emissions of greenhouse gases,'' 49 percent said they did not know enough to judge the proposal's merits. Fifteen percent said it was a good idea, and 17 percent said it was a bad idea.</p>
        <p>How the Survey Was Conducted</p>
        <p>The latest New York Times Poll is based on telephone interviews conducted on Sunday and Monday with 953 adults across the United States.</p>
        <p>The sample of telephone exchanges called was selected by a computer from a complete list of exchanges in the country. The exchanges were chosen to assure that each region of the country was represented in proportion to its population. For each exchange, the telephone numbers were formed by random digits, thus permitting access to both listed and unlisted numbers. The numbers were then screened so that calls would be placed to residences only. Within each household one adult was designated at random to be the respondent for the poll.</p>
        <p>The results from all regions were weighted to reflect the actual adult population of the nation. The results have also been weighted to take account of household size and number of telephone lines and to adjust for variations in race, sex, age, and education.</p>
        <p>In theory, in 19 cases out of 20 the results based on such samples will differ by no more than three percentage points either way from what would have been obtained from all American adults.</p>
        <p>In addition to sampling error, the practical difficulties of conducting any survey of public opinion may introduce other sources of error into the poll.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
