<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Mission Is to Shine Up A Grimy City</title>
    <meta content="09ABOU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="About New York" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="921571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="About New York"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stuart-Dean</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maxwell, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">About New York (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CEED7173CF93AA35757C0A961958260" item-length="836" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Mission Is to Shine Up A Grimy City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>About New York column discusses work of those who keep buildings and other structures in New York City clean; Bill Maxwell, supervisor at Stuart-Dean, comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''THIS is what you call a stress area,'' Bill Maxwell said as he approached 30 Rockefeller Center. The weary faces on the 9-to-5 stragglers who slowly walked out into the night confirmed that. His solution for that worn look? Acetone.</p>
        <p>Had he been talking about the office workers, that would have put a spring to their step. Mr. Maxwell barely noticed them. He was explaining how to clean the bronze door handles that are grabbed and dulled by thousands of hands each day. That's one of the details he notices in his supervisor's job for Stuart-Dean, a company that sends legions of its workers into the city each night to buff and restore the sleek metal and gleaming stone that lend a touch of class to the best addresses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''THIS is what you call a stress area,'' Bill Maxwell said as he approached 30 Rockefeller Center. The weary faces on the 9-to-5 stragglers who slowly walked out into the night confirmed that. His solution for that worn look? Acetone.</p>
        <p>Had he been talking about the office workers, that would have put a spring to their step. Mr. Maxwell barely noticed them. He was explaining how to clean the bronze door handles that are grabbed and dulled by thousands of hands each day. That's one of the details he notices in his supervisor's job for Stuart-Dean, a company that sends legions of its workers into the city each night to buff and restore the sleek metal and gleaming stone that lend a touch of class to the best addresses.</p>
        <p>''How can somebody not like this?'' said Mr. Maxwell as he walked among the granite and mirror-slick bronze in the lobby of 520 Madison Avenue, near 53d Street. ''And some people hate New York.''</p>
        <p>He hates the car exhaust, acid rain, grubby hands and inconsiderate pedestrians that wreak havoc on his beloved architectural details in New York, where the sheer density of commercial towers makes it the epicenter for his kind of work. The push to landmark buildings erected by armies of craftsmen earlier in the century has also helped propel the industry.</p>
        <p>Face it. New York is where the buildings, money and the dirt are.</p>
        <p>''On a nice day like today, our phones ring off the hook,'' said John Gargiulo, who heads the company that his grandfather founded 65 years ago. ''Soon as we have a few spring days with sun, building managers walk outside, look at their buildings and say, 'Good grief!' This is the time when people panic.''</p>
        <p>THE result might be a gentle polishing of out-of-reach metal entryways or a spa-like overnight poultice -- a mud pack -- to draw out the grime lodged in stone walls. Revolving door frames, scratched by everything from shopping carts and those bulky buckles on messenger bags, also need a lot of attention. A simple scratch can take up to an hour to remove with sandpaper and polish.</p>
        <p>But despite the city's image as a sometimes uncaring place, Mr. Gargiulo said he is heartened by some recent trends. Decades after some priceless structures were torn down to make way for progress, more buildings are being refurbished, especially in parts of Chelsea and midtown. Increasingly, the city is actually looking pristine is some parts, too.</p>
        <p>''The Mayor has really cleaned this city up and brought it back to the prestige it once had,'' he said. ''It's clear to us the city is cleaner and more interest is going into commercial buildings. It's just the pride.''</p>
        <p>He contrasted the attention paid to this work in New York with cities in Europe or Asia, where his company has branched out.</p>
        <p>''This isn't done everywhere,'' he said. ''Believe it or not, even though Germany is a clean country, they don't look as pristine as the buildings do in New York. The European way is not to concern themselves with ongoing maintenance.''</p>
        <p>THAT'S William Gonzalez's mission. The setting sun cast a warm glow on him as it reflected off the revolving doors he was cleaning in Two World Financial Center. He likes the variety of his work, how it takes him all over the city. But his dedication has a limit. ''At home, I don't like to clean anything at all,'' he said. ''My wife wanted to get a brass bed. I said no way, Jose. I do enough at work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maxwell, who had stopped by the site to check on the job's progress, laughed in solidarity when he heard that. He drove north to another building, marveling at the city that emerges from the shadows each night, more fascinating than any elegant structure he has seen in his 70 years.</p>
        <p>''There's a show out there and you don't even have to pay a dime,'' he said. ''Watching people walk into the theater and seeing how good they look. How beautiful people look at night. The fires. The crime. The whole ball.''</p>
        <p>He once tried to work in Los Angeles, which he hated almost as much as the brief fling he had with retirement six years ago.</p>
        <p>''I missed the streets,'' he said. ''I was born in the streets.''</p>
        <p>A seen-it-all smile crossed his face when he talked about the hustlers who stroll past his company's garage on 10th Avenue at 31st Street.</p>
        <p>''Here, you got everything, rich and poor right next to each other,'' he said. ''You go outside and the prostitutes solicitate you. Fifteen minutes later, I could be at the Rainbow Room.''</p>
        <p>A little grit is good for the soul, not to mention his business.</p>
        <p>About New York</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
