<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Refuses to Concede Fund-Raising Mistakes</title>
    <meta content="05GORE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978013"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3DD103DF936A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Refuses to Concede Fund-Raising Mistakes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, in interview with New York Times, refuses to concede that he had made any mistakes in how he raised money or how he handled political accusations against him; says Republican Party is determined to prevent change in campaign financing; says it is unfair for people to dwell on months of publicity about his appearance at Buddhist temple, fund-raising solicitations from White House and his legalistic defense of himself at news conference in March (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first extensive interview about the fund-raising storm that has enveloped him for nearly a year, a defiant Vice President Al Gore today refused to concede that he had made any mistakes in how he raised money or how he handled the political accusations against him.</p>
        <p>Casting the furor in partisan terms, Mr. Gore asserted that ''the Republican Party is bound and determined to prevent change'' in campaign financing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his first extensive interview about the fund-raising storm that has enveloped him for nearly a year, a defiant Vice President Al Gore today refused to concede that he had made any mistakes in how he raised money or how he handled the political accusations against him.</p>
        <p>Casting the furor in partisan terms, Mr. Gore asserted that ''the Republican Party is bound and determined to prevent change'' in campaign financing.</p>
        <p>And he said it was unfair for people to dwell on the months of scorching publicity about his appearance at a Buddhist temple, fund-raising solicitations from the White House and his legalistic defense of himself at a news conference in March.</p>
        <p>''A snapshot does not have as much accuracy as a moving picture,'' Mr. Gore said. ''Perspective is very important in politics. At the beginning of January in 1997, we had a high deficit, higher unemployment, less people with health insurance.''</p>
        <p>Many of the closest advisers to Mr. Gore have said he regrets some aspects of how he reacted to the campaign finance accusations. The advisers, inside and outside the White House, also described the accusations as the most severe political crisis of Mr. Gore's career -- one that had upset his carefully planned efforts toward the Democratic Presidential nomination in 2000.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore said he was not distracted by the drumbeat against him. Asked repeatedly whether he had made mistakes -- in raising money or in reacting politically -- he did not answer. The closest he came to acknowledging that it had been a difficult year was when Mr. Gore referred to ''adversity.''</p>
        <p>''This has been a great learning experience, really and truly,'' he said in the interview with The New York Times, in his White House office. ''I think that you learn more from adversity than you do from the success. I think growth comes more easily and naturally when you learn how to move past the difficult moments. I think this past year really has been a great year for the country.''</p>
        <p>For months, Mr. Gore declined requests for interviews. His aides said he was waiting for the Dec. 2 deadline for Attorney General Janet Reno to announce whether she would seek an independent counsel to investigate telephone calls by President Clinton and Mr. Gore. Ms. Reno declined to appoint a counsel, but she said the Justice Department's inquiry into campaign finance practices in the 1996 campaign was not over.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Gore was clearly seeking to move beyond the accusations about his conduct. Asked about the controversy over Louis J. Freeh, the Director of the Federal Bureau of Investigation, who had made clear his disagreement with Ms. Reno's decision, Mr. Gore said:</p>
        <p>''I haven't heard such comments. The only comments I heard were perfectly proper, and I've had a productive, appropriate working relationship with him. But this was Attorney General Reno's decision.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore did not say he had regrets about the March news conference, for which he has been lampooned for repeatedly defending his phone calls from the White House by saying there was ''no controlling legal authority'' on whether they were permissible. Today, he said of the event: ''There were misunderstandings that came out. But the full and independent review confirms the essential elements of what I said.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore also defended some of his closest advisers who have been accused of using their connections to him to lobby the Government in exchange for lucrative fees. Asked about Peter S. Knight, one of Mr. Gore's closest friends who has come under scrutiny for his lobbying, the Vice President said:</p>
        <p>''Peter is one of the most honorable, honest men I have ever known in my life. The partisan attack against him has hit way wide of their intended mark. He's a great friend.''</p>
        <p>Among other things, Republicans accuse Mr. Knight of using his 20-year friendship with the Vice President to help a Massachusetts company win Government contracts and a visit from Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he did not feel responsible for friends who had been pulled into the inquiries.</p>
        <p>''Everybody who gets involved in national politics,'' he said, ''understands that the partisanship is higher now than a few years ago.''</p>
        <p>The Vice President struggled for an answer when asked several times whether he had learned any lessons from this year, or whether he would do anything differently in how he raised money. He asserted that the attacks on his integrity had not exacted any personal toll on him.</p>
        <p>''Putting things in perspective involves understanding part of the attacks are part of the American political system,'' he said. ''It's always better to see them in perspective and not as a personal matter. That's an important lesson to learn. It was reinforced periodically this year.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the interview, Mr. Gore adhered to generalities, declining even to describe what he disliked about the existing system of raising money for campaigns. Asked about what some lawmakers consider an unseemly process, Mr. Gore said, ''The American people are right to demand change, and we agree that sweeping campaign finance reform is needed.'' He then said the Republicans were ''content with the current system.''</p>
        <p>Determined not to be engaged on the subject, Mr. Gore responded to some questions by referring to the news conference he held eight months ago -- saying his perspective had not changed.</p>
        <p>Asked whether he would be more cautious in raising money, he said it was ''premature to speculate'' about his political ambitions.</p>
        <p>He was far more interested in talking about matters like global warming and the humming economy.</p>
        <p>Charles Burson, counsel to Mr. Gore, said in an interview that the Vice President was bracing for more accusations from Republicans.</p>
        <p>''They're going to keep attacking him,'' Mr. Burson said. ''They're going to keep dredging up the Buddhist temple. You just got to deal with it because it's going to keep coming. I don't see it letting up.''</p>
        <p>But Ralph Reed, the Republican strategist, offered a bright outlook for Mr. Gore today.</p>
        <p>''My bet is Al Gore will be the nominee,'' Mr. Reed told reporters. ''I think relatively handily.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
