<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skeptic Asks, Is It Really Warmer?</title>
    <meta content="01SKEP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="GLOBAL WARMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindzen, Richard S (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0D9143AF932A35751C1A961958260" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skeptic Asks, Is It Really Warmer?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, MASS., June 17, 1996</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with leading climate scientist Dr Richard S Lindzen, who holds there is no evidence that emissions of greenhouse gases could disrupt world's climate; he notes carbon dioxide and other waste industrial gases generate only small amount of warming, while limits of atmospheric water vapor content, factor that could greatly amplify effects of gases, are not known; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS climate experts firm up their view that human activity is seriously altering the atmosphere, one voice stands out in clarion dissent. It is that of Dr. Richard S. Lindzen of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a shoemaker's son from the Bronx who has risen through the academic hierarchy as a leading expert on the physical processes of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Is there truly cause to worry that emissions of waste industrial gases that trap heat like carbon dioxide could disrupt the world's climate?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS climate experts firm up their view that human activity is seriously altering the atmosphere, one voice stands out in clarion dissent. It is that of Dr. Richard S. Lindzen of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, a shoemaker's son from the Bronx who has risen through the academic hierarchy as a leading expert on the physical processes of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Is there truly cause to worry that emissions of waste industrial gases that trap heat like carbon dioxide could disrupt the world's climate?</p>
        <p>Dr. Lindzen does not equivocate. ''We don't have any evidence that this is a serious problem,'' he says flatly, with precise diction, in a friendly voice that resonates strongly in his 17th-floor office overlooking Boston across the Charles River. A clutter of folders and papers, coupled with Dr. Lindzen's untrimmed black beard and hornrim glasses, suggest the academic theorist he is.</p>
        <p>His opinions attacking the formal consensus about climate change have made the 56-year-old Dr. Lindzen a bete noir to environmentalists who trumpet the dangers of global warming and a champion to political conservatives and industrial interests who minimize the threat. Admirers see him as a force for intellectual honesty in a highly politicized debate. Critics fault him for professing unwarranted sureness in a field of research rife with uncertainty. Many say he is simply wrong.</p>
        <p>But everyone takes him with the utmost seriousness because of a reputation for brilliance that got him elected to the National Academy of Sciences at age 37.</p>
        <p>Regents' and National Merit scholarships at the Bronx High School of Science (class of 1956) propelled him as a student first to Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute and then to Harvard University, where he was attracted by classical physics, and then atmospheric physics. After various academic posts, he joined the M.I.T. faculty in 1983, where he is the Alfred P. Sloan Professor of Meteorology.</p>
        <p>In recent years, while pursuing his main interest of atmospheric dynamics in trying to help ''figure out how climate works,'' he has leveled a variety of criticisms at the idea of serious climatic change, some with telling effect. The idea that has attracted most attention is based on a fundamental point of physics: that carbon dioxide and the other waste gases generate only a small amount of warming. Something has to amplify that warming for the larger amount of warming predicted by the United Nations panel to materialize.</p>
        <p>The main candidate, whose presumed amplifying effect is built into the computer models, is water vapor -- also a heat-trapping gas, and the most powerful one since there is so much of it and it is so pervasive. The theory is that a warmer atmosphere holds more water vapor, thereby increasing the warming even more. Without this amplification, Dr. Lindzen argues, the average global temperature will rise by only about a degree Fahrenheit if atmospheric carbon dioxide is doubled.</p>
        <p>While it is well known that warmer air generally holds more vapor, he says, ''we don't know what determines upper level water vapor,'' a factor he says is crucial, and central to the predictions of future climate change.</p>
        <p>To some critics, Dr. Lindzen's confidence about the climate's low sensitivity to carbon dioxide emissions embodies more certitude than the facts allow. ''I don't know what line from God he has,'' says Dr. Stephen Schneider of Stanford University, who cites what he sees as the overprecise estimate Dr. Lindzen gives.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lindzen replies that he at least gives some reasons for his estimate rather than simply following a ''herd instinct'' that he says is very common in science.</p>
        <p>He says that he prizes the environment, but that global warming and other issues have prompted environmental groups to go ''off the deep end'' and produce ''a drum roll that gets rid of perspective.''</p>
        <p>In 5 or 10 years, Dr. Lindzen says, direct observations of the climate's behavior might well make it clearer who is right in the greenhouse debate. Could he turn out to be wrong when all is said and done?</p>
        <p>''I think it's unlikely,'' he said, ''but it can happen.''</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
