<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>100 Years Of Being Really Big</title>
    <meta content="28SAFI0AC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="983663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4D81F3EF93BA15751C1A961958260" item-length="2451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>100 Years Of Being Really Big</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kenneth T. Jackson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A century ago New Yorkers celebrated New Year's Eve with special exuberance. Dec. 31, 1997, was filled with speeches, parades, fireworks, brass bands and the reading of a commissioned ''Ode to Greater New York.'' At midnight, illuminated by the glow of 500 magnesium lights, thousands of people gathered in front of City Hall (there was as yet no Times Square and no descending ball) to sing ''Auld Lang Syne'' and watch the raising of the city's new flag.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A century ago New Yorkers celebrated New Year's Eve with special exuberance. Dec. 31, 1997, was filled with speeches, parades, fireworks, brass bands and the reading of a commissioned ''Ode to Greater New York.'' At midnight, illuminated by the glow of 500 magnesium lights, thousands of people gathered in front of City Hall (there was as yet no Times Square and no descending ball) to sing ''Auld Lang Syne'' and watch the raising of the city's new flag.</p>
        <p>Five counties and 40 municipalities were now one enormous metropolis. New York's population instantly jumped to 3.4 million from 2 million, making it the second-largest city in the world, trailing only London. and by absorbing Brooklyn as well as remote outlying villages like Jamaica, Douglaston and Flushing in Queens and Tottenville, Stapleton and Great Kills on Staten Island, the city expanded to 300 square miles from 44.</p>
        <p>The consolidation of the five boroughs, coming 272 years after Dutch colonists gave birth to the city, was the brainchild of Andrew Haswell Green, the president of the Central Park Commission, who in 1868 had proposed uniting under one municipal roof all the territory that today comprises the Bronx, Brooklyn, Manhattan, Queens (a portion of which was withheld - it would soon become Nassau County) and Staten Island.</p>
        <p>The final push for consolidation came from a Republican governor and Republican state legislators, who evidently hoped that the addition of middle-class voters from outlying districts would dilute the influence of Tammany Hall, Manhattan's powerful Democratic organization.</p>
        <p>Considering the magnitude of the issue, it generated surprisingly little debate, although individual communities reacted differently to consolidation. Some parts of the Bronx, like Kingsbridge, Morrisania and West Farms, had joined the city as early as 1874. The rest of the borough, however, lagged 21 years behind.</p>
        <p>Brooklynites were especially reluctant. They feared, justifiably, that their proud community, at the time the nation's fourth-largest city, would be overwhelmed by its more powerful neighbor and that consolidation would change the Protestant character of Brooklyn's neighborhoods. In a non-binding referendum held in 1894, Brooklynites voted to join Manhattan by the slimmest of margins - 65,744 to 65,467. The victory was secured only because Brooklyn was strapped fiscally and needed tax revenue from Manhattan to pay for schools, roads, water mains and sewers.</p>
        <p>Had New York City remained as Manhattan alone, its population would have peaked at 2.3 million in 1910, leaving the city second in size to Chicgao. Had Manhattan added only the Bronx, the city's population would never have reach 3.4 million - Chicago still would have surpassed it in population eventually.</p>
        <p>But consolidation gave Gotham vast new spaces, and its population continued to soar. From 1900 to 1930 both Queens and the Bronx grew six-fold, and Brooklyn more than doubled. By 1930, New York had almost seven million inhabitants and had overtaken London as the world's largest city.</p>
        <p>Without consolidation, the other boroughs might have become important cities in their own right. In 1997, Brooklyn has about as many inhabitants as Chicago, Queens more than Philadelphia, the Bronx more than Detroit and Staten Island more than St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Not that New York was unique in its territorial expansion. Almost every major American city expanded its boundaries after 1850. And in the 20th century, Los Angeles, Houston, Dallas, Jacksonville, Oklahoma City, Memphis, Phoenix, Indianapolis and San Diego have all annexed space; All are now bigger in area than New York and have had proportionately larger population increases. (The growth of New York, of course, did not stop at the city border - the entire region has grown tremendously. Now, 63 percent of the 20 million people in the metropolitan region live outside the city.)</p>
        <p>What is unusual about New York is that its transformation has been consistent with its own past and different from that of other American cities. In at least 10 ways, the metropolis remains distinct in ways exaggerated, not diminished, by the passing of 100 years.</p>
        <p>Temp. New Yorkers walk faster, work longer, eat later and compete harder than most other Americans.</p>
        <p>These behavioral patterns have deep roots. In 1626, when the Dutch set up a permanent trading post on Manhattan, their goal was not to convert the Indians or to achieve religious freedom, but to make money.</p>
        <p>Visiting Manhattan in 1774 from Puritan Boston, Johna Adams complained, ''I have not seen one real gentle-man, one well-bred man, since I came to town.'' New Yorkers, he added, ''talk very loud, very fast, and altogether.''</p>
        <p>''If they ask you a questions,'' Adams continued, ''before you can utter three words of your answer, they will break out on you again and talk away.''</p>
        <p>Poor breeding? Perhaps. But New Yorkers established the first Chamber of Commerce in the Western Hemisphere in 1768, developed the concept of regularly scheduled shipping service in 1818, built the erie Canal by 1825 and established the nation's dominanat stock exchange by the 1840's.</p>
        <p>Diversity. In recent decades, every important city has become multicultural, multiracial and multireligious. But New York has never been anything else. As early as the 1640's, 18 different languages were already being spoken in colonial New Amsterdam, whose population was still less than a thousand.</p>
        <p>Ever since, New York has been the most polyglot place on earth. By 1880, when the city had the world's largest immigrant labor force, tourists might walk for blocks without hearing, or seeing, a word of English. As Jacob Riis noted in his 1890 classic, ''How the Other Half Lives,'' ''A map of the city, colored to designate nationalities, would show more stripes than on the skin of a zebra, and more colors than any rainbow.''</p>
        <p>In 1947, when New York became the headquarters of the United Nations, it was already a United Nations in miniature. Fifty years have not changed this. In 1997, more than 11 of every 20 New Yorkers are immigrants or the children of immigrants. The metropolitan region has more Brazilians than any similar area outside South America, more Greeks than any city outside Greece, more Chinese than any city outside Asia, and more Jews, Puerto Ricans and Deominicans than any city anywhere.</p>
        <p>Tolerance. Despite tragic ethnically charged incidents in Howard Beach, Crown Heights and other neighborhoods, most New Yorkers have learned to control their prejudices.</p>
        <p>Again, the Dutch set the standard. In the early 17th century, even as Anne Hutchinson was being kicked out of Boston because of minor religious differences, the West India Company was welcoming Lutherans, Quakers, Anabaptists, Catholics and Jews to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>New York has always been ahaven for outcasts, sinners, revolutionaries, anarchists and dissidents. Can it be mere coincidence that the American Communist Party, the N.A.A.C.P. and the gay rights in the city? Or that Pakistanis and Indians, Arabs and Jews, Bosnians and Serbs, and Irish Portestants and Catholics manage, for the most part, to coexist in New York in peace?</p>
        <p>Density. Compared with other American cities, New York has always been crowded. The first Dutch settlers hudled together below Wall Street. A century ago, the average population density on the Lower East Side exceeded 260,000 per square mile, and in certain precincts it reached 600,000 per square mile, a total never matched at any other time or in any other place.</p>
        <p>Today, New York still stands apart. The population density of San Francisco is 16,000 per square mile; in Chicago the number is 12,000, and in Los Angeles it is 7,500. The density figure for the five boroughs is 25,000 per square mile, and for Manhattan it is 65,000 per square mile.</p>
        <p>As a rule, Americans have been fleeing fromt he inner city. Since 1950, the population of Chicago proper has dropped 25 percent, Baltimore 28 percent, Phildadelphia 29 percent, Washington 32 percent, Cleveland 43 percent, Pittsburgh 45 percent, Detroit 46 percent and St. Louis 54 percent.</p>
        <p>New York and San Francisco are the exceptions. The population of each is down only about 5 percent from its peak and has grown for the past 15 years. Houston, San Diego, Phoenix, San Antonio, Dallas and many other cities have made huge gains recently, but they have done so by annexing surrounding territory, and their population density has declined substantially since World War II.</p>
        <p>What makes New York exceptional is that even as many have left the city, others have always been ready to take their place.</p>
        <p>Public transportation. A century ago, the United States had the best and most extensive public transit system in the world. Since thne, in city after city, Americans have ripped up their streetcar tracks, starved their bus systems and built superhighways.</p>
        <p>New York is the exception. Its proportion of the nation's transit riders has doubled in the 20th century, and its subways, buses and commuter trains are used by more people today than a quarter century ago.</p>
        <p>Vibrant central business district. Bustling department stores, once the signature institution of every city, are now only memories in many places, thanks to the urban exodus of the last 50 years, which has given us subdivisions, shopping malls, office parks and highway strip developments but has left American downtowns desolate and forlorn, especially after dark.</p>
        <p>New York again is an exception. Despite the loss of Gimbels, B. Altman and Bonwit Teller, the sidewalks of midtown Manhattan remain crowded, and grand emporiums like Macy's, Lord &amp; Taylor, Bloomingdale's, Saks Fifth Avenue, Brooks Brothers, Bergdorf Goodman and a dozen others continue to enchant windown shoppers as not mall ever could.</p>
        <p>A substantial middle and upper class. In most North American cities, the rich live on the edges and the poor reside in the middle. New Yorkers, to be sure, started this trend. The pioneered the suburban movement in Brooklyn Heights and later in Westchester County, Long Island and New Jersey.</p>
        <p>But the middle class has never really abandoned the center of New York. Neighborhoods throughout the city include the kinds of people who elsewhere would be firmly ensconced in the suburbs. The affluent are conspicuous, too, so much so that Manhattan is the richest county in the nation per capita, the wealthiest ZIP code in America is Manhattan's 10021, and the highest residential real estate values in the United States are along Fifth Avenue, Park Avenue and Central Park West.</p>
        <p>A sustainable environment. The idea of pristine nature and of clean air and water conjures up images of wood-burning Vermonters, not cliff dwellers in Manhattan. But New Yorkers also tread lightly on the land. They use fewer fossil fuels to get from place and to heat and cool their residences. By any measure, apartments are more energy efficient than houses, just as walking and using public transit are more efficient than moving a ton and a half of metal to make a trip to the grocer.</p>
        <p>Public housing. Today, public housing, expecially fo the high-rise variety, is generally considered a failure in the United States. Thousands of units have been abandoned because even the poor refuse to live in such miserable environments. As a result, cities across the nation have razed entire complexes. But not in New york, where tens of thousands of families are on the waiting list and many of the public housing complexes are in remarkably good order, despite major cuts in Federal subsidies in the last 15 years.</p>
        <p>Safety. The scary image of New York, fed by movies and television, causes newcomers a to feel a twinge of fear when they venture out. Actually, New York has seldom been among the nation's most dangerous cities. In part this is the result of a homicide rate that only rarely has been in the nation's top 10 and that recently has plunged so low that Gotham no longer ranks in the top 100 most violent American cities.</p>
        <p>But the unusual freedom from sudden death that New Yorkers enjoy is related to the transportation system and population density, not crime. Quite simply, most New Yorkers are less likely to die prematurely than other Ameicans because of a low automobile fatality rate.</p>
        <p>In other parts of the country, automobiles are required for virtually all journeys. But New Yorkers walk to many destinations. Short trips are the norm. By reducing distance traveled, New Yorkers remain out of the street and thus out of harm's way.</p>
        <p>These 10 characteristics have contributed to New York's status as a unique metropolis. Although many consider it out of date and out of touch, in truth it should be a model for other American cities.</p>
        <p>New York City has intractable problems. Since 1980, the incomes of the poor have fallen dramatically, even as public sympathy for the plight of poor people has eroded. And the gap between rich and poor is higher in New York than anywhere else.</p>
        <p>New York's public schools, once the pride of the city, have in all too many cases become dangerous or dysfunctional. The water system, long the finest in the world, is leaking beneath the streets and in need of major investment. Bridges are rusting dangerously, and New Yorkers often navigate streets that would be an embarrassment to a developing nation. The port, once the busiest in the world, is silting up and losing market share. There were a million factory jobs in 1954; now there are fewer than 200,000.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, over the last 372 years, New York City has shown remarkable resilience and a capacity for change and renewal. Since 1945, for example, it has led the nation into a new service-oriented economy. Meanwhile, its high population density, its reputation for tolerance and acceptance, its concentrated wealth and its striking heterogeneity - in short, its urbanity - have made it the artistic and cultural citadel of the age.</p>
        <p>No other place can so convincingly claim to be the capital of capitalism, the capital of the 20th century and the capital of the world. As John Steinbeck said: ''It is an ugly city, a dirty city. Its climate is a scandal. Its politics are used to frighten children. Its traffic is madness. Its competition is murderous. But there is one thing about it - once you have lived in New York and it has become your home, no other place is good enough.''</p>
        <p>Kenneth T. Jackson, a professor of history at Columbia University, is the author of ''Crabgrass Frontier'' and the editor of ''The Encyclopedia of New York City.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kenneth T. Jackson, a professor of history at Columbia University, is the author of ''Crabgrass Frontier'' and the editor of ''The Encyclopedia of New York City.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
