<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="24FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="939333"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6D71631F937A15755C0A961958260" item-length="1371" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>India and Pakistan Pledge New Effort on Kashmir</p>
        <p>India and Pakistan pledged to make a new effort to reconcile their differences over the disputed territory of Kashmir. After three days of talks, their foreign ministers agreed to make Kashmir a separate topic for discussion within broader negotiations aimed at achieving detente. The dispute has been the biggest irritant between the two countries for much of the last 50 years. A6</p>
        <p>France Debates Arrests</p>
        <p>The French Justice Minister, Elisabeth Guigou, wondered aloud if gendarmes had gone too far in a huge sweep against pedophiles after four of those arrested apparently committed suicide. Some 800 people were picked up, but only 24 remained under arrest. Human rights groups charged that defendants' rights were trampled, and relatives of one man believed to have killed himself said they would sue.  A6</p>
        <p>U.S. Decried as Polluter  European leaders came before the United Nations and singled out the United States for failing to take forceful action on environmental issues, like reducing emissions of greenhouse gases that contribute to global warming. They had gathered to review how the world has fallen short of the ambitious goals set at a conference five years ago in Rio de Janeiro.  A9</p>
        <p>Intrigue Surrounds Pol Pot  The enemies of Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge leader, are likely to kill him rather than let him testify at a trial where he could implicate them, Cambodia's First Prime Minister Norodom Ranariddh said. He did not identify any country or person in particular, but China was once a Khmer Rouge patron and various Thai interests continue to have close links to the guerrillas.  A10</p>
        <p>Canadian officials, meanwhile, expressed doubt that their genocide law could be used to seek extradition of Pol Pot, as the United States has suggested. The suspect would have to be present in Canada, officials noted, and Canada has no extradition treaty with Cambodia. A10</p>
        <p>Effort to Revive Tories  William Hague, the new Tory leader, pledged to turn Britain's battered Conservatives into a ''party of the future,'' but decided to reinstall a party chairman from the Thatcher era. The choice was considered surprising because Mr. Hague has made a commitment to eliminating scandal, and the new chairman, Cecil Parkinson, 65, was once forced to leave government after his parliamentary secretary revealed she was pregnant with his child.  A11</p>
        <p>U.N. Opens Effort on Cyprus  In a letter to the Security Council, United Nations Secretary General Kofi Annan has called for a ''sustained process of direct negotiations'' to reach a comprehensive settlement in Cyprus. He notified the council that the leaders of the Greek and Turkish Cypriot communities would hold face-to-face talks in July. (Reuters)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-17, B10-11</p>
        <p>In Reversal, Court Allows Aid in Religious Schools  The Supreme Court overturned one of its own precedents to declare that the Constitution permits public school systems to send teachers into parochial schools to teach remedial and supplemental classes to needy children. The 5-to-4 decision ends a 12-year period during which public school systems, obliged by Federal law to provide the special services to all students who qualified but barred by the Court from delivering them on parochial school premises, had to use expensive alternatives. A1</p>
        <p>President Clinton suffered a setback in the Whitewater investigation when the Court refused to review a subpoena that orders White House lawyers to surrender notes they had taken of conversations with Hillary Rodham Clinton. A1</p>
        <p>The Court also ruled that states may confine violent sex offenders in mental hospitals after they have served their criminal sentences, even if the offenders are not so mentally ill as to meet a state's ordinary criteria for civil commitment against their will. B11</p>
        <p>Army Hearing Is Opened  Civilian judges on the military's highest court ordered the Army to open to the public a hearing involving sexual misconduct charges against the Army's most senior enlisted soldier. Lawyers said they could not recall any instance in which the court, which has jurisdiction over the entire military justice system, had ordered one of the military services to open a hearing that the service wanted closed. A17</p>
        <p>Senate Alters Health Plan  Leaders of the Senate Finance Committee said they had agreed to revise their proposal to make affluent elderly people pay more for Medicare. The change would retain the idea of such a ''means test,'' but would make it easier for the Government to administer. A13</p>
        <p>Tobacco Pact Under Attack  Critics began a concerted attack on the proposed $368 billion tobacco liability settlement, citing numerous provisions they consider too favorable to cigarette makers and demanding that major portions of the agreement be rewritten. Dr. C. Everett Koop, the former Surgeon General and longtime anti-tobacco crusader, called the deal ''deeply flawed.'' A17</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the Liggett Group, the first tobacco company to negotiate a deal with government officials, said that the settlement reached with other leading tobacco companies last week could force it into bankruptcy. A16</p>
        <p>Hubbell Faulted in Audit  Former Associate Attorney General Webster L. Hubbell overstated the amount of work he performed as a lobbyist for the Los Angeles Department of Airports in 1994 and the city should seek to recover $24,750 in fees, an inquiry by the city controller's office concluded. B11</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION  B1-9</p>
        <p>Railway Workers Lose Asbestos Exposure Case  The Supreme Court ruled that 140 pipe fitters and underground workers from Grand Central Terminal exposed to cancer-causing asbestos dust are not entitled to seek damages from Metro North Commuter Railroad for emotional distress before the onset of actual disease. The ruling noted that the lead plaintiff, Michael Buckley, had ''suffered wrong at the hands of a negligent employer,'' but with no signs of disease or emotional distress he could not seek recourse. B1</p>
        <p>Mayor Gains Union Support  The largest firefighters union plans to endorse the re-election effort of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who so far is faring better in the battle for union support than Republicans typically do in New York City. B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS  B13-19</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES  C1-8</p>
        <p>Diabetes Threshold Moved  Levels of blood sugar that have long been accepted as normal are actually too high and should be considered a sign of diabetes, according to new guidelines issued by the American Diabetes Association and endorsed by Federal health authorities. A1</p>
        <p>Obesity Linked to Genetics  Human obesity, a condition affecting a third of Americans, has for the first time been found to have a genetic cause, at least in some cases. The condition, a defect in a gene that controls body weight, has been found in two cousins studied by scientists in England. C3</p>
        <p>ARTS  C9-19</p>
        <p>Insects Invade Hollywood  At least a half-dozen scripts involving insects are in various stages of development and production in Hollywood, turning them into a formidable screen presence. The last wave of insect films took place at the outset of the atomic age, exemplified by ''Them!,'' the 1954 classic about giant ants running wild in the Southwest after an atomic test. C9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY  D1-19</p>
        <p>Gates Creates Foundation  William H. Gates, the software entrepreneur sometimes criticized for being too slow to give away his billions, is creating a new foundation that intends to spend $200 million over five years to bring new computers and the Internet into the nation's public libraries. D1</p>
        <p>Dow Plummets at Close  The stock market plunged in a late wave of selling that turned what seemed to be a routine session into the worst of the year. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 192.25 points, or 2.47 percent, to 7,604.26. D1</p>
        <p>Compaq to Buy Tandem  The Compaq Computer Corporation agreed to acquire Tandem Computers in a stock swap valued around $3 billion. D1</p>
        <p>Pennzoil Is Target of Bid  Union Pacific Resources began a hostile $4 billion offer for the Pennzoil Company, seeking to capture rich petroleum reserves and a venerable brand name. D4</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES  D20</p>
        <p>Betty Shabazz  The widow of slain civil rights leader Malcolm X who sought to preserve his memory and teachings while raising their six daughters and making a career as a college official was 61. A1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL  A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: A trial for Pol Pot; public teachers in parochial schools; Steven R. Weisman on the Denver summit.</p>
        <p>Columns: A. M. Rosenthal, Russell Baker.</p>
        <p>Chronicle B8</p>
        <p>Bridge C18</p>
        <p>Chess  C6</p>
        <p>Crossword C18</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-11</p>
        <p>India and Pakistan Pledge New Effort on Kashmir</p>
        <p>India and Pakistan pledged to make a new effort to reconcile their differences over the disputed territory of Kashmir. After three days of talks, their foreign ministers agreed to make Kashmir a separate topic for discussion within broader negotiations aimed at achieving detente. The dispute has been the biggest irritant between the two countries for much of the last 50 years. A6</p>
        <p>France Debates Arrests</p>
        <p>The French Justice Minister, Elisabeth Guigou, wondered aloud if gendarmes had gone too far in a huge sweep against pedophiles after four of those arrested apparently committed suicide. Some 800 people were picked up, but only 24 remained under arrest. Human rights groups charged that defendants' rights were trampled, and relatives of one man believed to have killed himself said they would sue.  A6</p>
        <p>U.S. Decried as Polluter  European leaders came before the United Nations and singled out the United States for failing to take forceful action on environmental issues, like reducing emissions of greenhouse gases that contribute to global warming. They had gathered to review how the world has fallen short of the ambitious goals set at a conference five years ago in Rio de Janeiro.  A9</p>
        <p>Intrigue Surrounds Pol Pot  The enemies of Pol Pot, the Khmer Rouge leader, are likely to kill him rather than let him testify at a trial where he could implicate them, Cambodia's First Prime Minister Norodom Ranariddh said. He did not identify any country or person in particular, but China was once a Khmer Rouge patron and various Thai interests continue to have close links to the guerrillas.  A10</p>
        <p>Canadian officials, meanwhile, expressed doubt that their genocide law could be used to seek extradition of Pol Pot, as the United States has suggested. The suspect would have to be present in Canada, officials noted, and Canada has no extradition treaty with Cambodia. A10</p>
        <p>Effort to Revive Tories  William Hague, the new Tory leader, pledged to turn Britain's battered Conservatives into a ''party of the future,'' but decided to reinstall a party chairman from the Thatcher era. The choice was considered surprising because Mr. Hague has made a commitment to eliminating scandal, and the new chairman, Cecil Parkinson, 65, was once forced to leave government after his parliamentary secretary revealed she was pregnant with his child.  A11</p>
        <p>U.N. Opens Effort on Cyprus  In a letter to the Security Council, United Nations Secretary General Kofi Annan has called for a ''sustained process of direct negotiations'' to reach a comprehensive settlement in Cyprus. He notified the council that the leaders of the Greek and Turkish Cypriot communities would hold face-to-face talks in July. (Reuters)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A12-17, B10-11</p>
        <p>In Reversal, Court Allows Aid in Religious Schools  The Supreme Court overturned one of its own precedents to declare that the Constitution permits public school systems to send teachers into parochial schools to teach remedial and supplemental classes to needy children. The 5-to-4 decision ends a 12-year period during which public school systems, obliged by Federal law to provide the special services to all students who qualified but barred by the Court from delivering them on parochial school premises, had to use expensive alternatives. A1</p>
        <p>President Clinton suffered a setback in the Whitewater investigation when the Court refused to review a subpoena that orders White House lawyers to surrender notes they had taken of conversations with Hillary Rodham Clinton. A1</p>
        <p>The Court also ruled that states may confine violent sex offenders in mental hospitals after they have served their criminal sentences, even if the offenders are not so mentally ill as to meet a state's ordinary criteria for civil commitment against their will. B11</p>
        <p>Army Hearing Is Opened  Civilian judges on the military's highest court ordered the Army to open to the public a hearing involving sexual misconduct charges against the Army's most senior enlisted soldier. Lawyers said they could not recall any instance in which the court, which has jurisdiction over the entire military justice system, had ordered one of the military services to open a hearing that the service wanted closed. A17</p>
        <p>Senate Alters Health Plan  Leaders of the Senate Finance Committee said they had agreed to revise their proposal to make affluent elderly people pay more for Medicare. The change would retain the idea of such a ''means test,'' but would make it easier for the Government to administer. A13</p>
        <p>Tobacco Pact Under Attack  Critics began a concerted attack on the proposed $368 billion tobacco liability settlement, citing numerous provisions they consider too favorable to cigarette makers and demanding that major portions of the agreement be rewritten. Dr. C. Everett Koop, the former Surgeon General and longtime anti-tobacco crusader, called the deal ''deeply flawed.'' A17</p>
        <p>A lawyer for the Liggett Group, the first tobacco company to negotiate a deal with government officials, said that the settlement reached with other leading tobacco companies last week could force it into bankruptcy. A16</p>
        <p>Hubbell Faulted in Audit  Former Associate Attorney General Webster L. Hubbell overstated the amount of work he performed as a lobbyist for the Los Angeles Department of Airports in 1994 and the city should seek to recover $24,750 in fees, an inquiry by the city controller's office concluded. B11</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION  B1-9</p>
        <p>Railway Workers Lose Asbestos Exposure Case  The Supreme Court ruled that 140 pipe fitters and underground workers from Grand Central Terminal exposed to cancer-causing asbestos dust are not entitled to seek damages from Metro North Commuter Railroad for emotional distress before the onset of actual disease. The ruling noted that the lead plaintiff, Michael Buckley, had ''suffered wrong at the hands of a negligent employer,'' but with no signs of disease or emotional distress he could not seek recourse. B1</p>
        <p>Mayor Gains Union Support  The largest firefighters union plans to endorse the re-election effort of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, who so far is faring better in the battle for union support than Republicans typically do in New York City. B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS  B13-19</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES  C1-8</p>
        <p>Diabetes Threshold Moved  Levels of blood sugar that have long been accepted as normal are actually too high and should be considered a sign of diabetes, according to new guidelines issued by the American Diabetes Association and endorsed by Federal health authorities. A1</p>
        <p>Obesity Linked to Genetics  Human obesity, a condition affecting a third of Americans, has for the first time been found to have a genetic cause, at least in some cases. The condition, a defect in a gene that controls body weight, has been found in two cousins studied by scientists in England. C3</p>
        <p>ARTS  C9-19</p>
        <p>Insects Invade Hollywood  At least a half-dozen scripts involving insects are in various stages of development and production in Hollywood, turning them into a formidable screen presence. The last wave of insect films took place at the outset of the atomic age, exemplified by ''Them!,'' the 1954 classic about giant ants running wild in the Southwest after an atomic test. C9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY  D1-19</p>
        <p>Gates Creates Foundation  William H. Gates, the software entrepreneur sometimes criticized for being too slow to give away his billions, is creating a new foundation that intends to spend $200 million over five years to bring new computers and the Internet into the nation's public libraries. D1</p>
        <p>Dow Plummets at Close  The stock market plunged in a late wave of selling that turned what seemed to be a routine session into the worst of the year. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 192.25 points, or 2.47 percent, to 7,604.26. D1</p>
        <p>Compaq to Buy Tandem  The Compaq Computer Corporation agreed to acquire Tandem Computers in a stock swap valued around $3 billion. D1</p>
        <p>Pennzoil Is Target of Bid  Union Pacific Resources began a hostile $4 billion offer for the Pennzoil Company, seeking to capture rich petroleum reserves and a venerable brand name. D4</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES  D20</p>
        <p>Betty Shabazz  The widow of slain civil rights leader Malcolm X who sought to preserve his memory and teachings while raising their six daughters and making a career as a college official was 61. A1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL  A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: A trial for Pol Pot; public teachers in parochial schools; Steven R. Weisman on the Denver summit.</p>
        <p>Columns: A. M. Rosenthal, Russell Baker.</p>
        <p>Chronicle B8</p>
        <p>Bridge C18</p>
        <p>Chess  C6</p>
        <p>Crossword C18</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
