<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="06FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4DD1E3DF935A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>Netanyahu Calls for Delay In Palestinian Transfers  After meeting in Paris with Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel said his Government wanted to wait at least five months before handing any more territory to the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>Netanyahu Calls for Delay In Palestinian Transfers  After meeting in Paris with Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel said his Government wanted to wait at least five months before handing any more territory to the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Mayor for Mexico City  Cuauhtemoc Cardenas Solorzano was sworn in as the first elected mayor of Mexico's huge capital city. Mr. Cardenas, who many Mexicans believe was fraudulently deprived of victory in presidential elections in 1988, vowed to ''take this city away from the criminals.''</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Partial Progress in Kyoto  An agreement on cutting the industrial countries' emissions of heat-trapping waste gases seemed possible at a conference on global warming in Japan. But the prospects were threatened by a lack of progress on the immediate role that developing countries should play in controlling the gases.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Irish May Drop Belfast Claims  Prime Minister Bertie Ahern said the Irish Republic was prepared to drop its constitutional claim to sovereignty in the British province of Northern Ireland. He said a referendum could be held to change the Constitution. His remarks were not taken kindly by leaders on both sides of the peace talks in Belfast.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Swiss Banks Pay Some Claims  Swiss banks said they have begun paying claims related to dormant accounts dating back to World War II. A spokeswoman for the Swiss Bankers Association said the first payments went to ''10 or 12'' cases and that ''30 to 40'' others were ready for payment, but she declined to specify the amounts or the nationalities involved. The banks published lists of dormant accounts in July and October that identified some 5,500 accounts opened by foreigners before the end of the war and now worth around $47 million.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Strike Goes Forward in Israel  A three-day-old strike by about 700,000 public sector workers in Israel appeared likely to continue after unions pledged not to capitulate to a pending court order that may impose fines on union leaders. Halted airline service has stranded thousands of passengers in the airport at Jerusalem. Cash machines began to run dry, as did irrigation pipes to many communities and farms.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>The Price of Freedom in Congo  President Laurent Kabila of Congo told 31 detainees accused of embezzling state money during the time when Mobutu Sese Seko, the late dictator, was in power that they could buy their freedom by repaying the state. Mr. Kabila urged the detainees, who have spent up to six months in jail awaiting trials, to ''pay what you owe.'' Mr. Kabila toppled Mr. Mobutu in May in the former Zaire and jailed numerous cronies of the old regime. Many others fled before Mr. Kabila's forces reached the capital.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-17, A20</p>
        <p>Police Official 'Confident' Of End to Ramsey Case  Almost one year after the killing of JonBenet Ramsey, the new commander of the police investigation in Boulder, Colo., said the little girl's parents remain under ''an umbrella of suspicion.'' Commander Mark Beckner, who took over the investigation nine weeks ago, said he was confident that the mystery ''will be solved,'' but declined to estimate when he would have a case to present to Boulder's District Attorney, Alexander M. Hunter.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Retreat on AIDS Spending  Less than six months after announcing that it hoped to expand Medicaid to cover all low-income people who are infected with the AIDS virus, the Clinton Administration has backed away from the plan, saying it cannot be done nationwide without increasing spending.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>100 Arrested on Drug Charges  Federal and local authorities from around the nation announced that they had smashed one of the biggest methamphetamine networks in the United States. They reported the arrest of 100 suspects and the breaking up of a ring that had been a major American contractor of Mexico's largest methamphetamine gang.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Court to Hear Schools Case  The Supreme Court agreed to decide when school districts can be found liable under Federal law for a teacher's sexual abuse of a student.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Questions on Shuttle Mission  The astronauts on the space shuttle Columbia returned to a lukewarm welcome and an inquiry into their bungled release of a satellite during the most recent mission.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Tobacco Makers Obey Order  Four giants of the tobacco industry ended a fight with a loyal friend in Congress when they turned over more than 800 internal documents that some investigators suspect hold clues to criminal wrongdoing. The four cigarette-makers complied with subpoenas issued the day before by Representative Thomas J. Bliley Jr., a Virginia Republican who heads the Commerce Committee. Mr. Bliley has long been one of the industry's strongest allies.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>McVeigh Described as Zealot  Lawyers for Terry L. Nichols, who is charged with murder and conspiracy in the April 19, 1995, Federal Building bombing in Oklahoma City that killed 168 people, tried to paint Timothy J. McVeigh as an anti-Government zealot who frequently handed out extremist literature and even wore a T-shirt with a wanted poster for Abraham Lincoln to a child's birthday party.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Inquiry on Arlington Burial  President Clinton ordered an investigation into whether the late U.S. Ambassador to Switzerland, M. Larry Lawrence, lied about his service in the merchant marine during World War II and was appropriately granted a waiver to be buried at Arlington National Cemetery.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-5</p>
        <p>Giuliani Moves to Cement City Control of Gambling  Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, saying he is now convinced casino gambling is coming to New York City, took two major steps to cement the city's control over gambling when it arrives. He said his administration is thinking seriously about where to build a casino in the city, specifically citing Governors Island as a perfect location for a Monte Carlo-like casino and resort. At the same time, he imposed sharp new restrictions on shipboard gambling in New York City, which could begin in earnest next year, and made it clear that the same restrictions would eventually apply to casinos on land.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>3 Charged in T.W.A. Theft  A T.W.A. pilot involved in the investigation of the Flight 800 crash has admitted stealing pieces of the reassembled wreckage and giving them to an author who argued that a missile downed the jetliner, the pilot's lawyer said. The pilot, Terrell Stacey, is likely to plead guilty to a misdemeanor theft charge in the case, the lawyer said, and is cooperating with a Federal investigation of the author, James Sanders, and his wife, Elizabeth Sanders, a T.W.A. flight attendant. The Sanderses were charged with the more serious crime of illegally removing plane crash evidence.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-14</p>
        <p>Survivor's Papers Donated  In spirited bidding in London, the personal documentary history of a Jewish woman who survived Hitler's Germany by assuming an Aryan identity and marrying a Nazi sold at auction for $169,250, five times the top estimate by Sotheby's. The Edith Hahn Archive, as the hundreds of pages of intimate letters, Nazi documents and photographs are called, was purchased by two wealthy Philadelphia businessmen. They said that after having read an account of Ms. Hahn and the auction in The New York Times, they agreed to split the price and donate the contents of the archive to the Holocaust Museum in Washington.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-6</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Morgenthau v. White; Mexico's vulnerable workers; the fight over ''Amistad''; turmoil in the Subcontinent.</p>
        <p>Columns: Maureen Dowd, Frank Rich.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-14</p>
        <p>Unemployment at Record Low  The American economy showed surprising strength last month by creating 404,000 new jobs as the unemployment rate edged down to another 24-year low and wages surged.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Loses Trade Case  The World Trade Organization stunned the United States and Eastman Kodak by vindicating Japan in a dispute over whether the Japanese unfairly protect their photographic film market. The ruling sided completely with Kodak rival Fuji Photo Film and marked an embarrassing failure for the Clinton Administration, which had portrayed the dispute as a challenge to what it contends is a basic problem with the way Japan's economic system works.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Korean Bailout Raises Doubts  Details of South Korea's record bailout agreement depict a broad and bold attempt to reform the world's 11th-largest economy, but the agreement also contains vague provisions that are raising doubts about how it will be enforced.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Chain to Make Barney's Bid  The DFS Group, the world's largest chain of duty-free shops, is preparing to make a bid for Barney's Inc., the New York luxury retailer now in bankruptcy, executives involved in the negotiations said.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>D15</p>
        <p>John E. Moss  The dogged California Congressman whose long, lonely fight against Government secrecy led to the landmark Freedom of Information Act in 1966 was 84.</p>
        <p>D15</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D14</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>B12</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
