<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PREMIER OF INDIA QUITS, DEEPENING POLITICAL BEDLAM</title>
    <meta content="29INDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="976429"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gujral, I K (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EFDB103AF93AA15752C1A961958260" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PREMIER OF INDIA QUITS, DEEPENING POLITICAL BEDLAM</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Saturday, Nov. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>I K Gujral resigns as India's Prime Minister, deepening country's political chaos and economic uncertainty; move comes in wake of Congress Party's withdrawal of support for Gujral's 14-party coalition; few can say who might succeed Gujral or what his departure will mean for issues that have been stalled for months; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>India's fourth Government in 18 months resigned today, deepening the political chaos and economic uncertainty that have overtaken the country since a 1996 election produced a fractured Parliament, almost no political leaders of national stature and no consensus on the issues facing the impoverished nation of 980 million.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister I. K. Gujral, who has served for seven months, went to India's President at midnight on Friday to resign after three weeks of turmoil and scenes of such pandemonium in Parliament that the Speaker, fearing violence, adjourned the session indefinitely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>India's fourth Government in 18 months resigned today, deepening the political chaos and economic uncertainty that have overtaken the country since a 1996 election produced a fractured Parliament, almost no political leaders of national stature and no consensus on the issues facing the impoverished nation of 980 million.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister I. K. Gujral, who has served for seven months, went to India's President at midnight on Friday to resign after three weeks of turmoil and scenes of such pandemonium in Parliament that the Speaker, fearing violence, adjourned the session indefinitely.</p>
        <p>The turmoil, adding to economic woes throughout Asia, sent Indian financial markets into a sharp decline and brought appeals from India's business leaders for the politicians to stop feuding and concentrate on dealing with the country's multiple problems.</p>
        <p>Even after Mr. Gujral quit, few could say who would succeed him or what the implications might be for issues that have been stalled for months.</p>
        <p>The Government's collapse came at a time when hopes had subsided for a period of rapid modernization and growth.</p>
        <p>Partly, that is because a succession of Governments have failed to change the country's inflexible labor laws, cut back on sluggish state-owned enterprises that account for half the country's economy, fulfill promises to open key sectors like insurance to foreign investment or attack a pervasive culture of corruption, criminality and red tape.</p>
        <p>Hours before Mr. Gujral's resignation, three influential business groups issued a collective statement appealing for common sense from the politicians.</p>
        <p>The statement, by the Confederation of Indian Industry, the Associated Chambers of Commerce and Industry and the Federation of Indian Chambers of Commerce and Industry, said the ''political drama'' in New Delhi was draining business confidence and pushing the economy backward.</p>
        <p>''Political expediency and competitive populism must end,'' it said.</p>
        <p>The decisive role now rests with President K. R. Narayanan, who must decide whether to call a new election, an outcome opposed by most parties, or cast about for a new coalition in the existing Parliament.</p>
        <p>The betting among politicians is that Mr. Narayanan will ask Mr. Gujral to remain as interim Prime Minister and call an election in January or February.</p>
        <p>But a revised version of the previous coalition, or some other alignment capable of winning a parliamentary confidence vote, cannot be ruled out.</p>
        <p>The only issue on which most of the parties agree is stopping a Hindu nationalist group, the Bharatiya Janata Party, from taking power. To many parties, this implies avoiding an election, since the Hindu nationalists have been gaining popular support from the parliamentary chaos.</p>
        <p>A number of pressing issues remain before the Government. Mr. Gujral was working to improve India's relations with Pakistan, reform the country's creaky economy and fashion a response to international demands for new limits on emissions of gases blamed for global warming.</p>
        <p>The immediate cause of the Government's collapse was a decision on Friday by the Congress Party, out of power after governing India for 45 of the 50 years since independence, to withdraw its backing from Mr. Gujral's 14-party coalition.</p>
        <p>''The anxiety among the people is now over,'' Sitaram Kesri, the Congress leader, told reporters after he went to Mr. Narayanan to confirm the Congress decision, which doomed the Gujral Government.</p>
        <p>The governing coalition, with 177 members in the 544-seat lower house of Parliament, required the support of the 144 members from the Congress Party and allied groups to maintain its majority.</p>
        <p>Many Indians seem to think that the anxieties over the country's political state will only worsen, especially if a new election produces an equally fractured Parliament, as virtually all opinion polls have predicted.</p>
        <p>Some interpreted the Congress Party move as an attempt toward somehow taking power again despite a steady decline in popular support.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kesri said Congress leaders had acted because of the refusal of Mr. Gujral and his coalition partners to oust from the Government a southern regional group, the Dravida Progressive Party.</p>
        <p>A judicial report published earlier this month linked the group to the assassination in May 1991 of Rajiv Gandhi, a former Prime Minister who was campaigning as Congress Party leader when he was killed at rally in a small town in the southern state of Tamil Nadu.</p>
        <p>At the time, Indian investigators identified Mr. Gandhi's assassin as a 26-year-old female suicide bomber belonging to the Tamil Tiger separatist group in Sri Lanka.</p>
        <p>But a report by M. C. Jain, a judge appointed to investigate the killing, said the Dravida Progressive Party and its leader, Muthuvel Karunanidhi, were complicit in the Gandhi killing because of the group's policy of ''assisting and encouraging'' the Sri Lankan rebels. The party governed the state of Tamil Nadu at the time.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Jain offered little evidence to support his finding, Indians have long known that the Sri Lankan rebels have a strong base of support among Tamil Nadu's 55 million Tamils, who are separated from the Tamil minority in Sri Lanka by a narrow ocean strait.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gujral, a reluctant Prime Minister from the moment he was unexpectedly thrust into the post seven months ago, won widespread respect in India for what many saw as an honest if perhaps insufficiently crafty stewardship of the country.</p>
        <p>At the end he seemed relieved when his United Front coalition decided that it could no longer follow the Congress Party's often whimsical dictates.</p>
        <p>''I am Prime Minister for only a few more days,'' he told a women's conference that met in New Delhi on Thursday to discuss progress on issues like a parliamentary bill reserving one-third of parliamentary seats for women. ''But I will always support you, if not as Prime Minister, then as a person.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kesri told President Narayanan that his party opposed a new election and would seek to form a government itself, an unlikely prospect given that all of the parties in the coalition have vowed not to join Congress in a new government.</p>
        <p>In an election, Mr. Kesri's main hope would rest on reviving old enthusiasms by emphasizing the role of Sonia Gandhi, 51, Rajiv Gandhi's Italian-born widow, who has finally joined the Congress Party and begun appearing at some of its sessions.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gandhi speaks little Hindi, and her emergence as a political figure, Indian commentators have said, is a measure of the Congress Party's desperation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
