<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Internet Changing How Research Centers Work</title>
    <meta content="09THIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="935857"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">rosenberg, geanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFD8153CF93AA35755C0A961958260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Internet Changing How Research Centers Work</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEANNE ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">rosenberg, geanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts in fields as diverse as politics, economics, the environment, law and business are choosing Internet as most efficient forum for policy research; Internet gives everyone opportunity to contribute their thoughts without leaving their desks; long-distance collaboration has been organic part of Internet since it began in academic and Government circles in 1980's, but now it is being used as tool for research centers to reorganize policy discussions, build agreements among specialists and reach out for new voices and new perspectives; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The year is 2050. The place: Earth. The possibilities: a chaotic world at the mercy of warring factions; a world in which sustainable development is mediated by governmental action; a world in which technology has eliminated the threats posed by global warming, population growth and diminished natural resources. Which future is in store and what, if anything, can or should be done about it?</p>
        <p>These questions were collectively addressed by environmentalists, economists, academicians and policy makers. But while the Rand Corporation and the World Resources Institute helped set up the debate, the arena was not a conference room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The year is 2050. The place: Earth. The possibilities: a chaotic world at the mercy of warring factions; a world in which sustainable development is mediated by governmental action; a world in which technology has eliminated the threats posed by global warming, population growth and diminished natural resources. Which future is in store and what, if anything, can or should be done about it?</p>
        <p>These questions were collectively addressed by environmentalists, economists, academicians and policy makers. But while the Rand Corporation and the World Resources Institute helped set up the debate, the arena was not a conference room.</p>
        <p>Instead, it was Hyper Forum, a site in cyberspace where experts convened earlier this year to ''grapple with the range of plausible futures,'' said Robert Lempert, a senior scientist at Rand who helped develop Hyper Forum along with others at Rand, the World Resources Institute, the Markle Foundation and Bruce Murray, a professor of planetary science and geology at the California Institute of Technology and Hyper Forum project leader.</p>
        <p>At Rand, Dr. Lempert said, ''We still have our tank.'' But the notion of a tankless ''think tank'' is not an oxymoron -- not in cyberspace at any rate. Experts in fields as diverse as politics, economics, the environment, law and business are choosing the Internet as the most efficient forum for policy research.</p>
        <p>A case in point is the Cyberspace Law Institute, an Internet-based research group devoted to promoting discussion on the law of cyberspace.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, according to Maggie Powell, electronic publishing manager at the World Resources Institute in Washington, the Internet ''gives everyone the opportunity to be able to contribute their thoughts without leaving their desks.''</p>
        <p>Long-distance collaboration has been an organic part of the Internet since it was incubated in academic and Government circles in the 1980's. Businesses have been built around software, like Lotus Notes, which enhances such collaboration.</p>
        <p>But now the technology that arose from an academic environment is returning in a new guise: as a tool for research centers to reorganize policy discussions, build agreements among specialists and reach out for new voices and new perspectives.</p>
        <p>Hyper Forum provides a clear example of how the Internet is changing the way research centers operate. ''The idea is, a forum is a place where people come together to debate,'' Dr. Lempert said. Group software allowing people to collaborate on complex issues is only one component of Hyper Forum. It contains some of the features of software like Lotus Notes, but adds information, structure and methodology.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the face-to-face meetings that research centers have traditionally held, Hyper Forum allows ''more stakeholders,'' or policy makers, to participate and can reach people who otherwise might not contribute, Dr. Lempert said.</p>
        <p>Opening the doors when there is free food for thought, however, can draw crowds. David Post, a law professor who co-founded the Cyberspace Law Institute, discovered this virtual reality when his institute played host to a cyberconference for nonlawyers on the law of cyberspace. According to Professor Post, more than 20,000 people participated via E-mail. ''There's just not enough time in the universe to deal with that,'' he said, and not all of the queries could be answered.</p>
        <p>''The problem that everyone is trying to deal with with the Web is the information glut,'' which ''degrades the usefulness of the information,'' Dr. Lempert observed. To resolve this problem, he said, Hyper Forum uses a moderator to guide the discussion.</p>
        <p>Roger Hurwitz, research scientist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, predicted that ''the need for collaboration and managing the complexity of collaboration'' is going to increase.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hurwitz and John Mallery, also an M.I.T. research scientist, have developed software for wide- area collaboration. ''Wide-area collaboration is the idea of letting everyone who is relevant within the enterprise work on the material,'' Dr. Hurwitz explained. His software manages and directs participation.</p>
        <p>The Virtual Institute of Information, a search and link network for telecommunications, cybercommunications and mass media research operated by the Institute for Tele-Information at Columbia University has been host to cyberconferences. Topics have included cryptography, electronic publishing and telecommunications law, said Carla Legendre, communications program manager.</p>
        <p>Eli Noam, professor of finance and economics at Columbia and director of the Institute for Tele-Information, has experience with radio and video Internet communications. ''There's a certain aspect at this point of 'Look Ma, no hands,' '' he said of the emerging technologies. But, he added, what distinguishes the Internet is that ''you have the ability to establish very rapidly shifting groups of people to form ad hoc collaborative arrangements.''</p>
        <p>The Internet is providing ''a better informed and better expressed forum for deliberative discourse,'' Dr. Murray said, adding: ''I think the Web is an amazing revolution. I think it's a millennial change and not just a decennial or centennial one.''</p>
        <p>While Internet users can chat with each other in real time on line, Dr. Murray believes that electronic correspondence -- which, while quick, allows participants a chance to think before they write -- is the key to collaboration on complex projects.  Dr. Murray compares use of the Net for ''deliberative discourse'' to Thomas Jefferson's correspondence through letter writing in that individuals can take the time to analyze a complex situation and carefully construct and communicate their own thoughts, reactions or additions. However, unlike the painfully slow process of written correspondence between two authors in the days before the locomotive, the Internet allows almost instantaneous and simultaneous access to up-to-the-minute updates of huge amounts of information by multiple correspondents in a medium that unlike the penned word, ''is particularly well suited for visualizing things.''</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, while huge amounts of information have previously been organized ''in a serial sense,'' alphabetically, or by number, information on the Net ''is defined only in connection with other information'' which is ''much more the way the human brain works -- pattern recognition.''</p>
        <p>But while the Net may be changing the mode of collaboration at research centers and elsewhere, even Internet aficionados agree that actual meetings are not obsolete.</p>
        <p>Charles M. Firestone, director of the Aspen Institute's communications and society program, said the Internet ''affects almost every level of what we do.''</p>
        <p>But, while he concedes that the World Wide Web allows for ''more people to participate'' in discussions, and ''eliminates physical and social barriers'' to collaboration, ''what you really want to do is have the people whom you want to resolve the problem at the table,'' he said. ''People still want to meet face to face.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
