<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Congress and White House, Debate Begins on How to Use Future Budget Surpluses</title>
    <meta content="03SURP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971104T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="970210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFDE1530F930A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Congress and White House, Debate Begins on How to Use Future Budget Surpluses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congress and White House face possibility that Government will begin running budget surpluses in next few years, and heated debate is already breaking out over what to do with money; rapidly improving fiscal situation has opened door to wide-ranging consideration of policy and political priorities as glow of prosperity is beginning to alter way official Washington is addressing nation's long-term problems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After decades in which huge Federal budget deficits cast a shadow over politics and the economy, Congress and the White House face the possibility that the Government will begin running surpluses in the next few years, and  a heated debate is already breaking out over what to do with the money.</p>
        <p>Many conservative Republicans want to dedicate all or most of any surpluses to paying down the mountain of debt accumulated over decades of wars, recessions and fiscal profligacy. Other Republicans are pushing for tax cuts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After decades in which huge Federal budget deficits cast a shadow over politics and the economy, Congress and the White House face the possibility that the Government will begin running surpluses in the next few years, and  a heated debate is already breaking out over what to do with the money.</p>
        <p>Many conservative Republicans want to dedicate all or most of any surpluses to paying down the mountain of debt accumulated over decades of wars, recessions and fiscal profligacy. Other Republicans are pushing for tax cuts.</p>
        <p>Members of both parties are eagerly promoting more spending on roads, bridges and other politically appealing construction projects. Many Democrats lean toward additional spending on education and health programs.</p>
        <p>Both White House officials and members of Congress are pondering how surpluses could help address the looming shortfall in financing for Social Security retirement benefits and the Medicare system of health insurance for the elderly.</p>
        <p>That the debate is taking place at all strikes some officials as premature, given that the budget deficit, while falling rapidly, has not been eliminated and may never be if the economy falters. Even if the economy remains robust, just talking seriously about surpluses could erode the political will needed to bring the budget into balance, they said.</p>
        <p>''We need to stop hyperventilating and complete the job of balancing the budget,'' said Representative John R. Kasich, the Ohio Republican who is chairman of the House Budget Committee.</p>
        <p>The rapidly improving fiscal situation has nonetheless opened the door to a wide-ranging consideration of policy and political priorities as the glow of prosperity is beginning to alter the way official Washington is addressing the nation's long-term problems.</p>
        <p>The deficit for the Government fiscal year that ended Sept. 30 was $22.6 billion, its lowest level since the early 1970's. If the economy remains strong, many analysts say, the budget could show a surplus within the next several years and continue to do so for years to come.</p>
        <p>''For 15 years or more, the most important question you could ask about a public policy idea was what its effect was going to be on the budget deficit,'' said Franklin D. Raines, the White House budget director. ''Now you have to ask what an idea's contribution to the country is going to be and how does that compare to other options.''</p>
        <p>In its broadest terms, the debate is dominated by two camps. One considers reducing the national debt to be the best use of any surplus, likening the nation's fiscal condition to that of a consumer who has learned not to use a credit card so much but still must muster the discipline to pay off the card's balance. The national debt is $5.3 trillion, and interest payments on it account for 15 percent of all Federal spending.</p>
        <p>The other camp believes that there are other more pressing uses for the money, like tax cuts, transportation projects, higher Pentagon spending, school system improvements and access to medical care.</p>
        <p>''Maintaining a surplus for use in reducing the national debt is good policy but bad politics,'' said Robert D. Reischauer, a fellow at the Brookings Institution in Washington and former director of the Congressional Budget Office.</p>
        <p>''It would help increase the productivity of the work force and national living standards, help keep interest rates down and significantly reduce the fraction of the total budget that goes to debt service,'' he said. ''But those types of benefits are very distant and diffuse, and politicians want concrete rewards and immediate ones. So it's natural for this debate to begin, and it's likely to intensify.''</p>
        <p>When Speaker Newt Gingrich presented his views on how to use the surplus to the House Budget Committee several weeks ago, he provided a perhaps unintentional look at how expansive a political appetite there is for new and expensive initiatives.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich started by saying that Congress should do whatever it takes, including cutting Federal spending further, to eliminate the annual deficit and push the budget into surplus. Then, he said, the country should push to run an annual surplus ''large enough that a reasonable recession doesn't stop it'' for use in paying off the national debt.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gingrich went on to lay claim to a slice of any surpluses for other uses, starting with a tax cut every year. Then he called for increased spending on science, the military and transportation. And last, he noted Congress's responsibility to shore up the Social Security and Medicare programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kasich responded, somewhat wryly, by telling Mr. Gingrich that his proposals were ''a tall order, you will have to admit, for a surplus that is yet to materialize'' and that any surpluses that do materialize might never be big enough to pay for Mr. Gingrich's entire wish list.</p>
        <p>''I think you are pushing the envelope with what you propose, but nevertheless, I think it is the kind of debate we need to have,'' Mr. Kasich told Mr. Gingrich.</p>
        <p>There is no shortage of proposals to debate. Representative John A. Boehner of Ohio and Senator Spencer Abraham of Michigan, both Republicans, have introduced a bill that would set aside any revenue collected by the Government beyond that projected in the balanced budget deal negotiated by Congress and President Clinton earlier this year. The money would be reserved primarily for tax cuts or to pay for the costs of a fundamental overhaul of the tax code, another Republican priority. But the legislation would bar the use of any of the money for new spending programs.</p>
        <p>Representative Mark W. Neumann of Wisconsin, a Republican, has introduced a bill that would cap increases in Federal spending at one percentage point below the rate of increase in tax revenues and mandate that two-thirds of the resulting surplus be applied to paying off the national debt and the other third to tax cuts.</p>
        <p>''I feel pretty strongly that we have a moral and ethical responsibility to pay off the debts we've run up in the last 15 years,'' Mr. Neumann said.</p>
        <p>But Representative Bud Shuster, a Republican from Pennsylvania who is chairman of the House Committee on Transportation and Infrastructure, is leading a push for more spending on highways and other transportation projects.</p>
        <p>Democrats in Congress, wary of being tagged as tax-and-spend liberals, have shied away from detailed proposals for increased spending. But their leaders, including Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, have made clear that they see health, education and transportation as priorities.</p>
        <p>The White House has taken a hard line against using any unexpectedly high tax revenues to finance spending programs before the budget is balanced. But Administration officials have begun meeting to discuss how to use any consistent surpluses. Officials said the options included things like tax incentives to reducing the emissions that cause global warming, more spending on education, training and health care, and getting an early start on fixing Social Security.</p>
        <p>''Our general approach,'' said Gene Sperling, the director of the White House's National Economic Council, ''is to take a deep breath, don't spend money you don't have and, if it does turn out that you have sustainable surpluses, to think long and hard about what would be best for the economy and average families.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 4, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a debate over what should be done with a possible budget surplus misattributed a quotation in response to Speaker Newt Gingrich's proposals at a House Budget Committee hearing. The speaker -- who called Mr. Gingrich's proposals ''a tall order, you will have to admit, for a surplus that has yet to materialize'' -- was Representative John M. Spratt Jr. of South Carolina, the ranking Democrat on the committee, not Representative John R. Kasich, the Ohio Republican who is the committee's chairman.</p>
        <p>''I think you are pushing the envelope with what you propose,'' Mr. Spratt said, ''but, nevertheless, I think it is the kind of debate we need to have.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 4, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a debate over what should be done with a possible budget surplus misattributed a quotation in response to Speaker Newt Gingrich's proposals at a House Budget Committee hearing. The speaker -- who called Mr. Gingrich's proposals ''a tall order, you will have to admit, for a surplus that has yet to materialize'' -- was Representative John M. Spratt Jr. of South Carolina, the ranking Democrat on the committee, not Representative John R. Kasich, the Ohio Republican who is the committee's chairman.</p>
        <p>''I think you are pushing the envelope with what you propose,'' Mr. Spratt said, ''but, nevertheless, I think it is the kind of debate we need to have.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
