<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="07FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E0D81E3DF934A35753C1A961958260" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Israel Defends Attack On an Islamic Leader</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu defended the botched Israeli assassination attempt against a Hamas leader as a setback in a just fight against terrorism. Several hours earlier, the founder and revered icon of the Islamic movement returned to an ecstatic welcome from his supporters in the Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Israel Defends Attack On an Islamic Leader</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu defended the botched Israeli assassination attempt against a Hamas leader as a setback in a just fight against terrorism. Several hours earlier, the founder and revered icon of the Islamic movement returned to an ecstatic welcome from his supporters in the Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>War Crimes Suspects Give Up  After several months of intense negotiations between Washington and Croatia, 10 Bosnian Croats charged with crimes against Muslim civilians during the war in Bosnia turned themselves in to the international tribunal in The Hague. The surrender of the group, which included one of the most-wanted war crimes suspects in Bosnia, was a major step in Croatia's effort to improve its standing with the United States.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Yugoslavia Vote Deadlocked</p>
        <p>The races for President in the two republics that make up Yugoslavia appeared to be headed for a deadlock that would force a new election in Serbia and a runoff in Montenegro, according to official results. In Serbia, elections will start over from scratch because the turnout was below 50 percent. In Montenegro, the top two candidates will compete in a runoff election.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S., France Meet Over Iran Oil  Secretary of Defense William S. Cohen, who had several hours of talks with the French Defense Minister, said any action the United States takes against a French oil company's decision to invest in Iran would not disrupt relations between the United State and France. The United States is concerned that the oil transaction would help Iran pay for arms.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>In France, Right-Wing Muscle  The southern French town of Vitrolles, one of the few municipalities governed by the far-right National Front, has shut down a cafe that had become a center for young critics of its policies. The Government in Paris denounced the move. The closing came days after about 4,000 people attended a concert to raise money for the association that runs the cafe.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>$8.5 Billion in Nazi Gold  A study for the World Jewish Congress concluded that Nazi Germany looted $8.5 billion in gold from 1933 to 1945 and for the first time, it estimated an amount -- nearly a third -- that came from private individuals and businesses rather than banks. It also estimates that more than $2 billion of the privately owned gold ended up in Swiss banks.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Bush Fires Rage in Australia  The worst bush fires in memory burned out of control in northwestern Australia, the agency that fights the fires said. Some of the fires have burned for weeks in an area the size of Great Britain, and have destroyed hundreds of thousands of acres of pasture and blanketed the area in smoke.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-23</p>
        <p>White House Officials Find More Fund-Raising Tapes  As White House officials tried for a second day to explain their failure to turn over to investigators long-sought videotapes of President Clinton at 44 coffees with wealthy supporters, they acknowledged that even more tapes of political events and Presidential fund-raisers had surfaced and that they were likely to find still more.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Line Vetoes 38 Items  President Clinton used his new line-item veto power to pinpoint and strike out more than three dozen military spending items cherished by Senators and Representatives who said projects in their districts were essential to the national defense.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Ex-Radicals Face Spy Charges  Three onetime student radicals at the University of Wisconsin were charged with spying -- with mixed results -- for Communist intelligence services since the 1970's.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Nobel Awarded for Prion Work  The Nobel Prize in physiology or medicine was awarded to Dr. Stanley B. Prusiner, a 55-year-old maverick scientist in San Francisco whose discoveries about infectious particles called prions have been criticized by other researchers as unproved. The Nobel committee compounded its departure from the tradition of rubber stamping well-accepted scientific work by awarding the prize to one researcher only, emphasizing their confidence in Dr. Prusiner's discovery of a ''new genre of disease-causing agents.'' These agents, neither bacteria nor fungi nor viruses, have been linked to mad cow disease and other lethal brain-wasting conditions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Court Declines Campaign Cases  The Supreme Court refused to hear two campaign finance cases that might have moved the Justices to the center of the public debate over money and politics.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Two fierce competitors for the consumer banking dollar -- banks and credit unions -- battled before the Supreme Court on its opening day in arguments over the validity of a Federal regulation that has permitted credit unions to expand far beyond their traditional base among employees of a single company or members of a single occupation.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>Foundation Names President  The Rockefeller Foundation has chosen Gordon Conway, a British agricultural ecologist and the vice chancellor of the University of Sussex, to be the 12th president of one of the nation's oldest and largest foundations. He will be the first person who is not a United States citizen to head the foundation, which has $2.8 billion in assets.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Clinton Opposes Energy Tax  President Clinton said the danger of global warming is real but that Americans will not tolerate higher energy taxes to fight it and that such levies would probably doom an anti-pollution treaty.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Harlem School Closes Because of Toxic Fumes  A Harlem elementary school that opened last month on the site of an old dry-cleaning factory was shut down suddenly and indefinitely after test results revealed the presence of toxic fumes at levels exceeding state guidelines.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Girl Attacked at High School  Four teen-age boys and two teen-age girls were charged with sodomy after forcing a 13-year-old girl to perform oral sex in a fifth-floor boy's bathroom at Martin Luther King High School on the Upper West Side, the police said. The incident was discovered after a school safety officer saw the students leaving the bathroom and brought them to the principal's office.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Cashing In Draws Yawns  Four of the nation's largest financial institutions started a multimillion-dollar test of chip cards, which are a plastic-and-silicon substitutes for coins and small bills, on the Upper West Side of Manhattan. But the experiment with a truly cashless society aroused only faint enthusiasm among merchants and shoppers in a neighborhood chosen because of the buying patterns of its wealthy, au courant residents.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
        <p>F10</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Less Food, Longer Life  Scientists have long known that rodents on a lower-calorie diet live longer and healthier than those that eat all they want, and new studies involving monkeys -- to help determine whether people might similarly benefit -- have shown similar results.</p>
        <p>F3</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-23</p>
        <p>U.S. Sells Major Oilfield  The Federal Government moved to get out of the oil business by accepting a bid of $3.65 billion in cash from the Occidental Petroleum Corporation for the Government's share of a huge oilfield in California that was acquired in the early 1900's to insure that the Navy had plenty of oil in reserve as it converted from coal.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Indians End Yankee Season  The Cleveland Indians defeated the Yankees, 4-3, at Jacobs Field to win the division series and advance to the American League Championship Series against Baltimore.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Justice Department meltdown; Trent Lott's strangulation strategy; assassination ill befits Israel; politicizing the death penalty.</p>
        <p>Columns: Russell Baker, A. M. Rosenthal.</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B12</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
