<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A/Dr. Austin L. Dooley ; Telling the Real El Nino From the Hype</title>
    <meta content="NINO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="983475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dooley, Austin L (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DB123EF93BA15751C1A961958260" item-length="1291" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A/Dr. Austin L. Dooley ; Telling the Real El Nino From the Hype</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA GREENE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greene, Donna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts of interview with Dr Austin L Dooley, meteorologist and oceanographer at State University of NY at Purchase, who comments on El Nino; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST as weather is one of those topics everyone talks about El Nino has become the topic of weather reporters. It seems the periodic phenomenon -- the warming of sea surface temperatures along the Equator in the Pacific Ocean -- has become the explanation for a wide variety of weather happenings.</p>
        <p>At his continuing education class at Purchase College, Dr. Austin L. Dooley, a meteorologist and oceanographer, tries to help students sort out El Nino the reality from El Nino the latest hyped event. Global warming -- what it means, what its effect could be -- is also looked at in this course.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST as weather is one of those topics everyone talks about El Nino has become the topic of weather reporters. It seems the periodic phenomenon -- the warming of sea surface temperatures along the Equator in the Pacific Ocean -- has become the explanation for a wide variety of weather happenings.</p>
        <p>At his continuing education class at Purchase College, Dr. Austin L. Dooley, a meteorologist and oceanographer, tries to help students sort out El Nino the reality from El Nino the latest hyped event. Global warming -- what it means, what its effect could be -- is also looked at in this course.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dooley, a resident of City Island in the Bronx, is president of Dooley Sea Weather Analysis Inc., which provides services to companies that insure ships and law firms involved in cases affected by meteorology, oceanography and marine operations. He has a Web page, which has links to a variety of weather-related sites: www.netcom.com/ dseawx.</p>
        <p>Here are excerpts from a recent conversation with Dr. Dooley:</p>
        <p>Q. It seems as if everything is attributed to El Nino. Is El Nino causing all this, or is it the latest hype?</p>
        <p>A. Certainly, with this particular El Nino, which was first detected back in May, attention started early and so strongly. Also, this is one of the first El Ninos since national weather agencies have gotten some of their global monitoring programs up and running, so they've been able to follow it from the very beginning. But is it the driving force behind a lot of our weather as we look today? Well, there are some scientists that say there is a direct correlation between the number of hurricanes we would have here in the Atlantic and El Nino. In a strong El Nino year, the number of hurricanes in the Atlantic would be minimized, and certainly, this past hurricane season would fit that model. There was, however, a recent storm in Los Angeles, and there were questions on the news here whether we were going to get the storm, whether El Nino was going to affect New York City. I thought some of that was a little bit too much waving of red flags. But El Nino is certainly responsible for a lot of changes in weather conditions.</p>
        <p>So I think because this one started earlier than usual -- they don't usually start until the fall or early winter -- and it's stronger than others, that's what has gotten everybody's attention.</p>
        <p>Q. Describe exactly what El Nino is.</p>
        <p>A. It's what we call an inter-annual event. It's a semi-periodic warming of sea surface temperature conditions along the Equator in the Pacific Ocean. Some scientists say that corresponding with the typical strong El Nino there is also a cooling of ocean conditions to the north and south of El Nino. You might find a warmer tropical Pacific -- in other words, at the Equator -- and corresponding to that would be cooler waters in certain parts of the North and South Pacific. But the bulk of El Nino is focused on the higher temperatures in the tropical Pacific, which extends all the way from the coast of South America and Ecuador, or farther.</p>
        <p>Q. Warmer waters impact every place they touch, correct?</p>
        <p>A. Basically, this is how I explain it to my students: if you look at river rapids, and at the top of the river you see where the waves are in the rapids, you understand that those waves in the rapids come from the rocks. If you want to change the condition of those waves at the top of the river, all you have to do is move the rocks. And they do this, I think, in some Olympic events, such as kayaking. When they move the rocks around, they change the course of the river, and that's basically what El Nino does. By injecting at a particular time hotter water in the Tropics, it distorts the general circulation of the atmosphere, and as that happens, it moves what we call the upper air patterns -- not just over the tropical Pacific but over the higher latitudes in the 30-  to 40-  to 50-degree range of latitudes in the North Pacific. This upsets the Jet Stream, and the Jet Stream causes the storm centers to take a different path than they would if there were not an El Nino.</p>
        <p>Q. How often does El Nino come?</p>
        <p>A. Generally, every two years or so, sometimes up to seven years.</p>
        <p>Q. What's your prediction for the weather of the New York City area for this winter?</p>
        <p>A. I'm not really into the long-term climatic forecasting business. People spend a lot of time and money poring over charts and looking at that stuff. But if El Nino has the normal effect, the West Coast and the Southeast U.S. would get more precipitation than normal. The Northeast would generally have warmer, milder winters.</p>
        <p>Q. Other factors can influence the weather, can't they?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely. All kinds of events take place in the meteorological world. Weather forecasting is part art and part science, although it is becoming more and more of a science. The skills of the National Weather Service and the other forecasting agencies have improved dramatically in the last 10 or 15 years due to improved theory, bigger and better computers and also better instrumentation and observational techniques. The Government has spent a lot of taxpayers' money on weather collection and analysis, and it's well worth it.</p>
        <p>The nation has invested in this new airplane to monitor hurricanes. And then there is Doppler Radar that enhances short-term forecasting. That will benefit people on a very local level. Hopefully, it will prevent boating accidents by giving people more advanced notice on such things as thunderstorms and tornadoes.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you involved at all with the issues of global warming?</p>
        <p>A. At Purchase, we're trying to develop a sequence of courses that can help people better understand the onslaught of information that is coming to them. The purpose of the course is to give people the background and the principles of science so that they can sit down and read a newspaper, see the information or listen to the news about the conference on global warming, for example, and make independent analysis.</p>
        <p>Q. There are skeptics about global warming.</p>
        <p>A. One of the problems is that I can tell you what today's climate is -- but only in five years after I have done the analysis -- when the results are in. A lot of things happen to upset conditions on a year-to-year basis. Take volcanoes: the ash in the stratosphere results in a net cooling and all kinds of conditions result. You talk about greenhouse gases, which is the main problem in terms of global warming right now -- sure there is no doubt if you inject and double the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere we are going to have a hotter world.</p>
        <p>Is it going to be hotter every place? All the time? Well, it's not that the first of September will always be hotter than the previous first of September. But it's a cumulative effect. That's the danger.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
