<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ice Shifts May Be Tied to Warming</title>
    <meta content="18ICE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971119T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DB1138F93BA25752C1A961958260" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ice Shifts May Be Tied to Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Weather satellites operating over 18-year period reveal increase in ice covering Antarctic waters and decrease in extent of Arctic sea ice; scientists say this asymmetric trend is consistent with one theory of what would happen if gradual increase of carbon dioxide in atmosphere were causing global warming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WEATHER satellites operating over an 18-year period have revealed an increase in the ice covering Antarctic waters and a decrease in the extent of Arctic sea ice. This asymmetric trend, a team of scientists says, is consistent with one theory of what would happen if a gradual increase of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere were causing global warming.</p>
        <p>Results of the satellite investigation by Dr. Donald J. Cavalieri and his colleagues at the Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., were published recently in the journal Nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WEATHER satellites operating over an 18-year period have revealed an increase in the ice covering Antarctic waters and a decrease in the extent of Arctic sea ice. This asymmetric trend, a team of scientists says, is consistent with one theory of what would happen if a gradual increase of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere were causing global warming.</p>
        <p>Results of the satellite investigation by Dr. Donald J. Cavalieri and his colleagues at the Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Md., were published recently in the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>The oceanic ice-cover data were produced by four satellites whose useful lives overlapped to yield an 18-year record. During the period from late 1978 through 1996, the team found, Arctic sea ice shrank at a rate of 2.9 percent per decade, while Antarctic sea ice increased by 1.3 percent per decade.</p>
        <p>Scientists participating in a project called Sheba, an acronym for Surface Heat Budget of the Arctic Ocean, have also observed a shrinkage of the ice covering the Arctic Ocean. Sheba is administered by the University of Washington.</p>
        <p>'It's a very clear signal,'' Dr. Cavalieri said in an interview.</p>
        <p>But the significance of the discovery is less certain.</p>
        <p>Although one highly regarded mathematical model predicts just such an outcome, other mathematical models of carbon-dioxide-induced global warming predict a decrease in Antarctica's sea ice rather than an increase.</p>
        <p>Complicating the interpretation of the observed trend, Dr. Cavalieri said, is natural variability in ice cover and sea surface temperatures in the Arctic and Antarctica. These variations seem to be partly periodic; in the Arctic, the period of variation is about five years, while in Antarctica it is three or four years, he said.</p>
        <p>From space, clouds and ice look much the same in visible light, so the investigators relied instead on microwave scanners aboard the Nimbus 7 weather satellite and three Defense Department meteorological satellites. Computer programs were used to weed out false images of ice; ''we know, for example, that we should not be seeing ice off the coast of Spain,'' Dr. Cavalieri said.</p>
        <p>Because of the natural variability of oceanic ice and surface temperatures, Dr. Cavalieri cautioned ''not to read too much into these results.''</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, he said, evidence is mounting that increasing levels of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere are causing a gradual increase in global temperatures.</p>
        <p>''We certainly should be concerned,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is known to be a ''greenhouse gas,'' which freely transmits most radiation from the sun to the ground. When this energy reaches the ground, some of it is converted into infrared radiation, which is transmitted upward but is blocked by carbon dioxide and certain other gases in the atmosphere. These gases trap heat. The result is a warming of the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is produced by volcanoes and other natural sources, but it is also a product of industrial and automotive combustion, and many nations are seeking to curb the production of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 19, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday about a study that found an increase in sea ice in Antarctic waters and a decrease in Arctic waters misidentified the journal that published the study. It was Science, not Nature.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 19, 1997, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times yesterday about a study that found an increase in sea ice in Antarctic waters and a decrease in Arctic waters misidentified the journal that published the study. It was Science, not Nature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
