<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tough Guy at Treasury; Rubin's Point Man on Policy Is in Tune On Economics, Off-Key on Politics</title>
    <meta content="Y05LAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="970708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Lawrence H. Summers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Treasury Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Summers, Lawrence H (Deputy Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7DF1130F936A35752C1A961958260" item-length="2230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tough Guy at Treasury; Rubin's Point Man on Policy Is in Tune On Economics, Off-Key on Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER and LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis; Sanger, David E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Lawrence H Summers, Deputy Treasury Secretary; says Summers has taken an aggressive role behind scenes in trying to shape US economic policy; holds some of issues that he has worked on recently include global warming, reform of Internal Reform Service and Asian economic turmoil; drawings; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At times in the last few weeks, it has seemed as if the hand and mind of Lawrence H. Summers could be found lurking beneath the surface of just about every tangled problem facing the White House.</p>
        <p>When President Clinton finally declared America's position on global warming last month, Mr. Summers, the Deputy Treasury Secretary, led the economic camp that won the day over the State Department and the Environmental Protection Agency, scaling back America's commitments on its emission of pollutants. He did it with detailed arguments about the potential -- and unknowable -- costs to American industry if Mr. Clinton committed to aggressive targets, with no escape clauses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At times in the last few weeks, it has seemed as if the hand and mind of Lawrence H. Summers could be found lurking beneath the surface of just about every tangled problem facing the White House.</p>
        <p>When President Clinton finally declared America's position on global warming last month, Mr. Summers, the Deputy Treasury Secretary, led the economic camp that won the day over the State Department and the Environmental Protection Agency, scaling back America's commitments on its emission of pollutants. He did it with detailed arguments about the potential -- and unknowable -- costs to American industry if Mr. Clinton committed to aggressive targets, with no escape clauses.</p>
        <p>But a day later, it was Mr. Summers's turn to lose a major battle. The onetime economics professor, now one of the more influential voices in the Clinton Administration, and his boss, Treasury Secretary Robert E. Rubin, badly misjudged the political landscape. For months, Mr. Summers had headed the Treasury Department's effort to rescue the Internal Revenue Service from itself. He recruited a proven manager, instead of the traditional tax lawyer, as commissioner, and forced the scrapping of a huge computer project that had gone wildly awry.</p>
        <p>He was so caught up in the internal fixes, in fact, that he underestimated the effectiveness of a carefully orchestrated Republican onslaught to loosen the Treasury's hold over the I.R.S. Facing overwhelming pressure from both parties, Mr. Rubin and Mr. Summers were forced to accept an oversight board to supervise the agency.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. battle was remarkable because in Washington these days, Mr. Summers rarely loses -- or even gives much ground. The youngest academic ever to receive tenure at Harvard, at age 28, he has turned into one of Washington's shrewdest political infighters. Rarely do economists make the transition from university life to Government as successfully as the 42-year-old Mr. Summers has. Indeed, no one else in his generation has been in Washington for as long, or in a series of such high-profile posts.</p>
        <p>Along the way, he has bruised more than a few egos, from Republican members of Congress who complain they have been lectured on economic principles as if they were classroom dullards, to Administration colleagues who have felt some sharp bureaucratic elbows. In recent months, as Mr. Summers's authority and world view have expanded, he has clearly tried to tone down.</p>
        <p>''I've learned that being precisely analytically accurate is neither necessary nor sufficient for being constructive in Washington's debates,'' he said recently over lunch a block from the White House. ''After being a professor of political economy, I guess now I'd give more weight to the political than to the economic than when I first got here.''</p>
        <p>It has been an uneven transition. He was the principal architect of the successful 1995 bailout of Mexico -- but he was also a lightning rod for Congress's anger about the use of $12 billion in American funds, all of which have been repaid. ''Congress did not want to approve so huge a loan and then take the blame if Mexico failed to repay, and Larry became an excuse for saying no,'' said a Democratic Congressional aide involved in the negotiations. ''He was insensitive to the political issue at stake. He told the members they had to approve the bailout; they had no choice. Well, members of Congress always have a choice.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the President made the loan on his own authority.</p>
        <p>In the last few weeks, he has devoted most of his time to the Administration's efforts to contain the economic crisis in Southeast Asia. Mindful of the sensitivities in Congress, though, he made sure this time that the International Monetary Fund took the lead and that America's exposure was limited to $3 billion in a ''second line of defense'' for Indonesia. Nonetheless, some colleagues back in academia warn that austerity measures that worked in Mexico may not fit the problems of the Southeast Asian economies.</p>
        <p>Often he has been called in to play the heavy. When the I.M.F. was blanching in August at forcing Thailand to disclose fully its key financial transactions, Mr. Summers forcefully reminded officials at the fund that Washington could still effectively pull the plug on the aid package for Bangkok. The I.M.F. backed down.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Summers is never far from the levers of power. When Mr. Rubin and Alan Greenspan, chairman of the Federal Reserve, have their weekly breakfast, he is the only other person present -- and he often does much of the talking.</p>
        <p>The issue now is where Mr. Summers is headed. There is no question he is eager to break out of Mr. Rubin's long shadow: he angled, unsuccessfully, for the presidency of the World Bank. (The job went to the financier James Wolfensohn.)</p>
        <p>He also considered becoming chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers earlier this year (plenty of academic prestige, he decided, but not enough influence), and he was judged too confrontational to become the consensus-seeking head of the National Economic Council.</p>
        <p>Many consider him a contender to become the next Treasury Secretary, should Mr. Rubin decide to return to New York before the end of the current term. Mr. Rubin himself is among Mr. Summers's boosters.</p>
        <p>''He has an incredibly sensitive political mind, as well as being a brilliant economist,'' said Mr. Rubin, who first met his deputy when they worked on the failed 1988 Presidential campaign of Michael S. Dukakis. ''He is extraordinarily equipped to function at the intersection of economics and political reality.''</p>
        <p>Should Mr. Rubin decide to call it quits, however, there are other contenders to become the next Treasury Secretary, including Franklin D. Raines, the director of the Office of Management and Budget. And there are still questions -- usually uttered off the record -- about whether Mr. Summers's sometimes impolitic style could prevent him from moving to the other side of the elegant, antique-filled suite he shares with Mr. Rubin. He is frequently the target of a lot of political vitriol, in part because he will say things in public that Mr. Rubin will not.</p>
        <p>''Bob is legendary for speaking in an extraordinarily restrained way,'' Mr. Summers said, when asked to compare his style with Mr. Rubin's. ''But if you thought about my speech pattern, you'd go through a lot of other adjectives before you got to restrained and unprovocative.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers, in short, is not one of those people about whom Washingtonians or economists have neutral opinions.</p>
        <p>State Department officials fume that Mr. Summers seized the Mexican crisis, and now policy toward Southeast Asia, without adequately consulting them. In turn, Mr. Summers has offered blistering assessments of the State Department and Central Intelligence Agency's economic analysis in an age when currency devaluation can often be destabilizing.</p>
        <p>He is also the subject of criticism  in the economics profession. One longtime antagonist of Mr. Summers, Fred Bergsten, the president of the Institute for International Economics, calls him ''turf conscious'' and ''not a strategic thinker.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Summers's style put him in conflict with another prominent Ivy League economist, Alan Blinder of Princeton, who came to Washington in 1993 as a member of the Council of Economic Advisers and then was named vice chairman of the Federal Reserve. Mr. Blinder holds views on economic matters similar to Mr. Summers's. Nevertheless, Mr. Blinder turned down an invitation from President Clinton to be chairman of the council in the second term. He did so in part because he would have found himself in almost daily policy discussions -- and confrontations -- with Mr. Summers.</p>
        <p>The council job finally went to another university economics professor, Janet Yellen, who once taught economics to Mr. Summers. She works closely with him now but stays largely out of the limelight.</p>
        <p>''He is a brilliant economist,'' says Laura D'Andrea Tyson, a former chairwoman of the council. ''He has strongly held views. He is ambitious. He debates down to the last minute. He gets exasperated with people who he feels don't understand. But finally he is a team player.''</p>
        <p>Those arguments usually take place as the stout Mr. Summers downs Diet Cokes, apparently his main source of sustenance as he races between the White House and the Treasury. His staff is constantly feeding his voracious appetite, too, for statistics, and he is intolerant of what he calls ''standard, government-issue, we-should-have-a-partnership talking points'' when meeting finance ministers and other officials from around the world.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Summers is often trotted out by the Administration to put its spin on the day's confluence of market tumult and political maneuvering. Usually those conversations begin with Mr. Summers's asking the first question, to gauge just how much he will have to reveal.</p>
        <p>''So,'' he says casually, ''what are you hearing?''</p>
        <p>Often, what reporters are hearing are tales about Mr. Summers. He outraged Republicans earlier this year when he declared that their effort to wipe out the inheritance tax amounted to ''utter selfishness.'' Mr. Rubin, who clearly agreed with him but would not put it so bluntly at a time the Administration was trying to cobble together a budget deal, stuck his head in Mr. Summers's office the next morning, unable to resist inserting the needle.</p>
        <p>''I told him that I didn't really mind what he said,'' recalled Mr. Rubin, a man whose own sizable estate is nothing to sneeze at. ''But I said my son was really angry.''</p>
        <p>On a long flight to Hong Kong last month, Mr. Summers's aides delighted in finding evidence of the policy wonk at work: a full page, in Mr. Summers's hand, of indecipherable equations, doodled during a meeting on computer encryption, an issue that has divided the Treasury, the intelligence agencies and the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>Instantly, the page was circulating from seat to seat. ''I was trying to work out some of the principles of encryption,'' he said, smiling sheepishly. It's a wiser way to pass the time, he suggested, ''than other things I could be caught doing at meetings, like rolling my eyes.''</p>
        <p>Other participants in those meetings say there is no question Mr. Summers is a powerful voice, sometimes even disagreeing with Mr. Rubin. He pressed, over Mr. Rubin's initial objection, for inflation-indexed Treasury bonds, something many economists have been urging for years. He is a free trader, skeptical of the argument that competition from low-wage countries pulls down American wages. He argued for milder application of trade sanctions against Japan in the automobile dispute in 1995. He holds that America's labor force is fully employed today, and that long-stagnant wages are beginning to rise, although the statistical evidence is in dispute.</p>
        <p>While his political antenna can sometimes miss signals, Lawrence Henry Summers comes to economics naturally. He is the child of economists and the nephew of two Nobel laureates in economic science -- Paul Samuelson on his father's side, Kenneth Arrow on his mother's. He earned his Ph.D at Harvard in 1982, and made his name with contrarian papers demonstrating how some previously held economic thesis was off base.</p>
        <p>But academia is receding. Mr. Summers's life is increasingly rooted here -- his wife, Victoria, is a tax expert working at the I.M.F., and his weekends are spent between tennis games (''I'm better than you'd think, looking at me,'' he says) and playing with his children -- 7-year-old twin daughters and a 4-year-old son.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Summers's future, here is a leading indicator: He just sold his house in the Boston suburbs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
