<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine Talk</title>
    <meta content="23WINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Wine Talk" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="945583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Wine Talk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trademarks and Trade Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E7D9133BF930A15754C0A961958260" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Prial column on American practice of giving cheap blended wines names like chablis, burgundy and champagne that are not sanctioned by France and other European wine-producing countries; notes that trade friction over generic use geographic designations comes at time when more and more wine producers are turning to varietal names; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT is chablis? It depends. According to one definition, it is a French white wine named after the town southwest of Paris where it is made. But in the United States, it can be anything a winemaker wants it to be, and an obscure provision in the tax bill the Senate is considering makes sure things stay that way.</p>
        <p>In the American wine trade, chablis, burgundy and champagne are generic names used mostly for inexpensive blended wines. In ''The New Connoisseur's Handbook of California Wines'' (Knopf, 1995), Norman Roby and Charles Olken describe California chablis as a wine that is ''inexpensive, sweet and blended primarily to sell in the least demanding white wine markets.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT is chablis? It depends. According to one definition, it is a French white wine named after the town southwest of Paris where it is made. But in the United States, it can be anything a winemaker wants it to be, and an obscure provision in the tax bill the Senate is considering makes sure things stay that way.</p>
        <p>In the American wine trade, chablis, burgundy and champagne are generic names used mostly for inexpensive blended wines. In ''The New Connoisseur's Handbook of California Wines'' (Knopf, 1995), Norman Roby and Charles Olken describe California chablis as a wine that is ''inexpensive, sweet and blended primarily to sell in the least demanding white wine markets.''</p>
        <p>In France, genuine Chablis must be made from chardonnay grapes, and red Burgundy from the pinot noir. American jug-wine chablis can be made from any grape; so can jug-wine burgundy. ''California burgundies,'' Roby and Olken write, ''are usually soft, often slightly to medium sweet, and aimed at a broad market. Needless to say, they have absolutely nothing in common with French Burgundies.''</p>
        <p>Efforts by France and other European wine-producing nations to end the use of these geographic names by California jug-wine producers have mostly failed. Even the Champagne industry, which has successfully barred the use of its name elsewhere in the world, has been turned down by the United States courts in its attempts to prevent American sparkling-wine producers from calling their product champagne.</p>
        <p>One bright spot, so far as the Europeans are concerned, is Beaujolais. Last month, the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms issued a ruling that will eventually ban the use of the name Gamay Beaujolais in describing any American wine. There is no grape called gamay beaujolais, but the name has been used to describe a small amount of wine almost invariably made in California from pinot noir or an obscure grape called valdiguie.</p>
        <p>Through 1998, the name can be used, but only if the real origin of the wine is indicated. After that, until April 8, 2007, the name Gamay Beaujolais can be used only in conjunction with the source of the wine and the name of the grape it is made from. In France, the Beaujolais producers' organization and the Government-sponsored National Institute of Wine Appellations hailed the ruling and shrugged off the 10-year wait. The two Governments, they said, had battled over the Gamay Beaujolais issue for 50 years.</p>
        <p>Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms regulations have long permitted American winemakers to use European names on wines like Gallo's Hearty Burgundy and Almaden Vineyards' Blush Chablis. The Senate tax bill would write those regulations into law.</p>
        <p>The idea is to strengthen the Americans' hand in coming trade negotiations with France and other wine-producing members of the European Union. The Europeans hope to use their combined strength to force the Americans to drop the foreign names.</p>
        <p>At stake are the names of literally millions of gallons of American wine. A spokesman for the American wineries seeking the new law said last week that changing the names of jug wines would be ''devastating'' to wine production in California and New York State.''</p>
        <p>Actually, the trend among smaller premium wineries has been away from these European names. They now use ''white table wine'' and ''red table wine'' to identify their less expensive blends.</p>
        <p>The wine name controversy is an old one. Originally, American winemakers adopted the European names because Europe's best wines had always been associated with the places where they were made, and the immigrants who once made up the bulk of the American wine market were familiar with those names.</p>
        <p>In this country, where winemakers are still determining the best places to grow their vines, grape types are the most important guarantee of wine quality. Thus, the use of varietal names -- the names of the grapes from which the wine is made -- was an early attempt to distinguish the best wines from the inexpensive blends with European names.</p>
        <p>The varietal name is not a guarantee of quality, but it points in that direction because regulations require that at least 75 percent of any varietal wine come from the grapes whose name it bears.</p>
        <p>So popular has the use of varietal names become that many imports have adopted the American practice. Chile, Argentina, Australia and South Africa -- all important wine producers -- rely almost exclusively on varietal names. In France and Italy, too, some exporters are switching to varietal names, to the dismay of the traditional wine regions, where geography still prevails.</p>
        <p>Champagne is an exception. Its name is synonymous with its quality; no one is really interested in what grapes go into it. Hardly any serious sparkling-wine producers in this country express a desire to use the Champagne name, but it is not difficult to envision a French Champagne maker staring disconsolately at a $4 bottle charged with carbon dioxide and labeled Champagne.</p>
        <p>The market for wines with names like Mountain Burgundy and Chablis Blanc is still enormous. Gallo makes some 70 million cases of wine a year, much of it low-priced blends. But that market is not growing, and even Gallo has begun to emphasize its expanding line of fine varietal wines over its traditional products.</p>
        <p>Even in the lower end of the American wine business, varietal names are growing in importance. Many bag-in-the box wines, the fastest growing segment of the wine business, are varietals.</p>
        <p>In a sense, the jug wines and cheap sparklers with foreign-sounding names are dinosaurs, relics of an earlier time in the wine business. In a few years the whole issue may become moot.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the Europeans know that it is important to defend any franchise. Let someone abuse it, and eventually you might lose it. Lawyers for Coca-Cola, Xerox and a host of other large companies are kept busy letting the world know that these corporations take their good names very seriously.</p>
        <p>TASTINGS  Villa di Trefiano Carmignano 1994, Tuscany. About $30.</p>
        <p>Carmignano was a famous wine in the 14th century and one of the first in the world to be regulated and protected by law, in 1716. It was eclipsed by Chianti for many years, but following World War II, Count Ugo Contini-Bonacossi restored its ancient glory at Capezzana, his estate west of Florence. The wine is made from sangiovese and canaiolo, the two principal Chianti grapes, with the addition of cabernet franc and cabernet sauvignon. Adding French grapes to Tuscan wines is fashionable now, but they have been part of Carmignano since the last century. In 1979, the Contini-Bonacossis began producing two single-vineyard Carmignanos, the Villa di Capezzana and the Villa di Trefiano. Starting with this, the 1994 vintage, the Trefiano is being made from a different sangiovese clone. This 1994 is a generous, intense wine, perhaps a bit less elegant than the Capezzana, even though it contains more cabernet: 15 percent compared with 10. The wine is delicious and ready to drink now, but keeping it for another five years could smooth it out nicely.</p>
        <p>Wine Talk</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
