<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Cuts Effort to Urge Conservation</title>
    <meta content="24POWE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5DA1E3BF937A15752C1A961958260" item-length="1296" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Cuts Effort to Urge Conservation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Nov. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State, once national leader in promoting energy conservation, has, with little public notice, cut its conservation effort to about one-fourth its former size, even though program has been highly praised by environmentalists; amount state has required utilities to spend on program has fallen to $73 million ths year from $280 million in 1993 and is set to drop over nexy few years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York State, once a national leader in promoting energy conservation, has, with little public notice, cut its conservation effort to about one-fourth its former size, even though the program has been highly praised by environmentalists.</p>
        <p>The conservation program, begun in the late 1980's, requires the seven regional power companies in the state to reimburse their customers for some of the cost of replacing light fixtures, electric motors and appliances with more energy-efficient models. Reducing the demand for electricity cuts down on air pollution by lowering the amount of fuel burned in power plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York State, once a national leader in promoting energy conservation, has, with little public notice, cut its conservation effort to about one-fourth its former size, even though the program has been highly praised by environmentalists.</p>
        <p>The conservation program, begun in the late 1980's, requires the seven regional power companies in the state to reimburse their customers for some of the cost of replacing light fixtures, electric motors and appliances with more energy-efficient models. Reducing the demand for electricity cuts down on air pollution by lowering the amount of fuel burned in power plants.</p>
        <p>The amount the state has required the utilities to spend on the program has fallen to $73 million this year, from $280 million in 1993, and is set to drop more over the next few years. The utilities' expenses are ultimately borne by ratepayers, but the savings from conserving energy typically cover those costs in the long term.</p>
        <p>The program's decline began toward the end of the Cuomo administration, which inaugurated the program, and has continued under Gov. George E. Pataki. It has coincided with the growth of similar programs in other states, so that New York, once a model that others followed, now ranks below the national average in energy efficiency spending, and far behind most other states in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>The cuts have angered and perplexed conservation groups, which often view the Republican Governor as an ally. Democratic lawmakers say they see the administration's treatment of the program as a potential weak spot for the Republican Governor in a re-election campaign in 1998.</p>
        <p>''This governor's record on energy efficiency has been a total failure,'' said Ashok Gupta, an economist with the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>The Governor's office declined to discuss the matter, referring questions to the State Public Service Commission, the agency that governs utilities and sets the level of conservation spending. The commission's members are appointed by the Governor.</p>
        <p>Rather than requiring energy efficiency spending, ''The commission believes that the market should be allowed to develop innovative programs and cost-effective energy conservation measures,'' said David Flanagan, the commission's spokesman.</p>
        <p>The commission is moving the state away from the traditional system giving utilities a monopoly on power distribution, and toward a competitive market in which customers can choose among competing electricity providers. When that happens, Mr. Flanagan said, some energy companies will try to attract customers by offering conservation services.</p>
        <p>But there is not yet any electric competition in New York, and under the current plan, most consumers will not be able to choose their supplier until the year 2002. It is not clear how many customers would voluntarily pay more for their power to gain access to a conservation program.</p>
        <p>Although the program is paid for by slightly higher bills for every electric user,  consumer groups have not opposed it. The utilities generally have not been hostile to the program, either, as long as the state set high enough rates to guarantee their profits.</p>
        <p>The only organized opposition to the efficiency program has come from a coalition of heavy industries, which has protested that high electric rates hinder economic development, and has urged the state to lower them by any means possible. Manufacturers use large amounts of power, and so stand to gain from even a small drop in the price of electricity. Also, they have generally not been able to take much advantage of the rebate program.</p>
        <p>This year, the industrial coalition's lobbying helped defeat a bill on energy policy that would have increased the level of conservation spending. The bill passed the Democratic-controlled Assembly, but was stopped in the Republican-led Senate.</p>
        <p>''This is an example of the schizophrenia on environmental matters in the Pataki administration,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Democrat and chairman of the Environmental Conservation Committee. ''They're very good on some things, but when there's a corporate interest involved, they fold.''</p>
        <p>For power consumers in New York, whether home or business, 0.7 percent of the average monthly electric bill now goes toward the conservation program. In nearby states, the current average is 5.5 percent in Connecticut, 4 percent in Massachussets and 3.4 percent in Vermont, according to a recent study by the New York State Energy Research and Development Authority.</p>
        <p>The utilities and environmental groups estimate that the new equipment installed under the program saves more than 5 million megawatt/hours per year, or 3 percent of the electricity consumed statewide, about equivalent to the output of two medium-sized power plants. That translates to almost $500 million a year in savings on electric bills, far more than the amount spent on the rebates.</p>
        <p>Reducing the demand for power is a cherished goal of environmentalists because power plants are a major source of air pollution and greenhouse gases. They produce two-thirds of the nation's sulfur dioxide emissions, one-third of the carbon dioxide and one-third of the nitrogen oxides.</p>
        <p>At the peak of New York State's program, a power user, usually a business, that wanted to replace its fixtures with energy-efficient ones could apply to the local utility for a rebate that would, in many cases, cover the entire cost of the new equipment. Often, the customer would hire an energy consultant to determine what changes were needed, install the equipment and prove to the utility that the work had been done. The customer had to pay the consultant's fee and labor charges for installation, but often earned it back within a few years through lower electric bills.</p>
        <p>''In a typical office building that's 20 to 30 years old, we could find cost-effective measures that would reduce energy usage 20 to 40 percent, and it's primarily because new, modern equipment is more efficient,'' said Dennis T. Wilson, president of Manhattan-based Enersave, the largest consultant on energy use in New York City.</p>
        <p>Today, the utilities are obliged to pay only a fraction of equipment costs, 20 percent in Consolidated Edison's case. With the smaller rebate, it takes customers longer to recover their expenses, so the program is less attractive to them. Also, the pool of money for rebates has grown so small that applicants are often turned away.</p>
        <p>''Our business has been cut almost in half, which gives you some idea of what's going on,'' Mr. Wilson said.</p>
        <p>Most users of the program have been office-based businesses, whose energy use consists mostly of lighting and climate control, which can often be made more efficient at relatively little cost. The program has been available, on a more limited basis, to homeowners, as well, but they have used it less often. Residents rarely shop for new appliances if the old ones, no matter how inefficient, are still working, and the out-of-pocket cost for new equipment and installation is often more daunting to an average person than to a business.</p>
        <p>For factories, the program has had less to offer than for office buildings. The rebate program applies only to common uses, like better lighting and electric motors, not the more complex, often highly specialized machinery that accounts for much of a factory's power use.</p>
        <p>In moving toward competition, the commission is making some changes in the conservation program that environmentalists welcome: the effort will be run by the state, not the utilities, and reimbursements will be based on the amount of energy saved, not the amount of money spent.</p>
        <p>But as part of the industry restructuring, the commission is continuing to cut the program. Con Edison's spending on conservation, already down to $48 million this year, from $125 million in 1993, will drop to $30 million a year during the five-year transition to competition, and similar cuts are in the works for the other regional power companies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
