<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Demystifying (but Glamorizing) Engineers</title>
    <meta content="TECHNO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Q&amp;A: Samuel C. Florman" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="920744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Westchester Q&amp;A: Samuel C. Florman"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greene, Donna</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Florman, Samuel C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Introspective Engineer, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Engineering and Engineers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DC1F3AF935A35757C0A961958260" item-length="1539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Demystifying (but Glamorizing) Engineers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONNA GREENE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greene, Donna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Samuel C Florman, civil engineer who is author of recently-published book, The Introspective Engineer, which addresses effects of technology on various aspects of life; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Samuel C. Florman's fantasy, there would be a television show titled ''L.A. Engineer,'' which would dramatize the exciting world of the engineer. Why, he wonders, are television producers focusing mainly on lawyers, doctors and police officers?</p>
        <p>It is one of the questions Mr. Florman, a 72-year-old civil engineer for more than four decades, raises in his latest book, ''The Introspective Engineer'' (St. Martin's Press), in which he addresses the effects of technology on various aspects of life, including bird watching and poetry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Samuel C. Florman's fantasy, there would be a television show titled ''L.A. Engineer,'' which would dramatize the exciting world of the engineer. Why, he wonders, are television producers focusing mainly on lawyers, doctors and police officers?</p>
        <p>It is one of the questions Mr. Florman, a 72-year-old civil engineer for more than four decades, raises in his latest book, ''The Introspective Engineer'' (St. Martin's Press), in which he addresses the effects of technology on various aspects of life, including bird watching and poetry.</p>
        <p>A resident of Manhattan, Mr. Florman has a weekend home in Kent in Putnam County. His engineering concern is in Scarsdale.</p>
        <p>Here are excerpts from a recent conversation with him:</p>
        <p>Q. Why is there no television show called ''L.A. Engineer'' or something similar?</p>
        <p>A. That's a question that I am always trying to answer. There is a lot of excitement in engineering. Polls show that a third of the people in this country really don't know what an engineer does, and half of those people not only don't know but have erroneous ideas such as that engineers run trains. There are other parts of the world where engineering is thought to be exciting. But for a number of reasons -- social and historical, very long-standing complex reasons -- engineering just doesn't have the public attention today that it should in this country.</p>
        <p>Q. If there were such a show, what would it accomplish?</p>
        <p>A. It is just one way of getting people in general to be aware of how exciting engineering is, how important engineering is, how much fun engineering can be. Most important, it could attract young people who, because they're bright and ambitious, think they should be studying law or business, or if they're idealistic, that they should become Ralph Nader or social workers or prosecuting attorneys or anything other than working practically to help people to lead better lives. That is what engineers do.</p>
        <p>Q. In your book you write about technology and the changing society. Are there things we should fear?</p>
        <p>A. I think, like so many things, we go back and forth. Public opinion is a pendulum. Years ago, technology was thought of as a cure-all, a way to some sort of utopia. That was an unrealistic way of thinking. When those dreams were not realized, a certain kind of counter reaction set in. And, of course, we then had some real concerns that came along -- with nuclear weapons, our environmental crisis and the whole feeling in the 60's that our nation was headed in the wrong way all together. So we had a tremendous counter reaction, a hostility to technology. Today I do believe that we have a much more balanced attitude toward technology.</p>
        <p>Q. Is this because of the home computer?</p>
        <p>A. That's one part of it, but I think that balances itself out, too. I think some people are very excited about it, and some people are very anxious and unhappy about it. I think overall we see the potential to use technology to help us solve our problems, to help the world, the poor people of the world, particularly underdeveloped nations, to satisfy their most basic needs. Technology is vital to the well being of the human race.</p>
        <p>At the same time, we've learned a lot of lessons, and there is a new caution. We have dozens and dozens of regulatory agencies and laws, most of them dating back to the 70's.  I know there is a lot of complaining about that and in business a certain amount of inconvenience, but I think all in all it's a healthy development for our society. And we're trying through international agreements on a worldwide scale to address problems such as global warming and others. I think we're in a good state of balance right now.</p>
        <p>Q. In your book you also raise the subject of the impact of technology on bird watching and the cultural side of life. What is that impact?</p>
        <p>A. I happen to be a bird watcher and an engineer at the same time, or a technologist. There are some bird-watching friends who, I won't say accuse me of being responsible for the problems of the birds, but there is an element of that in our conversations sometimes. The fact is, yes, development has endangered the bird species and is a problem for the natural world. On the other hand, the natural world has been quite resilient. The birds have been quite resilient. It has been pointed out by the late Roger Tory Peterson, a great expert on birds, that we have many millions more songbirds today than we did before the Pilgrims arrived. A variety of environments is what gives us a variety of birds.</p>
        <p>So there is a very complex relation between the march of civilization -- to use the old-fashioned language -- and the environment. And here I think we're getting a healthier balance in that wherever you go in our nation, every town, every community is much more sensitive to preserving good things about the environment than our grandparents were or maybe we ourselves were when we were thinking of just development.</p>
        <p>Q. You seem to be saying that technology and poetry are not mutually exclusive, although you wrote about the hostility of poets to technology.</p>
        <p>A. Yes, I think scientists have done a much better job than we, the engineers have, on this -- about writing about science and really having science in the public and artistic world more accepted than engineering has been. But there have been some wonderful books about technology written by David McCollough, one about the Brooklyn Bridge, another about the Panama Canal. I think the potential is there for engineering to be part of our literary culture. But there is right now a pretty wide gulf. I don't think you could go up to your typical poet or novelist and ask them to write sympathetically or philosophically about engineering or technology.</p>
        <p>Q. You write about the public's unawareness of the decline in the United States of being the leader in technology. Where do you see that taking us if it is not reversed?</p>
        <p>A. We have economic consequences of social policy and social belief. To the extent that we're not aware of the importance of technology we can very well suffer economically and in other ways. One specific way is to look at the Federal budget and see what allocations are being made for research and development. This is a constant battle that is influenced by popular attitudes, particularly because we have hardly any engineers in our Congress -- I think about 1 percent or less of our Congress and our state legislatures and practically any other public body that you can think of -- is made up of engineers. We mostly have lawyers.</p>
        <p>Actually, I am cautiously optimistic. After we dropped from our supreme position as the great technological power -- as we saw competition from Japan and other countries, not only in trade but also in development in engineering products -- we have come back in the last few years in industry. In spite of all the battles and dire warnings about what Congress might be doing, the research and development funds of the Federal Government have not fallen.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think there is a reason that few engineers are not attracted to politics, or is it that they cannot get elected because they are viewed as boring people?</p>
        <p>A. Again, we have a complex situation. To a certain extent we have self-selection. There are a lot of people who go into engineering who just don't make good politicians. Something about the engineering approach to the problems doesn't take into account the people element.</p>
        <p>Herbert Hoover, the famous engineer-president, and Jimmy Carter, who was educated as an engineer, both were accused of being too simplistic, if you will, about rights and wrongs and practicalities, without placing people first. But there are places in the world where if you were to be successful in politics -- or in almost anything else -- you think of going to an engineering school. This attitude toward engineering -- that it is wonderful preparation for any career -- you find throughout the world. More than half the Ph.D.'s in engineering in this country are awarded to people from other nations. And some of them are leaders in technology, and others go into politics in their home countries. So, it's not just a question of whether engineers can be politicians.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you have children who are engineers?</p>
        <p>A. I have one son who is a lawyer; one son is a doctor. Some poetic justice in there, but I have three granddaughters, and maybe they'll become engineers.</p>
        <p>Westchester Q&amp;A: Samuel C. Florman</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
