<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Asia Nations Limp Into Fiscal Talks As Turmoil Rages</title>
    <meta content="23APEC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975359"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vancouver (British Columbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Thailand</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Indonesia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Indonesia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Thailand</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/British Columbia/Vancouver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/British Columbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DC113BF930A15752C1A961958260" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Asia Nations Limp Into Fiscal Talks As Turmoil Rages</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>VANCOUVER, British Columbia, Nov. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leaders of US, China, Japan and other nations of Pacific Rim, since first meeting as group in 1993, have swaggered into their annual gatherings almost arrogant in their confidence that region will be 21st century's economic engine and new locus of world power; as they assemble in Vancouver, British Columbia, Pres Clinton and his counterparts will nearly all be limping, wounded by global economic forces beyond their control; financial turmoil that has been coursing through Asia claimed its largest victim, South Korea, on Nov 21; it has called on international community for financial bailout, humbling step that has already been taken by Thailand and Indonesia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since first meeting as a group in 1993, the leaders of the United States, China, Japan and other nations of the Pacific Rim have swaggered into their annual gatherings, almost arrogant in their confidence that the region would be the 21st century's economic engine and the new locus of world power.</p>
        <p>But as they assemble here this weekend, President Clinton and his counterparts from 17 Asian and North and South American members will nearly all be limping, wounded by global economic forces beyond their control and, in Mr. Clinton's case, undercut by domestic political defeats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since first meeting as a group in 1993, the leaders of the United States, China, Japan and other nations of the Pacific Rim have swaggered into their annual gatherings, almost arrogant in their confidence that the region would be the 21st century's economic engine and the new locus of world power.</p>
        <p>But as they assemble here this weekend, President Clinton and his counterparts from 17 Asian and North and South American members will nearly all be limping, wounded by global economic forces beyond their control and, in Mr. Clinton's case, undercut by domestic political defeats.</p>
        <p>On Friday, the financial turmoil that has been coursing through Asia claimed its largest victim, South Korea, the nation with the world's 11th-biggest economy. The Government in Seoul was forced to call on the international community for a financial bailout, a humbling step that has already been taken by Thailand and Indonesia.</p>
        <p>The upheaval has also hit hard in Taiwan, Hong Kong and the Philippines, and could even dent Japan. As a result, the turmoil and how to stop it will no doubt dominate the discussions among the leaders, although they are unlikely to take any action beyond offering reassuring words about their determination to restore calm in financial markets and prosperity throughout Asia.</p>
        <p>But the problems in Asia will have some concrete effects on American policy and on Mr. Clinton's ability to use the two-day gathering, which formally convenes Monday, to advance his own economic agenda championing free trade. The United States, particularly since Mr. Clinton became President, has based its approach to the region largely on expanding trade, a strategy embodied in a 1994 agreement with the Asia-Pacific countries to create a free-trade zone as early as 2010.</p>
        <p>Asia's economic woes are already reducing the region's demand for American exports and are showing signs of sending the trade deficit in the United States to new highs. Consumed by their domestic economic problems, and by their associated political difficulties, few of the Asian leaders here will have much stomach for new market-opening initiatives that might bring objections at home.</p>
        <p>Moreover, having failed this month in his all-out effort to win new trade-negotiating authority from Congress, Mr. Clinton clearly has less standing to demand that other nations take politically painful steps to drop their tariffs and other trade barriers.</p>
        <p>And if Mr. Clinton cannot quickly convince liberal Democrats in Congress to change their position and grant him the negotiating power, his opportunity to pursue new trade deals in many product categories will be all but closed off, even if Asian trading partners are willing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is also still smarting from Congress's rejection last week of his request for $3.5 billion in additional financing for the International Monetary Fund, the vehicle through which the bailouts of South Korea and other nations are being coordinated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has been pressing for more I.M.F. financing all year to deal with exactly the kind of situation that has now erupted in Asia. Although Administration officials are confident that Congress will approve the financing next year, some foreign officials said the situation hurts the United States in its efforts to maintain its effective control over the terms of the international bailouts.</p>
        <p>The mix of difficulties make this year the first real test of the annual gathering, known as the Asia Pacific Economic Cooperation forum, or Apec. Founded in 1989 as a way for lower-level officials of Pacific Rim countries to discuss common interests, it was elevated to the status of a regional summit meeting by Mr. Clinton starting in 1993 as part of his effort to shift the nation's sights toward the economic opportunities and security challenges presented by a rapidly growing and modernizing Asia.</p>
        <p>The leaders ''face the most critical and difficult series of issues in the history of this young institution,'' said C. Fred Bergsten, the director of the Institute for International Economics. ''Their ability to respond effectively and decisively will go far toward determining whether Apec will become a central player in resolving regional and global crises.''</p>
        <p>White House officials, while acknowledging the difficulties the Administration faces here, said the gathering would still be an effective stage on which to exert global economic leadership and, in particular, to highlight the benefits of trade and the need for Mr. Clinton to be granted so-called ''fast-track'' trade authority by Congress. With such authority, he can negotiate trade deals that Congress can approve or reject, but cannot amend.</p>
        <p>They said the meeting was expected to give formal approval to the policies at the heart of American strategy in the region: that nations  need to take responsibility for dealing with their financial problems by adopting more prudent economic policies, that the I.M.F. should take the lead when a bailout plan is necessary, and that countries should still work toward freer trade even while coping with economic difficulties.</p>
        <p>That policy was embodied in an agreement worked out by American and Asian officials in Manila this week. The agreement effectively scuttled an idea first floated by Japan, and strongly opposed by the United States, to create a bailout fund for Asian nations that would operate outside the I.M.F., which typically requires stringent austerity programs in return for its financial assistance.</p>
        <p>''In the past four years, obviously, with the enormous success of economies in Asia, there's been a good deal of emphasis upon what more can be done and how to take advantage of the rapidly growing economies,'' said Daniel Tarullo, Mr. Clinton's adviser on international economic affairs.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, this year, with the recent turmoil in a number of East Asian financial markets, there is a different tone and different atmosphere,'' Mr. Tarullo said.</p>
        <p>But he added the annual summit meeting would prove to be ''a good instrument in trying times as well as good times.''</p>
        <p>American officials said that while they did not expect any big new trade deals, they were confident of winning agreement to drop trade barriers among the Pacific nations in one or two product categories ahead of the general deadline they have set of 2010 for the more developed nations.</p>
        <p>There is also likely to be some discussion with Asian countries of their willingness to agree to a proposed World Trade Organization plan to allow banks, investment firms and other financial services providers more freedom to do business in other countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton will also use the gathering to meet individually with leaders of several other countries, including Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto of Japan. Analysts and government officials are increasingly concerned that Japan's weak economy and the huge number of bad loans weighing down its banking system leave the country vulnerable to the spillover effects of the troubles in South Korea and Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton may also meet with President Jiang Zemin of China. American officials said they would like to build on the Chinese leader's release last weekend of the prominent political dissident Wei Jingsheng and to discuss Mr. Clinton's planned visit to China next year.</p>
        <p>The leaders will also exchange ideas about how to deal with global warming in advance of an international meeting on the topic next month. And they are likely to consider inviting several new members into Apec, including Peru, Vietnam and Russia.</p>
        <p>The current members are Australia, Brunei, Canada, Chile, China, Hong Kong, Indonesia, Japan, Malaysia, Mexico, New Zealand, Papua New Guinea, the Philippines, Singapore, South Korea, Taiwan, Thailand and the United States.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Stocks Plummet in South Korea</p>
        <p>SEOUL, South Korea, Nov. 22 (Reuters) -- Stocks plunged more than 4 percent here today in response to South Korea's decision to seek a loan from the I.M.F.</p>
        <p>''Investors turned skeptical as they realized the I.M.F. bailout package would not be like a free lunch,'' said Choo Hee Yup, a broker at Dongwon Securities. The composite stock index shed 4.08 percent, or 20.64 points, to close at 485.43.</p>
        <p>South Korea said late on Friday that it had asked the I.M.F. to provide about $20 billion in standby credits to overcome the country's financial crisis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
