<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="FORSUM14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="901738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E7DB1038F937A25752C0A961958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A3-9</p>
        <p>TWO INJURED BY LONDON BOMBS</p>
        <p>Two mail clerks were injured when a letter bomb sent to an Arabic-language newspaper exploded in London; at the United Nations headquarters, three other bombs were found and disarmed.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A3-9</p>
        <p>TWO INJURED BY LONDON BOMBS</p>
        <p>Two mail clerks were injured when a letter bomb sent to an Arabic-language newspaper exploded in London; at the United Nations headquarters, three other bombs were found and disarmed.  A1</p>
        <p>DETAILS DELAY HEBRON ACCORD</p>
        <p>Israeli and Palestinian negotiators working with American mediators pored over every dot and comma in their drafts, delaying again an elusive agreement on Hebron. A1</p>
        <p>KOREAN LAW, TRADITION CLASH</p>
        <p>In South Korea, where the bearing of sons is felt to be an age-old social obligation, one of every 12 fetuses is aborted because of its sex, leaving the country with an impending shortage of women. A3</p>
        <p>I.R.A. ISSUES WARNING TO CITIZENS</p>
        <p>Acknowledging that an increasing number of Catholics in Belfast have begun to inform on their planned violent attacks, the Irish Republican Army warned that it will punish such informers.  A4</p>
        <p>PROMISE IGNORED IN SERBIA</p>
        <p>The local electoral commission in Nis, Serbia's second-largest city, has balked at fulfilling a Government promise to honor election results and give an opposition coalition control of the city.  A4</p>
        <p>CHINA CONVICTS TRASH-SMUGGLER</p>
        <p>A Chinese court found an American businessman guilty of smuggling American garbage into China, fined him $60,000 and will expel him.  A3</p>
        <p>PLEA FOR DIALOGUE IN SOFIA</p>
        <p>Barricaded into its headquarters in order to protect itself from mass demonstrations outside, Bulgaria's Socialist Party announced that it was ready for to open talks with the opposition party.  A8</p>
        <p>CLINTON URGES WEAPONS BAN</p>
        <p>President Clinton renewed his drive to win Senate ratification of a treaty banning chemical weapons.  A8</p>
        <p>SHOTS HEARD IN PERU</p>
        <p>Leftist insurgents fired eight gunshots from the Japanese Ambassador's residence in Lima, where they have been holding 74 hostages, but no injuries were reported.  A9</p>
        <p>Russia promised to remove nuclear materials from Georgia.  A8</p>
        <p>Bonn Journal: A capital worries about becoming a small town.  A4</p>
        <p>National A10-13, B6-7</p>
        <p>CLINTON'S CASE IN COURT</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court heard arguments in a lawsuit against President Clinton, with the main issue being whether a President can be made to face trial..  A1</p>
        <p>A BOLD BUDGET MOVE</p>
        <p>Though some leaders in his own party object, President Clinton is drafting a budget that would set firm limits on Federal Medicaid spending as a way to help balance the budget.  A1</p>
        <p>CLASH AT THE CITADEL</p>
        <p>The head the Citadel, South Carolina's historic military college, expressed his determination to make coeducation work at the institution despite the departure of two female cadets.  A1</p>
        <p>LONG-DELAYED HONORS</p>
        <p>Half a century after most of them died in combat, seven black men were awarded Medals of Honor at a ceremony.  A1</p>
        <p>CONCERN ABOUT SELDANE</p>
        <p>The Food and Drug Administration proposed to ban Seldane, a widely prescribed antihistamine, because of rare but potentially deadly side effects.  A1</p>
        <p>ADJUSTING A CONTROVERSIAL PLAN</p>
        <p>The school board in Oakland, Calif., will scratch parts of a plan involving the use of black English in the classroom.  A10</p>
        <p>CAPE COD'S CONCERN</p>
        <p>With the number of permanent, year-around residents increasing steadily and putting new pressures on its limited supplies of fresh water, Cape Cod is now wrestling with the question of how many more people can be permitted to move here.  A10</p>
        <p>Metro Report B1-5</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment C9-20</p>
        <p>Bucharest rediscovers houses by a modernist.  C9</p>
        <p>The Long Wharf Theater names a new artistic director.  C12</p>
        <p>Theater: ''Victor/Victoria'' with Liza Minnelli.  C9</p>
        <p>Music: Tricky at Irving Plaza.  C9</p>
        <p>New Edition is back.  C10</p>
        <p>McCoy Tyner's piano.  C10</p>
        <p>Pavarotti at the Met.  C12</p>
        <p>American Composers Orchestra.  C12</p>
        <p>Chamber Music Society.</p>
        <p>Dance: A visitor from Paris.  C13</p>
        <p>Books: Dick Morris's campaign views.  C20</p>
        <p>Television: ''Frontline: Betting on the Market.''  C14</p>
        <p>Bill T. Jones and Moyers.  C14</p>
        <p>Sports B10-15</p>
        <p>Baseball: New search for a commissioner. B15</p>
        <p>Basketball: Nets lose to Magic.  B14</p>
        <p>Knicks' Johnson uncertain on return. B14</p>
        <p>Colleges: Victory for student-athletes. B11</p>
        <p>Football: Parcells goes for No. 3. B11</p>
        <p>Fassell likely to get Giant post. B13</p>
        <p>Columns: Anderson on Irvin  B11</p>
        <p>On Hockey B12</p>
        <p>TV Sports B13</p>
        <p>Hockey: Islanders top Rangers. B11</p>
        <p>Cases made for N.H.L. expansion teams. B12</p>
        <p>Tennis: Capriati ousted in Australian Open. B11</p>
        <p>Science Times C1-8</p>
        <p>Newly identified black holes add to scientists' understanding.  C1</p>
        <p>Heart disease and depression: sorting out the links.  C1</p>
        <p>Global warming trend showed some blips in 1996.  C3</p>
        <p>Possible benefits of nicotine get serious study.  C3</p>
        <p>Sumatran rhino seems to be two incompatible populations.  wsC4</p>
        <p>Q&amp;A  C7</p>
        <p>Personal Computers  C5</p>
        <p>Fashion B9</p>
        <p>Going sheer but not going overboard</p>
        <p>Obituaries B8</p>
        <p>Editorials/Op-Ed A14-15</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>Budget equity in New York.</p>
        <p>The Citadel's culture of abuse.</p>
        <p>A welcome dialogue in Bulgaria.</p>
        <p>Superman as Cyberman.</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: His quill is fast.</p>
        <p>A. M. Rosenthal: What Bibi got.</p>
        <p>Steven R. Shapiro: The President is not above the law.</p>
        <p>Robert D. Kaplan: Limited options in Serbia.</p>
        <p>Joseph Nocera: Playing the stock market Lotto.</p>
        <p>Chronicle B4</p>
        <p>Chess C6</p>
        <p>Crossword C20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
