<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Comet's Gift: Hints of How Earth Came to Life</title>
    <meta content="01COME$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970403T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="919645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comet Hale-Bopp</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DB1E3AF932A35757C0A961958260" item-length="2053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Comet's Gift: Hints of How Earth Came to Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First comprehensive findings of study of Comet Hale-Bopp support theory that cometary ices bear chemical precursors of life and that vast numbers of comets fell on aboriginal Earth, sowing precursors for what eventually became planet's biological diversity; same mechanism is thought to be at work throughout cosmos, sowing seeds of life on untold worlds; comet is spewing out array of chemical compounds rich in carbon; diagrams; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A TRILLION or so comets are thought to lurk beyond the planets on the dark fringes of the solar system. Lost to a realm where the Sun's faint rays do nothing to lessen the interstellar chill, most of these whirling chunks of dirty ice orbit endlessly.</p>
        <p>But over recorded time, a few comets have left this deep freeze and sped into the inner solar system, at times lighting Earth's skies. Past civilizations often saw them as harbingers of death and doom, and irrational reactions to comets still occur, as evidenced by the grim suicides in Rancho Santa Fe, Calif., where 39 people recently died in the apparent belief that Hale-Bopp was their ticket to aliens and extraterrestrial bliss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A TRILLION or so comets are thought to lurk beyond the planets on the dark fringes of the solar system. Lost to a realm where the Sun's faint rays do nothing to lessen the interstellar chill, most of these whirling chunks of dirty ice orbit endlessly.</p>
        <p>But over recorded time, a few comets have left this deep freeze and sped into the inner solar system, at times lighting Earth's skies. Past civilizations often saw them as harbingers of death and doom, and irrational reactions to comets still occur, as evidenced by the grim suicides in Rancho Santa Fe, Calif., where 39 people recently died in the apparent belief that Hale-Bopp was their ticket to aliens and extraterrestrial bliss.</p>
        <p>Modern astronomers are fascinated by Hale-Bopp for other reasons. Never before have they witnessed anything quite so spectacular. Its icy core is estimated at 25 miles wide, more than 10 times the size of the average comet and big enough to swallow many Manhattans. Its great size makes it unusually bright and easy to study. Since it  was first discovered 20 months ago beyond the orbit of Jupiter, astronomers have scrutinized it unceasingly as the Sun warmed its outer layers, causing the gargantuan ice ball to shed many tons of clues every second about the nature of its chemical makeup.</p>
        <p>Now, the first comprehensive findings are in and give support to a remarkable theory. It suggests that cometary ices bear the chemical precursors of life and that comets fell on the aboriginal Earth in vast numbers and sowed these precursors for what eventually became the planet's riot of biological diversity. The same mechanism is thought to be at work throughout the cosmos, sowing the seeds of life on untold worlds.</p>
        <p>This view is now getting major support as telescopes around the globe find Hale-Bopp spewing not just tons of water but methanol, formaldehyde, carbon monoxide, hydrogen cyanide, hydrogen sulfide and many compounds rich in carbon -- in other words, the basic ingredients thought to be necessary for the origin of life.</p>
        <p>''This is the ironclad link to the new paradigm,'' Dr. Dale P. Cruikshank, an astronomer at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Ames Research Center in California, said in an interview. ''We've never had such a panorama of important molecules.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cruikshank is the first author in a series of eight articles on the Hale-Bopp findings in the current issue of the journal Science. The new discoveries are seen as a milestone in the developing field of bioastronomy, which looks to the heavens for the chemical forerunners of life. And the tidings of cosmic fertility are strikingly at odds with the old view of comets as portents of doom.</p>
        <p>Hurtling through space at more than 27 miles a second, the comet today makes its closest approach to the Sun. Scientists say its return trip to the outer limits of the solar system will probably produce even more insights into its nature, as well as striking nighttime shows in the Northern Hemisphere throughout April and early May.</p>
        <p>''It's not over yet,'' said Dr. Brian G. Marsden of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics in Cambridge, Mass., who helps track comets and other heavenly bodies for the International Astronomical Union. ''It's going to be improving its visibility in the evening sky.''</p>
        <p>Such a comet appears ''once every 200 years or so,'' Dr. Marsden added. ''What makes it great is its persistence.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Harold A. Weaver, an astrophysicist at Johns Hopkins University and lead author on one of the Science papers, said Hale-Bopp might actually outperform itself while heading back toward its icy abode.</p>
        <p>''The nucleus sometimes stores heat and might remain at elevated temperatures for longer outbound than inbound,'' he said in an interview. ''We already have this beautiful set of data and we want to watch it go back out again. There's clearly a lot of excitement.''</p>
        <p>Some telescopes must stop tracking Hale-Bopp as it approaches the Sun or be damaged by bright sunlight. This is particularly true for the Hubble Space Telescope, orbiting d Earth.  Later, as the comet races toward the dim hinterlands, astronomers will redouble their efforts to gather clues to Hale-Bopp's chemical and physical makeup in hope of strengthening the uncanny link between comets and the first stirrings of life on Earth.</p>
        <p>Such thinking is a radical departure from the traditional view developed over the decades by scientists, mainly geologists and geophysicists.</p>
        <p>In the old picture, Earth was thought to have coalesced out of primordial dust as a bare sphere with no atmosphere, basically a rocky desert. The gases and water vapors and carbonaceous brews that formed the atmosphere and filled the seas were seen as having come from within Earth in an early period of intense volcanism. Lightning storms then stirred the primordial soup and created carbon-rich molecules that organized themselves into self-replicating units, or crude forms of life.</p>
        <p>Not so, says a newer theory, which astronomers, astrophysicists and planetary scientists tend to advance.</p>
        <p>More than four billion years ago in its early days, Earth was hot enough to expel into space most of the water and lighter materials and chemicals, this theory holds. So the planet remained a barren rock.</p>
        <p>For the makings of life, the new theory looks to the wastelands out among the stars, especially to the dark clouds that loom against starry backdrops. Such dim zones are common among the countless stars that make up the Milky Way, Earth's galaxy. On a clear dark night, the naked eye can easily see the voids amid the milky brightness.</p>
        <p>These dark interstellar clouds turn out to be peppered with grains of matter about the size of talcum particles that are virtual factories for the production of complex chemicals. To date, scientists have identified nearly 100 molecular species.</p>
        <p>Interstellar water was found in 1968, formaldehyde in 1969, methyl alcohol in 1970, hydrogen sulfide in 1972, methylamine in 1974, ketene in 1976, methane in 1978, ethylene in 1980, methyl diacetylene in 1984, methyl isocyanide in 1987 and butatrienylidene in 1990. Such molecules were discovered to make up about half of the interstellar matter, the rest being mainly atomic hydrogen.</p>
        <p>These chemical finds were made as astronomers turned radio, infrared, ultraviolet and visible-light telescopes on the icy wastelands and studied signals that showed molecules giving off their own precise signatures amid a chaos of electromagnetic waves.</p>
        <p>One pioneer of such analysis is Dr. Yvonne J. Pendleton of the Ames Research Center. She works there with Dr. Cruikshank, her husband and occasional co-author. In the March 1994 issue of Sky and Telescope magazine, the couple wrote about finding evidence of chemical  precursors to life in space.</p>
        <p>No signs of amino acids -- the constituents of DNA, life's master heredity molecule -- have yet been found amid the interstellar wastes. But lots of forerunners have, including ammonia and hydrogen cyanide. The leap to amino acids is said to take only the addition of liquid water.</p>
        <p>Today, scientists see the interstellar factory as working in several steps. First, dying stars lace the void with an array of relatively simple molecules such as methane (CH4 ), water (H2 O) and carbon monoxide (CO), as well as tiny gains of silicon, the element found in rocks, sand and semiconductors. Over eons, the molecules coat the silicon grains with icy mantles.</p>
        <p>Dense clouds of such materials condense in places to form new stars that irradiate nearby grains with bursts of ultraviolet light, transforming the simple molecules into more complex ones like formaldehyde (H2 CO) and methyl alcohol (CH3 OH).</p>
        <p>In theory, such complex interstellar dusts then become the raw material for new generations of stars, perhaps accompanied by planets as well as trillions of icy comets.</p>
        <p>Astronomers on Earth observe comets rushing through the inner solar system only fleetingly. In contrast, the interstellar wilds are always visible. Despite the difficulty, astronomers, aided by recent advances in telescopes and instrumentation, have begun to learn some of the chemical secrets of the icy visitors.</p>
        <p>The first glimmers came in 1985 and 1986 with Halley's comet, which yielded signs of water, carbon dioxide and formaldehyde (used on Earth as a disinfectant and preservative). In 1989, another comet showed evidence of methyl alcohol (used as antifreeze), while one in 1990 gave signs of hydrogen sulfide (the poison that smells like rotten eggs).</p>
        <p>The big advance came last year with Comet Hyakutake, which was extremely bright and easy to analyze. Its signals gave evidence of many different molecules akin to those of the interstellar wastes.</p>
        <p>Now astronomers studying Hale-Bopp, discovered on July 22, 1995, have topped even that. The findings are significant both for the sheer number of molecules and, as important, for a detailed description of when the chemicals evaporated from the giant ice ball as it raced inward from the deep freeze toward the Sun.</p>
        <p>In Science, a 12-member team headed by Dr. Nicolas Biver at the Observatoire de Paris-Meudon, in Meudon, France, describes nine chemicals sighted by radiotelescopes: Carbon monoxide (CO) in September 1995, methyl alcohol in March 1996, hydrogen cyanide (HCN) in April 1996, hydroxyl radical (OH) in April 1996, hydrogen sulfide (H2 S) in May 1996, formaldehyde in June 1996, carbon monosulfide (CS) in June 1996, methyl cyanide (CH3 CN) in August 1996 and hydrogen isocyanide (HNC) in November 1996.</p>
        <p>''It's a landmark,'' Dr. Cruikshank said of the list. ''It shows when and how these molecules turn on, and shows the evaporation sequences. They're also found in space. This is the link that really clinches the connection to the interstellar medium and proves that this material is essentially unaltered.''</p>
        <p>Put differently, it shows that comets are heavenly vans carrying tons of carbon-rich materials from interstellar space to addresses throughout the solar system.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cruikshank said bombardments of cometary ice undoubtedly hit not only the early Earth (heavily for a period of perhaps a billion years or so) but also Mercury and the Moon. Both those bodies have recently yielded signs of hidden ice.</p>
        <p>Even today, he added, microscopic dust particles from comets and rocky asteroids rain down on Earth at the rate of about 300 tons a year.</p>
        <p>The prevailing wisdom, bolstered by Hale-Bopp, is now that comets played a pivotal role in begetting life on Earth.</p>
        <p>''Thirty years ago we thought you had to have lightning storms,'' Dr. Michael J. Mumma, a longtime comet expert at NASA's Goddard Space Flight Center in Maryland, said in an interview. ''Now it's recognized that the materials are delivered automatically.''</p>
        <p>''That doesn't mean you get life out of that,'' Dr. Mumma added. ''But it means you deliver large amounts of simple chemicals, and maybe some complex ones, that can lead to life directly.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 3, 1997, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about research on comet Hale-Bopp and on molecules found in it and in interstellar space defined amino acids incorrectly. They are the building blocks of proteins, not of the genetic material DNA.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 3, 1997, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about research on comet Hale-Bopp and on molecules found in it and in interstellar space defined amino acids incorrectly. They are the building blocks of proteins, not of the genetic material DNA.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
