<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases</title>
    <meta content="17VIDB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="965664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E3DB123FF934A25753C1A961958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Capsule reviews of new video releases (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Batman and Robin</p>
        <p>Poured into his anatomically correct rubber suit, a rather stiff-caped crusader (George Clooney, left) plays second dramatic fiddle to two garishly decked-out villains from decidedly opposite poles of the global warming question. At one time a mousy and abused botanist, the gorgeous and sneeringly nasty green revolutionist Poison Ivy (Uma Thurman) joins forces with an icicle of a fellow called Mr. Freeze (Arnold Schwarzenegger). A two-time Nobel Prize winner who now needs to remain permanently on ice, the vengeful Freeze threatens to turn Gotham into a popsicle. With these two putting on a campy costume party, Joel Schumacher's film, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, ''is more than happy to steamroll over questions of plotting and character.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Batman and Robin</p>
        <p>Poured into his anatomically correct rubber suit, a rather stiff-caped crusader (George Clooney, left) plays second dramatic fiddle to two garishly decked-out villains from decidedly opposite poles of the global warming question. At one time a mousy and abused botanist, the gorgeous and sneeringly nasty green revolutionist Poison Ivy (Uma Thurman) joins forces with an icicle of a fellow called Mr. Freeze (Arnold Schwarzenegger). A two-time Nobel Prize winner who now needs to remain permanently on ice, the vengeful Freeze threatens to turn Gotham into a popsicle. With these two putting on a campy costume party, Joel Schumacher's film, Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times, ''is more than happy to steamroll over questions of plotting and character.''</p>
        <p>1997. Warner. $22.97. Laser disk, $39.98. 125 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Night Falls on Manhattan</p>
        <p>In Sidney Lumet's film, a young prosecutor, Sean Casey (Andy Garcia), is assigned to a case involving a police detective (Ian Holm) who also happens to be his father. Corruption is a fact of life as Sean goes up against both a crafty defense lawyer (Richard Dreyfuss) and a crowd of city politicians with the truth to hide and ambitions to protect. With his sure sense of place, Mr. Lumet creates a graphic and hard-boiled picture of a New York justice system in the hands of those on the make. The one problem is Mr. Garcia, who doesn't rise to the intense pitch required and too often ''remains a polite and neutral presence'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1997. Paramount. $99.11. Laser disk, $34.98. 114 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Austin Powers: International Man of Mystery</p>
        <p>Cryogenically preserved for 30 years, a go-go private eye named Powers (Mike Myers) returns to cut a silly swath as a buffoonish adventurer in a ruffled shirt. No, there's no point whatsoever, other than to have some goofy fun, which Mr. Myers has done so well on past occasions (in ''Wayne's World,'' for example). Here he is in good form in a 70's-style Bondian caper that deliberately makes no sense but ''is so dauntless and just plain nutty that it's hard to resist'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1997. New Line. $105.52. Laser disk, $39.99. 87 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Gray's Anatomy</p>
        <p>In his 14th monologue, Spalding Gray moves on from politics and other concerns of the human condition to concentrate on his own bodily woes, specifically his ocular troubles. With Mr. Gray, eye problems can involve anything from an oedipal obsession to a condition that might find a remedy in an American Indian sweat lodge. Though he doesn't operate at the energy level he did in ''Swimming to Cambodia'' and other monologues, this effort is ''still a chatty, colorful, nicely sardonic account'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1996. Fox Lorber. $89.98. 80 minutes. No rating.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
