<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore to Join U.S. Team at Global Climate Conference in Japan</title>
    <meta content="02GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kyoto (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFDA163DF931A35751C1A961958260" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore to Join U.S. Team at Global Climate Conference in Japan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton, concerned that global climate-change conference in Kyoto, Japan, will adopt more stringent pollution targets than US is willing to accept, says he will send Vice Pres Gore to meeting to argue US position forcefully (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton, concerned that the global climate-change conference now under way in Kyoto, Japan, will adopt more stringent pollution targets than the United States is willing to accept, announced today that he was sending Vice President Al Gore to the meeting to argue the American position forcefully.</p>
        <p>The choice of Mr. Gore as the senior United States representative at the conference came after months of intense debate within the Administration and was made public after the 10-day meeting had already begun. Mr. Gore will spend only one day in Kyoto, next Monday, during which he will present the American policy in a speech and meet briefly with members of other delegations before returning to Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton, concerned that the global climate-change conference now under way in Kyoto, Japan, will adopt more stringent pollution targets than the United States is willing to accept, announced today that he was sending Vice President Al Gore to the meeting to argue the American position forcefully.</p>
        <p>The choice of Mr. Gore as the senior United States representative at the conference came after months of intense debate within the Administration and was made public after the 10-day meeting had already begun. Mr. Gore will spend only one day in Kyoto, next Monday, during which he will present the American policy in a speech and meet briefly with members of other delegations before returning to Washington.</p>
        <p>As recently as last week, Administration officials had said that Mr. Gore would not attend the Kyoto meeting because other Governments would be represented by lower-level officials. But as the momentum for a sweeping declaration from Kyoto for reducing climate-warming emissions as grown in recent days, White House officials decided that Mr. Gore needed to attend to prevent the United States position from being shouted down.</p>
        <p>The President said at a White House picture-taking session today that the American policy was ''aggressive and achievable,'' setting realistic targets for reducing gases that trap heat in the atmosphere. He warned delegates from more than 150 nations now meeting in Kyoto against ''promising to do something that neither we nor others can do.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was alluding to a European position that calls for cuts in production of so-called greenhouse gases far beyond anything that American businesses or the Clinton Administration believe can be achieved in the next 10 to 20 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he and the President ''are perfectly prepared to walk away from an agreement that we don't think will work.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''So it should be crystal clear to all the parties there that we're going to present the U.S. position forcefully and clearly.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has much at stake in the global-warming debate, having been one of the first American politicians to raise an alarm about the problem. Mr. Gore was a central figure in the Administration debate and only reluctantly accepted the compromise position that is far more modest than the prescriptions he offered while in the Senate and in his book, ''Earth in the Balance.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore will not lead the United States delegation to the climate talks, nor will he negotiate with other nations on what commitments the conference will make. Those jobs remain with Stuart E. Eizenstat, the Under Secretary of State.</p>
        <p>This fall, the Clinton Administration pledged that the United States would cut emissions to 1990 levels in the next 10 to 15 years. This would be achieved with tax incentives, subsidies for clean energy production and conservation, and by trading pollution permits among industries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that the American proposal would bring a 30 percent reduction in greenhouse gases in the United States by the year 2010. He called that a ''huge change'' that can be achieved without significant economic pain.</p>
        <p>And he said, ''Whether there is an agreement in Kyoto or not, the United States is prepared under President Clinton's leadership to unilaterally take the steps that we believe should be taken in order to deal with this problem.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
