<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; Is Ollie Allie?</title>
    <meta content="13DOWD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Tipper</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Segal, Erich</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Love Story (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0D81E3CF930A25751C1A961958260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; Is Ollie Allie?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column on Vice Pres Al Gore's assertion that his college romance with his future wife, Tipper, inspired Love Story, novel written by Erich Segal, one of Gore's roommates at Harvard (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forget Henry Cisneros, global warming and Janet Reno.</p>
        <p>The week's most stunning revelation was a report in Time magazine that Al and Tipper Gore are the models for that touchstone couple of bad literature -- Oliver Barrett IV and Jenny Cavilleri, the uptight Harvard preppie and free-spirited 'Cliffie of ''Love Story.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forget Henry Cisneros, global warming and Janet Reno.</p>
        <p>The week's most stunning revelation was a report in Time magazine that Al and Tipper Gore are the models for that touchstone couple of bad literature -- Oliver Barrett IV and Jenny Cavilleri, the uptight Harvard preppie and free-spirited 'Cliffie of ''Love Story.''</p>
        <p>The Vice President dropped this literary bombshell, disclosing that his college romance with Tipper inspired his Harvard pal, Erich Segal, who lived in Dunster House at the same time that Mr. Gore and Tommy Lee Jones were roommates there in the late 60's. Mr. Segal hung out with the lovebirds, the chiseled scion of a Tennessee political dynasty and the perky Boston University coed, Mary Elizabeth (Tipper) Aitcheson.</p>
        <p>''Love Story'' was about a jock who cried. A preppie defies his wealthy father to marry an ethnic, working-class pianist, and learns she is dying of a mysterious disease. Until ''The Bridges of Madison County,'' it was the most famous bad weepy. When the movie starring Ryan O'Neal and Ali MacGraw came out -- with Tommy Lee Jones reprising his role as roommate -- the author bragged that the ushers would need mops.</p>
        <p>It's somewhat suspicious that Mr. Gore has chosen this moment to drop the news -- unknown even to many close friends and aides. Does he think, going into 2000, that this will give him a romantic glow, or a romantic afterglow? It reminds me of Jackie Kennedy whispering in Teddy White's ear about ''Camelot.''</p>
        <p>''I was, like, 'Wow!' This means Al's going to be President,'' laughs Carter Eskew, a Gore friend. ''That was a huge book and movie about the coolest couple. The guy was a sensitive stud, an athletic Alan Alda.''</p>
        <p>I called Erich Segal to see if Ollie was Allie, but his London agent said Mr. Segal was writing in seclusion.</p>
        <p>He did tell The New York Times in 1970 that Oliver was a fellow student at Harvard. Jenny, he said, was a pastiche, which makes sense since Tipper is still alive, and was raised by a banker, not a baker. She met Al when he was prepping to become a preppie at St. Alban's, the brother school of her alma mater, the National Cathedral School. Tipper, in fact, was the sort Jenny disdained as ''Wendy Wasp.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. Segal, who contributed to Mr. Gore's 1984 senatorial campaign, is squirreled away bringing the saga of Ollie-Allie up to date so it can be published in time for the campaign. Mr. Segal could model this sequel on a couple with a real class chasm -- an uptight preppie Vice President and a free-spirited President from a working-class background. Instead of a life-threatening illness, there are life-threatening legal problems. Instead of a beloved wife wasting away, beloved issues and ideas waste away. In this version, the preppie does not rebel against authority, except occasionally, when he refuses to go over to Marty Peretz's to eat canapes and debate the Middle East. And this time around, Tommy Lee Jones gets all the girls.</p>
        <p>Imagine a Segalesque chapter where Al and Bill, at their regular White House lunch, contemplate the unthinkable: breaking up.</p>
        <p>Al is talking about ''digital earth'' and ''distributed intelligence,'' but he can tell Bill is distracted.</p>
        <p>''Wise up, Preppie, wouldja please?'' Bill says. ''I don't give a hoot about digital earth. We won't be doing that at Dreamworks SKGC.''</p>
        <p>''You are going to Hollywood?'' Al asks, dumbfounded.</p>
        <p>''Steven and David and Jeffrey really want me. I can hardly wait.''</p>
        <p>Al grabs him by the shoulders, maybe a bit too roughly. ''Hey -- you're going to leave me here alone with Janet Reno?''</p>
        <p>Al feels the barriers in his soul returning, those inner divisions between head and heart. Suddenly his earth is not in balance.</p>
        <p>''Allie, don't be stupid,'' Bill says. ''It's inevitable that we go our separate ways. You're a preppie zillionaire with a sense of entitlement and I'm a social zero with a lot of legal bills.''</p>
        <p>Al is still holding onto Bill's shoulders. ''But we're together now,'' he pleads. ''We're happy.''</p>
        <p>Bill bites his lip. ''I wish I wasn't leaving you with this mess over the phone calls, the Indian casinos, the Buddhist temple and all.''</p>
        <p>Al does what he has never done in the President's presence. He cries.  Bill wraps him in a big hug, murmuring, ''It'll be O.K.'' ''Just remember, Preppie, you're perfect. Being Al Gore means never having to say you're sorry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
