<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Weather at 11, and More or Less All Winter</title>
    <meta content="26EGAN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="968177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pacific Ocean</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DA1E3EF935A15753C1A961958260" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Weather at 11, and More or Less All Winter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many people are concerned that El Nino, perfectly normal but obsessively observed warming of Pacific Ocean, will cause epic unsettling of winter weather this year, but Government scientists and TV weather forecasters for first time are making precise predictions about what it will do; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A RICH man this winter may be the one who purchased futures in sand, roofing material and Midwestern grain last summer. Not that there are looming shortages. But enough people think El Nino, the perfectly normal but obsessively observed warming of the Pacific Ocean, will cause such an epic unsettling of winter weather this year that there is already a run on all sorts of things usually taken for granted.</p>
        <p>Try hiring a roofing contractor in California; it's a three-month wait in some places. Snow is supposed to be scarce in the places where it is most wanted: ski resorts in the northern Rockies and Nagano, Japan, site of the 1998 Winter Olympics. At the same time, heating oil prices are flat, in large part due to forecasts of a comparatively balmy winter in the northern half of the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A RICH man this winter may be the one who purchased futures in sand, roofing material and Midwestern grain last summer. Not that there are looming shortages. But enough people think El Nino, the perfectly normal but obsessively observed warming of the Pacific Ocean, will cause such an epic unsettling of winter weather this year that there is already a run on all sorts of things usually taken for granted.</p>
        <p>Try hiring a roofing contractor in California; it's a three-month wait in some places. Snow is supposed to be scarce in the places where it is most wanted: ski resorts in the northern Rockies and Nagano, Japan, site of the 1998 Winter Olympics. At the same time, heating oil prices are flat, in large part due to forecasts of a comparatively balmy winter in the northern half of the United States.</p>
        <p>But what happens if California is dry, the Northeast is cold, and the jet stream carpet-bombs the Rockies in snow -- if there is, in other words, a normal winter? A whole army of climate predictors, web site producers and politicians may have to find new indoor pursuits.</p>
        <p>El Nino is real, no question about it. Temperatures in the eastern Pacific in August and September were higher than any recorded in 50 years. And that mass of warm surface water, radiating on infrared weather maps like the coals of a fake fire, is now about the size of Canada. Yikes!</p>
        <p>Been There</p>
        <p>But even if it looks a bit outsize this year, the phenomenon -- basically, a change in the normal east-west flow of trade winds across an ocean that covers nearly a third of the earth's surface -- has been around  perhaps since the time that humans stopped dragging their knuckles across the ground. Since 1950, there have been 13 appearances of The Kid.</p>
        <p>What has changed this time around are technology and the forecasting business, which go together. For the first time, scientists from all sorts of Government agencies and their less-well-trained but better-dressed colleagues at TV weather departments are making rather precise predictions about what this El Nino is supposed to do. And helped by such Nino-related phenomena as warm-water fish like marlins being caught off the normally frigid Northwest coast and wildflowers busting out in the Baja desert, it's a ratings winner.</p>
        <p>Here's what they predict for the United States this winter: high winds, pounding surf and sheets of rain for much of California -- hence the run on sandbags, tarps and new roofs. The Northwest will be warmer and drier -- bad for salmon, good for people whose melancholia is weather-influenced. Parts of the Rockies will be snow-starved, ditto the Great Plains, and not as cold. The South is a tossup, except Florida and the Gulf Coast, which are supposed to be wetter than usual. The Atlantic Coast and the Northeast will be warmer, with less snow.</p>
        <p>All of this is speculation, of course. But it is bolder and more pronounced than ever before, lending itself to headlines and news accounts that sound like 1950's sci-fi films. ''Word's out that El Nino is coming,'' The San Francisco Examiner announced in a fairly typical article last week. ''Not just any El Nino, but the biggest, baddest El Nino to mosey up the coast in 150 years.'' An article in The San Francisco Chronicle carried this large-type comment: ''The cry has gone out: El Nino is coming, El Nino is coming.''</p>
        <p>It is not just journalists and weather forecasters generating the storm of superlatives. Also joining the choir are politicians, psychiatrists and scientists whose usual idea of a daring exchange is to share cartoon lines from the ''The Far Side.''</p>
        <p>Rain in Southern California</p>
        <p>At an El Nino ''summit'' this month in Santa Monica, Calif., the Federal Government's top oceanographer issued some dire warnings. Ants Leetmaa, director of the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration, predicted that rainfall in Southern California would be 200 percent above normal, which would make it one of the wettest winters on record. Already, he said, temperatures in the ocean were ''unprecedented in amplitude.''</p>
        <p>This prompted Vice President Al Gore, who attended the summit, to declare, ''We must act before the rains begin,'' and then to speculate that perhaps global warming was to blame. El Nino has been a boost for both sides in the debate over what to do about emissions of earth-warming gases. One side sees the higher-than-usual warming of the ocean as evidence of human meddling in the fragile earth, the other sees Nature asserting itself at the top of the earthly order with a vengeance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leetmaa based his forecast on the mind-boggling array of observation materiel trained on El Nino, from sensor buoys bobbing all over the Pacific to satellite cameras sending back a flow of images that look pretty cool on the World Wide Web.</p>
        <p>But for all that, he added, his forecast could be wrong. Even if the predictions are accurate, El Nino may not be all that bad. For one thing, winds from the heavily-vexed ocean have cleaned Southern California's air, bringing one of the best years to breathe in Los Angeles in 50 years.</p>
        <p>The Northwest surely will mourn the continued loss of its Pacific salmon, but El Nino is also supposed to be hard on sea lions, the scourge of salmon. Seattle has been trying for nearly 10 years just to get rid of a half-dozen or so sea lions who do nothing but lounge around with their mouths open at the entrance to a once-bountiful salmon entry point.</p>
        <p>Western lands starved by drought, particularly in New Mexico and Arizona, may get full reservoirs and fresh life in parched washes. Some forecasters say Florida will get fewer hurricanes in 1998, the year of El Nino Grande. Also, few people are expected to complain about lower heating bills in New England.</p>
        <p>Overall, the United States is expected to fare better than the rest of the world. Already, droughts in Australia, Brazil and South Africa, and fires in Indonesia are blamed on El Nino.</p>
        <p>For that matter, El Nino can be and probably will be blamed, or credited, for almost anything, from the fate of Mr. Gore's political future to the overbearing funk of a fifth-grader. People who are making money, or careers, off El Nino are benefiting from expectations, not from real changes. Analysts have been running up the stocks of certain home repair chains, anticipating record years for hardware warehouses. The insurance industry is doing booming business in parts of the West. Commodities traders, banking on forecasts of dry days for the farm belt, are taking El Nino talk to the bank. Some farmers have sold their cattle and altered their planting schedules.</p>
        <p>If all the Sturm und Drang does come about, it will be useful to remember that it has happened before, and long before El Nino was given its name -- a reference to the Christ child, since it usually appears in the eastern tropical Pacific around Christmas -- in 1895. People went about their lives, working and complaining about the weather as usual, wondering why there is no white Christmas some years, without any idea about the temperature changes in the middle of the Pacific.</p>
        <p>And there is another comforting thought, courtesy of The Old Farmer's Almanac. For 205 years, the almanac has been forecasting the weather, based on ''a secret formula devised by the founder of the almanac in 1792,'' as the book explains. This year, the outlook for winter is nothing very dramatic: snowfall above normal in New England, rainfall below normal in the southeast, a wet Pacific Northwest and California scheduled to get ''near-normal precipitation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
