<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seltzer Men Deliver Fizz (by the Case) Right to the Front Door</title>
    <meta content="SELTZE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bottled Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoppe, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musleah, Rahel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3DB1431F932A0575BC0A961958260" item-length="1827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seltzer Men Deliver Fizz (by the Case) Right to the Front Door</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAHEL MUSLEAH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Musleah, Rahel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on old-time seltzer delivery man Paul Hoppe, who plies his trade on Long Island; customers comment on beverage, stored in thick, glass siphon bottles; history of seltzer traced; carbonated water sales totaled $560 million in 1996; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PAUL HOPPE makes his living on nostalgia, but nothing about him gives away his profession: not his spray of frizzy brown hair or his work attire of shorts and T-shirt, not the staccato honk of his delivery van's horn announcing his arrival in a customer's driveway.</p>
        <p>Paul Hoppe is an old-fashioned seltzer man.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PAUL HOPPE makes his living on nostalgia, but nothing about him gives away his profession: not his spray of frizzy brown hair or his work attire of shorts and T-shirt, not the staccato honk of his delivery van's horn announcing his arrival in a customer's driveway.</p>
        <p>Paul Hoppe is an old-fashioned seltzer man.</p>
        <p>''Hey, seltzer here!'' he sang out like a hot-dog vendor at a ball park on a recent delivery route in Plainview, grinning and smoking a cigarette as he knocked at the door.</p>
        <p>''I grew up on seltzer,'' said Laurie Barocas, a teacher, who answered  the door. ''I have to have it. When I moved from Little Neck 12 years ago, I didn't know a seltzer man here. My seltzer man in Queens continued to deliver to the store we owned in Little Neck, and my husband had to schlep the cases back and forth once a month. We did that for two years until my husband said, 'This is it!' ''</p>
        <p>''The charm of seltzer is that it's almost like an antique,'' Mr. Hoppe explained. ''It reminds people of their childhood, when their parents used to get it delivered.''</p>
        <p>Seltzer has undergone a revival of sorts, and is available bottled in supermarkets in plain and flavored varieties. But Mr. Hoppe's customers prefer the kind he brings to their doors. Beyond nostalgia, seltzer in the old-time siphon bottles Mr. Hoppe recycles never goes flat. It retains its trademark spritz whether its fans drink it plain, the quintessential, calorie-free diet beverage, or combine it with chocolate or other syrups to whip up egg creams and lemon-lime cherry rickeys. The bottles, thick green, blue or clear glass, stamped on the bottom with their country of manufacture -- often Czechoslovakia -- seal in the pressurized carbonated fizz that makes seltzer devotees grope for words. On Mr. Hoppe's delivery route, some customers tried to capture the mystique.</p>
        <p>''It's got a better taste than water,'' said Sarah Barocas, 12. ''I like  pushing the siphon.''</p>
        <p>''It's more refreshing than anything,'' said Phil Karas, 52. ''Growing up it was a staple, like milk. It reminds me of the Lower East Side and egg creams and all the nice things,'' said Susan Hemley, 54.</p>
        <p>''We lived in the countryside when I was a child in Hungary, so we had seltzer delivered,'' said Bela Ladyani, 63, a mechanic who was an Air Force pilot before he emigrated from Hungary in 1971.</p>
        <p>''In Budapest you could get it in the store.''</p>
        <p>Madelyn Smallberg said: 'My neighbor in Brooklyn was a seltzer man. His daughter was my best  friend.''Ms. Smallberg, 46, is a nutritionist and electrologist who lives in Melville. ''We used to climb on his truck all the way to the top. That's one of my earliest memories.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Smallberg's children, 11, 14 and 17, drink most of the seltzer. On  this delivery, Mr. Hoppe loaded 11 cases, 66 bottles, into the front closet.</p>
        <p>He and his assistant, Edgar Sierra, carried in two six-pack wooden crates of seltzer at a time, one 28-pound crate in each hand. They hauled away the crates of empty bottles and dunked them onto a metal bed on to the roof of the van.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoppe, 48, of Melville, is one of  three seltzer men on Long Island. His route includes 600 customers who pay more than $1 for each 26-ounce bottle. Most are between 30 and 50, with two or three children, and range from airline pilots to  accountants, from retired rock stars to rabbis. Jim DeNucci, who owns  Tri-Boro Beverage in West Babylon, the only seltzer bottling plant on Long Island, delivers to about 1,000 customers, most of them elderly, in Long Island, Brooklyn, Queens and Manhattan. Jeff Brown, of Bayshore, runs a route of 250 customers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoppe estimates that 85 percent of his customers are Jewish, 10 percent Italian, and 5 percent a ''mixed bag.'' None of Long Island's seltzer men are Jewish.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Hoppe and Mr. Brown, seltzer's roots are in Germany. The  Columbia Encyclopedia describes seltzer as ''mineral water containing free carbon dioxide, obtained originally from springs at Niederselters, Germany. Reputed to have curative value in treating several diseases, it became very popular in the 19th century. In the 20th century, it was produced synthetically.'' The German ''Selterser wasser'' became ''seltzer water'' in English.</p>
        <p>For immigrants, seltzer was an inexpensive thirst quencher, but today, sales of carbonated water, plain and flavored, and club soda, which has added salt, are in the millions of dollars. According to Information Resources, a marketing research company, sales in 1996 totaled $560 million in supermarkets with sales over $2 million.</p>
        <p>Despite its appeal for a few customers, old-fashioned seltzer delivery is a dinosaur, Mr. Hoppe said. He estimated that of 150 seltzer men who once worked in the New York area, there are now about 45, most in Brooklyn. Seltzer men also still work in areas like Miami, Chicago and Los Angeles, he said, but the lightweight,  inexpensive plastic bottles of club soda and seltzer that became easily  available in supermarkets in the late 1960's spelled the decline of siphon bottles.</p>
        <p>The hard physical work involved in seltzer delivery is another factor in its decline, said Ron Dworkin, treasurer of Castle Seltzer, a family-run bottling plant and delivery company in Milford, Conn. ''It requires a lot of work to get a case of bottles ready. The bottles have to be cleaned. Washers wear out. Often the collars have to be repaired. The bottles have to be filled, and after that, all you do is drag them in and out.''</p>
        <p>Repairing damaged bottles and  crates is the first order of the day for Mr. Hoppe and Mr. Sierra. Mr. Hoppe's yard, sculptured with 1,000 empty seltzer bottles under a black tarpaulin, also holds two huge hills of  firewood, which he sells in the winter to supplement his income. He stores  another 450 filled bottles in his garage.</p>
        <p>Twice a week, he stops at Tri-Boro Beverage to fill up. There, the science behind the bubbles becomes evident in an array of pipes and tanks. The seltzer begins as water, filtered first through two tanks, one filled with 130 pounds of charcoal, the other with 300 pounds of sand. It then travels through a paper filter and is channeled into a 90-gallon chilling tank. To make the fizziest seltzer, Mr. De Nucci said, the water has to cool from 55 to 40 degrees to best absorb the carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Until three months ago, Mr. DeNucci used a chilling machine dating from the 1939 New York World's Fair. But its Freon-cooled system was not as effective as the new $10,000 chiller he recently bought.</p>
        <p>The carbon dioxide is kept in a four-ton tank at a pressure of 300  pounds. A pipe leads the carbon dioxide into a carbonator, where it mixes  with the water that has been pumped into it from the chiller at a rate of 500  gallons an hour. Then the empty bottles are placed in two cast iron bottling machines that can fill a thousand bottles an hour. The machine squirts each bottle twice: once with gas and water, and once with of gas  alone. Each bottle is sealed with 125 pounds of pressure.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Hoppe's 100 cases are forklifted into his van, he hits the road. For him, the novelty of being a seltzer man is one of the perks of the job. ''It's unique,'' he said. ''I'm not a doctor, a lawyer or a mechanic. I'm a  seltzer man! Paul Hoppe, the seltzer king!''</p>
        <p>He laughed, carefully maneuvering his van around curves and over speed bumps while bottles rattled in a symphony of glass. ''I'm my own boss. It beats a boring office job.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoppe didn't have sentimental associations with seltzer. His earliest recollection of it is a fizz fight at a  friend's Halloween party when he was 16. He grew up in Queens, attended Roman Catholic elementary and high schools and went on to Bronx Community College, with the goal of becoming a marine biologist.</p>
        <p>School was not his forte, however, and he went to work in the mail room of The New York Times. In 1978, he  saw a small seltzer route of 50 customers advertised in the newspaper. He bought it. His business has expanded mostly through word of mouth.</p>
        <p>During his 19 years as a seltzer man, he has heard plenty of stories about the old days. He knows about the reported rendezvous between seltzer men and their female customers who were home alone. He's had his share of propositions.</p>
        <p>''I've had customers who used to ask me to come in and have a drink, or have a joint, and more than that too,'' he said. ''I handle it diplomatically. I've got a wife and two kids.''</p>
        <p>He makes his deliveries between 2 and 7 P.M., usually after children have come home from school. Irving Press, the former owner of Tri-Boro Beverage, regaled him with tales of seltzer inspectors who would follow drivers to make sure they didn't steal other drivers' bottles or take their customers. The metal collars of the bottles were often engraved with the seltzer man's name to protect the  bottles' ownership.</p>
        <p>Nowadays the business is less cutthroat. During the spring and fall, the  best seasons, Mr. Hoppe sells 200 six packs a week. The worst part of the  job, he said, are the traffic jams he encounters while driving 400 miles a week.</p>
        <p>Accidents happen. Once he spilled chocolate syrup all over a kitchen floor and spent an hour mopping the gooey mess. Another time he had a fight with his wife and kicked a case of bottles in anger. A bottle exploded and he got six stitches in his knee.</p>
        <p>The rare incidents of customers' getting hurt by exploding bottles have caused Mr. Hoppe to carry $1 million in liability insurance. ''If you handle the bottles intelligently -- don't drop them on concrete floors or let children swing them around -- they are not dangerous,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoppe doesn't hide the 60 percent markup on each seltzer bottle, which costs 25 cents to fill. But he does have one secret. Paul Hoppe doesn't drink much seltzer. ''Occasionally I take a spritz,'' he admitted.</p>
        <p>The seltzer man prefers iced tea.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
