<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpt From Clinton Comments on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="T23TEXT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Geographic Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7DE133EF930A15753C1A961958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpt From Clinton Comments on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpt from Pres Clinton's remarks to National Geographic Society on global warming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following is an excerpt from remarks by President Clinton today to the National Geographic Society on the proposal for stabilizing industrialized nations' release of gases that may cause global warming, as recorded by the Federal News Service, a private transcription company:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following is an excerpt from remarks by President Clinton today to the National Geographic Society on the proposal for stabilizing industrialized nations' release of gases that may cause global warming, as recorded by the Federal News Service, a private transcription company:</p>
        <p>The vast majority of the world's climate scientists have concluded that if the countries of the world do not work together to cut the emission of greenhouse gases, then temperatures will rise and will disrupt the climate. In fact, most scientists say the process has already begun. Disruptive weather events are increasing. Disease-bearing insects are moving to areas that used to be too cold for them. Average temperatures are rising.  Glacial formations are receding.</p>
        <p>Scientists don't yet know what the precise consequences will be, but we do know enough now to know that the Industrial Age has dramatically increased greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, where they take a century or more to dissipate and that the process must be slowed, then stopped, then reduced if we want to continue our economic progress and preserve the quality of life in the United States and throughout our planet.</p>
        <p>We know what we have to do. Greenhouse gas emissions are caused mostly by the inefficient burning of coal or oil for energy. Roughly a third of these emissions come from industry, a third from transportation, a third from residential and commercial buildings. In each case, the conversion of fuel to energy use is extremely inefficient and could be made much cleaner with existing technologies or those already on the horizon, in ways that will not weaken the economy but in fact will add to our strength in new businesses and new jobs. If we do this properly, we will not jeopardize our prosperity; we will increase it.</p>
        <p>With that principle in mind, I'm announcing the instruction I am giving to our negotiators as they pursue a realistic and effective international climate change treaty. And I'm announcing a far-reaching proposal that provides flexible, market-based and cost-effective ways to achieve meaningful reductions here in America.</p>
        <p>I want to emphasize that we cannot wait until the treaty is negotiated and ratified to act. The United States has less than 5 percent of the world's people, enjoys 22 percent of the world's wealth, but emits more than 25 percent of the world's greenhouse gases. We must begin now to take out our insurance policy on the future. In the international climate negotiations the United States will pursue a comprehensive framework that includes three elements, which taken together will enable us to build a strong and robust global agreement. First, the United States proposes at Kyoto that we commit to the binding and realistic target of returning to emissions of 1990 levels between 2008 and 2012. And we should not stop there. We should commit to reduce emissions below 1990 levels and the five-year period thereafter, and we must work toward further reductions in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>The industrialized nations tried to reduce emissions to 1990 levels once before with a voluntary approach, but regrettably most of us, including especially the United States, fell short. We must find new resolve to achieve these reductions. And to do that we simply must commit to binding limits.</p>
        <p>Second, we will embrace flexible mechanisms for meeting these limits. We propose an innovative joint implementation system that allows a firm in one country to invest in a project that reduces emissions in another country and receive credit for those reductions at home. And we propose an international system of emissions trading.</p>
        <p>These innovations will cut worldwide pollution, keep costs low and help developing countries protect their environment, too, without sacrificing their economic growth.</p>
        <p>Third, both industrialized and developing countries must participate in meeting the challenge of climate change. The industrialized world must lead, but developing countries also must be engaged. The United States will not assume binding obligations unless key developing nations meaningfully participate in this effort. As President Carlos Menem stated forcefully last week when I visited him in Argentina, a global problem such as climate change requires a global answer.</p>
        <p>If the entire industrialized world reduces emissions over the next several decades, but emissions from the developing world continue to grow at their current pace, concentrations of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere will continue to climb. Developing countries have an opportunity to chart a different energy future, consistent with their growth potential and their legitimate economic aspirations. What Argentina, with dramatic projected economic growth, recognizes is true for other countries as well. We can and we must work together on this problem in a way that benefits us all.</p>
        <p>Here at home, we must move forward by unleashing the full power of free markets and technological innovations to meet the challenge of climate change. I propose a sweeping plan to provide incentives and lift roadblocks to help our companies and our citizens find new and creative ways of reducing greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
