<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toasted In China</title>
    <meta content="26DOWD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Liberties" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="918411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Liberties"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">China-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E0DA1F3BF935A15750C0A961958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toasted In China</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed column questions wisdom of Vice Pres Gore's visit to China (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Vice President stood as still as a terra cotta warrior, facing the cameras in the Great Hall of the People with a fixed smile as the Chinese tossed him bouquets of Buicks and Boeing jet deals worth $2 billion.</p>
        <p>But his eyes were darting back and forth. And there, on the periphery of his vision, was a terrifying sight: two women beneath the glistening chandeliers, coming toward him bearing glasses of champagne.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Vice President stood as still as a terra cotta warrior, facing the cameras in the Great Hall of the People with a fixed smile as the Chinese tossed him bouquets of Buicks and Boeing jet deals worth $2 billion.</p>
        <p>But his eyes were darting back and forth. And there, on the periphery of his vision, was a terrifying sight: two women beneath the glistening chandeliers, coming toward him bearing glasses of champagne.</p>
        <p>He got a Gore-in-the-headlights look, a look that this Vice President, unlike the last, more easily rattled one, rarely gets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was outfoxed, maneuvered into a cozy champagne toast at a morning business deal signing ceremony with Li Peng, the man who choreographed the Tiananmen Square massacre. It was the sort of cozy toast that got Brent Scowcroft into trouble when he snuck over not long after the momentous atrocity; the sort of cozy toast that Richard Gephardt is panting to use in a campaign ad in 2000, to suggest that the Clinton Administration's China policy prefers money to morality.</p>
        <p>The frazzled Gore crowd clearly underestimated the complexity of this trip and have been caught up in an ever-escalating series of clarifications on diplomatic issues. Yesterday they spent the evening explaining how they got Shanghaied on the toast.</p>
        <p>''You rent the room, you get the glasses,'' Ginny Terzano, Mr. Gore's press secretary, said. But even Leon Fuerth, the Vice President's relentlessly uninformative national security adviser, conceded surprise.</p>
        <p>During the marathon negotiations for the trip, the Gore team tried to control every detail and put a news blackout on anything that could seem embarrassing, even American Chamber of Commerce meetings that might include corporate donors. The toasts at Tuesday night's dinner with Mr. Li were cut out, and an Administration official lamely explained that highly unusual action by saying: ''This wasn't a banquet. It was just a large social dinner.'' But it is unthinkable that the Chinese, whose culture is so drenched in protocol, would not have wanted to toast such an honored guest at a formal dinner -- and perhaps leak the pictures, as they did with Mr. Scowcroft.</p>
        <p>Besides, Mr. Gore's relationship with Mr. Li is anything but social. Even though the Prime Minister is anxious that the visit go well, so the post-Deng leadership can show it can still get American technology and market share while doing little in return, he could not resist a public jab. He admonished Mr. Gore that the U.S. ''should play a more positive role in international affairs.''</p>
        <p>China resents America for holding up its admission to the World Trade Organization. Many Chinese are also fuming over the assertion in ''The Coming Conflict With China,'' by Richard Bernstein and Ross H. Munro, that China threatens world peace.</p>
        <p>Picnicking with the tiger is never easy. But this time it was folly. The Chinese may have tried to buy our Government. They may have tried to use espionage to penetrate the White House through the Democratic fund-raising operation. They may be engaged in a ruthless attempt to transform themselves into a military and economic superpower.</p>
        <p>And here is Al Gore reassuring his hosts that, while the Feds are investigating whether the Chinese tried to corrupt Democrats, or whether the Democrats wanted to be corrupted, this will in no way deflect the Clinton Administration from pursuing its policy of engagement with China.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore wanted it known that he had told the Chinese the Administration was taking the inquiry ''seriously'' -- to avoid an unfortunate echo of Mr. Scowcroft's secret reassurances that Tiananmen would not derail engagement with China.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Fuerth was asked about complaints that the U.S. has little to show on human rights in China, he dismissed the idea ''that it's got to be an on-the-barrelhead exchange.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore raised the issue of human rights in a way he considered ''vigorous.'' But he talked more to his hosts about the environment, whipping out his carbon dioxide emission charts for the Prime Minister. (''No, as a matter of fact they were all fascinated,'' insisted Ms. Terzano.) He opined about the start of civilization, recalling the last ice age, ''when humankind moved from hunting and gathering to agriculture'' and then to technology.</p>
        <p>He might also have pointed out that, at least in other parts of the world, it moved from hunting and gathering to agriculture to technology to human rights.</p>
        <p>Liberties</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
