<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Animal Studies, Vitamin Treatment Reverses the Effects of Emphysema</title>
    <meta content="28LUNG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="933034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Emphysema</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EED7143AF93BA15756C0A961958260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Animal Studies, Vitamin Treatment Reverses the Effects of Emphysema</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Researchers said today that they had the first evidence from animal studies that a vitamin derivative might  reverse the damage of emphysema, an incurable lung condition.</p>
        <p>Scientists at the Georgetown University School of Medicine here used retinoic acid, a derivative of vitamin A, to treat rats with emphysema-like changes in their lungs. After the treatment, they said, damaged air sacs in the lungs returned to normal size and number.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Researchers said today that they had the first evidence from animal studies that a vitamin derivative might  reverse the damage of emphysema, an incurable lung condition.</p>
        <p>Scientists at the Georgetown University School of Medicine here used retinoic acid, a derivative of vitamin A, to treat rats with emphysema-like changes in their lungs. After the treatment, they said, damaged air sacs in the lungs returned to normal size and number.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gloria De Carlo Massaro and Dr. Donald Massaro said it appeared that the treatment regenerated the adult rats' ability to produce alveoli, the small air sacs where oxygen and carbon dioxide move between the lungs and the bloodstream. The production of alveoli normally ends in childhood.</p>
        <p>''For the first time, we have been able to induce the formation of alveoli,'' Dr. Donald Massaro said in an interview. ''And we used that to induce the formation in an animal model of emphysema.''</p>
        <p>The researchers noted that it was too early to tell whether the potential treatment would apply to humans.</p>
        <p>Emphysema is a chronic lung disease that afflicts two million Americans to varying degrees, causing about 17,000 deaths each year, according to the American Lung Association. Though most cases appear in longtime smokers over age 45, about 100,000 cases represent a rare, inherited form stemming from an enzyme deficiency. Other cases result from exposure to toxic pollutants.</p>
        <p>The disease, characterized by impaired breathing, results in what has been irreversible tissue damage to the lung caused by the loss of elasticity in the alveoli, preventing the sacs from stretching and springing back normally. The loss of elasticity causes the air spaces to enlarge and impairs their ability to exchange oxygen and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Dr. Claude Lenfant, director of the National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute, which sponsored the research, said the Georgetown work was a significant first step in understanding the role of retinoic acid and similar agents in forming alveoli.</p>
        <p>''This is the first time that anyone has identified a means of reversing emphysema,'' Dr. Lenfant said. ''It could lead to the development of an agent for treating lung diseases like emphysema and bronchopulmonary dysplasia, in which the patient has insufficient alveoli to breathe efficiently.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lenfant and the Georgetown researchers cautioned that more studies were needed before anyone should consider applying the findings to people. Vitamin A and beta carotene, a more basic form of the vitamin, are already converted by the body into retinoic acid.</p>
        <p>''We caution that there is absolutely no evidence that vitamin A supplementation is useful in treating lung disorders,'' Dr. Lenfant said.</p>
        <p>The researchers said their new work, published in the June issue of the journal Nature Medicine, was an extension of earlier research they had done showing that treating normal newborn rats with retinoic acid increased the number of alveoli in their lungs.</p>
        <p>Elastin is a protein that maintains the structure and tone of the alveolar walls of the lungs. The researchers injected elastase, an enzyme that breaks down elastin, into the wind pipes of rats. When it was breathed in, the enzyme caused lung damage very similar to that seen with inherited emphysema.</p>
        <p>The treated rats were given daily injections of retinoic acid in their abdominal cavities for 12 days, and were killed and examined after the 25th day of the experiments.</p>
        <p>The researchers found that the treated rats who got the retinoic acid grew new alveoli and developed lung structure very similar to control rats that had not received either the damaging elastase or retinoic acid.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gloria Massaro said most humans stopped producing new alveoli within the first two years of life. Being able to restart production to replace damaged air sacs would change the course of emphysema, she said.</p>
        <p>''Our aim is to reverse the progress of the disease and regenerate alveoli,'' Dr. Donald Massaro said.</p>
        <p>The next step in the research will be testing the effect of retinoic acid on a specially bred mouse that is a model for emphysema, the researchers said. And they have applied to the National Institutes of Health for  money to test the approach on monkeys induced to have emphysema-like lung changes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
