<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turmoil in the Subcontinent</title>
    <meta content="06SAT4$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharif, Nawaz (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hinduism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1DF1E3DF935A35751C1A961958260" item-length="430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turmoil in the Subcontinent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says the current disheartening political turmoil in India and Pakistan shows that leaders in both countries have not yet learned to share power with others in a system of constitutionally protected checks and balances; expresses fear that crisis in India might work to advantage of Hindu chauvinist party; urges Prime Min Nawaz Sharif of Pakistan not to rely on on army support and to find of way of working with President and supreme court (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Four months after celebrating the 50th anniversary of their independence and partition, India and Pakistan are in political chaos. India's third Government in the last two years has collapsed, forcing new elections. In Pakistan, Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif has won a constitutional battle with the President and supreme court chief justice, but he had to get the army's support to prevail. The common theme in both countries is that their political leaders are not yet accustomed to sharing power with others in a system of constitutionally protected checks and balances.</p>
        <p>The political crises are disheartening because they have dampened investor confidence in India and Pakistan and set back their efforts to reach a political rapprochement. As a result, both countries are likely to continue spending too much money on arms, leaving scant resources for schools, infrastructure and public health. Also damaged is the American effort to enlist the help of two countries representing nearly one-sixth of the world's population in the global drive against nuclear proliferation, drugs and greenhouse gases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Four months after celebrating the 50th anniversary of their independence and partition, India and Pakistan are in political chaos. India's third Government in the last two years has collapsed, forcing new elections. In Pakistan, Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif has won a constitutional battle with the President and supreme court chief justice, but he had to get the army's support to prevail. The common theme in both countries is that their political leaders are not yet accustomed to sharing power with others in a system of constitutionally protected checks and balances.</p>
        <p>The political crises are disheartening because they have dampened investor confidence in India and Pakistan and set back their efforts to reach a political rapprochement. As a result, both countries are likely to continue spending too much money on arms, leaving scant resources for schools, infrastructure and public health. Also damaged is the American effort to enlist the help of two countries representing nearly one-sixth of the world's population in the global drive against nuclear proliferation, drugs and greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>But the most immediate danger is the possibility of some old demons gaining new strength. In India, the threat comes from the rising strength of the Indian People's Party, a Hindu chauvinist organization that would transform the nation's Muslims into second-class citizens. A coalition of parties representing different ideological, regional and caste groupings has tried without success to govern India. The squabbling and corruption charges that wrecked the coalition could now persuade some Indians hungering for stability to turn to the People's Party's dangerous prescriptions in the next elections, due in February.</p>
        <p>Since 1988 Pakistan has managed to keep its principal demon, the military, on the sidelines. But in the last week the army sided with Prime Minister Sharif in his battle with the supreme court chief justice and the President, who was threatening to dismiss him. The army behaved responsibly by insuring the continuation of an elected Government. Still, it is discouraging to see the army remain such a powerful arbiter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharif becomes the most powerful elected leader of Pakistan since Zulfikar Ali Bhutto, who was ousted in a military coup and executed two decades ago. History should teach Mr. Sharif not to capitalize on his triumph and turn dictatorial. His main challenges will be to work with his domestic adversaries and keep the army out of politics.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
