<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmental Groups Say Gore Has Not Measured Up to the Job</title>
    <meta content="22GORE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="938984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">League of Conservation Voters</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Information Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callahan, Deb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clapp, Philip E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E5D8113EF931A15755C0A961958260" item-length="1713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmental Groups Say Gore Has Not Measured Up to the Job</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, one of environmental movement's steadiest allies, is under attack from major conservation groups in unlikely turn that carries important implications for environmental policy as well as Presidential politics; groups say they are frustrated, even angry, that, in their view, Gore has failed to exert strong influence on two of environmental movement's top priorities this year: toughening air pollution standards, and negotiating deep cuts in worldwide emissions of greenhouse gases; although environmentalists form core of Gore's political base, organizations that have sided with Gore throughout his public career are now using extraordinarily blunt langauge to warn that 'green' voters might abandon him in Democratic primaries in 2000 unless he delivers now these crucial issues; Gore defends his environmental record; among Gore's critics are Deb Callahan of League of Conservation Voters, and Philip E Clapp of Environmental Information Center; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, one of the environmental movement's steadiest allies, is under attack from major conservation groups in an unlikely turn that carries important implications for environmental policy as well as Presidential politics.</p>
        <p>The groups say they are frustrated, even angry, that, in their view, Mr. Gore has failed to exert strong influence on two of the environmental movement's top priorities this year: toughening air pollution standards and negotiating deep cuts in worldwide emissions of greenhouse gases. In the next few days, President Clinton, who defers to Mr. Gore on most environmental matters, is expected to spell out his positions on both questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore, one of the environmental movement's steadiest allies, is under attack from major conservation groups in an unlikely turn that carries important implications for environmental policy as well as Presidential politics.</p>
        <p>The groups say they are frustrated, even angry, that, in their view, Mr. Gore has failed to exert strong influence on two of the environmental movement's top priorities this year: toughening air pollution standards and negotiating deep cuts in worldwide emissions of greenhouse gases. In the next few days, President Clinton, who defers to Mr. Gore on most environmental matters, is expected to spell out his positions on both questions.</p>
        <p>Although environmentalists form the core of Mr. Gore's political base, organizations that have sided with the Vice President throughout his public career are now using extraordinarily blunt language to warn that ''green'' voters might abandon him in the Democratic primaries in  2000 unless he delivers now on these crucial issues.</p>
        <p>Top environmental lobbyists have even met with Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House minority leader who is a leading rival for the Democratic nomination, urging him to demand that the White House display more leadership on their issues.</p>
        <p>The environment is but one issue in which Mr. Gore's positions and influence in the White House will draw intensified attention as he gears up to run for President.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has for years also  scored politically on other issues that are very much in the news now, like telecommunications policy, anti-tobacco measures, television ratings, biomedical ethics and censorship on the Internet. Now that many of these issues have become particularly contentious, Mr. Gore may well be forced to play a more public role in the debates over them.</p>
        <p>In an interview late Friday, Mr. Gore defended his environmental record and said that his job demanded that he work behind the scenes. ''Everybody knows my views,'' he said. ''But I am not going to publicly try to back the President into a corner. I never have done that, and I never will.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore acknowledged that the pressure from environmental groups had been intense in recent weeks.  The Sierra Club has begun television advertising campaigns in early primary states, urging Mr. Clinton and Mr. Gore to ''stand up to the special interests.''</p>
        <p>Environmental groups have distributed a polemic to editorial writers that derides remarks by the President and the Vice President on global warming as ''hot air.''</p>
        <p>And in a letter last week on the air standards, 84 environmental and health groups wrote, ''We are deeply disturbed and perplexed by the apparent lack of visible and vocal support from the White House for the proposed new standards.''</p>
        <p>''What we need and what we expect is leadership,'' said Deb Callahan, president of the League of Conservation Voters, a political action committee that stands out from other environmental groups because it openly endorses candidates. ''Not to speak out and not to influence the President is not leadership. It is a bit perplexing that he would step back from providing this leadership.'' Ms. Callahan worked for Mr. Gore's Presidential campaign in 1988.</p>
        <p>Philip E. Clapp, president of the Environmental Information Center, a relatively new but increasingly influential advocacy group, put it this way: ''The failure of the White House to provide any leadership on the clean air standards and on climate change raises real questions about what real environmental progress Vice President Gore can point to in claiming the mantle of the environmental candidate in the year 2000.''</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Gore did not seem distressed by the barrage of criticism. ''I quite understand why some group that feels passionately would decide to pull out all the stops to try to gain leverage in any way they can,'' he said. ''And that is their job. My job is not to publicly argue for a specific policy that has not yet been formally recommended to the President and take options away from him.''</p>
        <p>But as the complaints about what one environmentalist called ''Al Gore's silent spring'' have intensified, the Vice President has scrambled in the last two days to reassure environmental leaders privately. And his aides have begun to signal that Mr. Gore was weighing in behind the scenes for a decision on clean air standards that would satisfy the environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Carol M. Browner, the E.P.A. Administrator, said in an interview:  ''There is no doubt in my mind that the Vice President is in there doing what he has done on many difficult issues.</p>
        <p>''He is moving the ball,'' she said, ''providing the leadership, making the case for strong public health protection.'' For months, Ms. Browner advocated tougher air quality rules without a word in her defense from the White House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers accused his newfound critics of an orchestrated drive to prod him even further on their issues. ''I guess the problem is, you always hurt the one you love,'' said Kathleen McGinty, the senior environmental aide at the White House. ''The environmentalists have a strategy here to send a message to us because they know the Vice President does care about what they say.''</p>
        <p>The Administration's proposals on air quality and global warming have come under intense criticism in Congress and from major industries, especially oil, coal and car companies, and White House economic advisers are battling with environmental officials over how aggressive a stance to take.</p>
        <p>Some environmental leaders accused Mr. Gore of taking his environmental support for granted so he can make overtures to business and labor interests that could help him raise millions of dollars to compete in the Democratic primaries.</p>
        <p>This is not the first time that environmentalists have criticized Mr. Gore for wavering on their issues. But never before has the message been delivered so bluntly. Administration officials are bracing for demonstrators next week when the President and Vice President are in New York to meet with world leaders for a conference on climate change.</p>
        <p>And no longer is it only Republicans who are tearing apart copies of Mr. Gore's book on the environment, ''Earth in the Balance.'' Now, environmental groups are distributing passages from the book as evidence of the Vice President's failure to make progress on the environment.</p>
        <p>While environmentalists also criticize the Administration's positions on endangered species issues, the regulation of toxic water pollution from paper mills and a forest service plan for continued logging in the Tongass National Forest, the debate has become feverish as two of the environmentalists' top priorities -- clean air standards and global warming -- have come before the White House.  The Administration is under a court order to decide within a month how tightly to control emissions of smog and soot, and the White House's economic advisers, heeding pleas from industry, have been urging the Environmental Protection Agency to ease its earlier proposals.</p>
        <p>The other pending environmental issue, strengthening the treaty on climate change, will be at the forefront at a United Nations conference in New York beginning on Monday. Signatories to the treaty, written five years ago in Rio de Janeiro, are trying to negotiate by year-end a tougher version setting mandatory limits on the emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases, which are implicated in global warming and are continuing to rise. But the United States has refused so far to commit to a timetable for reducing greenhouse gases and has signaled that some other countries'  targets may be too ambitious.</p>
        <p>The Natural Resources Defense Council, one group joining in the chorus for stronger actions on climate change, has bought newspaper advertisements to that effect on the eve of the United Nations meeting.</p>
        <p>But John Adams, the head of the group, spoke sympathetically of Mr. Gore in an interview. ''I know people are angry and are upset and they want to win here, but I want to have a relationship based on the total record,'' he said. ''This is a good man who cares about the environment -- and he is a good man to have on our side.''</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists suggested that part of Mr. Gore's calculation was to win favor from Mayors Richard M. Daley of Chicago and Dennis W. Archer of Detroit and other influential Democrats who strongly oppose tightening air standards and could be important allies in the Presidential primaries. Potential Republican rivals -- Govs. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey, George E. Pataki of New York and William F. Weld of Massachusetts -- are already speaking out for stronger clean air standards.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Gore, party strategists say, cannot appear too willing to support environmental policies with no concern about the economic consequences. Linda DiVall, a Republican pollster, said the Democrats could not afford to be ''too hard on business at the risk of reducing job growth -- that's the conundrum they're in.''</p>
        <p>Ronald Klain, Mr. Gore's chief of staff, rejected those criticisms. ''They should have a little faith,'' he said of the environmental groups. ''His views on the environment have never been about votes or having things in his pocket, but about an agenda he deeply and personally believes in.''</p>
        <p>Even a senior aide to Mr. Gephardt, speaking on the condition that he not be identified, said the Vice President might well survive the onslaught from environmentalists. ''They may be downplaying their expectations,'' the adviser said of calculations in the White House, ''so Gore can claim he saved the day'' for the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>Jerry Jasinowski, president of the National Association of Manufacturers, said Mr. Gore could use these looming environmental decisions to repair his relationship with businesses. ''He's got a poor relationship with the business community on all of these regulatory issues,'' he said. The environmental groups are worried, he said, because ''if they lose Gore, they don't have anyone left.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
