<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Figures Show Budget Deficit Fast Shrinking</title>
    <meta content="21BUDG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982229"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Treasury Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05EED9173EF932A15751C1A961958260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Figures Show Budget Deficit Fast Shrinking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Treasury Department reports Government ran deficit of $53.3 billion in first two months of fiscal 1998, down from $77.7 billion in year-earlier period; quicker-than-expected drop in deficit means budget could be in balance or even show surplus this year; House Speaker Newt Gingrich suggests Pres Clinton speed up plan to balance budget; Administration responds coolly (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Government has released figures showing that the Federal budget deficit is falling much faster than official forecasts had reported, providing the first clear evidence that the budget could be balanced in this fiscal year or even show a surplus.</p>
        <p>The figures prompted Speaker Newt Gingrich to suggest today that President Clinton speed up the plan to balance the Federal budget.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Government has released figures showing that the Federal budget deficit is falling much faster than official forecasts had reported, providing the first clear evidence that the budget could be balanced in this fiscal year or even show a surplus.</p>
        <p>The figures prompted Speaker Newt Gingrich to suggest today that President Clinton speed up the plan to balance the Federal budget.</p>
        <p>''If the President could come into the State of the Union address and propose a balanced budget by 1999, three years ahead of schedule, we'd be very responsive,'' Mr. Gingrich said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>The White House greeted Mr. Gingrich's trial balloon coolly.</p>
        <p>''The best way for us to reach a balanced budget sooner than expected is to maintain the fiscal discipline of the last five years, not to spend money we don't have yet,'' said Gene Sperling, who heads the National Economic Council.</p>
        <p>President Clinton is likely to propose some small tax cuts in his budget proposals next month. They include providing incentives to reduce emissions of gases that cause global warming, and possibly tax cuts to promote greater access to child care.</p>
        <p>The Administration is still considering how it would deal with the appearance of any large budget surpluses, and officials said that Mr. Clinton might be ready to provide an outline of his philosophy for dealing with such a situation in his State of the Union Message, also next month.</p>
        <p>The Administration is not considering any plans for a large tax cut next year.</p>
        <p>Though the Government's figures, released on Friday, are only early indicators of the nation's fiscal health, they are sure to intensify planning at the White House and in Congress for what to do if the Government finds itself with money left over at the end of the fiscal year.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration continues to expect the deficit for the year ending next Sept. 30 to be higher than the $23 billion deficit the Government ran up in the fiscal year that ended on Sept. 30. Under the schedule laid out in the balanced-budget legislation agreed to by the Administration and the Republican leadership this year, the budget would not be balanced until 2002.</p>
        <p>The drive to eliminate the deficit could still be imperiled by any weakening of the economy or a reversal of a surprising surge in tax revenues. But the figures showed that for October and November, the first two months of the current fiscal year, the deficit was $24.4 billion lower than in the same period last year.</p>
        <p>If the trend of the first two months continues, analysts said, there could be a big surplus.</p>
        <p>Republicans have been pushing for tax cuts and more spending on the military. Democrats are talking about more spending on education and health programs. Lawmakers of both parties are looking at proposals to spend more on highways and at using any surplus to shore up Social Security and Medicare.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich said today that his priorities would be to achieve and maintain a balanced budget, then apply up to $30 billion a year toward the national debt. The Speaker said he would favor using any remaining surplus for an annual tax cut and to increase financing for science, transportation and national defense. He said he was still committed to a tax cut next year, staying within the balanced budget framework, by deferring certain spending.</p>
        <p>For the first two months of this fiscal year, the Government ran a deficit of $53.3 billion, compared with $77.7 billion in the same period last year, the Treasury Department said. Big deficits in certain times of the year are offset during periods of heavy tax collection, particularly in April and September.</p>
        <p>The results reflected both tax revenues that were greater than those in the same period last year and expenditures that were lower.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
