<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Students Hear Clinton Tell Of Priorities For the Fall</title>
    <meta content="Y10CLI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="956520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Security (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E2DC1539F933A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="1068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Students Hear Clinton Tell Of Priorities For the Fall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton outlines broad agenda for rest of year, on issues from expanding trade to tightening pollution controls to passing wide-ranging laws to restrict tobacco; photo during appearance at American University; also threatens to direct glare of public light toward senators who would block campaign finance reform; assures student audience on future of Social Security and lavishly praises recent Federal budget-balancing agreement (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Declaring the economic and political drag of budget deficits to be a thing of the past, President Clinton moved on today to a broad agenda for the rest of the year, trying to summon support for a grab bag of causes from expanding trade to tightening pollution controls to passing wide-reaching laws to restrict tobacco.</p>
        <p>Speaking to his second audience of students in two days, Mr. Clinton again called on Congress to support his plan for new national tests measured against voluntary standards in reading and math.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Declaring the economic and political drag of budget deficits to be a thing of the past, President Clinton moved on today to a broad agenda for the rest of the year, trying to summon support for a grab bag of causes from expanding trade to tightening pollution controls to passing wide-reaching laws to restrict tobacco.</p>
        <p>Speaking to his second audience of students in two days, Mr. Clinton again called on Congress to support his plan for new national tests measured against voluntary standards in reading and math.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also threatened today to direct ''the full glare of public light'' toward any senators who try to block legislation to tighten campaign finance laws. But even as he spoke this afternoon about the peril of money in politics and a Senate committee sharply questioned a former top Democratic official about fund-raising, Mr. Clinton planned to attend two dinners tonight to raise $550,000 for the Democratic National Committee.</p>
        <p>Addressing the students and faculty of American University here, Mr. Clinton invoked John F. Kennedy's vision of a world free from the cold war, articulated 34 years ago at the same university.</p>
        <p>''It is up to you and to me and to our fellow Americans to imagine what the 21st century will be, and then to do what is necessary to make that vision a reality for all our people,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton addressed topics as open-ended as whether the rush of technology could leave citizens ''each with our own Web page, but linked by few human bonds of community.'' But he also raised more specific matters, urging for the first time in weeks that his nominee for Ambassador to Mexico, William F. Weld, receive a hearing before the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton assured his college audience that Social Security would survive to benefit them, and pledged in the next three months to appoint members of a new commission to study Medicare. He also called on Congress to take this ''historic opportunity'' to pass ''sweeping legislation that focuses first and foremost on reducing smoking among young people.''</p>
        <p>The President was raucously received by some 4,000 students and faculty members packed into a basketball gymnasium, and flashbulbs pulsed from the bleachers throughout his 41-minute address. Like most of the President's other major addresses this year, the speech today divided into the triad of ''opportunity, responsibility, community, '' familiar from his 1996 campaign.</p>
        <p>One senior aide billed the address, which Mr. Clinton worked on in the last two weeks of his vacation, as a ''back to work, back to school, America's back'' speech. And Mr. Clinton provided a remarkably upbeat assessment of the nation's health, pointing to low inflation and unemployment as the products of an economy so robust that ''many of our poorest urban and rural communities are in a springtime of renewal.''</p>
        <p>He lavishly praised the recent agreement to balance the budget by 2002.</p>
        <p>''Now, after years in which the deficit dominated our politics and dampened our economy, America finally has lifted that burden from the next generation,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''After years in which the two parties seemed often as tired and trapped as punch-drunk fighters in a ring getting smaller and smaller, finally we found a way for Democrats and Republicans to work together for the national interest.''</p>
        <p>After he turned to foreign policy, however, Mr. Clinton sounded slightly defensive as he described his plans to meet here later this fall with President Jiang Zemin of China. He called the meeting ''a chance for us to address candidly and face-to-face our differences on issues like human rights and religious freedom.''</p>
        <p>He said that ''sitting down together across the table is far more likely to produce progress than pointing fingers across the Pacific.''</p>
        <p>Linking free trade with the growth of democracy, Mr. Clinton called for expanded trade with Asia and other parts of the world. On Wednesday he plans to announce a campaign to persuade Congress to increase his powers to negotiate trade agreements.</p>
        <p>For the first time since his address to the United Nations on June 26, Mr. Clinton returned to the subject of global climate change. He is trying to build public support for reducing emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases before a summit on climate change in December in Japan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton warned that, if it is not checked, climate change could cause flooding in southern Florida and Louisiana over the next 50 years, and he  said Americans could take cost-free steps to cut emissions of gases that contribute to climatic warming.</p>
        <p>''We could reduce them 20 percent tomorrow with technology that is already available at no cost if we just changed the way we do things,'' Mr. Clinton said, but offering no specific suggestions.</p>
        <p>His aides said today that they could not determine the source of his 20 percent figure, but that he was referring to measures like much more widespread use of refrigerators and light bulbs that require less electricity.</p>
        <p>While the Senate Governmental Affairs Committee continued today to investigate the price of access to politicians, including the President, Mr. Clinton turned that subject around, saying the primary cause of the mounting cost of campaigns was ''the cost of access to you, the voters.'' He called for free or reduced advertising time for politicians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton repeated his support for campaign finance legislation sponsored by Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, and Senator Russell D. Feingold, Democrat of Wisconsin, saying, ''Every year I have been President, I have supported a good campaign finance reform bill.''</p>
        <p>Under the McCain-Feingold bill, much of the money Mr. Clinton planned to raise at the events tonight -- the unlimited donations to parties classified as ''soft money'' -- would be illegal. Michael D. McCurry, the White House press secretary, wearily repeated today that the Democrats would not ''unilaterally disarm'' by abandoning soft money.</p>
        <p>''We'll continue to try to change the rules even as we try to compete effectively under the rules,'' Mr. McCurry said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
