<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Miso Goes Beyond Japanese Cooking</title>
    <meta content="03MISO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Miso (Soybean Paste)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soups</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soups</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970903T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E5DC1730F930A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="2422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Miso Goes Beyond Japanese Cooking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AMANDA HESSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing popularity of miso discussed; miso, fermented soybean paste, is as ubiquitous in Japan as olive oil is in Mediterranean; with miso market showing signs of growth in United States, increasing number of chefs and food-store owners are making miso better known in all its guises; miso-shiru, soup that is drunk for breakfast, lunch or dinner in Japan, is most common use of miso, but it can also be used as flavoring; some cooks comment; recipes; list of miso sources; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORKERS have embraced the corner sushi bar -- as well as the loftier Japanese restaurants -- so vigorously that you'd think few big mysteries about Japanese cuisine could remain. But many Westerners seem to know almost nothing about miso, a fermented soybean paste as ubiquitous in Japan as olive oil is in the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>Now, with the miso market showing signs of growth in the United States, an increasing number of chefs and food-store owners are making miso better known in all its guises.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORKERS have embraced the corner sushi bar -- as well as the loftier Japanese restaurants -- so vigorously that you'd think few big mysteries about Japanese cuisine could remain. But many Westerners seem to know almost nothing about miso, a fermented soybean paste as ubiquitous in Japan as olive oil is in the Mediterranean.</p>
        <p>Now, with the miso market showing signs of growth in the United States, an increasing number of chefs and food-store owners are making miso better known in all its guises.</p>
        <p>It's true that miso-shiru, a soup that is drunk for breakfast, lunch or dinner in Japan, is the most common use of miso. But as Nora Pouillon, the chef and owner of Asia Nora, an organic Asian restaurant in Washington, explains, it can also be used as a flavoring, like mustard.</p>
        <p>''We always add it,'' Ms. Pouillon said, ''a touch here, a touch there. I don't even think about it.''</p>
        <p>Edwyn Ferrari, the kitchen manager at Nobu, the Japanese restaurant in TriBeCa, also emphasized miso's importance. ''It's in everything we do,'' he said. ''We use it as a marinade, as a condiment, in our soups. We use it as a sauce, too.''</p>
        <p>In the restaurant, miso tends to be treated more as a food than as a seasoning like soy sauce. Yet, because misos vary so greatly in flavor and intensity, Mr. Ferrari said, the kitchen at Nobu likes to take advantage of this variety to control the taste of a dish.</p>
        <p>Unlike its soy relative tofu, miso alone leaves a rather distinct imprint on the taste memory: this is intense, salty stuff. Its flavor can range from light and nutty to winy, beefy and robust, but invariably it has a sweet, salty base. In cooking, miso is used in small quantities so as not to overwhelm a dish. Although it is salty, it diminishes, or eliminates, the need to add salt alone, while adding a complex, rich flavor to an array of dishes.</p>
        <p>In Japan, said Elizabeth Andoh, a cookbook author and cooking teacher based in Tokyo, miso is used primarily as a thickener for soups and stews; a seasoning for sauces, meats and fish pastes, and a marinade for fish and vegetables. It is an essential part of the dish dengaku, in which skewered vegetables or tofu are grilled and then spread with a miso sauce. Miso is sometimes used for pickling, as well, its salt working as a powerful preservative.</p>
        <p>In the United States, miso is found in pure Japanese dishes and more loosely in fusion cooking, as East meets West. It finds its way into salad dressings, dipping sauces, mashed potatoes, even mayonnaise.</p>
        <p>At Nobu, black cod is rubbed with miso and marinated for several days to draw out the oils and lightly preserve the fish before it is broiled, forming a dark caramelized crust on the fish. Miso is also added to the tempura sauce at Nobu, along with sugar, yuzu citron juice and the Japanese wines mirin and sake, and it is thickened with egg yolks for a sauce called tama miso, for broiled fish.</p>
        <p>Nina Simonds, an author of several books on Chinese cooking, believes that miso is not as exotic a food as it once was. ''Now, it's mainstream, really,'' she said. And because it is more readily available in supermarkets, she added, ''people are trying to figure out what to do with it.''</p>
        <p>Annemarie Colbin, the founder of the Natural Gourmet Cookery School in Chelsea, says she likes to use miso as a spread for crackers. And she takes it along when she travels. ''Instead of coffee, you just bring miso and mix it with hot water in the morning,'' she said. ''It's a real pick-me-up.''</p>
        <p>When macrobiotics gained popularity in the 1960's, miso found a following among members of the vegetarian crowd, who savor it not only for its taste, but also for its protein value. Miso can have as much as twice the protein of tofu.</p>
        <p>''It brings a savory flavor to vegetarian meals that is very hard to find,'' said William Shurtleff, the co-author with Akiko Aoyagi of ''The Book of Miso'' (Ten Speed Press, 1983). ''Miso provides a bridge between a steak and a vegetarian diet.''</p>
        <p>It is often said that miso is to soybeans what cheese is to milk. Fermenting soybeans to make miso is as subtle a process as making cheese. But when it is made the traditional way, miso begins not with soybeans (which come later in the process) but grains, usually rice or barley, which are inoculated with the mold spore Aspergillus oryzae. These molded grains, or koji, are combined with cooked soybeans and sea salt and packed into wooden barrels, the lids weighted with rocks, and then allowed to ferment and age for 3 to 36 months, depending on the type of miso.</p>
        <p>The length of time and temperature at which miso is aged, the proportion of soybeans to koji and the type of grain used all have a striking effect on the resulting miso. As with cheese making, these small differences produce myriad varieties. A miso made with minimal salt, for example, and aged for just a few months will be sweet and light in color, whereas a miso made with a high proportion of salt and aged for as long as two years will be darker and richer in flavor.</p>
        <p>A trip to the miso section of a Japanese market can be dizzying, given the spectrum of choices. At Katagiri &amp; Company, on the Upper East Side, there are more than 20.</p>
        <p>Misos may range from a lovely cream-colored sauce the consistency of beurre blanc to deep cocoa paste as thick as wet soil. It can be chunky or smooth, like peanut butter, and preferences among miso consumers are generally just as polar.</p>
        <p>There are three basic varieties of miso: rice, barley and pure soybean. Within each of these varieties are several types labeled according to flavor and color. As a general rule, lighter misos are sweeter and younger and contain less salt; darker misos are thicker and saltier and have been aged longer. Rice miso, or kome miso, begins with sweet white (shiro miso) and progresses along the color-age spectrum to mellow white (shiro koji miso) to light yellow (shinshu miso) to sweet red (edo miso) to red (aka miso).</p>
        <p>Barley miso, or mugi miso, is aged longer than most rice misos and has just two varieties, mellow barley and regular barley. Pure soybean miso is most commonly found in the form of the highly esteemed hatcho miso, which is aged for two to three years to develop its distinctively deep sweetness and sharp flavor. Other special varieties are available, including namemisos, or finger-lickin' misos, and recent Western inventions, like chickpea miso, an American creation, and lentil miso, developed in the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>Recipes for miso evolved from a Chinese soy product called chiang, which was introduced to Japan during the seventh century. Miso was made at home and in small workshops run by miso masters, who spent a lifetime perfecting their craft. The soybeans were cooked in large iron cauldrons heated with wood and then crushed underfoot as grapes once were for wine. Until recently, miso recipes varied from region to region, as well as between families and social classes. Once a young woman was married, she was supposed to preserve her family's recipe by making it at home.</p>
        <p>Large-scale production of miso in Japan has all but wiped out the traditional producers. In fact, you are more likely to find artisanal versions from producers in the United States, a few of whom over recent years have made serious efforts to preserve the miso tradition.</p>
        <p>Among them is the American Miso Company of Rutherfordton, N.C., a company that has grown 15 percent a year over the last 10 years, said Barry Evans, its president. Emulating its commercial forebears, the company's Miso Master brand uses organic soybeans and grains and sea salt (from the Bay of Biscay off the coast of France) and ages its long-term misos in cypress and redwood barrels.</p>
        <p>Mr. Evans believes that despite its saltiness, organic miso is a very healthful food. He said that miso ''is regarded by most people in the health food industry to be the most supremely healthy product.''</p>
        <p>Most people in Japan believe that, too. There, miso soup maintains a reputation as a cure-all, much like chicken soup is to Westerners.</p>
        <p>Soy products are generally said to contain chemicals that inhibit cancer growth, lower the risk of heart disease and reduce menopausal symptoms. Dr. Mark Messina, a nutritionist and a former program director at the National Cancer Institute, said, ''They're a high-quality protein, they're low in saturated fat, they're cholesterol free.'' He also said they were one of the few good plant sources of linolenic acid, an omega-3 fatty acid that is believed to lower the risk of heart disease and to strengthen the immune system.</p>
        <p>Miso is also writhing with good microorganisms that aid digestion and the assimilation of other foods in the body. Unfortunately, the pasteurization that most commercial miso undergoes destroys many of the beneficial bacteria and enzymes. Organic and traditional miso is not pasteurized.</p>
        <p>Dana Jacobi, the author of ''Soy!'' (Prima, 1996), advised that when unpasteurized miso is used in cooking, ''it should be stirred in at the end: heat it but don't let it boil.''</p>
        <p>The Package Says a Lot</p>
        <p>MISO is most often sold in 8-ounce or 16-ounce portions, packaged in sealed plastic bags, plastic tubs or glass jars. A plastic bag is a sure sign that the miso has been pasteurized, because unpasteurized miso continues to ferment and produce carbon dioxide, which would expand and possibly explode the packaging. Because of miso's high salt content, it will last for several months in a refrigerator, but it should always be spooned out of the container with a clean utensil to prevent destructive bacteria from invading the paste.</p>
        <p>If you are experimenting with miso for the first time, the cookbook author Dana Jacobi suggests trying three different kinds: a white rice and a red rice miso and either a hatcho (pure soybean) or a mugi (barley) miso.</p>
        <p>Misos labeled ''miso dashi iri'' include dashi, or broth, and are meant for making miso soup. In addition to salt, some misos contain monosodium glutamate and preservatives. The term ''gen-en'' means the misos are low in sodium; those labeled ''shio hikaeme'' have a moderate sodium content.</p>
        <p>Following are sources for misos.</p>
        <p>THE HEALTH NUTS -- 1208 Second Avenue (65th Street), (212) 593-0116; 835 Second Avenue (44th Street), (212) 490-2979; 2141 Broadway (75th Street), (212) 724-1972, and 2611 Broadway (98th Street), (212) 678-0054.</p>
        <p>INTEGRAL YOGA NATURAL FOODS -- 229 West 13th Street, (212) 243-2642.</p>
        <p>KATAGIRI &amp; COMPANY -- 224 East 59th Street, (212) 755-3566.</p>
        <p>WHOLE FOODS MARKET INC. -- 2421 Broadway (89th Street), (212) 874-4000.</p>
        <p>THE SOUTH RIVER MISO COMPANY -- South River Farm, Conway, Mass. 01341, (413) 369-4057 or fax (413) 369-4299.</p>
        <p>NATURAL LIFESTYLE SUPPLIES -- Asheville, N.C., (800) 752-2775 (it sells Miso Master, Onozaki, Mitoku and South River misos, all of which are traditionally made and organic).</p>
        <p>Nasu Miso (Eggplant With Miso)</p>
        <p>Adapted from Nobu restaurant</p>
        <p>Total time: 35 minutes</p>
        <p>For den miso:</p>
        <p>3/8 cup sweet white miso</p>
        <p>1/4 cup sugar</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons sake</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons mirin.</p>
        <p>For the eggplant:</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons vegetable oil</p>
        <p>4 medium Japanese eggplants, halved lengthwise</p>
        <p>Toasted sesame seeds.</p>
        <p>1. Heat miso, sugar, sake and mirin in small saucepan over moderate heat. Simmer 5 minutes, stirring constantly. Remove from heat.</p>
        <p>2. In large skillet, heat 3 tablespoons oil over medium-high heat. Add half the eggplant, and saute on both sides for 8 to 10 minutes, until tender and brown. Remove to plate. Repeat with rest of oil and eggplant.</p>
        <p>3. Lay eggplants, cut side up, on a serving plate. Spoon over den miso, and sprinkle with sesame seeds.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 340 calories, 25 grams fat, 0 milligrams cholesterol, 945 milligrams sodium, 4 grams protein, 25 grams carbohydrate.</p>
        <p>Miso Glazed Carrots</p>
        <p>Adapted from ''Soy!'' (Prima, 1996), by Dana Jacobi</p>
        <p>Total time: 35 minutes</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon cold-pressed sesame oil</p>
        <p>1/2 cup finely chopped onion</p>
        <p>3 cups carrots, in  1/2-inch slices</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon red miso</p>
        <p>3/4 cup vegetable broth or water</p>
        <p>2 teaspoons grated orange zest</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon grated ginger root</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon roasted sesame oil</p>
        <p>Salt and ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. In medium, heavy skillet, heat sesame oil over medium-high heat. Add onion and carrots. Cook, stirring occasionally, about 6 minutes, until soft on edges but not brown.</p>
        <p>2. In small bowl, cream miso with  1/4 cup broth. Stir this mixture, remaining broth, orange zest and ginger into carrots and onions. Reduce heat, and simmer for 12 to 15 minutes, until liquid is reduced to a glaze and carrots are crisp-tender.</p>
        <p>3. Stir in roasted sesame oil. Season to taste with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 110 calories, 4 grams fat, 0 milligrams cholesterol, 250 milligrams sodium (before salting), 2 grams protein, 15 grams carbohydrate.</p>
        <p>Nina Simonds's Broiled Halibut With Miso Glaze</p>
        <p>Time: 15 minutes, plus 30 minutes marinating</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon grated ginger</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons mirin</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons mellow white miso</p>
        <p>Vegetable oil for brushing pan</p>
        <p>1  3/4-pound halibut fillet, cut into four pieces.</p>
        <p>1. In small bowl, combine ginger, mirin and miso, and mix until smooth. Rub on flesh side of fish pieces. Marinate 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Heat broiler. Brush broiling pan with oil. Lay fish in pan, skin side down, and broil for 7 to 9 minutes, until flesh flakes and glaze bubbles and browns. Serve with steamed sticky rice and sauteed greens.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 125 calories, 3 grams fat, 25 milligrams cholesterol, 515 milligrams sodium, 20 grams protein, 4 grams carbohydrate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
