<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Perfect Setting Isn't For Electric Car Boom</title>
    <meta content="23ELEC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Orcas Island Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="924851"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Orcas Island Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Vehicles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Juan Islands (Washington State)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orcas Power &amp; Light Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Carey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/San Juan Islands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E5D8123EF930A15757C0A961958260" item-length="1147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Perfect Setting Isn't For Electric Car Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Carey</byline>
      <dateline>ORCAS ISLAND, Wash., April 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Orcas Power and Light Co, which has been testing electric cars on San Juan Islands of Washington State since 1991, says electric cars have not caught on with residents because of high initial cost and low range of cars; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Much earlier than most, islanders here have tasted the future of the car, and in some ways it is as sweet as the boosters of electric vehicles promised.</p>
        <p>They are quiet, clean, cheap to run; they even project a certain 21st-century Jetsons panache when they zip mutely into a special spot marked ''Electric Vehicle Recharge Space'' at the main island supermarket for a plugged-in pick-me-up. What with mild winters, expensive gasoline and environmentally minded residents, this would seem to be the ideal setting for battery-powered cars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Much earlier than most, islanders here have tasted the future of the car, and in some ways it is as sweet as the boosters of electric vehicles promised.</p>
        <p>They are quiet, clean, cheap to run; they even project a certain 21st-century Jetsons panache when they zip mutely into a special spot marked ''Electric Vehicle Recharge Space'' at the main island supermarket for a plugged-in pick-me-up. What with mild winters, expensive gasoline and environmentally minded residents, this would seem to be the ideal setting for battery-powered cars.</p>
        <p>But even here in the San Juan Islands -- which, local officials calculate, have the highest ratio of electric cars to traditional ones in the country -- the verdict is that such cars remain a thing of the future.</p>
        <p>''There's a long way to go until we see a large number of cars like this coming down the road,'' said Doug Bechtel, general manager of the Orcas Power and Light Company, as its Solectria Force hummed along like an oversized sewing machine.</p>
        <p>The slow pace of change is not for lack of trying. Orcas Power and Light volunteered in 1991 to become part of a Federal program to test electric cars in the field and spread information about them. It now calculates that San Juan County, with its 20 major islands and 11,000 people, has 1 electric vehicle for every 750 non-commercial vehicles powered by fossil fuels, a dozen in all.</p>
        <p>In 1993, the utility also became the first in the country to set up permanent chargers in public spots for electric drivers, with five now in place and two more to come.</p>
        <p>For all the efforts by the power company and local enthusiasts, the push for electric cars here has hit the same kind of wall encountered by proponents around the country. With the cars' range still short and prices still high -- double to triple the cost of similar gas-run cars -- the technology just is not quite there yet.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation began leasing its EV1 electric car last December with great hoopla, but only to hand-picked customers in Arizona and Southern California who said they were willing to work with limitations like its 90-mile range. And smog-conscious California, which had originally required that 2 percent of 1998 model cars produce zero emissions, has backed off, though it is still insisting on 10 percent zero emissions for the year 2003.</p>
        <p>Researchers are exploring the promising use of fuel cells to power cars -- on Monday, the Ford Motor Company announced plans to build a prototype -- and many believe future cars will run on a hybrid system of electric power and some other fuel. But that will not come about for years.</p>
        <p>On their own small scale, the San Juans, a cluster of exquisite emerald-and-rock peaks jutting between the Washington State mainland and Vancouver Island, mirror that broader picture.</p>
        <p>The enthusiasm of pioneers like Ward Phillips, an energy consultant on San Juan Island who has an electric car, an electric boat, an electric truck and even a fiberglass electric horse used in parades, has not flagged. But that enthusiasm has yet to spread from a dozen believers to the skeptical masses.</p>
        <p>The basic technology exists to give an electric car the range of a gasoline-driven one, Mr. Phillips said, but at such expense that he compared the car's current awkward state to early computers. ''The early computer was a monster -- it cost a million dollars and filled a gym,'' he said. ''We're at that same point.''</p>
        <p>The problem, say the islanders who have turned down the cars, is not the cars' performance but their economics, and the nagging anxiety about running out of electricity. As Mr. Bechtel figures it, gas on the island costs about $1.60 a gallon, or about 4 cents a mile. The electricity to run a car costs as little as a penny a mile, and the need for maintenance is greatly reduced -- except that the car's batteries need to be replaced every 5,000 to 7,000 miles, and cost $500 and $700, adding another 10 cents a mile. Not to mention the cost of the cars.</p>
        <p>The power company has often lent its two electric cars to San Juan officials and residents in hopes of winning them over, Mr. Bechtel said. But after an initial glee at the peculiarities of zero-emission driving, the response is almost always this, he said: ''We'll think about it.''</p>
        <p>That reluctance has been particularly discouraging, he said, because if the cars make sense anywhere, they do on the San Juans, where many residents have an ''island'' car for trips around home and a ''mainland'' car for longer journeys. The electric vehicles would seem like ideal island cars, Mr. Bechtel said, and there are many among the 3,000 people of Orcas Island who could afford them.</p>
        <p>''Maybe when they come out with an Oldsmobile electric car instead of these little ones, it will help,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Given the technical problems, even the biggest boosters of electric cars do not fault the holdouts here in the San Juans.</p>
        <p>''Those who turned down the opportunity were probably smart to do so,'' said John Castagna, spokesman for the Edison Electric Institute in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Castagna said, ''there's really good stuff in the pipeline,'' including an electric Honda expected out next month, a Toyota expected this fall and a Nissan mini-van.</p>
        <p>The technology is moving fast enough that chargers like those on Orcas are beginning to spring up elsewhere. Mr. Castagna said there were plans for 400 such charging stations in California and Arizona by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>But in the history of the great transition from fossil fuels, the San Juan Islands will still have the distinction, in some ways, of being first.</p>
        <p>''We were the very first to put in a place -- small, but still, in place -- an infrastructure to charge your cars on the islands,'' Mr. Phillips said. ''We were the first county, through our great utility, to buy into this future.''</p>
        <p>Orcas Island Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
