<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Home Abroad; Peace and Justice</title>
    <meta content="17LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cook, Robin (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5DB1038F934A25752C1A961958260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Home Abroad; Peace and Justice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column examines radical changes in Britain's foreign policy under new Foreign Sec Robin Cook since Labor Government assumed power early in 1997 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''We feel  a strong belief of my own,'' Robin Cook said, ''that we can't have peace in Bosnia unless we have justice against those who committed atrocities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cook, Foreign Secretary in the Labor Government, is a striking example of the impact political change can have on foreign policy. In the six months since Labor took office he has transformed British policy on Bosnia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''We feel  a strong belief of my own,'' Robin Cook said, ''that we can't have peace in Bosnia unless we have justice against those who committed atrocities.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cook, Foreign Secretary in the Labor Government, is a striking example of the impact political change can have on foreign policy. In the six months since Labor took office he has transformed British policy on Bosnia.</p>
        <p>During the Serbian aggression and ''ethnic cleansing,'' the Conservative Government of Prime Minister John Major repeatedly resisted international measures to stop the slaughter. Britain had thousands of troops in the U.N. peacekeeping force but was the most reluctant of the Europeans to use the force meaningfully. (Mr. Major's predecessor, Margaret Thatcher, sharply disagreed with the timid policy.)</p>
        <p>The firm new British attitude was demonstrated last July, when British troops undertook the first operation by international forces to arrest men wanted for trial as war criminals. One Serb was arrested, another killed in a gun fight.</p>
        <p>Since then Britain has put up the money for a second courtroom for the War Crimes Tribunal in The Hague and helped to staff the tribunal. I asked Mr. Cook, in an interview, how he felt about the need to arrest the most wanted indictee, Radovan Karadzic, who led the Bosnian Serbs in the war.</p>
        <p>''It is very, very important indeed to arrest Karadzic,'' he said. ''It would be a form of injustice if we ended up trying lesser figures while the bigger ones escaped. One of the messages Karadzic must now absorb is that there is no hiding place. Someday he will be tried. But one shouldn't be glib. He has a very large bodyguard.''</p>
        <p>Britain has 5,300 soldiers in the international stabilization force in Bosnia, second in numbers to America's 8,500. Mr. Cook said he favored firm deadlines for compliance by the parties with provisions of the Dayton Agreement, with ''sticks in the form of sanctions if those deadlines aren't met.''</p>
        <p>He can be critical of all sides in Bosnia. On a visit there in July he called attention to their concealment of public spending ''and the opening for corruption which that creates.'' The problem is at least being discussed now, he said, and as a result ''the secret police attached to the S.D.A. [the nationalist party dominant among Muslims] have been rather undermined.''</p>
        <p>In opposition, he was a Labor spokesman on domestic subjects such as health -- but was known for ferreting out the facts on dubious foreign arms deals. An intellectual, he has a soft voice but, when needed, a sharp debater's tongue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cook is often described here as desiring an ''ethical foreign policy'' with an emphasis on human rights. Some Tories have mocked the idea, but he said he saw no reason it should be a partisan matter.</p>
        <p>''It is said that foreign policy is about promoting the national interest,'' Mr. Cook said. ''But part of the national interest is being confident and proud of your values. That is why we believe an element in foreign policy should be about supporting those who have been denied the values of democracy and human rights.''</p>
        <p>There are not just two choices in dealing with authoritarian governments, he said: ''to kowtow -- prostrate yourself to get a contract -- or have a row.'' A third is to discuss economic cooperation but explore your concerns about human rights ''in a civilized and courteous way.'' That approach, he said, would appeal to a broad consensus.</p>
        <p>In any event, concern about human rights does not dominate Mr. Cook's policy. Military security is a major focus. Britain is the one country that has fully supported the United States  in the showdown with Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>The environment is another item on the Cook and Labor agenda. Going much further than the United States on the issue of global warming, Britain has committed itself to making a 20 percent cut in carbon emissions by the year 2010.</p>
        <p>Finally, there is Europe. For six months starting Jan. 1, Britain will hold the presidency of the European Union's Council of Ministers. At the top of his agenda, Mr. Cook said, will be enlarging the E.U.: ''Europe has a historic mission to open its doors to the new democracies of Central and Eastern Europe.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
