<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Mosquito Bites Back</title>
    <meta content="24MOSQUIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="952436"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dengue Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Yellow Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immune System</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taubes, Gary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Dengue Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immune System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fever</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EFD9133FF937A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="4811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Mosquito Bites Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gary Taubes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Taubes, Gary</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gary Taubes article on resurgence in Western Hemisphere of deadly Aedes aegypti mosquito and diseases it transmits: urban yellow fever, dengue fever and dengue hemorrhagic fever; cites mosquito's evolution to live in proximity to humans and breed in man-made containers holding stagnant water; notes earlier success of eradication efforts has reduced immunity to diseases; photos (L)l</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It begins with the bite. she alights on your skin, a small, elegant, grayish mosquito with a distinctive, silvery-white lyre-shaped pattern on her back. She has small wings and fernlike antennae. Her Latin name is Aedes aegypti. As with all mosquitoes, only the female bites you. Nothing personal: she simply requires protein to produce her eggs and has evolved the equipment to procure it from your blood. Males live exclusively on nectar.</p>
        <p>Upon landing, she probes for a blood vessel, inserting her mouthparts into your skin a millimeter or two at a time, lubricating the motion with saliva, then pulling them back out. The motion is oddly reminiscent of fly-fishing, of dipping the rod in a cast and bringing it back. When she finds a blood vessel, she forces the tip of her proboscis through the skin and into the flow of the blood. She then simultaneously sucks out blood while continuing to dribble saliva. The walls of her proboscis are double-barreled, so saliva dribbles down one barrel while the blood is imbibed through the other. If she happens to be infected with a virus or a parasite, it will pass by way of the saliva to you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It begins with the bite. she alights on your skin, a small, elegant, grayish mosquito with a distinctive, silvery-white lyre-shaped pattern on her back. She has small wings and fernlike antennae. Her Latin name is Aedes aegypti. As with all mosquitoes, only the female bites you. Nothing personal: she simply requires protein to produce her eggs and has evolved the equipment to procure it from your blood. Males live exclusively on nectar.</p>
        <p>Upon landing, she probes for a blood vessel, inserting her mouthparts into your skin a millimeter or two at a time, lubricating the motion with saliva, then pulling them back out. The motion is oddly reminiscent of fly-fishing, of dipping the rod in a cast and bringing it back. When she finds a blood vessel, she forces the tip of her proboscis through the skin and into the flow of the blood. She then simultaneously sucks out blood while continuing to dribble saliva. The walls of her proboscis are double-barreled, so saliva dribbles down one barrel while the blood is imbibed through the other. If she happens to be infected with a virus or a parasite, it will pass by way of the saliva to you.</p>
        <p>The bite is painless. If you are allergic to the saliva, the itching begins in about a minute, but the mosquito will probably be gone by then. If you are not allergic, you may never know you've been had. Aedes aegypti has evolved to bite you and get away alive.</p>
        <p>It is precisely that bite, and its implications for human disease, that prompted Paul Reiter, an entomologist with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, to visit the central highlands of Puerto Rico several months ago. Reiter picked me up at my hotel at 6:30 on an already muggy morning to beat the rush-hour traffic out of San Juan, which we failed to do. We were headed for Florida, a small town about an hour's drive west of the capital.</p>
        <p>The C.D.C. runs a laboratory in San Juan to keep track of Aedes aegypti and the diseases it causes, and there has been a lot to keep track of lately. The mosquito, long a bane in the Western hemisphere, has made a stealthy and disturbing comeback. For 200 years this one species brought devastating epidemics of urban yellow fever to the Americas, including significant outbreaks in New York and Philadelphia. The mosquito is also responsible for infecting about 100 million people each year with dengue (pronounced DEN-gee) fever, a severe flulike illness whose common name -- breakbone fever -- adverts to its excruciating pain; it infects another 200,000 to 500,000 people with dengue hemorrhagic fever, a potentially fatal form of dengue. To epidemiologists, the presence of dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever is a harbinger of urban yellow fever outbreaks to come.</p>
        <p>Dengue fever is now a constant presence in Puerto Rico, with occasional epidemic flare-ups. A small dengue epidemic swept through the town of Florida in 1991. Among its 8,900 inhabitants, 400 had been sick enough to need medical attention. Four had hemorrhagic fever, and one of those died. Reiter was making a series of visits to the town as part of an experiment to see if it were possible to block the dangerous traffic among viruses, mosquitoes and humans.</p>
        <p>As we drove out, Reiter, wearing a blue ''C.D.C. at 50'' T-shirt, his curly brown hair in disarray, explained the gist of the mosquito problem, which was not, as you might think, that the insect has become better adapted to the modern world, but rather that the world has become much more accommodating to the mosquito. Aedes aegypti is a mosquito that has evolved to live in proximity to humans and to breed almost exclusively in man-made containers capable of holding stagnant water. Thus the detritus of late-20th-century civilization, all the junk and discards and certifiably nonbiodegradable material that have been liberally strewn throughout the world, now constitutes the ideal breeding site for the mosquito. While mankind has driven thousands of species on this planet toward extinction by destroying their habitats, there are a few, like Aedes aegypti and Anopheles gambiae, the primary carrier (or ''vector'') of malaria, for which we have done nothing but provide new habitats.</p>
        <p>If anything, we may have created a severe public health crisis in the tropics. Despite a decades-long campaign to eradicate Aedes aegypti in this hemisphere, the mosquito has recolonized virtually every acre of its former breeding grounds. Of the 21 countries declared free of the mosquito in the 1960's, every last one has now become reinfested.</p>
        <p>What makes this especially significant is what Reiter calls the catch-22 of mosquito eradication: once you embark upon it, you can never stop, or the threat to public health actually gets worse. The reason is an unfortunate variable known to epidemiologists as ''herd immunity'' -- the proportion of the population that has become immune to a virus like dengue. Not everyone infected by the virus gets dengue symptoms, but everyone who has been infected develops immunity to the virus, and when a mosquito bites one of those people, it wastes precious bites that could otherwise be spreading the disease. This dilutes the force of the epidemic and eventually kills it off, since most of the populace becomes immune. The higher the herd immunity, the more mosquitoes necessary to start an epidemic. The lower the immunity, the fewer mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>Given the realities of herd immunity, you could argue that the worst possible public health situation would be to eradicate a mosquito like Aedes aegypti and then let it return. That is precisely what has happened in the Western hemisphere, and among the people who know it best, this particular insect is a formidable foe.</p>
        <p>''It's quite astonishing how resourceful the mosquito is,'' Reiter said, with a little wonder in his voice.</p>
        <p>Wonderment is not usually the first sentiment that comes to mind when dealing with mosquitoes. From the human perspective, the insects (there are more than 3,000 species in the world) fall into two crude categories -- mere pests and real menaces -- and much of the distinction depends on where you live. Those of us who live in temperate climes deal with the mosquito as an annoyance, although the bother would be nearly unbearable were it not for prodigious amounts of mosquito control. Most of the state of Florida would be uninhabitable by modern standards without control measures, and so, for instance, would the south shore of Long Island or much of New Jersey, which earlier in the century was known unaffectionately as the ''Mosquito State.''</p>
        <p>In more tropical regions, the mosquito is considerably more than a nuisance; the danger is real and getting worse after several decades of ill-conceived eradication campaigns. While the diseases that make headlines these days are the freakish ''emerging'' viruses -- the hantavirus outbreak that killed 27 people in the Southwest in 1993 or the rare Ebola that killed 245 in 1995 in one small corner of the former Zaire -- mosquitoes transmit disease to at least 700 million people each year, about one-eighth of the world's population, and cause almost three million fatalities. In its World Health Report 1996, the World Health Organization labeled the mosquito the ''greatest menace'' of all disease-transmitting insects. Even that may understate the problem. Mosquitoes will kill, by W.H.O. tally, roughly 1 in every 17 people currently alive on this planet.</p>
        <p>Perhaps 400 species of mosquito can transmit disease to humans. Malaria, for example, is carried by mosquitoes of the Anopheles family, of which some 60 species are reasonably competent vectors. One mosquito known colloquially as ''quinks'' (for Culex quinquefasciatus), which breeds in pit latrines, drainage ditches and any polluted water, spreads the filariasis worm that infects more than 100 million people, primarily in South Asia, the Pacific Islands and Africa. The parasite can cause either elephantiasis, in which the limbs become grossly swollen, or hydrocoele, in which the scrotum enlarges to gruesome proportions.</p>
        <p>Several species common to North America, including Culex tarsalis, transmit encephalitis viruses in the United States. These viruses -- in particular La Crosse encephalitis, St. Louis encephalitis and Eastern and Western equine encephalitis -- circulate unseen in forest settings, passed between sylvan mosquitoes and the local birds or rodents, but they occasionally cause serious disease in children. A few dozen cases are reported each year to the C.D.C., with outbreaks every decade or so. In 1990, 250 people in Florida were struck with St. Louis encephalitis and 25 died.</p>
        <p>''The general perception is that mosquito-borne diseases ought to be eradicable,'' said Harold Varmus, director of the National Institutes of Health, ''and they have not proven to be so. And not only have the mosquitoes not been eradicated, but some of these diseases they carry are resurgent. They have come back from a fairly low ebb.'' In response to this rebounding threat to public health, the National Institutes of Health and the World Health Organization are planning a long-range research effort, while the World Bank is seeking support for a 30-year plan to battle malaria, but the obstacles strike many as nearly insurmountable. An effective malaria vaccine, long a goal, seems years away, and no one talks about trying to eliminate malaria-carrying mosquitoes anymore. Like Aedes aegypti, the Anopheles mosquito rapidly developed resistance to insecticides like DDT. Eradication, as one World Bank official said, ''has become a dirty word.''</p>
        <p>Aedes aegypti, meanwhile, has returned in a big way to this hemisphere, and brought disease back with it. Dengue is once again well-established throughout Latin America, and the number of cases of dengue hemorrhagic fever is creeping upward. The year 1995 was the worst on record for dengue fever in the Americas, and this summer there have already been epidemics in Mexico and Cuba. And while there haven't been epidemics of yellow fever in cities in this hemisphere in 50 years, tropical-disease experts are not so much warning of imminent outbreaks as wondering why they haven't yet occurred in places like Caracas or Cali.</p>
        <p>''We now have in the American tropics several hundred million people who are susceptible to yellow fever,'' said Duane Gubler, who is the director of the division of vector-borne infectious diseases of the C.D.C. ''All these areas are infested with Aedes aegypti, and so we're at the highest risk in over 50 years for urban epidemics of yellow fever. Once urban transmission begins in the American region, it's probably going to spread very rapidly throughout the region to other urban centers and then from there to Asia and the Pacific.'' Yellow fever, sometimes known as the ''American plague,'' begins with fits of shivering, fever and thirst, rapidly progressing to furious headaches and joint pain and finally jaundice -- whence the ''yellow'' of its name. Despite the existence of a vaccine for yellow fever, public health experts like Gubler doubt that there is enough to handle an epidemic or that it could be distributed swiftly enough to blunt an outbreak.</p>
        <p>The odds of such an epidemic coming ''onshore,'' as experts refer to an outbreak in the United States, is considered remote. State and local governments spend roughly $200 million a year on mosquito control. (Suffolk County, N.Y., alone allocates $2 million to control its mosquito population, and Lee County, Fla., in the southwest corner of the state, budgets $9 million.) All of this, of course, would be ratcheted up considerably should any sign of serious disease develop. ''They have two cases of St. Louis encephalitis in Florida,'' one entomologist said, not entirely in jest, ''and they dip the whole state in malathion.''</p>
        <p>Yet yellow fever or dengue, like malaria, is only a plane flight away from the United States. In the nightmare scenario, someone gets on a plane in, say, Sao Paulo infected with yellow fever but showing no symptoms and deplanes in Miami or any other city south of Atlanta, where Aedes aegypti is well established and can survive the winter. It is not nearly as unlikely as it may seem. ''Last year,'' said Tom Monath, the former head of the C.D.C.'s insect-borne infectious disease division, ''we had an unfortunate individual who went on a river trip in Brazil, got infected and came back and was hospitalized in Nashville and died at Vanderbilt.'' All it takes is for an infected person to get bit by Aedes aegypti and the disease can begin to spread. It is a task for which this particular mosquito is exquisitely qualified.</p>
        <p>As a graduate student at Notre Dame University in 1969, Robert Gwadz performed one of the seminal experiments of mosquitology, and it survives today as perhaps the definitive demonstration of what manner of beast we are dealing with. Gwadz, a medical entomologist, now helps to run the malaria research program out of his subterranean office at the National Institutes of Health in Bethesda, Md.</p>
        <p>Gwadz took female Aedes aegypti mosquitoes and severed their ventral nerve, which is the closest thing a mosquito has to a central nervous system. He then allowed the mosquitoes to feed by placing them on his arm. With the ventral nerve severed, they proceeded to suck his blood until they had quadrupled their original body weight. Then their abdomens exploded. This did not, however, deter them from continued feeding. ''Because there is no nervous connection anymore,'' Gwadz told me, ''and because they don't know they have exploded, they will continue to pump and the blood just spills out on your arm.''</p>
        <p>When it comes to biting, the mosquito simply does not possess free will. Its behavior is effectively preprogrammed from larval stage to death, and the bite merely represents the last step in a complex and involuntary progression from stalking to landing to feeding.</p>
        <p>The biology of the bite is one of extraordinary complexity. Down the hall from Gwadz's office -- among the insectories where N.I.H. researchers raise their mosquitoes and next to a laboratory where I saw two malaria-infected chickens, shaved, anesthetized and tied to a counter top awaiting the mosquitoes that would feed on them -- is the office of Jose Ribeiro, who is probably the world's leading expert on mosquito saliva.</p>
        <p>Over the years, Ribeiro has culled from mosquito spit a remarkable pharmacopeia of chemical agents that allow mosquitoes to take in the greatest amount of blood in the least amount of time, to feed and escape alive; these include anticoagulants to prevent clotting, immunosuppressants to keep swelling down in the victim and vasodilators to open up vessels and let the blood flow freely. With a microscope and seventyfold magnification, Ribeiro gave me an entomologist's-eye view of the mouthparts of Aedes aegypti, which are one-third as long as the mosquito itself. Ribeiro described them as ''a very delicate piece of hardware'' and explained that for all the death and disease the bite has brought, the incentive, as far as the mosquito is concerned, is minuscule: a mere four-millionths of a quart of blood. In other words, it would take 250,000 mosquito bites to siphon off a single quart of your blood.</p>
        <p>While different mosquitoes have different strategies of attack, depending on their preferred targets, the search for prey is another marvel of programmed biology. They will fly great distances for a meal: on the south shore of Long Island, for instance, salt marsh mosquitoes will fly up to 10 miles inland to find blood. Not that they actually smell the blood; they simply detect molecules of carbon dioxide on the wind and move inexorably upstream toward the source, which is almost always a living, breathing animal -- like us. At closer range, body heat also draws them to the target.</p>
        <p>The mosquitoes most likely to bite you in your sleep in temperate climates in Europe and the United States (Culex pipiens) fly at ceiling height, detect the upward convection of hot air off your body and swoop downward, which is why you might hear one buzzing about your ears before it strikes. Aedes aegypti approaches at knee level, attracted by carbon dioxide, water vapor and perhaps lactic acid from your sweat, all of which are heavier than air and will drift downward.</p>
        <p>At even closer range, the mosquito will be attracted to bite a specific host and even a specific biting site by zeroing in on subtle chemicals or microorganisms that may be unique to each individual. Modern science has yet to elucidate exactly what those signals might be, but there is some evidence that they are surprisingly specific -- so specific that people who think they are being singled out for insect torment may have a point.</p>
        <p>Dan Kline, a research entomologist at the Department of Agriculture laboratory in Gainesville, Fla., has demonstrated that it's not just CO2 and body heat that induce biting. ''You can take glass marbles and roll them in your hand and put them in a cage of mosquitoes, and the mosquitoes will attack the marbles,'' Kline said. ''It may be they're attracted to lactic acid or some other chemicals the skin puts out.''</p>
        <p>The life of a mosquito -- and this may be the only good news about the insect -- is brutal and short. Roughly one in five die every day, and not from senescence. In the wild, most succumb to encounters with the hazards of their environment -- slapping hands or insect-feeding bats or spider webs or dessication, should they find themselves out and about in the midday sun.</p>
        <p>Yet the life expectancy of the mosquito has a great deal to do with how many people it might kill. In the mathematics of an epidemic, Duane Gubler explained, the crucial variable basically boils down to the rate of potentially infective contacts between the mosquito and us -- what entomologists refer to as ''vectorial capacity.'' A skittish mosquito like Aedes aegypti makes a lot of contact; it might bite an entire family in one afternoon before finally taking its full meal of blood. Each bite can transmit disease, so the greater the number of bites, the more likely that we'll have an epidemic on our hands and the more vicious it is likely to be.</p>
        <p>The mosquito's lifetime is crucial because it takes a while for a virus or a parasite like malaria to be passed along -- if it survives at all. ''For a virus to breed and grow successfully in both a warmblooded animal like a human and a coldblooded arthropod like a mosquito is quite an evolutionary trick,'' said Chet Moore, a C.D.C. entomologist, ''and it doesn't happen frequently.'' It takes from 10 to 12 days for dengue virus to spread from the gut to the salivary glands. The mosquito has to live at least that long to pass the virus successfully from one human host to the next.</p>
        <p>Because Aedes aegypti prefers to live, eat and lay its eggs indoors, Gubler said, it is protected from wind, rain and most predators, which increases its life expectancy and hence the probability that it will live long enough to pick up a virus from one of us and pass it on to another. The mosquito has a long life span, according to Ribeiro; it can live for several weeks, thus allowing it to bite that many more people.</p>
        <p>Aedes aegypti is a daylight feeder: it bites in the morning and then again from midafternoon until dusk. Because it bites humans when they can still see it, it has evolved into a nervous and temperamental eater. ''Even the slightest movement anywhere will make it interrupt its feeding and fly over and bite someone else,'' said Gubler, who has been studying the insect for 30 years. ''It's a survival mechanism, and it has made Aedes aegypti a very highly efficient epidemic vector.''</p>
        <p>In an earlier era, when public health officials were more optimistic about the weapons they could bring to bear in the insect wars, they believed that the best way to conquer disease was to reduce the number of mosquitoes until an epidemic could not be sustained -- or, better yet, to eliminate them entirely. That is in a sense what prompted Paul Reiter's trip to Florida, P.R., in the first place: a humble attempt to eliminate breeding sites. Over coffee and pastries in a bodega before we hit the streets, Reiter talked about the history of mosquito eradication -- and not with a great deal of enthusiasm. He called it one of the ''great myths of science.''</p>
        <p>Reiter and three public health workers had cleaned up this small neighborhood in March by removing every visible mosquito breeding site, which meant, in effect, carefully combing the neighborhood for any man-made junk that might hold a drop of water and thus the eggs of Aedes aegypti. Now we were back seven weeks later; to be precise, seven very dry weeks later, one of the driest spells in memory. Reiter had no illusions, however. ''It's a very successful species,'' he said. ''It lives all over the place, and so to eradicate it is very, very difficult.''</p>
        <p>Eradication is the ultimate weapon against mosquitoes, but the immensity (not to say futility) of the effort is hard to comprehend. Despite all the scientific and technological advances of this past century, no one has improved on the method William Gorgas first applied in Havana in 1901. For centuries, Havana had been ravaged by yellow fever. Gorgas and his sanitation crews went house to house and building to building, getting rid of every potential mosquito breeding site for Aedes aegypti in the entire city. As Gorgas did it, the operation bordered on the paramilitary, which is the only way it has worked since then.</p>
        <p>In 1947, the Pan American Sanitary Bureau (predecessor of the Pan American Health Organization) decided that a hemisphere-wide eradication campaign was the only way to put an end to the urban yellow fever epidemics that still devastated Latin America. By 1962, at the peak of the program and with liberal use of DDT, 18 nations were officially free of Aedes aegypti. Three more nations eventually accomplished the feat, but there were some notable failures, in particular the United States, where the mosquito infested virtually every southern state. The failure of the program was as much political as scientific. Mosquito-control experts complained at the time that Congress budgeted too little to accomplish the task. Donald Schliessmann, who directed the C.D.C.'s efforts, described the allocation as ''equivalent to instructions to fly across the Atlantic with half a tank of gas.''</p>
        <p>With such tepid support in the United States, the Pan American Health Organization's eradication program promptly died and the mosquito had little trouble recolonizing its former haunts. Its return has inevitably been followed by the return of dengue fever, which has experts at the C.D.C. and P.A.H.O. worried for three distinct reasons. First, unlike the case of yellow fever, there is no vaccine for dengue, which means that the only defense for locals or travelers, as one C.D.C. entomologist bluntly put it, is not to get bit. Second, dengue epidemics are explosive. ''The first time a country has an epidemic, it is usually in the capital city, and you can have 30 to 60 percent of the people all sick at the same time,'' Mike Nelson, a P.A.H.O. entomologist, informed me. A 1986-87 epidemic in Rio de Janeiro tallied one million cases. In 1988, dengue hit Guayaquil, Ecuador, with some 450,000 cases in four months.</p>
        <p>Most troubling to P.A.H.O. experts is the potentially fatal hemorrhagic manifestation of dengue. Researchers have identified four separate ''serotypes,'' or variants, of the dengue virus (known, unimaginatively, as dengue-1 through dengue-4). A first infection can bring on dengue fever. Subsequent infections with other serotypes are then likely to produce dengue hemorrhagic fever, which can lead to massive hemorrhaging or circulatory collapse.</p>
        <p>The first major appearance of dengue hemorrhagic fever in the Western Hemisphere occurred in 1981 during a Cuban epidemic: there were 300,000 cases of dengue and 10,000 cases of hemorrhagic fever with 158 deaths. Smaller outbreaks of dengue hemorrhagic fever appeared in Venezuela in 1989-90 and in Rio de Janeiro in 1990. The numbers have been climbing steadily. In Mexico, for example, there were 26 reported cases in the entire decade prior to 1994. In 1994 alone there were 30 cases, and in 1995 there were 92.</p>
        <p>To date, the problem in this hemisphere is predominantly a Latin American one, and is likely to remain so, but experts predict that the numbers of dengue and dengue hemorrhagic fever cases will continue to grow. Meanwhile, urban yellow fever is a ''modern-day time bomb,'' Gubler said. ''We're just sitting here waiting for it to happen.'' With all the renewed concern, the Pan American Health Organization is once again talking about eradication -- or, rather, what it calls ''amplification and intensification of combat.'' P.A.H.O. officials met in April in Caracas and came up with a five-step plan. Each step, if approved, will successively lower the infestation levels until transmission of the disease is entirely interrupted. Only then will they go on to eradication, if it is necessary and considered remotely possible.</p>
        <p>While P.A.H.O. is leaving the door open for eradication, none of the entomologists with whom I spoke believe it is still possible. Between the garbage of modern times and the ease of reinfestation, they suggested, the job has probably become undoable at any cost. ''There was probably a chance to eradicate Aedes aegypti in the 40's, 50's and 60's,'' said Tom Monath, the former C.D.C. official. ''But at this point in time, the war is lost.''</p>
        <p>If the small town of Florida is any indication, it is easy to understand why the smart money is on mosquitoes. Reiter took me on a tour through one neighborhood -- no shantytown but a middle-class housing development. Most of the homes were brightly painted, with nice Japanese and American cars in the carports. We went climbing through backyards, looking in carports, peering amid the tropical flowers, looking for breeding sites. They weren't hard to find.</p>
        <p>It was in a carport that I saw my first mosquito larvae. Reiter had to point them out to me. All I saw was an empty plastic SAE-40 oil bottle floating in five inches of water, along with a few rubber balls and an orange plastic Halloween pumpkin. Finally, Reiter directed my attention to the larvae, which were nearly invisible, S-shaped, thin and brown and flitting frenetically. Their nontechnical name is ''wrigglers,'' and that's exactly what they were doing. In a children's plastic wading pool.</p>
        <p>In the two hours I spent with Reiter and his colleagues, in a locale where every breeding site had been eliminated two months earlier, we found 23 newly infected breeding sites scattered among 16 houses. We found Aedes aegypti larvae in children's toys and soda cans, plastic cups and discarded automobile tires. We also found pupae, the next step up in mosquito development. In two or three days, Reiter pointed out, they would emerge as adults. ''We're looking at something like 5 mosquitoes per human,'' he said, ''maybe 20 female mosquitoes per home.''</p>
        <p>The numbers have been debated, but for a viable epidemic, one infected breeding site in those 16 houses would have been more than enough. The implications are obvious. ''Where you have successful control,'' Reiter said, ''and then you cease and you have a population that's largely susceptible, then you can have a rip-roaring epidemic and perhaps terrible tragedy.''</p>
        <p>''Is it possible to eradicate this species?'' Reiter asked me rhetorically. ''How can you possibly imagine you can eradicate a species as successful as aegypti? You could eradicate smallpox, because you eliminated its environment by vaccinating people. So that in the end there wasn't any habitat for the virus. But there's habitat for Aedes aegypti every time it rains.''  Gary Taubes often writes about science and technology. This is his first story for the Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gary Taubes often writes about science and technology. This is his first story for the Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
