<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="29FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="940517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DC1E31F93AA15755C0A961958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-15</p>
        <p>Big Contractors Push For Expansion of NATO  Military contractors are acting like globe-hopping diplomats to encourage the expansion of NATO, which will create a huge market for them. Admission to the Western fraternity will bring political prestige, but at a price: playing by rules that require Western weapons and equipment. The potential market for fighter jets alone is put at $10 billion.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Britain's Shadow on Hong Kong  Hong Kong survived as a colony much longer than Britain's other outposts, perhaps because the lease determined when independence would come. As it does, people are assessing and disputing the British legacy, and how it relates to the lively success of the Chinese residents.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-15</p>
        <p>Big Contractors Push For Expansion of NATO  Military contractors are acting like globe-hopping diplomats to encourage the expansion of NATO, which will create a huge market for them. Admission to the Western fraternity will bring political prestige, but at a price: playing by rules that require Western weapons and equipment. The potential market for fighter jets alone is put at $10 billion.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Britain's Shadow on Hong Kong  Hong Kong survived as a colony much longer than Britain's other outposts, perhaps because the lease determined when independence would come. As it does, people are assessing and disputing the British legacy, and how it relates to the lively success of the Chinese residents.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Georgia Limiting Adoptions  In the former Soviet state of Georgia, foreigners trying to adopt children are facing an impasse that tells much about a growing antipathy of the local people to the adoptions.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>A Cornerstone for Vietnam  Secretary of State Albright laid the cornerstone of an American consulate in Ho Chi Minh City, once Saigon, expressing the hope that both nations are moving ''from tragic conflict to mutual respect.''</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Arrest in Japanese Beheading  Japanese police arrested a 14-year-old boy in the beheading of an 11-year-old last month, the grisliest slaying in memory in Japan. The arrest of a juvenile, who knew the victim, stunned the Japanese.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Albanians Vote, With Fear  Disillusioned and anxious, Albanians vote Sunday in a parliamentary election that is expected to be marked by violence and fraud.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>16-21</p>
        <p>Tougher Standards For U.S. Car Makers  President Clinton's approval on Wednesday of stricter air quality standards for the nation's cities was a fear come true for the automobile industry. A day later, the President delivered an even more serious blow to the industry when he declared that at an international conference next December in Kyoto, Japan, the United States would favor the adoption of binding limits on so-called greenhouse gases, which may contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>G.A.O. Will Release Report  Over objections by the Pentagon, the General Accounting Office plans to release a report on Monday that says the Defense Department and arms manufacturers exaggerated the success of high-technology weapons that were used in the 1991 gulf war.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Protein Linked to Illness  Lesions made of a previously unidentified protein have been found in the brains of Alzheimer's patients, a discovery that could shed light on the cause of the disease and offer a means of early diagnosis and perhaps even treatment.</p>
        <p>21</p>
        <p>Computer Bandit Faces Jail  Kevin Mitnick, the computer outlaw who was trapped by another computer whiz in 1995, was sentenced in Los Angeles on Friday to nearly two years in prison. Mr. Mitnick, who pleaded guilty last year to using 15 stolen cellular phone numbers to dial into computer databases in North Carolina, is awaiting trial in California on 25 counts of computer and wire fraud, possessing unlawful access devices, damaging computers and intercepting electronic messages. (AP)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>23-28</p>
        <p>Inside Story Emerges After Tumultuous Rent War  The fight over rent regulations in New York began when Joseph L. Bruno, the majority leader of the New York State Senate and a Republican, called for the end of the system in two years. What followed, by most accounts, was a series of missteps by the Republicans. Most of all, Mr. Bruno and Governor Pataki misread the monumental importance of rent protections to New York City residents, regardless of party affiliation, and failed to anticipate how hard they would fight to maintain laws that many had come to regard as a middle-class entitlement.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Committing Sex Offenders  A new legislative assault on pedophiles and rapists goes beyond ''Megan's Laws'': This one is intended to keep the most dangerous of them from getting back on the streets in the first place. A handful of states have enacted laws giving officials the power to commit violent sex offenders to mental hospitals once their prison terms are up. In the last few years, more than 250 sex offenders have been committed, and the trend is expected to spread across the country with the Supreme Court decision last week upholding Kansas' Sexually Violent Predator Act.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Kenneth Dale McCormick  Doubleday's longtime editor in chief and a major figure in American book publishing was 91.</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>Television</p>
        <p>38</p>
        <p>Styles</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Weddings</p>
        <p>34-38</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
