<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Takes Off to Fortify the Mir Station</title>
    <meta content="16SHUT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="930198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atlantis (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mir (Space Station)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DB1538F935A25756C0A961958260" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Takes Off to Fortify the Mir Station</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>International crew of astronauts aboard space shuttle Atlantis takes off on planned nine-day mission to make repairs to aging Russian space station Mir; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An international crew of astronauts aboard the space shuttle Atlantis took off today on a planned nine-day mission for a critical visit to the aging Russian space station Mir.</p>
        <p>Lifting off in the dark before dawn, the shuttle climbed to an orbit 184 miles above Earth, where it began maneuvering toward a rendezvous with the Mir on Friday night over Russia. That will be none too soon for the three Mir astronauts, including an American physician.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An international crew of astronauts aboard the space shuttle Atlantis took off today on a planned nine-day mission for a critical visit to the aging Russian space station Mir.</p>
        <p>Lifting off in the dark before dawn, the shuttle climbed to an orbit 184 miles above Earth, where it began maneuvering toward a rendezvous with the Mir on Friday night over Russia. That will be none too soon for the three Mir astronauts, including an American physician.</p>
        <p>The years are catching up with the Mir, which has circled the world more than 64,000 times since its launching in 1986.</p>
        <p>A fire broke out on board in February, and the main oxygen generator shut down in March. The cooling equipment is leaking, and the system for removing carbon dioxide from the cabin air has been a constant headache.</p>
        <p>So the Atlantis is going to the rescue, taking more than 7,000 pounds of water, food, a new oxygen generator the size of a home water heater and other supplies. Several repair kits containing hoses, clamps and other plumbing equipment will also be delivered. Transferring the provisions will probably take five days.</p>
        <p>Valery Ryumin, a former Russian astronaut who is now an executive of the Energia Company, a major contractor for the Mir project, acknowledged on Tuesday that this and previous supply missions by the American shuttles were keeping the space station in operation.</p>
        <p>''Every single flight is almost critical,'' Mr. Ryumin told reporters at the Kennedy Space Center here.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ryumin and American space officials insisted that the space station, almost the size of a boxcar, remained safe enough for continued occupation. A Soyuz spacecraft is always docked to the Mir as an emergency escape vehicle.</p>
        <p>The Atlantis was launched on schedule at 4:08 A.M., after what space officials called the most trouble-free countdown in recent memory. Flight controllers reported that all systems were functioning normally and that the shuttle was on course to meet the Mir.</p>
        <p>Almost an hour later, the faint light of the Mir could be seen passing high over the shuttle launching pad  like a slow shooting star. The Russian astronauts said they could see Cape Canaveral through binoculars. The Mir had been 1,200 miles west of Australia, more than 12,000 miles from here, at the time of the shuttle launching.</p>
        <p>As befits a mission by one country on the way to the space station of another, the seven-member crew of Atlantis has a diverse international flavor. It includes a French astronaut, a British-born astrophysicist, a Russian woman, a scientist whose parents were born in China and another astronaut born in Peru.</p>
        <p>''I think we could probably walk into a restaurant anywhere in the world and order,'' said Dr. Edward Tsang Lu, an American physicist whose parents came from China.</p>
        <p>The shuttle crew is headed by Col. Charles J. Precourt, the commander, and Lieut. Col. Eileen M. Collins, the pilot. Both are Air Force officers, and Colonel Collins's initial flight in 1995, which also had a rendezvous with the Mir, made her the first  female shuttle pilot.</p>
        <p>The other crew members, besides Dr. Lu, are Maj. Carlos I. Noriega of the Marines, an American astronaut who was born in Lima, Peru; Jean-Francois Clervoy, a French astronaut who is representing the European Space Agency; Elena V. Kondrakova, a Russian astronaut who is married to Mr. Ryumin, and Dr. C. Michael Foale, an astrophysicist who was born in England and is a naturalized American citizen.</p>
        <p>For Dr. Foale, the flight will be a one-way trip, for the time being. He is to remain on the Mir for four months, replacing another American, Dr. Jerry L. Linenger, who has been living there since mid-January, through the trying times of leaks, fires and other malfunctions. Dr. Linenger is to return home.</p>
        <p>When Russian flight controllers informed Dr. Linenger that the shuttle had been launched and was on the way, he was reported to have said, ''That's great.'' How much emotion he put into his response was not reported.</p>
        <p>The two Russians aboard the Mir, Vasily Tsibliyev and Aleksandr Lazutkin, are to remain at their posts until August, when they will be relieved by three additional astronauts who are to arrive on a Russian Soyuz craft. Russians and astronauts from other nations have been living and working almost continuously in the space station for 11 years.</p>
        <p>The launching today was the fourth of the year for a shuttle. And this is the sixth of nine planned shuttle missions to the Mir. The missions are part of the preparations to assemble and operate an international space station, now scheduled to begin in June 1998. Officials expect the Atlantis to end its flight with a landing here on May 24.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
