<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Meltdown Has Begun'</title>
    <meta content="26FRANKT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="904247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frank, Elizabeth</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hecht, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Do the Windows Open? (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E3D9173BF935A15752C0A961958260" item-length="1896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Meltdown Has Begun'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elizabeth Frank</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Frank, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Frank reviews book Do the Windows Open? by Julie Hecht; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO THE WINDOWS OPEN?</p>
        <p>By Julie Hecht.</p>
        <p>212 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $21.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO THE WINDOWS OPEN?</p>
        <p>By Julie Hecht.</p>
        <p>212 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Random House. $21.</p>
        <p>In ''The Thrill Is Gone,'' the sixth in Julie Hecht's debut collection of superb short stories, the narrator wakes up in Nantucket one summer morning with a terrible headache. Midlife has struck her right between the eyes, and her temples throb with disaffection. After a day spent trying out various headache remedies, making invidious comparisons between herself and Hillary Clinton, Jacqueline Onassis and Princess Di, ruminating about her ''loss of enthusiasm for everything,'' she eventually visits a bookstore and looks up the word ''heart'' in ''Bartlett's Familiar Quotations'': ''I was momentarily distracted by 'Heartstrings are a lute.' Why hadn't I read more poetry? Another way I had wasted my life occurred to me. 'My heart is pure,' 'my heart is sick and sad,' 'my heart is heavy,' 'my heart is at rest,' 'I am sick at heart,' and nothing about 'my heart-rate target zone during aerobic activity' -- the way the word is used now.''</p>
        <p>For this narrator, whose voice links all the stories, now is the problem. Everything's gone wrong. The greenhouse effect causes six-month summers and ''world meltdown has begun.'' For no good reason, human beings, as she frequently calls them, still eat animal products. To get from one place to another is to take your life in your hands: ''They're always telling us that cars are more dangerous than planes. Why not be afraid of both?''</p>
        <p>This is a speaker who generously invites you to share her daily harvest of terror, pessimism, bafflement and misadventure and just as generously offers tips on how to survive them. For example, ''to transcend the endodontic experience,'' you need, among other things, ''a view of Central Park from the dental chair, you must be in a perfectly clean, white, sterile room with a clean beige or light-gray waiting room, a no-smoking sign, a few flowers on the desk and a Mozart opera to listen to on your stereo earphones.''</p>
        <p>Married, childless, somewhere in her 40's, the nameless narrator is a photographer who likes to take pictures of ponds and has completed a series of photographs no gallery wants of flowers in decline. One of her projects is to photograph every house the poet Anne Sexton ever lived in. Having fled Manhattan to live most of the year in East Hampton, except for summers, which she spends in Nantucket, she is a fanatical vegetarian and disciple of alternative medicine, and a connoisseur of Mozart, Elvis, vintage movies and Xanax.</p>
        <p>Because her husband, an architect, works weekdays in the city, she spends much of her time alone, and the daily incidents that give rise to her varied monologues reflect her rich companionship with her own solitude. For even in East Hampton and Nantucket, places synonymous with the felicitous collaboration of money and nature, she remains an outsider and an observer, truly at home nowhere except in language.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hecht refuses to play it safe with her heroine, whose eye for detail is deadly. Nothing and no one, including herself, is exempt. She has devastating things to say about the way people look and act. The ethical implications of Gary Hart's comb-over, the poor quality of contemporary ''peanut-eating styles,'' the exact topography of a certain kind of ''toupee mistake'' are all scrutinized, interrogated and catalogued; she compulsively sorts out the surfaces of the world as if looking for evidence or trying to solve for x. Acutely aware of time, place and history, she identifies a man as ''so young he was from the generation of human beings who use the word 'like' to mean 'said.' ''</p>
        <p>But her narrator is neither detached nor willfully ironic. She isn't a snob and she has no answers. She can't help seeing what she sees, and wisely Ms. Hecht sometimes lets her go too far. In ''Perfect Vision,'' the first story in the collection, she is convinced that a German optician on Park Avenue is a Nazi, or a former Nazi: ''I looked into those stone-cold icy-blue eyes, and they seemed not to be eyes at all but some frozen mineral substance through which every kind of cruelty could be transmitted either in or out.'' At certain points in the story you wonder whether she's crazy: at the very least she seems a crank; at the same time you are forced to concede that nothing in even her wildest fantasies couldn't be true.</p>
        <p>The narrator's capacity for obsession -- her imagination, really -- is what gives the stories (all previously published in The New Yorker) their novelistic coherence. Her profound and desperately funny fascination with ''Dr. Arnold Loquesto, the world-renowned reproductive surgeon,'' establishes a pretext of sorts for plot and continuity. Formerly his patient (though reproductive success has eluded her and has even receded in favor of photography), the narrator chronicles her frequent and baroque attempts to photograph Dr. Loquesto at home with his dog, or at conferences and meetings where he is usually the star and on the run. The problem is that this short man with a big voice that ''could be thrown across long corridors through the closed doors of examining rooms and operating rooms, and could wake patients from light or even medium anesthesia as he operated on them,'' is never in one place long enough for his picture to be taken. Nor can he sit still. Yet he fills the narrator's thoughts at all times and all places. In the title story, ''Do the Windows Open?,'' a comic masterpiece, the narrator, during a horrendous journey on the South Fork Bus (read here Hampton Jitney), overhears two women discussing an unusual childbirth technique and plans to ask Dr. Loquesto about it, but on second thought realizes ''that it might enrage him. I'd once heard him yell at someone who asked his opinion of the birthing chair, 'Great, the doctor has to sit on the floor in a raincoat!' '' Loquesto leaps out at us from story to story like a pagan god so chaotically and kinetically alive that he contains and dissolves all contradictions. For the narrator, whose reproductive sadness is everywhere felt but nowhere spoken, the goal of photographing the elusive doctor holds out the solution to an ultimate conundrum: ''If I made a study of the personality of the happy-go-lucky reproductive surgeon -- and the way to do this would be to photograph him with his little dog -- I would have the answer to the question of how to live in the world.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hecht is a brilliant comic writer. The stories are breathtakingly funny, and over and over again I found myself laughing till I cried. Yet the laughs are unforced and unmanufactured; Ms. Hecht's narrator isn't a comedienne and she doesn't do shtick. Like other classic deadpan talkers (Tristram Shandy, Huckleberry Finn, Thomas Bernhard's narrators), she doesn't even seem to realize how funny she is. The tone is seamless and magnetic and remarkably gentle, even delicate. Moreover, the humor in the stories is so organic to the narrator's rambling and digressive sensibility that it's hard to tell when it becomes fused with sadness or stained with desolation. But suddenly things change. A seemingly drifting series of anecdotes about the narrator's acquaintance with two pixilated brothers who, like her, live in East Hampton, summer in Nantucket and share her nostalgia for New England inns with lovely Christmas ornaments becomes a pointed lamentation for the inevitable loss of freshness and hope in marriage. Entirely silent about love and sex, the stories bulge with excluded middles and metaphysical heartaches. Concluding a passage about Dr. Loquesto's frantic movements from one thing to the next, the narrator, who is fascinated by the phenomenon of time, pauses to reflect, ''The sunlight at certain afternoon angles showed moments to be more dead and empty than they were on a cloudy day. On a cloudy day, the moments of afternoon could merge into one long moment, but on a sunny day you had to be on guard and watch what the light was doing to the time. The way the sun was shining into our garage and lighting up an old pink silk chair made it seem to me that we were already dead.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hecht's stories do not move in a straight line. Each one is like a long afternoon walk; each takes all the time it needs. But pressure accumulates, and sudden epiphanies reveal and relieve the narrator's chronic attacks of undefended clarity and uncompromising consciousness. Though time and age are no longer on her side, it is human inadequacy that haunts her the most. The neighbors who live in the loveliest houses in Nantucket all hate one another. A man with a house on the beach in East Hampton has nothing to say to a man with a house on the highway. A young couple have no bookshelves in their house because they have no books. A fabulously rich Nantucket neighbor who asks the narrator's advice about tomatoes and is ''sick'' over not being able to buy a certain piece of land says: ''I deserve more. I can have Scalamandre fabric in every room. I deserve whatever I want.'' The narrator keeps worrying about the ways she thinks she has wasted her life, and finds it painful to look at herself in the mirror.</p>
        <p>What she is, however, is complex, trying, engaging and lovable. Like the Ancient Mariner, she takes hold and won't let go, and by the time you finish the book you are hers forever. What finally comes through is the exhausting pains she takes to restore life to itself, and herself to life. Her eye and ear are faultless. Fully present at every instant of her existence, she transforms her inexhaustible capacity for observation and response into narrative tapestries woven from the freshest and loveliest colloquial speech to grace American fiction in a long time. Ms. Hecht's heroine does indeed have ''perfect vision,'' not because she works at it but because she can't help it. Affronted by styrofoam cups, terrified by truckloads of asbestos dust on the Long Island Expressway, annihilated by the inhuman architecture of New York and utterly nonplused by people, ''their faces, their bodies, their hairstyles,'' she is a victim -- and survivor -- of what H. L. Mencken in a brilliant essay of the same name called ''the libido for the ugly,'' the raging American lust to create human environments of spirit-destroying hideousness. In giving us a narrator with the courage to be her own unapologetically fearful, obsessive, vegetarian, frustrated, hilarious, elegiac, envious, desolate, lyrical, judgmental, Mozart-loving, acidulous, speculative, determined, literate, anxious, quixotic and absolutely idiosyncratic self, Ms. Hecht fights back against this murderous blight with the only weapons that count -- the mind and the heart -- and enough wit to get us through the end of this century and well into the next.  Elizabeth Frank teaches literature at Bard College and is writing a novel about Hollywood in the 30's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Frank teaches literature at Bard College and is writing a novel about Hollywood in the 30's.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
