<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solar Power In Big Leap In California</title>
    <meta content="19SOLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="931029"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sacramento Municipal Utility</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Photovoltaics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4D81138F93AA25756C0A961958260" item-length="620" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solar Power In Big Leap In California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sacramento Municipal Utility District signs contract to buy 10 megawatts of solar cells by 2002, and cost of cells is expected to be pushed down to competitive level through economies of scale possible with a long-term contract; will put 300 square feet to 500 square feet of cells on roofs of about 4,000 customers, and these will produce about three kilowatts of power during the day; cells will come from Energy Photovoltaics of Princeton, NJ (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A California electric utility has signed a big contract to buy solar cells that the utility and the Department of Energy say will push the cells' cost down to a competitive level by 2002.</p>
        <p>The utility, the Sacramento Municipal Utility District, will buy 10 megawatts of solar cells by 2002, enough to supply hundreds of houses. The total is small by the standards of conventional power plants, but experts say it is the largest purchase ever by a utility of solar cells, which make electricity from sunlight. The type that the utility district will buy, thin-film silicon, is similar to what pocket calculators run on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A California electric utility has signed a big contract to buy solar cells that the utility and the Department of Energy say will push the cells' cost down to a competitive level by 2002.</p>
        <p>The utility, the Sacramento Municipal Utility District, will buy 10 megawatts of solar cells by 2002, enough to supply hundreds of houses. The total is small by the standards of conventional power plants, but experts say it is the largest purchase ever by a utility of solar cells, which make electricity from sunlight. The type that the utility district will buy, thin-film silicon, is similar to what pocket calculators run on.</p>
        <p>Outside experts say that it is difficult to predict future costs but that the contract is likely to help push prices down substantially.</p>
        <p>The utility district expects to buy cells in 1998 at a cost equal to 16.3 cents per kilowatt-hour. The price will fall to 8.2 cents by the final year of the contract, 2002. The driving force behind the price drop, officials said, will be economies of scale possible with a long-term contract.</p>
        <p>The utility will put 300 square feet to 500 square feet of cells on the roofs of about 4,000 customers who volunteer, and these will produce about three kilowatts of power during the day, said Donald E. Osborn, who is in charge of solar power for the utility district. Over the year, he said, the cells will produce about the same amount of power as a house uses.</p>
        <p>Solar cells produce energy only during daylight hours, a time frame that matches Sacramento's hours of greatest need, Mr. Osborn said. The system can tolerate 10 percent to 20 percent of its production coming from such intermittent power sources, he said.</p>
        <p>About 700 customers already have such installations and pay $4 a month extra as ''PV Pioneers.'' Since June 1989, when voters in the district decided to shut their nuclear plant, Rancho Seco, the utility district has tried to cut demand, paying customers to buy more efficient refrigerators and planting thousands of tress that shade houses and lower air-conditioning costs. It has also installed solar cells, some on the site of the nuclear plant.</p>
        <p>The new solar cells will come from Energy Photovoltaics of Princeton, N.J., which will build a factory in Sacramento. The Energy Department has subsidized the research.</p>
        <p>At the Energy Department, Joseph Romm, the Acting Assistant Secretary for the Office of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, called the contract signing ''an exceptional moment for the solar energy program.''</p>
        <p>Solar experts said the size and duration of the contract made it exceptional. John P. Thornton, an expert in photovoltaic markets at the National Renewable Energy Laboratory, an Energy Department laboratory in Golden, Colo., said, ''It actually could have a significant influence on driving the price down.''</p>
        <p>Total worldwide production of solar cells is about 96 megawatts a year, about 45 megawatts of which is in the United States, Mr. Thornton said. Many of the cells are exported to developing countries, he said.</p>
        <p>At the Solar Energy Industries Association, a trade group based in Washington, Scott Sklar, the executive director, said that the contract was unprecedented in size for a utility, but that several other companies were ''not far behind.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
