<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Spectacular Shudders of Dying Stars</title>
    <meta content="23STAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="982489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hubble Space Telescope</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sun</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hubble Space Telescope</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DF153EF930A15751C1A961958260" item-length="1977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Spectacular Shudders of Dying Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Astronomers using instruments on Hubble Space Telescope obtain vivid new images of dying stars that prompt them to revise their theories of stellar death; hope observations with new infrared instruments installed on Hubble in February will further clarify many mysteries; images suggest Sun's ultimate fate; photos show various stars in various states of dying (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEATH comes to the average star in fitful stages. The star's depleted core, contracting, becomes hotter and hotter. The heat bloats the star's exterior, which reddens and swells more than 200 times its normal diameter. As the star throbs and shudders in a kind of last gasp, clouds of glowing gas and dust erupt and spread out to distances equivalent to about 1,000 times the breadth of the entire solar system.</p>
        <p>Finally, all that remains is the compact, burned-out core, a stellar corpse known as a white dwarf. But in death, such stars, each with about the same mass as the Sun, reseed the cosmos. They scatter the raw material for creating succeeding generations of stars and planets. Human bodies are made of the carbon and other elements cooked in stars that lived and died long ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEATH comes to the average star in fitful stages. The star's depleted core, contracting, becomes hotter and hotter. The heat bloats the star's exterior, which reddens and swells more than 200 times its normal diameter. As the star throbs and shudders in a kind of last gasp, clouds of glowing gas and dust erupt and spread out to distances equivalent to about 1,000 times the breadth of the entire solar system.</p>
        <p>Finally, all that remains is the compact, burned-out core, a stellar corpse known as a white dwarf. But in death, such stars, each with about the same mass as the Sun, reseed the cosmos. They scatter the raw material for creating succeeding generations of stars and planets. Human bodies are made of the carbon and other elements cooked in stars that lived and died long ago.</p>
        <p>New photographs taken by the Hubble Space Telescope have provided the clearest look yet at this phenomenon, which occurs once every year somewhere in the Milky Way galaxy to an aged star and will be the Sun's fate in five billion or six billion years. Even though  astronomers are left with many questions about the dynamics of these stellar death throes, they now have many reasons to revise their theories.</p>
        <p>''The first time we looked at the Hubble's breathtaking pictures, we knew that our older and simpler ideas of how these objects are formed had to be overhauled,'' said Dr. Howard Bond, an astronomer at the Space Telescope Science Institute in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>Astronomers are especially surprised by the variety of colorful patterns spun into interstellar space by the ejected gases illumined by the ultraviolet light from the dying stars. No two patterns appear the same. The pictures show that one cloud of gaseous debris is roughly spherical, which had been the conventional image in pre-Hubble theory. But others look like a huge pinwheel, an hourglass, a cat's eye, a goblet and the wings of a butterfly.</p>
        <p>''These are beautiful laboratories up in the sky,'' said Dr. Yervant Terzian of Cornell University, a specialist in the study of these objects. ''We can sit down here and look at them and learn a lot of physics.''</p>
        <p>If nothing else, the new pictures reveal that Sunlike stars, the vast majority of the stellar population, make their exits almost as spectacularly as the extremely massive stars, those that each have a mass at least eight times that of the Sun. These massive stars come to a more sudden end, in supernova explosions with the brightness of a billion Suns, but these are rarer occurrences than the deaths of more ordinary stars.</p>
        <p>On closer examination of the new pictures, astronomers make out glowing red blobs at the edge of some of the clouds and jets of high-speed particles shooting out in opposite directions from the dying star.</p>
        <p>If there is any common pattern, astronomers note, all the clouds display a symmetrical ejection of material, suggesting some order in the apparent chaos. ''Hubble's ability to see very fine structural details, usually blurred beyond recognition in ground-based images, enables us to look for clues to this puzzle,'' said Dr. Bruce Balick, an astronomer at the University of Washington in Seattle. ''These pictures will change the textbooks.''</p>
        <p>The mystery of these dying stars has intrigued scientists for more than two centuries. In the 18th century, astronomers with weak telescopes first observed the phenomenon of stellar death. They saw vast spherical clouds of ejected gas, the faint greenish hue of which reminded them of the Sun's outer planets, particularly the newly discovered Uranus. To this day, these clouds go by the confusing misnomer of planetary nebulae, even though astronomers realized that they could not be seeing planets that far away.</p>
        <p>An understanding of what they were seeing developed over the years. As a star exhausts its primary supply of hydrogen fuel, it moves into  the red giant stage, a time of gradual swelling that can last up to a billion years. It also consumes its helium, producing heavier elements like carbon and oxygen. In the final stages, lasting about 30,000 years, an outer shell of gas is ejected as a ''slow wind,'' expanding at 10 miles a second, and then hotter inner gases are blown out at 1,000 miles a second, or 3.6 million miles an hour.</p>
        <p>This ''fast wind'' eventually plows into the slower-moving outer shell, which presumably shapes the so-called planetary nebulae that astronomers observe. In the star's ultraviolet light, the clouds glow red from heated hydrogen, green from oxygen and blue from helium. This brilliant display probably lasts for only 10,000 years, before the cloud dissipates and leaves behind only a white dwarf, an Earth-sized frozen object so dense that one handful of the dwarf's matter would weigh as much as a 747 airplane.</p>
        <p>More than 1,000 planetary nebulae have been observed, but the few dozen photographed in detail by the Hubble telescope have inspired the freshest thinking about them.</p>
        <p>Some astronomers, for example, now think that the more complex and dazzling patterns of the gaseous clouds are created by interactions between the aging star and unseen companions, either a large planet or another small star in the vicinity. Such an idea is conceivable because many stars come in pairs and large planetlike objects have recently been detected around other stars.</p>
        <p>Perhaps, according to this line of reasoning, the dying star envelops its companion, and the rotation of the smaller object spins up the big star. The centrifugal force of the more rapidly spinning star slings out material in the equatorial plane.</p>
        <p>Dr. Mario Livio, another astronomer at the space telescope institute, likens the effect to that of an eggbeater whipping the gaseous debris into bizarre shapes. That might account for the presence of doughnut-shaped disks of dust that have been seen girdling some dying stars.</p>
        <p>''This doughnut acts almost like a corset, and the material expands outward in a perpendicular way,'' Dr. Livio explained.</p>
        <p>With such a pinching action, gas would spurt out on two sides; the cloud structures on one side of the star would be mirrored on the opposite side. That might explain the symmetrical patterns seen, particularly in the pinwheel, double-jet and butterfly patterns.</p>
        <p>Dr. Terzian of Cornell said he  doubted that the gravitational effects of companion stars could be causing the observed patterns. But he said any theoretical models must start from the observed symmetry of each star's cloud of debris.</p>
        <p>Such symmetry also seems to apply to another aspect of the nebulae that Dr. Terzian and others have been investigating: the red blobs of gas seen at opposite sides in some of the clouds. The blobs were first studied in pictures taken by the Palomar Observatory in California. But they are particularly clear in Hubble pictures of an object designated NGC 6826, which looks something like a green eye; astronomers call it the cat's eye, or blinking, planetary nebula.</p>
        <p>These blobs -- called fliers, an acronym for fast, low-ionization emission regions -- resemble bubbles, are made mostly from nitrogen and are shot out of nebulae in a symmetrical pattern. But Dr. Terzian said it was not possible to tell whether fliers had emerged along the polar or equatorial planes of nebulae. It seems, he said, that they are bubbles of older gas caught in the stellar gale of hot-flowing material from dying stars.</p>
        <p>''To tell you the truth,'' Dr. Terzian said, ''we still don't have an explanation, only speculation, but many planetary nebulae have these fliers at their edges.''</p>
        <p>Astronomers hope that observations with the Hubble's new infrared instruments, installed last February, will further clarify the thinking on this and other mysteries. The infrared detector should provide glimpses of the ejection of material from a dying star at an earlier stage, before the nebulae start to become visible in other wavelengths.</p>
        <p>Astronomers are seeing the Sun's ultimate destiny in these planetary nebulae. Not that anyone has reason for concern. The Sun, already about 4.6 billion years old, is estimated to have enough hydrogen for at least another five billion years of robust life. By that time, judging by the history of extinctions on Earth, there will be no humans around to see the ominous swelling of the Sun's red-giant phase.</p>
        <p>The expanding solar surface might swallow up Earth or stop just short of that. Even if Earth was not swallowed up, the Sun would fill half the sky. The heat would be so intense that it would scorch the planet's atmosphere, vaporizing vegetation and boiling away the oceans.</p>
        <p>''We'll have the ultimate in global warming,'' said Dr. Bond of the space telescope institute.</p>
        <p>The Sun's dying nebula may not match the spectacles being viewed by the Hubble scientists. If the idea of a companion star as eggbeater is correct, the shells of ejected solar gas would probably remain fairly spherical but luminous in many colors.</p>
        <p>After the Sun passes from a red giant to a white dwarf, Earth will be no more than a cold, lifeless cinder, if there is anything left. Somewhere else, though, gravity will eventually sweep up the litter of solar dust into new Suns and new worlds, perhaps another habitat for intelligent beings who would one day look into the sky and marvel at the Sun's death throes, not recognizing them as the source of their being.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
