<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="29DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="DIARY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="940107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DIARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D61339F93AA15755C0A961958260" item-length="1964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN M. ROSEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUPREME COURT  Liberty for Cyberlibertines  In a sweeping endorsement of free speech in cyberspace, the Supreme Court declared unconstitutional a Federal law that was intended to protect minors by making it a crime to put ''indecent'' material on the Internet. The decision delighted a coalition of Internet users, the computer industry and civil liberties groups. In other decisions affecting business, the court gave Federal prosecutors and securities regulators a major victory, ruling that insider trading laws apply to people with confidential information even if they have no connection to the company involved. The court also struck down a landmark $1.3 billion class-action settlement for victims of asbestos exposure; upheld a New Deal-era Federal marketing program that requires agricultural companies to help pay for industrywide advertising, and denied prison guards employed by private companies the immunity from prisoner lawsuits enjoyed by guards on public payrolls.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS  Forget Stocks. Cut Velvet.  Stocks had a zigzag week that left traders' psyches as battered toward the end of the week as prices were on Monday, when they plunged 192 points on fear that the Japanese might sell United States Treasury securities. Tokyo hastily declared that remarks by Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto had been misinterpreted, and the market climbed back up. By the end of the week, prices were back at last week's levels. The Dow Jones industrial average was off 108.79 at 7,687.72, and the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index was down 8.95 at 1,438.15. A much better investment, it seems, was made by Diana, Princess of Wales. At a packed Christie's auction in Manhattan, an off-the-shoulder, ink-blue dinner dress in which she danced at the White House with John Travolta sold for a record $222,500. Altogether the auction of 79 dresses owned by Diana raised $3.25 million for cancer and AIDS charities. The dresses originally cost about $5,000 each, so the gain was more than eightfold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUPREME COURT  Liberty for Cyberlibertines  In a sweeping endorsement of free speech in cyberspace, the Supreme Court declared unconstitutional a Federal law that was intended to protect minors by making it a crime to put ''indecent'' material on the Internet. The decision delighted a coalition of Internet users, the computer industry and civil liberties groups. In other decisions affecting business, the court gave Federal prosecutors and securities regulators a major victory, ruling that insider trading laws apply to people with confidential information even if they have no connection to the company involved. The court also struck down a landmark $1.3 billion class-action settlement for victims of asbestos exposure; upheld a New Deal-era Federal marketing program that requires agricultural companies to help pay for industrywide advertising, and denied prison guards employed by private companies the immunity from prisoner lawsuits enjoyed by guards on public payrolls.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS  Forget Stocks. Cut Velvet.  Stocks had a zigzag week that left traders' psyches as battered toward the end of the week as prices were on Monday, when they plunged 192 points on fear that the Japanese might sell United States Treasury securities. Tokyo hastily declared that remarks by Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto had been misinterpreted, and the market climbed back up. By the end of the week, prices were back at last week's levels. The Dow Jones industrial average was off 108.79 at 7,687.72, and the technology-heavy Nasdaq composite index was down 8.95 at 1,438.15. A much better investment, it seems, was made by Diana, Princess of Wales. At a packed Christie's auction in Manhattan, an off-the-shoulder, ink-blue dinner dress in which she danced at the White House with John Travolta sold for a record $222,500. Altogether the auction of 79 dresses owned by Diana raised $3.25 million for cancer and AIDS charities. The dresses originally cost about $5,000 each, so the gain was more than eightfold.</p>
        <p>THE ENVIRONMENT  Tightening Pollution Rules  President Clinton approved significantly tighter pollution limits on deadly soot and choking smog, while offering states and cities substantial flexibility in reaching the new goals. Ending a fierce behind-the-scenes battle, Mr. Clinton sided with the head of the Environmental Protection Agency, Carol M. Browner, against the concerns of his economic advisers. They had balked in the face of industry complaints that the rules would cost far more than they were worth. Earlier in the week, European leaders were openly critical of the United States at a United Nations-sponsored conference, demanding that Washington be far more aggressive in reducing emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>TOBACCO SETTLEMENT  A Bargain at $368.5 Billion?  Will there indeed be a $368.5 billion tobacco settlement, or is it all a pipe dream? President Clinton called the agreement, which is intended to pay for public service advertising and medical costs, flawed but a beginning. It might hobble the Government's regulation of nicotine, he said. Critics contended that it was too favorable to the tobacco industry, and a panel of public health experts named to advise Congress labeled it unacceptable. The state Attorneys General who negotiated the landmark pact defended it. ''It's the best anyone has put forward,'' said Christine Gregoire of Washington.'' If it is accepted, Philip Morris will provide the bulk -- $6.5 billion -- of the initial payment of $10 billion.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL COMPUTERS  They Call Them 'User Friendly'  Today's personal computers have too many features and demand that users learn far too much. Calling the machines ''user friendly'' because of their endless choice of fonts and screen patterns ''is tantamount to dressing a chimpanzee in a green hospital gown and earnestly parading it as a surgeon.'' The technophobe who uttered these words? None other than Dr. Michael L. Dertouzos, head of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology's computer laboratory. ''People should really revolt,'' he said. ''I think we should take up arms.'' But children, of course, can master the monsters. So William H. Gates, the co-founder of Microsoft and the nation's richest person, is creating the Gates Library Foundation. It will spend $200 million over five years to bring new computers and the Internet into the nation's public libraries.</p>
        <p>DIGITAL TV  Giving Broadcasters a Break  In April, Federal regulators lent each of the nation's 1,600 television stations a second channel so they could do parallel broadcasts -- standard and digital. Once the transition to new high-definition digital broadcasting was complete, the extra channels were to be vacated, and the Government would auction them for a projected $5 billion. But under provisions that lobbyists have managed to work into House and Senate budget bills, the broadcast-television industry could keep the additional channels indefinitely, while possibly delaying the introduction of digital television broadcasts far beyond Government-set deadlines.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY  Confidence at a 28-Year High  Americans' confidence in the economy continued to climb this month, suggesting that consumer spending may rebound. The Conference Board said that its index of consumer confidence reached a 28-year high of 129.6, up from May's revised index of 127.9. And little wonder. The Commerce Department reported that the economy grew at a slightly faster pace than estimated in the first quarter, at a 5.9 percent annual rate, but inflation remained in check. Also easing fears of inflation, durable-goods orders unexpectedly fell six-tenths of 1 percent in May. Home resales in the month also confounded analysts' expectations, increasing 4.4 percent.</p>
        <p>THE HAND-OVER  Red Chips Over Hong Kong  As the sun sets on 156 years of British rule, the Hong Kong stock market's Hang Seng Index rose 68.77 points, or five-tenths of 1 percent, to a record 15,196.79, led by the red chips -- the shares of China-backed investment companies. China Everbright International Ltd. jumped 36 percent, and Cosco Pacific Ltd. soared 18 percent. Chinese companies, eager to draw on Hong Kong's expertise in global marketing, see enormous business opportunities when Beijing takes over on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>MERGERS  Compaq's $3 Billion Deal  Compaq Computer agreed to swap stock worth $3 billion for Tandem Computers, which makes fault-tolerant systems -- large mainframe-like machines used by banks, airlines and telecommunications centers that cannot risk computer failure. Compaq's goal is to grow beyond PC's -- where it is already No. 1 -- to become the world's third-largest computer company after I.B.M. and Hewlett-Packard. In other big merger moves, Union Pacific Resources began a hostile $4 billion offer for Pennzoil, and Wachovia agreed to buy Central Fidelity Banks of Richmond for stock worth $2.3 billion. The Zurich Group plans to acquire Scudder Stevens &amp; Clark for $1.67 billion in cash and stock, and Nationsbank was reported to be negotiating to buy Montgomery Securities for as much as $1.2 billion. Other bidders were also expected.</p>
        <p>DIARY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
