<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Downsizing Activism: Greenpeace Is Cutting Back</title>
    <meta content="16GREE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="958082"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Greenpeace (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Carey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DE1438F935A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="1761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Downsizing Activism: Greenpeace Is Cutting Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Carey</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Greenpeace, world's best-known environmental action group, is suffering through biggest rentrenchment ever in US because of weak finances, plummeting membership and $2.6 million deficit halfway through year; is disassembling all 10 of its permanent branch offices and ending signature door-to-door canvassing; is laying off about 335 of 400 staff members and cutting annual budget for US to $21 million from $29 million; is narrowing focus, planning to concentrate more on campaigns against global warming and forest destruction and somewhat less on toxic waste and overfishing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 48 hours of daredevil dangling on ropes from a bridge in Seattle, trying to block outgoing trawlers in a recent protest against overfishing, Greenpeace staff members returned to solid ground, only to be told that the environmental group had just laid three of them off.</p>
        <p>Here in Boston last week, a staff member in the group's Back Bay office unhappily carted out a giant Greenpeace sign, no longer needed now that the place was all but abandoned. And in a handful of other cities from Minneapolis to Santa Cruz, Calif., Greenpeace offices had been dismantled or were in the last stages of closing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 48 hours of daredevil dangling on ropes from a bridge in Seattle, trying to block outgoing trawlers in a recent protest against overfishing, Greenpeace staff members returned to solid ground, only to be told that the environmental group had just laid three of them off.</p>
        <p>Here in Boston last week, a staff member in the group's Back Bay office unhappily carted out a giant Greenpeace sign, no longer needed now that the place was all but abandoned. And in a handful of other cities from Minneapolis to Santa Cruz, Calif., Greenpeace offices had been dismantled or were in the last stages of closing.</p>
        <p>Around the country, Greenpeace officials say, the world's best-known  environmental action group is suffering through the biggest retrenchment it has ever seen in the United States. It is disassembling all 10 of its permanent branch offices and ending the signature door-to-door canvassing that led one critic to call it the Avon Lady of the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>It is also laying off about 335 of its 400 staff members, most of them canvassers. The spirit is still willing, officials say, but the finances are weak, and in the face of plummeting membership and a deficit of $2.6 million halfway through the year, Greenpeace is cutting its annual budget in the United States to $21 million from $29 million. The group is also narrowing its focus, planning to concentrate more on campaigns against global warming and forest destruction and somewhat less on toxic waste and overfishing.</p>
        <p>''If this is a signal that the public has become so apathetic or uninformed about our environmental devastation, it's tragic,'' said Niaz Dorry, the Boston staff member carting off the sign for a smaller office in Gloucester, Mass.</p>
        <p>Since its grandstanding beginning in 1971, when a dozen protesters in a small boat sought to block nuclear testing in the Aleutian Islands, Greenpeace has weathered many an internal storm, many a tactical mistake and many a cutback.</p>
        <p>But the scale of the current downsizing has prompted a new spell of particularly intense soul-searching, and the 170-member board of the United States arm of Greenpeace  met in Washington last weekend to discuss what went wrong and what should be done.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace International has offices in 32 countries, a worldwide budget of nearly $146 million and worldwide membership of almost 3 million people. Global membership has remained stable while the United States organization's memberships have fallen. Because Greenpeace is expanding its work in Asian and Latin American countries -- work that the United States offices subsidize -- it can no longer afford a financial drain in its American operations, said Kristen Engberg, acting director in the United States.</p>
        <p>The United States group's cutbacks have prompted outsiders to analyze what the group's problems say about how environmental organizations in this country have had to change in the last few years as the world has changed around them.</p>
        <p>The whales are pretty well saved, environmental historians and top officials in several other national groups say; the Clinton White House is generally friendly to the environment; many more businesses try to respect the environment than ever before, and other national groups have developed highly sophisticated lobbying and outreach methods.</p>
        <p>It could well be, some said, that in an era when environmental issues seem to hinge more on complex trade-offs than on an all-or-nothing approach, the time has passed for the classic Greenpeace tactics of telegenic ''direct actions'' in which protesters rode tiny inflatable motorboats to face down whalers.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace, said Rindy O'Brien, vice president of public policy for the Wilderness Society, has tended to look for ways to publicize problems instead of ways to actually solve them. Her comments echoed longstanding criticism by others that Greenpeace is too much of a self-promotion machine.</p>
        <p>''I do think the public, in more of the political realm, are looking for solutions rather than maybe extremists,'' Ms. O'Brien said, ''and I think that separates Greenpeace from the other environmental groups.''</p>
        <p>Four things happened that hurt Greenpeace, said a top official at another environmental group who insisted on anonymity. With an international moratorium on commercial whaling, Greenpeace lost a flagship issue; its tactics became more familiar and so drew less attention; it fell into a debilitating internal debate about its own mission, and it shifted more toward helping local environmental groups behind the scenes, which lowered its profile.</p>
        <p>''They ended up with a confused and weak public perception of what they were,'' the official said. ''They're not really a grass-roots organization like the Sierra Club or the Audubon Society. When people stopped seeing Greenpeace on TV and started reading confusing things about it, they drifted away.''</p>
        <p>But Greenpeace officials say that though they will be narrowing their focus and shifting from permanent branch offices to mobile campaign teams, their basic philosophy and tactics of uncompromising, high-profile protests will remain in force. And they have always sought solutions with industry and government, the officials say, but those efforts never received wide attention.</p>
        <p>The cutbacks, Greenpeace staff members say, are mainly a reflection of past poor management, including shoddy record-keeping that allowed membership to drop to about 400,000 from 1.2 million in 1991, and annual United States donations to fall to about $25 million from $45 million. The staff members also say that by dropping the canvassers and the offices from which they worked, the organization can do its work more efficiently.</p>
        <p>''The canvass was a costly operation in terms of its administrative and overhead cost,'' said Ms. Engberg, the acting director. ''By having these fixed costs of 10 offices, it gave the U.S. organization less flexibility in how it could spend its money on campaigning.''</p>
        <p>The canvassers' function was dual: They signed people up for dues-paying memberships, at a minimum of $30 a year for those who wanted to receive the group's magazine, and educated them on current issues and campaigns.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace International has been headed for the last two years by Thilo Bode, a bottom-line German economist who has also overseen the streamlining of several offices in other countries.</p>
        <p>But the United States group is particularly important, said Ms. Engberg, because each national office sets aside a percentage of its proceeds to be redistributed for work in needier countries. The United States organization, which contributes 18 percent, is one of the four biggest Greenpeace branches, she said.</p>
        <p>''It's a very difficult but necessary decision for the health of Greenpeace around the world,'' Ms. Engberg said.</p>
        <p>As Greenpeace's work has stabilized in Western countries, the international organization has focused increasingly on environmental problems in Southeast Asia, China and Latin America -- work it needs American money to help pay for.</p>
        <p>The decision to cut back the United States offices was made by the organization's board of directors for the United States, an executive group that could not be overridden at the meeting last weekend of the board of all voting members. The weekend meeting created a committee to plot a strategy for the future of Greenpeace in the United States.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace staff members in United States offices also attributed the downsizing to new competition for charity money from social service groups in this period of cutbacks in Government support for the poor.</p>
        <p>''We used to compete with other environmental organizations,'' said Mark Floegel, a Seattle staff member who is being laid off. ''Now we compete with the homeless. People who gave $50 a year to Greenpeace now have to decide between that and Save the Children and a homeless shelter.''</p>
        <p>Other national environmental groups, however, say that their membership and donations have stayed about steady over the last several years. In the period when  Greenpeace lost 800,000 members, for example, the Sierra Club has stayed roughly steady at 600,000 and the Wilderness Society at 250,000.</p>
        <p>The main explanation, some Greenpeace officials acknowledge, may be that the group was simply  not equipped to sustain the membership boom that occurred after  French frogmen sank the group's ship, the Rainbow Warrior, while it was trying to block nuclear testing in the Pacific in 1985.</p>
        <p>''There's no question our development office made tremendous mistakes,'' said Dave Batke, a research coordinator in the Seattle office. ''Names were not entered when people joined Greenpeace. There was some mismanagement.''</p>
        <p>Faulty recruitment arrangements may be relatively simple to remedy; what is less clear to both members and environmental historians is whether the tactic of closing branch offices, while keeping its Washington headquarters largely intact, is a good idea.</p>
        <p>''If they're going to concentrate on Beltway stuff, they're getting into a crowded market,'' said Philip Shabecoff, a former reporter for The New York Times and author of ''A New Name for Peace,'' (University Press of New England, 1996), a book on international environmentalism. ''I personally think it's a big mistake for Greenpeace. They had their own mission in the environmental movement -- they were kind of the troublemakers, the people who made noise and raised tension on issues, and on top of that they were one of the few national groups that actually went out door to door.''</p>
        <p>Aside from possible doubts about the decision, staff members in Greenpeace offices around the country have been grappling with the pain of losing jobs that are much more than jobs to most.</p>
        <p>''Certain jobs I've had in my life were 9-to-5 jobs,'' said Mr. Floegel in Seattle. ''Greenpeace is a way people identify themselves. It's like if you take a bunch of priests and tell them they're laid off because of cutbacks.</p>
        <p>''There's a sense of loss about the work. That's ahead of people's concern for their well-being and how they're going to make the rent.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
