<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trading on the Pollution Exchange; Global Warming Plan Would Make Emissions a Commodity</title>
    <meta content="Y24WAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bolivia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Electric Power Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pacificorp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Petroleum Co Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3D6103EF937A15753C1A961958260" item-length="2074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trading on the Pollution Exchange; Global Warming Plan Would Make Emissions a Commodity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rights to spew carbon dioxide into atmosphere will eventually be traded by energy producers, utilities and even investors on futures exchanges if Pres Clinton's global-warming plan becomes reality; while Clinton Administration's plan for curtailing greenhouse gases demands no immediate action by businesses, it confirms that a system of tradable emissions permits will figure prominently in any long-term effort to control pollutants; such a system would allow companies that voluntarily reduce emissions below certain level to sell difference to others as unused 'rights' to pollute; American Electric Power, which owns coal-burning operation in Rockport, Ind, is working on pilot project with Pacificorp and British Petroleum to spare five million acres of Bolivian forests from logging; forest absorbs carbon dioxide, effectively storing millions of tons of carbon that would otherwise end up in atmosphere; drawings; charts; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If President Clinton has his way, rights to spew carbon dioxide into the atmosphere will eventually be traded by energy producers, utilities and even investors on exchanges the way pork bellies, German marks and interest rate futures change hands today.</p>
        <p>While the Administration's plan for curtailing greenhouse gases -- announced Wednesday in preparation for the world climate change talks in Kyoto, Japan, in December -- demands no immediate action by businesses, it confirms that a system of tradable emissions permits will figure prominently in any long-term effort to control pollutants. Such a system, already being used under the Clean Air Act of 1990 to cut sulfur emissions, would allow companies that voluntarily reduce emissions below a certain level to sell the difference to others as unused ''rights'' to pollute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If President Clinton has his way, rights to spew carbon dioxide into the atmosphere will eventually be traded by energy producers, utilities and even investors on exchanges the way pork bellies, German marks and interest rate futures change hands today.</p>
        <p>While the Administration's plan for curtailing greenhouse gases -- announced Wednesday in preparation for the world climate change talks in Kyoto, Japan, in December -- demands no immediate action by businesses, it confirms that a system of tradable emissions permits will figure prominently in any long-term effort to control pollutants. Such a system, already being used under the Clean Air Act of 1990 to cut sulfur emissions, would allow companies that voluntarily reduce emissions below a certain level to sell the difference to others as unused ''rights'' to pollute.</p>
        <p>The reliance on free markets in reducing carbon emissions to 1990 levels has been greeted with enthusiasm by specialists who have long argued that managing the task with traditional regulation would be hugely wasteful.</p>
        <p>''An approach that promises to reduce the cost of containment by 90 percent is certainly worth a try,'' said Richard Richels of the Electric Power Research Institute in California.</p>
        <p>But many economists caution that emissions trading is no panacea. They emphasize the desirability of bringing developing countries into the trading systems as soon as possible and the need for care in designing the control mechanisms that will redirect billions or even trillions of dollars in pollution-control investments worldwide.</p>
        <p>''At this point, the learning is more important than the doing,'' suggested Robert Hahn of the American Enterprise Institute, a research group in Washington.</p>
        <p>The Administration's plan has been criticized by many foreign governments that will also attend the Kyoto conference, where the participants will try to work out a global climate treaty. The critics say the American plan is not aggressive enough because it would not roll back emissions to 1990 levels until sometime between 2008 and 2012. Whatever happens in Kyoto, Mr. Clinton seems committed to emissions trading.</p>
        <p>It is no secret why: It costs less and keeps Big Brother in the background.</p>
        <p>To date, the most ambitious use of tradable permits has been in containing the sulfur emissions from power plants that contribute to acid rain. Under the Clean Air Act, total sulfur emissions were capped by giving electric utilities rights to emit sulfur roughly in proportion to their lower, 1980 emissions levels. Companies that reduce emissions below their allowance by closing plants, switching fuels or attaching chemical scrubbers to their smokestacks are free to sell their surplus pollution rights, while others are free to exceed their limits by buying those rights.</p>
        <p>The market for sulfur emissions has flourished as utilities with low-cost sources of clean fuel have found it profitable to operate within the Government standards and sell part of their allotments to pollute. Last year, the market price of sulfur allowances averaged just more than $100 a ton.</p>
        <p>''Emissions have been reduced at a cost far lower than the most optimistic forecasts,'' said Richard Sandor, the chief executive of Centre Financial Products and vice chairman of the Chicago Board of Trade.</p>
        <p>Some economists are confident that similar serendipities await a trading system for carbon dioxide and perhaps other greenhouse gases. Global warming occurs when such gases accumulate in the atmosphere, trapping heat.</p>
        <p>''Since none of the effect is localized, carbon is a perfect pollutant for emissions trading,'' argued Dan Dudek, an economist at the Environmental Defense Fund who was instrumental in pushing through the sulfur program in 1990.</p>
        <p>But many a slip is possible between cup and lip. For one thing, the scale would be much larger. A few hundred utilities with a few thousand power plants emit most of the sulfur regulated under the Clean Air Act. Carbon dioxide, however, comes not only from power plants but also from hundreds of millions of boilers and vehicles, which could not possibly be monitored like electric utilities.</p>
        <p>That suggests the need for a different approach, says Robert Stavins, an economist at Harvard University's Kennedy School of Government. He suggests that producers of coal, oil and natural gas be required to obtain emissions permits equal to the carbon content of their products rather than putting the burden on fuel consumers.</p>
        <p>Limits on volumes that could be sold would raise the competitive price of all carbon fuels. But because coal emits more carbon dioxide for every unit of heat than natural gas, the price of coal would rise far more than the price of gas. That would give utilities an incentive to abandon coal.</p>
        <p>Under the sulfur trading system, electric utilities receive roughly $1 billion (at current trading prices) worth of permits free each year -- a large but not overwhelming benefit to a $100 billion industry. And because utilities are regulated by the states, virtually all of the saving is passed on to rate payers. By contrast, if fossil-fuel producers received free carbon permits, there is no reason to think that the windfall, which could measure in the tens of billions of dollars annually, would go to consumers.</p>
        <p>The Government would, in theory, have the option of auctioning carbon emissions permits rather than giving them away. But the political battle over limiting emissions is likely to be fierce: reducing carbon output to 1990 levels, for example, would almost certainly require phasing out coal as a boiler fuel within a few decades. Thus, while economists see merit in auctioning permits and using the proceeds to cut other taxes, coal producers and their unions would most likely work aggressively to block legislation that did not give them a big piece of the action.</p>
        <p>The potential gains from international trading of carbon emissions permits are even greater than from domestic trading. While the industrialized world has a multitrillion-dollar investment in boilers and engines that would have to be scrapped rapidly to reach 1990 emissions levels, the third world has opportunities galore for easy carbon conservation.</p>
        <p>Buildings have not been insulated; industrial boilers have not been retrofitted with efficient combustion systems. Most important, rapidly growing economies -- notably China -- have yet to sink huge sums in modern coal-fired boilers or fuel-hogging vehicles.</p>
        <p>Opportunities to weaken the link between economic growth and carbon emissions are complemented by opportunities to preserve natural carbon ''sinks'' -- vast inventories of carbon stored in trees. Two big utilities, American Electric Power and Pacificorp, along with British Petroleum, are experimenting with a program to spare five million acres of forest in Bolivia from logging in what amounts to an act of philanthropy. The estimated cost of sequestering a ton of carbon this way is just 37 cents, less than 1 percent of the cost of many emissions-reducing industrial projects contemplated for Europe and North America.</p>
        <p>The intuition that the greatest opportunities are in poor countries is borne out by computer simulations. William Nordhaus of Yale University estimates that the cost of meeting the developed world's commitment to getting back to 1990 emissions levels would be cut by at least 85 percent if the containment largely consisted of paying developing countries to adopt a carbon-lean growth strategy.</p>
        <p>A strategy that used international trading to focus on containing carbon emissions in developing countries would also pay local dividends, such as reducing urban pollution. ''Increasing fuel efficiency and switching to natural gas would incidentally mean lower levels of smog, which now threatens health in virtually all the big cities,'' notes Mr. Dudek of the Environmental Defense Fund.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the difficulties in creating and enforcing a trading system that crosses borders are formidable, beginning with the problem of apportioning the initial obligations to contain carbon.</p>
        <p>The European Community wants to start from a 1990 emissions base line, which would cost it little because Europe would receive credit for the conversion of Britain and eastern Germany from coal to natural gas in the 1990's. Meanwhile, Brazil, China, India, Indonesia and most of the rest of the third world want controls to kick in only when their per capita emissions have reached parity with the West -- a formula for doing nothing until the middle of the next century.</p>
        <p>Thomas Schelling, an economist at the University of Maryland's School of Public Policy, emphasizes the distinction between making promises to reduce emissions by some amount at a certain date and translating talk into action. ''Global emissions trading is an elegant idea,'' he said, ''but I cannot seriously envision national representatives sitting down to divide up rights in perpetuity worth a trillion dollars.''</p>
        <p>That explains why President Clinton, who on Wednesday reaffirmed that ''developing countries must participate in meeting the challenge of climate change,'' seems willing to fudge the issue for a while by encouraging voluntary investment of American cash and technology in third world efforts to contain emissions.</p>
        <p>The American Electric Power-British Petroleum forest preservation project in Bolivia fits the model well. And Mr. Clinton is apparently planning to bolster such voluntary efforts by guaranteeing participants credits against mandatory emissions limitations highly likely to be imposed after 2008.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Stavins of Harvard argues that monitoring such deals is bound to be problematic. Apart from the practical issues of insuring compliance in countries with inadequate infrastructure, corrupt governments and courts unwilling to enforce contracts, he is concerned that in agreements between companies, ''both parties will have powerful incentives to exaggerate the gains.''</p>
        <p>American policy makers thus face some difficult issues. Market-based strategies to contain global warming promise far more bang for a buck than traditional regulation. But carrying out such efforts poses new problems that engender skepticism, even among free-market advocates. ''We just have not thought through the mechanics of international trading,'' argued Mr. Nordhaus of Yale.</p>
        <p>That is why many economists and some environmentalists are quietly pleased with the part of the Administration's plan that would delay mandatory market-based limitations for another decade.</p>
        <p>''If it's worth doing,'' argued Paul Portney, president of Resources for the Future in Washington, ''surely it's worth waiting long enough to do the job right.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
