<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State to Buy 339 Acres For Preserve At Montauk</title>
    <meta content="22LAND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="924666"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Montauk (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wetlands</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDC153EF931A15757C0A961958260" item-length="429" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State to Buy 339 Acres For Preserve At Montauk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State is preparing to purchase 339 acres of undeveloped wetlands near Montauk Point as part of its efforts to establish uninterrupted belt of protected beaches, forests and scrubland in Long Island's East End (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The state is preparing to purchase 339 acres of undeveloped wetlands near Montauk Point as part of its efforts to establish an uninterrupted belt of protected beaches, forests and scrubland in Long Island's East End, Gov. George E. Pataki is expected to announce on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Known as the Sanctuary, the property adjoins Montauk State Park, the home of the popular light house, Montauk County Park and beachfront property that is owned by conservation groups. Environmentalists described it as the largest privately owned, undeveloped piece of property in the Montauk area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The state is preparing to purchase 339 acres of undeveloped wetlands near Montauk Point as part of its efforts to establish an uninterrupted belt of protected beaches, forests and scrubland in Long Island's East End, Gov. George E. Pataki is expected to announce on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Known as the Sanctuary, the property adjoins Montauk State Park, the home of the popular light house, Montauk County Park and beachfront property that is owned by conservation groups. Environmentalists described it as the largest privately owned, undeveloped piece of property in the Montauk area.</p>
        <p>Under the plan Mr. Pataki is to outline on Tuesday, the property will first be purchased by the Nature Conservancy, a private environmental group, from its current owners, a group of investors. Using money generated by the $1.75 environmental bond act that passed last year, the state will buy the tract from the Nature Conservancy for $4.2 million later this year.</p>
        <p>''This is just another example of where this Governor has marched forward with the bond act to protect sensitive land that, particularly when the economy is booming, could be subject to development and then lost to the people of the state forever,'' said Carol Ash, state director for the Nature Conservancy.</p>
        <p>Nature Conservancy officials described the Sanctuary as rolling scrub, crisscrossed by fresh-water streams, swamps and forests where trees have been gnarled and stunted by the whipping salt-water winds of the ocean. It is home to several endangered species, including spotted turtles and the blue spotted salamander, they said. The state plans to designate the property a nature preserve, meaning it will not be open to the public.</p>
        <p>The Long Island event is just one of four Earth Day news conferences Mr. Pataki has planned.</p>
        <p>In the morning, he plans to appear in Manhattan to renew his call for an emissions testing program for large trucks. Currently, large trucks are not required to undergo emissions tests when they are registered, even though they are widely considered a major source of air pollution, particularly in large cities.</p>
        <p>After the Long Island event, the Governor plans to fly by helicopter first to Syracuse, where he will stand with United States Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato to endorse Federal legislation designed to reduce acid rain, and then to the Albany area, where he will unveil several projects financed by the bond act that are intended to protect drinking water.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
