<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Rules Imposed For Refrigerators: Efficiency, at a Cost</title>
    <meta content="24FRID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="925133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Refrigerators</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DD113EF937A15757C0A961958260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Rules Imposed For Refrigerators: Efficiency, at a Cost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Dept says refrigerators sold in 2001 will have to use 30 percent less electricity than those now on market; rule is meant to cut electric bills by over $1 billion a year by 2010 and reduce air pollution from power plants; it will add about $80 to cost of standard refrigerator-freezer but will lower its annual operating cost by about $20; with over 8.5 million refrigerators sold annually, power saved will eventually be equivalent to production of eight large power plants; change, which updates rule that took effect in 1993, has been delayed for years by opposition from manufacturers and one-year moratorium ordered by Congress (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Refrigerators sold in 2001 will have to use 30 percent less electricity than those now on the market, the Energy Department said today, ordering a change meant to cut electric bills by more than $1 billion a year by 2010 and reduce air pollution from power plants.</p>
        <p>The rule, which sets minimum standards for the most power-hungry appliance in most American homes, will add about $80 to the cost of a standard 22-cubic-foot refrigerator-freezer but will lower its annual operating cost by about $20. With more than 8.5 million refrigerators sold annually, the power saved will eventually be equivalent to the production of eight large power plants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Refrigerators sold in 2001 will have to use 30 percent less electricity than those now on the market, the Energy Department said today, ordering a change meant to cut electric bills by more than $1 billion a year by 2010 and reduce air pollution from power plants.</p>
        <p>The rule, which sets minimum standards for the most power-hungry appliance in most American homes, will add about $80 to the cost of a standard 22-cubic-foot refrigerator-freezer but will lower its annual operating cost by about $20. With more than 8.5 million refrigerators sold annually, the power saved will eventually be equivalent to the production of eight large power plants.</p>
        <p>The change, which updates a rule that took effect in 1993, had been delayed for years by opposition from manufacturers and a one-year moratorium ordered by Congress. The announcement today sets off a scramble by manufacturers, who already must find a substitute for the ozone-depleting chemicals they have used for decades to make the foam insulation in refrigerator walls that keeps the cold in and the warm out. Improving that insulation is key to raising efficiency, but manufacturers want to avoid reducing interior space or making the box bigger than standard kitchen designs allow. The chemical, which is also used in the refrigeration system, but they have found a substitute for that use.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Federico F. Pena said manufacturers and energy conservation groups had agreed to the new standard.</p>
        <p>''Not to steal from the President, but we're building a fridge for the 21st century,'' Mr. Pena said with a laugh.</p>
        <p>An aide, referring to bitter battles over how strict the new rules should be and when they should take effect, referred to the settlement as an end to the cold war.</p>
        <p>Lloyd D. Ward, president of Maytag Appliances, said manufacturers agreed to the settlement in part out of a desire for predictablity. And part of the compromise was a delay in the new standard, which will take effect about the same time as the Environmental Protection Agency ban on ozone-depleting chemicals, so both changes could be made at once.</p>
        <p>Others involved in the negotiations said Mr. Pena had tried hard to resolve the issue.</p>
        <p>David B. Goldstein, co-director of the energy program at the Natural Resources Defense Council, which has lobbied for years for greater efficiency, said that when the new models were phased in they would reduce power plants' output of nitrogen oxides, a component of acid rain and smog, by 0.7 percent. New standards for air-conditioners, clothes washers and other appliances are still in the works, Mr. Goldstein said.</p>
        <p>Under the new rules, a typical 22-cubic-foot refrigerator-freezer with automatic defrosting will use about 535 kilowatt-hours a year, down 30 percent from 767 kilowatt-hours for an average model now. In 1978, when a standard refrigerator was 20 cubic feet, average energy consumption was 1,548 kilowatt-hours per year.</p>
        <p>The annual difference between the current standard and the new one would keep a 55-watt light bulb lit from dusk to dawn for a year.</p>
        <p>Some new energy-efficient products -- like compact fluorescent bulbs -- have not cut consumption as much as expected, because as electricity consumption per hour goes down, people use the products more.</p>
        <p>But David M. Nemtzow, president of the Alliance to Save Energy, said better refrigerators would cut consumption.</p>
        <p>''Refrigerators are always on, and no matter what the price of electricity, you don't say, I'm going to leave the door open,'' Mr. Nemtzow said.</p>
        <p>There has been declining interest in conservation, with the energy crises of 1974 and 1979-80 fading from memory and most power companies scaling back on the electricity conservation programs they financed in the late 80's and early 90's. In addition, the price of electricity has been falling for the last few years.</p>
        <p>The extra cost of a more efficient refrigerator should be a popular investment, experts say. The Energy Department figures the cash outlay should earn a 20 percent rate of return, year in, year out, tax free. But Mr. Nemtzow said more than 40 percent of refrigerators were bought by people like landlords and builders, who will never pay for the electricity the appliances consume.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
