<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MINDING YOUR BUSINESS ; Where to Go to Make Some Really Cold Cash</title>
    <meta content="14MIND$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="MINDING YOUR BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Pole</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prag, Elliott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pedersen-Pietersen, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5DE1139F937A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="1511" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MINDING YOUR BUSINESS ; Where to Go to Make Some Really Cold Cash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA PEDERSEN-PIETERSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pedersen-Pietersen, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Laura Pedersen-Pietersen responds to Elliott Prag's letter on becoming a cook at South Pole; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Q. I'm told one can make a lot of money as a cook at the South Pole. How do I go about getting a job there?</p>
        <p>ELLIOTT PRAG  Detroit</p>
        <p>A. East Hampton it's not. Even the masochistically inclined will tell you there are better places below the Equator to get a kitchen job this fall than in Antarctica, the world's coldest, driest, windiest and most remote continent, where summer temperatures range from a balmy 40 degrees Fahrenheit to 40 below.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Q. I'm told one can make a lot of money as a cook at the South Pole. How do I go about getting a job there?</p>
        <p>ELLIOTT PRAG  Detroit</p>
        <p>A. East Hampton it's not. Even the masochistically inclined will tell you there are better places below the Equator to get a kitchen job this fall than in Antarctica, the world's coldest, driest, windiest and most remote continent, where summer temperatures range from a balmy 40 degrees Fahrenheit to 40 below.</p>
        <p>Picture a land one-fifth larger than the United States and Mexico, 98.4 percent of it covered by ice and the rest by wind-scoured rocks. Since the establishment of the Little America encampment by Adm. Richard E. Byrd in 1929, the United States has had a major presence there, exploring the polar region, its ecosystems and climate, using the vast ice shield as a scientific platform for studying not only the earth's upper atmosphere but also near-outer space. It was in Antarctica, site of the cleanest air in today's world, that we first learned the character and causes of the ozone hole, of global warming and, from a meteorite pried out of  the ice, of the possibility of extraterrestrial life on Mars.</p>
        <p>More revelations may be forthcoming. By 2005, the 25-year-old dome-shaped South Pole station will undergo a multimillion-dollar renovation that will require much manpower and should greatly increase the ability to do modern scientific research.</p>
        <p>Still, considering that for now, fewer than 200 people a year make the three-hour ski-plane flight from the main American base at McMurdo Sound to work at the geographic South Pole, I don't think there will be much demand for a sous-chef. But whoever works in the kitchen at the Amundsen-Scott polar station will still need an aptitude for creative cooking. Much of the fare is canned, frozen or freeze-dried, though bread is baked fresh daily and soups are made from scratch. One specialite de la maison is ''buzz bars'' -- brownies with chocolate-covered espresso beans baked into them.</p>
        <p>Food supplies, flown in periodically from New Zealand, often arrive in odd proportions; for instance, a huge bundle of green onions, but no lettuce or any other salad makings. This might lead one to ponder the fortunes awaiting the person who sets up Antarctica's first sled-through fast-food joint.</p>
        <p>Seriously, your source was probably referring to joining the support staff at one of the three American scientific research facilities and two ships operated under the aegis of the National Science Foundation. Each year, the United States (one of 26 nations studying Antarctica) deploys about 650 people to perform scientific research and an additional 2,500 to fill an array of support jobs in areas like global communications, data entry, hospital services, safety training, housing construction, vehicle maintenance, firefighting, housekeeping, waste management, recreation, airfield crash rescue, janitorial services and, yes, food handling. Those numbers will grow with the renovation project.</p>
        <p>(The National Science Foundation will also provide field support for a few artists, writers, historians and scholars who wish to  experience the bottom of the world, though it will not pay them.)</p>
        <p>Most jobs require an uninterrupted four- to six-month stint during the austral summer months, October through February. The ranks thin during the winter months, when the weather can be diabolical: temperatures as low as 117 degrees below zero, hurricane-strength winds and blinding snowstorms that can last three or more days. Despite all this, many workers go back for more.</p>
        <p>While there are no hardship bonuses, the pay for nonscientific work isn't bad. Salaries are based on Denver-area wages and range from $300 a week for unskilled labor to $1,200 for managers and those with technical skills. A cook makes $400 to $600 for a 54-hour workweek plus a 16 percent bonus for completing the stint. A repeat visit would earn a 5 percent base pay increase and an 18 percent completion bonus.</p>
        <p>However, you would probably save more money than if you worked stateside because your expenses are paid and, well, there aren't many places to spend your money (though there is an A.T.M. at McMurdo Station). Rob Holmes, a meteorologist who has worked several stints at an Antarctica  weather station, says he has his paychecks deposited directly into his bank account, collecting interest until his return to Oregon, Wis.</p>
        <p>The research stations are small communities, with a variety of jobs and activities.  Off-hour pursuits include hiking, cross-country skiing, crafts, sports, movies, and -- surprise -- science lectures.</p>
        <p>''There's a small PX-like store for souvenirs, alcohol and toiletries, a few bars and you can always order from Lands' End or L. L. Bean,'' Mr. Holmes said. ''Just don't ask for overnight delivery.''</p>
        <p>That's some Antarctish humor, because the sun never sets during part of the summer, so there is no night. E-mail, satellite TV and Internet access have also lessened the isolation, so you don't have to worry about arriving at McMurdo, the only United States installation south of Guantanamo Bay with a bowling alley, and being greeted by a bunch of hirsute green-stamp collectors grabbing at your lapels and demanding, ''Who shot J.R.?''</p>
        <p>If you are interested in nonscientific work in Antarctica, you can get in touch with the  Antarctic Support Associates in Englewood, Colo., (800 688-8606, extension 3198), the main contractor supplying the National Science Foundation with support staff. The contractor usually starts accepting summer job applications in April.</p>
        <p>The process is essentially the same as seeking employment stateside unless you specifically ask for a ''winter-over'' job.  Those who do will have to pass a psychological test and an extensive physical exam because medical care is limited and emergency evacuation impossible during the winter.</p>
        <p>Some winter workers are advised to travel extremely light -- in particular, by getting rid of their impacted wisdom teeth before embarking. Pregnant women need not apply.</p>
        <p>Incidentally, more women than ever are signing up for Antarctic duty, noted Rebecca L. Johnson, author of ''Braving the Frozen Frontier: Women Working in Antarctica'' (Lerner, 1997, $17.96).</p>
        <p>''You'll see women working in all the traditionally male-dominated fields, including construction and engineering,'' she said, finding remarkably little sexism on the job. ''Ironically, there's a larger percentage of men working in food service.''</p>
        <p>After their selection, the workers go to Christchurch, on New Zealand's South Island, where they receive their cold-weather gear, take a safety training course and then take a five-hour flight to McMurdo Station.</p>
        <p>To pursue study in Antarctica as a scientist or research assistant, one may call the National Science Foundation (703 306-1234) or visit its Web site at http://www.nsf.gov/.</p>
        <p>''Antarctica is the place for scientists in many disciplines to really make their mark,'' said Dr. Bernard Stonehouse, an authority on Antarctica at the Scott Polar Research Institute in Cambridge, England, and author of the forthcoming ''Antarctica, the Traveller's Guide'' (Harold Martin &amp; Redman, 1997, $21.95).</p>
        <p>Coincidentally, say a number of travel-trend spotters, Antarctica beckons as a destination for plucky tourists. This year, more than 12,000 visitors are expected to touch down on ''the ice.'' By the millennium, as many as 20,000 will head for the Penguin Trail annually. In anticipation, Lonely Planet Publications last year published ''Antarctica,'' a 362-page guidebook aimed specifically at such intrepid travelers, and sold a bundle of them at $17.95 each.</p>
        <p>But what is the appeal, if not the free ice? ''It's an expensive adventure holiday for people that have been everywhere and want to view magnificent, unspoiled alpine scenery, sculpted ice, penguins, wildlife, and enjoy some history,'' Dr. Stonehouse said. And, of course, some travelers collect continents and need that elusive seventh.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stonehouse says more than a few seasoned American tourists trace their decision to encounters with Admiral Byrd in the 1930's. He is said to have ended many a lecture by patting the heads of schoolchildren and insisting, ''You must go there someday.'' Apparently, now in their 60's and 70's and with 401(k) money to spare, those kids are taking him at his word.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stonehouse also says Antarctica has been climatically maligned.</p>
        <p>''Individuals have experienced much worse weather during winters in the northern Midwest and Canada than they'll find in Antarctica during the summer,'' he said.  ''I've met some elderly ladies from the Bronx who hadn't walked more than 50 yards in the last 10 years and were having a fine time.''</p>
        <p>That may be all well and good, but frankly, having spent 17 years growing up outside frigid Buffalo, I'll pass on any more cold-weather duty, thank you.</p>
        <p>Questions about investing, careers and personal finance can be sent to Minding Your Business, Money and Business, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036. Or send them by E-mail to yourmind@nytimes.com. Questions can be answered only in the column, not by mail, E-mail or telephone.</p>
        <p>MINDING YOUR BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
