<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clue to Global Warming: The Tango Is Coming Back</title>
    <meta content="19TANG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN UP CLOSE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, Kimberly</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE143BF93AA25752C0A961958260" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clue to Global Warming: The Tango Is Coming Back</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIMBERLY STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, Kimberly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Number of restaurants in New York are offering tango nights; photos; diagrams explaining famous Latin dance (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The crowd watched nervously from the sidelines at Bistro Latino as Daniela Arcuri and Armando Orzuza glided gracefully from one end of the dance floor to the other. Arm in arm, eyes locked, they moved effortlessly to the beat, teaching the dance of love, the tango. Moments later couples spilled onto the floor, some expert and some just beginning, hoping to experience ''the connection'' that people at the restaurant were talking about in hushed tones.</p>
        <p>Inspired perhaps by several recent dance shows and the movie ''Evita,'' featuring the dance, a growing number of people are ready to tango, and restaurants around Manhattan have started to offer evenings of tango dancing. Bistro Latino, Il Camponella, La Trattoria and Novecento are among the restaurants that now make it possible to tango almost every night of the week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The crowd watched nervously from the sidelines at Bistro Latino as Daniela Arcuri and Armando Orzuza glided gracefully from one end of the dance floor to the other. Arm in arm, eyes locked, they moved effortlessly to the beat, teaching the dance of love, the tango. Moments later couples spilled onto the floor, some expert and some just beginning, hoping to experience ''the connection'' that people at the restaurant were talking about in hushed tones.</p>
        <p>Inspired perhaps by several recent dance shows and the movie ''Evita,'' featuring the dance, a growing number of people are ready to tango, and restaurants around Manhattan have started to offer evenings of tango dancing. Bistro Latino, Il Camponella, La Trattoria and Novecento are among the restaurants that now make it possible to tango almost every night of the week.</p>
        <p>At Bistro Latino one recent night, a crowd of young and old ate dinner at tables surrounding the dance floor or sipped cocktails by the bar. Newcomers studied the fashion of tango closely. Women with their hair slicked back, dressed in glittery evening dresses and wearing strappy heels, and men in dark colors had achieved the desired look, according to the instructors.</p>
        <p>''As my partners often tell me, I dance with my head, not my heart,'' said Susan Isaacs, a regular at Bisto Latino, who is striving to put more feeling into it. ''I love it and it has become an obsession. If you really connect with your partner it is incredibly sensual. It is the moment the two partners are completely in sync.''</p>
        <p>Marga Mitchell, a singer, says the tango is a symbol of cultural pride.</p>
        <p>''The way the Americans have jazz, the Latin Americans have the tango and the music that accompanies it,'' she said. ''There is magic and passion and everyone wants to feel it.''</p>
        <p>The musicians, Enrique Quagliano on the bandoneon, an accordion-like instrument central to the tango, and Horacio Blanc on the guitar, play at both La Trattoria and Novecento. Mr. Quagliano said he had concerns about the renewed interest in the tango.</p>
        <p>''In the 1940's the bandoneon was a fever,'' he said. ''Everyone wanted to know how to play. They no longer manufacture them in Germany, so it is difficult for people who want to learn to find an instrument.''</p>
        <p>Dance Manhattan, which has the largest Argentine dance program in the city, offers a weekly tango night in its studio on Mondays. Fabienne Bongaro, an instructor at Dance Manhattan who also dances at Novecento, has advice for those just beginning to learn to tango. ''Patience is key,'' she said, ''and it's important to enjoy every moment of learning a new language of love.''</p>
        <p>As she was whisked away by her partner, she added, ''You will find only the most sensitive men tango.''</p>
        <p>KIMBERLY STEVENS</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: MANHATTAN UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
