<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spotlight On Comets In Shaping Of Earth</title>
    <meta content="03COME$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="934295"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Iowa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7DE153DF930A35755C0A961958260" item-length="1816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spotlight On Comets In Shaping Of Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists at University of Iowa studying series of satellite images discover that many thousands of comets bombard atmosphere daily, inconspicuously providing water; discovery gives rise to new theory about source of water and life on Earth; news has left analysts impatient for confirmation; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EXPERTS have long disagreed on where Earth's waters came from, and how they gave birth to the first rudimentary forms of life.</p>
        <p>Earth scientists look to the planet's interior, arguing that intense bouts of volcanism in the planet's early days produced clouds of water vapor that formed the early oceans. Then, they say, flashes of lightning turned parts of this sea into a rich stew of chemicals that over time gave birth to the planet's riot of biologic diversity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EXPERTS have long disagreed on where Earth's waters came from, and how they gave birth to the first rudimentary forms of life.</p>
        <p>Earth scientists look to the planet's interior, arguing that intense bouts of volcanism in the planet's early days produced clouds of water vapor that formed the early oceans. Then, they say, flashes of lightning turned parts of this sea into a rich stew of chemicals that over time gave birth to the planet's riot of biologic diversity.</p>
        <p>Space scientists tend to look to the heavens. They believe that giant comets striking Earth delivered water by the ton to form the early oceans and that the cometary snow also carried a host of complex molecules from space that produced a primordial soup ripe for life.</p>
        <p>Last week scientists announced a startling discovery that could settle the question once and for all. If verified, it would instantly revise decades of pronouncements about the origins of life and the restless waters that cover most of the planet's surface, including those that fill lakes and pour from taps.</p>
        <p>Many thousands of comets as big as houses are bombarding the atmosphere every day, creating a kind of extraterrestrial rain that inconspicuously wafts down through the air, scientists from the University of Iowa announced after studying a series of satellite images. Most likely, they  added, the unobtrusive rain has fallen for billions of years.</p>
        <p>That news has left analysts startled, stunned, wary, excited and -- most of all -- impatient for confirmation.</p>
        <p>''If the rates are what they claim, it's a major discovery,'' said Dr. Heinrich D. Holland, a planetary scientist at Harvard University who urges caution until the observations are verified.</p>
        <p>Some observers talk of a possible Nobel Prize in Physics or Chemistry.</p>
        <p>''It's amazing,'' Dr. Stephen P. Maran, a spokesman for the American Astronomical Society, said in an interview. ''We don't know with any certainty how much water is involved, or how big they are, or how much they weigh. Lots of research has to be done. There's going to be extraordinary interest in trying to figure out what these objects are and where they come from.''</p>
        <p>Comets are remnants of creation made up largely of water ice and cosmic dust. Most are a mile or two wide. Occasionally, astronomers see big ones like Halley, some 10 miles wide, or Hale-Bopp, whose icy core is estimated to be 25 miles wide.</p>
        <p>The dark fringes of the solar system are thought to harbor a trillion or so comets whose diameters are about a mile or more. Some of these large comets occasionally speed into the inner solar system, at times lighting Earth's skies.</p>
        <p>What makes the recent announcement so startling is that it suggests a new class of small, previously unseen comets up to 40 feet wide. More important, their ranks are said to be gargantuan, pelting Earth's atmosphere at the extraordinary rate of 5 to 30 per minute -- or potentially more than 40,000 a day, or 15 million a year.</p>
        <p>That instantly makes them candidates as prime shapers of the planet and perhaps of the solar system, since whatever strikes Earth's atmosphere is probably bombarding other planets as well.</p>
        <p>The main discoverer of the cosmic snowstorm, Dr. Louis A. Frank, whose initial hypothesis was ridiculed when he presented it in 1986, now says with great confidence that the terrestrial bombardment could easily have supplied all the planet's water and perhaps also many of the chemicals that are essential for life.</p>
        <p>''If the flux has been similar over geologic time, say, over four billion years, then it very closely accounts for the oceans we have now, including the ice caps,'' Dr. Frank, a physicist at the University of Iowa, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>''The changes are going to be enormous'' in people's view of how the oceans and life arose, Dr. Frank predicted. ''It's quite possible,'' he said, ''that all the carbon in our trees and bodies has come in on these small comets.''</p>
        <p>The announcement of the find was made by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, whose Polar spacecraft, launched in February 1996, produced the arresting images. The space agency quoted Dr. Thomas M. Donahue, an atmospheric physicist at the University of Michigan and a prominent space authority, as saying that the pictures ''definitely demonstrate that there are objects entering the Earth's upper atmosphere that contain a lot of water.''</p>
        <p>The revelation that ''a lot of water'' is raining down from space could be a mortal blow to the scientific orthodoxy concerning the origin of the sea.</p>
        <p>It was more than a century ago, in 1894, that geologists first proposed that volcanoes formed Earth's air and water in a violent era of early eruptions, and this view eventually won many allies. After all, analysis showed that volcanic fumes, on average, were made of 10 percent sulfur dioxide and other gases, 30 percent carbon dioxide and 60 percent water steam.</p>
        <p>''Most geologists believe that the origin of the oceans and atmosphere can be tracked to Earth itself,'' Dr. Frank Press and Dr. Raymond Siever wrote in their 1994 college text, ''Understanding Earth,'' published by Freeman. ''The amount of water vapor released by currently active volcanoes indicates that over several billion years, volcanic activity could easily have filled the oceans.''</p>
        <p>But space and planetary scientists have vigorously attacked this view in recent years. They argue that most, if not all, of the volcanic water is not primordial in origin but recycled during the slow upheavals of plate tectonics.</p>
        <p>The recycling is seen as occurring as wet oceanic crust collides with crustal plate, is pushed down into the planet's hot interior, is melted and is lifted up into the atmosphere during volcanic outbursts before the whole process starts over again.</p>
        <p>Belief in the seas' forming by pure volcanism is ''blind extrapolation of the present recycling,'' Dr. Armand H. Delsemme, an astronomer at the University of Toledo, wrote in ''Comets and the Origin and Evolution of Life,'' a set of conference papers published in 1997 by Springer-Verlag.</p>
        <p>Space scientists see big comets as the logical alternative, producing huge bombardments of water during the planet's early days, as well as such features as the scars on the Moon's face. Increasingly, clues suggest that large objects from space have struck Earth repeatedly over the ages and at times traumatized it, doing in the age of the dinosaurs, for instance.</p>
        <p>Moreover, astronomers increasingly see cometary ices as bearing the chemical precursors of life. For instance, telescopes around the globe recently found that Hale-Bopp was spewing not just tons of water into its icy tail but methanol, formaldehyde, carbon monoxide, hydrogen cyanide, hydrogen sulfide and many compounds rich in carbon -- in other words, the basic ingredients thought necessary for the origin of life.</p>
        <p>Such chemicals are envisioned as being made in the wastelands out among the stars, eventually finding their way into comets. To date, scientists have identified nearly 100 complex molecules in interstellar space.</p>
        <p>But in a spirited attack, earth scientists have questioned the idea that comets are responsible for the planet's life chemistry. Among other things, they argue that the great heats generated as mountains of ice plunge though Earth's atmosphere would destroy most complex molecules.</p>
        <p>One prominent critic is Dr. Stanley L. Miller of the University of California at San Diego, who in the 1950's performed the classic tests suggesting the main alternative: that lightning strikes in Earth's primitive sea and air produced the right kinds of chemicals for the emergence of life. The initial luster of that idea has dimmed over time.</p>
        <p>Today, many space scientists concede that complex molecules of comets would probably be destroyed by the blistering fires of atmospheric passage. But they counter that in Earth's early atmosphere, new ones might have been instantly formed at the edges of the fireballs.</p>
        <p>Dr. Christopher P. McKay and Dr. William J. Borucki of the space agency's Ames Research Center in Moffett Field, Calif., give the chemistry and evidence for this kind of mechanism in the April 18 issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>Decade after decade, year after year, earth and space scientists have quietly battled over such issues.</p>
        <p>That is why the new discovery is sending out so many shock waves. With great suddenness, it promises to end the interminable debate and finally shed a bright light on some the knottiest and most interesting topics ever confronted by science.</p>
        <p>For instance, the small size of the newly discovered comets suggests that any complex chemicals laced in their ices would face little or no high heat.</p>
        <p>The small comets are observed to break up at heights of 600 miles to 15,000 miles above Earth, long before the onset of the intense heating that bigger objects undergo as they plunge intact through the lower atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frank, the discoverer of the small comets, said in an interview that they produced not only a fine cosmic rain in the atmosphere but on occasion probably objects on the ground.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes,'' he said, ''if the trajectory is right, some little bit of snow will plop down'' intact.</p>
        <p>Additional factors in favor of the small comets are their current observability -- large impacts in Earth's early days can only be inferred from such ancient evidence as old scars on the Moon -- and their vast numbers, which suggest an unambiguous mechanism for filling the seas.</p>
        <p>Dr. Frank and his co-author, Dr. John B. Sigwarth of the University of Iowa, have submitted four papers outlining the discoveries to Geophysical Research Letters, a journal published twice each month by the American Geophysical Union in Washington.</p>
        <p>A rule of science is that big claims require big evidence. By that measure, many scientists are eagerly awaiting both the publication of the four papers as well as independent confirmation of the nature and pervasiveness of the small comets.</p>
        <p>''Everybody's stirred up,'' said Dr. Holland of Harvard University. ''But we need to slow down and look at the data.''</p>
        <p>If Dr. Frank turns out to be right, he added, ''it's going to have a significant effect'' on studies not only of the origin of Earth but of planetary bodies throughout the cosmos.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
