<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Steamy Summer Leftover</title>
    <meta content="07WARM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E4D61E3DF934A35753C1A961958260" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Steamy Summer Leftover</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Unseasonably warm weather hits New York City metropolitan area, raising temperatures into mid 80's; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having peeled off his T-shirt yesterday morning in Central Park, Matthew Cornelissen said he was surprised that it was so warm in New York. He said he expected it to be about 10.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cornelissen is from Apeldoorn, the Netherlands, and was thinking in degrees centigrade, not Fahrenheit. But it certainly wasn't 10. It wasn't even 20, the norm for early October, which is 68 on the temperature scale favored on this side of the Atlantic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having peeled off his T-shirt yesterday morning in Central Park, Matthew Cornelissen said he was surprised that it was so warm in New York. He said he expected it to be about 10.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cornelissen is from Apeldoorn, the Netherlands, and was thinking in degrees centigrade, not Fahrenheit. But it certainly wasn't 10. It wasn't even 20, the norm for early October, which is 68 on the temperature scale favored on this side of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>By midafternoon, the National Weather Service reported that it was a summery 85 in Central Park, which Mr. Cornelissen quickly converted to 29.</p>
        <p>''I'm still a bit sweaty,'' he said. But he could not shed the too-big jeans that he had put on in the morning.</p>
        <p>From the moment a fiery red-orange disk of a sun cleared the horizon in the morning, yesterday was like a three-H day left over from summer -- hot, hazy and even a bit humid.</p>
        <p>It was a day when office workers called in sick and promptly headed for the park or the beach. It was a day that tempted Coney Island beachgoers to consider breast-strokes and butterflies, until they waded in and decided that the water wasn't warm enough after all.</p>
        <p>It was a day when Manhattan taxi hailers with rolled-up sleeves hunted for cabs with rolled-up windows, the promise of an air-conditioned ride. It was a day when gardeners worried about whether the chrysanthemums would die early deaths and whether the fall foliage would do its Technicolor transformation sooner than expected.</p>
        <p>It was a day when October, a month that can usher in wintriness, allowed summer to pay a lingering goodbye, not just in New York, but in much of the East and Midwest.</p>
        <p>It was 75 in Milwaukee; 82 in Dayton, Ohio; 82 in Detroit; 85 in Evansville, Ind., and 84 in Peoria, Ill. And it was 87 at Kennedy and Newark International Airports, and 86 in White Plains, N.Y., Islip, N.Y., and Morristown, N.J.</p>
        <p>Still, yesterday was not a record setter in New York. The Central Park record for Oct. 6 is 90 degrees, set in 1941. And only two years ago, the high for Oct. 6 was 86.</p>
        <p>But yesterday was the warmest day since Aug. 17, a 93-degree scorcher. The temperature hit 83 several times in September.</p>
        <p>Watching a low-pressure system that has parked itself over the Midwest, forecasters were unequivocal: temperatures would remain warmer than usual for the rest of the week -- but a few degrees cooler than yesterday.</p>
        <p>Indeed, by yesterday Minneapolis had cooled down to the mid-70's, a far cry from the 90's of late last week.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't strike me that there are going to be many more records set, because the Gulf of Mexico is now open for business,'' said Lee Grenci, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University. ''Humidity is again flowing northward, and where there is humidity, can clouds be far behind? And if there are clouds to block the sun, records are difficult to break.''</p>
        <p>But it is still going to be warm, to the delight of convertible owners like David Barzakas, an equities analyst who spent his lunch hour idling in the sun outside the Gateway Center in Newark.</p>
        <p>''I've never had the top down like this in October before,'' he said. ''I need some Beach Boys music for the tape deck. I need some sunscreen.''</p>
        <p>And then there is the what-to-wear problem. People who went by the calendar, who tried to be organized, put away their summer clothes the moment autumn arrived last month. Now they cannot find anything in their closets that they can bear to wear.</p>
        <p>''It was burning hot, and I was wearing a wool suit,'' said Gina Kim, the national environmental coordinator of the New York Public Interest Research Group, who appeared at an outdoor press conference on the Columbia University campus to discuss the White House conference on climate. ''It was perfect weather for a press conference, and we were thrilled about that, but it is ironic that it was 85 degrees when we were talking about global warming.''</p>
        <p>This being New York, not everyone likes it hot.</p>
        <p>''I moved to New York to get away from hot weather,'' said Vittoria Conn, a legal secretary at the firm of Davis Polk &amp; Wardwell who arrived from Louisville, Ky., in June. She went to work yesterday to escape her un-air-conditioned apartment in Larchmont, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''It's cold as a morgue on my floor'' at the office, she said happily. ''I'm happy as a clam -- a little frozen clam. Or maybe an oyster on the half shell, on a bed of ice. I'd be very happy with snow.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
