<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Yorker, Out of G.O.P. Post, Plans His Return</title>
    <meta content="09PAXO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Bill Paxon</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paxon, Bill (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E0DC143CF93AA35751C1A961958260" item-length="1502" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Yorker, Out of G.O.P. Post, Plans His Return</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>AIKEN, S.C., Dec. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with US Repr Bill Paxon, who was forced to resign as chairman of House Republican leadership for role in abortive rebellion against Speaker Newt Gingrich, and who is plotting return from exile; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More resolute than penitent, Representative Bill Paxon is plotting his return from exile.</p>
        <p>Forced to resign as chairman of the House Republican leadership last summer for his role in the abortive rebellion against Speaker Newt Gingrich, Mr. Paxon has not gone quietly into oblivion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More resolute than penitent, Representative Bill Paxon is plotting his return from exile.</p>
        <p>Forced to resign as chairman of the House Republican leadership last summer for his role in the abortive rebellion against Speaker Newt Gingrich, Mr. Paxon has not gone quietly into oblivion.</p>
        <p>Instead, with the precision of a military planner, he is crisscrossing America in a fund-raising tour for fellow House Republicans -- a classic method for building a loyal following. By the end of the year Mr. Paxon, 43, from western New York, expects to have been in 41 Congressional districts, outdistancing even Mr. Gingrich in districts visited, though not in money raised.</p>
        <p>The shrewd operative with the choirboy demeanor -- so slender and youthful that he can be mistaken for a college student borrowing his father's suit -- insists that he is doing nothing more than fighting to win a larger Republican majority in 1998.</p>
        <p>''I'm happy to go wherever I can be helpful to the members,'' Mr. Paxon said as he gulped down breakfast after a 7:30 A.M. pep talk to supporters of Representative Charlie Norwood in Augusta, Ga.</p>
        <p>Republicans, however, believe Mr. Paxon is now positioning himself to make a play for the Speaker's job in the post-Gingrich era, whenever that occurs. And some House rebels still make clear that they would not be dismayed if that era began sooner rather than later.</p>
        <p>''The Speaker's a very gifted guy,'' said Representative Lindsey O. Graham, discussing Mr. Gingrich even as he was showcasing Mr. Paxon in his South Carolina district. ''But when you've got a person who's hanging around in the 25 to 30 percent approval level for a year and a half, there's only so far that person can advance the agenda.''</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Paxon, Representative Graham said, ''He doesn't have that baggage.''</p>
        <p>Nor does Mr. Paxon yet have the support of the House Republican caucus. And he could still end up more like Trotsky than like Napoleon marching triumphantly, if briefly, back into power. But he has already turned a setback into a strength, emerging to the annoyance of some of Mr. Gingrich's allies as the most watched potential successor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Paxon does not like to talk about the summer coup attempt, saying, ''I have no intention of reliving July. It was an unpleasant period for us all.''</p>
        <p>But Republicans who know him say he was initially shocked when he became the lone figure banished from the House Republican leadership. Though all of Mr. Gingrich's senior lieutenants were meeting with the dissenters, Mr. Gingrich took a resignation only from Mr. Paxon because he had served in an appointed -- not elected -- post as leadership chairman.</p>
        <p>This left Mr. Paxon, a man known far more for a consuming love of politics and tactics than of legislating, without a perch in the inner strategy sessions of the House Republicans. Moreover, it was the first serious professional setback for Mr. Paxon, a career politician who won a seat in the Erie County legislature when just out of college, becoming its youngest member ever. He then rose to the New York State Assembly and Congress, where he represents an area stretching from Seneca Falls to Rochester to the Buffalo suburbs.</p>
        <p>But a funny thing happened to Mr. Paxon almost immediately after his fall. At the post-coup House Republican caucus, he won an ovation as he told lawmakers: ''If you want a head, you've got mine.'' The conservatives saw him as a martyr for their cause. The moderates saw him as a man of principle who took responsibility for a mistake.</p>
        <p>''Bill's certainly emerged as the big winner,'' said Representative Peter T. King, a Long Island Republican. ''He has strong support in all camps.''</p>
        <p>Even stalwart Gingrich backers are not shunning him. Representative Robert L. Livingston of Louisiana, the powerful head of the Appropriations Committee, toured upstate New York recently to help Mr. Paxon with his own fund-raising.</p>
        <p>''I was repelled and appalled by the coup,'' Mr. Livingston said. ''That's behind us, and I happen to think Bill Paxon is a good fellow.''</p>
        <p>Part of Mr. Paxon's appeal to House members comes from his energy, part from his careful attention to their needs and concerns, part from his money-raising and part from his image.</p>
        <p>In a confessional age, he and his wife, former Representative Susan Molinari -- the former Staten Island representative turned television personality -- are comfortable living telegenic lives on public stages. Mr. Paxon proposed to Ms. Molinari on the House floor. And when she was the Republican keynote speaker at the party's convention in 1996, cameras repeatedly panned to Mr. Paxon, cradling their newborn, Susan Ruby. They give conservatism a family-friendly face.</p>
        <p>Though he is just as partisan as Mr. Gingrich, Mr. Paxon does not have the Speaker's razor edge. On the stump he is positively chirpy. At his early morning appearance with Mr. Norwood, he cheerfully pumped hands and kept up a steady patter of ''this is a glorious Georgia day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Paxon's political message is uncomplicated, delivered with his hand chopping the air as he speaks. Since summer, Mr. Paxon has been riding two issues designed to fire up the Republican base.</p>
        <p>He has introduced a bill that would call for the tax code to expire by 2001. And he warns that the Clinton Administration's approach to the global-warming talks in Japan will inevitably lead to a proposed gas tax increase that the Republican Congress will have to stop. ''I can tell you these energy taxes will be dead on arrival,'' he pledges.</p>
        <p>This is bedrock Republican politics. But Mr. Paxon displays his political shrewdness in how he has written his tax expiration bill. Distinguishing his plan from a similar one offered by Representative Steve Largent, Republican of Oklahoma, Mr. Paxon would not allow the entire tax code to expire but would keep Social Security, Medicare and other retirement taxes in place.</p>
        <p>''We certainly don't want to give the Democrats the issue to pound our people on that they are sponsoring a bill to sunset Social Security and Medicare,'' Mr. Paxon said. ''That would be political suicide.''</p>
        <p>Yet his choice of issues also displays what his detractors call the weakness that could derail him: a lack of legislative heft. Mr. Paxon does not take a stand on what should replace the current tax code. Nor does he himself grapple with the issue of global warming.</p>
        <p>When asked about his legislative record, Mr. Paxon for a moment gave a glimpse of the steel behind his cheery demeanor. He tossed a question back at an interviewer and asked just what was the legislative record ''of Newt's?''</p>
        <p>Then he quickly added, ''I'm proud of the fact that like Newt I fought long and hard on the political side to get us in the position where we could pass our initiatives.''</p>
        <p>In his battles, Mr. Paxon has unabashedly used fund-raising to make his way. When he looked as if he could be hurt by Congressional reapportionment in 1992, he curried favor with state legislators drawing the district lines by giving nearly $31,000 in campaign funds to the Republican committees for the New York State Assembly and Senate. He also pledged to give $10,000 a year to the state's Senate Republican campaign committee.</p>
        <p>In 1994, as the chairman of the National Republican Congressional Committee, he turned around an organization that was teetering near bankruptcy and became the implementer of Mr. Gingrich's plan to elect a House Republican majority. Mr. Paxon barnstormed the country in fund-raising trips in 1994 and 1996. In the process, he won allies in those influential classes.</p>
        <p>Now, without a portfolio, he is doing the same thing.</p>
        <p>Even sudden vision problems did not stop him from completing the Southern tour that brought him through South Carolina. When spots appeared before his eyes, he took time out to consult not one, but two eye doctors.</p>
        <p>Reassured that he did not need emergency surgery, however, he gamely showed up late at a fund-raising lunch for Mr. Graham.</p>
        <p>When one of the donors asked Mr. Paxon and Mr. Graham, who was a ringleader of the attempted coup, ''Have you guys kissed and made up with the Speaker of the House?'' Mr. Paxon said: ''I respect the Speaker. I support our leadership.''</p>
        <p>And then, despite doctors' advice to take it easy, he was off to Alabama and Kentucky.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
