<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Leaner Budgets Curtail Plans For South Pole</title>
    <meta content="15ANTA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="923000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Pole</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Science Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E0DA163FF936A25757C0A961958260" item-length="1647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Leaner Budgets Curtail Plans For South Pole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Science Foundation seeks ways to cut cost of Antarctic research to fund urgently needed restoration of its South Pole Station; plans to transfer most Navy operations to civilian contractors to save $30 million and reallocate $20 million in research funds, mainly by cutting overall number of scientists working in region; map; photo; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the green parkas worn by United States Navy men and women in Antarctica are rapidly replaced by the red parkas of civilians, major changes in American Antarctic operations are taking place, driven by leaner budgets, safety concerns, the end of the cold war and new scientific priorities.</p>
        <p>Although it is only 23 years old, America's South Pole Station is sinking under the ice and warping under the pressure of drifting snow and ice crystals. Mounting problems with sewage disposal, garage space, electricity generation, fuel storage, fire prevention and a host of other things have convinced experts that the station needs to be replaced. But the earliest the station could be replaced, even if work began in the next summer season, is 2005.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the green parkas worn by United States Navy men and women in Antarctica are rapidly replaced by the red parkas of civilians, major changes in American Antarctic operations are taking place, driven by leaner budgets, safety concerns, the end of the cold war and new scientific priorities.</p>
        <p>Although it is only 23 years old, America's South Pole Station is sinking under the ice and warping under the pressure of drifting snow and ice crystals. Mounting problems with sewage disposal, garage space, electricity generation, fuel storage, fire prevention and a host of other things have convinced experts that the station needs to be replaced. But the earliest the station could be replaced, even if work began in the next summer season, is 2005.</p>
        <p>To restore South Pole Station to a safe condition by 2005 is urgent and requires a large investment, independent analysts agree, and the money may have to come partly out of Antarctic budgets for research on ozone depletion, global warming, ice sheet melting, the birth of stars in distance galaxies and the search for extraterrestrial life.</p>
        <p>So the National Science Foundation -- the Federal agency that directs United States operations in Antarctica -- is seeking ways to slash the cost of research on the ice.</p>
        <p>One way will be to reduce the time scientists actually spend on the continent. Agency officials expect to continue supporting most active research in Antarctica, but they will encourage scientists to stay home, perhaps for one year out of three, to do their desk work and computer analyses.</p>
        <p>By transferring most Navy operations to civilian contractors in the next two years, the agency expects to save some $30 million. But a saving that will be less welcome to many scientists will be a projected reallocation of $20 million in research funds, to be achieved mainly by reducing the overall number of scientists working in Antarctica in the next five years.</p>
        <p>The 23-year-old dome at South Pole Station, meanwhile, is settling ever deeper into the two-mile-thick ice sheet and posing many safety and operational hazards. The science foundation plans to dismantle it and ship it back to the United States, erecting in its place a pair of horseshoe-shaped residential and office buildings expected to cost about $120 million. They will be mounted on stilts to prevent the accumulation of drifting snow around their bases -- a major problem with the old dome.</p>
        <p>Dr. Cornelius W. Sullivan, the marine biologist who has headed the foundation's polar programs since 1993, believes that his agency will win the approval of Congress for financing the new South Pole Station at the Amundsen-Scott base as well as preserving the other two permanent American stations in Antarctica: McMurdo Station on Ross Island,  and Palmer Station, near the tip of the Antarctic peninsula. Last Thursday, he summarized the program's needs at a Congressional hearing before flying to Christchurch, New Zealand, for talks with his counterparts from Britain, New Zealand and South Africa about cooperation on logistics and ways to cut costs in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>To lend support to the cause of Antarctic research, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright recently added her signature to an open State Department letter that said: ''Maintaining an active and influential United States presence in Antarctica serves important strategic and foreign policy objectives. This presence in Antarctica gives us a decisive voice in the Antarctic Treaty system, which is the basis for the peace and stability of the area.'' The letter was sent to Norman R. Augustine, chief executive of the Lockheed Martin Corporation and head of a panel of experts who recently assessed the needs of America's Antarctic program.</p>
        <p>To date, 43 nations have established bases in Antarctica under the Antarctic Treaty, but even though scientific relations between them are harmonious, seven nations -- Argentina, Chile, Britain, France, Norway, New Zealand and Australia -- have longstanding and conflicting claims to Antarctic territory. These claims are held in indefinite abeyance by the treaty, but they have never been relinquished. United States stations are by far the most populous on the continent, and American influence is regarded as an important factor in keeping the peace.</p>
        <p>Every dollar the National Science Foundation can save for rebuilding South Pole Station will be needed, and even if large savings are realized, the foundation might have to close Palmer Station for several Antarctic winters. Palmer is the smallest of the three stations, but it is especially important for marine biologists because of the rich variety of birds and sea animals around it.</p>
        <p>The current interest in the search for signs of extraterrestrial life has raised the stakes for financing American-supported science in Antarctica, including support for Russian programs.</p>
        <p>Scientists have long suspected that primitive microorganisms living at temperatures as low as minus 100 degrees Fahrenheit between layers of rock sediment in Antarctica's Dry Valleys might have counterparts on Mars and elsewhere. During the last two decades, much research has focused on these ''endoliths,'' as such organisms are called. Scientists are also looking for signs of life in meteorites found in Antarctica that are believed to have come from Mars.</p>
        <p>Recently, however, scientific interest has focused on a huge lake of liquid water, 140 miles long and 30 miles wide, lying some two miles beneath the ice sheet near Russia's Vostok Station. Russian scientists and their collaborators, Americans and others, have been drilling deep into this ice.</p>
        <p>Because of fears that penetrating the subglacial lake, called Lake Vostok, would contaminate it with microbes from the surface, leaders of the international drilling project have halted the ice drilling a few hundred feet above the water. They hope that when they have found a sure way to prevent contamination, they will be able to pierce the last layer of ice and look for primeval forms of life in the lake -- forms that might resemble life in the liquid water that is thought to lie under the frozen surface of Europa, one of Jupiter's moons.</p>
        <p>A conference of scientists studying possible links between Lake Vostok and Europa's conjectured subglacial oceans was held last week at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif. The conferees proposed that a sterilized robot be sent into the ice above Lake Vostok, melting its way down and injecting a sensing device into the water to look for signs of life.</p>
        <p>While scientists in Antarctica will feel a sharp financial pinch in the next few years, the Navy presence will be virtually eliminated.</p>
        <p>The Navy, which built McMurdo Station in the mid-1950's and has provided logistical support for all United States Antarctic operations ever since, including C-130 transport flights, has already begun to leave. In 1998, the 109th Wing of the New York Air National Guard will begin flying the small fleet of ski-equipped C-130 planes that are the backbone of South Pole logistics; the shift from the Navy to the National Guard is expected to save $30 million a year.</p>
        <p>When the Southern Hemisphere spring arrives next August, flights to Antarctic bases from the outer world will resume, ending Antarctica's usual winter isolation. The Navy contingent in Antarctica will then be reduced to fewer than 300 men and women; its peak in earlier years was 770.</p>
        <p>The flow of tourists to Antarctica continues to grow, meanwhile, despite the remoteness of the continent and the expense of trips. During the 1994-95 summer season, the last year for which figures were available, 9,098 tourists visited the white continent, most by ship but some by chartered airplane to Patriot Hills or the 16,000-foot-high Vinson Massif (Antarctica's highest mountain), or even the South Pole. The National Science Foundation, which once strongly opposed tourism on the continent, now actively cooperates with tour operators in planning safe itineraries that will not disturb fragile ecosystems.</p>
        <p>In his capacity as head of a special advisory committee, Mr. Augustine concluded that ''we quickly saw that the present time is one of extraordinary change in the management of the U.S. Antarctic program,'' requiring the rebuilding of South Pole Station.</p>
        <p>Some Navy men and women said they were saddened by the departure of their service, which has played an important role in Antarctic exploration and settlement since the 19th century, including the landmark expeditions in the 1920's and 1930's by Adm. Richard E. Byrd.</p>
        <p>But Brian H. Shoemaker, a retired Navy captain who commanded the Military Support Force in Antarctica from 1982 to 1985, said he had no regrets about the changes.</p>
        <p>''Times change,'' he said, ''and although sailors feel nostalgia for Antarctica, the Antarctic program will do fine without the Navy.''</p>
        <p>Military men are trained ''to maintain peace by preparing for war,'' he said, ''but with me, it was different: I maintained peace in Antarctica by practicing peace. No military people in Antarctica had guns, but although we were unarmed, we helped keep the peace. There was a cold war in the outer world, but in Antarctica, we and the Russians made common war on the cold, not on each other. Peace will prevail in Antarctica.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
