<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Earth Does a Slow Burn</title>
    <meta content="03MCKI$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckibben, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDF1730F930A35756C0A961958260" item-length="673" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Earth Does a Slow Burn</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bill McKibben</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckibben, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>JOHNSBURG, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bill McKibben Op-ed article on enormous and significant changes on earth that are due to global warming; warns that compared with magnitude of problem, response of politicians, and even most environmentalists, has been feeble (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We live on a new planet. That's what a string of recent scientific studies demonstrates. Because of global warming, caused by cars, factories and burning forests, the earth is shifting beneath us with stunning speed and unpredictability. Consider:</p>
        <p>* The number of ''extreme precipitation events'' (rainfall of more than two inches in 24 hours) on this continent has jumped 20 percent since the turn of the century, according to a study by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We live on a new planet. That's what a string of recent scientific studies demonstrates. Because of global warming, caused by cars, factories and burning forests, the earth is shifting beneath us with stunning speed and unpredictability. Consider:</p>
        <p>* The number of ''extreme precipitation events'' (rainfall of more than two inches in 24 hours) on this continent has jumped 20 percent since the turn of the century, according to a study by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration.</p>
        <p>* Spring comes a week earlier in the Northern Hemisphere, according to the Scripps Institution of Oceanography, which used carbon dioxide records to document its finding.</p>
        <p>* Vegetation has increased 10 percent above the 45th parallel, which crosses Seattle and Milan, since 1980, according to Boston University scientists who analyzed satellite data to track solar radiation.</p>
        <p>* The northern tundra may have warmed enough that in some years it adds carbon to the atmosphere instead of soaking it up, George Kling, a biologist at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, reported last winter.</p>
        <p>Understand this about these changes: They are enormous. They do not represent small shifts at the margin, the slow evolution that has always occurred on earth. Spring a week earlier; 20 percent more storms, 10 percent more vegetation since 1980. These studies are like suddenly discovering that most Americans are 7 feet tall. If we were looking through a telescope and seeing the same things happen on some other planet, we would find it bizarre and fascinating. If someone's watching us, they're doubtlessly bewildered.</p>
        <p>With this level of warming, the Antarctic ice sheet could fail more quickly than previously believed. The most recent El Nino ocean warming lasted five years, not the usual two, which researchers at the National Center for Atmospheric Research think may result from the extra global heating. Lancet, the British medical journal, reports that yellow fever mosquitoes, previously unable to survive at altitudes above 1,100 yards, now live in elevated parts of South America.</p>
        <p>Even news that sounds good probably isn't; longer snow-free seasons in the Northern Hemisphere mean that soils start to dry out that much sooner. This and rising temperatures make drought much more likely.</p>
        <p>Compared with the magnitude of the situation, the response of our politicians (and even most environmentalists) has been feeble. Although the United States promised at the 1992 Rio conference that we wouldn't be emitting any more carbon dioxide in the year 2000 than we did in 1990, we've done virtually nothing to meet our promise, and like almost every other developed nation on earth we will miss the goal, probably by more than 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Now negotiators are trying for an agreement with more teeth -- but the deadlines are far away and the targets modest. Instead of locking ourselves into a document that physics, biology and chemistry are rendering instantly outdated, it's probably better to convene the world's leaders on the crumbling edge of the West Antarctic Ice Sheet. Maybe then we'd get quick action.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago, James Hansen, the NASA scientist who has used his computer model of the climate to make the most prescient forecasts about global warming, predicted that by the late 1990's the effects of global warming would become apparent. For eight years, I've believed this was true, and still this spring's flood of new data shocks and scares me.</p>
        <p>All those things that people said would happen if we didn't clean up our act? They're happening. This is a new planet, not the earth we were born on.</p>
        <p>Bill McKibben is the author of ''Hope, Human and Wild: True Stories of Living Lightly on the Earth.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bill McKibben is the author of ''Hope, Human and Wild: True Stories of Living Lightly on the Earth.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
