<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Or Else' Gives Seattle Voters the Last Laugh</title>
    <meta content="07MONO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978730"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monorails</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Seattle (Wash)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Falkenbury, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cogswell, Grant</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Egan, Timothy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington/Seattle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEEDA1F3DF934A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Or Else' Gives Seattle Voters the Last Laugh</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY EGAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Egan, Timothy</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, Dec. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials in Seattle, Wash, are trying to figure out what to do about new law, which obligates City Council members to expand monorail system at cost of $1 billion or lose their salaries if they fail to put measure into effect; referendum, brainchild of cabdriver Dick Falkenbury and poet Grant Cogswell, won unexpected support of 53 percent of voters in perhaps biggest political upset in Pacific Northwest in 10 years; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At a time when many ballot measures are presented to voters by mercenaries and every stump speech seems screened for minimal offensiveness, it was easy to see the charm of the campaign waged here last month by a part-time poet and a cabdriver.</p>
        <p>They were two men with no money, scorned by the political establishment and ignored by the press, whose campaign consisted of going around Seattle with a plywood sign that urged people to build a $1 billion mass transit system. When the two won, gaining nearly 53 percent approval, it was perhaps the biggest political upset in the Pacific Northwest since a bartender was elected mayor of Portland 10 years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At a time when many ballot measures are presented to voters by mercenaries and every stump speech seems screened for minimal offensiveness, it was easy to see the charm of the campaign waged here last month by a part-time poet and a cabdriver.</p>
        <p>They were two men with no money, scorned by the political establishment and ignored by the press, whose campaign consisted of going around Seattle with a plywood sign that urged people to build a $1 billion mass transit system. When the two won, gaining nearly 53 percent approval, it was perhaps the biggest political upset in the Pacific Northwest since a bartender was elected mayor of Portland 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>But now the glow of victory has passed, and elected officials are trying to figure what to do with the poet, the cabdriver and the law, which requires them to get going on what would be the world's most elaborate monorail system -- or else.</p>
        <p>It is the ''or else'' part that still has people chuckling. Members of the City Council will lose their salaries if they fail to put the measure into effect, according to one provision of the law.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, that probably wouldn't hold up in court,'' said Dick Falkenbury, the cabdriver half of the monorail campaign. He laughed at the thought of it, a throwaway idea of pure populism, now the law of the city.</p>
        <p>''But I wanted something in there to show that we're serious, that this is not just a cute thing,'' Mr. Falkenbury said.</p>
        <p>The idea of no policy, no salary has certainly had immediate effects. ''At the very least, I guess it's incentive not to ignore them,'' Councilwoman Martha Choe said as she spoke just after a Council meeting on how to proceed with the monorail law.</p>
        <p>''My first reaction was, 'Oh, my God, how am I going to deal with this?' '' Mayor-elect Paul Schell said. ''But I'm taking it seriously. We're open to new technology and old technology.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Falkenbury, 45, knows about traffic from the ground level. He drives for a living in a metropolitan region that has added nearly half a million people in the last decade. He is also what newspaper editorial boards call a ''civic gadfly.''</p>
        <p>While stuck in traffic, Mr. Falkenbury has had plenty of time to contemplate something that moves much faster than most cabs, the one-mile monorail between downtown and the City Center, home of the Space Needle. When it opened in 1962 for a World's Fair whose theme was Century 21, the elevated monorail indeed looked futuristic.</p>
        <p>It has served passengers for 35 years, though it is sometimes derided as the monorail to nowhere, going from one food court to another. But it has no doubt won a place in the heart of Seattleites. Built in six months at a cost of less than $2 million, quiet, reliable and relatively nonpolluting, the transit system evokes a time when public works were hardly more complicated than treehouses.</p>
        <p>Now, with the 21st century at the door, Mr. Falkenbury said he believed that it was time to extend the monorail citywide. To make the dream a reality, he needed 20,000 voters' signatures and, then, a majority vote. In the campaign, he was joined by Grant Cogswell, 30, who says he is a writer of poetry that nobody has read (a redundancy, in some people's minds).</p>
        <p>To place an issue on the ballot, most initiative campaigns hire signature gatherers who are paid upward of $3 a signature. The monorail campaign consisted of Mr. Falkenbury and Mr. Cogswell's going around with their plywood billboard with a map of an enlarged monorail.</p>
        <p>''We were 'subgrassroots,' '' Mr. Cogswell said. ''This whole thing ended up costing about 2,000 bucks.''</p>
        <p>Like his colleague, Mr. Cogswell has some deep concerns about the culture of the car. In addition to the usual complaints about the automobile as a cause of urban sprawl and global warming, Mr. Cogswell said, ''our use of the car is conducive to all kinds of paranoia, violence and the creation of unlivable cities.''</p>
        <p>The two men were denounced as silly, naive or irrelevant in the campaign. The Seattle Chamber of Commerce, in an early broadside, said, ''Let's send these dreamers and con artists back to the drawing board.''</p>
        <p>The main argument against the monorail was that a $3.9 billion mass transit system of light and commuter rail was already being built, after approval by voters in three counties in the region last year. But monorail supporters say surface rail is yesterday's transportation, is too loud and intrusive and takes too long to build.</p>
        <p>Basing his plan on a monorail that runs between two hotels in Las Vegas, Nev., Mr. Falkenbury calculated the cost to build a system here at $25 million a mile. He gave a particularly memorable performance in the campaign while arguing the points of cost and time.</p>
        <p>''I was talking to the League of Women Voters -- blue hairs all of them -- and I said, 'None of you will even be alive by the time they build that other system,' '' he recalled. ''Boy, did that room go silent.''</p>
        <p>One reason that the monorail may have won, at a time when most ballot measures here and around the nation went down to defeat, was because opponents did not take it seriously. And the monorail is much-loved. Now that it is the law, the monorail ordinance calls for the city to explore how it can build up to 40 miles of monorail -- elevated electric trains that run on rubber tires. The law envisions 28 stations, including one that has to be ''located within 1,000 yards of the nose of the Fremont Troll,'' a neighborhood icon in statue form.</p>
        <p>But now comes the truly hard part. The measure did not provide for any financing. It simply said that the city had to create a public board that would then go out and find the money. To cynics, that means that after the board has been set up, people can forget about a monorail, and Council members, having satisfied the letter of the law, can keep their salaries.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Schell said he would appoint serious transportation advocates to the board, holding out the chance that something may be done.</p>
        <p>The poet and the cabdriver, refusing to wake from the dream, can see no other possibility. At their Friends of the Monorail office, where the phone was not working well enough to both receive a call and dial out, they have a new message that says, ''See you on the train.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
