<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forecasters Begin to See Who Will Feel Effects of El Nino</title>
    <meta content="26NINO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EFDF1F3EF935A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forecasters Begin to See Who Will Feel Effects of El Nino</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Forecasters are getting clearer picture of latest version of El Nino, powerful weather-maker that is developing into giant of its breed in tropical Pacific; say El Nino's warming of Pacific waters will carry over into Atlantic, tending to abort any developing hurricanes during coming Atlantic hurricane season; but in winter, El Nino will bring abnormally high rainfall to California and entire southern tier of United States; already, early signs of El Nino's work are appearing in some parts of world; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS the latest version of the powerful weather-maker known as El Nino develops into a giant of its breed in the tropical Pacific, forecasters are beginning to get a clearer idea of how and where its impact will be felt globally in the weeks and months ahead.</p>
        <p>For openers, there may be good news: El Nino has called into serious question earlier forecasts of an unusually active Atlantic hurricane season. The warming Pacific waters that define El Nino spawn wide-ranging atmospheric conditions that carry over into the Atlantic and tend to abort developing hurricanes. And as the 1997 hurricane season enters what should be its busiest period, the tropical regions that give rise to the big storms are almost eerily quiet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS the latest version of the powerful weather-maker known as El Nino develops into a giant of its breed in the tropical Pacific, forecasters are beginning to get a clearer idea of how and where its impact will be felt globally in the weeks and months ahead.</p>
        <p>For openers, there may be good news: El Nino has called into serious question earlier forecasts of an unusually active Atlantic hurricane season. The warming Pacific waters that define El Nino spawn wide-ranging atmospheric conditions that carry over into the Atlantic and tend to abort developing hurricanes. And as the 1997 hurricane season enters what should be its busiest period, the tropical regions that give rise to the big storms are almost eerily quiet.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing a dead Atlantic at the moment; there's nothing going on out there'' and El Nino is surely the reason why, said Vernon Kousky, an expert at the Climate Prediction Center of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Camp Springs, Md.</p>
        <p>But come winter, El Nino may not be so benign. If the forecasters are right, it will bring abnormally high rainfall to California and virtually the entire southern tier of the United States. The last time El Nino appeared with strength comparable to this year's, in 1982-83, California and much of the southern tier were drenched again and again, causing floods, mud slides and general climatic havoc. Worldwide that year, El Nino caused more than 1,000 deaths and exacted staggering economic costs.</p>
        <p>Already, early signs of El Nino's work are appearing in some parts of the world. Indonesia is drier than normal, for example, and the forecasters expect this situation to widen into a drought affecting the entire region, including Australia. That is characteristic of El Nino. So are the heavy rains that have recently fallen in Chile, giving that country a year's supply of precipitation in two drenching downpours. The weak monsoon and dry conditions now being experienced in Pakistan and northwestern India, the breadbasket of the Indian subcontinent, are also characteristic of El Nino disturbances.</p>
        <p>El Nino is a vast pool of abnormally warm water that is brought about from time to time by naturally occurring oscillations in atmospheric pressure and ocean movements in the equatorial Pacific. Until recently, this pool materialized every two to seven years, but in the 1990's the warm El Nino waters have been in place most of the time. Why this is so is not clear; some scientists suspect that it may be somehow related to global warming, but others disagree.</p>
        <p>In any case, the warmer ocean pumps more energy and moisture into the atmosphere, and this in turn alters wind and rainfall patterns around the world. The nature and severity of the resulting disturbances is directly related to how warm the equatorial water gets.</p>
        <p>Just now, equatorial water off South America is about 9 degrees Fahrenheit above normal, according to the Climate Prediction Center, and it is expected to warm further in the months ahead, reaching a peak from February to April, when the equatorial waters would normally be  warmest. This year, the water is already as warm as it was in the winter of 1982-83, when El Nino's bite was its sharpest of the 20th Century.</p>
        <p>The forecasters are confident that California and the southern tier will experience abnormally heavy rainfall this winter and next spring, said Mr. Kousky, because that has been the invariable result when El Nino is at its strongest. But whether the abnormal precipitation will actually translate into the havoc of 1982-83, he said, depends on how the atmospheric circulation patterns that transport storms from the Pacific to the West Coast and across the continent develop.</p>
        <p>El Nino, when it materializes, presents forecasters with an especially good predictor of weather trends months in advance; without it, they are hard pressed to make long-range predictions. With El Nino's aid, the Climate Prediction Center has just issued a forecast for January through March of next year.</p>
        <p>The forecast calls for higher-than-normal precipitation for most of California, New Mexico, Arizona, most of Texas, the Gulf Coast, Florida and eastern Georgia, South Carolina and North Carolina. Below-normal precipitation is predicted for the Ohio Valley, the Midwest east of the Mississippi and Montana. Elsewhere, including the Northeast, normal rain, snow, ice and sleet are forecast.</p>
        <p>The prediction says that warmer-than-normal temperatures will prevail on the West Coast and most of the northern tier of the country as far east as the Great Lakes, but it is expected to be colder than normal in much of the Southeast.</p>
        <p>While the forecasters cannot be sure until this fall's atmospheric circulation patterns become established, they say the Northeastern United States may be in for a relatively mild winter. One reason for iffiness about the Northeast is that atmospheric circulation over eastern North America is influenced by sea-surface temperatures in the North Atlantic as well as by El Nino, and forecasts for Atlantic temperatures for this winter are uncertain.  Even if the Northeastern winter does turn out to be mild, said Mr. Kousky, that does not rule out some snowstorms.</p>
        <p>A more immediate uncertainty for the Eastern United States has to do with the Atlantic hurricanes. El Nino generates strong west-to-east winds that blow into the hurricane cradle of the tropical Atlantic. These winds tend to shear tropical disturbances apart before they can develop into hurricanes.</p>
        <p>In June, forecasters at Colorado State University in Fort Collins predicted that this year's hurricane season would be more active than normal for the third consecutive year. In an early August update, the Colorado group revised its forecast downward somewhat but still predicted an above-average year. The prediction calls for a total of six Atlantic hurricanes, two of them major ones, and five other lesser tropical storms strong enough to be assigned names.  So far there have been four named storms, including one minimal hurricane. All occurred in July.</p>
        <p>Dr. William M. Gray, the chief author of the Colorado forecast, said his group agonized over the revised August prediction. El Nino aside, he said, a wide range of conditions, including warm sea-surface temperatures in the Atlantic, favor hurricane development. ''This is the hardest forecast I've ever made, with El Nino breathing down our throats like this,'' said Dr. Gray, whose predictions have been generally accurate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kousky said even the revised prediction was too pessimistic. ''My feeling is that we'll get fewer hurricanes than what he's forecasting,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gray conceded: ''Vern could be right. I don't know what's going to happen. Nobody knows. We gave it our best shot, and we'll go with the forecast.''</p>
        <p>A word of caution: Even if Mr. Kousky is right and there are fewer hurricanes than expected, it takes only one to cause a disaster; 1992 was a year of infrequent hurricanes and tropical storms, yet the big one that did develop that year was Hurricane Andrew, the most destructive storm in American history.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
