<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>News Summary</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFDB1338F935A25754C0A961958260" item-length="1455" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>News Summary</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Russia Requests U.S. Help In Repairing Space Station  The head of the Russian Space Agency proposed that the American astronaut Michael Foale participate in a tricky space walk to repair the stricken Mir space station. The Russian commander has been judged unable to carry out the job because of heart irregularities. NASA officials said they needed to be persuaded of the urgency of the repair before they would allow Mr. Foale to take on the potentially risky mission.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Arrest Plan Dropped in Bosnia  Plans to capture several prominent Bosnian Serb figures wanted for war crimes from their capital at Pale were abandoned when France declined to join the NATO operation, senior American officials said. Pale is in the French sector, and is the headquarters of the former Bosnian Serb president, Radovan Karadzic, and the former military commander, Ratko Mladic, both of whom have been charged with war crimes.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Russia Requests U.S. Help In Repairing Space Station  The head of the Russian Space Agency proposed that the American astronaut Michael Foale participate in a tricky space walk to repair the stricken Mir space station. The Russian commander has been judged unable to carry out the job because of heart irregularities. NASA officials said they needed to be persuaded of the urgency of the repair before they would allow Mr. Foale to take on the potentially risky mission.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Arrest Plan Dropped in Bosnia  Plans to capture several prominent Bosnian Serb figures wanted for war crimes from their capital at Pale were abandoned when France declined to join the NATO operation, senior American officials said. Pale is in the French sector, and is the headquarters of the former Bosnian Serb president, Radovan Karadzic, and the former military commander, Ratko Mladic, both of whom have been charged with war crimes.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.N. Sees Terror in Cambodia  At least 40 people have been executed and hundreds of others arrested since the coup last weekend in Cambodia, according to a senior United Nations official. He described a systematic campaign of terror and said the death toll could climb much higher. Former Second Prime Minister Hun Sen, who led the coup, told the Voice of America that he had ''no report'' of widespread executions.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Gold Scandal Crosses Ocean  Gold looted by the Nazis during World War II may have been laundered through the Federal Reserve Bank of New York and the Bank of Canada in Ottawa, according to newly declassified American documents studied by the World Jewish Congress. The Bank of Canada began its own investigation after the disclosures. The Federal Reserve Bank chose not to comment.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>U.N. Condemns Israeli Projects  The General Assembly of the United Nations overwhelmingly approved its third resolution in four months condemning Israel for building Jewish housing settlements in disputed territories. The resolution asked Israel to identify products produced in those areas, with the intention of calling for a boycott of them. Israel, Micronesia, and the United States voted against the resolution.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Georgian Adoption Freeze  Diplomats worried that President Eduard Shevardnadze of Georgia would be overwhelmed by questions on a visit to Washington about a dozen orphans that American families had arranged to adopt. Several orphans have died in miserable conditions during a moratorium declared by Mr. Shevardnadze until Georgia's Parliament establishes a new law on adoption.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Rwandan Role Denied in Congo  Laurent Kabila, the new leader of Congo, said he had a few Rwandan advisers but denied that Rwanda planned and led the war that brought him to power.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-16</p>
        <p>Fugitive Being Sought In Murder of Versace  Gianni Versace, the fashion designer, was shot and killed as he opened the gate of his palatial home in the trendy South Beach section of Miami. A Federal law-enforcement official said the lead suspect in the case was Andrew Cunanan, who is on the F.B.I.'s 10 most-wanted fugitive list. Mr. Cunanan is being sought in the killings of four men.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Huang Seen as Close to Chinese  John Huang, the off-stage protagonist of the Senate hearings on campaign finance practices, was depicted as the highly paid agent of an international conglomerate that has close ties to the Chinese Government and a record of generous contributions to the Democratic Party. During the time Mr. Huang worked at the Commerce Department and the Democratic National Committee, the Senators were told, he retained his ties to his former employer, the Lippo Group, a financial holding company based in Indonesia.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A British citizen with Asian business interests was granted a meeting in 1995 with Sandy Berger, who was then the deputy national security adviser, several weeks after the businessman's American wife contributed $100,000 to the Democratic National Committee, according to documents released by the Senate.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Weld Fights for Nomination  Gov. William F. Weld of Massachusetts challenged the White House to fight to win him the job as Ambassador to Mexico and said he would accept no substitute. Mr. Weld, a moderate Republican, also took on Senator Jesse Helms, who is chairman of the Foreign Relations Committee, in what he cast as a battle for the soul of the Republican Party. Senator Helms has vowed to kill the Governor's ambassadorial nomination by refusing to hold a committee hearing on it.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Nominee Named for Joint Chiefs  Defense Secretary William S. Cohen will recommend Gen. Henry H. Shelton of the Army, who commanded the American military operation in Haiti in 1994, to be the next Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, a senior Administration official said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Ruling Sought on Wiretaps  Telephone industry officials said they would ask the Federal Communications Commission to resolve a dispute over the limits of surveillance in the information age. The executives said the F.B.I. is attempting to force them to develop wiretapping equipment that goes beyond the law.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>New Data on Global Warming  The Clinton Administration predicted that measures to reverse global warming would have a far less dramatic effect on the economy than has been projected by industries opposed to restraints on their energy use. The Administration's analysis opens what is expected to be a long campaign to build support for a proposed binding treaty to limit the emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>The Heat Makes Itself Felt On People and Utilities  New York's first extended heat wave of the summer began taking its toll, with city officials urging people to turn their air conditioners down. The temperature hit 97 degrees in Central Park, 5 degrees cooler than the record for July 15 set two years ago.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Cosby Denies Paternity  Bill Cosby told a jury in Federal District Court in Manhattan that he paid a woman with whom he had had an affair $100,000 to keep their relationship quiet, but said that he was not the father of the woman's daughter, who is charged with attempting to extort $40 million from Mr. Cosby.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Plan Urges Majors for Students  Students in New York State will be required to declare a major in a field like advertising, health, or a foreign language in order to get their high school diploma, under a proposal by State Education Commissioner Richard P. Mills.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Silver Backs Lilco Plan  The $7.3 billion partial state takeover of the Long Island Lighting Company appears likely to win final state approval today, after Assembly Speaker Sheldon Silver said he would vote for it if certain conditions are met. Mr. Silver said that there must be a guarantee of the double-digit electric rate reductions Gov. Pataki has promised the buyout would produce.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>B8-14</p>
        <p>LIVING</p>
        <p>C1-10</p>
        <p>HEALTH</p>
        <p>C10</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>$2 Billion Sought for Schools  Gov. Pataki and the Legislature are considering an ambitious proposal that would authorize the state to borrow $2 billion over the next five years to build or repair classrooms throughout the state.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-18</p>
        <p>Utility Expands Eastward  Calenergy, a large independent power producer, announced it had begun a hostile attempt to buy the New York State Electric and Gas Corporation, a utility that serves 804,000 customers in upstate New York. The bid is aimed in part at giving Calenergy a base in the Northeast to sell its electricity as states move toward opening their utility markets to competition, allowing customers to choose their power suppliers.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>C11-18</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Rachel Gillett Fruchter  An associate professor of obstetrics and gynecology at the State University of New York's Health Science Center at Brooklyn, she was 57.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Samuel Brookner Gould  A visionary educator who fused 58 New York campuses into a unified State University system, he was 86.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Open the China file; resisting reform in Kenya; fame's free fall, in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Columns: Maureen Dowd, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>C18</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>B5</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
