<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting New York Ready For a Hotter, Wetter Future</title>
    <meta content="01YORK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="GLOBAL WARMING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Regional Plan Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6DD163AF932A35751C1A961958260" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting New York Ready For a Hotter, Wetter Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Variety of groups begin identifying steps to limit potential impact of global warming on New York metropolitan region--steps experts say are worth taking no matter how climate changes; most predictions concern length of summer heat waves, which currently average approximately 14 days, but which could be twice as long in warmer world; findings of study of likely effects of global warming in New York region, carried out by Regional Plan Assn, discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Port Authority isn't planning to start building dikes around the runways at Kennedy International Airport just yet. But a variety of groups have begun identifying steps to limit global warming's potential impact on the New York region -- steps that, in many cases, experts say are worth taking no matter how the climate changes.</p>
        <p>The most serious predictions concern the length of summer heat waves, which now average about 14 days. In the warmer world predicted by some climate scientists, the heat waves may stretch out to become twice as long.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Port Authority isn't planning to start building dikes around the runways at Kennedy International Airport just yet. But a variety of groups have begun identifying steps to limit global warming's potential impact on the New York region -- steps that, in many cases, experts say are worth taking no matter how the climate changes.</p>
        <p>The most serious predictions concern the length of summer heat waves, which now average about 14 days. In the warmer world predicted by some climate scientists, the heat waves may stretch out to become twice as long.</p>
        <p>Under a recent study by the Regional Plan Association, a private group that analyzes long-term trends around New York City, global warming could lead to a less reliable supply of drinking water as precipitation patterns shift, more smog, shortages of electricity and flooding. ''This is not going to unfold overnight, but it could have enormous consequences for us here,'' said H. Claude Shostal, the association's president.</p>
        <p>City planning officials and engineers for the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey have determined that the city does not yet need to start spending money to protect, say, its low-lying airports, which could be vulnerable to flooding if sea levels rise as predicted. ''This will be a gradual change over 100 years,'' said Allen Morrison, a spokesman for the Port Authority.</p>
        <p>But some planning experts say cities like New York could immediately begin taking some steps to lessen the impact of any warming, steps that also make sense for other reasons, like increasing energy efficiency by toughening building codes, planting trees and encouraging building owners to replace black rooftops with light reflective materials.</p>
        <p>Studies by the Department of Energy  show that planting trees and making roofs and pavement light instead of dark, so they reflect sunlight, could cut summer temperatures on city streets by up to 7 degrees.</p>
        <p>''That's enough to offset the predicted warming,'' said Dr. Douglas Hill, a consulting engineer from Huntington, N.Y., and the editor of ''The Baked Apple: Metropolitan New York in the Greenhouse,'' a book published last year by the New York Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>Because of what is called the heat-island effect, the city, with all its concrete and asphalt, already tends to be 3 to 5 degrees hotter, on average, than surrounding areas during the summer.</p>
        <p>Along with higher temperatures would come higher levels of ozone pollution in the air close to the ground, leading to more smog and endangering the health of the elderly and people with breathing problems.</p>
        <p>New York City has more deaths from heat than any other large American city, Dr. Hill said. ''The mortality rate from heat in New York is twice that of Chicago,'' he said. ''And it could double by 2030.''</p>
        <p>The region may also experience coastal flooding if seas rise a foot or more, as many climate models predict. Flooding and erosion are already costly problems in many parts of the New Jersey coast and Long Island.</p>
        <p>Finally, he said, there are likely to be significant indirect effects of a warming world.</p>
        <p>''There could be 17 million refugees just in Bangladesh from sea level rise,'' Dr. Hill said. ''They're going to want to go somewhere. And New York City has always been a magnet for dislocated people. In the end, the most severe consequences of all this could be indirect.''</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
