<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Reversal, G.O.P. Courts The 'Greens'</title>
    <meta content="02ENVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="941085"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4D61430F931A35754C0A961958260" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Reversal, G.O.P. Courts The 'Greens'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republicans are declaring themselves champions of environment, even though movement is so closely identified with Democrats; Republicans' shift may be sharper in tone than in substance, but it is particularly stark because Democrats seem unsure about how much to press for environmental causes they have long supported; Republicans gentler approach is clearly driven by electoral politics; polls show that perception among voters that Republicans do not care about environment cost party dearly in 1996 elections (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The environmental movement is so closely identified with the Democrats, the joke goes, that to the Republicans, ''green'' is a place to putt at their country club golf courses.</p>
        <p>But far from attacking the Democrats as belonging to ''the eco-terrorist underworld,'' as House Republican leaders did only a year or so ago, many Republicans now declare themselves champions of the environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The environmental movement is so closely identified with the Democrats, the joke goes, that to the Republicans, ''green'' is a place to putt at their country club golf courses.</p>
        <p>But far from attacking the Democrats as belonging to ''the eco-terrorist underworld,'' as House Republican leaders did only a year or so ago, many Republicans now declare themselves champions of the environment.</p>
        <p>Speaker Newt Gingrich, the Georgia Republican who helped lead a failed drive in 1995 to dismantle environmental regulations, rose on the floor recently to press for conservation efforts. Gov. George E. Pataki of New York is one of a parade of Republican governors who sound like tree-huggers as they trumpet  their environmental records. And Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, Republican of New York, warned the White House last week that it had better strengthen its resolve on tightening the nation's clean air standards.</p>
        <p>The shift may be sharper in tone than in substance, but it is particularly stark because Democrats themselves seem unsure about how much to press for environmental causes they have long supported. Just last week, many environmentalists were heartened that Mr. Clinton declared his support for new clean air requirements. But only a day later, they were distressed when he rebuffed calls for a specific target for reducing greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The Democrats' ambivalence was clear early this year when the environment was nowhere to be found in the Congressional Democrats' ''Families First'' manifesto for the current Congress.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats who were considered staunch allies are now under question. Representative Tom Sawyer, Democrat of Ohio, was endorsed last year by the Sierra Club but is now the target of a television commercial by the same group warning him not to cave in to ''corporate interests'' on clean air standards.</p>
        <p>In fact, nearly 80 of Mr. Sawyer's Democratic colleagues in the House had urged Mr. Clinton to reject the tougher air quality plan.</p>
        <p>Most recently, several environmental organizations expressed outrage when Senator Carl Levin, a Michigan Democrat, last week introduced a regulatory overhaul bill that they said would threaten environmental rules.</p>
        <p>The Republicans' gentler approach is clearly driven by electoral politics. A variety of polls show that the perception among voters that Republicans do not care about the environment cost the party dearly in the 1996 elections, especially among independents, women, men under the age of 45 and suburban voters. Surveys also found that the environment was a principal reason voters had favored Democratic challengers over Republican incumbents in several close races for Congress last year.</p>
        <p>''The environment is potentially the sleeper issue going into the next millennium,'' said Kellyanne Fitzpatrick, a Republican pollster who has advised Mr. Gingrich and Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi , the majority leader, to tone down their anti-environment oratory. ''We're doing abysmally on this issue. In the Northeast, it can be a potential killing field for Republicans in the future.''</p>
        <p>Recalling her conversations with Republican leaders, Ms. Fitzpatrick said, ''If I want any of them to pay attention to the environment, I start out with two words: 'gender gap.' ''</p>
        <p>Many Republican politicians recite like a mantra the findings of a nationwide survey of adults in both parties who voted in the 1996 election  by Linda DiVall, a Republican pollster. Asked what caused their greatest concern about Republicans controlling Congress, the largest proportion, 24 percent, cited the party's position on the environment.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty clear that the environmental ballot box lessons of 1996 were learned by some Republicans better than by some Democrats,'' said Michael Casey, a spokesman for the Environmental Information Center and a former Democratic Party official.</p>
        <p>Though Republicans are generally perceived as more sympathetic to industry, the notion of Republicans as ''green'' is not at odds with history. Teddy Roosevelt, after all, was always more comfortable in the outdoors than in the Oval Office, and he once predicted that his greatest legacy as President would be his conservation policies. It was Richard M. Nixon who created the Environmental Protection Agency by executive order. And many environmental battles have been fought as much on regional as on partisan grounds.</p>
        <p>Still, the repositioning by the parties leaves many environmentalists wary. Some environmental groups said they did not trust the Republicans and accused them of going underground with their anti-environmental agenda.</p>
        <p>Despite their oratory, many Republicans persist in quietly pressing for legislation that environmental groups sharply oppose, like diluting the Endangered Species Act, altering toxic cleanup efforts and limiting the protection of ancient timber.</p>
        <p>But Representative Sherwood Boehlert of New York, one of the environmental movement's most prominent Republican allies, complained that his party had been unfairly maligned. ''Don't judge us by the harsh rhetoric of a few people spouting off with ridiculous exaggerated statements,'' Mr. Boehlert said.</p>
        <p>While some leading Republicans said that they hardly expected to become militant environmentalists, they are determined to neutralize the issue so it does not cause more damage. ''It is a very important, maybe even crucial issue in the 1998 elections: how we handle our stewardship of the great treasures of America,'' said Senator John McCain, Republican of Arizona, who nevertheless draws poor ratings from environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists suggest that Democrats have wavered because they assume that conservation-minded voters will never defect to the Republicans. They also accuse Democrats of cozying up to business interests who could help finance their re-election campaigns. Another factor is that since Congressional Republicans have stopped pressing aggressively for an anti-environment agenda, Democrats in Congress no longer can coalesce as easily against Republicans.</p>
        <p>That has left the White House to take the lead on environmental issues, which has seemed only to complicate matters.</p>
        <p>''The White House has been more muffled, so it's been confusing for Democrats,'' said Celinda Lake, a Democratic pollster. In 1996, Democrats were not helped as much by identification with environmental causes as the Republicans were hurt, she pointed out. ''Voters don't give you as much credit for being good as they give you demerits for being bad,'' Ms. Lake said.</p>
        <p>Daniel J. Weiss, political director of the Sierra Club, argued that Democrats were still generally more devoted to the group's causes. ''Congressional Democrats are hiding on the environmental issues,'' Mr. Weiss said, ''while Republicans have drawn a smiley face on their poison.''</p>
        <p>One sign of the disaffection among Democratic voters who care about environmental issues is that a Green Party candidate in a special Congressional election in New Mexico recently pulled in enough votes to assure victory for a Republican.</p>
        <p>When Senator Lott told a small group of environmental leaders early this year that they were appendages of the Democratic Party, Fred Krupp, executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund, was among those who challenged the Republican leader.</p>
        <p>But now Mr. Krupp suggests that there may be ''a new dynamic'' and that the outreach by Mr. Lott and other Republicans may be fruitful. ''Traditionally, the Democrats have taken the environmental community for granted,'' he said. ''Except maybe before an election when they wanted to score points.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
