<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>White House Begins Push for New Global Warming Pact</title>
    <meta content="16CLIM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Council of Economic Advisers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yellen, Janet L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1DB1338F935A25754C0A961958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>White House Begins Push for New Global Warming Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration predicts steps to combat global warming by limiting emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases might, over next few decades, shave fraction of percent from nation's economic growth, followed by recovery; Council of Economic Advisers head Janet Yellen tells House panel that move could have barely discernible economic effect or net economic benefit if done deftly; panel members are skeptical (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After tinkering with computer models for more than a year, the Clinton Administration predicted today that measures to combat the growth of global warming by limiting the emissions of  carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat from the sun would have a far less dramatic effect on the economy than had been projected by industries opposed to restraints on energy use.</p>
        <p>The Administration's analysis opens what is expected to be a long campaign between now and the end of the year, when international negotiations are scheduled to conclude in Kyoto, Japan, to build support for a proposed binding treaty to limit the emissions of those kinds of gases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After tinkering with computer models for more than a year, the Clinton Administration predicted today that measures to combat the growth of global warming by limiting the emissions of  carbon dioxide and other gases that trap heat from the sun would have a far less dramatic effect on the economy than had been projected by industries opposed to restraints on energy use.</p>
        <p>The Administration's analysis opens what is expected to be a long campaign between now and the end of the year, when international negotiations are scheduled to conclude in Kyoto, Japan, to build support for a proposed binding treaty to limit the emissions of those kinds of gases.</p>
        <p>Any measures to reverse the steady growth in such emissions, mostly given off by burning fossil fuels to operate cars and generate electricity and heat, would probably involve the biggest Federal intervention in energy markets since oil-exporting countries raised oil prices substantially in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>But the Administration's computer models suggested that the economic side effects would be only half as severe as those projected in a recent study by economists at Charles River Associates for the American Petroleum Institute, a lobbying group for fuel producers.</p>
        <p>Critics who say the Administration is moving too fast on global warming have warned that mines and factories would close, inflation would rise and productivity would fall. But another school of thought holds that energy conservation can pay for itself and that new technologies can be found, offering major economic gains, not to mention the benefits of limiting global warming and its potentially serious effects.</p>
        <p>As the Administration tries to decide how fast and how far to cut those gas emissions, the question of the treaty's economic effect is being asked with increasing urgency in Congress, which has ultimate authority over the country's energy policy. In addition, any treaty would have to be submitted to the Senate for ratification.</p>
        <p>In a staff paper released today, the White House said tough action on such gas emissions might, over the next few decades, shave a fraction of a percent from the nation's economic growth, followed by a recovery -- or might, if implemented cleverly, have a barely discernible effect or even a net economic benefit.</p>
        <p>''It just boils down to this,'' Janet Yellen, chairwoman of the Council of Economic Advisers, said at a hearing of the House Commerce committee. ''If we do it dumb, it could cost a lot, but if we do it smart, it will cost much less, and indeed could produce net benefits in the long run.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Yellen's comments were met with skepticism from both the ranking Republican and Democrat on the committee, and by many junior members of the panel as well.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, in the area of global climate change, the Administration has not yet presented a persuasive case,'' said Representative Thomas J. Bliley Jr., the Virginia Republican who heads the chairman.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, treated Ms. Yellen and Timothy Wirth, the Undersecretary of State for Global Affairs, to a sometimes blistering questioning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell, whose district is a prime manufacturer of automobiles, said the analysis suggested ''huge economic constraints'' on American businesses.</p>
        <p>According to the Administration's projections, Mr. Dingell said, stabilizing emissions at their 1990 levels by 2010 would require steps equivalent to charging about $100 for every ton of carbon emitted when a fossil fuel is burned. That would be like raising the tax on gasoline of about 26 cents a gallon, a tax on electricity of 2 cents per kilowatt hour, a tax on coal of $52.52 per ton, and a tax on natural gas of $1.49 per thousand cubic feet.</p>
        <p>But, Administration officials said, the projections are put in terms of taxes merely because that is the easiest way for economists to model things that are even more complex than the tax code.</p>
        <p>Nobody seriously expects the White House to propose a big increase in the gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>The White House supports a treaty that would bind the United States and other developed countries to significant reductions in emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping gases, leaving each country to decide how it wanted to do so.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
