<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wild Creatures as Nuisances</title>
    <meta content="NUKELAW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="943298"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drownings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Raccoons</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Libby, Sam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruelty to Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E3D71239F930A25754C0A961958260" item-length="875" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wild Creatures as Nuisances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM LIBBY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Libby, Sam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on enactment of controversial Connecticut law, following September 1996 arrest of nuisance wildlife control operator for drowning two raccoons, that requires humane euthanasia of captured wild animals (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE arrest of a Nuisance Wildlife Control Operator last September for the drowning of two raccoons at a West Haven boat ramp has led to the enactment of a controversial new state law that requires ''humane'' euthanasia of captured wild animals, and new regulation and licensing requirements for the state's growing ''nuisance wildlife'' businesses.</p>
        <p>During the trial of Michael Lipsett in Superior Court in Milford it was noted by defense attorneys that state law did not prohibit the drowning of captured wild animals and that an eight-hour state training course for N.W.C.O.'s taught drowning as an approved form of euthanasia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE arrest of a Nuisance Wildlife Control Operator last September for the drowning of two raccoons at a West Haven boat ramp has led to the enactment of a controversial new state law that requires ''humane'' euthanasia of captured wild animals, and new regulation and licensing requirements for the state's growing ''nuisance wildlife'' businesses.</p>
        <p>During the trial of Michael Lipsett in Superior Court in Milford it was noted by defense attorneys that state law did not prohibit the drowning of captured wild animals and that an eight-hour state training course for N.W.C.O.'s taught drowning as an approved form of euthanasia.</p>
        <p>Cruelty to animal charges against Mr. Lipsett were dismissed in November.</p>
        <p>In June, Gov. John G. Rowland signed a bill that prohibits the drowning of captured wild animals, requires more extensive training of N.W.C.O.'s (including instruction in non-lethal measures for addressing  wildlife problems) and requires N.W.C.O.'s to inform prospective customers about the non-lethal methods.</p>
        <p>The law limits euthanasia techniques to those approved by the American Veterinary Medical Association -- carbon dioxide chambers, firearms or euthanasia fluid, a controlled substance that can only be administered by veterinarians.</p>
        <p>''Mike Lipsett did not do anything illegal,'' says Richard Daniotti, president of the Connecticut Nuisance Wildlife Control Operators Association. ''But he did do something stupid.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Daniotti explained that Mr. Lipsett should not have killed the raccoons in public and given animal rights' activists an opportunity to further their agenda to outlaw all trapping and hunting and the very existence of the N.W.C.O. industry.</p>
        <p>As a result a law was passed that was not needed, he said. Any serious practitioner does not drown animals, but uses carbon dioxide. A good N.W.C.O. will inform a customer of non-lethal means of dealing with a nuisance, although such methods often are more expensive and not as effective as lethal methods, Mr. Daniotti said. It should be up to the consumer, he said, to decide how a problem that is endangering property and people's health is resolved.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there is no reason why people cannot co-exist with wild animals, says Laura Simon, president of the Connecticut Wildlife Rehabilitators Association, and an urban wildlife specialist for the New York-based Fund for Animals.</p>
        <p>''There is absolutely no reason to kill wild animals and to kill them in such cruel ways,'' says Ms. Simon.</p>
        <p>Ever since rabies was found in the state in 1991 people have become needlessly frightened of all wild animals, and the growth of the state's N.W.C.O. industry is a symptom of this, she said, arguing that there is no wildlife problem that can't be solved in a non-lethal humane way, she said.</p>
        <p>Every practicing N.W.C.O. knows that no two nuisance wildlife situations are the same, says Mr. Daniotti. People who call them have problems that have to be solved, problems that he says unfortunately often involves killing animals.</p>
        <p>The greatest difficulty this law poses for N.W.C.O.'s is added paperwork, he said. The law requires N.W.C.O.'s to submit a report to the State Department of Environmental Protection that lists the means used to control wildlife. But the thing that N.W.C.O.'s have the biggest problem with is the disruption of the orderly process of discussion and process by which the State Department of Environmental Protection has regulated and licensed the state's N.W.C.O. industry. N.W.C.O.'s agree that there should be higher training and professional standards. This law only confuses the issues, Mr. Daniotti said.</p>
        <p>Drowning was taught as an approved euthanasia method, and during public hearings on the bill in February representatives of the D.E.P. testified against the bill, acknowledges Michele Sullivan, a spokeswoman for the state agency.</p>
        <p>The agency agrees with the parts of the law that will raise the training and professional standards of the state's N.W.C.O.'s, she said.</p>
        <p>But the parts of the law that require compliance with American Veterinary Medical Association guidelines for euthanasia are problematic since those guidelines were established for domestic, not wild, animals, Ms. Sullivan said.</p>
        <p>These guidelines have been applied to wild animals in Michigan and New Jersey, said Ms. Simon. There is no reason they can't be applied in Connecticut, she said.</p>
        <p>People should realize there are limited options when they call a N.W.C.O., said Ms. Sullivan. Rabies vector species such as raccoons, skunks and foxes most be killed or released on the property where they were captured, she said.</p>
        <p>''Connecticut is a bad place to be a wild animal,'' said Steven Gambini, an associate director of the North American Wildlife Association, a wildlife rescue and rehabilitation organization.</p>
        <p>In 1991, Connecticut could have addressed rabies by seeding the state with animal feed that contained an oral rabies vaccine that would have solved all the problems and panic, he said. ''Now,'' Mr. Gambini says, ''the people of Connecticut must choose between horrors that will be inflicted on the state's wild animals.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
