<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Great Green Hope; Are Fuel Cells the Key to Cleaner Energy?</title>
    <meta content="Y08CEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971118T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="963488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Cells</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ballard Power Systems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Fuel Cells</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrogen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0D61F3DF93BA35753C1A961958260" item-length="2210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Great Green Hope; Are Fuel Cells the Key to Cleaner Energy?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>BURNABY, British Columbia</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on fuel cells that use hydrogen to make electric power without combustion and with less waste than conventional power sources; says either hydrogen gas or hydrogen-rich liquids like methanol or gasoline can be used as fuel; fuel cells developed by Ballard Power Systems Inc and International Fuel Cells, division of United Technologies Corp, described; diagrams; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In their crusade to find a cheap, clean, efficient source of power, car makers, utilities, transit operators and even submarine builders have all made their way to a muddy suburban office park here on the outskirts of Vancouver.</p>
        <p>Their destination is the headquarters of Ballard Power Systems Inc., whose drab exterior promises nothing out of the ordinary. Once the crusaders step inside, though, a Ballard executive escorts them to a small conference room on the second floor and there delicately unveils the secret they have come from around the world to see.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In their crusade to find a cheap, clean, efficient source of power, car makers, utilities, transit operators and even submarine builders have all made their way to a muddy suburban office park here on the outskirts of Vancouver.</p>
        <p>Their destination is the headquarters of Ballard Power Systems Inc., whose drab exterior promises nothing out of the ordinary. Once the crusaders step inside, though, a Ballard executive escorts them to a small conference room on the second floor and there delicately unveils the secret they have come from around the world to see.</p>
        <p>It is a fuel cell -- a flimsy-looking tablet about a foot across and no thicker than a computer diskette, which  experts say may hold at least a partial answer to some of the world's most troubling energy problems.</p>
        <p>''They may have the Holy Grail,'' said Roland Hwang, head of transportation programs for the Union of Concerned Scientists in Berkeley, Calif. ''The innovation we have seen from them over the last five years has just blown us away.''</p>
        <p>For years, Ballard has been a leader in fuel cells, which create electricity not by burning fuel but by the process of chemically rearranging the fuel's molecules to produce current with no emissions but water.</p>
        <p>When Daimler-Benz A.G. signed a $325 million deal in August to buy 25 percent of Ballard and jointly develop fuel-cell systems for cars and buses, Ballard solidified its lead, though company executives say they can hear the competition yipping right behind.</p>
        <p>International Fuel Cells of South Windsor, Conn., a division of the United Technologies Corporation, is trying to develop a cell based on work it did for the space program.</p>
        <p>''You'd have to say Ballard is ahead now,'' said Fredrick L. Whitaker, a vice president of International Fuel Cells. ''But I wouldn't say they are way ahead.''</p>
        <p>International Fuel Cells has already installed 95 stationary power plants of 200 kilowatts each, the longest-running of which has been in service five years. The company has also developed a simpler design than Ballard's for ridding the automobile fuel cell of its waste water. And others have already put fuel cells in cars and submarines.</p>
        <p>Last year, the Toyota Motor Corporation presented a fuel-cell vehicle that did not use a Ballard cell and was based on an unusual hydrogen storage system. At the Frankfurt Auto Show in September, Toyota introduced another fuel-cell car, this one based on carrying the hydrogen in methanol.</p>
        <p>While even its rivals have been impressed by Ballard, some claims have been hard to believe. How, some ask, could a handful of engineers at Ballard so drastically reduce the cost and improve the effectiveness of the membrane that is at the heart of Ballard's success when industry leaders like W. L. Gore &amp; Associates, maker of Goretex, have not made similar claims? Others suspect some degree of hype by a small company that needs to catch the eye of investors.</p>
        <p>There are still plenty of obstacles to mass-producing a system that could someday replace, or at least compete head to head, with the internal combustion engine. One of the biggest is simply deciding which fuel to use and how to supply it. This debate pits fuel-cell supporters against big oil companies, since the fuel of choice is pure hydrogen, which does not come from an oil well but can be derived from methane and natural gas.</p>
        <p>There are also concerns about reducing a fuel cell's stubbornly high costs and about whether tough emissions regulations in California and elsewhere will be enforced. The regulations that require ''zero emission vehicles'' have already been delayed once, from 1998 till 2003, and another long delay could undercut both industry and consumer demand for clean cars, which are initially expected to cost more than conventional ones.</p>
        <p>But if they even come close to the vision of Ballard and Daimler-Benz, fuel-cell cars will easily outperform today's battery-powered electric cars. A fuel cell can come to full power almost immediately, giving the cars quick acceleration and -- depending on the fuel used -- practically unlimited range.</p>
        <p>But will the public accept such a radical departure? A lot will depend on how easy the fuel cell is to use, how clearly identified its benefits are and how standardized it becomes. The world is littered with technological advances that withered from consumer neglect, like Sony's beta video system, Mazda's rotary engine and the old eight-track audio tape.</p>
        <p>Still, most top auto companies are rushing forward with fuel-cell cars. Besides Daimler's Mercedes division, the General Motors Corporation, the Ford Motor Company, the Chrysler, Corporation, the Nissan Motor Company, the Honda Motor Company, Volkswagen A.G. and Volvo A.B. have all bought Ballard fuel cells for their research.</p>
        <p>Some, like Ford, are sticking with hydrogen gas in tanks, while others use liquid methanol. Chrysler is working on a fuel cell that runs on gasoline.</p>
        <p>Mercedes also used the Frankfurt  show to roll out its latest ''green'' car: one of its A-class subcompacts retrofitted with a Ballard cell that has a range of about 250 miles between fill-ups of liquid methanol.</p>
        <p>Fitting the package into the 12-foot frame of an A-class Mercedes surprised many auto analysts and gave Ballard another leg up on its rivals.</p>
        <p>''That is the good thing about working with Daimler-Benz,'' Mossadiq S. Umedaly, Ballard's chief financial officer, said in an interview. ''The most challenging application of fuel cells is the car, and the most challenging of all cars would be a subcompact. They set the bar really high and said, 'If we make that, the rest is easy.' ''</p>
        <p>Ferdinand Panik, senior vice president at Daimler-Benz, said in a telephone interview from Germany that he had a chance to drive the fuel-cell-powered car in Frankfurt. ''Frankly, it was terrible,'' he said. The cell fit in the floor cavity, but the methanol reformer, which liberates hydrogen gas from the methanol, took up the whole back seat. But at the pace Mercedes is moving, with full production planned for 2004, such problems should be cleared up soon.</p>
        <p>''When you are doing the first drive in a new vehicle, there is always a lot of room for improvement,'' Mr. Panik said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panik said the fuel cell's ability to cut pollution was a bonus, but the goal was to offer a car that is more efficient, more reliable and no more costly than a standard automobile.</p>
        <p>Autos are a huge potential market, but just part of Ballard's fuel-cell initiative. In September, Ballard delivered the first of three fuel-cell-powered buses to the Chicago Transit Authority. The company will soon deliver three more buses to BC Transit in Vancouver.</p>
        <p>Last year, the company formed an alliance with GPU International, a subsidiary of GPU Inc., the utility company based in Parsippany, N.J.  They will develop an electric generator, using a fuel cell, that can run on hydrogen or natural gas and generate up to 1.5 megawatts.</p>
        <p>Ballard also has a contract with the German company Howaldtswerke-Deutsche Werft A.G. for a fuel-cell power plant in a submarine.</p>
        <p>Besides transportation and electricity, Ballard is developing fuel cells so small they could power cabin lamps and laptop computers for up to 25 hours without a refill.</p>
        <p>All that activity has brought Ballard to the attention of many investors, even though the Canadian company has never turned a profit and does not expect to until 2001.</p>
        <p>''The big picture is positive,'' wrote Christine Farkas, an analyst with Midland Walwyn of Toronto. ''Daimler's investment essentially adds both confidence and muscle to Ballard's efforts.''</p>
        <p>[Ballard stock closed at $59.20 (Canadian) on the Toronto Stock Exchange, where it rose $4.05 on Tuesday, and $43.125 (United States) on Nasdaq, after advancing $3. Both closing prices were slightly off the 52-week highs the stock hit during the session after an analyst at Morgan Stanley, Dean Witter, Discover &amp; Company rated the company ''outperform.'' An investment company in Vancouver, Goepel Shields &amp; Partners, has predicted that Ballard will rise to $200 in a decade.]</p>
        <p>Not bad for a 17-year-old company that had worked almost exclusively on batteries until it responded to a Canadian National Defense Department proposal for a field generator that could not be detected by heat-seeking missiles.</p>
        <p>Ballard's engineers, like most others in the field, knew the theory behind fuel cells had been demonstrated as far back as 1839 but remained a laboratory curiosity until the 1960's, when America's space program used the cells without worrying about cost.</p>
        <p>Any high school chemistry student who has run an electrical charge through a beaker of water to separate hydrogen molecules from oxygen has been introduced to fuel cells, but in reverse. That is, if electricity causes water to split into hydrogen and oxygen, then combining hydrogen with oxygen creates electricity.</p>
        <p>Simply put, a fuel cell isolates the hydrogen, then combines it with oxygen to produce power, and Ballard found a way to vastly increase the amount of power produced. To capitalize on that discovery, the founder, Geoffrey Ballard, took the company public in 1989. A new chief executive, Firoz Rasul, was found, and shortly afterward Mr. Rasul brought his old friend Mr. Umedaly on board.</p>
        <p>The two men, both educated in Canada, met on an Outward Bound program on Mount Kilimanjaro in 1967, when they were 17. Both are of Indian descent. Mr. Rasul was born in Kenya, while Mr. Umedaly was born in Uganda.</p>
        <p>In 1989, Ballard's earliest stack of about a cubic foot of cells produced 3 kilowatts of power -- ''totally insufficient to run an automobile,'' Mr. Umedaly said. Refinements pushed output to 10 kilowatts in 1993, 28 in 1995 and, most recently, well over 35, -- enough to power a car.</p>
        <p>''But the critical issue is fuel, both infrastructure and technology,'' said Robert Rose, executive director of Fuel Cell 2000, a nonprofit group in Washington that advocates the development of alternative energy sources.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen works best but is hard to store and can be dangerous if a tank leaks. Creating hydrogen from methanol has advantages because methanol can be stored in underground tanks at existing gasoline stations.</p>
        <p>But converting methanol to hydrogen requires added steps and compressors that take up space. The process also releases carbon dioxide and trace amounts of nitrous oxide, which could prevent it from meeting the tough California standards.</p>
        <p>Still, the fuel cell's future is bright, and no one is more surprised by Ballard's success than Mr. Umedaly, who was about to start a swimming pool company before Mr. Rasul persuaded him to join Ballard. Looking ahead, he is confident that Ballard and Daimler will overcome pollution problems and bring costs down to the point that fuel-cell cars are true alternatives to conventional cars.</p>
        <p>The key, Mr. Umedaly said, will be to make sure the Ballard fuel cell does not end up like his sporty red rotary-engine Mazda RX-7: a great concept that ultimately failed because other companies never adopted the technology.</p>
        <p>Even though Ballard has entered a joint venture with Daimler, the contract does not prevent Ballard from selling cells to other companies.</p>
        <p>''This way we can create a momentum, which we couldn't create on our own,'' Mr. Umedaly said. ''We figure that the pie is big enough that as long as we keep the core of it to ourselves we can share a lot of it with others.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 18, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day on Oct. 8 comparing the amount of pollutants emitted from fuel-cell motors with those emitted from battery-powered car motors and combustion engines carried incomplete labels. The emissions caused by the generation of power to charge a battery-powered electric motor were based on figures at electric plants in Germany. Figures at plants in California, for example, would be much lower, while those in the Midwest would be much higher. Research for this correction was delayed by an editing lapse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 18, 1997, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day on Oct. 8 comparing the amount of pollutants emitted from fuel-cell motors with those emitted from battery-powered car motors and combustion engines carried incomplete labels. The emissions caused by the generation of power to charge a battery-powered electric motor were based on figures at electric plants in Germany. Figures at plants in California, for example, would be much lower, while those in the Midwest would be much higher. Research for this correction was delayed by an editing lapse.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
