<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whether It Creates Jobs or Joblessness, the Agreement Will Affect Everyone</title>
    <meta content="12IMPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979785"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE CLIMATE ACCORD: THE IMPACT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment and Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Solar Energy Industries Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wharton Econometric Forecasting Associates</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sklar, Scott</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Novak, Mary H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7D8113CF931A25751C1A961958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whether It Creates Jobs or Joblessness, the Agreement Will Affect Everyone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Solar Energy Industries Association exec dir Scott Sklar says nothing can be better for business than agreement on controlling gases that contribute to global warming; Wharton Econometric Forecasting Associates vice pres Mary H Novak predicts that agreement will result in job losses in millions; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To Scott Sklar, the executive director of the Solar Energy Industries Association, nothing could be better for business than an agreement on controlling gases that contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>Already, the solar business is booming, and with tax and research subsidies its growth might go from 27 percent a year to 40 percent, he predicted, and the price of clean electricity from the sun could drop by 25 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To Scott Sklar, the executive director of the Solar Energy Industries Association, nothing could be better for business than an agreement on controlling gases that contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>Already, the solar business is booming, and with tax and research subsidies its growth might go from 27 percent a year to 40 percent, he predicted, and the price of clean electricity from the sun could drop by 25 percent.</p>
        <p>In the niche of the economy that aims to replace coal, oil and other sources of carbon dioxide, the main gas implicated in global climate change, ''the United States could create 400,000 new jobs by 2010, equal to the largest U.S. corporate employer,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mary H. Novak, vice president of Wharton Econometric Forecasting Associates, an economic consulting firm engaged by industry groups opposing the climate change treaty, says her forecasts predict job losses in the millions.</p>
        <p>''The coal mining industry in this country will be wiped out,'' she predicted. ''Agriculture, manufacturing and transportation will all be seriously affected. Farm incomes could be cut by as much as 50 percent.''</p>
        <p>Whoever is right, every American uses energy, almost everybody wastes it, and its price affects every product's costs. So nobody can escape the repercussions of the treaty that was emerging in Kyoto -- assuming that the binding new protocol is signed by the United States, after it is approved by the Senate.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department, in a study by five national labs, found that with aggressive research, new technologies aimed at meeting Kyoto's goals could be brought to market. But for many of them to be cost-effective, fossil fuel prices would have to rise the equivalent of 12.5 cents per gallon of gasoline to help stimulate most of the emissions savings the treaty envisions. Further price increases would bring even more exotic technologies into play.</p>
        <p>Wind power, for example, is getting more cost-effective and in some places is close to under-pricing fossil fuels, said Terry Peterson, manager of green power marketing at the Electric Power Research Institute, an organization financed by the energy industry.</p>
        <p>''The prospects of getting the costs down through a combination of further technology development and larger scales of production are very good,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But asking how much energy will cost in 10 or 15 years, or which technologies will win the race to replace coal, is like predicting the price of a cellular phone in the year 2010.</p>
        <p>Perhaps in the future all new schools will use geothermal heat pumps for cooling and heating, the way the new Choptank Elementary School in Cambridge, Md., did this year. The devices can cut greenhouse gas emissions by 40 percent compared with conventional technology, and Dorchester County, Md., expects to save $400,000 in energy and maintenance costs at the school in the next 20 years, according to a consortium of businesses that is pushing the technology.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the American Power Corporation, a Boston utility, and the Electric Power Research Institute of Palo Alto will achieve a breakthrough in the field tests they announced last week of a small fuel cell to produce electricity at home. Fuel cells cleanly and efficiently convert natural gas and other fuels to electricity. Their device is expected to cost $5,000 and is big enough to easily provide the energy needs of a typical household.</p>
        <p>More energy consumers and producers will make such novel choices, presumably, if the cost of fossil energy goes up in the next 10 or 15 years, when the treaty's terms would effectively put a lid on the nation's emissions of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>The auto industry would be profoundly affected, since gasoline consumption is the biggest single factor, and the fastest growing, in American emissions of carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>And the industry might risk billions of dollars in losses if emissions are capped, because virtually all its profits come from making large sport utility vehicles and light trucks that use much more gas than cars.</p>
        <p>But even a big vehicle can be made more fuel-efficient.</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company predicted in a recent study for the Energy Department that it could make an electric van using fuel cell technology that would get 32 to 34 miles a gallon, more than twice the Econoline model's current performance. And the engine, the study said, could be mass-produced at a price competitive, if not quite on a par, with today's internal combustion engines.</p>
        <p>The other big source of carbon emissions is coal burned by electric utilities, which generate 56 percent of the nation's power that way.</p>
        <p>The Edison Electric Institute, an industry trade group that represents most of the private utilities in the nation, estimated in a study that it would cost the industry close to $30 billion to convert most of the coal burning capacity to plants that would produce power by burning natural gas, which would produce steam to drive turbines.</p>
        <p>THE CLIMATE ACCORD: THE IMPACT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
