<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warming Could Bring Some Cold Surprises</title>
    <meta content="09SURP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="956213"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E0DC1639F93AA3575AC0A961958260" item-length="514" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warming Could Bring Some Cold Surprises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Big wild card in game of climate change is possibility of unwelcome surprises that would suddenly occur if some threshold of warming caused climate system to shift to new state; some scientists say, for example, that warming could melt more snow and ice, flooding North Atlantic with fresh water and upsetting workings of large ocean currents; if that happened, world might suddenly find itself with disruptions in currents like Gulf Stream that transport heat around globe, keep Europe warm and maintain favorable conditions for marine life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE big wild card in the game of climate change is the possibility of unwelcome surprises that would suddenly occur if some threshold of warming caused the climate system to shift to a new state.</p>
        <p>For example, some scientists say, the warming could melt more snow and ice, flooding the North Atlantic with fresh water and upsetting the workings of large ocean currents. If that happened, the world might suddenly find itself with serious disruptions in currents like the Gulf Stream that transport heat around the globe, keep Europe warm and maintain favorable conditions for marine life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE big wild card in the game of climate change is the possibility of unwelcome surprises that would suddenly occur if some threshold of warming caused the climate system to shift to a new state.</p>
        <p>For example, some scientists say, the warming could melt more snow and ice, flooding the North Atlantic with fresh water and upsetting the workings of large ocean currents. If that happened, the world might suddenly find itself with serious disruptions in currents like the Gulf Stream that transport heat around the globe, keep Europe warm and maintain favorable conditions for marine life.</p>
        <p>Just such an event may have been responsible for plunging the world back into glacial conditions for several centuries, starting about 12,000 years ago, after it had temporarily warmed near the end of the last ice age.</p>
        <p>A study reported last month in the journal Nature suggested that the critical ocean currents could be shut down altogether should atmospheric concentrations of heat-trapping carbon dioxide double within 100 years, as mainstream scientists expect to happen if emissions of the gas from power plants, industries and motor vehicles are not reduced. The study, by Thomas F. Stocker and Andreas Schmittner of the University of Bern in Switzerland, was based on computer simulations of the ocean-atmosphere system.</p>
        <p>Moreover, they found, the currents slow but do not stop if the atmospheric concentration of carbon dioxide grows more slowly. This, they wrote in Nature, has ''potentially important implications'' in deciding how much and how fast to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>Earlier computer modeling studies, by scientists at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory at Princeton University, had suggested that the ocean currents would shut down irreversibly if atmospheric carbon dioxide were to reach four times today's levels. Most studies have stopped at a doubling of carbon dioxide, and have not carried the analysis of global warming beyond 2100.</p>
        <p>Dr. Jerry Mahlman, the director of the Princeton laboratory, says that if no action is taken to reduce emissions, concentrations of carbon dioxide could quadruple before 2200. According to the computer simulations, the quadrupling would result in a rise of about 12 degrees Fahrenheit in the average global temperature within 500 years. In much of the Northern Hemisphere, the rise would be around 20 degrees. In the Southeastern United States, according to the computer model, the typical July heat index (a combination of temperature and humidity) would rise to about 110 degrees, compared with 85 to 90 degrees now.</p>
        <p>That is a long time away, of course, and the nightmare scenario may or may not come to pass. But to Dr. Mahlman, it is real enough to inject yet another concern into the policy debate over greenhouse emissions: if too little is done too late, the world may in time regret the consequence. ''If you get to where you don't like, there's not a lot you can do about it -- you're wired in for a long time,'' Dr. Mahlman said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
