<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trivial Concerns Writ Very Large</title>
    <meta content="24KAKUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BOOKS OF THE TIMES" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="903919"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hecht, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Do the Windows Open? (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0D6163AF937A15752C0A961958260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trivial Concerns Writ Very Large</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Do the Windows Open?, book of short stories by Julie Hecht (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO THE WINDOWS OPEN?  By Julie Hecht  212 pages. Random House. $21.</p>
        <p>To get a picture of Isabelle, Julie Hecht's delightfully neurotic narrator, imagine a funny version of one of Joan Didion's high-strung heroines. Imagine Diane Keaton playing a health-food fiend addicted to Xanax.</p>
        <p>As delineated in these nine interwoven stories, which originally appeared in The New Yorker, Isabelle emerges as a world-class phobic and nut case, a charming but thoroughly ditzy heroine who gives us a wickedly satiric window on the self-indulgent habits of that upper-middle-class species of yuppie that divides its time among Manhattan, East Hampton and Nantucket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO THE WINDOWS OPEN?  By Julie Hecht  212 pages. Random House. $21.</p>
        <p>To get a picture of Isabelle, Julie Hecht's delightfully neurotic narrator, imagine a funny version of one of Joan Didion's high-strung heroines. Imagine Diane Keaton playing a health-food fiend addicted to Xanax.</p>
        <p>As delineated in these nine interwoven stories, which originally appeared in The New Yorker, Isabelle emerges as a world-class phobic and nut case, a charming but thoroughly ditzy heroine who gives us a wickedly satiric window on the self-indulgent habits of that upper-middle-class species of yuppie that divides its time among Manhattan, East Hampton and Nantucket.</p>
        <p>Needless to say, the world that Isabelle inhabits is a spoiled one. People pass the time gardening, shopping and trying out expensive new sports equipment. They worry about redoing their floors and renovating their summer homes. They wear Brooks Brothers and Ralph Lauren, drive Volvos and Alfa Romeos and furnish their kitchens with the latest Sub-Zero refrigerators. They have the time and leisure to develop all sorts of neurotic worries.</p>
        <p>Isabelle must qualify for some sort of Guinness record in the department of paranoia and dread. She worries about the greenhouse effect, the eroding ozone layer and the dangers of contracting Lyme disease and rabies. She worries about panic attacks driving the Grand Central Parkway, and she worries about having to sit next to a stranger on the South Fork bus. She worries about being trapped in midtown Manhattan during a heat wave, and she worries about being shot by a careless deer hunter while walking through the Southampton woods. She even worries about the smell of peanuts on a poorly ventilated bus: after all, peanuts, she says, are often ''contaminated by the carcinogenic mold aflatoxin.''</p>
        <p>To raise the odds of her daily survival, Isabelle takes a lot of precautions. On the bus to East Hampton, she makes sure she takes a seat in the middle of the right side (where, she figures, the odds of surviving a head-on crash are better) and she ties herself into the seat with the belt from her alpaca coat. For many years she has subscribed to a macrobiotic vegetarian diet, thereby avoiding the toxic effects of eating meat and dairy products.</p>
        <p>Independently wealthy, Isabelle spends her days husbanding her many anxieties, making appointments with assorted dentists and doctors (she has been seeing a reproductive surgeon in an effort to have children), watching CNN and making desultory plans to take photographs. Among the many projects she has never been quite able to complete are a series of photographs of doctors and their dogs, a series of photographs of ''flowers in every stage of decline'' and a series of photographs of houses lived in by the poet Anne Sexton.</p>
        <p>Isabelle is not terribly satisfied with her own life -- she compares herself unfavorably with Hillary Rodham Clinton, Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis and the Princess of Wales -- but she is even harder on the people around her. She is constantly carping about her husband's failure to communicate (not to mention his penchant for eating dead animals and birds), and she has a sharp word for just about everyone she meets. She is put off by men with bad toupees and men who try to cover their bald spots with hair from another part of their head. She is impatient with friends who don't care about Mozart and Elvis and dismissive of the new sort of East Hampton resident who favors toreador pants and big earrings. She once rejected an endodontist for wearing ''a gold chain, bell-bottoms and white patent-leather loafers.''</p>
        <p>Some of Isabelle's judgments are decidedly wacky. In one story, she becomes convinced that her optician is ''definitely a Nazi, was a Nazi (age is right for Hitler Youth), is the son of Nazis, is a neo-Nazi or is at least a Nazi sympathizer.'' The basis for this judgment? His ''stone-cold icy-blue eyes,'' his obsessive work habits, his German accent.</p>
        <p>Then she has second thoughts. ''He was a simple, upper-middle-class businessman,'' she tells herself. ''He was very good at his job. He had a special interest in it. That's it. He was just a lens-and-frame nut. Maybe I'd misunderstood the whole thing.''</p>
        <p>On third thought she thinks: ''No. It was the cold virus weakening my powers of observation.''</p>
        <p>It would be easy to dislike Isabelle, to dismiss her as a self-indulgent and paranoid kook, yet Ms. Hecht always grounds Isabelle's more extreme anxieties in recognizable fears we've all experienced in navigating the precarious shoals of daily life -- fears of random illness and disaster, fears of mortality, fears that we're frittering away our days in hectic and meaningless activity. Indeed, she makes us see that Isabelle's sillier worries are a kind of distraction, a defense against confronting the deeper fissures in her life: her chilly marriage, her inability to have children, her sense that life has become a daily round ''of wrong choices and futile pursuits.''</p>
        <p>What makes Isabelle such a nervous, judgmental heroine is the same thing that makes Ms. Hecht such a lively writer: an eye for the incongruous detail (the floor paint warmed up with a Betadine orange tint; the Xanax pill colored the same pale-peach shade as the Apricot Beauty tulip) and an ear for the damning remark (''She has an emergency about tomatoes''). Add to this a loopy sense of logic (''If Ted Kennedy was barefoot, overweight and sun-damaged, not to mention the condition of his liver, why did I need to dress decently and put on mascara to buy coffee beans?) and a cheerfully warped imagination (''Then I got the idea that the surgeon could play the part of Papageno in an all-surgeon production of 'The Magic Flute' ''), and you have one of the most amusing, willfully loony heroines to come along since Gilda Radner created her gallery of neurotics on ''Saturday Night Live.''</p>
        <p>Think Roseanne Roseannadanna as a wealthy New York housewife, or Emily Litella as a well-heeled yuppie.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
