<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Nation; Clinton Can Now Sing, 'Me and My Shadow President'</title>
    <meta content="14BERK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971221T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E2DE1F3CF937A25751C1A961958260" item-length="1203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Nation; Clinton Can Now Sing, 'Me and My Shadow President'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>KYOTO, Japan</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Expansion of Vice Pres Gore's policy-making role in second Clinton Administration discussed; photo of Pres Clinton and Gore walking in lock-step at White House; Clinton is turning more and more Gore as possible successor who could help insure his own legacy, although Gore's role also grows out of their genuine friendship (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VICE PRESIDENT AL GORE swept into the international talks on global warming here last week and, with a bit of drama, added a passage to his speech that was not in the prepared text. He told the delegates from about 160 nations that after conferring with President Clinton by telephone, he was instructing the American delegation ''to show increased negotiating flexibility.''</p>
        <p>The oratory was hardly soaring -- Mr. Gore's usually isn't -- but with those words, the Vice President helped break an impasse in the talks. And although he invoked the President's name, Mr. Gore later made it clear that adding the critical passage was his idea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VICE PRESIDENT AL GORE swept into the international talks on global warming here last week and, with a bit of drama, added a passage to his speech that was not in the prepared text. He told the delegates from about 160 nations that after conferring with President Clinton by telephone, he was instructing the American delegation ''to show increased negotiating flexibility.''</p>
        <p>The oratory was hardly soaring -- Mr. Gore's usually isn't -- but with those words, the Vice President helped break an impasse in the talks. And although he invoked the President's name, Mr. Gore later made it clear that adding the critical passage was his idea.</p>
        <p>''It was primarily influenced by my assessment of the state of play here,'' he said. ''I then consulted with President Clinton back in the White House and added the paragraph that you're referring to.''</p>
        <p>In other words, it was pretty much Al Gore calling the shots -- another confirmation that the early portrayals of Hillary Rodham Clinton as a ''co-President'' are no longer accurate. Mr. Gore comes closer to filling that role, and now his portfolio is expanding.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Clinton now running for nothing but his place in history, and wearying of some of the starkly political duties he once enjoyed, he is increasingly turning to Mr. Gore, the man who could help insure the Clinton legacy, as his stand-in. Never one for the funereal fare of past Vice Presidents, Mr. Gore is taking on big roles with gusto as he carefully, but surely, steps forth as a contender for the Democratic Presidential nomination in 2000.</p>
        <p>On the Team</p>
        <p>''It seems weekly there are illustrations of the Vice President taking on greater roles, more visible projects that clearly enhance his position,'' said Senator Thomas A. Daschle of South Dakota, the Democratic leader. ''They put him in a strong position to be perceived as heir apparent.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Gore's high-profile assignments -- from debating Ross Perot on free trade early in the Clinton Administration, to landmark telecommunications legislation in 1996, to meetings with leaders in Moscow and Beijing just this year -- have given Americans ample opportunity to grow accustomed to him as an engaged leader, one perhaps even worthy of their trust and future votes. ''He bought into the team -- he's part of it now,'' said Roy Neel, a longtime aide and confidant to Mr. Gore and former deputy chief of staff for Mr. Clinton. ''He's not going to walk away from it.''</p>
        <p>Which, of course, could be a problem for Mr. Gore: There are perils to being inextricably tethered to a President as shaken by controversy as Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Consider the inquiries into the Administration's fund-raising practices that knocked Mr. Gore's carefully planned political agenda off stride this year. Though he has perhaps regained momentum after Attorney General Janet Reno's refusal this month to seek an independent inquiry into his fund-raising calls, the Vice President's vulnerability is clear. It has often seemed as if Mr. Gore -- and not the President -- was the favored target of Republicans. Why bag a lame duck when you can weaken the guy who wants his job?</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore again could have been a target here in Kyoto, particularly since he was the highest-ranking leader to attend -- if only for a day -- and because his credentials on environmental issues are such that Mr. Clinton takes his cues on global warming from Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>In the sort of balancing act that will occupy him for the next three years, the Vice President sought to satisfy environmentalists who are the heart of Democratic Party's traditional liberal base as well as the more moderate business interests who helped elect Mr. Clinton in the first place.</p>
        <p>In this case, the balancing act may have worked. While the global-warming accord reached here won the unqualified praise of few -- and it faces a daunting battle for ratification in the Senate -- Mr. Gore was widely credited by participants for at least helping to keep the negotiations alive.</p>
        <p>It was the kind of performance that Mr. Gore's loyalists say should help convince people that he deserves the top job.</p>
        <p>''For the first time in history we have a Vice President who can step into the role of President literally on a moment's notice without missing a beat,'' Mr. Neel said, ''and with the world understanding it would be a seamless handoff.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's role grows out of the working relationship, and genuine friendship, that has developed between him and the President since the two baby-boom Southerners formed their ticket in the 1992 Presidential campaign. They have weekly private lunches, and their rapport carries over into a high degree of integration between their staffs.</p>
        <p>White House Boosters</p>
        <p>In fact, there is something of a shadow Gore Administration in place already: many of Mr. Clinton's senior aides first worked for Mr. Gore, and have a stake in seeing the Vice President win the office himself in 2000. And in the Cabinet, Andrew Cuomo, the Housing Secretary, and William Daley, the Transportation Secretary, are particularly close to the Vice President. (When he departed Kyoto, Mr. Gore left behind a protege and important player in the talks, Katie McGinty, chairwoman of the Council on Environmental Quality.)</p>
        <p>The White House's drive to help Mr. Gore is intensifying, as was evident after a recent speech by Representative Richard A. Gephardt, the House minority leader, who is angling to run for the Democratic nomination in 2000.</p>
        <p>Speaking at Harvard University, Mr. Gephardt offered a sharp critique of the Clinton-Gore agenda, though he did not mention either the President or Vice President by name. The response was swift: Rahm Emanuel, a senior White House aide, publicly castigated Mr. Gephardt for his ''flip-flops on multiple issues.'' It was a surprising break from the tradition of White House officials staying neutral in nomination battles within their own party.</p>
        <p>Knowing One's Place</p>
        <p>As he has assumed more Presidential roles, Mr. Gore has taken care not to behave too much like a President. His success thus far has come because he has been careful not to upstage Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''Al Gore has all the qualities of being a very strong leader,'' said Richard W. Riley, the Secretary of Education. ''But he's the Vice President. He's not trying to be the President as Vice President. That's why they get along so well together.''</p>
        <p>And as much as Mr. Clinton wants a President Al Gore to complete his legacy, the current President also wants it known that he has not finished burnishing it himself.</p>
        <p>Insisting he was as engaged as ever, Mr. Clinton said in a recent interview in the Oval Office that ''there will be a lot going on next year.''</p>
        <p>''And there will be a lot going on in '99,'' he added. ''And a lot going on in 2000.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 21, 1997, Sunday  An article last Sunday about the relationship between President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore referred incorrectly to a member of the Cabinet. William Daley is Secretary of Commerce, not Transportation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 21, 1997, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about the relationship between President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore referred incorrectly to a member of the Cabinet. William Daley is Secretary of Commerce, not Transportation.</p>
        <p></p>
        <p></p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
