<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fish Are Victorious Over Dam As U.S. Agency Orders Shutdown</title>
    <meta content="Y26DAM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="975945"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Edwards Dam (Maine)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maine</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kennebec River (Maine)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Energy Regulatory Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Carey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DE143AF935A15752C1A961958260" item-length="1149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fish Are Victorious Over Dam As U.S. Agency Orders Shutdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Carey</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Nov. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, handing landmark victory to fish defenders and river enthusiasts, refuses for first time to relicense hydroelectric dam and, going even further, orders aging structure on Maine's Kennebec River demolished at owner's expense; rules that hindrance Edwards Dam poses to migratory fish outweighs benefit it provides in electric generation; maps; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Handing a landmark victory to fish defenders and river enthusiasts, a Federal agency refused today for the first time to relicense a hydroelectric dam and, going even further, ordered the aging structure on Maine's Kennebec River demolished at the owner's expense.</p>
        <p>The agency, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, ruled that the hindrance the Edwards Dam posed to migratory fish outweighed the benefit it provided in electric generation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Handing a landmark victory to fish defenders and river enthusiasts, a Federal agency refused today for the first time to relicense a hydroelectric dam and, going even further, ordered the aging structure on Maine's Kennebec River demolished at the owner's expense.</p>
        <p>The agency, the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, ruled that the hindrance the Edwards Dam posed to migratory fish outweighed the benefit it provided in electric generation.</p>
        <p>The 160-year-old dam, which produces one-tenth of 1 percent of Maine's electricity, largely blocks the passage of sturgeon, salmon and other fish that struggle upstream to spawn, the commission said.</p>
        <p>''Today's order requiring the removal of the Edwards Dam reflects a balanced view of environmental as well as social and economic considerations,'' said James J. Hoecker, chairman of the commission, which oversees the nation's power industry.</p>
        <p>Since a 1986 change in Federal law, the commission has been required to balance conservation, recreation and other environmental values with energy generation in deciding whether to renew licenses. But the Edwards Dam is the first case in which it has exercised the power to deny a license.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hoecker emphasized that the decision to remove the dam, which is in Augusta, need not be viewed with trepidation by the hydroelectric industry, which provides 14 percent of the nation's electricity, because Edwards is a special case involving a tiny amount of generation and a great deal of environmental damage.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the decision had been  anxiously awaited, particularly in Western states with many large dams. About 550 dams will come up for relicensing in the next 15 years, and many hinder the spawning routes of salmon and other fish.</p>
        <p>Though the 3.5-megawatt Edwards Dam may be a special case, its pending demise was hailed by environmentalists today as a major triumph. ''This is the first time the commission has said no,'' said Pete Didisheim of the Natural Resources Council of Maine, which helped lead opposition to the dam.</p>
        <p>The decision also brought warnings of peril from the Edison Electric Institute, representing investor-owned public utilities, which noted that hydropower provided more than 95 percent of America's renewable energy. ''This is a dangerous precedent,'' said James Evans, the institute's manager of hydropower issues. ''Declining to issue a new license for a dam, or going even further to order the owner to remove the dam, are precedent-setting steps that Congress has not authorized in the Federal Power Act.''</p>
        <p>For all of today's drama, however, the demise of the Edwards Dam does not look especially imminent. The Edwards Manufacturing Company, which owns the dam and holds its license together with the City of Augusta, plans to appeal the commission's decision, first before the panel itself and then, if need be, in court, said Mark Isaacson, the company's vice president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Isaacson said that under the 1920 Federal law that governs dam licensing, if the Government wants to deny renewal to a licensee, it must compensate the company for its net investment in the project. That would amount to $6 million to $10 million for Edwards Manufacturing, he estimated. But the energy commission ruled that it was within its rights not only to deny that compensation but also to order the company to pay for the demolition, which is expected to cost more than $2 million, and to pay for any environmental damage the demolition causes.</p>
        <p>''Why do they think they can get away with it?'' Mr. Isaacson asked. ''Because they're so much bigger than we are. We're a small private company with four employees.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the forces in the fight over the dam have not been very evenly matched. A broad coalition of environmental groups, state agencies right up to Maine's Governor, and Federal agencies right up to the Secretary of the Interior all advocated the removal of the dam.</p>
        <p>Since the change in law, the Federal commission has ordered the removal of seven other dams, but this was the first case involving a dam owner that wanted to continue its operations. It was also a case skewed heavily in favor of the fish.</p>
        <p>Before the dam was built in 1837, the Kennebec River was extraordinarily rich in aquatic life, providing a migratory route and spawning grounds to virtually every species in the Northeast that struggles upstream to breed, from sturgeon to salmon. The dam devastated many of them, and fish ladders installed later did little to restore the stocks.</p>
        <p>In more recent years, though, Maine worked to improve its water quality and help migrating fish return with fish lifts. In its application for relicensing, Edwards Manufacturing offered to install new and improved ways to help fish get upstream to spawn, and the Federal commission's staff at first offered tentative approval to the plans.</p>
        <p>But environmentalists responded with 7,000 pages of rebuttal, arguing that some species, like the endangered shortnose sturgeon and the Atlantic sturgeon, could not effectively use ''fish passages.'' Also, they said, returning the river to its natural state would restore 15 miles of river habitat that were favored spawning grounds of several species.</p>
        <p>Recreation enthusiasts also argued that fishing and boating on the river would be vastly improved if the dam was eliminated, giving them an uninterrupted 60-mile stretch of river.</p>
        <p>In its decision today, the commission noted that the dam did produce energy that would otherwise probably be produced by nonrenewable fossil fuels. And that is Mr. Isaacson's main argument as well: that hydroelectric power is clean and renewable, and provides additional side benefits like irrigation reserves.</p>
        <p>But the commission decided that the benefits of the dam were definitively outweighed by its costs, saying, ''We believe that the public interest in this proceeding lies in our denying the license application.''</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview today, Mr. Isaacson asserted that The New York Times Company co-owns two dams upstream on the Kennebec in connection with its paper interests in Maine; He would be happy to remove the Edwards dam at his own cost, he said in a challenge only partly in jest, if The Times would do the same with its dams.</p>
        <p>(In fact, The New York Times Company has only a 40 percent equity interest -- and therefore not a controlling one -- in Madison Paper Industries, which owns and operates the two dams, said Nancy Nielsen, spokeswoman for The Times.)</p>
        <p>The appeals process could go on for months or years, Mr. Isaacson said. In the meantime, he said, the dam's licensees must apply yearly for short-term licenses, as they have been doing since their long-term license ran out in 1993.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
