<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study of Shuttle's Exhaust Plume Aims to Show Effects on Ozone Layer</title>
    <meta content="01OZON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="919638"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Columbia (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Forces</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3DC1E3AF932A35757C0A961958260" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study of Shuttle's Exhaust Plume Aims to Show Effects on Ozone Layer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers plan to fly reconnaissance jet into space shuttle Columbia's exhaust plume to study how exhaust affects ozone layer; Air Force-funded program seeks to determine if space shuttles and other rockets cause local weak spot or depression in protective ozone layer (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN a space shuttle rockets into orbit, most eyes turn to other things as soon as the flame and smoke of takeoff dissipate. However, for hours after the shuttle Columbia flies on Thursday, researchers are to make detailed studies of the spaceship's exhaust to see how it affects the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Columbia, which is to carry a seven-member crew on a 16-day science mission, will be entering orbit around Earth when a former Air Force reconnaissance jet flies into the trail of its exhaust to see what has been left behind and how it has changed the chemistry of the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN a space shuttle rockets into orbit, most eyes turn to other things as soon as the flame and smoke of takeoff dissipate. However, for hours after the shuttle Columbia flies on Thursday, researchers are to make detailed studies of the spaceship's exhaust to see how it affects the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Columbia, which is to carry a seven-member crew on a 16-day science mission, will be entering orbit around Earth when a former Air Force reconnaissance jet flies into the trail of its exhaust to see what has been left behind and how it has changed the chemistry of the air.</p>
        <p>When the WB-57F plane enters Columbia's exhaust plume, it will mark the first time such detailed studies have been made of a space shuttle's impact on the atmospheric chemistry of the stratosphere. The aircraft previously conducted similar studies of the launchings of two Titan 4 rockets, the nation's largest unmanned boosters, and a smaller Delta rocket.</p>
        <p>The studies are trying to determine if space shuttles and other rockets cause a local weak spot or depression in the protective ozone layer that would allow harmful ultraviolet rays from the Sun to reach Earth, which could pose a localized health hazard. Exposure to ultraviolet rays increases the risk of skin cancer and other health problems.</p>
        <p>The research is part of an Air Force-sponsored program called Rocket Impacts on Stratospheric Ozone, or RISO, initiated to comply with a Federal law requiring Government agencies to understand the environmental impacts of their operations.</p>
        <p>''We've been trying to chase a shuttle for almost a year, and we are finally getting our chance,'' said Dr. Philip Whitefield of the University of Missouri at Rolla, an atmospheric researcher with an experiment on the airplane. The tests can be conducted only during daytime launchings of the shuttle and only when the heavily used research plane is available. A research flight scheduled for November, for example, had to be canceled because of repeated delays of the shuttle's launching, he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Whitefield, working with Dr. Donald Hagan of the university's Cloud and Aerosol Sciences Laboratory, has an experiment to measure the size and distribution of particles in the air produced by the shuttle's booster rockets. Their instruments,  in the plane's bomb bay, will measure particles in the air as the jet zigs across the shuttle's path and bottles some samples for later analysis.</p>
        <p>The tests are to begin 20 minutes after Discovery's liftoff, the soonest that safety rules will allow. The countdown began yesterday for a launching scheduled for 2:01 P.M. on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The high-altitude plane, which is to be loitering in the air near the Kennedy Space Center at launching time, is to climb to 55,000 feet and fly figure-eight patterns through the shuttle's plume. In more than two hours of maneuvering, the twin-engine jet is to climb to an altitude exceeding 65,000 feet, scientists say.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists first raised concerns about the impact of rocket exhaust, particularly from solid fuel rockets, on stratospheric ozone about eight years ago. Most solid rocket fuel contains an ingredient, ammonium perchlorate, that when burned produces large amounts of hydrochloric acid and chlorine, chemicals that act as catalysts to break down ozone.</p>
        <p>Ozone, a molecule made up of three oxygen atoms, forms a protective zone in the stratosphere at altitudes of 9 to 30 miles to screen harmful ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>Studies conducted by the Government and independent groups have concluded that while large solid rockets can dump a significant amount of chlorine-related chemicals into the atmosphere above a launching site, rockets contributed to much less than 1 percent of global ozone loss, far less than industrial sources.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, a space shuttle's 149-foot-tall, twin solid boosters, the largest in the world, injects some 75 tons of chlorine into the stratosphere, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration estimates. In addition, the rockets deposit tons of aluminum compounds. Those particles do not harm ozone by themselves, but they could provide a surface area on which chlorine chemicals become more active, researchers say.</p>
        <p>Steven Aftergood, a senior analyst with the Federation of American Scientists, a private policy group based in Washington that was among the first to call attention to the rocket-ozone issue, said that NASA and the Air Force were correct in continuing to study the problem.</p>
        <p>''Rocket exhaust is not a major source of general ozone depletion, but rocket launches are the source of intense, localized ozone depletion that we don't understand the consequences of,'' Mr. Aftergood said. ''It is good to try to narrow the level of uncertainty around this issue.''</p>
        <p>Martin Ross, director of the RISO program for theAerospace Corporation, an El Segundo, Calif., company that manages the effort for the Air Force, said the test jet that is to study the shuttle's exhaust carried instruments from the University of Houston to make direct measurements of ozone levels and equipment from the Air Force's Phillips Laboratory to look for chlorine atoms and compounds.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Ross said, the program has operated a ground-based laser scanning system at Cape Canaveral since October 1995 to measure the breakup of rocket plumes and how they distribute themselves through the air column. Researchers have also placed ultraviolet radiation sensors on the ground to see if there is an increase as the plume passes between the Sun and the ground. So far, he said, no increases in ground-level ultraviolet readings have been noted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
