<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Study Climate, Freeze Into Arctic Ice</title>
    <meta content="28ARCT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="968596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Icebreakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Des Groseilliers (Icebreaker)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Icebreakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDD1431F93BA15753C1A961958260" item-length="1962" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Study Climate, Freeze Into Arctic Ice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <dateline>ICE STATION SHEBA, in the Arctic Ocean</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists from five nations allow icebreaker to be frozen into floe drifting in Arctic Ocean, where they will gather gigantic treasury of data during coming year; hope their measurements will settle some disagreements among theorists about interaction of Arctic climate with that of rest of world and eliminate some major uncertainties in global climate forecasting; photo of icebreaker Des Groseilliers, now frozen into ice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOPING to eliminate some major uncertainties in global climate forecasting, scientists from five nations have allowed an icebreaker to be frozen into a floe drifting in the Arctic Ocean, where they will gather a gigantic treasury of data during the coming year.</p>
        <p>With luck, their measurements, many made at the cost of acute discomfort, frostbitten fingers and other injuries, will settle some disagreements among theorists about the interaction of the Arctic climate with that of the rest of the world. The yearlong program is called Sheba, an acronym for Surface Heat Budget of the Arctic Ocean. It is a web of interrelated measurements that will put climate theories to practical tests, perhaps ruling out some theories and confirming others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOPING to eliminate some major uncertainties in global climate forecasting, scientists from five nations have allowed an icebreaker to be frozen into a floe drifting in the Arctic Ocean, where they will gather a gigantic treasury of data during the coming year.</p>
        <p>With luck, their measurements, many made at the cost of acute discomfort, frostbitten fingers and other injuries, will settle some disagreements among theorists about the interaction of the Arctic climate with that of the rest of the world. The yearlong program is called Sheba, an acronym for Surface Heat Budget of the Arctic Ocean. It is a web of interrelated measurements that will put climate theories to practical tests, perhaps ruling out some theories and confirming others.</p>
        <p>Some theorists believe, for example, that a doubling of the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere in the next century could warm it enough to melt all of the Arctic sea ice, which covers an area the size of the United States. Such a change would have profound consequences for the global climate.</p>
        <p>But other climatologists believe that the effect of increased carbon dioxide would be less severe. Only by measuring fine details of the complex climate engine will it be possible to assess and perhaps resolve such broad questions, said Dr. Richard E. Moritz of the University of Washington, director of the Sheba project.</p>
        <p>An understanding of the dynamics of the Arctic climate, moreover, will allow analysts to make much better use of satellite pictures of the polar ocean, which cannot now reliably distinguish between cloud cover and surface ice. Clouds and sea ice have very different roles in shaping climate, and an improvement in the interpretation of satellite pictures -- made possible by comparing them with actual ground observations -- would be an important achievement.</p>
        <p>Sheba, costing $19.5 million, is by far the most expensive and complex research program ever financed by the National Science Foundation in the Arctic. (The agency spends much more than this every year for research in Antarctica.) The work is also supported by the Office of Naval Research, the Japanese Government and other organizations.</p>
        <p>The project's 50 scientists, most of them Americans, are gathering data with the help of the icebound icebreaker, an escort icebreaker and two auxiliary vessels, as well as research aircraft and sounding balloons. Another contributor to the project is the nuclear submarine Archerfish, which periodically cruises beneath the floe supporting the Sheba camp, measuring the underside and contours of the ice.</p>
        <p>The center of this activity is the  Des Groseilliers, a heavy icebreaker of the Canadian Coast Guard that has been chartered by the scientists for one year. The ship rammed its prow into a floe some 320 miles north of the Alaskan coast and shut down its powerful engines on Oct. 2. It will remain here for one year.</p>
        <p>Solidly hemmed in by thick ice covering water some 11,000 feet deep, the Des Groseilliers is the first research ship to be deliberately frozen into Arctic pack ice since the great Norwegian explorer and scientist Fridtjof Nansen allowed his wooden ship, the Fram, to freeze into the ice in 1893 so he could make  scientific observations.</p>
        <p>The strategy adopted by the Sheba team was to mark out a roughly cylindrical column with a radius of about 30 miles, extending from the upper ocean through the ice-covered surface and on up through the clouds to the top of the atmosphere. At the center of this column is the icebreaker. Its position was chosen so the column would include representative samples of thick pack ice, melted surface ponds, open water in cracks (known as leads), many types of snow cover and all possible cloud conditions. The idea is to study intensively a region that typifies the entire Arctic Ocean.</p>
        <p>Teams of scientists have deployed thousands of sensors within the column: in the water, in the surface ice and in the air, on towers and balloons. Upward-looking radar and laser beams penetrate and chart the upper atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In the water, sensors continuously measure temperature, salinity and current speeds and directions at various depths.</p>
        <p>Sensors embedded in holes drilled into the pack ice measure ice temperature and composition and ice stress.</p>
        <p>A network of stress sensors implanted in the last three weeks in the ice by Jacqueline Richter-Menge, an engineer from the United States Army's Cold Regions Research and Engineering Laboratory in Hanover, N.H., is continuously measuring stresses that can cause sudden cracks in the ice. Cracks may widen to produce open leads that quickly freeze over as smooth ice, or they may slam closed, with one sheet of ice riding up over its neighbor to create a feature known as a pressure ridge. All these changes affect the reflection or absorption of energy, the transfer of heat and the local climate.</p>
        <p>The sudden appearance of a lead can cause difficulties for inhabitants of the Sheba floe. A lead that opens across an ice runway, for example, would force engineers to find another stretch of level ice on the floe and smooth it out to accommodate the Twin Otter transport planes that link Sheba with the town of Deadhorse on Alaska's northern coast. A new lead could also leave one or more of the many field camps temporarily cut off from the ship.</p>
        <p>But most of the scientists here look forward to cracks forming in the ice.</p>
        <p>''A lead opening nearby would offer us a chance to do science right on our doorstep,'' said Dr. Donald Perovich of the Army's cold regions laboratory, who also serves as Sheba's chief scientist. ''Leads are vitally important factors in heat transfer, and it would be convenient to have one nearby.''</p>
        <p>In the air, sensors mounted on towers and in aircraft and suspended from sounding balloons equipped with Global Positioning System receivers record changes in wind direction, velocity, humidity and other conditions at all altitudes, while satellites passing above Sheba generate still more information.</p>
        <p>Most of the many thousands of instruments in the project will gather data continuously for one year, creating a very detailed record of everything of importance that occurs within the ocean-ice-atmosphere column.</p>
        <p>The ice station, a collection of plywood huts, towers, instruments and the icebreaker itself, spread across a rectangular floe about four by nine miles in size, is moving constantly in response to wind, ocean currents and the Coriolis force, an effect of the earth's rotation. It is surrounded on all sides by neighboring floes.</p>
        <p>Current sensors in the water under the ice quickly detect any motion imparted to the big floe by even a light breeze.</p>
        <p>The main thrust of the Sheba program is to gauge the relative importance of various natural feedback mechanisms.</p>
        <p>An example of negative feedback, in which a process limits itself automatically, could start with the formation of a warm region on the earth's surface. A rising column of warm air from this region would encounter cold air, and the resulting condensation might produce a cloud. The cloud would obstruct sunlight from reaching the surface, cooling the initially warm region.</p>
        <p>Both negative and positive feedback control climate, particularly in the Arctic, where clouds, ice and water all affect each other in complex ways.</p>
        <p>An example of positive feedback might also involve sunlight. When sunlight strikes highly reflective ice, most of the energy is bounced back into space. But when a crack forms in an ice floe, unfrozen ocean water is exposed, and open water, unlike ice, absorbs most of the solar radiation reaching it. Under certain conditions, that might warm and open up even more water, reinforcing the effect.</p>
        <p>Although scientists believe that they understand the general feedback mechanisms affecting climate, the directions and intensities of the feedback loops are largely unknown.</p>
        <p>''We can't even be sure whether some of these feedback mechanisms are positive or negative, much less know anything about their numerical values,'' said Taneil Uttal of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration. Mrs. Uttal leads a team of investigators probing the atmosphere and cloud structure using radar and laser beams.</p>
        <p>''Our work will measure the size of particles in clouds, the thickness of clouds and their optical qualities, the number of cloud layers above the ship and so on,'' she said. ''Combined with measurements being made of the surface ice and of the water beneath us, these should help us know a lot more about Arctic feedback mechanisms.''</p>
        <p>Although Sheba is the first drifting ice station with a ship at its center since Nansen's day, many ice islands in the high Arctic have served as research stations over the years. The largest of these, named Fletcher's Ice Island, or T-3, was discovered in 1947 and, beginning in 1952, occupied by a party led by Lieut. Col. Joseph O. Fletcher of the Air Force. It was periodically used as a research base until the early 1960's.</p>
        <p>Another major climate research program, the Arctic Ice Dynamics Joint Experiment, was conducted for a year in 1975-76, and many leaders of the Sheba expedition worked on that experiment.</p>
        <p>But no previous research effort in the Arctic Ocean has approached the scope and complexity of Sheba or used a ship embedded in ice as a headquarters.</p>
        <p>The Des Groseilliers (named for the 17th-century explorer Medard Chouart, Sieur des Groseilliers, co-discoverer of the Great Lakes) offers a comfortable base of operations for research, but it also creates problems. Even with its engines shut down, the Des Groseilliers burns four tons of diesel fuel each day just to keep warm and generate electric power. Most of the heat this represents flows into the ocean around the ship, so it could skew temperature nearby measurements.</p>
        <p>The scientists believe, however, that most of their instruments are far enough away from the ship that heat pollution will be negligible.</p>
        <p>Another kind of problem may result from the ship's discharge of sewage.</p>
        <p>Two Canadian scientists, Dr. Harold Welch and his wife, Catherine, are observing algae, plankton, fish and other organisms near the ship, and all of them could be affected by sewage. Working with them, Dr. Igor A. Melnikov, of the Shirshov Oceanography Institute in Moscow, has begun making frequent dives under the ice near the ship to photograph and record biological changes during a complete cycle of seasons.</p>
        <p>And two scientists from Oregon State University, Dr. Patricia Wheeler and Sandy Moore, are measuring nutrients in the water near the ship.</p>
        <p>''If we find that we're getting high levels of phosphates,'' Dr. Wheeler said, ''we'll know we're seeing detergents in sewage from the ship, and sewage can affect the growth of bacteria, protozoa and other organisms. That's something we'll have to take into consideration.''</p>
        <p>The flood of data from Sheba is reaching the outer world through a ''data policeman,'' James A. Moore of the University Corporation for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo. Mr. Moore organizes the data in convenient form and quickly moves it to the Internet, where it can be used by scientists everywhere.</p>
        <p>''This data will be studied for a good 30 years,'' Dr. Perovich said.</p>
        <p>But an analysis of Sheba's harvest will not be easy. Fitting all the pieces into a coherent framework capable of making accurate predictions will require a bewildering thicket of partial differential equations and other mathematical tools.</p>
        <p>''It may also take a touch of genius,'' Dr. Moritz said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
