<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the New Europe, a Tilt To Using Wind's Power</title>
    <meta content="07WIND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Denmark</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Denmark</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Denmark</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Windmills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D81E3DF934A35751C1A961958260" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the New Europe, a Tilt To Using Wind's Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>COPENHAGEN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wind power is booming across Europe, encouraged by improved technology, falling costs and Government incentives like tax credits and guaranteed prices; 4,700 windmills in Denmark generate 6 percent of country's electricity; policymakers point to boom as key example of how pollution can be cut without jeopardizing jobs or economic growth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On weekends, when Per Volund goes jogging around Copenhagen harbor, he is drawn to a pier with a row of sleek, modern windmills. As he watches the fiberglass blades spin in the breeze, he knows that they are sending electricity to the grid -- and money into his pocket.</p>
        <p>Mr. Volund belongs to a cooperative that bought and installed four 160-foot towers on this prime spot by the sea. He is also part of a large Danish movement -- the Organization for Renewable Energy -- with a daring and ambitious goal. Its backers set out a decade ago to prove that even if big business or utilities had no interest in such experiments, private citizens could produce inexpensive  energy that did not pollute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On weekends, when Per Volund goes jogging around Copenhagen harbor, he is drawn to a pier with a row of sleek, modern windmills. As he watches the fiberglass blades spin in the breeze, he knows that they are sending electricity to the grid -- and money into his pocket.</p>
        <p>Mr. Volund belongs to a cooperative that bought and installed four 160-foot towers on this prime spot by the sea. He is also part of a large Danish movement -- the Organization for Renewable Energy -- with a daring and ambitious goal. Its backers set out a decade ago to prove that even if big business or utilities had no interest in such experiments, private citizens could produce inexpensive  energy that did not pollute.</p>
        <p>''We call it power from the people,'' said Mr. Volund, a 33-year-old engineer. ''We do it because we believe in it.''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Volund, thousands of committed environmentalists, including students, professionals and farmers, have dug into their savings to buy turbines and licenses to operate them. They lobbied the Government and the utilities until they finally agreed to buy wind energy. The result has been a quiet revolution.</p>
        <p>Today, close to 100,000 Danes own shares in the hundreds of small cooperatives that operate 4,700 windmills here. And they are making profits. Wind power generates 6 percent of Denmark's electricity, giving this country the highest per capita output of wind energy in the world.</p>
        <p>While the American wind industry has stalled, wind power is booming across Europe, encouraged by improved technology, falling costs and Government incentives like tax credits and guaranteed prices. Several governments have set targets to stimulate production.</p>
        <p>European policymakers point to the boom as a key example of how pollution can be cut without jeopardizing jobs or economic growth. With  windmills springing up from the coasts of Sweden to the tip of southern Spain, Europe's wind industry already employs 20,000 people.</p>
        <p>One reason for the growth is that the European Union wants to diversify its energy sources while clamping down on polluters; almost no country could get the political support to expand nuclear plants. The other, more compelling, reason is that in many areas wind power is becoming economically viable.</p>
        <p>Powerful new wind turbines can already generate electricity far less expensively than solar panels, biomass or other nontraditional sources, according to the International Energy Agency, a research organization based in Paris. Its studies show that wind energy is now becoming competitive with electricity from Europe's ubiquitous oil-  and coal-fired power plants. For wind, supply starts at the windmills, which do not require mines, oil fields, tankers, dumps, refineries and combustion. Moreover, windmills do not emit sulphur dioxide, which causes acid rain, and carbon dioxide, the most widespread greenhouse gas.</p>
        <p>''Wind energy is now one of the cheapest ways to cut back on greenhouse gases,'' said Ritt Bjerregaard, the European Union Commissioner for the Environment.</p>
        <p>The future role of renewable energy is on the agenda for the international conference on global warming in Kyoto, Japan. Before the conference, the European Union announced a plan to double the share of renewable energy in its 15 member countries -- to 12 percent by 2010. Today's 6 percent share comes largely from hydroelectric power. But the new $23 billion plan is a key part of the union's strategy to cut greenhouse gases. It will provide additional  funds and incentives for wind, solar and other projects.</p>
        <p>In wind power, Europe has already overtaken the United States, which led the drive to wind in the 1980's. Europe's capacity of 4,100 megawatts now amounts to two and a half times that of the United States, with Germany alone surpassing the capacity of American wind farms.</p>
        <p>The way wind is produced underlines a contrast between Europe and the United States. American entrepreneurs, seeing wind as big business, built large wind farms with huge numbers of turbines. When oil prices fell and tax credits were cut because of policy changes, growth stalled. In Northern Europe, wind power is basically a cottage industry.</p>
        <p>Denmark, Germany, Sweden and the Netherlands have each spawned grass-roots movements with small groups of often politically motivated investors installing one or a few machines at a time and scattering them.</p>
        <p>In Spain, Britain and Greece, the clusters are larger because money has been provided by local governments and utilities. The latest trend in Europe is to start building wind farms offshore, where there is more wind and fewer complaints that they clutter up the landscape.</p>
        <p>''Many projects are small because this fits in with our history,'' said Marielle van Aggelen, a consultant at the Dutch Bureau for Wind Energy. Indeed, less than a century ago, before national grids expanded and electricity output became centralized, much of Europe was studded with the traditional windmills, often privately owned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
