<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="05FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="948653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970805T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D8113DF936A3575BC0A961958260" item-length="1607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>North Koreans Pushed To Starvation, Officials Say  Two months of high temperatures and no rain in North Korea have pushed millions of people in the isolated country, whose food stocks were already low, to the brink of famine, reported relief officials returning from recent visits there.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>North Koreans Pushed To Starvation, Officials Say  Two months of high temperatures and no rain in North Korea have pushed millions of people in the isolated country, whose food stocks were already low, to the brink of famine, reported relief officials returning from recent visits there.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Oil Giant Adopts New Stance  Delegates to a meeting on climate change in Bonn were surprised to hear British Petroleum, the world's third-largest oil company, announce that it believed that concern about the burning of fossil fuels was scientifically warranted. Industry lobbyists had previously denied a link between greenhouse gases and climate change.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Yeltsin Revalues the Ruble  Russians cynically watched tycoons and bankers feud over the privatization of a nickel mine, but reacted when President Boris N. Yeltsin announced that as of Jan. 1, his government will redenominate the ruble by a factor of 1,000. The move was meant to counter a symbol of inflation, which has led to the current exchange rate of 6,000 rubles to the dollar. Mr. Yeltsin, speaking while on holiday at a health spa, sought to assure wary Russians that the reform would ''not be a confiscation.'' People have until the end of the century to exchange their old bills.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>U.S. Suspends Bosnia Contact  The Clinton Administration announced it would suspend its contacts with Bosnia's Ambassador to the United States. The major European countries have done the same, after Bosnia's three-member presidency in Sarajevo failed to agree upon and name ambassadors capable of representing Bosnia's Muslims, Croats and Serbs. Agreeing upon the diplomatic appointments was required by the Dayton peace accords that ended the civil war.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Israel Halts Revenue Transfer  The Israeli Government suspended reimbursement of taxes and other fees owed to the Palestinian Authority. The fees account for the majority of the Palestinian Authority's annual revenue and represent a variety of taxes collected by Israel from Palestinians. Israeli officials acknowledged that the tactic violated the peace accord but said the funding could be restored if Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat and his Government begin to crack down on Islamic militants.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Israeli officials believed the suicide bombers in last week's attack in Jerusalem belonged to the militant Islamic group Hamas but their identity remained a mystery.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>74 Killed in Algerian Massacres  A total of 74 Algerian villagers were  killed in a new series of massacres in the Blida and Ain-Defla regions, local residents said. The killings occurred within hours of a call by President Liamine Zeroual for public ''vigilance'' in the wake of a series of  bloody massacres attributed to Islamic extremists that have left more than 600 dead in the last two months.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-17</p>
        <p>Panel Proposes Abolishing U.S. Immigration Agency  A Federal advisory panel has decided to recommend abolishing the embattled Immigration and Naturalization Service and assign its duties to other Government agencies in an effort to improve the nation's immigration system. The United States Commission on Immigration Reform is proposing that the Justice Department, the immigration service's parent agency, retain responsibility for controlling the border and removing illegal immigrants. The State Department, which now deals with visas at American embassies overseas, would handle immigration services and benefits, like citizenship requests. And the Labor Department, which now monitors wage and hour laws, would also enforce rules covering the hiring of foreign workers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Medicare Poised for Reform  The budget bill awaiting President Clinton's signature includes two new health insurance options that give Medicare beneficiaries greater freedom to choose their doctors and hospitals, but it also exposes elderly patients to much higher costs. The options, which represent a radical departure from current Medicare policy, are likely to appeal to rugged individualists who resent Government interference with their medical care and can afford to pay more for it.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Impact of U.P.S. Strike Felt  A strike by 185,000 members of the teamsters' union idled most of the familiar brown trucks of the United Parcel Service, slowing the movement of millions of packages and inconveniencing businesses and their customers across the country.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Weld Draws Renewed Support  The White House said that it would ''go to the mat'' for William Weld to be Ambassador to Mexico but that it would not directly challenge the decision by Senator Jesse Helms, chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, to deny Mr. Weld a hearing.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Action Delayed on Tobacco Deal  President Clinton is likely to delay acting on the proposed $368.5 billion tobacco settlement proposal until after he returns next month from a two-week summer vacation, White House officials said. Mr. Clinton had originally been expected to indicate his position on the proposal before leaving on vacation at the end of next week. But the White House press secretary Michael D. McCurry said that even if Mr. Clinton received the recommendations of an Administration task force currently reviewing the plan, he was unlikely to announce his position on it until September.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Hostage Taker Kills Himself  A man took a former girlfriend hostage at the corporate headquarters of the Inland Container Corporation in Indianapolis, and then kept police officers at bay for three hours before killing himself as she ran down a hallway. The man, Ronald Lowe, 48, died of self-inflicted gunshot wounds after he told the police that he did not want to return to jail.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>School District Created For Hasidic Jews Again  The New York State Legislature passed legislation that would create a special public school district for a small but influential community of Hasidic Jews in the village of Kiryas Joel. The United States Supreme Court and the Court of Appeals, New York State's highest court, have struck down two similar pieces of legislation, saying that those measures violated a key Constitutional principle that establishes the division between government and religion.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Picture of Suspects  Investigators retracing the steps of Ghazi Abu Mezer and Lafi Khalil, the two suspects in an alleged subway bombing plot, are increasingly mystified to discover that, rather than having shown strong religious or political convictions, they appear to be merely a pair of drifters and street hustlers.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Insurer Fights Disclosure  The Prudential Insurance Company agreed in a national class-action settlement several months ago to pay at least $410 million to policyholders deceived by its sales agents, but since then the company has quietly begun a legal fight to keep documents from customers who rejected the settlement.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>B10-16</p>
        <p>Cowboys Coach Arrested  Dallas Cowboys coach Barry Switzer was arrested after a loaded .38 caliber revolver was found in his carry-on baggage at Dallas-Fort Worth Airport. The incident raises questions about Switzer's long-term future as coach.</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Aboriginal Makes Track History  Cathy Freeman of Australia became the first Aboriginal to win a major international track and field title, taking the quarter mile in 49.77 seconds at the world championships in Athens. She becomes a gold medal hope for Australia at the upcoming 2000 Summer Olympics in the capital of Sydney.</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Direct Marketing for Drugs  Dozens of prescription drugs are now being marketed directly to consumers in an escalating blitz of magazine, newspaper and television advertisements. The campaigns have intrigued patients, startled doctors and left policy makers and regulatory agencies scrambling to catch up.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>C9-15</p>
        <p>Nashville in New York  The conventional wisdom in Nashville is that New York, a stronghold of liberalism, single adults and ethnic cultures, is a tough market for country-music acts. But country-music star Garth Brooks is giving a concert in Central Park on Thursday night, and the buzz has it that a million people will attend.</p>
        <p>C9</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-20</p>
        <p>HarperCollins to Reorganize  The News Corporation announced it would take a $270 million charge against earnings in fiscal 1997 to revamp its HarperCollins unit. The company said the charge was largely for inventories of returned books and author advances for unprofitable books. The charge is one of the largest taken in the publishing industry. Contrary to recent rumors, company executives insisted the business was not for sale.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Columbia Names Executives  Columbia/HCA Healthcare named a former top executive with the Hospital Corporation of America as president and chief operating officer. The executive, Jack O. Bovender Jr., is a longtime colleague of Thomas F. Frist Jr., who last month was named chairman and chief executive of the giant health care company. The announcement finalizes a new management team intended to stabilize the company as it faces a growing criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>D2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Jeanne Calment  A native of Arles, France, who was the oldest human being whose age had been verified by official documents, she was 122.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>Ruth Adler  The editor of the New York Times' in-house journal Times Talk was 87.</p>
        <p>B8</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19  Editorials: China's resistance to fair trade; Nynex captures the regulators; history that remains hidden.</p>
        <p>Columns: A. M. Rosenthal, Russell Baker.</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B20</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>C5</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D20</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
