<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Astronauts Fail to Locate A Puncture Crippling Mir</title>
    <meta content="07ORBI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="955906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mir (Space Station)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Solovyev, Anatoly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foale, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DD1E30F934A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="1188" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Astronauts Fail to Locate A Puncture Crippling Mir</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>KOROLYOV, Russia, Sept. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Six-hour space walk by Russian and US astronauts Anatoly Solovyev and Michael Foale fails to locate hole in damaged Mir space station; complicated and risky spacewalk had been billed as reconnaissance mission to find a hole or holes punched into Mir during collision with space cargo vessel on June 25; collision damaged Spektr module, which was used for scientific research, forcing crew to seal off section and curtailing its power supply; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A six-hour spacewalk by Russian and American astronauts this morning was unable to locate the hole in the damaged Mir, dealing a major setback to efforts to repair the stricken space station.</p>
        <p>The complicated and risky spacewalk had been billed as a reconnaissance mission to find a hole or holes punched into Mir during a collision with a space cargo vessel on June 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A six-hour spacewalk by Russian and American astronauts this morning was unable to locate the hole in the damaged Mir, dealing a major setback to efforts to repair the stricken space station.</p>
        <p>The complicated and risky spacewalk had been billed as a reconnaissance mission to find a hole or holes punched into Mir during a collision with a space cargo vessel on June 25.</p>
        <p>But after a painstaking and fruitless search in which the Mir commander, Anatoly Solovyov, was hoisted to the damaged section of the space station on a special crane, the spacewalk team was ordered to return to the relative safety of the spacecraft.</p>
        <p>''Finish your job and come home,'' the Mission Control Center here instructed the astronauts.</p>
        <p>Russian space officials did not conceal their disappointment that the crew had been unable to locate any punctures.</p>
        <p>''We will find some ways to find it,'' Vladimir Solovyov, head of Mission Control, said with more resignation than confidence. ''If it is in the solar array area, it's going to be the most complicated case.''</p>
        <p>Other officials said that dismantling a damaged solar array to try to locate the hole would be an extremely difficult operation. Mission Control officials are considering a plan to inflate the damaged Spektr module partially and then try to track the source of the leak.</p>
        <p>Another spacewalk will be carried out early next month, Russian space officials said.</p>
        <p>The collision in June damaged the Spektr module, which was used for scientific research, forcing the crew to seal off this section of Mir and curtailing its power supply.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mir's crew has fought an uphill battle to repair the space station, enduring one breakdown after another along the way.</p>
        <p>The crew has already reconnected electrical cables. And despite the day's frustrations, today's mission achieved one important goal when the Russian astronaut in the spacewalk team managed to turn two of the four solar arrays more directly toward the sun. That repair was necessary because the crew of Mir has been unable to direct the arrays electronically from inside the station, hampering the effort to charge their batteries.</p>
        <p>Russian officials said that Mir had now restored most of the power it had before its collision. That not only provides more power for scientific experiments but also it means that the crew will have more power in reserve in the event of a malfunction or emergency.</p>
        <p>''Unless you can recover power it is going to be very difficult to get productive scientific work done,'' Jerry Linenger, the American astronaut who completed a mission on Mir earlier this year, said in an interview here today.</p>
        <p>''Power gives you reserve,'' Mr. Linenger said. ''It gives you a cushion. The more reserve power you have, the more options you have should something fail. If one of your oxygen generating systems drops off line and you have enough power you can fire another one back up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Linenger said the crew still needed to restore the ability to direct the arrays electronically so that the systems can regularly be maneuvered into a good position to capture solar energy. One problem may be that the motors that are supposed to drive the arrays do not work well inside the vacuum of the damaged Spektr module.</p>
        <p>Because the crew cannot automatically steer the arrays, today's manipulation of the arrays was a little like having to climb on the roof of a house and fiddle with a television antenna to improve reception.</p>
        <p>That is not the only piece of unfinished business. Because today's search for the hole was more time consuming than expected, several other tasks were deferred.</p>
        <p>The crew did not install a special valve for the carbon dioxide system they hope to connect in the future. They also did not have time to install a series of hand rails along Mir to make today's tasks and future missions easier.</p>
        <p>Today's space walk began about 5 A.M. Moscow time. The American astronaut, Michael Foale, who was wearing a Russian-made Orlan spacesuit, was the first to move through a hatch in Mir's Kvant-2 module and venture into space. He was followed by the Mir commander, Mr. Solovyov.</p>
        <p>To move around Mir, Mr. Foale controlled a special crane to hoist Mr. Solovyov toward the damaged section of the Spektr module.</p>
        <p>American astronauts generally conduct spacewalks within the open bay of the Space Shuttle.</p>
        <p>Operating in open space outside  Mir is a totally different and often unsettling experience, Mr. Linenger said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Linenger recalled that during his spacewalk he constantly had the sensation that he was falling off a cliff.</p>
        <p>''No matter what I did I mentally could not overcome the sensation of falling,'' he said at the Mission Control Center here. ''I just had to do the job and not think about it. It was like free-fall parachuting, only 100 times faster.''</p>
        <p>Nor was Mr. Linenger enamored of his experience on the crane. He described it like being a ''fish on a long fly rod.''</p>
        <p>''It did not have a good, solid feel to it,'' he said. ''It sways back and forth.''</p>
        <p>The main problem today, though, was not the crane. It was the search for the puncture, which concentrated on an area near an externally mounted radiator and a damaged solar array.</p>
        <p>The crew fell behind schedule as the search took more time than expected.</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Solovyov used a special knife to slice through the insulation near the radiator to try to locate the puncture beneath it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solovyov expressed some frustration when the insulation fluffed up as he tried to cut it. ''I should have taken scissors but not a knife,'' he said, in comments that were broadcast at the Mission Control Center here.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Solovyov found no holes beneath the thermal skin. ''It is strange -- to rumple this way and destroy nothing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Russian space officials said later that the astronauts had investigated five of seven possible areas where the point might be located.</p>
        <p>Even though the puncture could not be found, the crew still has plenty to do.</p>
        <p>''We have to give the cosmonauts a good rest and beginning on Tuesday we will start working on the life support system -- oxygen supply, thermo-regulation,'' Mr. Solovyov of the Mission Control center said.</p>
        <p>The larger question is whether Mir will have many productive days ahead of it if the Spektr module can be fixed.</p>
        <p>''If you are not doing something productive you should not be up there,'' Mr. Linenger said. ''Mike Foale has not been able to do that with his science program and we have shifted emphasis into more of a repair mission. And if that is valuable or not is something that the people at NASA and the people that are looking at future space station operations have to weigh.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
