<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Experts Doubt Rise Of Greenhouse Gas Will Be Curtailed</title>
    <meta content="03CLIM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="970250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D71530F930A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Experts Doubt Rise Of Greenhouse Gas Will Be Curtailed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <dateline>BONN, Nov. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts Doubt Rise of Greenhouse Gas Will Be Curtailed** Climate experts say doubling of heat-trapping carbon dioxide in atmosphere will be difficult if not impossible to avoid since world's economic and political systems cannot depart from business as usual rapidly enough; many say any action emerging from world conference in Kyoto, Japan, in early December will be insufficient to prevent an eventual doublig of greenhouse gases (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Climate experts have warned for years that a doubling of heat-trapping carbon dioxide in the atmosphere could have serious consequences worldwide. Now a growing number of scientists and policy makers say it will be difficult if not impossible to avoid such a rise.</p>
        <p>The reason, they say, is that the world's economic and political systems cannot depart from business as usual rapidly enough. In one metaphor that acquired some currency at talks on global warming, which ended inconclusively here on Friday, it is like trying to turn a supertanker in a sea of syrup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Climate experts have warned for years that a doubling of heat-trapping carbon dioxide in the atmosphere could have serious consequences worldwide. Now a growing number of scientists and policy makers say it will be difficult if not impossible to avoid such a rise.</p>
        <p>The reason, they say, is that the world's economic and political systems cannot depart from business as usual rapidly enough. In one metaphor that acquired some currency at talks on global warming, which ended inconclusively here on Friday, it is like trying to turn a supertanker in a sea of syrup.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is emitted by the burning of coal, oil and natural gas. These fuels are an integral part of the modern economy, and weaning the world from them has always been acknowledged as a difficult task at best. In the long debate about global warming, a doubling of carbon dioxide from pre-industrial levels in the 19th century has been such a frequent object of analysis and anxiety as to become almost a talismanic benchmark.</p>
        <p>Mainstream climatologists say that such a doubling would raise the average surface temperature of the globe anywhere from a moderate 3 degrees Fahrenheit to a potentially catastrophic 8 degrees, disrupting the earth's climate and causing the seas to rise. By comparison, the world has warmed by 5 to 9 degrees since the depths of the last ice age, about 18,000 to 22,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>While there are dissenters, a growing number of scientists and policy makers now say a doubling may be unavoidable late in the next century. This is so, they say, despite whatever steps to limit emissions of the gases emerge from international talks that were held here and will conclude in Kyoto, Japan, in early December.</p>
        <p>For the most part, attention until now has focused on the next two decades or so, in the belief that the most important thing is to make a start in reducing emissions. But it is widely agreed, based on proposals on the table, that any action emerging from Kyoto would be insufficient to prevent an eventual doubling of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The proposals outline a range of relatively modest reductions by industrialized countries, none of which are enough to prevent overall atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide from continuing to rise.</p>
        <p>''What Kyoto will do, almost predictably, is produce a small decrease in the rate of increase,'' said Dr. Jerry Mahlman, director of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Geophysical Dynamics Laboratory at Princeton University.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto conference has been universally viewed as a first step, and doubts about the long term are forcing people to pay more attention to a basic but long-deferred policy question: what should be the ultimate goal in stabilizing carbon dioxide concentrations? One objective of President Clinton's climate plan, announced Oct. 22, is to establish a scientifically sound goal with the assistance of the National Academy of Sciences.</p>
        <p>But if the experts' new fears are borne out, a rough doubling of carbon dioxide concentrations, or perhaps a bit less, may be the best to which the world can aspire. Under the most likely outcome, this could mean a rise in sea levels that would inundate low-lying coastal areas and small island nations, more frequent and severe floods and droughts, a shift in climatic zones, and disruption of natural ecosystems.</p>
        <p>Not everyone agrees that a doubling is inevitable. Environmentalists say it is possible and necessary to stabilize concentrations at 450 parts per million by volume -- about one and a half times the pre-industrial concentration of 280 parts per million.</p>
        <p>This, according to a study by the Environmental Defense Fund, would limit the global temperature increase to 1.5 to 2 degrees Fahrenheit during the next 100 years. The estimate assumes that the climate's sensitivity to carbon dioxide is in the middle of the range implied by mainstream scientists' conclusion that a doubling would produce a warming of 3 to 8 degrees.</p>
        <p>Atmospheric carbon dioxide is now about 360 parts per million, and the average surface temperature of the globe has risen by about 1 degree during the last century. At 450 parts per million, if the environmentalists are right, the total temperature increase by 2100 would be about 2.5 to 3 degrees. This would still make the world warmer than at any time in the last 10,000 years, and some further warming would occur after 2100.</p>
        <p>Virtually nobody believes that it is possible to stabilize atmospheric concentrations below 450 parts per million, and a number of experts say it will be very difficult if not impossible to stabilize them even at 550 parts per million, the next plateau on which some policy makers are beginning to focus. That number is close to a doubling of the pre-industrial concentration.</p>
        <p>While it is physically possible to stabilize concentrations at 550 parts per million, ''I don't think the emissions levels it would take are possible from a political point of view,'' said Dr. Luiz Gylvan Meira Filho of Brazil, who is in the thick of the political battle and the scientific debate. In the talks leading up to the Kyoto conference, he has headed the crucial negotiating subgroup dealing with targets and timetables for emissions reductions. A physicist, he is also a vice chairman of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, which produces the world's most authoritative assessments of the global warming problem. He said he was speaking for himself, not any of the official groups.</p>
        <p>Many others share Dr. Meira's assessment in general. It will be ''clearly challenging to stay below 550,'' said David Sandalow, a member of the Clinton Administration's National Security Council and Council on Environmental Quality.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevin Trenberth, a climate scientist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research at Boulder, Colo., says there has been a general sense that ''if we want to stop this experiment, we can do so with really strong, willful action.''</p>
        <p>''I think that's not the case,'' he said, adding that a doubling of carbon dioxide is likely, and that ''we need to pay more attention to adapting to climate change.''</p>
        <p>What appears to be going on is ''a subtle shift in the declaration of what constitutes success,'' said Dr. Mahlman. It looks now, he said, as if the long-term task is to keep atmospheric carbon dioxide from soaring beyond a doubling to catastrophic levels of as much as three or four times pre-industrial concentrations.</p>
        <p>Concentrations could as much as triple by 2100 and continue growing after that if third world countries follow business as usual, even if the most ambitious emissions reduction proposals for rich countries were adopted, said a report made public here by the intergovernmental panel.</p>
        <p>As is true of any climate problem, uncertainty permeates the question of stabilizing greenhouse gas concentrations. There is uncertainty not only in how much warming a given concentration of carbon dioxide would produce, but also in estimates of how the world's supply of carbon is recycled continuously among the atmosphere, the oceans, animals, plants, microbes and sedimentary rocks. Forecasting the nature of the  economy 100 or even 50 years from now is also difficult.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Oppenheimer, an atmospheric scientist with the Environmental Defense Fund, argues that ''it's premature to give up'' on the goal of 450 parts per million.  Patterns of energy use can change rapidly, he said, as demonstrated by energy efficiencies prompted by the Arab oil embargo of the 1970's.</p>
        <p>The task in Kyoto, he said, is to take action sufficient to insure that the ''450 option'' is not foreclosed, a task he described as ''difficult.'' All emissions reduction proposals now on the table for industrialized countries would preserve that option for a time, he said, provided that third-world countries also begin reductions soon after rich nations start.</p>
        <p>Less ambitious proposals for rich nations now under discussion, like those of the United States and Japan, would provide less leeway for the poorer countries, he said.</p>
        <p>Scientists agree that the lower the concentration level desired, the sooner substantial reductions in emissions must take place. An earlier start means a softer economic landing in the long term as well, in the view of Dr. Oppenheimer and others.</p>
        <p>But this does not necessarily mean that deep cuts are necessary in the next decade or so, in the view of a number of experts. There are a number of pathways to a given concentration goal, they say, all of which  have different economic effects. One influential study, for instance, found that modest reductions in the near term followed by sharper ones later on would be less costly to the economy than sharp reductions now.</p>
        <p>Delaying sharper reductions for a time would make little difference to the climate, according to the 1996 study by Dr. Tom Wigley of the National Center for Atmospheric Research, Dr. Richard Richels of the Electric Power Research Institute and Dr. J. A. Edmonds of the Pacific Northwest Laboratory. But it would make a substantial difference to the economy, they concluded, since replacing existing power plants and other capital stock prematurely would be expensive.</p>
        <p>That, the authors said, did not mean nothing should be done, not least because it is essential to take early action to stimulate more energy-efficient capital stocks, including installations that do not use fossil fuels, when new investments are made. Environmentalists argue that aggressive action is necessary in Kyoto to signal industry that such investments are required.</p>
        <p>''We can't turn the world's economy on its nose in 15 years,'' said Dr. Wigley, ''but over 30 years, I think we can. We should be doing things now to reduce emissions after 2030.''</p>
        <p>But he said ''unavoidable change'' in the climate system is in store no matter what action is taken.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
