<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Renaissance Methods To Create a Mission's Fresco</title>
    <meta content="FRESCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="909197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Montfort Catholic Mission (Central Islip, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jaleshgari, Ramin P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lecky, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DC1E3CF935A25751C0A961958260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Renaissance Methods To Create a Mission's Fresco</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAMIN P. JALESHGARI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jaleshgari, Ramin P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Artist James Lecky is painting Renaissance-style fresco at the Montfort Catholic Mission in Central Islip, LI; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CENTRAL Islip is a long way from Italy, and the Montfort Catholic Mission building in this run-of-the-mill Long Island town is a far cry from a grand Roman cathedral built in the Renaissance style.</p>
        <p>With its 1960's facade, the Montforts' mission is a glass and brick structure in the best fashion of institutional Americana. But on the inside there's a different story. In a plain second story chapel, Jim Lecky, an artist from St. James, works on an enormous fresco in the Raphaelite tradition. It is a labor of another era -- in more ways than one.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CENTRAL Islip is a long way from Italy, and the Montfort Catholic Mission building in this run-of-the-mill Long Island town is a far cry from a grand Roman cathedral built in the Renaissance style.</p>
        <p>With its 1960's facade, the Montforts' mission is a glass and brick structure in the best fashion of institutional Americana. But on the inside there's a different story. In a plain second story chapel, Jim Lecky, an artist from St. James, works on an enormous fresco in the Raphaelite tradition. It is a labor of another era -- in more ways than one.</p>
        <p>''When I was commissioned to do this project, I considered all the options -- canvas painting or a typical wall mural,'' said Mr. Lecky, an art professor at Suffolk Community College and a regular exhibitor at Setauket's Gallery North. ''I realized that only a true fresco could best complement the renovated chapel space.''</p>
        <p>True fresco is the technique of applying fresh pigment to wet plaster. Unlike the commonly used plaster of paris, fresco plaster is a mixture of lime, sand and water prepared by the artist immediately before use.</p>
        <p>In order to maintain a wet painting surface, only a small area is plastered and painted at a time and requires a fast, efficient technique. After laying the surface, the artist applies a subject to the wall by rubbing charcoal powder over a perforated full-size sketch of the area to be painted. Instead of premixed acrylic or watercolor paints, fresco artists like Giotto and Michelangelo traditionally worked with pure, powdered pigment mixed with water, providing vibrant color. Mr. Lecky is using this method also.</p>
        <p>''There are only a handful of American artists currently doing frescoes in the Renaissance technique, so the materials were a bit hard to find,'' said Mr. Lecky. ''I managed to get the right quality lime from a guy in Vermont and the pigments come from a German company based in Manhattan. Plus, there are only a few art suppliers that have brushes specific for the frescoes.''</p>
        <p>While highly popular in Europe up to the last century, fresco has all but died as a modern art form. Today, the most recognized fresco center is in Mexico.</p>
        <p>''True fresco seemed a natural choice here, partly because of traditionally religious themes embodied in the work of the great masters -- Giotto, for example,'' said Mr. Lecky.</p>
        <p>As the painting's plasters dries, it will react with the carbon dioxide in the air, becoming limestone, at a rate of  1/4 inch every 100 years. Mr. Lecky's work will take a total of 300 years to fully dry.</p>
        <p>The Montfort fresco consists of two outside panels of 5 by 12 feet and two inner panels of 6 by 15 feet. The inside panels are an Annunciation scene -- Mary and the angel Gabriel -- while the outside represent the mission's 18th-century founder, St. Louis de Montfort.</p>
        <p>The last panel is of Sister Mary Louise, founder of the Montfort's sister order, the Daughters of Wisdom. The order's vow to serve the poor and sick brought them to Long Island at the turn of the century. The Daughters of Wisdom founded such hospitals as St. Charles, Good Samaritan and what later became Maryhaven.</p>
        <p>The group's long-term association with Long Island was another deciding factor to use the fresco technique. ''We loved the idea that the fresco would be a vibrant entity reacting with its atmosphere for the next three centuries; it's almost like a living thing,'' said the Rev. Gerald Fitzsimmons, the organization's United States Provincial Superior, ''To us it's a metaphor for the Montfort calling -- to try and interact with our environment in a positive way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
