<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ice Sheets Seem Unmoved by the Volcanic Eruptions Below</title>
    <meta content="02VOLC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iceland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Iceland</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bjornsson, Helgi (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DB1F3AF931A35751C1A961958260" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ice Sheets Seem Unmoved by the Volcanic Eruptions Below</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study of volcanic activity beneath Iceland's Vatnajokull ice cap suggests that some subglacial eruptions have little long-term effect on stability of ice sheets; conclusion was reported in Oct 30 issue of the journal Nature by Dr Helgi Bjornsson and his colleagues at University of Iceland in Reykjavik (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN volcanoes erupt beneath thick sheets of ice, the resulting flash floods sometimes devastate communities, roads and farms. But there is new evidence that the effects of these eruptions are mostly local, with little overall effect on the ice sheets themselves.</p>
        <p>Scientists have a special reason for worrying about subglacial volcanoes. Since 1993, it has been known that volcanoes have been erupting under the ice sheet covering West Antarctica. If geothermal heat associated with volcanic activity should create a wide layer of water beneath this ice, it has been speculated, the water might moisten the volcanic ash on which much of the ice rests, creating a lubricant on which the ice might slide. If the West Antarctic Ice Sheet were to slide into the ocean, the sea level would rise by 65 feet worldwide, flooding low-lying nations like Bangladesh and the Netherlands and causing a global catastrophe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN volcanoes erupt beneath thick sheets of ice, the resulting flash floods sometimes devastate communities, roads and farms. But there is new evidence that the effects of these eruptions are mostly local, with little overall effect on the ice sheets themselves.</p>
        <p>Scientists have a special reason for worrying about subglacial volcanoes. Since 1993, it has been known that volcanoes have been erupting under the ice sheet covering West Antarctica. If geothermal heat associated with volcanic activity should create a wide layer of water beneath this ice, it has been speculated, the water might moisten the volcanic ash on which much of the ice rests, creating a lubricant on which the ice might slide. If the West Antarctic Ice Sheet were to slide into the ocean, the sea level would rise by 65 feet worldwide, flooding low-lying nations like Bangladesh and the Netherlands and causing a global catastrophe.</p>
        <p>A new study of volcanic activity beneath Iceland's Vatnajokull ice cap suggests that some subglacial eruptions have little long-term effect on the stability of ice sheets. This reassuring conclusion was reported in the Oct. 30 issue of the journal Nature by Dr. Helgi Bjornsson and his colleagues at the University of Iceland in Reykjavik.</p>
        <p>The object of their investigation was a 13-day eruption that occurred a year ago, when a subglacial volcano blasted its way through a fissure named Gjalp (after a mythological giantess) and up through ice nearly a half-mile thick. The eruption sent plumes of steam and ash some 33,000 feet into the air and melted one-half cubic mile of ice.</p>
        <p>For five weeks, water melted by the eruption flowed into a subglacial lake, which finally overflowed, unleashing a flood that destroyed bridges, cut roads and felled power lines. But because Icelandic experts had given ample warning of the flood, the region had been evacuated and there were no casualties.</p>
        <p>Such floods occur every 5 to 10  years, Dr. Bjornsson said in an interview, because the ice cap covers a geological hot spot that continuously melts ice. The periodic overflow of the subglacial lake, he said, has created a channel some 30 miles long under the ice, leading to the edge of the glacier. The subglacial channel serves as a duct for the flood water.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bjornsson and his colleagues concluded on the basis of aerial surveys and ground measurements that the ice cap was not significantly changed by the 1996 eruption and that it remains firmly anchored to underlying bedrock.</p>
        <p>On Oct. 13, 1996, when the eruption ended, the peak of a new volcanic mountain appeared above the surface of an ice caldron formed by the eruption. ''But we know that the mountain peak will disappear in a few years because new ice is already filling in the caldron,'' Dr. Bjornsson said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Donald D. Blankenship of the University of Texas at Austin, a leading expert on the West Antarctic Ice Sheet, said observations made of the Icelandic eruption did not necessarily apply to Antarctica.</p>
        <p>''There are big differences between Iceland and Antarctica,'' he said. ''For one thing, the ice sheet in Antarctica is up to 9,000 feet thick, while its Icelandic counterpart is only 2,500 feet thick.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Blankenship said that relatively little was known about the geology underlying the West Antarctic Ice Sheet but that a system of Antarctic channels, similar to those in Iceland, might exist -- channels that could carry meltwater away from regions of volcanic activity. If so, he said, there could be local volcanic effects on the ice sheet but no general melting at its base, and therefore no major sliding.</p>
        <p>''There's a growing consensus among glaciologists that subglacial volcanoes in West Antarctica are unlikely to have a major impact on the stability of the ice sheet,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
