<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GLOBAL WARMING: How Fast to Cut Back? Two Views; Turning Green Puts Some in the Black Now</title>
    <meta content="01INCE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907E2D6143AF932A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GLOBAL WARMING: How Fast to Cut Back? Two Views; Turning Green Puts Some in the Black Now</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article examines Pres Clinton's promise that shift to economy that relies far less on carbon-emitting fuels that cause global warming will be essentially painless and can begin today; Administration's proposals would limit emissions of carbon dioxide by issuing emissions permits that companies could buy and sell; effect would be to put price on carbon in fuel--price that would reflect cost of controlling emissions; traditional economists and big industry groups say unless energy prices rise sharply, companies and consumer will be slow to adopt new technologies, even though investments may pay off at current energy prices; others say profitable shift to greener energy pastures is already under way and will accelerate if Government adopts policies that promote conservation; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GARY HIRSHBERG, the president of Stonyfield Farm, knows two ways to increase his profits. By expanding his yogurt-manufacturing capacity, he can pay back his investment in a year and keep growing. Or by installing readily available technology for energy conservation at his New Hampshire plant, he can recoup his costs in two years or less and bank the future savings till the cows come home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirshberg has chosen to do both. Stonyfield, he says, will increase production 40 percent next year. By taking steps like installing efficient lights and reusing waste heat, he is now using 9 percent less energy each year per pint of yogurt, increasing his profit margin. And by investing some of those energy savings in forestry projects that trap carbon dioxide, the main greenhouse gas, in the atmosphere, he has reduced the company's net manufacturing emissions of carbon dioxide to zero, he says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GARY HIRSHBERG, the president of Stonyfield Farm, knows two ways to increase his profits. By expanding his yogurt-manufacturing capacity, he can pay back his investment in a year and keep growing. Or by installing readily available technology for energy conservation at his New Hampshire plant, he can recoup his costs in two years or less and bank the future savings till the cows come home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hirshberg has chosen to do both. Stonyfield, he says, will increase production 40 percent next year. By taking steps like installing efficient lights and reusing waste heat, he is now using 9 percent less energy each year per pint of yogurt, increasing his profit margin. And by investing some of those energy savings in forestry projects that trap carbon dioxide, the main greenhouse gas, in the atmosphere, he has reduced the company's net manufacturing emissions of carbon dioxide to zero, he says.</p>
        <p>''Forget the moral principles, forget our children, forget the flooding of South Florida, forget malaria,'' he said, ticking off reasons to fight global warming. ''We are willing to support this strictly on the economics.''</p>
        <p>Stories like this have gripped President Clinton's attention and prompted him to promise that the transition to an economy that relies far less on carbon fuels will be essentially painless and can begin today.</p>
        <p>''If we do it right, protecting the climate will yield not costs, but profits; not burdens, but benefits; not sacrifice, but a higher standard of living,'' Mr. Clinton said in October when he outlined the Administration's proposals for fighting climate change. ''Energy savings give better service at lower cost with higher profit.''</p>
        <p>Traditional economists and big industry groups say that unless energy prices go up sharply, companies and consumers will be slow to adopt new technologies, even though the investments may pay off at today's energy prices. But there is also a substantial group of analysts who say that a profitable shift to greener energy pastures is under way and will accelerate if the Government adopts policies that promote conservation.</p>
        <p>If prices for the carbon in fossil fuels rise in the future as a result of the Administration's proposals, this group says, that will only expand opportunities faster, tamping down any economic damage.</p>
        <p>The Administration's proposal would limit emissions of carbon dioxide by issuing emissions permits that companies could buy and sell. Companies that achieved emissions reductions cheaply could profitably sell their excess permits to companies with higher emission-control costs. The effect would be to put a price on the carbon in fuel, a price that would reflect the costs of controlling emissions. Some forecasters predict that under this approach, the price of the carbon in fuel would rise by $100 a ton or more, making oil, coal and gas much more expensive; others say innovations would keep the cost much lower.</p>
        <p>''Somewhere between $25 and $50 a ton of carbon, new technologies become so unbelievably attractive that you cap the price,'' said Joseph J. Romm, the Energy Department's top official in charge of renewable energy and efficiency programs. ''At $50 per ton of carbon, people will be installing windmills as fast as the manufacturers can make them.''</p>
        <p>As the prices of fossil fuels rise, he explained, it makes less sense to operate coal-fired power plants, which would be swept away by cheaper ways to make electricity.</p>
        <p>''We are not betting on one technology,'' Mr. Romm said. ''It is a hundred technologies, each one of which can do its share.''</p>
        <p>AMORY Lovins, the co-founder of the Rocky Mountain Institute, a research group that is a leading proponent of energy conservation, said, ''There are huge opportunities for profitably improving the energy of using energy, but they remain unbought because of 30-odd specific types of roadblocks that keep the market from working properly. Turning each of those obstacles into a business opportunity can save a lot of energy quickly even at present energy prices.''</p>
        <p>All manner of gizmos for home, office and factory are either on the drawing board or on the shelf to help conserve energy or to produce it more cleanly in the 21st century, the optimists say. The list includes photovoltaics, fuel cells, biomass fuels, fluorescent lights, insulating windows, efficient cars, stingy thermostats and miserly appliances.</p>
        <p>But doubters, especially traditional economists, say it is well documented that people neglect to invest in devices that save energy and pay for themselves at current energy prices. In their daily lives, many people forgo simple conservation measures that offer quick savings, like turning a water heater's temperature to 125 degrees from 150 degrees.</p>
        <p>''If only 20 percent of the homes in the U.S. used high-efficiency washers,'' said John Tomlinson, the project manager of a study done by the Oak Ridge National Laboratory on Maytag's new washing machines, ''we would save enough energy to heat 800,000 homes.''</p>
        <p>But those washing machines can cost $900, and many consumers hesitate to shell out that much money to save money later.</p>
        <p>On the other side of the energy business, where power is produced and sold, the optimists predict that lots of clean technology is just over the horizon.</p>
        <p>An analysis of research goals done by the President's Committee of Advisers on Science and Technology optimistically suggested in November that wind-power farms in the Great Plains could ''plausibly'' export  electricity all over the country at a competitive price by 2030.</p>
        <p>One reasonable target, the report suggested, would be to replace old coal-fired power plants with windmills. The plants that produce nearly a third of American carbon dioxide emissions will be ready for retirement in the next few decades. If wind power production grows about 33 percent annually from now until then, the switch to carbon-free electricity would be well under way by then.</p>
        <p>''This is a very rapid growth rate, but is less than that of the U.S. nuclear industry from 1957 to 1977,'' the report noted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
