<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>But U.S. Solar Cell Makers See Clouds Rolling In From Overseas</title>
    <meta content="16SOLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="An Industry Relishes Its Day in the Sun" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="950829"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="An Industry Relishes Its Day in the Sun"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DD133FF935A2575BC0A961958260" item-length="1796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>But U.S. Solar Cell Makers See Clouds Rolling In From Overseas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American solar power industry has never been so successful; with $850 million in sales last year, American manufacturers remain global leaders in systems that make electricity from sunlight; industry is worried about future because so far most of demand for solar power systems is overseas; foreign competitors, aroused by American industry's mounting success, have begun sniffing about; Federal Government is taking steps to keep American solar companies in technical vanguard; having poured some $1.5 billion of research money into solar industry over last 25 years, Government wants to help keep some of benefits in US; major part of effort involves easing American companies' reliance on exports by fostering demand and stimulating innovative uses in US; graph; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American solar-power industry has never been so successful.</p>
        <p>With $850 million in sales last year, American manufacturers remain the global leaders in systems that make electricity from sunlight. Orders are months ahead of production and several companies are building new plants to turn out more solar cells. Demand is so strong and the current shortage is so acute that prices for solar cells are even on the rise -- reversing a decade-long price decline driven by more efficient technology and improved manufacturing processes.</p>
        <p>So why is the industry so worried about its future? Because so far most of the demand for solar-power systems is overseas. And foreign competitors, aroused by the American industry's mounting success, have begun sniffing about.</p>
        <p>''It's sort of like making nuclear bombs,'' said James MacKenzie, a senior associate and energy expert at the World Resources Institute, an environmental group based here. ''Once the secret is out, a lot of people will figure out how to do it.''</p>
        <p>That's one reason why the Federal Government, hoping to avoid the kind of erosion that in the 1980's threatened the nation's edge in computer semiconductors, is taking steps to keep American solar companies in the technical vanguard. Having poured some $1.5 billion of research money into the solar industry over the last 25 years, the Government wants to help keep some of the benefits on shore.</p>
        <p>A major part of the effort involves easing the American companies' reliance on exports by fostering demand and stimulating innovative uses in this country, where advanced production techniques will be required to make the industry competitive with conventional electricity.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations conference on global warming this summer, President Clinton introduced the ''Million Solar Roofs Initiative'' as part of the nation's halting efforts to slow the increase in ''greenhouse'' gases produced by burning fossil fuels. The goal is to put a million solar systems on the roofs of commercial and residential buildings by 2010 -- whether photovoltaic units that convert sunlight into electricity or thermal systems for space heating and hot water.</p>
        <p>''I'm really fearful that without a strong domestic market, this industry will never grow,'' said Harvey Forest, president and chief executive of the Solarex Corporation, a joint venture of Amoco Oil and Enron that is now the largest American-owned producer, with about a quarter of the solar cells sold.</p>
        <p>The Federal effort will take a variety of forms. The Government itself, the nation's largest landlord, recently moved to simplify its process for buying and installing solar cells on its own buildings. To help others, the Government may also label solar products, much as the Environmental Protection Agency does with energy-saving appliances.</p>
        <p>State governments may play a role, too. California intends to give $54 million in subsidies next year to users of solar and other forms of renewable energy, while Arizona will require that at least 1 percent of its new electrical generation come from the sun. And 18 states, ranging from California and Arizona to Massachusetts and Connecticut have established ''net metering'' rules, which require utilities to purchase -- at retail rates -- any surplus solar electricity produced by households or small businesses. Albany just approved a law this week that will introduce net metering to New York.</p>
        <p>But given consumer expectations that electricity should remain relatively cheap, stimulating the domestic market for solar power will not be easy.</p>
        <p>Domestic products range from roof systems to run an entire house to mini-systems to turn on a few lights and a small television for a few hours. In this country, panels power everything from billboard lights to roadside emergency call boxes.</p>
        <p>But because the utility industry's power grid is so extensive, and its output so inexpensive, only about 30 percent of solar-power sales are within this country. For years to come, solar cells will probably be too expensive to compete directly with electricity from the power grid.</p>
        <p>There are no authoritative price indexes for solar cells, but industry executives and customers say that brisk demand has recently sent prices up. Thomas J. Vonderharr, the vice president of sales at one of the leading cell suppliers, BP Solar Inc., of Fairfield, Calif., said prices had recently edged above $4 a peak watt of capacity. (A peak watt is the amount produced when the sun is strong and directly overhead. A system, with storage batteries, capable of about 5,000 peak watts could run a typical suburban house with central air-conditioning.)</p>
        <p>To compete with traditional power sources in the United States, solar electricity needs to fall to $1 to $1.50 a peak watt -- unless solar energy gets tax credits for not polluting, or is adopted by utilities to patch weak spots in their distribution and avoid stringing costly new power lines.</p>
        <p>But even at current prices, solar cells are attractive to buyers all over rural parts of the developing world and in Eastern Europe, where people have been making due with kerosene lanterns or with batteries charged up on occasional trips to town.</p>
        <p>According to Keith L. Kozloff, a solar expert at the Arlington, Va., consulting firm Hagler Bailly, one of the most popular products in developing nations is a 50-watt module that can charge a battery with enough power to run a couple of small fluorescent lanterns plus a small television or a radio for a few hours in the evening. The entire system, with an estimated life of 20 to 25 years, sells for about $500.</p>
        <p>While the solar industry could probably thrive for years on the expected increased demand from abroad, its output would barely register as more than a blip in the huge American energy market. The fear is that solar power will be simply overlooked here even as other countries move to establish a beachhead.</p>
        <p>Already, some 11 percent of the world's production of photovoltaic cells comes from the developing world. But so far, the bigger competitive threat to American industry is coming from Japan and Europe.</p>
        <p>Last year global production was 88.6 megawatts and the American share was 44 percent, down slightly from the year before, according to the industry publication PV News. After the United States industry, the Japanese rank second, producing 24 percent of the global market, up from 21 percent the year before.</p>
        <p>While the United States still produces the most advanced solar cells, others are gaining. ''Our edge is being eroded,'' said Robert A. Freling, executive director of the Solar Electric Light Fund, a nonprofit group based here that sells small systems to the developing world.</p>
        <p>To dull that American edge, Tokyo and Bonn -- each of which already spends more than the $60 million Washington devotes to solar energy research and development -- have set up large subsidy programs for purchasers to nurture the industry.</p>
        <p>Foreign companies, too, have moved to acquire advanced technology by buying some of the leading American solar companies: Siemens of Germany bought ARCO Solar to become Siemens Solar, the largest producer of solar cells in the United States, and British Petroleum bought Advanced Photovoltaic Systems to be part of BP Solar.</p>
        <p>A third major producer in this country, Solec International, is controlled by two Japanese giants, the Sanyo Electric Company and the Sumitomo Corporation.</p>
        <p>So far, Washington has not opposed these takeovers, in part because the foreign-owned factories keep Americans in jobs. The solar electric industry employs about 12,000 people here. By 2010, the Energy Department predicts, 70,000 new jobs will be created in this country as the industry expands to meet the needs of the Million Roofs program.</p>
        <p>The challenge is to keep the American industry in the lead until the price of solar cells falls enough to stimulate domestic demand. One strategy: spur solar innovations that can exist alongside, or supplement, conventional power sources.</p>
        <p>One such installation is planned for Four Times Square, a 48-story office tower that the Durst Organization is building to house Conde Nast and the Skadden Arps law firm at the corner of Broadway and 42d Street in Manhattan. Upper portions of the south and east walls will be covered with solar cells to supplement the power from Consolidated Edison.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department has subsidized another promising new product -- a solar cell incorporated into a roofing shingle, built by the United Solar Systems Corporation of Troy, Mich., which began production in March. The company, a subsidiary of Energy Conversion Devices, also of Troy, is trying on a residential scale what the Durst architects, Fox &amp; Fowle, are attempting on a commercial building.</p>
        <p>With demand from overseas so strong these days, most American producers, whatever their fears of future foreign competition, have adopted an attitude of making cells while the sun shines. In fact, many of the companies are kicking themselves for not having invested more in their factories in recent years.</p>
        <p>Amoco's solar division, which produced 10.8 megawatts of cells last year, just opened a plant near Richmond that will nearly double its output. And the company has other large plants under construction.</p>
        <p>''We've put on 40 percent more capacity this year,'' Mr. Forest of Amoco said. ''We were worried about it last year when we were thinking about it. But now I'm sorry that I didn't put 60 percent more.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American solar-power industry has never been so successful.</p>
        <p>With $850 million in sales last year, American manufacturers remain the global leaders in systems that make electricity from sunlight. Orders are months ahead of production and several companies are building new plants to turn out more solar cells. Demand is so strong and the current shortage is so acute that prices for solar cells are even on the rise -- reversing a decade-long price decline driven by more efficient technology and improved manufacturing processes.</p>
        <p>So why is the industry so worried about its future? Because so far most of the demand for solar-power systems is overseas. And foreign competitors, aroused by the American industry's mounting success, have begun sniffing about.</p>
        <p>''It's sort of like making nuclear bombs,'' said James MacKenzie, a senior associate and energy expert at the World Resources Institute, an environmental group based here. ''Once the secret is out, a lot of people will figure out how to do it.''</p>
        <p>That's one reason why the Federal Government, hoping to avoid the kind of erosion that in the 1980's threatened the nation's edge in computer semiconductors, is taking steps to keep American solar companies in the technical vanguard. Having poured some $1.5 billion of research money into the solar industry over the last 25 years, the Government wants to help keep some of the benefits on shore.</p>
        <p>A major part of the effort involves easing the American companies' reliance on exports by fostering demand and stimulating innovative uses in this country, where advanced production techniques will be required to make the industry competitive with conventional electricity.</p>
        <p>At the United Nations conference on global warming this summer, President Clinton introduced the ''Million Solar Roofs Initiative'' as part of the nation's halting efforts to slow the increase in ''greenhouse'' gases produced by burning fossil fuels. The goal is to put a million solar systems on the roofs of commercial and residential buildings by 2010 -- whether photovoltaic units that convert sunlight into electricity or thermal systems for space heating and hot water.</p>
        <p>''I'm really fearful that without a strong domestic market, this industry will never grow,'' said Harvey Forest, president and chief executive of the Solarex Corporation, a joint venture of Amoco Oil and Enron that is now the largest American-owned producer, with about a quarter of the solar cells sold.</p>
        <p>The Federal effort will take a variety of forms. The Government itself, the nation's largest landlord, recently moved to simplify its process for buying and installing solar cells on its own buildings. To help others, the Government may also label solar products, much as the Environmental Protection Agency does with energy-saving appliances.</p>
        <p>State governments may play a role, too. California intends to give $54 million in subsidies next year to users of solar and other forms of renewable energy, while Arizona will require that at least 1 percent of its new electrical generation come from the sun. And 18 states, ranging from California and Arizona to Massachusetts and Connecticut have established ''net metering'' rules, which require utilities to purchase -- at retail rates -- any surplus solar electricity produced by households or small businesses. Albany just approved a law this week that will introduce net metering to New York.</p>
        <p>But given consumer expectations that electricity should remain relatively cheap, stimulating the domestic market for solar power will not be easy.</p>
        <p>Domestic products range from roof systems to run an entire house to mini-systems to turn on a few lights and a small television for a few hours. In this country, panels power everything from billboard lights to roadside emergency call boxes.</p>
        <p>But because the utility industry's power grid is so extensive, and its output so inexpensive, only about 30 percent of solar-power sales are within this country. For years to come, solar cells will probably be too expensive to compete directly with electricity from the power grid.</p>
        <p>There are no authoritative price indexes for solar cells, but industry executives and customers say that brisk demand has recently sent prices up. Thomas J. Vonderharr, the vice president of sales at one of the leading cell suppliers, BP Solar Inc., of Fairfield, Calif., said prices had recently edged above $4 a peak watt of capacity. (A peak watt is the amount produced when the sun is strong and directly overhead. A system, with storage batteries, capable of about 5,000 peak watts could run a typical suburban house with central air-conditioning.)</p>
        <p>To compete with traditional power sources in the United States, solar electricity needs to fall to $1 to $1.50 a peak watt -- unless solar energy gets tax credits for not polluting, or is adopted by utilities to patch weak spots in their distribution and avoid stringing costly new power lines.</p>
        <p>But even at current prices, solar cells are attractive to buyers all over rural parts of the developing world and in Eastern Europe, where people have been making due with kerosene lanterns or with batteries charged up on occasional trips to town.</p>
        <p>According to Keith L. Kozloff, a solar expert at the Arlington, Va., consulting firm Hagler Bailly, one of the most popular products in developing nations is a 50-watt module that can charge a battery with enough power to run a couple of small fluorescent lanterns plus a small television or a radio for a few hours in the evening. The entire system, with an estimated life of 20 to 25 years, sells for about $500.</p>
        <p>While the solar industry could probably thrive for years on the expected increased demand from abroad, its output would barely register as more than a blip in the huge American energy market. The fear is that solar power will be simply overlooked here even as other countries move to establish a beachhead.</p>
        <p>Already, some 11 percent of the world's production of photovoltaic cells comes from the developing world. But so far, the bigger competitive threat to American industry is coming from Japan and Europe.</p>
        <p>Last year global production was 88.6 megawatts and the American share was 44 percent, down slightly from the year before, according to the industry publication PV News. After the United States industry, the Japanese rank second, producing 24 percent of the global market, up from 21 percent the year before.</p>
        <p>While the United States still produces the most advanced solar cells, others are gaining. ''Our edge is being eroded,'' said Robert A. Freling, executive director of the Solar Electric Light Fund, a nonprofit group based here that sells small systems to the developing world.</p>
        <p>To dull that American edge, Tokyo and Bonn -- each of which already spends more than the $60 million Washington devotes to solar energy research and development -- have set up large subsidy programs for purchasers to nurture the industry.</p>
        <p>Foreign companies, too, have moved to acquire advanced technology by buying some of the leading American solar companies: Siemens of Germany bought ARCO Solar to become Siemens Solar, the largest producer of solar cells in the United States, and British Petroleum bought Advanced Photovoltaic Systems to be part of BP Solar.</p>
        <p>A third major producer in this country, Solec International, is controlled by two Japanese giants, the Sanyo Electric Company and the Sumitomo Corporation.</p>
        <p>So far, Washington has not opposed these takeovers, in part because the foreign-owned factories keep Americans in jobs. The solar electric industry employs about 12,000 people here. By 2010, the Energy Department predicts, 70,000 new jobs will be created in this country as the industry expands to meet the needs of the Million Roofs program.</p>
        <p>The challenge is to keep the American industry in the lead until the price of solar cells falls enough to stimulate domestic demand. One strategy: spur solar innovations that can exist alongside, or supplement, conventional power sources.</p>
        <p>One such installation is planned for Four Times Square, a 48-story office tower that the Durst Organization is building to house Conde Nast and the Skadden Arps law firm at the corner of Broadway and 42d Street in Manhattan. Upper portions of the south and east walls will be covered with solar cells to supplement the power from Consolidated Edison.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department has subsidized another promising new product -- a solar cell incorporated into a roofing shingle, built by the United Solar Systems Corporation of Troy, Mich., which began production in March. The company, a subsidiary of Energy Conversion Devices, also of Troy, is trying on a residential scale what the Durst architects, Fox &amp; Fowle, are attempting on a commercial building.</p>
        <p>With demand from overseas so strong these days, most American producers, whatever their fears of future foreign competition, have adopted an attitude of making cells while the sun shines. In fact, many of the companies are kicking themselves for not having invested more in their factories in recent years.</p>
        <p>Amoco's solar division, which produced 10.8 megawatts of cells last year, just opened a plant near Richmond that will nearly double its output. And the company has other large plants under construction.</p>
        <p>''We've put on 40 percent more capacity this year,'' Mr. Forest of Amoco said. ''We were worried about it last year when we were thinking about it. But now I'm sorry that I didn't put 60 percent more.''</p>
        <p>An Industry Relishes Its Day in the Sun</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
