<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Warm Globe, Hot Politics</title>
    <meta content="11ASSE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979586"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kyoto (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EFD6133CF932A25751C1A961958260" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Warm Globe, Hot Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>James Bennet analysis contends that under Kyoto agreement, US will have to take more drastic steps than Clinton Administration had hoped to reduce greenhouse emissions; maintains that walking away from treaty, as Vice Pres Gore said he was willing to do, would have enraged environmentalists who are key constituents for him and Pres Clinton; asserts that it would have isolated US as leading emitter of greenhouse gases and only industrial nation unwilling to address problem jointly (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the end, Bill Clinton and Al Gore could not walk away.</p>
        <p>They faced unpleasant political options as talks in Kyoto, Japan, wound done, and as more than 150 nations neared agreement on a treaty to cut the emissions that lead to global warming. Under the agreement that emerged, which the Administration plans to sign, the United States will have to take more drastic steps than the White House had hoped to cut greenhouse emissions. Heavy industry, from cars to coal to steel to electricity, has already joined with organized labor to fight the proposal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the end, Bill Clinton and Al Gore could not walk away.</p>
        <p>They faced unpleasant political options as talks in Kyoto, Japan, wound done, and as more than 150 nations neared agreement on a treaty to cut the emissions that lead to global warming. Under the agreement that emerged, which the Administration plans to sign, the United States will have to take more drastic steps than the White House had hoped to cut greenhouse emissions. Heavy industry, from cars to coal to steel to electricity, has already joined with organized labor to fight the proposal.</p>
        <p>But walking away from the treaty -- as Mr. Gore said he was willing to do last week -- would have enraged the environmentalists who are key constituents for him and Mr. Clinton. It would have isolated the United States -- which just refused to sign a treaty banning land mines -- as the leading emitter of greenhouse gasses and the only industrial nation unwilling to address the problem jointly. And it would have been contrary, their aides said, to a belief shared by the President and Vice President that global warming presents grave dangers.</p>
        <p>But now the Administration has a larger fight on its hands, a fight that will help define not only budget negotiations next year but the 1998 Congressional elections and even the next Presidential race.</p>
        <p>Even before the treaty was worked out, Democratic allies of the Administration were warning the White House not to seek approval in the Senate. ''What we have here is not ratifiable in the Senate in my judgment,'' Senator John Kerry, Democrat of Massachusetts, said in a telephone news conference from Kyoto.</p>
        <p>Before the Kyoto meeting began, the Senate voted 95 to 0 to pass a resolution that the United States would not agree to a treaty that did not provide a role in cutting emissions for developing nations. That became a negotiating goal for the Administration.</p>
        <p>In Kyoto, Senator Chuck Hagel, Republican of Nebraska, said flatly, ''There is no way, if the President signs this, that the vote in the United States Senate will even be close. We will kill this bill.''</p>
        <p>The treaty emerging in Kyoto tonight (Thursday morning, Kyoto time) includes a new program sought by the Administration to funnel capital and environmentally friendly technology to developing nations. But White House aides said that, while they considered the provision a victory, it was not strong enough to win ratification.</p>
        <p>The White House is also planning to propose tax incentives to encourage cuts in greenhouse-gas emission as part of its budget proposal next year, but that, too, will be subject to Congessional approval.</p>
        <p>Two officials said that, judging by the early criticism, the public would get a positive impression of the Administration's actions. ''We figured that we would probably be criticized by both industry and environmental groups,'' one of them said, ''which has the effect of saying, 'Well, they must have ended up in a place that's pretty sensible.' ''</p>
        <p>Indeed, in Kyoto, one industry coalition went as far as to issue a statement denouncing the agreement hours before the deal was final. And the World Wildlife Fund attacked the plan, saying that the outcome was ''a flawed agreement that will allow major polluters to continue emitting greenhouse gasses through loopholes.''</p>
        <p>But Fred Krupp, executive director of the Environmental Defense Fund, said: ''There's still much more work to be done to assure that the protocol's targets are met'' but ''Vice President Gore should be commended for coming to Japan and opening the doors to an agreement.''</p>
        <p>In recent polls the public has expressed solid support for action on global warming. Two weeks ago, in a poll taken by The New York Times , 65 percent said that the United States should take steps now to cut its own emissions ''regardless of what other countries do.'' Only 17 percent agreed that cutting emissions ''will cost too much money and hurt the U.S. economy.''</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Mr. Clinton promised to reduce United States emissions to their 1990 levels by the year 2000. But such emissions are now more than 10 percent above 1990 levels and rising. Mr. Clinton rarely mentioned the issue until early this summer, when, in anticipation of the Kyoto meeting, he began warning of the dangers of global warming.</p>
        <p>But, even as he began addressing the subject again, Mr. Clinton has repeatedly said that the United States can meet what amount to rigorous emissions targets with little or no economic pain.</p>
        <p>''I am convinced that we can demonstrate to the American people that we can substantially reduce our greenhouse gas emissions and fulfill our global environmental responsibilities as well as our responsibilities to our own people without giving up economic growth,'' Mr. Clinton said in an interview with The New York Times last Thursday. ''But it will require a very disciplined, organized, coordinated effort to do it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
