<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ontario to Shut 7 Border Nuclear Reactors</title>
    <meta content="T14CAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="950471"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ontario (Canada)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Ontario</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Huron</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ontario Hydro</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farlinger, William A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kupcis, Allan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada/Ontario</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970814T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DC173FF937A2575BC0A961958260" item-length="961" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ontario to Shut 7 Border Nuclear Reactors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Aug. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ontario Province (Canada) is shutting down 7 of its 19 operating nuclear reactors, all within 100 miles of United States border, after internal report finds Ontario Hydro, owned and run by province, is so badly managed it compromised safety of entire nuclear power system; will spend $2.2 billion over next four years to replace lost energy, using existing fossil fuel generating stations; will spend $1.5 billion to overhaul dozen reactors on shores of Lake Ontario and Lake Huron that will continue to operate; company chairman William A Farlinger says closed reactors will be brought back on line if move is cost effective, news conference; says rates will not rise; Allan Kupcis has resigned as Ontario Hydro president; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The province of Ontario is shutting down 7 of its 19 operating nuclear reactors -- all within 100 miles of the United States border -- after an internal report concluded that the province's utility company was so badly managed that it had compromised the safety of its entire nuclear power system.</p>
        <p>By the time the report was released today, the president of Ontario Hydro -- one of the largest utilities in North America, owned and operated by the province -- had already resigned, and company officials said they expected more departures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The province of Ontario is shutting down 7 of its 19 operating nuclear reactors -- all within 100 miles of the United States border -- after an internal report concluded that the province's utility company was so badly managed that it had compromised the safety of its entire nuclear power system.</p>
        <p>By the time the report was released today, the president of Ontario Hydro -- one of the largest utilities in North America, owned and operated by the province -- had already resigned, and company officials said they expected more departures.</p>
        <p>To replace the lost nuclear energy, Ontario will shift to existing generating stations that use coal and oil and will have to spend about $2.2 billion over the next four years to cover the increased costs. William A. Farlinger, chairman of Hydro Ontario, said rates would not have to be increased, although he was unable to say exactly where the money would come from.</p>
        <p>Ontario Hydro will also spend $1.5 billion between now and 2001 to overhaul the dozen reactors on the shores of Lake Ontario and Lake Huron that will continue to operate. The shuttered reactors will be brought back on line only if doing so is cost effective, Mr. Farlinger said at a news conference in Toronto today.</p>
        <p>The reactors being closed, a workhorse model called Candu, are a Canadian design that is at the center of Canada's nuclear energy program as well as a multibillion dollar export strategy by the Government.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Farlinger and other Ontario Hydro officials stressed that the report did not question the safety of the Candu design, but rather how the plants were run and maintained.</p>
        <p>''Our problems are people,'' Mr. Farlinger said, ''not machines.''</p>
        <p>But, according to the report, inadequate maintenance and replacement of parts ''incrementally erode the margin of safety'' that is supposed to be built into the reactor.</p>
        <p>The problems at Ontario Hydro could have an impact far beyond the province of Ontario. Candu reactors have been sold to Argentina, Romania and South Korea. During a trade mission last November, Canada also signed a $3 billion contract to sell two of the reactors to China. Sales in recent years have been sparse, and officials said today that the problems in Ontario will definitely make future contracts even harder to come by.</p>
        <p>Ontario Hydro, which relies on its nuclear plants to supply 60 percent of its electricity, also sold about $128 million worth of electricity to utilities in Michigan last year. It also supplies electricity, through power grids and a daily spot market, to other states, including New York. Just under 1 percent of Con Edison's electric purchases for the first seven months of this year came from Ontario Hydro.</p>
        <p>Although Ontario Hydro officials said today that they would continue to meet the electricity needs of all its nearly three million customers, there is concern that by switching to coal and oil the utility will increase pollution in the Great Lakes and other areas already badly contaminated, some in the United States.</p>
        <p>The environmental group Greenpeace Canada said today that Hydro's decision to switch to fossil fuels will increase greenhouse gases and other emissions by as much as 400 percent. Another concern is that burning coal and oil would increase the danger of acid rain.</p>
        <p>The report that triggered the closings was ordered last year after a malfunctioning backup valve at the company's Pickering I nuclear plant, 20 miles northeast of Toronto, forced the plant to be shut down. That incident was the latest in a series of mishaps at the plant that had caused concern both within the company and the surrounding community.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farlinger, who stepped in as acting president after the resignation of Allan Kupcis, said that the trouble at Pickering made it evident that there were serious management failings within the company.</p>
        <p>''The nuclear unit was operated over all those early years as some sort of a special nuclear cult,'' Mr. Farlinger said. ''Senior management didn't dig into what was going on in this special unit to the extent that we must now say they should have.''</p>
        <p>The Candu reactor, whose name is short for Canadian Deuterium-Uranium, differs from designs common in the United States by its reliance on natural uranium, as it comes from the ground, instead of enriched uranium. It was designed for countries with a limited industrial base.</p>
        <p>In all, Canada has 21 operating Candu plants that supply 17 percent of the country's energy needs, less than the 22.5 percent that comes from nuclear power in the United States. All but two of the plants are in Ontario. The others are in New Brunswick and Quebec.</p>
        <p>Ontario Hydro played a major role in advancing the Candu technology. Its complex of 8 reactors on Lake Huron, including one that is mothballed, and three others that will be shut as a result of today's announcement, forms the largest nuclear site in the world, according to the International Atomic Energy Agency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
