<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What You See Is What You Get</title>
    <meta content="07SCHWART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="88" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Hillel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Marc C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Hiding (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2DA143AF934A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1378" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What You See Is What You Get</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hillel Schwartz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schwartz, Hillel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hillel Schwartz reviews book Hiding by Mark C Taylor (L)N</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIDING</p>
        <p>By Mark C. Taylor.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 354 pp. Chicago:</p>
        <p>The University of Chicago Press.</p>
        <p>Paper, $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIDING</p>
        <p>By Mark C. Taylor.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 354 pp. Chicago:</p>
        <p>The University of Chicago Press.</p>
        <p>Paper, $29.95.</p>
        <p>In an era of disembodied voices and digitized replicas, when transparency is all and density a pejorative, a book entitled ''Hiding'' would seem well positioned to deal with our anxieties. How do we find ourselves amid electronic dubs and doubles? How can we find meaning where everything turns tail upon itself? What lies beneath the troubled surfaces of our lives?</p>
        <p>A philosopher of religion and technology, Mark C. Taylor means to disabuse us of our archaic notion that what lies beneath the surface is any more significant or real than what rides on the skin of things. ''In the end,'' he begins, ''it all comes down to a question of skin. And bones. The question of skin and bones is the question of hiding and seeking. And the question of hiding and seeking is the question of detection. Is detection any longer possible?'' His answer: not if you expect the unequivocal. ''Who is the detective?'' All of us, inveterately, ineluctably. ''What is detected?'' The fluidity of identity and the plurality of worlds. ''Is there anything left to hide?'' Yes and no, because everything these days lies exposed, waiting to be examined. ''Is there any longer a place to hide?'' We wish there were, but if wishes were horses, we would be riding backward. ''Can anyone continue to hide?'' No; the social habit and cultural tradition of hiding are now as unavailing as they are unwise. ''Does skin hide anything or is everything nothing but skin?'' Ah, that's a rhetorical question, and from this the rest of the book unravels.</p>
        <p>Physiologically, each of us develops from a hollow ball, or blastomere, that eventually forms two layers of skin, endoderm and ectoderm, out of which all else comes. ''Since the organism as a whole is formed by a complex of dermal layers, the body is, in effect, nothing but strata of skin in which interiority and exteriority are thoroughly convoluted.'' That settled, Taylor leads us through his first chapter, ''Skinsc(r)apes'' -- from skin cancer and psoriasis through Hegel's actualized spirit to the post-modern fictions of Dennis Potter and Paul Auster, in which authors and characters swap skins and voices like manic fur-trading ventriloquists.</p>
        <p>The next and best chapter, ''Dermagraphics,'' investigates our late-20th-century vogue for inscribing the self on the skin, tattoos burned into expanses of epidermis across the socioeconomic spectrum. Only by way of our flesh does our ''frustrating and repressive'' world allow most of us to take on personal significance, and in a multinational, dematerialized, computer-etherized society, the individual can only be skin-deep. That goes for beauty too, so Taylor explores fashion, ''profound in its superficiality,'' reflecting ''the infinite complexity of a play of surfaces that knows no end.'' His 70-page analysis, mistaken in its claim that fashion is a creature of modernity, falls hostage to the hyperbole of the fashion industry itself. Perhaps the chapter is a parody, superficial in its profundity?</p>
        <p>''Ground Zero,'' the penultimate chapter, about the skin and bones of modern architecture, is scarcely more insightful, though its focus on pyramids is further evidence that we tend at centuries' ends to look toward the pentahedron as a transitional geometry and an elemental force. Taylor is brave to take it on; its current popularity would seem to contradict his premise that these days we are depthless. We find the pyramid enticing because its surfaces imply an embedded secret, confirmed by labyrinths and burial chambers within, arcane celestial calculations performed on platforms above, chthonic ''power centers'' welling up from below, ''energy fields'' flowing invisibly around. Taylor is not amused; he retreats to an elevated discourse about the nature of sacrifice that ignores the experiential volume, mass, immediacy and interiority of pyramids.</p>
        <p>This is no mere quibble. What becomes obvious in ''Hiding'' is Taylor's oxymoronic effort to direct our gaze toward what is not obvious, toward what is in effect hidden on the surface of our lives that is deeply consequential. I suppose he might protest that his ambitions lie with dexterity rather than with discovery, the sure-handed consideration of that which is intellectually most slippery, but he is too thoughtful to let things rest at that. He and the book's designers, Michael Rock and Susan Sellers, struggle ever to provide context (historical depth), contour (cultural depth), concept (philosophical depth) and convergence (visual depths of palimpsest and textual trompe l'oeil). If we take to heart the melancho-lyrical refrain of the book -- ''Skin rubbing at skin, skin, skin, skin, skin'' -- Taylor's manner and method are squarely at odds with his mission: to persuade us toward ''a gay wisdom that freely accepts lack and embraces loss.''</p>
        <p>In his final chapter, ''Interfacing,'' Taylor proposes to solve the impasse of post-modern and post-structuralist cultural criticism: how to avoid insularity while developing ''a sustained critique of the totalizing and repressive propensities of comprehensive systems and all-inclusive structures.'' This problem is akin to that faced by anarchism in the 1890's: how to respond in a systematic, collective, concerted manner to long-term systemic (industrial, capitalist) outrages while repudiating the very notion of system.</p>
        <p>These days, our notion of a system is a web, and a peculiar notion that is. Webs may be suffocating or supportive, but either way their strength lies rather with their tension and their extension than with their depth. To attack a web for its ethical uncertainty or its lack of profundity is to go shadowboxing. How can one take a coherent moral and political stand against systems in a world of floating, fluctuating, virtual webs?</p>
        <p>Conspiring single-handedly toward a solution, Taylor rethinks the web in the light of philosophy (Kant, Hegel, Nietzsche), in the light of the web's virtual realities -- malls, neural nets, molecular computers, cyberspace -- which others (Michael Heim, Allucquere Rosanne Stone, Donna Haraway) have examined more vigorously and imaginatively. Originality, however, is beside the point, for the puzzles Taylor confronts are hardly new. His skin-and-bones puzzle returns us to Plato's allegory of the cave, where shadow and substance are swiftly confused; the puzzle of personal freedom and collective action returns us to classical debates about the One and the Many, where the balance between individual integrity and communal destiny is always perilous.</p>
        <p>Taylor's response to shadows on cave walls is to delight in those shadows as imperfections that suggest, at every flicker, another path. His response to conflicts between the One and the Many is to quote the philosopher Daniel Dennett on the ''parallel pandemonium'' of our biological and mental processes, for which there is, it now seems, no definitive hierarchy of processes, no central controller, not even a clear distinction between body and mind. So also our post-modern environment is, Taylor supposes, parallel pandemonium, a carnival of possibilities, an incessant ''skin rubbing at skin, skin, skin, skin, skin'' that leads sometimes to erosion, more often toward ''a seamy web in which what comes together is held apart and what is held apart comes together.''</p>
        <p>The book's last words serve better, therefore, as an epilogue to Beckett's ''Waiting for Godot'' than as a rallying cry against a repressive world: ''To err amidst shifty interfaces that know no end is to live an irreducible enigma: nothing is hiding.'' With occasional pages entirely blank or black, texts interrupted by drifting quotations and fonts commingled, the book wears its heart on its sleeve, but its sleeves are unhappily short, especially in this era of a thinning ozone layer when we must all cover up. If this paragraph appears to hop, skip and jump from one metaphor to the next to still another -- from shifty interfaces to shifting fonts to a shift in global atmospheric conditions -- let it be understood as the thinnest, skin-deep preview of Taylor's sheer athleticism of image and idea.</p>
        <p>The front flap of ''Hiding'' tells me post-modernism ''has given us a new sense of the superficial, one in which the issue is not the absence of meaning but its uncontrollable, ecstatic proliferation.'' This is how one might also define skin cancer -- where Taylor began.</p>
        <p>Hillel Schwartz's most recent book is ''The Culture of the Copy: Striking Likenesses, Unreasonable Facsimiles.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Hillel Schwartz's most recent book is ''The Culture of the Copy: Striking Likenesses, Unreasonable Facsimiles.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
