<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tropics in Europe: A Great Bordeaux?</title>
    <meta content="Y26EUR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="953129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitney, Craig R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E6D81F3EF935A1575BC0A961958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tropics in Europe: A Great Bordeaux?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitney, Craig R</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Aug. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Europe is sweltering through unusually warm summer, with air pollution and temperature inversions, that may be related to global warming or El Nino, Pacific Ocean current; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Norway,  tropical nights  more than a dozen this summer when the temperature never dropped below 68 degrees, or 20 degrees centigrade -- the most since records have been kept. By early August, Norsk Iskrem had sold 20 million more ice cream cones than usual.</p>
        <p>In France, scorching days -- 15 consecutive in August alone when the temperature hit 86 degrees, or 30 degrees centigrade, or higher -- the longest heat wave this century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Norway,  tropical nights  more than a dozen this summer when the temperature never dropped below 68 degrees, or 20 degrees centigrade -- the most since records have been kept. By early August, Norsk Iskrem had sold 20 million more ice cream cones than usual.</p>
        <p>In France, scorching days -- 15 consecutive in August alone when the temperature hit 86 degrees, or 30 degrees centigrade, or higher -- the longest heat wave this century.</p>
        <p>In central England the average temperature this month reached nearly 68 degrees, almost as high as in 1995, when the August temperature set an all-time record there.</p>
        <p>It's been an unpleasant heat, bringing with it temperature inversions and air pollution that was so severe in Paris last week that authorities cut fares in half on subways and buses.</p>
        <p>Europeans have had more than usual to complain about with their weather this year, starting with an April drought and a late-spring cold snap that produced snow in the Loire Valley in early May. June was cold and wet in most places, and prolonged heavy rains in central and eastern Europe caused devastating floods in the Czech Republic, Poland, and eastern Germany in July.</p>
        <p>August then turned so balmy in most parts of Europe that penguins had to be smeared with suntan lotion at the Edinburgh Zoo, according to authorities there who said the heat had caused the birds to moult so heavily that they were in danger of sunburn.</p>
        <p>''We don't yet have enough information to say whether the unusual weather has anything to do with global warming or the El Nino current in the Pacific,'' said Alain Foidart, a weather forecaster in Toulouse.</p>
        <p>''There was a stagnant situation in July when a low pressure area kept sucking cold air from Russia down into Central Europe and producing rain there,'' Mr. Foidart said, ''and there's been another stagnant situation since the 6th and 7th of August, with high pressure over the Continent and low pressure off the French Atlantic coast bringing up warm and dry air from the Sahara.''</p>
        <p>The heat wave is now coming to an end, Mr. Foidart promised, with the arrival of the first of a series of Atlantic storms that will soon bring Western European weather back to its usual pattern of cold, rainy spells interspersed with brief, sunny ones.</p>
        <p>''While the heat has been sustained, it hasn't been exceptionally hot,'' he pointed out, with temperatures coming nowhere near France's record high of 112 degrees.</p>
        <p>But Paris has had nights balmier than those in New York City this summer, with the overnight low temperature late last week reaching only 72 degrees.</p>
        <p>Anecdotally, at least, the European climate does seem to be changing. On 20 farms in southern England, where there have been a series of unusual droughts during the last decade, sunflowers now grow where none used to survive the damp weather, and birds began building nests two weeks earlier than usual this year.</p>
        <p>''Mediterranean days and tropical nights aren't what forged the British character,'' a columnist for the London Evening Standard, Lesley Garner, wrote last week.</p>
        <p>In Bordeaux, the Wine Trade Council said that the grape harvest began last Monday, a month earlier than usual and only three days later than the 1893 harvest, the earliest on record. ''The precocity of the harvest means this will be a legendary year,'' said Jean-Bernard Delmas, director of Chateau Haut-Brion, as perhaps he would also have said if the harvest had begun unusually late.</p>
        <p>The most serious side-effect of the heat wave in Paris and Strasbourg during the last week has the high air pollution worse in Strasbourg than in Paris, where the authorities relentlessly build underground municipal parking garages for automobiles and then endlessly debate what to do if cars create so much pollution that people can no longer breathe.</p>
        <p>Much hot air was devoted to this subject last Tuesday and Wednesday, when ozone levels reached 200 micrograms per cubic meter of air, enough to set off Alert Level 2. Alert Level 3 would require the authorities to forbid some drivers from using their cars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
