<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fill 'er Up? We Do.</title>
    <meta content="15JPCO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="937189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New England States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pennsylvania</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tosco Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Newman, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Pennsylvania</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB173FF936A25755C0A961958260" item-length="2590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fill 'er Up? We Do.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Newman, Andy</byline>
      <dateline>LINDEN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey, home of world's largest oil port and largest refinery on East Coast, has love-hate relationship with its key oil industry; area around Port of New York is storage and distribution center for NJ, New York, New England and Pennsylvania; state's six refineries account for half of East Coast's refinery output; operations of Tosco Corp's giant Bayway refinery described; table; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S just before 9 on a dazzling morning and the largest refinery on the East Coast is running full tilt, as it always is these days. The world's biggest catalytic cracker is cracking, crude and gas and diesel are surging through 675 miles of blue and gray pipe, the intermittent ''psssht'' of venting steam rises above the hum of compressor motors. And as Michael Karlovich, Bayway Refinery's head of community relations, stands on the deck of company headquarters admiring a surreal 300-foot-high skyline that looks like gargantuan thermos bottles and mixing bowls and flame-topped rocket-launching platforms, he is reminded of a recent conversation.</p>
        <p>''We had some people from Liberty Science Center up here and one woman said, 'Is there a registry of national historic places that this is on?' I said I wish everybody else felt that way.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S just before 9 on a dazzling morning and the largest refinery on the East Coast is running full tilt, as it always is these days. The world's biggest catalytic cracker is cracking, crude and gas and diesel are surging through 675 miles of blue and gray pipe, the intermittent ''psssht'' of venting steam rises above the hum of compressor motors. And as Michael Karlovich, Bayway Refinery's head of community relations, stands on the deck of company headquarters admiring a surreal 300-foot-high skyline that looks like gargantuan thermos bottles and mixing bowls and flame-topped rocket-launching platforms, he is reminded of a recent conversation.</p>
        <p>''We had some people from Liberty Science Center up here and one woman said, 'Is there a registry of national historic places that this is on?' I said I wish everybody else felt that way.''</p>
        <p>The fact that not everybody else does feel that way speaks volumes about New Jersey's love-hate relationship with its most visible industry and its crucial contribution to the region's economy. In Texas and Wyoming, they make a cultural fetish of their rigs and derricks. But New Jersey seems to be in a permanent state of apology for being home to the world's largest oil port -- of which Bayway, where on any given day there is enough gasoline on hand to drive a car to the sun and back 27 times, is only one part.</p>
        <p>Every year, more than 28 billion gallons of petroleum in various forms flows in and out of the Port of New York, whose facilities are mostly in New Jersey. It sloshes in the holds of hundreds of town-sized tankers and thousands of barges that ply the Arthur Kill, rides on the backs of trains and trucks and rumbles along underground at 20 miles an hour through the eastern United States' largest oil pipeline, which ends a few hundred yards from Bayway's door.</p>
        <p>And when it's not moving, of course, the stuff rests, in the big fat cylinders that make the flight approach to Newark International Airport look like an enormous checkerboard where white is beating the pants off black. In the northeast quarter of the state, mostly along the Arthur Kill, Newark Bay and the Hudson, Hackensack and Passaic rivers, roughly 700 king-size storage tanks hold more than 3 billion gallons of gas and oil awaiting processing or shipment all over New Jersey, New York, New England and Pennsylvania.</p>
        <p>Just as important as New Jersey's capacity to move and store fuel is its capacity to make it. The state's six refineries -- besides Bayway, the others are a Hess plant in Woodbridge, a Chevron asphalt plant in Perth Amboy, and plants run by Mobil, Coastal and Citgo along the Delaware River near Paulsboro, south of Camden -- account about half of the Eastern Seaboard's refinery output.</p>
        <p>And for the past 10 years, New Jersey's refineries have been getting busier. They now process about 30 million gallons of crude oil a day, up from 19 million a day in 1987 and more than enough to meet New Jersey's 25-million-gallon-a-day appetite for fuel if it all stayed in-state. Even with the increased production, though, refinery jobs, which pay top scale of about $20 an hour, are disappearing just as fast as other manufacturing jobs in New Jersey. The refineries  now employ 5,200 people, down 23 percent since 1990 and down by more than half since 1919, when New Jersey was the nation's leading refinery employer.</p>
        <p>Much of the increased production is at  Bayway, whose parent company, the Tosco Corporation, has doubled processing capacity to 12 million gallons a day since it bought the plant from Exxon in 1992 for a paltry $157 million (Mr. Karlovich estimated the whole refinery would cost $2 billion to replace). Tosco, based in Stamford, Conn., has become one of the nation's biggest independent refiners by buying up refineries that others no longer find profitable.</p>
        <p>The local refineries help keep fuel prices low in New Jersey, in part because they have to compete against imports that come into the Port of New York, which receives more than half of the nation's imported petroleum products, and against Gulf Coast refiners that use the Colonial Pipeline, which supplies more than half of the region's fuel and terminates in Linden. The main reason, though, for New Jersey's low prices at the pump, is the fact that the state has the nation's fourth-lowest gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>'You Have to Burn Fuel to Make Fuel'</p>
        <p>Of course there are drawbacks to this petrochemical wealth. The fourth-, fifth- and sixth-biggest polluters in the state are all oil refineries, according to the Department of Environmental Protection. The top three are all utility generating stations. In 1995, Bayway, ranked No. 5, belched out 5,092 tons of the ingredients that make smog, 551 tons of carbon monoxide and 1,208 tons of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain.</p>
        <p>But the refineries pollute far less than they used to -- no more burnt-popcorn smell as you drive up the New Jersey Turnpike -- and, with considerable prodding from state regulators, they are continuing to improve.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's any single industry that's more environmentally conscious than we are,'' said John Maxwell, associate director of the New Jersey Petroleum Council.</p>
        <p>Besides, said Ray Papalski, the supervising environmental specialist in the D.E.P.'s Bureau of Air Quality Planning: ''Somebody's got to be the largest. These are big facilities that have a lot of employees and a lot of pieces of equipment and process a lot of product, and they do stuff that by its inherent nature causes air contaminants. You have to burn fuel to make fuel.''</p>
        <p>At Bayway, crude oil from any number of places, including the North Sea, South America and several African countries, is pumped off a tanker at the company's dock on the Arthur Kill. It travels two miles through pipes, under the turnpike to a tank field, where it is blended with other types of crude and piped to a furnace.</p>
        <p>There, it is boiled at about 650 degrees and sent to a distillation tower. The resulting vapors rise to the top of the tower, and as each of the compounds that make up the crude cools below its boiling point, it condenses to a liquid and flows down through a series of trays. Heavier components with higher boiling points -- asphalt, fuel oil, jet fuel, diesel, heating oil, and the raw ingredients of rubber and plastic -- condense first and flow to lower levels. Lighter products -- gasoline components and lighter-than-air gases like propane and butane -- collect higher up.</p>
        <p>The black, arm-like sidepipes that reach out of the tower at regular intervals pull the components off and send them on their way. Some, such as jet fuel, require no further processing and proceed directly to storage tanks. Others require more processing.</p>
        <p>Because the demand for gasoline, compared to other petroleum products, is much greater than the supply that naturally occurs from distillation, some of the heavier components are sent on to the catalytic cracking unit, commonly known as the cat cracker. In the cracker, long, heavy oil molecules are bombarded with a finely powdered, 1,300-degree catalyst that breaks them into smaller molecules of gasoline or light heating oil.</p>
        <p>''It's like a big kitchen,'' Mr. Karlovich said. ''We're heating, we're cooling, we're mixing, we're blending, changing things from ingredients to finished product.'' The journey from the crude ship to the gasoline storage tank takes about four days.</p>
        <p>The finished product is liable to wind up just about anywhere in the Northeast. BP, Getty and Amoco tanker trucks fill up at Bayway's rack with custom-blended gasoline. Barges pick up heating oil and haul it to tank farms on Long Island or bring it to New Haven Harbor, where it is distributed throughout New England.</p>
        <p>And much of Bayway's product is delivered to the Buckeye Pipeline's Linden station, which connects to pipelines at the Station Manifold, a mansion-sized labyrinth of pipes and almost 800 valves. The Buckeye receives fuel from the Bayway and Hess refineries, a handful of storage terminals, the Colonial Pipeline and the Harbor Pipeline along the Delaware Bay, and sends it as far west as Pittsburgh and Buffalo. Buckeye also pumps fuel under the Hudson to New York City and pipes jet fuel to Newark, Kennedy and La Guardia airports.</p>
        <p>Storage terminals or tank farms, which make up much of the visible oil landscape in New Jersey, come in two varieties: those owned by an oil company that supply a single brand fuel, and those that rent out storage space to oil distributors and are essentially fuel warehouses. The 17-tank Amoco Terminal in Carteret, for instance, which fills 100 Amoco trucks a day and dispatches barges across the Arthur Kill to Staten Island or up the river to Mount Vernon, often takes deliveries from the independent G.A.T.X. terminal across the street.</p>
        <p>''If you decide you want to go into business and you want to buy 130,000 barrels of product coming in from, say, Venezuela,'' said Amoco's terminal manager, Lou Romano, ''you call up G.A.T.X., they store it for you and ship it out based on your instructions.''</p>
        <p>One drawback of the enormous concentration of oil tanks in the harbor is the small but ever-present risk of sabotage or attack. ''It's one of those unquestioned questions,'' Mr. Romano said. ''Everybody knows where they are; you can't hide them. We do have alerts when there are heightened tensions between the U.S. and other countries. Otherwise, it's a concern but not an overriding factor.''</p>
        <p>How to Make Money In a Competitive Market</p>
        <p>For Tosco, operating an oil refinery in the middle of the world's biggest petroleum market has its pros and cons. Obviously, it cuts transportation costs to be where the customers are. But the endless supply coming in on tankers from Europe, barges from the Gulf of Mexico and the Colonial Pipeline means prices must be kept low. At the same time, electricity in Texas costs half of what it does here, Mr. Maxwell of the New Jersey Petroleum Council said, and labor -- the Bayway refinery has 950 employees -- is considerably cheaper.</p>
        <p>Then there is added cost of doing business in New Jersey, which has some of the nation's strictest air regulations. And there is the ongoing problem of silt buildup in the harbor, which keeps out bigger tankers and forces many boats to unload some cargo at sea in order to become light enough to make it into the harbor. (Tosco got tired of waiting for the silt problem to be solved and commissioned a fleet of extra-wide tankers that hold 20 percent more than a conventional tanker of the same draft.)</p>
        <p>All of this has meant that Tosco has had to be lean and mean, and it has. In the process, industry analysts say, Tosco is making about 12 percent profit off a refinery that lost money for Exxon. ''Tosco's purchase of that refinery was good news for New Jersey, for Tosco, and for Exxon,'' said Fredrick Leuffer, an analyst with Bear Stearns.</p>
        <p>The only people who do not seem completely thrilled are the members of Teamsters Local 877. Tosco renegotiated the union contract when it took over and, according to the local president, Curt Greder, got rid of about 100 workers.</p>
        <p>''They basically trashed our contract,'' Mr. Greder said. ''They try to make the contract as vague as they possibly can, eliminate work rules so they have a more or less free hand in dealing with labor. That allows them to hold the sword of Damocles over you and make you hope they don't do anything else.''</p>
        <p>Labor relations notwithstanding, Bayway takes great pains to maintain its public image and cope with the headaches that come with running a mammoth factory along the state's main road.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, as part of its effort to improve the plant's esthetics, Bayway began dismantling a rusting 50-foot-high propane storage sphere just beyond the Turnpike fence. Not long after, Mr. Karlovich said, the company got a call from a state trooper who said the Governor wanted to know if there was anything wrong.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karlovich is particularly annoyed that Bayway's $22 million wet gas scrubber, which vents clouds of water vapor -- not smoke -- as it pulls waste gas and dust particles out of the emission stream, has somehow managed to become the news industry's stock shot of New Jersey pollution. ''It's like a hex on us,'' he said. ''Every time there's some kind of chemical calamity or pharmaceutical scandal, they show our scrubber.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Karlovich pointed out on a tour that Bayway's sprawling property -- at 2.1 square miles, it is roughly twice the size of Hoboken -- includes a lot more than pipes and towers. There are three named streams -- Peach Orchard Brook, West Brook and Morses Creek -- a reservoir, a modest birch forest, the Morse family's 18th-century burial ground, and a surprising amount of wildlife even in the most barren-looking places. A snow-white egret pecks along the gravel-lined banks of a cooling-water return channel. Geese and goslings swim in the rain puddles that pool in old tank pits. Cormorants sun their wings in the reservoir.</p>
        <p>One place where Bayway does not need to improve its image is in Linden itself, where the company is the biggest taxpayer and one of the few remaining industrial employers. It is also so active in the city's civic life that it received a state Good Neighbor award last week.</p>
        <p>''They've been very generous to our cultural heritage committee and our Golden Gloves boxing program,'' said the longtime Mayor, John Gregorio. ''And anytime anything happens out there, they call us immediately and let us know.''</p>
        <p>Last December, the refinery released a cloud of oily soot that settled on cars and houses. The next day, Bayway hired power-washers to clean off roofs and porches and offered free car washes to all those affected.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gregorio, who is 70, said he did not think the refinery was an environmental hazard. ''The oldest citizens we have live in Tremley Point, right in the middle of the tank fields,'' he said. ''I don't suspect the people in Linden are being hurt at all by any of the industry here.''</p>
        <p>And as for the thick refinery smell that once permeated the town, Mr. Gregorio said those days appeared to be gone for good.</p>
        <p>''I don't smell anything,'' he said. ''Besides, the prevailing winds go east, so Staten Island would get the smell if there was any.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
