<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Europe's Pollution Fighter Draws a Bead on U.S. and Japan</title>
    <meta content="T20BRUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="974387"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bjerregaard, Ritt (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5D9173BF933A15752C1A961958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Europe's Pollution Fighter Draws a Bead on U.S. and Japan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ritt Bjerregaard, European Union's outspoken Environment Commissioner, is complaining about 'weak' United States and Japanese proposals for limiting emissions of gases like carbon dioxide that may contribute to global warming; European Union has called for cuts in so-called greenhouse gases that are far more stringent than those of rest of industrialized world, stand opposed by European business leaders (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the gray world of the European Union's bureaucracy in Brussels, Ritt Bjerregaard, an unwavering politician from Denmark, stands out as a splash of color. While other officials deliver criticism in whispers and avoid confrontation, Ms. Bjerregaard speaks her mind.</p>
        <p>As Commissioner for the Environment, her job is to prod the 15 countries of the union to enforce their common rules and to cut pollution of air, land and water. Her manner is always polished and she delivers opinions in a cool style. But Ms. Bjerregaard, 56, has aimed her barbs where others have not dared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the gray world of the European Union's bureaucracy in Brussels, Ritt Bjerregaard, an unwavering politician from Denmark, stands out as a splash of color. While other officials deliver criticism in whispers and avoid confrontation, Ms. Bjerregaard speaks her mind.</p>
        <p>As Commissioner for the Environment, her job is to prod the 15 countries of the union to enforce their common rules and to cut pollution of air, land and water. Her manner is always polished and she delivers opinions in a cool style. But Ms. Bjerregaard, 56, has aimed her barbs where others have not dared.</p>
        <p>While her colleagues on the European Union's executive body chose diplomatic silence, she took on France's President, Jacques Chirac, for conducting nuclear test explosions in 1995.</p>
        <p>Europe's farmers, who are helped with generous subsidies, are polluters, she has said, because they use too many chemicals. This year, in an unusual step, she slapped three pollution fines on Germany, stinging a Government that likes to boast of its environmental concerns.</p>
        <p>Now Ms. Bjerregaard has taken on her biggest challenge so far, turning to the United States and Japan. As Europe's chief negotiator at the climate talks to be held in Kyoto, Japan, in early December, she has complained about ''weak'' anti-pollution proposals coming from Washington and Tokyo.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto conference aims to set binding limits on heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide that may contribute to global warming. Although wrapped in technical jargon, the talks involve these basic questions: Who has the right to pollute and by how much? Ms. Bjerregaard has called the negotiations ''hot-air trading.''</p>
        <p>The European Union has proposed cuts of so-called greenhouse gases that are far more stringent than those of the rest of the industrialized world, and Ms. Bjerregaard has been pressing Washington to change its stance.</p>
        <p>But European business leaders are not happy to see Europe go to Kyoto pledging high cutbacks of greenhouse gases. They argue they are already at a disadvantage in relation to the United States, where energy and fuel are far less expensive.</p>
        <p>The United States has said it will stabilize its emissions at 1990 levels by 2012. The European Union wants to cut emissions 15 percent below its 1990 level by 2010. Japan calls for a 2.5 to 5 percent cut by 2010.</p>
        <p>On her return from a recent trip to Washington, Ms. Bjerregaard said President Clinton's proposals were deeply disappointing, all the more so because the United States emits more greenhouse gases per capita than any other country.</p>
        <p>''The U.S. is going back on the commitments made in Rio,'' she told executives and lobbyists of energy industries in Brussels, referring to the Earth Summit in Rio de Janeiro in 1992. ''The European Union once again will have to take the lead. It is clear that we cannot depend on leadership by the U.S. and Japan.''</p>
        <p>Such outspokenness has sometimes startled officials at the Brussels European Union headquarters.</p>
        <p>Her most serious problem, though, is the lack of enforcement of the union's environmental rules. Some countries, she said, have not even bothered to incorporate the common rules into their national legislation.</p>
        <p>But she is the first environment commissioner to use the power of her office to impose fines for violations. ''The effect has been remarkable,'' she said. ''Already half the cases on my list are solved just because of this threat.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
