<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Intense Lobbying Against Global Warming Treaty</title>
    <meta content="07CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="978681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D71E3DF934A35751C1A961958260" item-length="1607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Intense Lobbying Against Global Warming Treaty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration's options in trying to strike a deal on global warming at talks in Kyoto, Japan, are limited by highly effective lobbying campaigns that have been waged for months by warring interests in US; environmental groups have succeeded in convincing public that threat of climate change caused by greenhouse emissions is a settled scientific reality that requires stronger correctives than Administration has proposed; powerful business interests emphasize economic risks and need to bring developing countries into any binding new treatments, arguments that have strongly influenced the Senate, where any pact must be ratified; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the Clinton Administration is struggling to strike a deal on global warming at talks in Kyoto, Japan, that is partly because warring domestic interest groups have spent many months -- and millions of dollars -- on highly effective lobbying campaigns designed to limit the White House's options.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups, traditionally closely allied with the Administration, have succeeded in convincing the public that the threat of climate change caused by emissions of greenhouse gases is a settled scientific reality that must be confronted head-on. They say the Administration's proposal for a treaty is too mild, and that a European alternative would be better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If the Clinton Administration is struggling to strike a deal on global warming at talks in Kyoto, Japan, that is partly because warring domestic interest groups have spent many months -- and millions of dollars -- on highly effective lobbying campaigns designed to limit the White House's options.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups, traditionally closely allied with the Administration, have succeeded in convincing the public that the threat of climate change caused by emissions of greenhouse gases is a settled scientific reality that must be confronted head-on. They say the Administration's proposal for a treaty is too mild, and that a European alternative would be better.</p>
        <p>But powerful business interests have emphasized the economic risks and the need to bring developing countries into any binding new treaty, arguments that have strongly influenced the Senate, where any pact must be ratified. They say the Administration is going too far and too fast, the more so since the Third World is balking at a bigger role.</p>
        <p>The private-sector lobbying, more intense, prolonged and costly than usual in the realm of diplomacy, has reached a fevered pitch this week in Kyoto, but it has been playing out in Washington for years.</p>
        <p>The antagonists include big corporations with revenues larger than the economies of little nations, labor unions with more members than some countries' armed forces, industrial trade associations with headquarters grander than embassies, and a corps of professional environmentalists that rivals the diplomatic corps in polish and pinstripes.</p>
        <p>''It is as if a large chunk of the lobbying community from the capital has been transported from Washington to Kyoto for two weeks,'' Senator Joseph Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut, marveled in a telephone interview from Kyoto, where he is an observer.</p>
        <p>Although the lobbyists are in Kyoto in force, they are relegated to the sidelines. ''Every night the U.S. delegation will come in and brief the 100 or so industry nongovernmental organizations who are present,'' said Constance Holmes, a lobbyist in Kyoto for the Global Climate Coalition, which represents major United States industries. ''They brief the U.S. business community for half an hour, and then they brief the environmental community for half an hour.''</p>
        <p>For the past two years, more than 150 nations have been trying to devise a new, stricter treaty to replace the largely voluntary one that they agreed upon five years ago in Rio de Janeiro. It is intended to set binding limits on emissions of greenhouse gases by industrial nations.</p>
        <p>Because confronting global warming means altering energy patterns throughout society, a solution to the emerging risk of climate change affects practically every conceivable interest group.</p>
        <p>Opposing a binding treaty are car makers and corn farmers, steel mills and oil refineries, electricity producers and the coal miners who stoke their boilers. They claim that cutbacks in emissions would raise energy costs sharply, rippling through the economy, creating inflation and destroying jobs or sending them overseas.</p>
        <p>Favoring a treaty are the main national environmental groups, who have spent a decade putting the issue on the global agenda. Among their most influential allies are businesses involved in conservation and renewable energy.</p>
        <p>''This is more than the environmental community has done on any single issue in 10 years,'' said Philip Clapp, head of the National Environmental Trust, an advocacy group set up three years ago to organize sophisticated media campaigns on major environmental issues.</p>
        <p>But Eileen Claussen, who was an Administration climate negotiator until she left the State Department recently to work as an environmental consultant, said that the industry campaign in Congress was especially effective.</p>
        <p>''By targeting the Congress, the industries responsible for the advertising campaign have widened the rift between the two branches,'' Ms. Claussen said. ''This has had the effect of pulling the United States farther away from most other countries in the negotiations, and hardening its position on what would constitute an acceptable target and on what should be required of developing countries.''</p>
        <p>For months, the news media have carried a steady drumbeat of advertising on the climate issue. The Global Climate Information Project, an ad hoc industry coalition, announced in September that it would spend $13 million on advertisements to defeat a treaty. Rather than attacking the scientific argument, the group's advertisements used the threat of price increases and a fairness issue: that many developing countries whose emissions of greenhouse gases are growing rapidly would not be held to the same obligations as the industrial nations.</p>
        <p>The advertisements echo the industry's slogan: ''It's not global, and it won't work.''</p>
        <p>Environmental groups swung into action, calling the advertisements misleading. They noted that details of the treaty were still being negotiated, that the Administration was calling for developing countries to play a role and that economists were divided on what the economic consequences were likely to be.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups demanded that CNN, the only national network that would air the advertisement during news programs, stop running it. At first the network complied, but it later reversed itself.</p>
        <p>Although environmental groups have not been able to afford an advertising campaign on the scale of the industry group, the Sierra Club produced a television spot recently that began with a picture of the Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein, whom it called an influential oil cartel leader, and castigated auto companies for producing gas guzzlers. And the National Council of Churches produced a spot featuring the poet Maya Angelou making a moral argument to save the planet. It is being aired free of charge, largely on Christian broadcasting stations, as a public service announcement.</p>
        <p>There is little sign that the industry's campaign has moved the public. In a New York Times poll last month, only 6 percent of adults surveyed by telephone nationwide recalled seeing industry advertisements opposing a treaty. Of those who recalled the advertisements, two-thirds said they were not influenced, and the remainder were as likely to have been swayed in favor as against the treaty.</p>
        <p>But that does not matter, said Kathleen Jamieson, dean of the Annenberg School for Communication at the University of Pennsylvania and an expert in media campaigns.</p>
        <p>''The goal of these sorts of campaigns is not ordinarily to change attitudes on the part of the public,'' Ms. Jamieson said. ''It is to persuade the legislative body that you are a player. You are involved, and you have ads on. And thus, in the next election campaign, you will have an effect by ultimately using advertising against them.'' It is in Congress, in fact, where the industry campaign appears to have the edge.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, business groups persuaded the Senate to pass a resolution insisting that developing countries like China play a bigger role in addressing the problem. The resolution was sponsored by Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, where coal dominates the economy, and Senator Chuck Hagel of Nebraska, a Republican who adamantly opposes a new treaty.</p>
        <p>Their argument is exactly the one the industry has been pressing in its advertising, and by October, when the President announced the United States negotiating policy, he, too, insisted that a treaty must include a role for key developing countries.</p>
        <p>But the Byrd-Hagel resolution, though passed unanimously, left an out. Senator John Kerry of Massachusetts, a treaty advocate, persuaded Mr. Byrd to state on the Senate floor that he did not demand that developing countries take on the same obligations as the developed world.</p>
        <p>In Kyoto, lobbyists from both sides said as the talks continued that the issue most likely to block a compromise was the question of what role developing countries should play in controlling global warming.</p>
        <p>An important component of the industry's success was its early decision to get organized labor involved. When the climate task force of the National Association of Manufacturers met earlier this year to map out a strategy for broadening opposition to a new treaty, it decided to look to the labor movement.</p>
        <p>The most obvious ally for industry was the United Mine Workers of America. Coal miners hold just 80,000 jobs in the United States, a number that is shrinking even faster than emissions of greenhouse gases are rising. But because coal gives off more carbon dioxide than any other fuel, a treaty to limit emissions of greenhouse gases would hit that union hardest.</p>
        <p>And coal miners' clout in the ranks of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. is far disproportionate to their share of the working population. Richard L. Trumka, a former United Mine Workers president and now the secretary-treasurer of the labor federation, has played a major role in presenting the coal miners' case on behalf of all labor.</p>
        <p>The labor federation's stance carries special weight these days, after its recent defeat of the Clinton Administration on trade policy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trumka used blunt words when he spelled out for the White House the views of the labor movement on the climate change talks.</p>
        <p>If some countries are exempt from the emission-control targets in the treaty, he said, ''We think our Government negotiators need to be prepared to walk away from Kyoto without a treaty in hand.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
