<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Still Defiant, but Subtler, Industry Awaits E.P.A. Rules</title>
    <meta content="27EPA.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Cooling Down the Heated Talk" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="932788"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Cooling Down the Heated Talk"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D6163AF934A15756C0A961958260" item-length="2028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Still Defiant, but Subtler, Industry Awaits E.P.A. Rules</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>As Environmental Protection Agency prepares to impose another set of strict new air pollution controls in July, industry is approaching new rules, aimed at reducing smog and soot, in disarray; many industries are trying to cut their own deals with the agency; others are putting pressure on mayors and governors to lobby Federal Government for them; still others are attacking the science--and sometimes the scientists--on which new rules are based; table; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Corporate America is not a quick study. Again and again, companies have responded to proposed environmental rules by threatening bankruptcies, huge layoffs, foreign inroads into American markets, even an end to the car-based American way of life -- and it has never worked.</p>
        <p>Finally, though, companies are acknowledging that the sky did not fall every time they were forced to clean up their act and their air. Now, as the Environmental Protection Agency prepares to impose yet another set of strict new air pollution controls this July, they are moving their doom-and-gloom approach, if not off the stove, to the furthest back burner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Corporate America is not a quick study. Again and again, companies have responded to proposed environmental rules by threatening bankruptcies, huge layoffs, foreign inroads into American markets, even an end to the car-based American way of life -- and it has never worked.</p>
        <p>Finally, though, companies are acknowledging that the sky did not fall every time they were forced to clean up their act and their air. Now, as the Environmental Protection Agency prepares to impose yet another set of strict new air pollution controls this July, they are moving their doom-and-gloom approach, if not off the stove, to the furthest back burner.</p>
        <p>''If we've learned any lesson, it's that you have to engage the debate on a different basis than costs,'' said John M. McManus, manager of environmental strategies for American Electric Power, a huge utility.</p>
        <p>But without the unifying plea of untenable burdens, industry approaches the E.P.A.'s latest rules, aimed at reducing smog and soot, in disarray. Many industries are trying to cut their own deals with the agency. Others are putting pressure on mayors and governors to lobby Washington for them. Still others are attacking the science -- and sometimes the scientists -- on which the new rules are based.</p>
        <p>The camps have been forming since November, when the agency began holding hearings on its proposed rules. The E.P.A. said existing levels in the air of ozone and ''fine particulates'' -- dust specks 28 times as thin as a human hair -- were causing a high incidence of childhood asthma, and possibly tens of thousands of adult deaths a year.</p>
        <p>Industry says the E.P.A. has not conclusively proved this, and thus should not set stricter rules. Environmentalists and regulators counter that the agency, which Congress set up for the purpose of keeping the environment healthy and safe, must issue regulations unless they are proved unnecessary, not the other way around.</p>
        <p>''Companies are attacking the scientific legitimacy of standards only because their cost arguments have been disproven so many times,'' said Daniel Rosenberg, a lawyer for the U.S. Public Interest Research Group, an environmental lobbying group.  Added David G. Hawkins, a lawyer for the Natural Resources Defense Council: ''This is not a scientific debate. It is an attempt to change policy and weaken the law.''</p>
        <p>Historically, the courts have sided with the environmentalists. A decade ago, the steel industry lost a suit, which went all the way to the Supreme Court, seeking to prohibit the E.P.A. from regulating pollutants unless it was certain they were a health risk. ''The Supreme Court basically said, the more uncertainty there is, the more discretion the E.P.A. should have,'' conceded Andrew G. Sharkey, president of the American Iron and Steel Institute.</p>
        <p>Still, industry sees no choice but to take this tack again. If the E.P.A. issues tougher rules in July, localities will probably force companies to filter out more dust, and to control emissions of nitrous oxides, benzene and other chemicals that are the precursors of ozone. That could cost companies millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Still, after so many years of crying wolf, companies are loath to make the cost argument. Even American Electric Power, once the undisputed ringleader of the anti-Clean Air Act gang, has muted its cries. Some quick history can show why.</p>
        <p>In the early 1970's, the utility mounted a $3.7 million advertising campaign to contend that technology did not exist to meet proposed rules on sulfur dioxide and particulates. In 1975 an equipment maker, Research Cottrell, began marketing a sulfur dioxide smokestack scrubber that proved American Electric wrong.</p>
        <p>So then the utility complained that it would cost $260 million a power plant to install enough scrubbers, leading to skyrocketing electric costs. The E.P.A. did not budge, the cleanup tab turned out to be much lower, and electric rates went up only marginally.</p>
        <p>Skip ahead to the late 1980's, when Congress and the E.P.A., worrying  about acid rain -- caused by sulfur-based pollution that can travel wide distances -- insisted on even stricter sulfur controls. American Electric said the new standards would cost utilities more than $5 billion, raising  residential electricity rates 12 percent and industrial rates as much as 39 percent.</p>
        <p>Again, Washington gave no ground. But scrubber technology improved and railroad deregulation made it cheaper to bring in low-sulfur coal. The utility industry's costs were less than half its projections.</p>
        <p>Small wonder that American Electric and its sister utilities are loath to cry economic foul this time. Instead, they are asking that the existing 10-year ozone and large-particulate- abatement program, which the E.P.A. mandated in 1990, be allowed to run its course.</p>
        <p>''Let us finish this first and then discuss what else must be done,''  said Robert A. Beck, vice president for environmental affairs at the Edison Electric Institute, the trade group for utilities.</p>
        <p>All the new approaches -- the begging for time, the emphasis on science, the absence of inflated cost claims -- reflect industry's new relationship with investors, customers and the courts.</p>
        <p>In the 70's, while the E.P.A. did not believe industry's threats of financial disaster, investors did -- and sent Rust Belt stocks plummeting. Now utilities, heavy manufacturers and steelmakers fear that inflated cost forecasts could touch off another selling spree.</p>
        <p>''I always ask companies, 'Are you budgeted to meet new rules?' and they always answer, 'Oh, certainly,' '' said Kenneth W. P. Hoffman, a steel analyst with Prudential Securities Research.</p>
        <p>Consumers, always edgy about placing a dollar value on health, have been made more uneasy by the debate over managed health care and disclosures about the tobacco industry's suppression of data.</p>
        <p>''The public has a bad taste in its mouth about cost-benefit issues,'' conceded Augustine E. Moffitt Jr., vice president for safety, health and environment at Bethlehem Steel.</p>
        <p>The courts have been little help. In 1992, for example, a Federal court ruled that the E.P.A. must stick to a strict timetable for reviewing whether rules must be tightened.</p>
        <p>In the face of all this adversity, industry's once-united front has fragmented. The inter-industry Air Quality Standards Coalition, which insists that the E.P.A. stick with existing rules, only pretends to speak with one voice. Petroleum companies, which might have to reformulate gasoline under new rules, also want to maintain the status quo. But electric utilities simply want to postpone new rules while they deal with deregulation.</p>
        <p>And chemical companies, which are far more worried about pending toxic-waste changes, are currying favor with the E.P.A. by offering to settle for a stricter interim air standard that could be strengthened or eased, depending on what additional research indicates.</p>
        <p>When the Chemical Manufacturers Association belatedly joined the air-quality coalition in February, Joe J. Mayhew, its assistant vice president for environmental policy, visited Mary Nichols, the E.P.A.'s assistant administrator for air and radiation, to reassure her that his industry would remain conciliatory.</p>
        <p>''We really believe that if we go to the E.P.A. with a supportive attitude and some data making our case, we'll do better than if we just keep arguing about costs,'' Mr. Mayhew said. Indeed, he concedes that Du Pont, Dow Chemical and several other companies have made money by recapturing ''pollutants'' like ammonia or other chemical ingredients from their waste-water streams, and by providing nonpolluting substitutes for some banned substances like chlorofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Still, the conciliatory approach remains a rarity. Most companies still contend that the E.P.A. is relying on flawed studies -- and too few of them, at that. They are particularly incensed about a study by two professors at Harvard's School of Public Health that links fine dust particles to premature deaths. The professors have refused to release their raw data or talk to the press; earlier this month, Harvard agreed to let an independent research group reanalyze the data.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. hotly disputes that it overemphasized that study. Gary Guzy, its chief policy adviser, said the agency combed 185 ozone studies, and 86 particulate studies, before deciding to set new standards.</p>
        <p>''Some say this is junk science, that we picked numbers out of a hat, but there is compelling evidence that people are getting sick,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The American Petroleum Institute, for one, is trying to muster equally compelling evidence that they are not. In the process, it is using science as a back door through which to reintroduce cost issues.</p>
        <p>The institute recently used scientific hypotheses about the link between soot and smog levels and respiratory illness to calculate the savings to society of a reduction in lost workdays or hospitalizations stemming from such illnesses. It concluded that in ozone-troubled Chicago, for one, industry expenditures of $2.5 billion a year to meet stricter standards would yield only $33 million worth of health benefits.</p>
        <p>''Ten years ago, I can't think of a single industry that really quantified the benefits as well as costs,'' said Paul Bailey, the institute's director of health and environmental affairs.</p>
        <p>Industry is not confining its attention to the E.P.A., of course. Last year's Congressional Review Act gives Congress the right to overturn rules it thinks are unreasonable, and some companies are trying to get their representatives to call for a vote on the proposed rules. But far more are taking their pleas to the citizenry; American Electric, for example, is sending its executives to speak to Rotary and Kiwanis Clubs.</p>
        <p>Some are even letting histrionics -- albeit not cost-related ones -- creep back into the fray. Citizens for a Sound Economy, an inter-industry group, is taking out ads warning that the E.P.A.'s new rules will mean the end of backyard barbecues and fireworks -- a prediction that a top E.P.A. official termed ''ridiculous.''</p>
        <p>Environmentalists, not surprisingly, are fighting back. The Sierra Club and Mr. Rosenberg's group recently collected thousands of postcards from families supporting tougher rules, and orchestrated a May 9 event in which mothers and their asthmatic children delivered them to the White House.</p>
        <p>For now, industry has forgone similar media events. But environmentalists expect that if civilized whispers and scientific studies do not derail the new smog and soot rules, industry will again make cacophony its tactic of choice.</p>
        <p>''The science argument is their lead argument inside the Beltway, but they're still running doom-and- gloom ads and Op-Eds elsewhere,'' Mr. Rosenberg noted. ''And if the science argument doesn't work, you're going to see even more.''</p>
        <p>Cooling Down the Heated Talk</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
