<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PARTIES RETHINK THEIR CORE GOALS AS DEFICIT SHRINKS</title>
    <meta content="28SURP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="983747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE6DB1731F93BA15751C1A961958260" item-length="1661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PARTIES RETHINK THEIR CORE GOALS AS DEFICIT SHRINKS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years dominated by Federal budget deficits, the capital faces a new quandary: how to deal with the prospect of surpluses.</p>
        <p>Ever since the early years of the Reagan Presidency, the Federal deficit has defined the political debate and limited the range of social policy. It caused George Bush to break with his party's dogma of tax cutting. It frustrated Democrats who wanted activist government. It gave a brief impetus to Ross Perot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After years dominated by Federal budget deficits, the capital faces a new quandary: how to deal with the prospect of surpluses.</p>
        <p>Ever since the early years of the Reagan Presidency, the Federal deficit has defined the political debate and limited the range of social policy. It caused George Bush to break with his party's dogma of tax cutting. It frustrated Democrats who wanted activist government. It gave a brief impetus to Ross Perot.</p>
        <p>Now, though, good times are presenting both President Clinton and the Republican leaders of Congress with a challenge to keep their political parties from fracturing and to prevent a new burst of unrestrained tax cutting and spending.</p>
        <p>To tamp down the enthusiasm as the strong economy brings a surge of revenue to the Government, Mr. Clinton has taken to warning that the Federal deficit has yet to disappear. But while he urges caution, some analysts on Wall Street are predicting that a surplus will appear, perhaps as early as this fiscal year -- and well before the target date of 2002, which was set in the summer's balanced budget agreement.</p>
        <p>Just as the end of the cold war left America's foreign policy makers on uncharted terrain, this prospect of surpluses radically alters the domestic debate, causing both parties to re-examine what they should stand for. ''This is a historic starting point for one of the most important dialogues that we are going to have in our generation,'' Speaker Newt Gingrich said before Congress adjourned this year.</p>
        <p>The last time the Government ran a surplus was in the 1969 fiscal year. The last time the Government ran two successive surpluses was in 1956 and in 1957 -- when Bill Clinton and Newt Gingrich were schoolboys.</p>
        <p>The budget act of 1990, which set in place the budgeting procedures used on Capitol Hill, does not even have mechanisms to deal with a surplus. In a discipline geared to keeping the deficit from growing, it requires that any tax cuts or recurring spending increases enacted by Congress be offset by equal spending reductions or revenue increases.</p>
        <p>''There's been a remarkable turnaround,'' said Gene Sperling, Mr. Clinton's chief economic adviser. ''In the blink of an eye, we've gone from being accused that our balanced budget would only balance for one second to being questioned about why we won't admit there's a huge surplus and why we're being so stingy about talking about spending it.''</p>
        <p>The visions of plenty could turn out to be premature. No one is certain how the financial turmoil in Asia will affect the growth of the United States economy, and unexpected downturns could always occur.</p>
        <p>White House and Congressional budget forecasters are planning to release new projections next month showing a positive development: that the deficit for the current fiscal year will be $20 billion to $30 billion less than the $58 billion the White House had previously forecast.</p>
        <p>Recent Treasury Department figures go even further and suggest the possibility of a surplus. They show that in the last 12 months the Federal Government took in $2.4 billion more than it spent. And some Wall Street analysts are already projecting a $20 billion to $40 billion surplus by the time the current fiscal year ends in September.</p>
        <p>Ever since an enormous structural deficit developed after the 1981 Reagan tax cut plan was approved by Congress, the red ink has constrained the domestic debate.</p>
        <p>Even the most liberal Democrats acknowledged that insolvency hemmed in the possibility of activist government. And Republicans fractured between a wing of ''deficit hawks'' devoted to balancing the budget and a supply-side, tax-cutting faction, many of whose members believed that lower tax rates would bring higher revenues.</p>
        <p>Now, just the glimmer of a post-deficit era has set off political pressures in Washington to break free of the balanced budget agreement struck by President Clinton and the Congress during the summer and allow more social spending and more tax cuts, or a more radical tax overhaul.</p>
        <p>''Ultimately, the biggest problem this year will be: Can the leadership keep its troops in line?'' said Stanley Collender, the managing director of the Federal budget consulting group for Burson-Marsteller, the public relations firm.</p>
        <p>In the Republican Party, divisions are already sharpening between the balanced budget advocates and the ardent tax cutters. Disputes are also looming between those Republicans who want a business-oriented tax cut, like a further reduction in the capital gains tax, and those who want a family-oriented tax cut, like elimination of the ''marriage penalty,'' under which many married couples who file jointly are pushed into higher tax brackets because of their combined income.</p>
        <p>Some Republicans are pushing an entire revision of the income tax code to put in place a flat tax or a national sales tax.</p>
        <p>The Republicans also have their spenders. Some want to increase military outlays or, like Representative Bud Shuster of Pennsylvania, chairman of the House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee, they want to spend billions on new highway and bridge projects.</p>
        <p>Democrats, meanwhile, are trying to sort out how to promote a new social agenda without reviving their image as big spenders.</p>
        <p>Like the Republicans, the Democrats have their fiscally conservative wing urging restraint. But there is strong sentiment in the party for programs to rebuild crumbling schools, address urban decay, provide health care for the uninsured and sponsor retraining programs for workers displaced by the information age economy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton has already indicated that in some policy areas he will be looking to use tax incentives instead of spending increases as a tool of social policy. He plans to propose tax incentives next year to promote day-care programs and to spur development of energy efficient technologies to curb global warming.</p>
        <p>In both parties, new political strategies are being formulated. Some Republicans are trying to move away from advocating a balanced budget, per se, to emphasize shrinking government.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a conservative because I believe in a balanced budget,'' said Representative Bill Archer, the chairman of the Ways and Means Committee. ''I'm a conservative because I believe that a smaller government with less power means greater freedom and more opportunity for the American people.''</p>
        <p>Democrats in the Administration and Congress, meanwhile, say they are trying to guard against being stampeded by the Republicans into large tax cuts, like the Reagan tax cuts of 1981. The Democrats say they fear such tax cuts could bring new deficits early in the next century -- which, in turn, could then bring decades of cutting back government.</p>
        <p>''The worst thing that could be done,'' Mr. Sperling said, ''is if -- based on a surplus -- long-term promises on either tax cuts or spending were made that would prove completely unsustainable if the surplus went away or was less than projected. Repeating the mistakes of 1981 should not be an option.''</p>
        <p>This ferment inside and between the parties is likely to drive the 1998 midterm Congressional elections and carry into the Presidential campaign of 2000. But it carries a high risk -- that it will unravel the very balanced budget agreement that is helping usher the nation into a new period of plenty.</p>
        <p>Administration officials and Congressional aides said Mr. Clinton, who wants to protect his legacy as a fiscally prudent leader, was acutely aware of this problem. ''There is a general concern that there could be a feeding frenzy that could blow away the fiscal progress,'' one Administration official said.</p>
        <p>Representative John R. Kasich, the Ohio Republican who is chairman of the House Budget Committee, is also trying to head off sentiment for deviating from the five-year budget agreement.</p>
        <p>''This is something we have to be vigilant about,'' he said. ''I don't want any additional Federal spending above the agreement.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gingrich recently weighed in by calling on Mr. Clinton to propose a balanced budget for the new fiscal year instead of waiting until 2002 to bring the budget into balance. An actual balanced budget -- as opposed to a plan to balance the budget -- would be a potent achievement on which incumbents could run in the 1998 Congressional elections.</p>
        <p>Some fiscal watchdog groups and some lawmakers want the Government to preserve any surplus, rather than devoting it to new programs or tax cuts. Such action would effectively allow the Treasury to begin retiring some of the nation's $5.5 trillion debt and have more resources on hand for when the baby boom generation begins retiring and putting a strain on Medicare and Social Security.</p>
        <p>The position of those who want to protect a potential surplus could be strengthened if the first surpluses to appear were small -- less than $10 billion, for example.</p>
        <p>That would not be enough money to accommodate many big initiatives. And spending it could involve some political risk if revenue projections prove faulty. Who, after all, would want to be the politician to propose the tax cut or new program that would be blamed for taking this first surplus, a true political milestone, and spending it -- thus sending the Federal Government back into deficit?</p>
        <p>''With it being an election year,'' said Representative David M. McIntosh, an Indiana Republican who is promoting the elimination of the marriage penalty, ''people are not going to be willing to be the one who will say they had a balanced budget and threw it away.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
