<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deadly Maelstrom's Secrets Unveiled</title>
    <meta content="02EDDY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maelstroms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Whirlpools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Norway</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Norwegian Sea</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Oslo</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gjevik, Bjorn (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E0D91F31F931A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deadly Maelstrom's Secrets Unveiled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Deadly maelstrom off Norwegian coast, which has terrified sailors for centuries and inspired dramatic literary descriptions, has been precisely explained and charted by Dr Bjorn Gjevik and two of his mathematics students at University of Oslo; report in journal Nature says that, although there is no funnel-like whirlpool within maelstrom as imagined by writers, dangers of currents and winds between Ferroe and Loffoden islands are formidable, causing big vessels to skirt area even today; 17th-century illustration; map; Gjevik says strong currents and waves in opposite directions create steep, choppy and breaking waves (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''The maelstrom! Could a more dreadful situation have sounded in our ears! We were then upon the dangerous coast of Norway. . . .</p>
        <p>''We knew that at the tide the pent-up waters between the islands of Ferroe and Loffoden rush with irresistible violence, forming a whirlpool from which no vessel ever escapes . . .</p>
        <p>''There, not only vessels, but whales are sacrificed, as well as white bears from the polar regions.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''The maelstrom! Could a more dreadful situation have sounded in our ears! We were then upon the dangerous coast of Norway. . . .</p>
        <p>''We knew that at the tide the pent-up waters between the islands of Ferroe and Loffoden rush with irresistible violence, forming a whirlpool from which no vessel ever escapes . . .</p>
        <p>''There, not only vessels, but whales are sacrificed, as well as white bears from the polar regions.''</p>
        <p>THUS, in his 1870 classic ''Twenty Thousand Leagues Under the Sea,'' did Jules Verne describe the terrors of the vast maelstrom whirlpool charted by chroniclers since at least the 16th century.</p>
        <p>The popular fascination once inspired by voracious, whirling funnels of sea water has been supplanted in recent times by fascination with black holes, whose cosmic appetites are far grander than those of mere oceanic whirlpools. Moreover, it is known today that neither Norway's maelstrom nor any other oceanic eddy ever creates a whirling funnel of the kind imagined by Verne and many earlier writers.</p>
        <p>But although the menace of Norway's maelstrom was greatly exaggerated by such writers as Verne, Edgar Allan Poe, Herman Melville and others, the Moskstraumen, as the maelstrom is called in Norwegian, is real. Over many centuries it has claimed countless lives among the hapless mariners who ventured into it at dangerous times in the tidal cycle.</p>
        <p>Now Norwegian scientists have developed the first comprehensive mathematical model of currents and sea levels within the Norwegian maelstrom. The authors of the report, Dr. Bjorn Gjevik and two of his students in mathematics at the University of Oslo, Halvard Moe and Atle Ommundsen, concluded that although there is no funnel-like whirlpool within the maelstrom, the dangers posed by currents and winds in the region are formidable. Their research is reported in the current issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>The word maelstrom, a synonym in English for a tumult, literal or figurative, is believed to be derived from the Dutch word ''malen,'' to grind. An ancient legend has it that a pair of magical millstones were once dropped into the sea off the coast of Norway and that their eternal grinding of sea salt produces the lethal eddies of the maelstrom.</p>
        <p>In fact, Dr. Gjevik said in an interview, ''we found in our numerical simulation that in parts of the maelstrom during certain times in the tidal cycle, the speed of currents can reach up to 12 knots,'' or about 14 statute miles an hour. ''What makes it so dangerous,'' Dr. Gjevik said, ''is you get strong current-wave interaction. When the waves kicked up by the wind are opposite to the direction of the current, you get very steep and choppy waves, and breaking waves.''</p>
        <p>The horrifying conic eddy or funnel described by Poe in his 1841 short story ''A Descent into the Maelstrom'' could never exist, he said. ''But even though Poe never visited Norway, his description of the coastal landscape is otherwise astonishingly accurate.''</p>
        <p>In any case, 19th-century writers like Poe based their factual errors on old accounts handed down from the Vikings and their kin.</p>
        <p>''The old Norse people had another name for the maelstrom,'' Dr. Gjevik said. ''They called it the 'havsvelg,' which means 'hole in the ocean,' because they thought it was a bottomless opening into which the water flowed. Many have died there, and I have heard of several accidents myself, although I don't think there are records of the overall death toll.''</p>
        <p>Fortunately, the maelstrom has little effect on large vessels, partly because they avoid it -- the main route for coastal shipping lies well to the west of the evil Lofoten currents. The maelstrom's main victims are fishermen in small boats, Dr. Gjevik said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gjevik, who is an antiquarian scholar and amateur sailor as well as a professional mathematician, began developing the modeling tools he used for his maelstrom simulation more than a decade ago after oil was discovered in the Norwegian part of the North Sea. Oil companies needed exact information about the possibility that oil platforms could encounter destructive currents of the kind found in the maelstrom.</p>
        <p>''As it turned out,'' Dr. Gjevik said, ''oil was not found under or near the maelstrom, but we have refined the model and used it to study ocean current dynamics in the Barents Sea, the Arctic Ocean and other regions along Norway's coast and continental shelf. It has proved to be useful.''</p>
        <p>The treacherous currents in and near the maelstrom, he said, are driven by relatively huge tidal differences in the level of the open sea west of the Lofoten Island chain and that of relatively sheltered water between the islands and mainland Norwegian coast. Northward ocean currents created by tides force water into the Vestfjorden between the mainland and the island chain, raising the sea level in the Vestfjorden.</p>
        <p>''The difference in sea level over a distance of just six miles can be as much as some 20 inches,'' Dr. Gjevik said. As the high water east of the islands streams westward through coastal fjords and a labyrinth of small islands, it is broken up into many currents, some of which form strong eddies. Dr. Gjevik noted that the predictions of current flow made using his model had never before been possible in such detail.</p>
        <p>It is remarkable that very few scientific efforts have been made before now to probe the dynamics of the maelstrom, he said.</p>
        <p>The first written description of the maelstrom was probably that of Olaus Magnus, a Swedish bishop, in 1550. Petter Dass, a Norwegian priest, left a more detailed account in 1685, which correctly attributed the strength of the eddy to phases of the moon. Poe's description of the maelstrom derived from a fictitious account written in about 1715 by Jonas Ramus. But in this century, little has been written.</p>
        <p>''No substantial modern studies of this strong tidal current have been reported,'' Dr. Gjevik and his students wrote in the Nature article. ''The Norwegian Pilot Book provides some information, albeit of limited scientific value.'' It was to remedy this lack that the Oslo mathematical team developed its model.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gjevik, who owns a sailboat and said he ''grew up aboard boats,'' plans to make further measurements of the maelstrom to check details of his model. He acknowledges that the maelstrom is not a place many would choose to visit without a compelling reason.</p>
        <p>In Melville's novel ''Moby Dick,'' the fanatical Captain Ahab explains to his crew that the purpose of their voyage is to chase the malevolent white whale that severed the captain's leg.</p>
        <p>''Aye, aye,'' said Ahab, ''and I'll chase him around Good Hope, and round the Horn, and round the Norway Maelstrom, and round perdition's flames before I give him up.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
