<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Auto Makers Lobby to Stop New Air Quality Regulations</title>
    <meta content="29AUTO$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="940506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DD1E31F93AA15755C0A961958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Auto Makers Lobby to Stop New Air Quality Regulations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, June 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States auto makers are lobbying against Clinton Administration move to tighten metropolitan air quality standards and its backing for international limits on carbon dioxide emissions to counter global warming; fear moves will give foreign rivals competitive edge (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After five years of worrying that the Clinton Administration might tighten air quality regulations, the auto industry's fears have finally come true.</p>
        <p>President Clinton approved more stringent metropolitan air quality standards on Wednesday. A day later, in a more serious blow to the auto industry, the President declared that at an international conference next December in Kyoto, Japan, the United States would favor the adoption of binding limits on so-called greenhouse gases, which may contribute to global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After five years of worrying that the Clinton Administration might tighten air quality regulations, the auto industry's fears have finally come true.</p>
        <p>President Clinton approved more stringent metropolitan air quality standards on Wednesday. A day later, in a more serious blow to the auto industry, the President declared that at an international conference next December in Kyoto, Japan, the United States would favor the adoption of binding limits on so-called greenhouse gases, which may contribute to global warming.</p>
        <p>Auto industry officials had been fretting about both issues for months, and they have already begun lobbying Congress to block both Administration initiatives. International carbon dioxide limits are an unnecessarily drastic response to a global warming threat that has not yet been proved to exist, said Andrew H. Card Jr., president of the American Automobile Manufacturers Association, a Washington trade group representing Detroit's Big Three.</p>
        <p>The metropolitan air quality rules, he said, ''are ill-conceived, economically disadvantageous to the country and will put a particular burden on the auto industry and the people of Michigan.''</p>
        <p>Controls on the emissions of carbon dioxide, one of the greenhouse gases, represent a potentially dire threat to auto makers. Carbon dioxide is produced in large quantities when gasoline is burned in an internal combustion engine. Reducing carbon dioxide emissions means improving fuel economy or reducing the number of cars on the road.</p>
        <p>Detroit auto makers in particular are already struggling to meet existing fuel economy standards as they sell ever more Jeeps and other gas-guzzling sport utility vehicles. Tighter standards could severely crimp profits.</p>
        <p>Auto industry executives have been downright caustic in recent speeches about the possibility of carbon dioxide limits. ''This sort of fuzzy thinking provides the warm illusion of saving the sky, which we're not even sure needs saving, but it won't have any impact at all on global warming,'' said Robert J. Eaton, the chairman and chief executive of the Chrysler Corporation. ''It will just move jobs to those countries which are allowed to spew whatever they want into the air.''</p>
        <p>President Clinton chose on Thursday not to impose immediate carbon dioxide limits, but auto executives had never expected that he would do so and were not impressed. The main goal of industry lobbying has been to make sure that any carbon dioxide limits negotiated in Kyoto were voluntary, not binding. Detroit executives are convinced that only the United States would actually obey binding limits while other countries would flout them.</p>
        <p>Auto makers have tried to market vehicles that can burn natural gas or alcohol or run on electric power from batteries. But demand has been remarkably weak, with Federal, state and local agencies often ignoring laws designed to force them to buy alternative-fuel vehicles.</p>
        <p>Ford, the main producer of such vehicles, announced on Friday that it would broaden its lineup to 11 models this autumn, including several that burn ethanol, a type of alcohol. Yet Ford had combined sales of just 8,461 alternative-fuel vehicles across five model lines last year.</p>
        <p>Behind the dismay in Detroit about the latest Administration moves lies a very real worry at General Motors, Ford and Chrysler that they will be put at a competitive disadvantage,  against their foreign-company rivals. Ford and particularly Chrysler already produce more sport utility vehicles, mini-vans and pickup trucks than cars. But cars tend to be much more fuel-efficient and therefore produce less carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>G.M. will be producing more so-called light trucks than cars within several years, while most foreign auto makers overwhelmingly make cars and will continue doing so.</p>
        <p>The metropolitan air quality standards could also hurt Detroit's Big Three. While the Big Three still have many of their factories in big Midwestern cities with pollution problems, Japanese and European auto makers have chosen to build their newer assembly plants in small Southern towns. Though these choices of factory sites were mainly aimed at forestalling unionization, the sites also tend to have clean air that is likely to meet the more stringent standards without any extra spending by the foreign auto makers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
