<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chemists Find Ways to Save Monuments From Pollution</title>
    <meta content="18STON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="973918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marble</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Limestone</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coates, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DC1138F93BA25752C1A961958260" item-length="1665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chemists Find Ways to Save Monuments From Pollution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE COATES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Coates, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers are coming up with new kinds of protective chemicals that adhere better to limestone and marble to help save world's decomposing monuments from acid rain and other effects of airborne pollution; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT if there was a way to rescue decomposed stone, particularly the marble and limestone that make up some of the world's best-loved monuments? Many of them, like the Parthenon, the Taj Mahal and even the Lincoln Memorial, have long been threatened by acid rain and other effects of airborne pollution.</p>
        <p>In fact, liquid chemical compounds that essentially glue weakened stone surfaces together have been around for years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT if there was a way to rescue decomposed stone, particularly the marble and limestone that make up some of the world's best-loved monuments? Many of them, like the Parthenon, the Taj Mahal and even the Lincoln Memorial, have long been threatened by acid rain and other effects of airborne pollution.</p>
        <p>In fact, liquid chemical compounds that essentially glue weakened stone surfaces together have been around for years.</p>
        <p>By many measures, these consolidants are impressive, but they also have many drawbacks. So researchers in the United States and Europe are continually looking for ways to improve them. Some promising work at Sandia National Laboratories in  Albuquerque, N.M., on ways to make consolidants adhere better to limestone and marble has recently received considerable attention.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, other researchers are studying how consolidants work long term, a major area of concern. Last month, for example, Minnesota approved a three-  to five-year study of the State Capitol in St. Paul, an important Cass Gilbert edifice opened in 1905, where consolidants were applied to the magnificent marble dome in 1989. Glenn Boornazian, an architectural conservator with Integrated Conservation Resources in Manhattan, said the tests would be among the first to involve extensive research specifically into the effects reapplication might have on the stone.</p>
        <p>Modern consolidants were developed in the 1960's, spurred by the widespread damage to stone buildings in Venice in a decade of flooding.  Since then, these chemicals have been used as a last-ditch defense against surface loss in a range of  architectural and artistic restoration projects, from the Washington  Square Arch in Manhattan to the medieval sculptures of the Church of St. Trophime in Arles, France.</p>
        <p>'You're asking a person not only to glue stone back together and stabilize it for the next 50 years, but you're telling them to do it so the stone still breathes,'' Mr. Boornazian said. ''It's a near-impossible feat, but this material comes very close to doing it.''</p>
        <p>But consolidants, which chemists and conservators say are still far from being a magic potion, have many limitations. They are toxic and difficult to apply. Their preservative effects, particularly on calcium carbonate stones -- limestone and marble -- are only temporary, and they permanently alter the nature of the stone. Most important, their long-term effects are uncertain. For these reasons, their use is banned on the Acropolis in Athens.</p>
        <p>The difficulties have led some experts to conclude that efforts should concentrate on preventing damage rather than repairing it. Others say the problems make the effort to improve consolidants more pressing.</p>
        <p>Many chemists and conservators expect a satisfactory consolidant for limestone and marble to remain elusive. It is not so much a failure of science, they say, as an illustration of the immense complexity of stone and the processes of its deterioration.</p>
        <p>''There are so many variables in stone deterioration that chaos theory really offers the only way to see the interreaction of them all,'' said Dr. Victor Mossotti, a geochemist with  the United States Geological Survey  in Menlo Park, Calif.</p>
        <p>For starters, Dr. Mossotti said that alarm over the acid damage from pollution had overshadowed a range of other important problems. It has often been pointed out that rainwater is naturally slightly acidic, he said, but even if it were not, marble and limestone are soluble in pure water. Dr. Mossotti said plain water, particularly flowing water, was probably the biggest single factor in architectural erosion.</p>
        <p>Water runoff also tends to deposit soot, fly ash, dust, bird droppings and associated biological growth in patterns over the surface of a building, where it can in turn absorb moisture and keep it on the stone. In addition to dissolving the stone, that moisture can become part of a freeze-thaw cycle that damages the surface and exposes it to further penetration.</p>
        <p>''We have to respond to a range of stone damage, not just from building to building but from stone to stone within a single building,'' said John Stubbs, director of programs for the World Monuments Fund, a preservation group. A good example, he said, is the Church of St. Ann and the Holy Trinity, a World Monuments Fund project in Brooklyn Heights. Conservators' block-by-block drawings for the current restoration of the 1844 brownstone church show a wide variety of stone pathologies arrayed in discernible patterns across the facade, among them spalling (the catastrophic loss of layers), flaking, biological damage and various degrees of soiling and pollution damage.</p>
        <p>Despite the limitations of consolidants, the 12th-century Primatial Church of St. Trophime in Arles, another recent World Monuments Fund project, shows how valuable these materials can be. By the end of the 1980's, pollution from cars and a local paper mill had caused a tough, black gypsum crust -- a product of the reaction between acid from pollution and the calcium carbonate in limestone or marble -- to build up on the important limestone sculptures of the building's main portal.</p>
        <p>''That crust was over a quarter of an inch in some places,'' said Mr. Boornazian, who was a consultant on the project. ''There were places that it had fallen off, and you could see that the crust itself had the details of the carving in it, but when the crust fell off, the details weren't there.''</p>
        <p>The stone underneath the gypsum was so soft that even cleaning off the crust would have irreparably damaged the sculpture, Mr. Boornazian said, so the consolidant -- which is liquid in form, with an appearance like rubbing alcohol, and is usually brushed or sprayed on -- was injected through the crust first.</p>
        <p>Consolidants work at St. Trophime and elsewhere by substituting for a crucial element of the structure of healthy stone. Most stone is made up of coarse particles held together by a network of softer binding material, which is particularly susceptible to erosion. In limestone, both binder and particles are calcium carbonate. (In marble, the grains are so tightly packed that there is really not a binder; the calcium carbonate particles fit together like pieces of a jigsaw puzzle, and erosion breaks the tabs on the pieces.)</p>
        <p>One expert on consolidants, Dr. George Wheeler, a research chemist at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in Manhattan, said there were two main kinds: organic polymers, like acrylics and epoxies, and compounds known as alkoxysilanes. All act as artificial binders, taking up the space between the loose grains and gluing them back together.</p>
        <p>Besides binding ability, a crucial virtue of consolidants is that they allow the stone to ''breathe'' water vapor. Otherwise, cycles of freezing and thawing by water trapped inside would do great damage.</p>
        <p>Because organic polymers break down in sunlight, Dr. Wheeler said, the alkoxysilanes are more common for outdoor use. Alkoxysilanes were actually designed to work by chemically bonding to silicate stone like sandstone, on which they are quite effective, conservators say. But because of a chemical incompatibility with limestone and marble, they do not adhere well to those stones and have to be reapplied every few years.</p>
        <p>What some conservators see as a promising project at Sandia National Laboratories aims to ease that problem. Kathryn Nagy, a geochemist who worked on the project, said researchers had developed a consolidant consisting of two layers. The first layer contains amine groups that bond well to the stone. It also has an inorganic silane ''tail,'' a molecule that bonds in turn to the second layer, made up of an ordinary alkoxysilane consolidant.</p>
        <p>But beyond the immediate problem of adhesion, the way consolidants function as a substitute binder is enough to suggest an array of things that could go wrong, said Kate Burns Ottavino, director of preservation at the A. Ottavino Corporation, a conservation and building firm in Queens. ''Will they be equally as permeable as the binding they replace?'' she asked. ''Will they expand and contract at a comparable rate? Do they absorb the same amount of water? How do micro-organisms react with them? Any of these factors could involve negative consequences.''</p>
        <p>To match stone with the right consolidant, tests are typically done on the before it is consolidated to measure water, acid and salt absorption; porosity; vapor transmission, and solubility. It is particularly important to test the depth of penetration of a consolidant, which needs to infiltrate through the deteriorated layer to bind with healthy stone. Otherwise, the consolidated surface is likely to delaminate, or peel away in sheets. Yet there are no established standards for applying the test results in choosing a consolidant or in deciding whether to use one at all.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty much been up to the judgment of the individual conservator,'' said Dr. David Wessel, a conservator with the Architectural Resources Group in San Francisco. Dr. Wessel, who said there were some concerns that consolidants were sometimes used unnecessarily, is helping to produce application guidelines for the American Society for Testing and Materials.</p>
        <p>The biggest concern of many preservationists is that despite accelerated weathering tests, the long-term effects of consolidants in the real environment are hard to predict. Ms. Ottavino said one of the most promising developments of stone preservation today was that advanced tests were increasingly being brought to bear on stone that has been consolidated and then weathered.</p>
        <p>''The verdict isn't in on what happens when you keep reapplying alkoxysilanes,'' Mr. Boornazian said. ''If you do that every decade, does it start to become a vapor barrier after, say, 50 or 70 years?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
