<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evidence Backs Theory Linking Origins of Life to Volcanoes</title>
    <meta content="11VENT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="922033"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huber, Claudia (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wachtershauser, Gunter (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volcanoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Evolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E2D8103CF932A25757C0A961958260" item-length="1355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evidence Backs Theory Linking Origins of Life to Volcanoes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Nicholas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Theory that life on earth began around volcano, perhaps at deep-sea vents where molten lava boils through ocean floor, has been bolstered by chemical reconstruction of essential step in metabolism of living cells; latest effort to reconstruct these natural chemical reactions, subject known as prebiotic chemistry, has been made by Dr Claudia Huber and Gunter Wachtershauser of Munich, Germany (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The theory that life on earth began around a volcano, perhaps at the deep-sea vents where molten lava boils through the ocean floor, has been bolstered by the chemical reconstruction of an essential step in the metabolism of living cells.</p>
        <p>If the new finding is correct, it means that the recipe for creating life on a newborn planet consists of mostly lethal ingredients and would read something like this: Drop a handful of fool's gold (the mineral iron pyrites) and a sprinkle of nickel into water, stir in a strong whiff of rotten eggs (caused by the gas hydrogen sulfide) and carbon monoxide, heat mixture near the crackle and hiss of a volcano and let simmer for an eon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The theory that life on earth began around a volcano, perhaps at the deep-sea vents where molten lava boils through the ocean floor, has been bolstered by the chemical reconstruction of an essential step in the metabolism of living cells.</p>
        <p>If the new finding is correct, it means that the recipe for creating life on a newborn planet consists of mostly lethal ingredients and would read something like this: Drop a handful of fool's gold (the mineral iron pyrites) and a sprinkle of nickel into water, stir in a strong whiff of rotten eggs (caused by the gas hydrogen sulfide) and carbon monoxide, heat mixture near the crackle and hiss of a volcano and let simmer for an eon.</p>
        <p>Some kind of natural chemical reactions presumably preceded the emergence of the first living cells some time before 3.5 billion years ago.</p>
        <p>But the nature of these reactions, a subject known as prebiotic chemistry, has become a matter of dispute as the textbook theory, developed by Dr. Stanley L. Miller of the University of California at San Diego, has come under challenge.</p>
        <p>The latest effort to reconstruct prebiotic chemistry has been made by Dr. Claudia Huber of the Technical University of Munich and Dr. Gunter Wachtershauser, also of Munich. Dr. Wachtershauser is a Ph.D. chemist who works as a patent lawyer but is respected among chemists who study the origin of life. Their article appears in today's issue of the journal Science.</p>
        <p>Dr. Christian de Duve, a biochemist and Nobel Prize winner who has written on the origin of life, said Dr. Wachtershauser's new work was ''an extremely interesting finding which fits with the idea that life may have originated in a volcanic setting.''</p>
        <p>''It stresses the importance of sulfur and iron, which again fits with what we know from biochemistry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert H. Crabtree, a Yale University expert on metals and chemical change, said it was tough to imagine that anyone would discover exactly how life started ''but nevertheless this is an important contribution'' and one that ''could come to be seen as comparable'' with Dr. Miller's if it should prove correct.</p>
        <p>There is a growing belief among some microbiologists that the locale for the origin of life was not tidal pools and lightning strikes, as implied in Dr. Miller's view, but in deep vents or other geothermal sources. ''We are seeing a miniparadigm shift,'' said Dr. Norman R. Pace, a microbiologist at the University of California at Berkeley. ''It's a field-wide split and Wachtershauser has certainly been a driver.''</p>
        <p>The classic experiment performed by Dr. Miller when he was a graduate student in 1953 seemed to solve the scientific problem of how life began, at least in broad outline. He took some water to represent the ocean, the gases methane, ammonia and hydrogen to represent the early earth's atmosphere and sent electric sparks through the mixture to simulate lightning strikes. After several days he found that many organic chemicals typical of living cells, including amino acids, the building blocks of proteins, had formed within the concoction. It seemed only a matter of time for chemists to figure out how the building blocks might have combined naturally into the complex molecules of life.</p>
        <p>But taking the next steps beyond Dr. Miller's brilliant beginning proved much harder than expected. One reason is that geologists changed their minds about the composition of the earth's early atmosphere. They now think it consisted largely of carbon dioxide and nitrogen, a far less reactive mixture than Dr. Miller used.</p>
        <p>''I would call the conventional origin of life chemistry as being at a dead end,'' said Dr. Carl R. Woese, a microbiologist at the University of Illinois.</p>
        <p>It was Dr. Woese who discovered that all living creatures belong to three very ancient lineages, bacteria, eukarya and archaea.</p>
        <p>Eukarya is the kingdom to which all plants and animals belong. The archaea, single-celled organisms confused with bacteria until Dr. Woese's discovery, are of interest to biologists studying the origin of life because they have certain primitive features and a liking for extreme environments, like the boiling springs of Yellowstone National Park and the superheated waters that swirl from deep-sea volcanoes.</p>
        <p>Deep-sea vents, first directly observed only 20 years ago, have become of increasing interest as a possible origin of the planet's life. These underwater volcanoes, or black smokers, are home to a strange array of creatures found nowhere else, as well as to many species of archaea. The vents spew out superheated water laden with a black cloud of chemicals, including carbon monoxide, hydrogen sulfide and various metal sulfides.</p>
        <p>These are the chemicals that have been studied by Dr. Wachtershauser, whose theory is that many reactions important to the origin of life took place on the surface of ferrous sulfide, fool's gold. In his latest experiment he has shown that with a slurry of ferrous and nickel sulfides to help the reaction, the gases known to be present in black smokers will form acetic acid and an activated form of acetic acid known as a thio ester.</p>
        <p>The synthesis of these chemicals is striking to biochemists because it demonstrates a natural way of chaining carbon atoms together, the basis of the living cell's chemical repertoire. The thio esters are also akin to a vital component, known as acetyl coenzyme A, of the energy metabolism pathway known as the citric acid cycle.</p>
        <p>Dr. Woese is enthusiastic about Dr. Wachtershauser's work, saying, ''His theory in my opinion is the only game in town because it is predictive and therefore testable.''</p>
        <p>He emphasized the theory's implication that the first forms of life created their own vital chemicals instead of sucking them in from the outside, as implied in the Miller version.</p>
        <p>Dr. de Duve, from his knowledge of biochemistry, has long believed that a sulfur-based chemistry involving thio esters was the probable basis from which the RNA world arose. The RNA world is the concept that ribonucleic acid, or RNA, which still plays many essential roles in living cells, was the predecessor of DNA as the repository of hereditary information.</p>
        <p>Iron-sulfur clusters exist at the center of many important enzymes, Dr. Pace noted.</p>
        <p>''They are fundamental biology and were invented back in the very early days,'' he said. ''Wachtershauser has dreamed up a number of wonderful iron-sulfur chemistries that could be involved.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Pace believes that the primary biochemistry of life was acquired in a geothermal sludge before the invention of the cell membrane. ''It wasn't cells crawling out of that sludge, it was something deeper,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. de Duve, who has joint appointments at Rockefeller University in New York and the University of Louvain in Belgium, said from his home in Belgium that Dr. Wachtershauser ''disagrees with Stanley Miller and vice versa'' but that there were likely to be important elements of truth in both theories.</p>
        <p>Dr. Wachtershauser said that as an amateur he had held off publishing his theory for fear of being ridiculed but was encouraged by the late philosopher Karl Popper and others to go ahead. The ''soup theory,'' he said in reference to Dr. Miller's version of the origin of life, had produced only inactive chemicals whereas his own theory, based on the idea of chemicals being held on a two-dimensional surface, showed how a basic metabolic cycle could start and be maintained.</p>
        <p>''Once I had published,'' Dr. Wachtershauser said, ''I was received with open arms.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Miller did not respond to a telephone message seeking comment.</p>
        <p>While not accepting the whole system, Dr. de Duve said Dr. Wachtershauser's latest results agreed with the general hypothesis ''that life may have originated in a hot, deep sea environment rich in sulfur.''</p>
        <p>If so, such a dark, hellish cradle would be a considerable elaboration on the ''warm little pond'' in which Darwin, in an often-quoted letter, suggested that life began.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
