<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967291"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1DA133EF930A15753C1A961958260" item-length="1385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Pol Pot Defends Record During Rare Interview  ''My conscience is clear,'' declared Pol Pot in the first interview he has given since early 1979. Claims that millions had died in Cambodia at the hands of the Khmer Rouge in the 1970's were exaggerated, he said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Weapons Destroyed in Balkans  Some 4,220 tanks, jets, helicopters and artillery pieces belonging to the various Balkan nations have been destroyed in the last 16 months, according to the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe. Officials at the organization would not discuss specific numbers, but noted that the demolition has been carried out by Yugoslavia, Croatia, the Bosnian Serbs and the federation of Bosnian Muslims and Croats, in accordance with a treaty those governments signed in June 1996.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-13</p>
        <p>Pol Pot Defends Record During Rare Interview  ''My conscience is clear,'' declared Pol Pot in the first interview he has given since early 1979. Claims that millions had died in Cambodia at the hands of the Khmer Rouge in the 1970's were exaggerated, he said.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Weapons Destroyed in Balkans  Some 4,220 tanks, jets, helicopters and artillery pieces belonging to the various Balkan nations have been destroyed in the last 16 months, according to the Organization for Security and Cooperation in Europe. Officials at the organization would not discuss specific numbers, but noted that the demolition has been carried out by Yugoslavia, Croatia, the Bosnian Serbs and the federation of Bosnian Muslims and Croats, in accordance with a treaty those governments signed in June 1996.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Rotavirus Vaccine Developed  A study done in Venezuela showed that a vaccine against the rotavirus, an infection that kills hundreds of thousands of children around the world each year, works effectively in developing countries. Studies had already shown the vaccine to be highly effective in developed nations. Rotavirus is the leading cause of severe diarrhea in childhood.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Turkish Police Avoid Court  Police officers accused of torturing 14 young people in Turkey refused to obey a court order that they appear and face their accusers. The three-judge panel handling the case lifted the order after lawyers for the officers argued that if they were forced to appear, their anti-terrorist work would be compromised.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>Mandela Visits Libyan Leader  President Nelson Mandela of South Africa hugged Col. Muammar el-Qaddafi upon arriving in Tripoli to visit the Libyan leader. No Western leader has visited the North African country since sanctions were imposed by the United Nations in 1992 after Colonel Qaddafi refused to turn over suspects in the 1988 bombing of Pan Am Flight 103 over Scotland. Mr. Mandela warmly recalled Colonel Qaddafi's early support of the struggle against apartheid.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Hamas Leader Calls for Jihad  Sheik Ahmad Yassin, the guiding symbol of the militant Islamic movement Hamas, vowed not to abandon holy war against Israel, proclaiming that ''a nation that does not wage jihad cannot exist.'' The sheik, nearly blind and deaf, was released from an Israeli prison three weeks ago in exchange for two Israeli special agents who were captured in Jordan after botching an attempt to kill another Hamas leader.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Iraqi Sanctions Bid Fails  The United States lost its battle to impose new sanctions on Iraq for continuing to obstruct the inspection and monitoring of its weapons programs and stock. France, Russia, China, Egypt and Kenya voted against imposing an international travel ban on high Iraqi military and intelligence officials.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-24</p>
        <p>Presidential Advisory Panel Backs Rights for Patients  A Presidential advisory commission decided to recommend a wide range of new rights for patients, including the right to appeal denials of care or coverage by insurance companies and health maintenance organizations. The panel also said that health plans, doctors and hospitals should be required to disclose substantial amounts of new information and data that could help patients assess the quality and experience of health care providers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Unveils Climate Plan  President Clinton outlined a moderate program to fight global warming, saying that it would be painless and even economically beneficial but that it must be put into effect quickly to be effective. The plan would rely on tax credits and research subsidies to spur conservation of energy in the next few years and would give American companies extra credit for moving more quickly than required to cut emissions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Laborers' Union Faces Scrutiny  A former Federal prosecutor hired to clean up the laborers' union plans to bring internal charges to oust the union's president, Arthur A. Coia, for associating with members of organized crime, officials said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Child Care Conference Opens  Hillary Rodham Clinton convenes a White House conference today to highlight what she and the President see as an urgent need for safe, affordable child care. But conservative Republicans say the conference will lay the groundwork for increased Government spending or regulation.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Women Plan Philadelphia Rally  Two years after hundreds of thousands of men came to Washington for a day of speeches and prayers at the Million Man March, a large group of women is expected in Philadelphia on Saturday for what is being billed as the Million Woman March, although local officials are planning for about 500,000.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Houses Passes I.R.S. Bill  The House Ways and Means Committee overwhelmingly passed legislation intended to bring sweeping changes to the Internal Revenue Service, with members of both parties saying the bill would protect taxpayers and impose new management standards.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Drug May Aid Smokers  An antidepressant drug can help people quit smoking, even those who are not depressed and would not normally take such a medication, researchers say.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>I.B.M. to Underwrite Schools  Louis V. Gerstner Jr., the chief executive of I.B.M., will announce today that the company is awarding $10 million in grants to a dozen school districts and state education departments, including those of New York City and New York State, to develop new ways to employ technology in the classroom.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Trade Center Suspect Expected Many Casualties  A Secret Secret agent testified that Ramzi Ahmed Yousef, charged with masterminding the World Trade Center bombing in 1993, had hoped that the blast would topple one of the center's towers and kill tens of thousands of people. The agent's testimony was based on six hours of conversations he said he and a colleague had with Mr. Yousef after his arrest in 1995. The blast killed six people and injured more than 1,000.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Messinger Lacks Party Support  Ruth W. Messinger, in the final days of her race against Mayor Giuliani, has had to contend with little support from leading Democrats across the city and state and the unwillingness of many of them to actively campaign with her as she tries to unseat a popular Republican mayor.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>D27</p>
        <p>Harold J. Rothwax  A judge who began his legal career as a combative defense lawyer and civil rights advocate in New York but who later gained wide attention in a campaign to limit the rights of defendants, he was 67.</p>
        <p>D27</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-18</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27  Editorials: The President bets on technology; a pivotal vote on campaign reform; dangerous sparks in Kosovo; failing to protect children.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman, Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-26</p>
        <p>Off and On Cigarette Planned  The Philip Morris Companies is planning to test a microelectronic cigarette holder that eliminates both the smoke from the end of a cigarette and ashes, while reducing the danger of fires. The battery-powered ''smoking system,'' tentatively called Accord, is the first of its kind, and cost $200 million to develop after years of research. The tobacco burns only when puffed; smokers could take a puff from a cigarette in its holder, put it down and take another puff an hour later. Critics say the new product demonstrates the lengths to which the tobacco industry will go to make a dangerous addiction more socially acceptable.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hong Kong Stocks Plummet  The financial forces wreaking havoc across Southeast Asia have turned on Hong Kong, hammering stocks down more than 23 percent this month and putting pressure on the Hong Kong dollar, the last currency in the region to have escaped devaluation.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Production Delays at Boeing  The Boeing Company stunned Wall Street by announcing that unexpected production delays in the booming market for its commercial planes will cost $2.6 billion and erase a good portion of the company's profits.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8</p>
        <p>Chronicle</p>
        <p>B16</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>C8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
