<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; State of the Union</title>
    <meta content="17SAFI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="981054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">State of the Union Message (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safire, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/William Safire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">State of the Union Message (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E5DB123FF934A25751C1A961958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; State of the Union</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Safire, William</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Safire column predicts that Pres Clinton's State of the Union address in January will probably focus on work and the family as twin platforms for an array of federally directed domestic largess; says Clinton's foreign-policy initiative will probably be a call for treaties on biological and chemical weapons that do not provide needed inspections of suspect states (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I wandered over to the White House the other day to find out what President Clinton is going to propose in 1998. The State of the Union address in January imposes a deadline on policy makers; if his agenda is to have any philosophical shape, the speechwriters need guidance fairly soon on themes and specifics.</p>
        <p>Despite his failure to prepare the ground in yesterday's marathon news conference, next month's message will try to establish two domestic platforms for government activism: work and family.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I wandered over to the White House the other day to find out what President Clinton is going to propose in 1998. The State of the Union address in January imposes a deadline on policy makers; if his agenda is to have any philosophical shape, the speechwriters need guidance fairly soon on themes and specifics.</p>
        <p>Despite his failure to prepare the ground in yesterday's marathon news conference, next month's message will try to establish two domestic platforms for government activism: work and family.</p>
        <p>Work? Aren't we at full employment already? Yes, but the Clinton approach is to use a worker's lifetime series of jobs as a launch pad  for an array of federally directed benefits.</p>
        <p>Examples of using the work platform include expanding employer-paid health-care and retirement benefits, and making them more portable for workers who keep moving on. He wants to channel money into community colleges to help workers upgrade skills or new workers get training. How financed? By block grants to the states (we used to call it revenue-sharing) or by tax incentives to businesses (an indirect Federal subsidy).</p>
        <p>On the family platform, beyond inveighing against tobacco, his focus will be on subsidizing health care of more children and on close monitoring of H.M.O.'s. His centerpiece will be public support of preschool supervision of the children of working parents, as thoroughly previewed by Robert Pear in last Sunday's New York Times, changing the name of ''day care'' to the harder-to-argue-with ''child care.'' Care-givers will get scholarships along with criminal-record checks.</p>
        <p>The family focus will embrace Federal support of consumerism, as well as the use of the bully pulpit in discouraging ''social promotion'' -- the tendency of elementary schools to give passing grades to failing students, which undercuts opportunity to compete for college entrance.</p>
        <p>This can be packaged thematically not as entitlement but as enablement, advancing the American dream of equal opportunity. Clinton appears ready to trade away his desire for national standards -- too obvious a centralization of power --  for the Federal money to finance local programs. If the President, in a setting of an address to the Congress in joint session, can place his proposals in a context of greater personal responsibility and community spirit, he will be doing what we expect Presidents to do.</p>
        <p>Instead of dismissing all this as ''dead on arrival,'' Republican leaders would do well to give his goals  consideration and come up with a serious State of the Opposition. The G.O.P.'s counter-theme is empowerment of the individual, which includes allowing each of us to spend and save more of what we earn -- and better generates the resources to care for those Ronald Reagan used to call the ''truly needy.''</p>
        <p>If Clinton can dispense with his overworked bridgework and fatuous futurism, and if he can present a philosophically coherent set of proposals instead of a laundry list of largess, his message would have to be taken seriously -- and responded to with more than sniping. That's not easy. He hasn't done it yet. He should give it a shot.</p>
        <p>On the foreign side of the coming speech, I wish he and his advisers had the energy and the world view to produce a persuasive State of the World report. Clinton has yet to reconcile his free-market attitude toward global competition with his slavish obeisance to global warming.</p>
        <p>If he dared break with his party's past, this President could surprise the world and his compatriots with a new look at space-based missile defense, in the light of oncoming biological weapon threats. Instead, brace yourself for Clinton's call for a biological weapons treaty, following the chemical one, relying on the kindness of strangers rather than a deployable anti-missile shield and intrusive inspections of suspect states.</p>
        <p>Perhaps he will rise to the occasion and put together a document that is partisan without being petty. Although next year may expose and punish the seamy side of Clintonism, there's still a country to run.</p>
        <p>In the hallway a few yards from the Oval Office, I spotted a character loosely based on Al Gore pass by. He seems as resilient as Clinton. They and the Union can roll with the punches.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
