<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="22OBSE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071657"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrous Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rivers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">south platte river</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asteroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rivers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radiation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bacteria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDB153CF931A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="611" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study of South Platte River finds that it gives off large amounts of nitrous oxide, a gas that acts as a catalyst in destruction of ozone in atmosphere; drawing...Scientists find evidence of an asteroid or comet impact in southeastern Argentina some 3.3 million years ago; say it may have caused local extinctions...Australian researchers report that bacteria must compete for nutrients in the ocean (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pollution Runs Through It</p>
        <p>A river is like a highway, flowing through the landscape. Unfortunately, according to a new study, it is also like a car, polluting the air as it rolls along.</p>
        <p>Scientists from the United States Geological Survey, in a study of the South Platte River in Nebraska and Colorado, determined that the river gives off large amounts of nitrous oxide, a gas that acts as a catalyst in the destruction of ozone in the atmosphere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pollution Runs Through It</p>
        <p>A river is like a highway, flowing through the landscape. Unfortunately, according to a new study, it is also like a car, polluting the air as it rolls along.</p>
        <p>Scientists from the United States Geological Survey, in a study of the South Platte River in Nebraska and Colorado, determined that the river gives off large amounts of nitrous oxide, a gas that acts as a catalyst in the destruction of ozone in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Like many rivers, the South Platte is rich in nitrates and ammonium, from agricultural runoff and the discharges from sewage treatment plants.</p>
        <p>Microbes turn these nitrogen sources into nitrous oxide. The researchers, whose work was published in the Internet edition of Environmental Science and Technology, found that the river in many places was supersaturated in nitrous oxide, with the result that much of it entered the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>The scientists estimated that the amount of the gas emitted along a 450-mile stretch of the river each year was equivalent to that produced by all the worst sewage treatment plants in the United States.</p>
        <p>And although they said more studies were needed, they added that if the South Platte is typical, as seems likely, rivers are a major source of man-made nitrous oxide pollution.</p>
        <p>Death From Above, Again</p>
        <p>The dinosaurs became extinct, so the common theory holds, when a large asteroid or comet struck the Earth near the Yucatan 65 million years ago, drastically altering weather patterns worldwide.</p>
        <p>Now, scientists led by a geologist from Brown University have discovered evidence in South America of a lesser, and far more recent, impact that they suspect caused local extinctions.</p>
        <p>The scientists studied glass fragments in sedimentary deposits on coastal cliffs in southeastern Argentina.</p>
        <p>The fragments, known as escorias, were first described in 1865, but their origin had never been satisfactorily explained.</p>
        <p>Writing in the journal Science, the scientists theorize that the escorias were formed by the impact of an asteroid or comet, the intense heat of the event fusing the sediment into glass. By dating the fragments, which are found over a distance of 20 miles, the researchers determined that the impact occurred 3.3 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Just above the level of the glass is another level of sediment that is notable for the absence of about three dozen species of animals that are present in older deposits.</p>
        <p>The scientists theorize that the impact caused enough of a climate change in the region to wipe out those animals.</p>
        <p>Fighting for a Bite</p>
        <p>Life is a rat race -- even for bacteria.</p>
        <p>Consider feeding, for example, or more specifically, how bacteria in seawater get nutrients. One might  think that the ocean is a homogeneous soup, with nutrients equally available to all. In this view, bacteria would not have to compete for food.</p>
        <p>But a study by scientists in Denmark and Australia shows that this is not the case. Food often becomes available at a distinct source, as when a protozoan excretes organic matter. The nutrients then quickly spread out into a tiny, spherical ''patch.'' The researchers, reporting in the journal Science, found that this sets off a microscopic feeding frenzy, with bacteria clustering around the patch for a few minutes and then dispersing.</p>
        <p>So feeding, rather than being a passive activity, becomes a competitive one. And the study showed that, for patches over a certain size, bacteria that can move toward nutrients or other chemicals (known as chemotactic bacteria) have a distinct advantage over those that cannot.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
