<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Urges Latin America to 'Be Patient' on Free Trade</title>
    <meta content="Y17PREX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1010315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Free Ports and Trading Zones</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chile</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frei, Eduardo (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Chile</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Ports and Trading Zones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E1D9153CF934A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Urges Latin America to 'Be Patient' on Free Trade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <dateline>SANTIAGO, Chile, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton pleads with leaders of Latin America to be patient with United States as it conducts a painful internal political debate over merits of free trade throughout hemisphere, speech, Santiago, Chile; Clinton is in Chile for Latin American summit meeting dedicated to creating hemispheric duty-free shop from Yukon to Tierra del Fuego; Clinton photo with Chilean Pres Eduardo Frei (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton pleaded with the leaders of Latin America today to be patient with the United States as it conducts a painful internal political debate over the merits of free trade throughout the hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, in Chile for a Latin American summit meeting dedicated to creating a hemispheric duty-free shop from the Yukon to Tierra del Fuego, felt compelled to explain Congress's refusal last fall to grant him unlimited trade negotiation authority, known as ''fast track.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton pleaded with the leaders of Latin America today to be patient with the United States as it conducts a painful internal political debate over the merits of free trade throughout the hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, in Chile for a Latin American summit meeting dedicated to creating a hemispheric duty-free shop from the Yukon to Tierra del Fuego, felt compelled to explain Congress's refusal last fall to grant him unlimited trade negotiation authority, known as ''fast track.''</p>
        <p>In a speech to an international business audience here today, Mr. Clinton acknowledged that he had so far failed to persuade a majority in  Congress of the benefits of free trade with the other nations of the hemisphere. The United States currently has a free-trade pact with Mexico and Canada.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said that ultimately the United States would not walk away from the ''colossal opportunity'' presented by the so-called Free Trade Area of the Americas, which is supposed to be in place by 2005.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton quoted Winston Churchill, who said, ''The United States invariably does the right thing, after having exhausted every other alternative.''</p>
        <p>The President said: ''So be patient with us. So just stay with us. We'll get there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's remarks set the tone for this visit, which American officials said marks a maturation of the United States' relations with its neighbors, which have veered over the decades from military intervention to not-always-benign neglect. By opening the trip with an explanation and implied apology, Mr. Clinton hoped to establish a dialogue of equals, officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said he would continue to press for approval of fast-track authority, under which Congress can approve or reject proposed trade treaties negotiated by Mr. Clinton, but cannot amend them. The Presidential authority is considered crucial to achieve trade breakthroughs because other countries will be reluctant to negotiate trade deals with the United States if they feel Congress will change the terms after an agreement is reached.</p>
        <p>A bill granting Mr. Clinton fast-track authority was withdrawn last November after Democrats in Congress said they were not persuaded that the trade deals the President is proposing would provide adequate protection for workers and the environment.</p>
        <p>The start of the complex seven-year trade negotiations is the centerpiece of the President's four-day visit to Chile.</p>
        <p>The first two days of the trip are dedicated to a state visit to Chile and talks with President Eduardo Frei. This weekend, 34 of the 35 countries of the hemisphere, with the exception of Cuba, which was not invited, will convene in a hemispheric summit meeting to celebrate the spread of democracy and an era of exceptional economic expansion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and Mr. Frei, at a joint appearance today, announced that they would work together to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases that lead to global warming. They also announced cooperative efforts on education, disaster preparedness and anti-drug programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton is to speak to a joint meeting of the Chilean legislature on Friday. To the relief of American officials, Gen. Augusto Pinochet, a lifetime member of the Senate, signaled today that he would not be present. American officials had feared that the appearance of the 82-year-old general, who led an authoritarian regime here from 1973 through 1990, would be a distraction from Mr. Clinton's message of hope, growth and democratic development in Latin America.</p>
        <p>Samuel R. Berger, the national security adviser, said Mr. Clinton would not alter his remarks on democracy and human rights, whether General Pinochet was in the audience or not. The operative theory of the trip appears to be that meeting and talking, even if with only modest achievements, are in themselves important benchmarks in the march toward hemispheric economic and political integration.</p>
        <p>The official line is that the President does not need fast track to begin the negotiations for the Free Trade Area of the Americas, to which the democratic nations of the region committed themselves at the first modern Latin American summit meeting, in Miami in December 1994.</p>
        <p>Charlene Barshefsky, the United States trade representative, said Washington had arranged the talks  in its own interest, setting out their terms at the beginning, and had assured itself the co-chairmanship of the talks at the end stage of the negotiations five years from now.</p>
        <p>In a briefing before leaving Washington, she brushed off concerns that in the interim Latin American nations will bypass the United States and form regional trade groups that will create economic ties with Europe and Asia and put American exporters at a disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Ms. Barshefsky said those regional trade deals are not ''an overly positive development'' for the United States. But she said the Latin American nations would ultimately have to accommodate United States trade terms if they want unrestricted access to the immense American market for goods and services.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
