<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just How Wacky Is the Weather?</title>
    <meta content="26FEAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980802T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewine, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2D81039F935A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="3282" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just How Wacky Is the Weather?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD LEWINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewine, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on renewed interest in and greater television coverage of weather and weather forecasts as weather around New York and across US acts contrary to past traditions; map; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW Yorkers have always talked about the weather, but lately their meteorological ruminations seem to be taking on a new kind of urgency. Out in Union Square Park on a recent Monday, vendors in the Greenmarket said they had been arguing a lot about why the weather had been so odd.</p>
        <p>''I think it's the pollution, the greenhouse effect,'' said David Graves, a beekeeper who sells honey and jams. Anthony Davis, who deals in film scripts, had another idea: ''I don't feel it's the greenhouse effect,'' he said. ''I think it's another ice age.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW Yorkers have always talked about the weather, but lately their meteorological ruminations seem to be taking on a new kind of urgency. Out in Union Square Park on a recent Monday, vendors in the Greenmarket said they had been arguing a lot about why the weather had been so odd.</p>
        <p>''I think it's the pollution, the greenhouse effect,'' said David Graves, a beekeeper who sells honey and jams. Anthony Davis, who deals in film scripts, had another idea: ''I don't feel it's the greenhouse effect,'' he said. ''I think it's another ice age.''</p>
        <p>Maybe it's all the news stories about ozone and El Nino that have people spooked. Or maybe it's simply that the weather appears to be so strange. In 1994-95, the city had its snowiest winter on record. But last winter was the warmest on record, followed by the coolest June. And that's just New York. Florida has had its fires, California its floods, Texas its heat waves, and there have been enough twisters around the country to fill a Hollywood epic.</p>
        <p>''People are wondering what is going on,'' said Spencer Christian, who does the weather for ABC's ''Good Morning America'' program. ''Is it global warming? Is it the end of the world?''</p>
        <p>With all these big questions out there, it's no surprise that there has been an explosion of weather coverage on television in the last five years. But while weather forecasters say they know a lot about the weather, they don't know everything. It's this mysterious quality that makes weather so fascinating.</p>
        <p>''My feeling is that the weather has become more central in our imaginations as the result of the world becoming more predictable,'' said David Laskin, who wrote ''Braving the Elements: The Stormy History of American Weather'' (Anchor Press/Doubleday, 1997). ''Weather is the last frontier.''</p>
        <p>When people have questions about the weather, they turn to newspapers, radio, the Internet and television. The Weather Channel, CNN and New York 1 deliver forecasts at regular intervals. National and local news programs have been hyping weather mercilessly. Next month, some local cable systems will be adding MSG Metro, a 24-hour weather and traffic station focusing on New York City.</p>
        <p>''Add it all up and there is simply much more weather on television,'' said Mike Echert, the president of the Weather Channel, which is based in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>Mr. Laskin said that when people tuned into a weather broadcast, they wanted not just for the forecast but to be reassured that all was well in the world, that the bad would blow over. They also wanted to know what to wear the next day. Those are some reasons why local television weather forecasters are so important to people.</p>
        <p>''Nine out of 10 people would cite weather as the most important element in the newscast,'' said Jim Willi, the president of Audience Research, a Dallas company that has been doing viewer surveys for 25 years.</p>
        <p>Local weather forecasters make six-figure salaries for their two- or three-minute turns on television, and most of them have meteorological degrees. But they all get their information from the same place, the National Weather Service, a branch of the Federal Government that is based in Silver Spring, Md.</p>
        <p>The nightly weather forecast begins each morning in the form of weather observations from satellites, ships at sea, balloons and volunteer weather enthusiasts all over the world. The information is sent to the Weather Service and fed into a complex computer model that simulates the movement of weather over a nine-day period. There are other models, too, run by countries, including Japan and Britain, and some universities, like the University of Washington and the University of Wisconsin at Madison. (No model predicts the weather exactly the same way.)</p>
        <p>The Weather Service, in turn, passes maps and charts derived from each model along with explanations to weather forecasters around the country. Go into any television station weather office and you will see reams of these charts pinned to the walls.  What remains for the forecaster to do is to choose the right model and fine-tune its predictions for the local area.</p>
        <p>But as forecasting models become more accurate, the human element diminishes. ''Over the past five years, there has been very little wiggle room for somebody locally to add much,'' said Louis W. Uccellini, the head of meteorology for the Weather Service. ''Our five-day forecast is now as accurate as the three-day forecast was seven years ago.''</p>
        <p>This means that the differences between television weather forecasters is more a matter of style than substance. Storm Field of Channel 9, the UPN affiliate, who has been on the air in New York since 1975, and whose father, Frank Field, was a weatherman for more than 30 years, said that most weather people fell into one of five style categories. Loosely translated, these are: hunk/hunkette, warm and fuzzy, expert, local guy or gal and funny character.</p>
        <p>Among the current crop of weather people who are on at 10 P.M. and 11 P.M., which is considered the top weather slot in the local news business, Nick Gregory of Channel 5 (WNYW), bills himself as the most accurate forecaster, which he said is based on a New York Post article and a high-school student's science project. He could be considered the classic expert type. Mr. G, he of the deep tan and bushy hair, does the local guy thing for Channel 11 (WPIX). (His real name is Irv Gikofsky.)</p>
        <p>Then there is Ira Joe Fisher, who Mr. Field said was brought to Channel 2 (WCBS) to win over warm and fuzzy fans when Al Roker, who owns warm and fuzzy, went from the 11 P.M. spot on Channel 4 (WNBC) to the network's ''Today'' show. Janice Huff, who is relatively neutral in her presentation, but the only weatherwoman on New York television, replaced Mr. Roker.</p>
        <p>Now Channel 2 is replacing Mr. Fisher with Mark Danon, who is 27 and has smoldering blue eyes, and Mr. Fisher is moving to mornings. ''There's a lot of momentum at the station,'' a station spokeswoman, Adrienne Schwartz, explained. ''We feel that these changes will capitalize on that momentum.''</p>
        <p>But the changes could spell trouble for Sam Champion, whose blond good looks gave Channel 7 (WABC) the hunk franchise. ''I hope that's not what I'm known for,'' Mr. Champion said, with a laugh. As Mr. Field sees it, though, ''If Mark Danon is the new hunk, then Sam will need a new schtick.''</p>
        <p>The original television weathermen in the 1940's, Mr. Laskin said, were tweedy professorial types whose style was proto-expert. That gave way in the 1950's to characters like NBC's Tex Antoine, who appeared with a cartoon sidekick named Uncle Wethebee.</p>
        <p>The 1960's, Mr. Laskin said, was the era of the so-called weather girls, like CBS's Carol Reed, who premiered in 1952. And the 1970's saw the advent of the news team, with the weather person expected to kid around with the anchors. (In 1976, Mr. Antoine's banter about rape victims -- he said they should ''relax and enjoy it'' -- led to his dismissal. Storm Field replaced him.)</p>
        <p>There was a weather imbroglio in 1979 when Bob Harris, who styled himself ''Dr.'' Bob Harris, was dismissed from WCBS-AM and The New York Times for misrepresenting his credentials. Mr. Harris had no academic degrees.</p>
        <p>The last two decades have seen a return to seriousness, punctuated by the emergence of the 24-hour Weather Channel on cable in 1982 and by the introduction of satellite maps and computer graphics. People in the weather business estimate that about half the TV and radio weather people nationwide have meteorology degrees, a significantly greater proportion than 20 years ago. And Al Primo, president of Eyewitness News Service, a television news consulting company in Old Greenwich, Conn., said many stations had invested in million-dollar high-tech weather centers, with radar and computer graphics equipment.</p>
        <p>These days, weather people typically spend twice as much time creating the graphics for their brief performances than they do actually forecasting the weather. ''The thought is that people need to be dazzled by technology,'' Mr. Fisher said. ''But I still want to see a human, of whatever shape, standing there.''</p>
        <p>The machines can get pretty elaborate. Some, for example, can simulate flight through weather conditions. ''At CBS they now have thunder sounds,'' Mr. Field said. ''They still haven't figured out what to do during sunny days.''</p>
        <p>Then there is Doppler 4000, which can show weather happening live, unlike most radar systems, which have a delay of a few minutes. Channel 4 promoted it relentlessly during broadcasts of the 1996 Olympics, until viewers complained furiously.</p>
        <p>''We ran this three and a half minute promo,'' said Mr. Roker, who was in Atlanta for the Olympics at the time. ''I had no idea how much the promo was running until my wife called me. Then we ran a promo that said we will not run the promo.''</p>
        <p>Last October, the White House invited some 100 weather people to a talk by President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore on global warming, in the hope that they would discuss the problem in their broadcasts. As President Clinton himself acknowledged, weather people have enormous influence on the way Americans perceive the weather. But none of New York's television forecasters have been talking about global warming, because they don't think it's related to the recent peculiarities of the weather in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>''Weather has always been cyclical, and we are in an active cycle,'' said Mr. G. ''The problem is that no one can figure out the cycle.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gregory was equally cautious. ''This is just one of those extreme periods of weather we go through,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Danon was more blunt. ''I'm not completely sold on global warming,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Most of New York's weather people do take global warming seriously, at least in theory. But for explanations of recent weather patterns, they point to El Nino, a periodic warming of the Pacific Ocean that has not, as yet, been connected to the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>Because of this year's El Nino, which was stronger than its predecessors, the jet stream (a strong westerly wind that runs across the United States and separates cold northern air from hot southern air) hung above the city all winter, drawing warm air from the south. Then it dropped down over the city in the spring, putting the region straight in the path of fast-moving storms that travel along the jet stream.</p>
        <p>''It's not really unusual when you have an El Nino situation,'' Mr. Field said.</p>
        <p>Still, people keep seeing signs of calamity in changing weather patterns, as they have for years. ''There is a long history of weather obsession and the conviction that we are changing the weather,'' Mr. Laskin said. ''I have quotes dating back to Cotton Mather. In Thomas Jefferson's writings there is a discussion of climate change caused by the settling of the West. This is not new, this cosmic sense of guilt and human causation, which is not to say that global warming is a myth.''</p>
        <p>Reliable weather observations date back only about 100 years. Beyond that, scientists are able to infer a great deal from natural evidence, but in the end it is really quite hard to say what is normal or appropriate weather for a given place. And since it is hard to say what is normal, it is impossible to say what is abnormal. What weather people call normal weather conditions for a given day represent merely the average conditions recorded at that date over time.</p>
        <p>''There is nothing at all unusual about unusual weather,'' said Joe Sobel, the weatherman on the AM station 1010- WINS, and an executive at Accuweather, a weather information service based in State College, Pa., which says it has more than 15,000 clients. ''Normal weather is really an average of extremes.''</p>
        <p>Aside from people's natural propensity to worry about the weather, there are other reasons why it seems worse lately. The increased emphasis on reporting bad weather news on  television may suggest that things are worse than they are, just as television news can make a city seem more dangerous than it really is by running lots of stories about violent crime even as the crime rate is falling.</p>
        <p>And there probably are more people experiencing bad weather as the population spreads out across the country. ''There is more danger because there are more people living in the way of violent weather,'' Mr. Laskin said. In the last three decades, he said, new housing has been built in Florida and California and along the nation's coastlines, right in the paths of powerful weather forces.</p>
        <p>So it seems that New York City and the rest of the country are in the same place, meteorologically speaking, that they have always been in. The weather is strange, but there's nothing strange about that. People worry that the climate is changing, and no one knows what the future will bring, which is nothing new. So take heart. It isn't as bad as it seems, although Storm Field says the city is long overdue for a hurricane.</p>
        <p>Reporting Weather to the Weather Service</p>
        <p>By EDWARD LEWINE</p>
        <p>A Department of Sanitation sewage pumping plant in Gravesend, Brooklyn, is just one of a dozen places around the city where weather measurements are taken. ''We are only concerned with temperature and rainfall,'' said Frank J. Martino, who at age 69 has retired from his paying job at the sewage plant but still works for fun as a weather observer for the Federal Government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martino and about a dozen other people scattered throughout the five boroughs are National Weather Service observers. They take readings twice a day and send them, with comments, to the service's main offices in Silver Spring, Md., once a month. Mr. Martino, who says he is the only observer in Brooklyn, has been doing this since 1950. Why? ''I just love the weather,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The first weather observatory in New York was set up by the city in Central Park in 1869. In 1891, the Federal Government founded its own station. It was at  various sites downtown before moving to Rockefeller Center in 1960.</p>
        <p>The Weather Service deserted the city for Suffolk County in 1996, but left behind computerized machines that continue to take readings at Kennedy and La Guardia airports and at Belvedere Castle, just south of the Great Lawn in Central Park. Mr. Martino and his fellow observers round out the picture.</p>
        <p>''They are volunteers,'' said Bob Chartuck, a Weather Service spokesman. ''We give them the equipment and they go out and take measurements.''</p>
        <p>As for the equipment? Forget Doppler 4000: observing the weather is a low-tech business. Mr. Martino has a simple thermometer that also records high and low temperatures, and a rain gauge that is no more than a tube within a tube to trap the accumulated level of rainwater. And he uses another tried-and-true method: looking out the window and recording what he sees.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martino said he discovered the joys of watching the weather when he was 17, in a high-school science class in Gravesend, where he has lived all his life. He has devoted about 20 hours a week to the task since he first applied for the nonpaying job of Weather Service observer 38 years ago.</p>
        <p>''I like to see these big storms come in,'' he said. ''I was lucky enough to have recorded 30.1 inches of snow during the 1947 storm. It was wonderful.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 2, 1998, Sunday  A chart last Sunday about local weather forecasters misstated the academic credentials of two of them. Storm Field of WOR-TV received a bachelor's degree from the Massachusetts College of Optometry, not Ophthalmology. Irv Gikofsky of WPIX-TV received a master's degree in secondary education from Hofstra University, not in meteorology. His master's thesis was on teaching weather.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 2, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>A chart last Sunday about local weather forecasters misstated the academic credentials of two of them. Storm Field of WOR-TV received a bachelor's degree from the Massachusetts College of Optometry, not Ophthalmology. Irv Gikofsky of WPIX-TV received a master's degree in secondary education from Hofstra University, not in meteorology. His master's thesis was on teaching weather.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
