<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists Gain Access to the Navy's 'Deep Ears' on the Oceans</title>
    <meta content="28OCEA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Microphones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scientific Environmental Research Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cox, Duane A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2D81F39F93BA15754C0A96E958260" item-length="761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists Gain Access to the Navy's 'Deep Ears' on the Oceans</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Navy, after years of delay, agrees to permit civilian scientists to routinely use its 'deep ears,' global network of deep underwater microphones that were built during cold war to track foreign ships and submarines; surveillance microphones, covering more than 70 percent of planet, can hear seals barking, fish schooling, ice cracking, seabeds shaking, undersea volcanoes erupting and storms lashing sea's surface; Navy will share parts of network with Scientific Environmental Research Foundation, private group led by retired naval officer Duane A Cox; Pres Clinton and Vice Pres Gore announce step (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE NAVY, after years of delay, has agreed to let civilian scientists routinely use its ''deep ears,'' which were built at a cost of $16 billion in the cold war to pinpoint the locations of enemy ships and submarines by tracking their machinery noises.</p>
        <p>Now, the global network of deep underwater microphones is ready to help reveal the natural secrets of the sea, which covers more than 70 percent of the planet and is considered the Earth's largest and most mysterious environment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE NAVY, after years of delay, has agreed to let civilian scientists routinely use its ''deep ears,'' which were built at a cost of $16 billion in the cold war to pinpoint the locations of enemy ships and submarines by tracking their machinery noises.</p>
        <p>Now, the global network of deep underwater microphones is ready to help reveal the natural secrets of the sea, which covers more than 70 percent of the planet and is considered the Earth's largest and most mysterious environment.</p>
        <p>The surveillance microphones can hear natural sounds like whales singing, seals barking, fish schooling, ice cracking, seabeds shaking, undersea volcanoes erupting and storms lashing the sea's surface. Remarkably, they can do so over distances of hundreds and even thousands of miles, as sound readily travels in water. Their sensitivity is such that they once tracked the movements of a blue whale for weeks as it sang.</p>
        <p>The Navy moved slowly to share the system. Before doing so, it wanted to make certain that released data would never give away the locations of American submarines, which still prowl the depths armed with missiles and nuclear warheads. Eventually, it found a way to keep their locations secret, clearing the way for the peace dividend.</p>
        <p>On June 4, the Navy agreed to share retired parts of its global network with the Scientific Environmental Research Foundation, a private group in Alexandria, Va. Its president is Duane A. Cox, a retired naval officer who for 16 years helped track warships with the microphones. Since 1995, he has campaigned to open the surveillance system to civilians, including scientists at universities and educators at other schools and museums.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore announced the step June 11 at the National Ocean Conference in Monterey, Calif.</p>
        <p>The next day, President Clinton said the opening would help scientists ''track marine mammals, predict deadly storms, detect illegal fishing and gain new insights into the complexities of climate change.''</p>
        <p>Periodically, a few scientists have gained access to the listening system. But now, Mr. Cox said in an interview, the way has been cleared for wide and routine access to hundreds of retired microphones that still dot the darkness throughout the depths of the global sea.</p>
        <p>''It's a great opportunity,'' he said of the burgeoning effort. ''We need to save this national treasure.''</p>
        <p>The Navy is still keeping the exact locations of the retired microphones secret, as well as their numbers, to maintain uncertainty about its sound surveillance abilities.</p>
        <p>Having finally received a green light to use the retired network, Mr. Cox is lining up patrons to help pay for its refurbishment, which is costly. He estimates that $4.7 million is needed to start. Two years ago, he had $3 million lined up, but that disappeared during the delays.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cox said he has received permission from the Navy to use seven retired stations where cables from networks of undersea microphones come ashore. In the Pacific, the sites are Guam; Adak Island, Alaska, in the Aleutians; Oahu in Hawaii; San Nicholas off California in the Channel Islands, and Point Sur on the central California coast. In the Atlantic the sites are Bermuda and Keflavik in Iceland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cox also said he has several partners trying to help open the system and raise money for its rebirth. They include the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation, a private group in Washington; the Pentagon's Strategic Environmental Research and Development Program, and the Federal Systems Division of Lockheed Martin, a contractor based in Manassas, Va., that helps run the Navy's deep ears.</p>
        <p>The first station scheduled for reopening is Adak, which is the most recent to have been retired, Mr. Cox said, adding that the chance of getting enough money from private sponsors appeared to be good.</p>
        <p>''Time is of the essence because these stations need to be reactivated to prevent their arrays from degenerating,'' he said. ''We're trying to see if we can keep them alive.''</p>
        <p>In its new incarnation, the listening effort is to be known as National Oceanographic Environmental Monitoring System, Mr. Cox said. He added that, despite the national emphasis, his plan is to share the data internationally.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
