<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As the Climate Shifts, Trees Can Take Flight</title>
    <meta content="10TREE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DA1530F933A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="1903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As the Climate Shifts, Trees Can Take Flight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists and conservationists study migration patterns of trees and how such migration is affected by climate change; many scientists now believe that temperate-zone forests would probably be able to migrate northward fast enough to adjust to rapidly warming climate; progeny of these transported seeds would spread out, filling in surrounding and intervening ground, setting stage for another long leap; but farms, development and roads could slow migration; drawings (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIME and again in the remote past, entire forests and other ecological communities have migrated hundreds of miles over the landscape in response to big warmings and coolings of the earth's climate. For example, sugar maples, beeches, firs and spruces that flourished in the Middle Atlantic states moved farther north as the world warmed after the last ice age, while oaks and hickories from farther south moved up to take their place.</p>
        <p>Scientists and conservationists have tended to assume that this sort of climate-driven migration happens in a single, consolidated block, as if pieces of a gigantic jigsaw puzzle were picked up and moved. And they have worried that if the earth's atmosphere warms at the rate predicted by many experts in the decades ahead, entire natural communities might not be able to migrate fast enough to keep pace with the change and could die out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIME and again in the remote past, entire forests and other ecological communities have migrated hundreds of miles over the landscape in response to big warmings and coolings of the earth's climate. For example, sugar maples, beeches, firs and spruces that flourished in the Middle Atlantic states moved farther north as the world warmed after the last ice age, while oaks and hickories from farther south moved up to take their place.</p>
        <p>Scientists and conservationists have tended to assume that this sort of climate-driven migration happens in a single, consolidated block, as if pieces of a gigantic jigsaw puzzle were picked up and moved. And they have worried that if the earth's atmosphere warms at the rate predicted by many experts in the decades ahead, entire natural communities might not be able to migrate fast enough to keep pace with the change and could die out.</p>
        <p>Now this picture is being drastically revised as researchers discover that it is more complex than has commonly been thought.</p>
        <p>First, it has become clear that many of the most important and valued species of trees have in the past migrated fast enough to keep up with temperature changes at least as large and rapid as the global warming of 2 to 6 degrees Fahrenheit that is predicted, as an annual average, over the next 100 years.</p>
        <p>''Migration rates are probably faster than some people have said, and have been sufficient for plants to keep up with rapid climate change,'' says Dr. Louis F. Pitelka, an ecologist at the University of Maryland's Appalachian Laboratory in Frostburg, Md., one of a number of experts who have lately been studying the situation. The effect of this realization, he said, ''is to downgrade the rate of migration as an issue'' in climate change.</p>
        <p>But as that issue subsides, others have moved to the fore.</p>
        <p>Ecologists say that humans have so altered the natural landscape that rules of migration that applied in the past may not apply as well in the future. Through agriculture and development, people have cut natural ecosystems into disconnected fragments. This, scientists say, might well frustrate the migration of trees, and especially of herbaceous plants, grasses and the whole panoply of small but essential creatures like fungi, insects and microbes that make for a whole and healthy ecosystem. The experts say that some species, especially endangered ones that find themselves walled off in isolated enclaves, might perish.</p>
        <p>Moreover, they say, hardy weeds that thrive in disturbed ground could race northward ahead of other species as the climate of Northern temperate regions warms, and dominate the landscape.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, humans might blunt the impact of fragmentation and weeds by transplanting favored trees, plants and grasses to places where the climate agrees with them, either on purpose or by accident.</p>
        <p>Everything is complicated by a realization that different species in the same ecosystem do not all migrate at the same pace, and by the theory, supported by one recent study, that rapid climatic change upsets the interactions between predators and prey, and between species that compete with each other. These upsets would further alter migration patterns in unpredictable ways.</p>
        <p>The combined result of global warming and human alteration of the landscape, according to the emerging new view, might therefore be a grand reshuffling of the natural world, producing a temperate-zone landscape very different from what it is now -- or has ever been.</p>
        <p>All of this underscores a pervasive uncertainty that has developed about how natural ecosystems actually behave in a changing climate.</p>
        <p>One thing that is known, from many lines of evidence, is that in the past, major species of trees responded to abrupt climate change by shifting their ranges hundreds of miles.  Both the climatic change and the shift in forest range have sometimes occurred in the span of a human lifetime, or less.</p>
        <p>A particularly arresting example comes from the New York area. Dr. Dorothy M. Peteet, a paleoecologist with the NASA Goddard Institute for Space Studies in New York, and her colleagues examined the fossils of tree pollen and plant remains in sediments from the bottom of Allamuchy Pond near the town of Allamuchy in northwestern New Jersey and Linsley Pond near New Haven, Conn.</p>
        <p>Analysis of the fossils indicated that as the earth was recovering from the last ice age about 10,000 years ago, the average annual regional temperature rose sharply by 5 to 7 degrees Fahrenheit in a period of about 50 years. In that same period, species of trees that are adapted to cold, like paper birch, fir and spruce, virtually disappeared from the region, while species adapted to warmer conditions, like oak and white pine, just as rapidly replaced them.</p>
        <p>If the climate were now to warm further, and quickly, ''I would think the trees would do exactly what they did in the old days,'' said Dr. Peteet: the ranges of both cold-adapted and warm-adapted species would move northward. This effect would likely be especially dramatic in the New York region, she said, because it is roughly on the border between the range of northern, or boreal, species of trees, and more southerly species of the temperate zone.</p>
        <p>Trees, herbs and grasses do not really move, of course; they extend their ranges by sending out seeds.  But how could seed dispersal expand their ranges as fast as the fossil evidence suggests? This question was posed as far back as a century ago by a scientist named Clement Reid, who noted that oaks reclaimed their modern-day position in Britain within 600 years after the last glaciation. But given the distance at which an acorn disperses from a tree on its own, Reid observed, the migration should have taken a million years or so.</p>
        <p>Ecologists still debate Reid's Paradox, as it is known, and a number of mechanisms by which the migration of trees might be hastened have been proposed. Wind, storms and stream currents disperse lighter seeds, while many birds and mammals carry heavier ones away; bluejays are considered especially effective dispersers.</p>
        <p>But these are inefficient mechanisms. Many seeds get ground up in the guts of animals. There is no guarantee that animals and winds will carry seeds in the right direction.  Many animals do not travel all that far anyway. And even when they do, germination and plant establishment are chancy.</p>
        <p>A favored answer is emerging, and it says that every once in a while, but rarely, seeds are transmitted long distances -- hundreds of yards to several miles -- against all odds, and germinate. These leapfrogging ''outliers,'' as they are called, are believed to be the nuclei that make rapid migration possible: the trees thus established send out their own seeds, which fill in the gaps left behind.</p>
        <p>It is ''a very haphazard, random, messy process where you don't have a migrating front at all,'' says Dr. James S. Clark, a botanist at Duke University. But, he said, computer modeling shows that this mechanism would be efficient enough to explain the rapid migrations of the past. Dr. Clark is the chief author of a report on the subject in the January issue of the journal BioScience.</p>
        <p>This ''long jump and outlier'' mechanism of plant migration has  been observed in the case of Eurasian grasses and other invaders from abroad that have flourished in North America, says Dr. Pitelka, the chief author of another recent report on migrations, this one in the journal American Scientist. (Both the Clark and Pitelka articles were based on the proceedings of recent scientific workshops.)</p>
        <p>The nimbleness and latter-day abundance of opportunistic weeds, Dr. Pitelka wrote, raises the ''unpleasant prospect'' that in the event of a warming climate, these interlopers could out-compete trees and other plants more valued by humans. This is so, he wrote, because outlying populations of more valued species may fail again and again before a founding population becomes sufficiently rooted and sends out enough seeds to fill in uncolonized ground. In the meantime, the prolific, adaptable weeds could move in and dominate.</p>
        <p>Fragmentation of the natural landscape has clearly changed the ground rules of migration, the scientists say, but they are at a loss as to what the details of fragmentation's impact would be. The most obvious effect, Dr. Clark said, is that ''it simply removes a large amount of the landscape; open areas and inhospitable areas could slow down the rate of spread.'' Paved and developed areas would also reduce the available landing spots for long-distance seed colonists.</p>
        <p>Fragmentation could also create barriers for herbaceous plants that live on the forest floor and are a necessary part of the ecosystem. The seeds of some of these are dispersed by insects. ''There's very little opportunity for them to move anyway, and then when you put on top of that large nonforested areas, it has to have a big effect,'' Dr. Clark said.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, he said, fragmentation may not be much of a problem for some species, especially those, like aspen and birch, which produce vast amounts of light seeds that can easily be dispersed by wind.  And even in the case of a heavier seed dispersed by a bluejay, Dr. Pitelka said, ''a jay knows where it wants to go, and if there is a good forest spot farther away, it will find it.''</p>
        <p>An even bigger uncertainty is the question of how rapid climate change would affect relationships among species, and how those relationships in turn might affect migration patterns.</p>
        <p>In an ingenious experiment reported in the Feb. 19 issue of the journal Nature, a team of British ecologists led by Dr. Andrew Davis of the University of Leeds manipulated laboratory populations of fruit flies and parasitic wasps to determine how they responded to a warming environment. They found that when the temperature was raised, the numbers and distribution of the insects were different when the species were commingled from those when they were kept separate.</p>
        <p>The lesson of the experiment, said Dr. Davis, is that temperature change so disrupts the abundance and distribution of organisms that the climatic change in itself becomes  one ecological factor among many in determining migration patterns.</p>
        <p>These considerations ''are even more complicated when we get to higher organisms like vertebrates and trees,'' Dr. Clark said. Rapid climate change could result in ''a complete rearrangement of biotic interactions,'' he said, and that makes it ''very difficult to take a future climate scenario and predict what sort of organisms you're going to have'' in a given locality or region.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
