<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At This Helsinki Home, Beware the Computer (and the Dog)</title>
    <meta content="T09HEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1030490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Finland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibrahim, Youssef M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Linturi, Risto</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Finland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6D81E3EF93AA35754C0A96E958260" item-length="624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At This Helsinki Home, Beware the Computer (and the Dog)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ibrahim, Youssef M</byline>
      <dateline>HELSINKI, Finland</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Risto Linturi, Scandinavia's high-tech guru, has designed his own new state-of-the-art computerized home, one that takes care of itself; sensors in home connect to computers that heat stone floors, regulate lights and air circulation, controlling level of gases like carbon dioxide in air; more than 30 Internet outlets are connected by seven miles of high-optic fiber wiring that snakes unseen around house, allowing portable computers to be plugged in almost anywhere; house has sophisticated security system with sensors that signal if intruder is present; house is in Finland, on Baltic Sea (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pity the burglar who breaks into Risto Linturi's new state-of-the-art computerized home. Scandinavia's high-tech guru, Mr. Linturi has designed a house that takes care of itself.</p>
        <p>Seconds after sensors signal his  mobile phone that an intruder is present, Mr. Linturi can track the burglar via voice-synthesized messages and do something about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pity the burglar who breaks into Risto Linturi's new state-of-the-art computerized home. Scandinavia's high-tech guru, Mr. Linturi has designed a house that takes care of itself.</p>
        <p>Seconds after sensors signal his  mobile phone that an intruder is present, Mr. Linturi can track the burglar via voice-synthesized messages and do something about it.</p>
        <p>With voice messages to the house's central computer, he can turn lights on, increase or cut off air circulation, lock doors automatically, and switch on music or the television at high volume -- all while the system dials the police, reporting the exact time of the break-in and the burglar's progress.</p>
        <p>Like many Finns, Mr. Linturi is very comfortable with cutting-edge  technology. Finns are the world's most intense users of mobile phones,  with three out of four carrying one.  Two out of four navigate the Internet daily.</p>
        <p>For the last five years, Mr. Linturi, 38, has worked on a ''virtual reality'' Yellow Pages guide to Finland's capital as technology manager of the  Helsinki Telephone Corporation. With pieces of it already in place, it will allow residents and visitors to navigate the streets of Helsinki in a virtual-reality taxi, enter its theaters in real time, watch its movies for a fee, and listen to public concerts free.</p>
        <p>It's all done with computers operated from homes that are equipped with a mouse and interactive audiovisual devices and will be fully operative in 18 months. So it seemed logical for Mr. Linturi, soon after he acquired a prime piece of property on the Baltic Sea three years ago, to dream up the ultimate computerized home.</p>
        <p>When finished some time in September, what Mr. Linturi calls ''the future remote work-home in Finn Bay'' will have cost $3 million to $4 million. The three-bedroom, four-story house and conference room is  atop a hill with an idyllic view of the serene Helsinki bay and the city. It has a mooring station for one or two small sailboats.</p>
        <p>The house is designed for ultimate comfort and what Mr. Linturi calls passive technology. ''The big emphasis is on economy, safety and ecology,'' he says. Floor-to-ceiling windows give a spectacular view of the Baltic. Sensors connected to the computers heat the stone floors (there is no need for carpets), and regulate lights and air circulation, controlling the level of gases like carbon dioxide in the air.</p>
        <p>There are few buttons or switches: lights will turn on or off depending on occupancy.</p>
        <p>A large electronic screen is affixed to a wall in the kitchen, where the average Finnish family spends a good deal of time in the long dark winter days.</p>
        <p>The screen can display electronic newspapers and the family can use it to send and receive E-mail over coffee, snacks or dinner.</p>
        <p>More than 30 Internet outlets are connected by seven miles of high-optic fiber wiring that snakes unseen around the house, allowing portable computers to be plugged in almost anywhere to communicate or call up  music, radio or television.</p>
        <p>Built of stone and thick bricks, the place is tightly designed around Mr. Linturi, his wife, Kaija, his two daughters, Henna, 16, and Anni, 10, and Dino, their 130-pound Irish wolfhound, which has its own entrance to the house that passes through a tub filled with water.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
