<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>29 Are Chosen for Fellowships From the MacArthur Foundation</title>
    <meta content="T02AWAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980603T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1021593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DB143BF931A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>29 Are Chosen for Fellowships From the MacArthur Foundation</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leonard Zeskind of Kansas City, Mo., has been working for two decades to increase awareness of hate groups, and in 1983 he founded the Institute for Research and Education on Human Rights.</p>
        <p>Now, with a $295,000 windfall as a MacArthur Fellow, he hopes to complete his book on the white supremacist movement in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leonard Zeskind of Kansas City, Mo., has been working for two decades to increase awareness of hate groups, and in 1983 he founded the Institute for Research and Education on Human Rights.</p>
        <p>Now, with a $295,000 windfall as a MacArthur Fellow, he hopes to complete his book on the white supremacist movement in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zeskind, 48, is among the 29 new MacArthur Fellows announced yesterday by the John D. and Catherine T. MacArthur Foundation of Chicago, which awards stipends to innovators to liberate them from financial constraints.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Zeskind, the fellows for 1998 are:</p>
        <p>Janine Antoni, 34, New York, an artist who mixes traditional sculpture and conceptual art, $225,000.</p>
        <p>Ida Applebroog, 68, New York, a painter and social critic, $375,000.</p>
        <p>Ellen Barry, 44, Oakland, Calif., the director of Legal Services for Prisoners With Children, $275,000.</p>
        <p>Tim Berners-Lee, 43, Lexington, Mass., who conceived and developed the World Wide Web, $270,000.</p>
        <p>Linda Bierds, 53, Bainbridge Island, Wash., a poet of historically detailed work, $320,000.</p>
        <p>Bernadette Brooten, 47, Cambridge, Mass., a professor of religion who has provided new interpretations of patterns of power, social structure and morality in ancient communities, $290,000.</p>
        <p>John Carlstrom, 41, Chicago, an astrophysicist who designs instruments to solve astronomical problems, $260,000.</p>
        <p>Mike Davis, 52, Pasadena, Calif., a historian who writes on urban, political, environmental and social issues, $315,000.</p>
        <p>Nancy Folbre, 45, Montague, Mass., an economist who explores how nonmarket production contributes to community development and economic growth, $280,000.</p>
        <p>Avner Greif, 42, Stanford, Calif., an economist who uses game theory to study beliefs and institutions, $265,000.</p>
        <p>Kun-Liang Guan, 35, Ann Arbor, Mich., a biochemist whose research has helped to explain how cells regulate internal processes and how they respond to external conditions, $230,000.</p>
        <p>Gary Hill, 47, Seattle, a video artist who has helped define his generation, $290,000.</p>
        <p>Edward Hirsch, 48, Houston, a poet and essayist, $295.000.</p>
        <p>Ayesha Jalal, 42, New York, a historian whose books have illuminated the culture of Pakistan and India, $265,000.</p>
        <p>Charles Johnson, 50, Seattle, a novelist, short-story writer, essayist, cartoonist and screenwriter whose works address fundamental philosophical questions, $305,000.</p>
        <p>Leah Krubitzer, 37, Davis, Calif., a neuroscientist whose studies have helped explain the relationship between brain organization and function, $240,000.</p>
        <p>Stewart Kwoh, 49, Los Angeles, a lawyer and human rights leader for the area's Asian population, $300,000.</p>
        <p>Charles Lewis, 44, Alexandria, Va., founder and executive director of the Center for Public Integrity, a nonprofit organization that produces book-length reports on issues like health-care lobbying, $275,000.</p>
        <p>William McDonald, 46, Douglas, Ariz., a cattle rancher who is leading efforts to create ecologically responsible cooperation among government, conservationists, scientists and ranchers, $285,000.</p>
        <p>Peter Miller, 33, Berlin, a German scholar of early modern European intellectual history, $220,000.</p>
        <p>Don Mitchell, 36, Syracuse, a cultural geographer whose studies illustrate how landscape is frequently a social construction influenced by human labor, $235,000.</p>
        <p>Rebecca Nelson, 37, Lima, Peru, a plant pathologist concerned with the protection of staple food crops in underdeveloped countries, $240,000.</p>
        <p>Elinor Ochs, 53, Los Angeles, a linguistic anthropologist who has made major contributions to linguistics, science studies, sociocultural anthropology and psychology, $320,000.</p>
        <p>Ishmael Reed, 60, Oakland, Calif., a novelist, playwright, poet and publisher of the works of minority authors, $355,000.</p>
        <p>Benjamin Santer, 43, Livermore, Calif., an atmospheric scientist whose research supports the finding that human activity contributes to global warming, $270,000.</p>
        <p>Karl Sims, 36, Cambridge, Mass., a computer scientist and pioneer in the field of computational evolution, $235,000.</p>
        <p>Dorothy Q. Thomas, 38, New York, a human rights advocate and women's rights leader, $245,000.</p>
        <p>Mary Zimmerman, 37, Evanston, Ill., a director and playwright who adapts seemingly untheatrical source material from classic world literature, $240,000.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 3, 1998, Wednesday  An article yesterday about MacArthur Foundation Fellowships misstated the nationality of one recipient, Peter Miller. He is American, not German.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 3, 1998, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about MacArthur Foundation Fellowships misstated the nationality of one recipient, Peter Miller. He is American, not German.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
