<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Notebook; Where Teachers Say 'Ribbit!'</title>
    <meta content="30GARD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1013427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Botanical Garden</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Garden Notebook</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E0DA173EF933A05757C0A96E958260" item-length="1737" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Notebook; Where Teachers Say 'Ribbit!'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Botanical Garden is about to open Everett Children's Adventure Garden, 12-acre, $9 million facility that is largest and most ambitious children's education project of its kind; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE moment Velarian Francis, a fourth grader, reached the top of the rocky hill, swiveled the high-powered telescope onto the marsh below and shouted, ''I see little bugs!'' the New York Botanical Garden's new Everett Children's Adventure Garden leaped to the forefront of children's education.</p>
        <p>''Children need natural environments they can get their hands on, explore, discover things about,'' said Robin C. Moore, a landscape architect and designer of children's environments. ''I think the adventure garden is breaking new ground. I'm not aware of any other environment like this in a botanical garden.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE moment Velarian Francis, a fourth grader, reached the top of the rocky hill, swiveled the high-powered telescope onto the marsh below and shouted, ''I see little bugs!'' the New York Botanical Garden's new Everett Children's Adventure Garden leaped to the forefront of children's education.</p>
        <p>''Children need natural environments they can get their hands on, explore, discover things about,'' said Robin C. Moore, a landscape architect and designer of children's environments. ''I think the adventure garden is breaking new ground. I'm not aware of any other environment like this in a botanical garden.''</p>
        <p>The $9 million, 12-acre Everett Children's Adventure Garden, which opens officially on Saturday, is the largest and most ambitious children's education project of its kind. Considered a model by the National Science Foundation, it meanders past a marshy pond and across a bridge into the oldest forest in New York City. Along the way, children can pretend to be lost on the ''kids only'' meadow path. They can learn the difference between petal and stamen, pollen and pistil. (It isn't a gun.) They can see a flower the way a bee does -- with ultraviolet vision -- so that a stripe on a petal looks like a runway right to the nectary.</p>
        <p>They can look for frogs in the pond, then examine the water's teeming life under a microscope in a lab inside an Adirondack-style cottage designed by the architect Richard Dattner. Who needs to go to the Adirondacks when nature is here in the heart of the Bronx?</p>
        <p>Last week, 40 children from two elementary schools gave the adventure garden a test run. As they hopped like sparrows over the boulder maze -- heading for the telescope -- teachers and designers watched them like hawks.</p>
        <p>Many minds from the worlds of science and education worked for more than a decade to bring the adventure garden into being. ''Back in the late 80's, the garden went through a master planning process,'' said Catherine Eberbach, the garden's project manager and visionary. ''There was nothing for children and families who just came through the gate. There was no reason to say, 'Let's go to the New York Botanical Garden.' ''</p>
        <p>At the same time, it was obvious that local schoolchildren needed a safe place where they could touch and be touched by nature. From surveys of parents, teachers and children -- and consultations with experts from England and the United States -- an ambitious plan emerged.</p>
        <p>''Some of what we found backed up national research, like girls being less enthusiastic than boys for science,'' said Ms. Eberbach, who arrived 10 years ago to design and run the existing children's garden. ''And everybody thought scientists were people in white lab coats.''</p>
        <p>Other responses exploded some myths. ''Parents and teachers thought their children didn't notice, or care about, nature,'' she said. ''But city kids really value the plants in their neighborhood. They express great sorrow when somebody breaks a limb off a tree.''</p>
        <p>It wasn't just New York City children who had never had the experience of free play in woods or a stream without their parents' hanging over every snapping twig.</p>
        <p>''I'm part of an international group of researchers who are very concerned about the growing lack of contact between children and the natural environment,'' said Mr. Moore, who teaches at North Carolina State University in Raleigh. ''This is a very recent phenomenon. Parents are very concerned about letting their children outside, out of fear they'll be abducted or molested. They worry about them getting injured or killed in traffic.''</p>
        <p>Such restrictions keep children from making a deep emotional attachment to the natural world, as Mr. Moore and Herb H. Wong say in ''Natural Learning: The Life and History of an Environmental Schoolyard'' (MIG Communications, 1997). The book describes 10 years of work with children and teachers in Berkeley, Calif., in turning an asphalt playground into a natural world with woods, a meadow and a creek.</p>
        <p>Eileen Adams, an educator who lives in London, is helping England's 30,000 elementary schools incorporate natural landscapes into their playgrounds. She sees parents' sheltering attitudes as restricting children's personal freedom. ''Kids are being more and more denied access to the outdoors,'' she said. ''They're taken everywhere by their parents. It's very controlled and constrained, and I don't think it's healthy.''</p>
        <p>The botanical garden's research showed that Bronx parents had the same concerns. So the staff designed a natural landscape where young children could set off down the kids-only path through the wildflower meadow, for example, and pretend to get lost, knowing that Mom or Dad, or the teacher, wasn't too far away.</p>
        <p>Near the pond, boys and girls tested their balance by leaping across big pieces of a 100-year-old white oak. ''Our mighty oak was split down the middle by lightning last summer,'' Ms. Eberbach said. ''So we decided to use it in the garden, where kids can study the tree rings.''</p>
        <p>Last week, fourth graders played with the Lean Green Food Machine, a make-believe rhubarb leaf about the size of a kayak that has all kinds of gizmos to help them understand how plants make food from the sun, water and carbon dioxide. They pushed on bellows to send air through the giant stomata, or holes, in the fiberglass leaf, as a docent explained how oxygen and water are released from the holes during photosynthesis.</p>
        <p>''How many teachers, with a master's in education, could explain photosynthesis?'' asked Gregory Long, the president of the New York Botanical Garden. ''Like, none. So this is a huge help to them.''</p>
        <p>While tests can't begin to measure the value of what a garden or natural space can mean to children, if their imaginations are sparked and their minds engaged, reading and math scores may rise. ''Over all, we have seen increases in science and reading proficiency,'' said Sandra Kase, the principal of Claremont Community School in the Bronx, where students grow things in a community garden next door. The school also has a long association with the botanical garden, with many of its children tilling plots in the family garden there. Mrs. Kase was in on the brainstorming for the adventure garden.</p>
        <p>The garden's Adirondack cottage has a sunny lab where children can look at the stomata of a real leaf under a microscope. There is also a herbarium, where students can press a plant onto the same high-quality paper that botanists use. A 15-minute film about plant scientists stars Bronx children and botanists from the botanical garden. The film is a lively look at what plant scientists do: adventurers paddling dugout canoes and climbing trees, they don't look like nerds at all.</p>
        <p>Outside the cottage, two fourth graders were trying to get some stuff about seed dispersal straight. ''When the flower dies the petals fall off, but the seeds are still there,'' Fernando Brito said.</p>
        <p>''Yeah,'' Christopher Correa said. ''But then a dog might come by, and the seed sticks to his fur, and he does most of the work.''</p>
        <p>Down the path, other children were building a giant bird's nest, using long pieces of straw and marsh grass. Real birds' nests were on display in a case, and out in the marsh, a Canada goose sat on its nest.</p>
        <p>''It's hard work being a bird,'' said Amina Saunders, 10, explaining that birds have to use their beaks for house building.</p>
        <p>Such nonformal education is crucial for learning, experts like Mr. Moore say. ''Children live an imaginary life,'' he said, ''and creating a place where they can have fun in a very free way can motivate them and expand their horizons.''</p>
        <p>For city children, it's especially valuable. As Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew put it, ''There is a tremendous opportunity in this garden for kids to experience a huge array of everything from career options to taking part in a natural world they might otherwise not know.'' He is a keen supporter of gardens in schools, but he doesn't like to measure their value with test scores.</p>
        <p>''Are they going to be reading better because there are gardens in schools?'' said Dr. Crew, an avid gardener himself. ''I don't think that's what it's all about. Having a broader picture of the natural world is a very important foundation for understanding their own responsibilities, that this is not an island unto itself, that they are connected to other living things for which they can assume responsibility. It profoundly changes their own framework.''</p>
        <p>The National Science Foundation has given $1 million to the adventure garden as a model for other programs across the country. The program in the Bronx parallels the state science curriculum for elementary schools and includes teacher training workshops, so teachers a little foggy on the parts of a flower can have some hands-on experience.</p>
        <p>Henry Everett, president of Lexington Associates, an investment partnership, and his wife, Edith Everett, a senior vice president of the securities firm of Gruntal &amp; Company, have contributed millions of dollars for the project, which is named after them, along with corporations and foundations. The whole Children's Adventure Project, which includes maintenance and endowment of the 10-year-old family garden, as well as the new children's garden and various trails through the wetlands and woods, totals $15 million.</p>
        <p>''What you can see growing up here is a whole New York City generation interested in plants,'' said Mr. Long, the botanical garden's president, as he stared out over the pond. ''How could you not be interested? It's so captivating.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Eberbach noted that science always begins with looking. ''If this is successful,'' she said, ''it will be because we helped kids start noticing things. If we can get that 'Aha! This is really cool!' we're on our way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
