<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED7133BF93AA35753C1A96E958260" item-length="1413" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>United States Rebukes Yugoslav Leader on Kosovo  The Clinton Administration accused President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia of ''cosmetic gestures'' that would not be enough to head off NATO air strikes in Kosovo. At the same time, the United States embarked on yet another round of negotiations with him.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>United States Rebukes Yugoslav Leader on Kosovo  The Clinton Administration accused President Slobodan Milosevic of Yugoslavia of ''cosmetic gestures'' that would not be enough to head off NATO air strikes in Kosovo. At the same time, the United States embarked on yet another round of negotiations with him.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The relief agency Doctors Without Borders warned that ethnic Albanian refugees from Kosovo were threatened by food shortages and contaminated drinking water.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>U.S. Debates I.M.F. Lending  Republican Congressional leaders presented the Clinton Administration with a list of lending conditions that they want imposed on the International Monetary Fund in order for Congress to approve $18 billion in new financing. Administration and Congressional officials said they hoped that they could soon agree on compromise legislation to provide the money to the I.M.F.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Iran Reports Clash With Taliban  Iran said its troops had clashed with Taliban forces along the Afghan border and had inflicted heavy casualties in a skirmish. The reported fighting, which followed more than two months of bellicose statements from both sides, would be the first between Iran and the Taliban, whose rival interpretations of Islam have contributed to open hostility.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Iraqi Missile Talks Sought  France asked for a meeting of technical experts at the United Nations to ''clarify'' the results of tests that its scientists had carried out on Iraqi warheads. Earlier American tests had found traces of chemicals linked to VX, a deadly nerve gas. Preliminary results from tests conducted in France and Switzerland did not find VX, but several weapons experts said that final French tests had found traces of VX components.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Japan Apologizes to Korea  Prime Minister Keizo Obuchi offered Koreans an unusually forthright apology for Japanese colonial occupation of the Korean peninsula early in this century. In the complex politics of apology that play an important role in Japan's relations with its East Asian neighbors, the statement marked one more step toward greater public contrition for World War II, and South Korea seemed pleased.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Death Penalty in Terror Attacks  Federal prosecutors in New York said the Government was seriously considering asking for the death penalty for two of the suspects arrested after the bombings of the American Embassies in Kenya and Tanzania in August.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Nobel Prize for Jose Saramago  Jose Saramago, a 75-year-old Portuguese writer who took up literature relatively late in life and whose imaginative novels soon won him a following of readers across Europe and admirers in the United States, was awarded the Nobel Prize in Literature by the Swedish Academy in Stockholm.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-24</p>
        <p>A Divided House Votes For Impeachment Inquiry  The House voted, 258 to 176, to open an impeachment inquiry of President Clinton, after rejecting a Democratic proposal for a more limited investigation. Thirty-one Democrats voted for the Republican plan.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>President Clinton maintained an ordinary schedule and an air of absorption in routine public business.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Among the 31 Democrats who voted for the Republican proposal, all but 6 came from the South and Midwest, and another half-dozen or so are in tough re-election races.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Only 2 of the 50 House members from New York, New Jersey and Connecticut -- Carolyn McCarthy of New York and James Maloney of Connecticut, both Democrats -- broke party ranks in voting on the Republican measure.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>A Federal judge said she would begin releasing evidence from the Paula Jones lawsuit on Oct. 19.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Attorney General Janet Reno said she would review accusations that Kenneth W. Starr might have misled the Justice Department when he sought permission to investigate the Lewinsky matter.</p>
        <p>A21</p>
        <p>Effort on Spending Bills Stalled  Congressional Republicans and the White House made little progress toward resolving differences over the spending bills needed to keep the Government open.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Nominees on the Long List  The Senate has yet to vote on 225 Clinton Administration nominees for full- and part-time jobs, including dozens who have been approved by Senate committees, as senators prepare to adjourn.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Movement Discloses Its Abuses  The Hare Krishna movement has detailed widespread physical, emotional and sexual abuse of children sent to live in the group's boarding schools in the 1970's and 1980's.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Tobacco Settlement Talks  Cigarette makers would not be required to pass along to consumers the cost of a national settlement that states are negotiating with the tobacco industry. Many public health experts assert that the passing along of such costs is a major weapon in reducing youth smoking.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Hubble Looks at a Distant Past  The Hubble Space Telescope has taken infrared pictures of what may be the most distant objects ever detected, early light from the galactic dawn of the universe.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>No Way, Yet, to Tag Gunpowder  A National Research Council panel said there was no proven way to mark gunpowder to make it more detectable in its use in bombs.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>The Cost to Fight Warming  An arm of the Energy Department has produced a very pessimistic forecast of rising energy prices if the United States fights global warming by clamping down on emissions of heat-trapping gases that come from the burning of fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Pataki Has Strong Lead Over Vallone, Poll Shows  Governor Pataki has a 2-to-1 lead in his re-election campaign against his Democratic opponent, Peter F. Vallone, who has barely registered in voters' minds, a New York Times/ CBS News Poll has found.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Ex-Officer Sent to U.S. Prison  A Federal judge sentenced Francis X. Livoti, a former New York City police officer, left, to 7 1/2 years in prison for violating the Federal civil rights of Anthony Baez, who died after a confrontation with the police in the Bronx in 1994.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Plan for Market Headquarters  City and state officials were scrambling to complete a series of deals that would create new headquarters for the New York, American and Nasdaq Stock Exchanges in lower Manhattan at a cost of more than $700 million to the city and state.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Psychiatrist Found Negligent  A Federal jury found a Manhattan psychiatrist negligent for failing to warn that a doctor undergoing psychoanalysis with him had confessed to being a pedophile.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-30; E31-48</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Knoblauch Owns Up to Lapse  The Yankee second baseman Chuck Knoblauch acknowledged that he made a mistake in not quickly retrieving the ball Wednesday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Padres Shut Down Braves  San Diego took a 2-0 lead in the four-of-seven-game N.L. Championship Series by beating Atlanta, 3-0.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>No Progress in N.B.A. Talks  The N.B.A. and the players union held the first substantive talks on their labor dispute and the league's lockout, but there was no sign of progress toward a settlement.</p>
        <p>D8</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18, 20</p>
        <p>Ripple Effects Reaching U.S.  Investor hopes faded that the American economy could avoid the full effect of the economic downturn that has struck elsewhere. The value of the dollar fell further, the bond market dropped and hundreds of stocks plunged even as the main market gauges showed minimal losses.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Foreign-exchange traders battered the dollar into what looked like a second consecutive free fall before the currency reversed course.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Stock prices tumbled in most markets around the world, before Wall Street mounted a late comeback in the third-heaviest trading session on record. After having fallen 274.20 points at midday, the Dow closed down 9.78, at 7,731.91. The S.&amp; P. 500 was down 11.24, at 959.44, and the Nasdaq was down 43.49, at 1,419.12, its lowest level in 16 months.</p>
        <p>C6</p>
        <p>Ruling Hurts Bid for AMP  A Federal judge dealt a blow to Allied Signal's $9.7 billion hostile takeover bid for AMP, ruling against Allied's effort to seek AMP shareholders' written consent of its offer.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Rough Quarter for Citigroup  Citigroup said it would report an estimated $700 million of net income for the three months ended on Sept. 30, after about $1 billion in losses from the turmoil in financial markets.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: A grim but historic day; competition for credit cards; Knoblauch's knuckleheaded play; huge gains, and huge worries, on AIDS.</p>
        <p>Columns: A. M. Rosenthal, Russell Baker.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E46</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
