<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>There'll Always Be . . .</title>
    <meta content="15VERNONT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1002330"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vernon, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Ronald</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Scientific Romance, A (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980315T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DF1F31F936A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>There'll Always Be . . .</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Vernon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vernon, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Vernon reviews book A Scientific Romance by Ronald Wright (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A SCIENTIFIC ROMANCE</p>
        <p>By Ronald Wright.</p>
        <p>352 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Picador USA. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A SCIENTIFIC ROMANCE</p>
        <p>By Ronald Wright.</p>
        <p>352 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Picador USA. $23.</p>
        <p>London's jumping. As the 20th century nears its end, Dickensian gloom seems all but abolished. The city, like Britain as a whole, has attained the peak of some sort of Brobdingnagian biorhythm. Thanks to mad cow disease, vegetarian restaurants sprout on every block, and not punks but vegans high on carrots and garlic stalk the London Underground. The polyglot sidewalks are crammed with pedestrians of every shade and size dressed in fleece, fake furs, djellabas and turbans, with platform shoes thick as London phone books and faces pierced through every lump and flap. There are theaters everywhere, pubs as well, and pubs in theaters and theaters in pubs. Millennial fever has gripped the city too. Across from the Isle of Dogs, a corona of enormous spikes climbs above the banks of the Thames, resembling a gargantuan jacks ball embedded in the earth: the framework for the Millennium Dome. With a price tag of about $1.25 billion, the Dome has become the object of old Labor's scorn -- for its conspicuous waste -- and of schoolchildren's essay contests, as in ''Name 10 Things to Put in the Dome.''</p>
        <p>What better city, then, in which to set one of the first of what is sure to be a spate of millennium novels? And what an opportunity to pop the gaseous millennium balloon and disclose the hidden costs of a booming economy. Ronald Wright's ''Scientific Romance'' does both with great skill. Wright, an Englishman living in Canada and the author of several history and travel books, has returned home for his first work of fiction, which looks backward, not forward, as it leaps into the future.</p>
        <p>Through a series of fresh takes on some familiar devices -- messages in bottles and posthumous letters -- he manages to place his narrator, David Lambert, at the return of H. G. Wells's empty time machine to a squatter's flat in London in 1999. It seems that Wells had consulted the inventor Nikola Tesla for advice on how to describe the fictional device in his 1895 novel. Tesla sent his protegee, Tatiana Cherenkova, to London, and the beautiful Tatiana not only bedded Wells but built him an actual time machine.</p>
        <p>The science here is deliberately fuzzy, and Wellsian in language. A ''simple path'' to atomic power involves ''a few coils and jars and electrolytes in the presence of certain rare elements,'' and this is used to drive a ''temporal displacement field generator.'' Clearly, Wright's intention is not to invite verisimilitude. Forget about descriptions of gleaming techno-widgets trailing reams of futurist explanations; instead, this time machine is a sort of rusty spiked torpedo on the outside, and on the inside ''a cross between a club car and a diving bell, deeply upholstered in button padding and burgundy leather.''</p>
        <p>Appropriately, David Lambert is a Cambridge Ph.D. in something called industrial archeology, a field he himself has pioneered. His measure of rational skepticism is enough to enable us to suspend our own disbelief but, just in case, the opening chapters invite us to make the same ''unicorn's bargain'' he makes with Wells's time machine -- ''I'll believe in you if you'll believe in me.''</p>
        <p>Partly to escape the millennial follies of London, Lambert travels to A.D. 2500 and finds the Thames running through ''steaming everglades,'' with monkeys roosting in calamander trees beside the ruins of St. Paul's and the tower of Big Ben, like something from Angkor Wat, displaying ''huge fig trees in its clockless eyes.'' Piranhas and crocodiles inhabit the Thames, but London is completely empty of people. The cumulative effect of these passages is powerful, since David is wandering through the ruins of his own civilization, not those of a dead one in the desert. Wright one-ups Shelley's ''Ozymandias'' in the vanity of human achievements department by reminding us that the debris of the year 2500 contains both our past and our future. In other words, London's population -- whatever happened to it -- had to sieve through the city's monuments on the way to its own future wreckage.</p>
        <p>It takes David most of the novel to discover the series of cataclysms that occurred in the half-millennium his time machine leapfrogged. Following the evidence, he walks north from London all the way to Scotland, past mobs of kangaroos hopping across the M1. He is searching for a remnant colony of humans, and to reveal what he finds would spoil the suspense. But the surprises and shocks are both comic and tragic; they unfold like a cross between Evelyn Waugh and Paul Bowles.</p>
        <p>Along the way, David also remembers events from his youth, thus uncorking a narrative that flows simultaneously in opposite directions. His route to Scotland is the same he'd once taken (in 1988) with an Egyptologist named Anita, the woman he'd stolen from his Cambridge friend, Bird. She has since died of -- what else? -- Creutzfeldt-Jakob disease, the human version of mad cow disease. In fact, David has learned that he has it too; hence his inability to escape the ghosts of the past and his reckless willingness to travel through time. At the end, the past and future converge ingeniously, and the ingenuity is cubed when we learn that British history, in its lunge toward apocalypse, acted out patterns going back to the time of Macbeth.</p>
        <p>A romance is a tale of improbable events, usually constructed to point a moral. In this case, the moral has to do with a host of eco- and bio-disasters: industrialization, global warming, the population bomb, mad cow disease, along with various unspecified immunity disorders and parasites from the animal kingdom that have gained the ability to attack human beings. Wright's cunningly fashioned story enables his romance to express a powerful nostalgia for explorers of the past without the treacle of nostalgia, as well as a disdain for the postindustrial age without seeming Luddite and without the grating friction of bitterness. Its Victorian version of science fiction manages effects that are rich and Gothic yet somehow innocent of irony. We may ascribe these effects to self-conscious literary echoes, tongue-in-cheek post-modernism or the desire to tell an old-fashioned adventure story: the novel works on all levels. It seldom creaks or groans beneath the weight of its devices, and its flair for description can be positively Dickensian. The result is a fresh take on an old formula -- the dystopian postapocalypse novel -- and a profound meditation on the nature of time.</p>
        <p>John Vernon's most recent novel is ''All for Love: Baby Doe and Silver Dollar.'' He teaches creative writing at the State University of New York, Binghamton.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Vernon's most recent novel is ''All for Love: Baby Doe and Silver Dollar.'' He teaches creative writing at the State University of New York, Binghamton.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
