<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1039134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D6113AF936A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="2482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A2-6</p>
        <p>Terror Threat Closes U.S. Embassy in Albania  The State Department said it had shut down routine operations at the American Embassy in Albania because of ''recent declarations by Islamic extremists against the United States.'' The department ordered some embassy employees to leave Albania and warned Americans not to travel there.  A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A2-6</p>
        <p>Terror Threat Closes U.S. Embassy in Albania  The State Department said it had shut down routine operations at the American Embassy in Albania because of ''recent declarations by Islamic extremists against the United States.'' The department ordered some embassy employees to leave Albania and warned Americans not to travel there.  A6</p>
        <p>Slow Rebuilding in Nairobi  Reconstruction has begun in Nairobi at the site of the blast, with cost estimates in the hundreds of millions of dollars. Big businesses have been immobilized, and small ones may be bankrupted, because insurers refuse to cover the losses. President Daniel arap Moi, whose ruling circle is widely viewed as corrupt, may act as a barrier to further outside aid. A6</p>
        <p>Iraq's Nuclear Plans Detailed  An Iraqi scientist who defected to the United States has publicly described the inner workings of Iraq's three-decade effort to build a nuclear bomb. He said he had trained scientists to resume Iraq's atomic weapons program quickly if the United Nations cut back on its inspections and lifted economic sanctions.  A1</p>
        <p>After Baghdad suspended cooperation with United Nations inspectors earlier this month, the United States and Britain urged the chairman of the inspectors, Richard Butler, not to confront Iraq by trying to conduct a surprise inspection, officials said.  A5</p>
        <p>Rush to Leave Congo Capital  Thousands fled the Congolese city of Kinshasa, after almost every major Western country called for its citizens to leave. Electricity was restored to the city after a 24-hour interruption, but there was increasing uncertainty that the Government would be able to ward off approaching rebel forces.  A3</p>
        <p>Russia's Markets on Upswing  Russia's financial markets rallied after the Kremlin and major Western powers indicated that they were working on more plans to end the nation's economic crisis. President Boris N. Yeltsin said there would be no devaluation of the ruble.  A2</p>
        <p>Myanmar Deports Foreigners  Eighteen foreigners, including six Americans, were sentenced to five years of hard labor for handing out pro-democracy leaflets in Myanmar, but the Government immediately deported them, on the condition that they not violate Myanmar laws again. The 18 foreigners arrived in Bangkok today, many of them met by weeping relatives. (Associated Press)</p>
        <p>Rights Review for East Timor  The United Nations and Indonesia signed an agreement to allow human rights observers access to East Timor. The region has endured civil unrest, guerrilla warfare and rights abuses since Indonesia invaded in 1975 and annexed it early the next year. The United Nations is brokering peace talks with Indonesia and Portugal, the territory's former colonial master, on East Timor's future.  (Associated Press)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A7-11, 14</p>
        <p>Court Strips F.D.A. Of Power Over Tobacco  A Federal appeals court in Virginia ruled that the F.D.A. did not have the authority to regulate cigarettes or smokeless tobacco. The ruling was a setback to anti-smoking groups, state attorneys general and members of Congress who had used the threat of Federal regulation to press the industry to reimburse states for the health costs of smoking, to limit advertising and to stop the marketing of cigarettes to teen-agers. A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Prepares for Monday  President Clinton has virtually cleared his calendar this weekend to prepare for his grand jury testimony in the Monica S. Lewinsky investigation on Monday afternoon. But he will not decide whether to give a public address to the country until he finishes answering prosecutors' questions on closed-circuit television, White House officials said. New details of Ms. Lewinsky's grand jury testimony emerged that could complicate Mr. Clinton's predicament. Ms. Lewinsky told jurors last week that she had performed sex orally and manually on the President on several occasions, lawyers said. A8</p>
        <p>Facing questioning under oath about his private life and with impeachment proceedings tuning up in the wings, Mr. Clinton has almost no one he can turn to for advice, say friends and current and former advisers. A1</p>
        <p>A distillation of two recent polls. A8</p>
        <p>A Rejection of Vouchers  A Federal judge has ruled that three Maine families whose small town does not have a public high school may not use public money to send their children to religious schools. A7</p>
        <p>Balloonist Nears Australia  Steve Fossett threaded his balloon through an atmospheric minefield with the help of meteorologists on the ground and approached the west coast of Australia, completing nearly half of his attempted round-the-world flight. A10</p>
        <p>Churches Press Climate Pact  Major church groups in the United States are mounting an unusually broad and active campaign to persuade the Senate to approve the Kyoto Protocol, an international agreement to fight global warming that was negotiated in Japan last year, leaders of the effort say. A10</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-5</p>
        <p>Mayor Pressing Ahead With Methadone Changes  Mayor Giuliani has decided that heroin addicts treated at city hospitals will typically be allowed to get methadone for no more than three months, health officials said. The policy change, which will occur in about 60 days, affects 2,000 addicts. A1</p>
        <p>Labor Dispute Hinders Rites  A four-month labor dispute at eight Jewish cemeteries in Queens and Brooklyn and on Long Island has left hundreds of mourners unable to dedicate gravestones of relatives and friends, as Jewish custom dictates, because monument company workers refuse to cross the picket lines of cemetery workers. B1</p>
        <p>Brokerage to Build Tower  Morgan Stanley Dean Witter was said to have agreed to build and occupy a one-million-square-foot office tower on Seventh Avenue between 49th and 50th Streets. B1</p>
        <p>Big Raise in Store for Crew  Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew would be paid $245,000 a year, more than any other top school administrator in the country -- as well as President Clinton -- under a new contract. B3</p>
        <p>Tenants Give Up Their Fight  Five elderly tenants who have battled developers' efforts to build a 31-story condominium tower on the site of their Regency-style apartments on the Upper East Side have agreed to a settlement and will move out. B3</p>
        <p>Prisoner Dead in the Hudson  A convicted thief recently charged in three killings kicked out the side window of a police van, hobbled in shackles to the edge of a bridge in Rensselaer County and leapt 65 feet to his death in the rocky shallows of the Hudson River, officials said. The 43-year-old thief had just been sentenced to 24 months in prison for violating probation. B5</p>
        <p>SPORTS C1-8</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS B7-16</p>
        <p>Best Books List, Reconsidered  The Modern Library, faced with widespread criticism of its list of the century's 100 best English-language novels, will significantly change the way it compiles a similar list of nonfiction books later this year. B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY D1-14</p>
        <p>Rates Drop as Stocks Fall  Long-term Treasury rates fell to their lowest level in 30 years -- 5.54 percent on the 30-year Treasury bond -- but stocks continued to slide. The S.&amp; P. 500 is down more than 10 percent from its high, the Wall Street definition of a correction. The Nasdaq and the Russell 2000 have already fallen more than 10 percent, and the Dow, which dropped 34.50 points, to 8,425, is just points away. D1</p>
        <p>The Government in Hong Kong confirmed it had intervened to shore up stock and futures markets by taking the rare step of dipping into its reserves to buy shares and futures contracts because it thought currency traders were improperly manipulating the financial markets. D1</p>
        <p>Partners See Shares Plunge  Shares of two makers of telecommunications equipment, Ciena and Tellabs, partners in a pending $7.1 billion merger, plunged after Ciena said its third-quarter profits would be less than half of expectations. The chief executive of Tellabs said the merger would proceed. D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES D16  Chalmers P. Wylie  The 26-year Congressman from Ohio, who was instrumental in the savings-and-loan bailout, was 77. D16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A12-13</p>
        <p>Editorials: Canada's noble gesture; toll phobia and America's Interstates; the tribulations of Afghanistan; power, electric and electoral.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich, Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Bridge B12</p>
        <p>Weather D15</p>
        <p>Crossword B12</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
