<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Harmful Heat Is More Frequent, Especially at Night, Study Finds</title>
    <meta content="10HEAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068615"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (Noaa)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaffen, Dian (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ross, Rebecca J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EFDF103AF933A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Harmful Heat Is More Frequent, Especially at Night, Study Finds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study by Dr Dian J Gaffen and Rebecca J Ross of National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Air Resources Laboratory finds that extreme summer heat and humidity of kind most threatening to health have become more frequent in US over the last half century; study, published in Dec 10 issue of Nature, also finds that increase in heat stress is greater at night than in daytime; apparent trend toward more extreme heat generally coincides with warming of earth's surface in recent decades; earth's average surface temperature, which has risen one degree in last century, is projected to rise two to six degrees over next century, further increasing humidity and making heat waves more frequent and intense; graph; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Extreme summer heat and humidity of the kind most threatening to health have become more frequent in the United States over the last half century, two Federal researchers say.</p>
        <p>According to their study, in today's issue of the journal Nature, the frequency of extremely hot, humid days and of heat waves lasting several days increased substantially from 1949 to 1995. In terms of the threat to health, however, another finding was especially significant: The increase in heat stress was greater at night than in the daytime.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Extreme summer heat and humidity of the kind most threatening to health have become more frequent in the United States over the last half century, two Federal researchers say.</p>
        <p>According to their study, in today's issue of the journal Nature, the frequency of extremely hot, humid days and of heat waves lasting several days increased substantially from 1949 to 1995. In terms of the threat to health, however, another finding was especially significant: The increase in heat stress was greater at night than in the daytime.</p>
        <p>Many experts say that extremely high temperature and humidity over successive nights is a crucial factor in heat-related deaths. When nearly 600 people died in a heat wave in Chicago in 1995, for example, many of the deaths were attributed to an unremitting combination of record high nighttime heat and humidity that allowed no respite from daytime heat stress.</p>
        <p>Some studies have shown that extreme summer heat has more impact on people's health than any other kind of severe weather and that the elderly are most vulnerable.</p>
        <p>''If these climate trends continue, they may pose a public health problem, particularly as there are increasing numbers of elderly people,'' wrote the authors of the study, Dr. Dian J. Gaffen and Rebecca J. Ross, research meteorologists at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Air Resources Laboratory in Silver Spring, Md.</p>
        <p>The apparent trend toward more extreme heat generally coincides with a warming of the earth's surface in recent decades, globally and in the United States. The dominant view among scientists is that at least some of this warming has been caused by emissions of heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide, which is emitted by the burning of coal, oil, natural gas and wood. The earth's average surface temperature, which has risen one degree in the last century, is projected to rise two to six degrees over the next century, further increasing humidity and making heat waves more frequent and intense. By comparison, surface temperature has risen five to nine degrees since the depth of the ice age 18,000 to 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>While the increasing frequency of extreme heat and humidity cannot be directly linked to the warming trend, Dr. Gaffen said it was ''consistent with what is predicted in the global warming scenario.''</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Karl, director of the National Climatic Data Center, agreed. ''I think these are the types of conditions that will become more frequent and more intense when they do occur'' if the climate warms as projected, Mr. Karl said. ''We've already seen examples of that this past year,'' he added, referring to last summer's heat wave in Texas.</p>
        <p>By and large, Mr. Karl said, the Gaffen-Ross findings ''seem to be consistent with what we know from other analyses.'' He said that if data through 1998 were included in the study, ''I'm sure they would find even stronger trends.''</p>
        <p>Worldwide, the last two years have been the two warmest on record.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gaffen and Ms. Ross had for some time been studying global distributions of temperature and water vapor, and they found an increasing trend of rising humidity accompanying rising temperatures. So, Dr. Gaffen said, they decided to see whether this meant that extremes of heat and humidity were also increasing.</p>
        <p>They defined ''extreme'' as the highest 15 percent of temperature and humidity measurements, as recorded every three hours around the clock in July and August from 1961 through 1990. This threshold, they report, is ''closely correlated'' with levels above which, other researchers say, mortality increases sharply.</p>
        <p>Dr. Gaffen and Ms. Ross analyzed records at 113 Government weather stations around the country, mainly at airports, in search of information on two variables: the combination of temperature and humidity that meteorologists call ''apparent temperature,'' and temperature alone.</p>
        <p>Apparent temperature is a measure of the combined impact of heat and humidity on people and the sensation that results. It is increasing faster than temperature alone, the researchers said, because humidity is increasing faster. This would be expected in a warmer climate, because more water evaporates and the atmosphere can hold more.</p>
        <p>The researchers computed their thresholds of extremity for the average daily temperature, the daily maximum temperature and the daily minimum temperature for July and August at each weather station. They found that from 1949 to 1995, the annual frequency of days on which the thresholds were surpassed increased at all but 16 of the 113 stations. The increases were largest for the minimum ''apparent temperature,'' which basically translates to a measure of combined nighttime heat and humidity.</p>
        <p>At some stations, Dr. Gaffen and Ms. Ross found that over the half century, the number of nights with extremely high apparent temperatures doubled, to about 18 days a year from about 9 days a year in some places. The largest and statistically most significant trends were in some of the nation's most populated areas, especially from the Middle Atlantic States south to Florida, as well as along the West Coast and in big cities in the Southwest. Eight of the 15 cities in which the trend was most pronounced were in the Southeast -- including Miami, which headed the list nationally. The New York metropolitan area did not figure in the study.</p>
        <p>Daytime increases were found to be not nearly as dramatic. In fact, the upward trend was statistically significant only west of the Rocky Mountains.</p>
        <p>East of the Rockies, the apparent temperature increased more than temperature alone. West of the Rockies, where summer humidity increases are less marked, the trends of the two variables were similar.</p>
        <p>The investigators defined heat waves as periods of three or four days in which the average daily apparent temperature exceeded the top 15 percent threshold. On average, they found, each weather station experiences 1.7 three-day heat waves and one four-day heat wave a year. In the contiguous United States, the number of heat waves increased by 88 percent from 1949 to 1995.</p>
        <p>Two caveats have been attached to the study. To some extent, said Dr. Gaffen and Ms. Ross, the rising heat probably reflects increased urbanization; the concrete and asphalt in urban areas absorb and retain more heat than rural areas. But Ms. Gaffen said that most of the trend cannot be explained this way. For one thing, she said, not all the weather stations in the study were in urban areas. For another, the researchers looked for but did not find a correlation between population growth -- a measure of urbanization -- and trends in extreme weather.</p>
        <p>The other caveat was offered by Dr. Laurence S. Kalkstein of the University of Delaware, who has long studied heat and health. The threshold of extreme heat adopted by the researchers was not selected on the basis of the relationship between health and extreme heat, he said. Earlier studies by Dr. Kalkstein found that the threshold at which heat begins to kill people varies from one city to another. ''That's my only disagreement'' with the study, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
