<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Talks Indicate Japan's Links With Russians Are Improving</title>
    <meta content="19JAPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1010966"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japan-International Relations-Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kawana (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hashimoto, Ryutaro (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World War II (1939-45)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3D7133CF93AA25757C0A96E958260" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Talks Indicate Japan's Links With Russians Are Improving</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, April 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Japanese Prime Min Ryutaro Hashimoto and Russian Pres Boris N Yeltsin begin two-day meeting in effort to improve economic cooperation and work toward peace treaty that will finally mark end to territorial disputes dating from World War II; meeting takes place in Japanese resort town of Kawana (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto began a two-day meeting with President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia today in an effort to improve economic cooperation and work toward a peace treaty that would finally mark an end to territorial disputes dating from World War II.</p>
        <p>Both men appeared vigorous and cheerful as they greeted each other with an embrace in the resort town of Kawana, 80 miles southwest of Tokyo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Ryutaro Hashimoto began a two-day meeting with President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia today in an effort to improve economic cooperation and work toward a peace treaty that would finally mark an end to territorial disputes dating from World War II.</p>
        <p>Both men appeared vigorous and cheerful as they greeted each other with an embrace in the resort town of Kawana, 80 miles southwest of Tokyo.</p>
        <p>The meeting is not expected to achieve a breakthrough, but it still marks a steady improvement in Russian-Japanese relations.</p>
        <p>Antagonism between the two countries has been a central feature of the Asian political landscape for decades; they never signed a peace treaty after World War II. Japan resisted economic cooperation with Russia in large part because it insisted on first recovering a group of islands that Russia seized in the closing days of the war.</p>
        <p>Over the last few years, however, Japan has switched tactics. It still wants the return of the islands -- which Japan calls its Northern Territories and Russia says are part of the Kurile Island chain. But Tokyo now seems prepared to discuss other issues and improve ties in the hope that this will eventually lead to return of the islands.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to having frank talks with Ryu,'' Mr. Yeltsin said, using a nickname for the Japanese Prime Minister. The two leaders disclosed little about their conversation today, but they are to hold a news conference on Sunday after their meetings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hashimoto's strategy has been to try to build trust and a personal relationship with Mr. Yeltsin. To that end he organized what he called a ''no necktie'' summit meeting in a resort villa. In Japan, it is often said that officials find it easier to speak directly and get to the bottom of a problem when they are meeting informally and have shed their neckties -- or easiest of all when they have shed everything and are drinking sake while bathing together nude.</p>
        <p>This meeting will not go that far, however, and in any case it is unclear whether the informality will make much difference for Mr. Yeltsin, who is impetuous and brash and thus everything that Mr. Hashimoto is not.</p>
        <p>The main point of the meeting will be to further develop the plan outlined at a similar meeting in Russia last November to achieve a peace treaty by 2000.</p>
        <p>As part of the economic cooperation measures envisioned in that plan, Mr. Hashimoto is expected to announce that he will make it easier to provide Japanese trade insurance for transactions with Russia. That step might in turn lead to more Japanese investment in Russia.</p>
        <p>The two countries will also discuss cooperation in combating global warming, and in organizing disaster drills in the Sea of Japan between their naval forces. They may also call for a regular security dialogue in Asia involving Japan, Russia, China and the United States.</p>
        <p>If the two nations can sign a peace treaty and improve relations, then there is potential for a mutually beneficial economic partnership. Russia has vast quantities of untapped natural resources in its far East, areas closer to Tokyo than to Moscow. And Japan has the technology and capital to exploit those resources, as well as the need for them to power its industry.</p>
        <p>Trade and investment between the two are already increasing, though slowly. And a fishing agreement signed in February may resolve disputes that in the past have frequently led Russian patrol vessels to seize Japanese fishing boats. In a sign of improved relations last year, a Russian destroyer made a courtesy call on a Japanese port for the first time in 103 years.</p>
        <p>After meeting today in Kawana and walking together with arms around each other, Mr. Yeltsin and Mr. Hashimoto burst into a wedding being held at the resort and offered their congratulations. Mr. Yeltsin kissed the stunned bride on both cheeks.</p>
        <p>''I hope you have many children,'' Mr. Yeltsin told her. ''I would like to convey the best wishes of the entire Russian people to you.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hashimoto is planning to visit Russia for further talks this fall, and Mr. Yeltsin is expected to return to Japan again next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
