<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trenton Takes On Impact Fees, Licenses and Little League</title>
    <meta content="20LEGI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="GOVERNMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Androstenedione (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drivers Licenses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Toms River (Nj)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Cardinals</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgwire, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sucato, Kirsty</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drivers Licenses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2D91630F933A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trenton Takes On Impact Fees, Licenses and Little League</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRSTY SUCATO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sucato, Kirsty</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Highlights of some bills put before New Jersey Legislature following six-week summer recess; bill would ban sale of androstenedione, used by Mark McGwire, to minors; another would allow residents to choose their electricity supplier; Assembly committee approves bill to make it felony to kill or injure police animal; Gov Christine Whitman signs into law bill that would delay full driving privileges until age 18; lawmakers plan to name street in honor of Little League World Series c hampionship team from Toms River; Assembly committee approves bill to restore cuts to prescription drug program for elderly and disabled; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawmakers returned to Trenton on Monday after a six-week summer recess to consider a new round of bills. Here are some highlights:</p>
        <p>IMPACT FEES: Towns could charge developers a fee to help pay for a wide array of municipal improvements under a bill approved on Monday by the Assembly's Local Government and Housing Committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawmakers returned to Trenton on Monday after a six-week summer recess to consider a new round of bills. Here are some highlights:</p>
        <p>IMPACT FEES: Towns could charge developers a fee to help pay for a wide array of municipal improvements under a bill approved on Monday by the Assembly's Local Government and Housing Committee.</p>
        <p>Under the bill, municipalities could set their own fees, known as impact fees, to be used for transportation, water or sewer projects, flood control and school construction. Currently, towns can only charge builders for on-site improvements like roads and sewers, and to help build affordable housing, said Charles A. Richman, an assistant commissioner in the State Department of Community Affairs.</p>
        <p>Supporters say the fees would help reduce property taxes in communities that are developing rapidly. In a report made public on Wednesday, the Governor's Commission on Property Taxes recommended the measure. But builders oppose the fees because they say the costs will be passed on to homebuyers, amounting to a double taxation.</p>
        <p>A Senate version of the bill cleared committee in June. The bill now goes to the Assembly's Appropriations Committee.</p>
        <p>McGWIRE BILL: Under a bill introduced in the Assembly on Thursday, New Jersey would become the first state to ban the sale of androstenedione, a drug that increases the level of testosterone, to minors. Mark McGwire of the St. Louis Cardinals, who earlier this month broke the season home run record of Roger Maris, disclosed earlier this summer that he uses the drug, which is legal.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Herbert C. Conaway, a Democrat from Delran who co-sponsored the bill, said there had not been adequate safety studies of the drug, which is sold over the counter.</p>
        <p>''Mark McGwire is a grown man and is free to decide what legal substance he puts into his body,'' Mr. Conaway said. ''But as a highly respected role model to millions of kids, his actions could send the wrong message: that improved performance on the field is worth the health risk.''</p>
        <p>Under the bill, vendors who sold or offered androstenedione to children would be fined $250 for a first offense, $500 for a second offense and $1,000 thereafter. The bill now goes to the Assembly's Health Committee.</p>
        <p>DEREGULATION: A bill that would allow residents to choose their electricity supplier beginning next June was introduced in the Senate and the Assembly last week.</p>
        <p>Currently, the state is served by four power companies, which operate like monopolies within their own regions. Under the bill, consumers could choose between the four utilities -- Public Service Electric &amp; Gas, GPU, Atlantic Electric and Rockland Electric. Rates would be ''unbundled,'' or listed separately in electricity bills, said Geraldine Mehu, a spokeswoman for the State Board of Public Utilities.</p>
        <p>The bill, which now goes to Assembly and Senate committees for consideration, would mandate a 5- to 10-percent reduction in electricity rates, and would require utilities to use renewable energy sources like hydroelectric power to generate one half of a percent of their electricity within two years.</p>
        <p>The bill also calls for the deregulation of the natural gas industry by December 1999.</p>
        <p>POLICE DOGS: Prompted by the shooting of a police dog in a standoff in Bradley Beach in June, an Assembly committee on Monday approved a bill that would make it a felony to kill or injure a police animal. Currently, the offense is a misdemeanor, carrying a fine only.</p>
        <p>Under the bill, which now goes to the full Assembly, the penalty would include a maximum prison term of three to five years and a fine of up to $15,000.</p>
        <p>''When you kill or injure a police dog, you are really taking out of the front lines a very serious protector of society,'' said Assemblyman Steven J. Corodemus, a Republican from West Long Branch who sponsored the bill.</p>
        <p>GRADUATED DRIVER'S LICENSE: Beginning in January 2001, New Jersey residents will have to wait until they are 18 to gain full driving privileges under a bill signed into law on Thursday by Gov. Christine Todd Whitman.</p>
        <p>The provisional license bars those under 18 from driving from midnight to 5 A.M. without special permission.</p>
        <p>LITTLE LEAGUE BOULEVARD: Still celebrating the victory of the Toms River team in the Little League World Series, lawmakers plan to name a street in its honor. A portion of Route 37, the main street in Dover Township, would be renamed ''Little League World Championship Boulevard'' under a  resolution introduced in both houses of the Legislature on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The team has already been honored with a parade and celebration that drew an estimated 40,000 fans to Dover Township on Sept. 5, complete with fire engines, antique cars, three marching bands and a visit by the State Senate President, Donald T. DiFrancesco.</p>
        <p>The resolution, approved by the Senate's Transportation Committee, now goes to both houses for a vote.</p>
        <p>PRESCRIPTION ASSISTANCE: The Health Committee of the Assembly approved a bill on Monday that would restore cuts to the state's prescription drug program for the elderly and disabled after residents complained of increased costs.</p>
        <p>In language inserted into the state budget that began July 1, Governor Whitman and Republican lawmakers had limited the quantity of drugs per prescription for which recipients were eligible. Instead of permitting a 34-day supply or 100 doses, whichever is greater, for a co-payment of $5, the cuts allowed only a 34-day supply, effectively tripling costs for residents for whom 100 doses lasted three months.</p>
        <p>The bill, which now goes to the full Assembly, is intended to reinstate the earlier limit. A Senate version was introduced on Thursday.</p>
        <p>VETO: Governor Whitman rejected a bill on Thursday that would have required residents to install carbon monoxide detectors in their homes, saying it was overly broad. She recommended that lawmakers consider an amended version that would require detectors in hotels, boarding houses and multi-family homes.</p>
        <p>The bill now goes back to the Senate, where it originated, for consideration.</p>
        <p>GOVERNMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
