<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The End of the Road</title>
    <meta content="12PROSET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prose, Francine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lurie, Alison</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Last Resort, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE4D81F3FF931A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The End of the Road</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Francine Prose</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prose, Francine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Francine Prose reviews book The Last Resort by Alison Lurie; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Last Resort</p>
        <p>By Alison Lurie.</p>
        <p>321 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $22.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Last Resort</p>
        <p>By Alison Lurie.</p>
        <p>321 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $22.</p>
        <p>A time-tested, generally dependable recipe for a certain sort of novel requires that the writer take a handful of temperamentally dissimilar or discordant characters and toss them together in an exotic locale or confining situation. A mountain sanitarium, a colonial outpost, a small hotel will do nicely. Let isolation or enforced proximity or a new arrival turn up the heat until the stew boils over and makes a mess that the author must tidy up, more or less, by the end of the final chapter.</p>
        <p>In her sparkling, smart new novel, ''The Last Resort,'' Alison Lurie has selected a dozen or so exemplary types, added some highly volatile elements and put them out to sizzle in a paradoxically balmy and claustrophobic setting. Key West, Fla., is, quite literally, the end of the road, the destination to which Lurie's men and women have traveled, each for some variously sensible, desperate, perverse or innocently misguided reason.</p>
        <p>The novel and its readers -- if not always its characters -- have great fun with what these people expect from their southward migration, and what they wind up getting. Jenny Walker, the much younger spouse of a famous nature writer, has left New England in the hope that a change of climate will work its magic on her increasingly distant, preoccupied husband, and turn him back into the loving (if somewhat imperious and exacting) man with whom she has spent much of her sheltered life. Her husband's wish is apparently simpler: all Wilkie Walker wants is to hasten and orchestrate an event -- his own death -- that he fears will happen soon enough without his help or volition. It is not the sand and the sun that have brought him south, but rather the lure of the sea, in which he plans on drowning, and on making it look accidental.</p>
        <p>The Walkers' presence in Key West creates a sort of ripple effect that soon has the town's ''semisolid citizens'' and regular visitors struggling to keep their heads above its surprisingly powerful currents. Among them is the generous, warmhearted Lee Weiss, a former psychotherapist who has officially left the helping professions but who still finds her therapeutic skills very much in demand as the proprietor of Artemis Lodge, a women-only guesthouse. When Wilkie's anomie deprives Jenny of her regular occupation -- typing and editing his manuscripts -- Lee employs Jenny as a part-time receptionist and finds herself romantically attracted to the waiflike, woefully underappreciated ''walking anachronism'' of uxorial devotion. Meanwhile, Gerry Grass, a ''New Age ninny'' and famous California poet, who recites his work to the beat of feathered and beaded drums, is deserted by his sexy, brainless girlfriend, and Jenny becomes the unwilling object of his smarmy attempts at seduction.</p>
        <p>The arc of the narrative may remind readers of Iris Murdoch's early novels: fictional characters as cards in a deck that, by the end, will be shuffled and dealt out in new combinations -- a complicated game witnessed by the minor players as they go about the less romantic business of living and dying. So as Jenny, Lee and Gerry try to sort out their entanglements, Perry (Jacko) Jackson, the handsome gardener, must cope with bad news about his H.I.V. infection and with a visit from his doting mother, his dithering cousin and his scheming aunt. And Molly Hopkins -- the novel's most reasonable character -- must resign herself to enduring the sufferings of old age, specifically, the pains of widowhood and of severe arthritis.</p>
        <p>Molly's lively judgments on the follies around her form the moral core of what -- despite the hedonistic riot of its tropical setting and the bright comedy of its graceful or clumsy erotic pairings -- is a highly moral and serious novel. Fans of Alison Lurie, whose ''Foreign Affairs'' won the Pulitzer Prize for fiction in 1985, will be cheered to discover that time (this is her first novel in a decade) has not blunted the sharpness of her observational powers -- or her impatience with arrogance, thoughtlessness and unwarranted excesses of self-esteem. So our doubts about Wilkie are confirmed, early in the novel, as he imagines the full and satisfying life that Jenny will lead after his demise, juggling ''the many responsibilities and duties that she would have as Wilkie Walker's widow and literary executor. . . . She had an orderly mind: she knew where everything was filed and which articles he would want reprinted. She would say the right things to the right newspapers and fend off predatory journalists. . . . She would work closely and efficiently with the professor in Maine whom Wilkie had already chosen as his official biographer. She would know instinctively which papers this young man should see and which should be held back.''</p>
        <p>Lurie is equally quick to puncture the ballooning piousness and self-regard of popular institutions and accepted social mores: the retirement home resembling ''an up-market motel'' but with ''deeper parallels to an expensive internment camp''; the charities and nature preservation groups that depend ''for their livelihood on a continued supply of the unfortunate individuals it was supposed to help. . . . Meanwhile, when the supply of damaged individuals fell off, there would be a natural tendency to keep them in care as long as possible, to sentimentalize them and treat them as pets.'' She notes the alternating monologues that pass for friendly conversation; the small, exculpatory lies people tell themselves about their vanities and mistakes; the condescension that can so easily turn a compliment into an insult; the Balzacian machinations that commence the moment relatives intuit the existence of anything worth inheriting; and the way that seeing life's troubles from a ''long-term perspective'' frees one from the burden of feeling genuine sympathy or compassion (''Compared to global warming or the destruction of animal species, even awful things like the fatal illness of Jenny's favorite aunt . . . began to diminish and dissolve. Such events, Wilkie's response suggested, were a natural part of life'').</p>
        <p>Much of the novel's humor has a melancholic edge; many of its comic scenes involve Wilkie's botched or foiled attempts at self-obliteration, and the ill-concealed excitement with which Jacko's Aunt Myra makes her practical plans for the aftermath of her nephew's death. What one soon begins to realize is that the notion of a ''last'' resort refers to the temporal as well as the geographical -- to something considerably more terminal than the location of Key West. Lurie writes touchingly, and rather beautifully, about the sorrows of old age, the loss of loved ones, the indignities of physical frailty, the fear of time running out and of the nearness of death. By the end of this astringently bittersweet novel, after the romantic triangles and quadrangles have been divided into suitable pairs, we are struck by how much Alison Lurie has managed to layer into this deceptively frothy romance about men and women ending and renewing their lives in the hothouse (or vacation paradise) perched on the southern tip of our country.</p>
        <p>Francine Prose's most recent book of fiction is ''Guided Tours of Hell.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Francine Prose's most recent book of fiction is ''Guided Tours of Hell.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
