<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Problem, Big Problems: Getting to Work on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="08CUSH$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Natural World" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E6DD173AF93BA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Problem, Big Problems: Getting to Work on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN JR.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Time is running out on resolving conflicts that stand in way of implementing 1997 Kyoto agreement on cutting emissions of gases that are believed responsible for global warming; outline of chief problems and possible solutions (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A YEAR ago, representatives of more than 150 nations faced a midnight deadline in Kyoto, Japan, for talks on an agreement to cut emissions of the gases that scientists warn may be warming the planet. After delegates caucused, argued, slumped and snored through the night -- and toward lunchtime, a pact was reached when the session's chairman decreed that an important conflict would be dealt with later.</p>
        <p>In November of this year, delegates from the same nations gathered in Buenos Aires to set a timetable to carry out the pact. Afterward, delegates were heartened by the progress they had made; they broke up in time for breakfast, with a firm agreement to work a few more years on the pact's biggest obstacles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A YEAR ago, representatives of more than 150 nations faced a midnight deadline in Kyoto, Japan, for talks on an agreement to cut emissions of the gases that scientists warn may be warming the planet. After delegates caucused, argued, slumped and snored through the night -- and toward lunchtime, a pact was reached when the session's chairman decreed that an important conflict would be dealt with later.</p>
        <p>In November of this year, delegates from the same nations gathered in Buenos Aires to set a timetable to carry out the pact. Afterward, delegates were heartened by the progress they had made; they broke up in time for breakfast, with a firm agreement to work a few more years on the pact's biggest obstacles.</p>
        <p>Such is the current status of the international effort to limit global warming: the work that has been done has produced a consensus that something will come of the Kyoto gathering. But the conflicts that clouded the accord have not grown easier to resolve, and time is racing by.</p>
        <p>The United States, long the leading emitter of greenhouses gases, is caught up in this delay. To be sure, the highlight of the Buenos Aires conference was the Clinton Administration's signing of the Kyoto accord. But the American representatives made it clear that they would not submit the agreement to the Senate for approval until many of the Administration's demands are met.  Negotiators at the conference settled on an ambitious two-year timetable for resolving those and other sticking points. But that means approval cannot come until after the 2000 elections, if it occurs at all.</p>
        <p>''Kyoto is not dead,'' said Eileen Claussen, a former State Department negotiator who is the executive director of the Pew Center on Global Climate Change, a public-interest group. ''But I don't know if this can be done in two years.''</p>
        <p>Michael Oppenheimer, a climate expert for the Environmental Defense Fund, an  advocacy group that favors the treaty, said: ''If significant progress is not made by the year 2000, we will never make the 2008 deadlines of the treaty. We have to get the rules in place, or the time will slip away.''</p>
        <p>Groups representing fossil-fuel producers and users are even more skeptical. ''I don't think the protocol is ever going to be ratified,'' said Connie Holmes, the chairwoman of the Global Climate Coalition, which opposes the agreement. ''In about 2001 or 2002, people are going to say, 'My God, we can't do this, let's stretch this thing out.' You need more time if you are going to change as radically as this.''</p>
        <p>Without the United States on board, the world will not meet the targets of the Kyoto Protocol, which calls for industrial countries to drastically cut their greenhouse gas emissions between 2008 and 2012. The United States is supposed to cut its emissions by more than a third, to a level 7 percent lower than 1990. But the Americans are insisting on commitments from the developing world, and on a complex scheme for trading emissions permits and credits. ''On all these issues, the biggest obstacles are political, not technical,'' Ms. Claussen said. ''Technical people could sit down and work out the details. But it all boils down to politics and sovereignty.''</p>
        <p>Here are the main issues that need to be resolved in the Kyoto Protocol:</p>
        <p>The Third World's Role</p>
        <p>PROBLEM: The United States and other developed nations account for about 60 percent of industrial greenhouse gases given off each year. But developing nations, led by China and India, are expected to catch up in about 15 years. By mid-century, they will account for most of the long-term buildup of gases that threaten the climate.</p>
        <p>SOLUTION: The United States says that the least expensive way to head off global warming may be to cut future emissions in other countries overseas. To entice third-world nations to pursue such a path, America favors a ''clean development mechanism,'' which would give donor nations credit for foreign aid or investments that cut emissions in developing countries.</p>
        <p>OBSTACLE: China and India are still resisting calls for big developing countries to promise emissions cuts. African and Latin American countries are more interested, but they want guarantees that they will get their share of the aid.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK: ''The monolithic phalanx that we saw in Kyoto in opposition to any and all participation has completely broken down,'' said Stuart E. Eizenstat, the chief American negotiator. In Buenos Aires, Kazakhstan and Argentina agreed to commit themselves to reductions.</p>
        <p>International Trading</p>
        <p>PROBLEM: It will cost a lot of money to control greenhouse gases -- especially on the rapid timetable that the United States is being asked to meet. If these costs are too high, the Senate will not support the treaty.</p>
        <p>SOLUTION: Many economists say the way to keep costs down is to let countries buy and sell emissions quotas, making the deepest cuts where it is cheapest to do so. The United States would be able to buy its way into compliance with the treaty by paying other industrial countries, like Russia, to cut emissions more than the treaty required.</p>
        <p>OBSTACLE: European nations are the biggest opponents of unfettered trading in emission credits. They are demanding that the United States achieve at least a majority of its emissions reductions within its own borders. Many third-world nations, too, have objected that it is unfair for rich countries to buy their way out of treaty obligations.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK: Mr. Oppenheimer at the Environmental Defense Fund, which favors emissions trading and other market-based pollution controls, says that other nations, realizing how important trading is to the United States, are ''holding it hostage'' as a bargaining chip. But schisms among developing nations are weakening their resistance, and Europeans are recognizing that they need to make concessions to the Americans if the treaty is to work.</p>
        <p>Credit for Early Action</p>
        <p>PROBLEM: Every year that goes by without controls on greenhouse gas emissions makes it harder for the United States and other industrial nations to comply with their targets. Emissions in the United States are currently 10 percent higher than they were in 1990; they rose 1.4 percent in 1997, and the Energy Department expects this trend to continue for another 20 years.</p>
        <p>SOLUTION: Many companies have already invested in energy saving and other approaches to cut their emissions, or are planning to do so soon. To encourage early reductions, legislation has been introduced to give these companies credits for their reductions, which could be used or sold if binding limits on emissions were imposed.</p>
        <p>OBSTACLE: Many treaty opponents in Congress have fought policy measures, like tax cuts. They have even fought voluntary steps that suggest back-door implementation of an unratified treaty.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK: Big companies, even some that would prefer no binding limits on emissions, are lobbying hard to get credits for early action, just in case. ''This is really the one area involving the whole issue of greenhouse gases where I think everybody ought to be able to agree,'' said Todd Stern, the White House official who coordinates the Administration's climate policy.</p>
        <p>Finally, participants are wondering how the American Presidential elections will affect the negotiating timetable -- especially the aspirations of Vice President Al Gore, the world leader most closely associated with the fight against global warming.</p>
        <p>''How does the process of moving toward the year 2000 play with the Presidential election campaign, and with President Clinton's known desire to make progress before he leaves office?'' Mr. Oppenheimer asked. ''Those questions are not imponderable, but they are very big factors, and they make it very hard to figure out where the process will be two years from now.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
