<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Who Pays For Mistakes In Making Electricity?</title>
    <meta content="DEREG.$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northeast Utilities</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tuhus, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5DB1E39F931A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="2001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Who Pays For Mistakes In Making Electricity?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA TUHUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tuhus, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Assembly to consider electricity deregulation again; opponents say latest version of bill is nothing more than bailout for Northeast Utilities, for its multibillion-dollar mismanagement of four closed-down nuclear plants; new bill, like last year's, requires separation of generation assets from transmission and distribution assets of state's utility monopolies, and mandates ten percent base-rate cut in first two years; other provision explained (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEGISLATION to deregulate the electricity industry is giving a repeat performance in the General Assembly this year, following a humiliating final act in last year's session -- the parliamentary equivalent of getting the hook. Some observers are saying the new bill, with careful reworking and attention to its previous shortcomings, is now ready for prime time; others are not so sure.</p>
        <p>The concept of deregulation of the electric utility industry has been captured -- though some would say buried -- in a 125-page proposal known as bill No. 5005. Its purpose, according to proponents like Northeast Utilities, business organizations and many members of the legislature's Committee on Energy and Technology, is to lower the price of electricity for customers, while allowing them more choice in sources of energy they buy, including from renewable options like solar and wind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEGISLATION to deregulate the electricity industry is giving a repeat performance in the General Assembly this year, following a humiliating final act in last year's session -- the parliamentary equivalent of getting the hook. Some observers are saying the new bill, with careful reworking and attention to its previous shortcomings, is now ready for prime time; others are not so sure.</p>
        <p>The concept of deregulation of the electric utility industry has been captured -- though some would say buried -- in a 125-page proposal known as bill No. 5005. Its purpose, according to proponents like Northeast Utilities, business organizations and many members of the legislature's Committee on Energy and Technology, is to lower the price of electricity for customers, while allowing them more choice in sources of energy they buy, including from renewable options like solar and wind.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the bill say it is nothing more than a bail-out for Northeast Utilities. The company is the largest utility company in New England, serving Connecticut through its subsidiary, Connecticut Light and Power, except for Bridgeport and New Haven, which are served by United Illuminating Company. (United Illuminating is in better financial shape than Northeast Utilities, and has its own problems with the bill.)</p>
        <p>Opponents say the bail-out is necessitated largely by the multibillion-dollar mismanagement of Northeast Utilities' four nuclear power plants, all of which are shut down, one permanently. Some of those opposing the bill have formed a coalition called POWER (People Opposing Wasteful Energy Ripoffs) to press their case. The coalition includes labor, environmental and consumer groups, some of the same groups that last year helped defeat utility restructuring. Last year's bill was widely seen, in the words of one legislative leader, as a ''giveaway for Northeast Utilities at the expense of consumers and business.'' (Guy R. Mazza, the state's Consumer Counsel, answers questions on utility issues, Page 3.)</p>
        <p>The new bill, like last year's, requires the separation of the generation assets from the transmission and distribution assets of the state's utility monopolies. It is the generation piece that is being deregulated, thereby giving other companies an opening to sell power to customers. Under the bill, Northeast Utilities and United Illuminating must sell their generating plants, though they are allowed to bid to buy them back. The bill mandates, for the first two years after deregulation, a 10 percent cut in the rate base compared with Dec. 31, 1996, rates.</p>
        <p>Two items will be included in the rate base: a competitive transition assessment and a systems benefit charge. The former permits recovery of what are called stranded costs, investments in generating plants, equipment and services not yet paid for. Total stranded costs for Northeast Utilities and United Illuminating are estimated at $3 billion to $5 billion.</p>
        <p>The position of the utilities operating in Connecticut is that consumers must pay to cover all the stranded costs in order for the utilities to compete as deregulation goes forward. For example, if a power plant is licensed for 40 years and the capital investment is scheduled to be recovered over those 40 years, the state's Department of Public Utility Control, the utilities say, should not be able to change the rules partway through the time period.</p>
        <p>The systems benefit charge, payable by all customers starting July 1, 1999, would, according to an analysis of the bill by the General Assembly's Office of Legislative Research, ''pay for consumer education, low-income energy conservation and dislocated worker programs, and the costs of hardship protections, post-retirement safe shutdown and site protection, nuclear plant decommissioning, and spent nuclear fuel storage and disposal.''</p>
        <p>Stranded costs would be paid for through the selling of bonds, which in turn would be paid for by consumers in their monthly electric bills, something POWER opposes. The position of Northeast Utilities is that such a bonding method, called securitization, would cost consumers less, that otherwise the consumers would be paying the competitive transition assessment directly.</p>
        <p>''We think these fees and charges are a subsidy for Northeast Utilities,'' says Mike DeRosa, a member of the Connecticut Green Party and a founder of POWER. ''So that negates the fundamental issue, which is, are we or are we not going to have competition? If you give one company a lot of money, they will have an advantage over other companies. The bottom line will be that utilities that offer solar, wind and other renewable energy sources will be forced to compete in a biased market where environmentally destructive companies are subsidized by the state while environmentally friendly producers are dismissed as being 'uncompetitive'.''</p>
        <p>Advocates of deregulation point to several other industries that have been deregulated and say that such action has lowered costs for consumers. Mr. DeRosa points to all the deregulated industries to make a point of his own: ''The term stranded costs has never been heard before in previous deregulatory deliberations. Firms in the telecommunications, trucking, railroad and aviation business did not have their losses refunded after going through deregulation. Why should electric utilities get a multibillion-dollar refund?''</p>
        <p>The Northeast Utilities position is that the bill does not provide enough money to cover its stranded costs. A spokesman for the company, Bruno Ranniello, says ''We want to recover 100 percent of our stranded costs through securitization.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ranniello says securitization is now limited to just the amount required to cover the consumer rate reductions. Northeast Utilities estimates total coverage of its stranded costs at $3 billion. Though such a system would be a benefit to Northeast Utilities shareholders, Mr. Ranniello says it would also be to the advantage of consumers, because the bonds -- with the backing of the state -- could be bought at low interest rates, enabling consumers to pay the money back at low rates.</p>
        <p>Joel Gordes, an independent energy consultant from Colebrook who is  helping Rhode Island implement its deregulation legislation, says that what percentage of stranded costs is  securitized is meaningless. ''It's the dollar amount of stranded costs that is important,'' Mr. Gordes says, ''and that is going to be determined after the passage of the legislation,'' by the state's Department of Public Utility Control.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes says this year's bill is an improvement over last year's in its inclusion of money for conservation and renewable energy, and in its more limited definition of stranded costs. He says the bill's biggest drawback is that, in order for the utilities to recover stranded costs related to their nuclear power plants, the plants must be operating.</p>
        <p>''That will mean throwing good money after bad,'' says Mr. Gordes, who does not believe that nuclear power plants can be competitive in the long run. He says, ''The only way to pay for nuclear power is to have captive ratepayers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes, a former state legislator, says the debate has created strange bedfellows. Robert A. Maddox Jr., a Republican Representative of Bethlehem whom Mr. Gordes describes as a friend who is conservative on most issues as well as a dedicated environmentalist, wrote a paper very critical of securitization; that view is shared by the Green Party, Connecticut Citizens Action Group, Don't Waste Connecticut and the Connecticut Energy Cooperative Project.</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddox, who has a master's degree in business administration, writes that ''Securitization has the potential to create a very large reverse Robin Hood effect. Take from the homeowner and small business and give to the large institutional and wealthy investor.''</p>
        <p>He also writes that restructuring of the electric utilities industry can only work through fair and open competition among all the companies that want to compete.</p>
        <p>But, he continues, ''Securitization distorts the playing field by giving Northeast Utilities and United Illuminating a competitive advantage.''  He concludes by pointing out that ''public securitization has never been implemented for an electric company anywhere in the United States. Public securitization simply privatizes all the gains and 'societizes' all the costs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes offers a compromise  on the securitization issue: He proposes securitizing just a small portion of the total amount said to be needed the first year, and covering the larger amounts said to be needed  only if it doesn't hurt consumers.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists say they prefer going along with some distasteful aspects of the bill in order to get the fraction of a cent per kilowatt hour mandated for conservation and renewable energy. To them, that's  preferable to the possibility that Northeast Utilities, without restructuring, would go into bankruptcy proceedings, leaving the courts rather than the legislature in charge of the outcome.</p>
        <p>Homer Scott, who is chairman of the legislative committee of the state chapter of the Sierra Club, thinks the courts would not be concerned about conservation and renewable resources, that ''anything that's done will be done to protect the investors.''</p>
        <p>Jim Newberry, an energy consultant and part-time staffer for the Connecticut Cooperative Energy Project, is opposed to the bill.</p>
        <p>''There are some good things in it,'' he says, but he adds that it contains so many problems ''that rebuilding it page by page is inappropriate, especially in a short session.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newberry says the issue of whether Northeast Utilities would go into bankruptcy without restructuring is ''a political judgment.''</p>
        <p>''Bankruptcy,'' he continued, ''is not so unpalatable if the people of the state can move into a more advantageous situation long term. It may be a way for the state to consider public ownership, such as an electricity cooperative, versus private ownership.'' He says such cooperatives exist in 44 states, but are not allowed under Connecticut law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newberry describes bill No. 5005 as ''the most important bill of the past decade'' in terms of its impact on consumers. But, he insists, ''It has nothing to do with renewable energy, reduced rates or competition.'' He and several other critics point out that after the two years of guaranteed 10 percent reduction in electric rates for consumers, anything could happen. He says even the 10 percent could be more a ceiling than a floor, allowing the industry to lower rates less than it might be able to.</p>
        <p>In the discussion of rates, another issue has been virtually ignored: If the price consumers pay goes down, usage is likely to go up, and producing more energy would produce more pollution -- unless the energy produced is from a renewable source. But renewables account for only a tiny fraction of the total, both under the current system and under the new bill. Mr. Gordes noted that ''This is a place where consumer interest and environmental interest don't converge.''</p>
        <p>Nationally, electricity deregulation involves huge amounts of money. In CounterPunch, a muckraking newsletter published in Washington, D.C., the editors Ken Silverstein and Alexander Cockburn write that the amount is on a par with the savings and loan debacle of the 1980's.</p>
        <p>They call it ''a convulsion of huge importance'' and say that it ''will cost the public upwards of $500 billion.'' That is the amount, they say, that utilities have tied up in debt on their nuclear power plants and that they would like to pass along to ratepayers and taxpayers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Newberry doesn't agree with those who say that this is a ''now or never'' year for electric utility deregulation in Connecticut. ''The idea that other states around us are deregulating and we will be left behind if we don't,'' he says, ''that's not true.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Newberry went on to say that  ''California is trying to fix their law, and Massachusetts is trying to repeal theirs. If we get out of the short session and do some planning for next year, and also see what the fallout is from other states,'' Connecticut could be a winner the third time around.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
