<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2DD1331F937A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="2334" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A3-7</p>
        <p>Neither U.S. Nor Iraq Gives Way in Confrontation  President Clinton and Saddam Hussein made clear the vastness of the differences between them, offering contradictory analyses of the crisis and incompatible solutions. While calling Mr. Hussein's defiance of the United Nations unacceptable, Mr. Clinton did not issue an ultimatum and offered a small opening to Mr. Hussein to end the impasse. A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A3-7</p>
        <p>Neither U.S. Nor Iraq Gives Way in Confrontation  President Clinton and Saddam Hussein made clear the vastness of the differences between them, offering contradictory analyses of the crisis and incompatible solutions. While calling Mr. Hussein's defiance of the United Nations unacceptable, Mr. Clinton did not issue an ultimatum and offered a small opening to Mr. Hussein to end the impasse. A1</p>
        <p>At the United Nations, representatives of France, Russia and China urged Secretary General Kofi Annan to go to Baghdad to try to persuade Mr. Hussein to back down. But Mr. Annan refused, saying he would go there only if such a mission were likely to succeed. A6</p>
        <p>More Air Force planes were sent to the Persian Gulf as the United States continued to build a force large enough to carry out a sustained bombing campaign. A6</p>
        <p>Riots in Indonesia Continue  At least eight people were killed and scores were injured as soldiers, students and thugs clashed in Jakarta. Parliament adopted several decrees intended to nudge Indonesia toward a more democratic future and voted to hold general elections next spring and to begin reforms. A1</p>
        <p>Motive of Attack Disclosed  One of the clear but unstated objectives of the American missile strike in Afghanistan last August was to kill Osama bin Laden and as many of his lieutenants as possible, Administration officials acknowledged. According to the officials, White House lawyers conducted a secret review in the months before the attack and concluded that such operations were legal under American and international law. A3</p>
        <p>Political Deal in Cambodia  Cambodia's rival political parties broke a three-month deadlock and agreed to a coalition government that left Hun Sen, who seized power in a coup last year, as sole Prime Minister. A7</p>
        <p>I.M.F. Announces Brazil Aid  The International Monetary Fund announced a $41.5 billion rescue package for the Brazilian economy that would require a level of sustained economic discipline and sacrifice that the largest nation in Latin America has not demonstrated in the past. A4</p>
        <p>Space Station Grounded  NASA and the Russian Space Agency have agreed to set aside a last-minute Russian request to launch an international space station into an orbit closer to Mir. A5</p>
        <p>Struggle at Talks on Climate  Negotiators in the Buenos Aires talks on global warming were locked in a last-minute struggle over the shape and pace of the work schedule for the Kyoto Protocol, an international agreement reached a year ago in Japan. A7</p>
        <p>World Briefing A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A8-11</p>
        <p>Clinton and Jones Agree To $850,000 Settlement  President Clinton agreed to pay Paula Corbin Jones $850,000 to settle her legal claim that he crudely propositioned her seven years ago. Ms. Jones dropped what she had once called her most important demand: that Mr. Clinton apologize and admit wrongdoing. Through his lawyer, the President continued to call Ms. Jones's accusation baseless. The settlement averted the possibility that an appeals court would reinstate her suit, and White House officials believe the settlement will help Mr. Clinton avoid impeachment. A1</p>
        <p>The independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr again indicted President Clinton's longtime friend, Webster L. Hubbell, left, in connection with the Whitewater matter. The 15-count indictment included the accusation that Mr. Hubbell had sought to conceal from Federal regulators actions of Hillary Rodham Clinton. A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr sent evidence concerning Kathleen E. Willey to the House Judiciary Committee, but did not say the material constituted grounds for impeachment. Ms. Willey accused the President of groping her in the White House. Mr. Clinton denied the assertion under oath. A10</p>
        <p>A Marine Corps officer who wrote a newspaper column rebuking President Clinton as an ''adulterous liar'' got the military equivalent of a stern talking-to from his commander, but was not otherwise punished. A10</p>
        <p>States' Tobacco Settlement  The nation's four biggest cigarette makers and officials of eight states have reached agreement on the outlines of a settlement designed to resolve all remaining state claims over health costs related to smoking, attorneys general and industry lawyers involved in the talks said. The plan would cost the tobacco companies $206 billion over 25 years and would restrict cigarette advertising and marketing, while eliminating the threat of state suits to recover the Medicaid costs of treating people with smoking-related illnesses. A1</p>
        <p>There is no shortage of proposals for how to spending New York's $20 billion share of the settlement. A9</p>
        <p>Church Charged in Death  Florida prosecutors filed criminal charges against an arm of the Church of Scientology, alleging abuse or neglect of a disabled adult and the unauthorized practice of medicine in connection with the death of a church member while she was under Scientologists' care. A8</p>
        <p>Preserving the Everglades  Officials in Florida decided to buy out hundreds of residents who live in an unincorporated area of west Miami-Dade County, in a move that environmentalists hailed as a significant step toward restoring the balance of water in the Everglades. A8</p>
        <p>Lawsuit Over a Shipwreck  Relatives of the crew of a pleasure ship lost during Hurricane Mitch have sued the vessel's owners for sending it to sea as the storm approached. A8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION  B1-7</p>
        <p>21 Troubled City Schools Are Added to State's List  State Education Commissioner Richard Mills designated 21 New York City schools as failing, bringing the total number of failing schools in the city to 97, which is 3 more than last year. About 9 percent of the 1,100 schools in the city are now designated as failing; only four schools elsewhere in the state are on the list. B1</p>
        <p>Whitman Has Appendectomy  Governor Whitman of New Jersey had surgery in Morristown to remove her appendix. B4</p>
        <p>Officers Accuse an Officer  Two of the four officers facing Federal civil rights charges in the brutalization of Abner Louima have incriminated Officer Justin A. Volpe, according to court documents. B2</p>
        <p>Mother and Lost Son Reunited  A 15-year-old autistic boy found wandering in the Erie Lackawanna Terminal in Hoboken, N.J., on Tuesday was reunited with his mother. B3</p>
        <p>Record Price for Ruth Ball  The baseball that Babe Ruth hit for the first home run in Yankee Stadium was sold for $126,500, a record for a baseball sold at auction. B3</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS B9-17</p>
        <p>Resignations of Protest  Two prominent American poets, both women, have resigned as chancellors of the Academy of American Poets to protest the absence of blacks and other minority groups on the academy's board of chancellors. B9</p>
        <p>SPORTS  D1-6</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES  C16</p>
        <p>Red Holzman  The coach who led the New York Knicks to their only two N.B.A. championships. He was 78. C16</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY  C1-15</p>
        <p>Consolidating Auto Industry  More large mergers are likely among auto makers because of a worldwide excess of assembly plants and the just completed marriage of Daimler-Benz and Chrysler, industry leaders said in interviews. C1</p>
        <p>Uncertain Markets Await Fed  The stock market finished mixed as investors looked toward the Fed meeting on Tuesday. The Dow rose 89.85 points, to 8,919.59, and the S.&amp; P. 500 climbed 8.03, to 1,125.72. But the Nasdaq fell 3.07, to 1,847.99. The price of the 30-year Treasury bond rose 2/32 , to 1004/32 , while its yield fell to 5.24 percent from 5.25 percent. C1</p>
        <p>Retail sales rose in October at the fastest pace in five months and producer prices crept higher, leading some economists to predict that the Fed would not cut rates. C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL  A12-13</p>
        <p>Editorials: Lawsuits against handguns; the case of Jonathan Pollard; Brazil gets a loan; Verlyn Klinkenborg on winter.</p>
        <p>Columns: Frank Rich.</p>
        <p>Bridge B16</p>
        <p>Weather B18</p>
        <p>Crossword B15</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
