<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Academy Disputes Attack on Global Warming</title>
    <meta content="T22WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seitz, Frederick (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EED71F3CF931A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Academy Disputes Attack on Global Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Academy of Sciences, in extraordinary move, disassociates itself from stand by former president, Dr Frederick Seitz, attacking scientific conclusions underlying international efforts to control emissions of industrial waste gases believed to cause global warming; Seitz circulates petition urging United States to reject treaty imposing limits on emissions of carbon dioxide and other gases; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Academy of Sciences has taken the extraordinary step of disassociating itself from a statement and petition circulated by one of its former presidents that attack the scientific conclusions underlying international efforts to control emissions of industrial waste gases believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>The petition, which its backers say has been signed by 15,000 scientists, calls for the Government to reject the Kyoto Protocol, a treaty imposing limits on emissions of gases like carbon dioxide that was negotiated by more than 150 countries in Kyoto, Japan, last December.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Academy of Sciences has taken the extraordinary step of disassociating itself from a statement and petition circulated by one of its former presidents that attack the scientific conclusions underlying international efforts to control emissions of industrial waste gases believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>The petition, which its backers say has been signed by 15,000 scientists, calls for the Government to reject the Kyoto Protocol, a treaty imposing limits on emissions of gases like carbon dioxide that was negotiated by more than 150 countries in Kyoto, Japan, last December.</p>
        <p>The petition was accompanied by what appeared to be the report of a scientific study concluding that emissions of carbon dioxide, the principal greenhouse gas, pose no climatic threat and instead amount to ''a wonderful and unexpected gift from the Industrial Revolution.'' The article was attached to a letter by Dr. Frederick Seitz, a past president of the academy and president emeritus of Rockefeller University, urging people to sign the petition and calling attention to the article.</p>
        <p>Many atmospheric scientists and ecologists who believe global warming to be a serious threat had expressed anger and alarm over the article because it was printed in a format and type face similar to that of the academy's own journal, Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. In his letter, Dr. Seitz, a longtime skeptic on the question of global warming, also identified himself as a past academy president.</p>
        <p>On Monday, citing ''confusion'' created by the petition and the unpublished article, the Council of the Academy, its governing board, disassociated itself from them and said in a statement that the petition ''does not reflect the conclusion of expert reports of the academy.''</p>
        <p>The eight-page article accompanying the petition was described by its authors as a review of research literature on global warming. It concluded that ''predictions of harmful climatic effects due to future increases in minor greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide are in error and do not conform to current experimental knowledge.'' It cited increased plant growth stimulated by atmospheric carbon dioxide as a benefit.</p>
        <p>Many scientists believe that global temperatures are rising because increasing levels of carbon monoxide and other man-made gases will trap and retain heat from the sun in a process similar to what happens in a greenhouse. They say this warming trend could cause sea levels to rise and severely disrupt the earth's climate and biological system.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bruce Alberts, the president of the academy, said he had received a number of telephone calls from influential members of Congress about the academy's association with the petition and the article.</p>
        <p>The ''clear message,'' Dr. Alberts said, was that ''people are confused.'' So the academy's governing council, in its statement on Monday, said that the petition had ''nothing to do'' with the academy and that the article was never published in the academy's journal.</p>
        <p>It also noted that the most recent academy report on global warming, in 1991, concluded that ''greenhouse warming poses a potential threat sufficient to merit prompt responses.'' This is in line with the most authoritative assessment of the question, by a panel of scientists advising the United Nations, which predicted in 1995 that the next century would bring widespread climatic dislocations if the greenhouse effect was not restrained.</p>
        <p>Dr. Arthur B. Robinson, the leading author of the article circulated with Dr. Seitz's letter, said it had been submitted for review by other scientists and for publication in a scientific journal but had not yet been published.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson said he ''never intended to imply'' that the academy endorsed it. He also said that he ''just wanted to put it into familiar format,'' and that he liked the academy journal's format. He noted that nowhere did the article say it was endorsed by the academy or published by its journal.</p>
        <p>Dr. Seitz, a physicist who was president of the academy in the 1960's, said, ''It's true; the academy was not involved.'' He also said he had urged the authors of the Robinson paper to  ''withdraw it'' and submit it to a journal for publication.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robinson is a physical chemist at the Oregon Institute of Science and Medicine in Cave Junction, Ore.., In an interview, Dr. Robinson described the institute as ''very small,'' and said its research was ''devoted mostly to the study of biochemistry.''</p>
        <p>He said the article was circulated before it was published because the delay and copyright considerations would have prevented it from being used in petition drive.</p>
        <p>Of the 15,000 signers of the petition, Dr. Robinson said, about 2,100 were physicists, geophysicists, climatologists and meteorologists, ''and of those the greatest number are physicists.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
