<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Calendar Confusion, in Sandals and T-Shirts</title>
    <meta content="05WARM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE6DD1E3BF936A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Calendar Confusion, in Sandals and T-Shirts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City residents enjoy spring in December as temperature climbs to record-breaking 74 degrees; photos; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sure, it was pleasant for Kevin Kane, a 43-year-old playwright, to stroll Central Park in a T-shirt and khaki shorts. Who wouldn't enjoy late May warmth in early December?</p>
        <p>But as the temperature climbed to a record-breaking 74 degrees, Mr. Kane could not shake the feeling that heat in December was unnatural and possibly an ominous sign of problems like global warming. ''It's a little scary,'' he said. ''It's strange. I worry about my daughter.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sure, it was pleasant for Kevin Kane, a 43-year-old playwright, to stroll Central Park in a T-shirt and khaki shorts. Who wouldn't enjoy late May warmth in early December?</p>
        <p>But as the temperature climbed to a record-breaking 74 degrees, Mr. Kane could not shake the feeling that heat in December was unnatural and possibly an ominous sign of problems like global warming. ''It's a little scary,'' he said. ''It's strange. I worry about my daughter.''</p>
        <p>But many of the people walking or jogging or sunning themselves in the park were simply luxuriating in the unseasonal spring. After seven consecutive days, some were beginning to take the warmth for granted, like Floridians who think that Christmas shopping in sandals and a T-shirt is perfectly normal.</p>
        <p>For many New Yorkers, it no longer seemed peculiar to go outside without a sweater, let alone a jacket, or to enter a subway car and feel a chilly blast from the air-conditioning. As a rider on the No. 1 line pointed out briskly: ''It's 70 degrees outside.''</p>
        <p>In fact, customers who had rented air-conditioning units for their homes and procrastinated about returning them were calling to request extensions, said Mel Parker, owner of Aabco, a Manhattan air-conditioning repair and rental store.</p>
        <p>A quick scan of the crowds in midtown Manhattan indicated that most people had dressed appropriately for the occasion. Relatively few were carrying -- let alone wearing -- coats or jackets. And if hot chocolate wasn't selling, ice cream definitely was. The Ben &amp; Jerry's at Times Square dispensed almost twice as many cones as usual in December, said Heidy Ardon, the supervisor.</p>
        <p>All over Bryant Park, people on lunch breaks were lounging outside, chewing and sipping and reading and talking. ''I haven't brought my jacket at all this week,'' said Craig Van Steenbergen, an architect from Fairfield, Conn., as he smoked a cigar.</p>
        <p>Throughout the Northeast, as far north as Vermont and Maine, people were carrying their coats or leaving them at home and treating themselves to cups of frozen yogurt and ice cream. There were record high temperatures in Newark, where it hit 75 degrees; Bridgeport, Conn., where the mercury reached 72 degrees, and Providence, R.I., at 71 degrees. In Concord, N.J., where temperatures reached 66 degrees, 2 degrees below the record, a United Parcel Service deliveryman could be seen making his rounds in shorts.</p>
        <p>In Providence, Sarah Fisher, a bank employee, pronounced the weather ''absolutely fabulous,'' as she basked in the sun yesterday afternoon.</p>
        <p>For the most part, people seem to be taking the warmth -- which has extended along the East Coast and across the entire country -- in stride. But for weather watchers, this out-of-season heat created excitement.</p>
        <p>''This gets my juices going,'' said Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist with the Pennsylvania State University weather communication group. ''This is a truly extraordinary weather pattern.''</p>
        <p>But it is rapidly nearing its end, he said. This weekend should be brisk and considerably cooler, with temperatures in the low 50's.</p>
        <p>The weather -- which has been warm for a week from San Francisco to the Rocky Mountains and the Middle West, and from the South up into Maine -- has been a result of floods of temperate air masses from the Pacific Ocean. This is contrary to the typical pattern this time of year, in which air masses move south from Canada. The unusual air-mass movements have created the second-warmest year, through October, for the entire country since records were first compiled in 1895.</p>
        <p>''Air over the Pacific is a heck of a lot warmer than air from Canada,'' Mr. Gadomski said.</p>
        <p>The record-breaking heat yesterday in and around New York was enhanced by winds flowing down from the Catskill Mountains, he said. ''As the air is forced downhill from the mountains, it compresses, which warms it,'' Mr. Gadomski said.</p>
        <p>By Tuesday, chilly weather should return, he said. The temperature will drop to the 40's during the day, and there may be snow in and around northern New York.</p>
        <p>For some -- say, the people selling Christmas trees and the managers of the Wollman and Rockefeller Center ice-skating rinks -- that will come as welcome news.</p>
        <p>''I've been telling people I should be selling palm trees instead of balsam firs,'' said Alan Johnston, who came down from Quebec City for the month to work at the tree stand at 94th Street and Broadway. Sales have been very slow, he said. ''People aren't used to buying trees in such warm weather.''</p>
        <p>Clay Courter, the manager of a high-rise building in San Diego, said he had been looking forward to ''Christmas weather.'' In anticipation, he spent $400 on a heavy winter coat, which he left in the hotel room. ''Needless to say, that's where it will stay.''</p>
        <p>Ron Williams, 30, and Jay Funderburke, 32, visiting from Donaldsville, Ga., seemed determined to have a good time in New York, despite the un-Christmaslike heat. ''I'm still seeing the city,'' said Mr. Williams, who was looking forward to his first experience of snow. ''But,'' he added dolefully, ''it would really be nicer if it was cold.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
