<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solution Announced to an Obscure Environmental Problem: the Television</title>
    <meta content="Y09ENE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television Sets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Videocassette Recorders (Vcr)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recording Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television Sets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electronics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E7DF1F30F93AA35752C0A96E958260" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solution Announced to an Obscure Environmental Problem: the Television</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency and electronics industry say that most of major television and VCR manufacturers have agreed to cut standby power consumption of their products by 50 percent to 75 percent; Vice Pres Al Gore announces new labeling program to help consumers choose more efficient models (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Government and the electronics industry agreed today to fix an environmental problem that is found in almost every American home -- and one that almost nobody knows about.</p>
        <p>Television sets, like many other modern electronic appliances, need a dribble of electricity whether or not they are on. That makes every set, and its accompanying videocassette recorder, responsible for a small but steady emission of carbon dioxide, a byproduct of making electricity and the main culprit in global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Government and the electronics industry agreed today to fix an environmental problem that is found in almost every American home -- and one that almost nobody knows about.</p>
        <p>Television sets, like many other modern electronic appliances, need a dribble of electricity whether or not they are on. That makes every set, and its accompanying videocassette recorder, responsible for a small but steady emission of carbon dioxide, a byproduct of making electricity and the main culprit in global warming.</p>
        <p>Add up those little leaks, said Vice President Al Gore today as he announced a new labeling program to help consumers choose more efficient models, and they are the equivalent of the heat-trapping gases emitted by a million automobiles.</p>
        <p>The waste is only a few watts per set, but nationwide it adds up to billions of kilowatt hours costing hundreds of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Until now, the only thing a frugal consumer could do was to unplug the set when it was not being used. The trickle of power to the television is necessary for the remote control to be able to turn the set on. And as for the VCR, if it is unplugged, it forgets its settings for time, timer and programmed channels.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement announced today between the Environmental Protection Agency and most of the major television and VCR manufacturers, the manufacturers said they would cut the standby power consumption of their products by 50 percent to 75 percent.</p>
        <p>Under the product labeling program, consumers will soon be able to identify TV's and VCR's that meet new efficiency guidelines. They are not expected to cost any more, or to offer any fewer features.</p>
        <p>Television manufacturers will be able to declare their products to be efficient and clean, doing so with an ''Energy Star'' label. Products carrying the label will use no more than three or four watts of power when they are turned off. Some current models use as much as 10 or 12 watts, others as little as a watt.</p>
        <p>''If every American family replaced their TV's and VCR's with Energy Star models, it would reduce carbon dioxide emissions by five million tons every year,'' Mr. Gore said in a video address to the International Consumer Electronics Show in Las Vegas, Nev.</p>
        <p>Nobody believes that every household should junk a TV or VCR before it is obsolete. The energy savings to an individual household would add up to just a few dollars a year.</p>
        <p>So it will take many years before the energy savings Mr. Gore spoke of will materialize. And his estimate of emission reductions, while it sounds like a big number, is less than one-thousandth of the amount of carbon dioxide given off each year in the United States.</p>
        <p>Collectively, consumers spend an estimated $1 billion a year in electric bills to pay for standby power in their televisions and video players, according to the American Council for an Energy Efficient Economy.</p>
        <p>It would cost manufacturers almost nothing, E.P.A. officials said, to switch to standby power circuitry that draws far less electricity than most current models. The wiring  that draws as little as one watt is readily available to replace versions that draw 5 or 10 times that much.</p>
        <p>The energy efficiency council, a nonprofit advocacy group, calculated that comparable savings are available from all kinds of consumer products: answering machines, microwave ovens, coffee pots, bread machines and rechargeable devices from hand-held tools to cellular telephones. ''If we had an aggressive standard with full participation covering virtually all major uses,'' said Howard Geller, the council's president, ''we could save 25 billion kilowatt hours per year, more than four times as much as what was announced today.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
