<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="13FSUM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4DB1531F930A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A3-14</p>
        <p>U.S. Buildup Continues As Isolation of Iraq Grows  The United States continued to build up its forces for a possible attack on Iraq, which gave no indication that it was willing to back down and resume United Nations arms inspections. And unlike previous confrontations with Saddam Hussein, this one saw no last-minute efforts to mediate with the Iraqis.  A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A3-14</p>
        <p>U.S. Buildup Continues As Isolation of Iraq Grows  The United States continued to build up its forces for a possible attack on Iraq, which gave no indication that it was willing to back down and resume United Nations arms inspections. And unlike previous confrontations with Saddam Hussein, this one saw no last-minute efforts to mediate with the Iraqis.  A1</p>
        <p>Israel Seeks Housing Bids  Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu opened bidding for a major state-run housing development in the predominantly Arab east side of Jerusalem, one day after the Cabinet approved the agreement with the Palestinians on the next Israeli withdrawal from the West Bank. A1</p>
        <p>Global Warming Pact Signed  The Clinton Administration signed the international agreement to fight global warming, affirming an American role in a long environmental crusade, though not raising hope of Senate approval in the near future. A1</p>
        <p>Loan Package for Brazil  The International Monetary Fund and more than a dozen nations are expected to announce a package of loans to Brazil totaling at least $42 billion to stabilize that country's economy. A1</p>
        <p>Disturbances in Indonesia  Riot police in Jakarta, the capital, fired tear gas, water cannons and rubber bullets to keep student demonstrators from invading the grounds of Parliament. Dozens were injured and a policeman was reported to have been beaten to death.  A3</p>
        <p>Japan Drafts Economic Plan  The governing Liberal Democratic Party issued a draft plan to bolster the economy, but the financial markets greeted it skeptically and analysts described it as a hodgepodge that would have little effect. A3</p>
        <p>China Gangster Given Death  Chinese courts sentenced a Hong Kong crime boss, Cheung Tze-keung, to death, ending to one of the most sensational criminal trials in recent Chinese history, a trial that has spurred heated discussion over whether China is encroaching on Hong Kong's judicial authority.  A8</p>
        <p>British Paper's Turnabout  The daily Sun said it would no longer reveal the identity of any gay man or woman, except in cases of ''overwhelming public interest.'' The statement follows years of relentlessly anti-gay reporting and editorial writing, including a front-page editorial on Monday that warned that Britain was ruled by a cabal of gay men. A7</p>
        <p>Denial in Reporter's Death  A Dublin drug dealer accused of helping to murder a prominent investigative journalist, Veronica Guerin, left, denied at his trial that he had anything to do with the 1996 slaying. The trial, in its third week, has refocused national attention on the case and provided a unusual look into Dublin drug-dealing.  A13</p>
        <p>World Briefing A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL  A18-28</p>
        <p>Doubts Begin to Grow About a Cancer Treatment  Officials at the National Cancer Institute have begun to express frustration over their inability to reproduce the striking discoveries described a year ago by Dr. Judah Folkman, a Harvard researcher who reported that he and his colleagues had wiped out malignant tumors in mice by using the compounds angiostatin and endostatin. A1</p>
        <p>Gun Industry Is Target of Suit  The City of Chicago and Cook County filed a $433 million lawsuit against the gun industry, asserting that the police had found that firearms dealers in Chicago's suburbs were flooding the city with illegal guns with the knowledge of makers and distributors. A18</p>
        <p>Findings on Vinyl Toy Ingredient  A chemical ingredient of vinyl, used by the toy industry since the early 1980's because an earlier compound caused liver damage in laboratory rats, caused essentially the same problems in rats in later tests, a manufacturer acknowledged. A20</p>
        <p>Gephardt's Complaint  The House Democratic leader, Richard A. Gephardt, offered a scathing criticism of the Congressional investigation of President Clinton, accusing Republicans of wasting time. A24</p>
        <p>Official Wants Record Cleared  Lawyers for Ira C. Magaziner, the chief architect of President Clinton's ill-fated health care plan, urged a Federal appeals court to clear him of a judge's accusation that he had lied under oath. A20</p>
        <p>Secret Service Chief Retiring  Lewis C. Merletti, 50, the Director of the Secret Service, who tried to a establish a right of confidentiality for Presidential bodyguards, will become security director for the new Cleveland Browns football team. A22</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION  B1-13</p>
        <p>Ballot Counting Goes On In Attorney General Race  The Democratic candidate for attorney general, Eliot L. Spitzer, left, increased his lead to about 22,000 votes over the incumbent, Dennis C. Vacco, in the day's counting of paper ballots and rechecking of machine voting. Mr. Spitzer now has 2,006,834 votes to Mr. Vacco's 1,984,459, with 100,000 or so to be counted. B1</p>
        <p>Crackdown on Youth Smoking  Officials said that a New York City undercover effort to reduce the sale of cigarettes to minors had led to a 66 percent decline in such sales in the stores being tested, apparently as word of the operation spread and fines and tobacco license suspensions were imposed. Thirty-one teen-agers sought to buy cigarettes in nearly 8,200 retail shops. B1</p>
        <p>Confusion in Officer's Shooting  An undercover detective wounded on Wednesday was not attacked by a drug dealer but by two men who picked a seemingly random argument with him, the police said, while also not discounting the possibility that the officer was shot by a fellow officer coming to his aid. B3</p>
        <p>WEEKEND  E1-34; E35-48</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES  B14-15</p>
        <p>SPORTS  D1-8</p>
        <p>Chalk Up One More for Torre  Joe Torre, who led the Yankees to 114 regular-season victories and their second World Series championship in three years, was named the A.L. manager of the year. D4</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY  C1-18</p>
        <p>Texaco Cuts Costs and Jobs  Texaco will eliminate 1,000 oil-exploration jobs worldwide, or about 5 percent of its work force, as part of an effort to save $200 million a year. It previously reported a 58 percent decline in third-quarter earnings. C1</p>
        <p>Microsoft Assails Intel Witness  Microsoft lawyers sought to discredit a senior Intel executive who has emerged as an important Government witness, portraying him as a resentful employee and introducing a supervisor's testimony that differed from the executive's. C1</p>
        <p>A New Line for State Farm  Federal thrift regulators will let State Farm Insurance begin using its vast network of agents to sell such banking products as car loans, mortgages and certificates of deposit. C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL  A30-31</p>
        <p>Editorials: Yardsticks for action against Iraq; speeding and civil liberties; a first step against sweatshops; Floyd Norris on Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>Columns: A. M. Rosenthal, Russell Baker.</p>
        <p>Crossword E44</p>
        <p>Weather D5</p>
        <p>Public Lives  B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
