<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plan to Lay Gas Pipeline Sets Off Dispute</title>
    <meta content="PIPELI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Lake Erie</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Millennium Pipeline System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDF153CF936A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="1700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plan to Lay Gas Pipeline Sets Off Dispute</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Millennium Pipeline System proposal to lay 32 miles of natural gas pipeline through heart of densely populated Westchester County, NY, stirs opposition in many quarters, but wins qualified support from environmentalists and consumers; 422-mile pipeline would transport up to 700 million cubic feet of gas a day from Lake Erie to East Coast markets; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was only four years ago that a natural gas pipeline exploded in Edison, N.J., killing one person and injuring 100. Not surprisingly, a private energy company's recent proposal to lay 32 miles of pipeline through the heart of Westchester has provoked fierce opposition in many quarters of this densely populated county, rekindling memories of that and several other deadly gas-line blasts.</p>
        <p>But the proposal has also garnered at least qualified support among environmentalists and consumers seeking fuels that are cleaner and cheaper than coal and oil. Natural gas is considered the best fossil fuel for reducing emissions that can lead to global warming, according to a report by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was only four years ago that a natural gas pipeline exploded in Edison, N.J., killing one person and injuring 100. Not surprisingly, a private energy company's recent proposal to lay 32 miles of pipeline through the heart of Westchester has provoked fierce opposition in many quarters of this densely populated county, rekindling memories of that and several other deadly gas-line blasts.</p>
        <p>But the proposal has also garnered at least qualified support among environmentalists and consumers seeking fuels that are cleaner and cheaper than coal and oil. Natural gas is considered the best fossil fuel for reducing emissions that can lead to global warming, according to a report by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>''The public is naturally concerned, and no one wants a pipeline in their backyard,'' County Legislator Michael B. Kaplowitz of Somers, the chairman of the Board of Legislators' Committee on the Environment, which is reviewing the latest pipeline application, said recently. ''But there may in fact be a plus side to all of this.''</p>
        <p>Millennium Pipeline System, a consortium of gas companies, is proposing a $650 million project to thread 422 miles of pipeline underground from Lake Erie through New York and Pennsylvania, with the final section entering Westchester in Cortlandt and ending in Mount Vernon. The consortium is headed by Columbia Gas Transmission Corporation, which is based in Fairfax, Va., and includes TransCanada Pipelines, Westcoast Energy and the M.C.N. Energy Group. The consortium would transport up to 700 million cubic feet of natural gas a day to East Coast markets.</p>
        <p>The consortium has filed an application with the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission, seeking permission to construct and operate the pipeline. It is also holding a series of public informational meetings to discuss details of the plan with municipalities, environmental groups and residents. Representatives of Columbia Gas met Tuesday with the Environment Committee and the Health Committee of County Board of Legislators.</p>
        <p>Because the pipeline would cross county property in northern Westchester, the Board of Legislators and the County Planning Department are investigating whether local approval might be needed before the consortium buries pipeline on that land.</p>
        <p>Proponents of natural gas say it is the largest single new source of energy for the New York region since the 1950's. It is also a far cleaner fuel than coal for running the turbines that generate the region's electricity. While much of the gas will be used to heat homes and industrial buildings, there is a growing demand for natural gas to fuel electrical power plants.</p>
        <p>Those arguing for natural gas also observe that it produces significantly less sulfur pollution in the atmosphere than gasoline or heating oil. New sources of natural gas will most likely generate more competition among fuel distributors and discourage sellers of heating oil from taking advantage of temperature plunges or political upset in oil-producing nations to impose price increases.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are watching carefully but with caution, attracted to the cleaner burning fuel. Andre Mele, a director of Hudson River Sloop Clearwater, a 12,000-member group based in Poughkeepsie, said that in general environmentalists strongly favor a shift away from traditional fossil fuels to natural gas. ''It's still not a renewable energy source,'' he said, ''but it's much cleaner.''</p>
        <p>Mostly, groups like Clearwater are heartened by the fact that the consortium has taken a proactive approach to the environmental impact of its project. ''We're being recognized as a collective force to contend with,'' Mr. Mele said, ''and there seems to be a legitimate awareness that the environment is important.'' He said representatives of the consortium had contacted his organization two months ago to present their plans.</p>
        <p>Still, memories of deadly pipeline explosions linger, and the recent proposal has stirred fears anew. In 1996, two years after the Edison blast, flames erupted from a ruptured natural-gas pipeline in Brooklyn's Coney Island section as a construction crew tried to repair a water-main break. A dozen people were burned, some seriously.</p>
        <p>In 1989, a natural-gas pipeline exploded in the Bronx, leveling two buildings and incinerating 50 cars; 2 people died. In 1991, a propane line ignited in the village of North Blenheim in Schoharie County, leveling a dozen homes and killing 2 residents.</p>
        <p>Statistics tell a more reassuring story. Records from the Federal Department of Transportation, for example, show that 21 people died in pipeline accidents in 1995, compared with 41,000 on highways nationwide.</p>
        <p>More than half the heating oil, gasoline and other petroleum products used in the United States is transported through 1.8 million miles of pipeline. Although most of the pipelines lie in remote areas, some pass through populated regions on their way to cities. Fatal pipeline accidents, however, are rare.</p>
        <p>''We've never had a fatality along one of our pipelines,'' Bentley K. Archer, a spokesman for Columbia Gas, said Tuesday at the informational meeting on the proposal at the County Office Building in White Plains. Columbia Gas owns 13,000 miles of pipeline in 10 states and delivers a trillion cubic feet of gas -- about 10 percent of the gas consumed in the United States -- to customers each year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Archer said that most accidents are caused either by corrosion of the pipes -- tougher pipe material is now being used -- or third-party dig-ins. To counter that problem, programs like ''Call Before You Dig'' have been started.</p>
        <p>Reassurances from public relations representatives notwithstanding, a National Transportation Safety Board report issued in 1996 said that while the number of pipeline accidents had remained constant in the last decade, the potential threat to public safety ''has become more severe in recent years as residential and commercial development adjacent to both natural gas and hazardous liquid pipelines has accelerated.''</p>
        <p>Fear about a natural-gas disaster is compounded in the county because the area lies atop a geological fault. In 1985, an earthquake in Ardsley registered 4.0 on the Richter scale; it was one of the largest seismic events ever reported in the metropolitan area. Other quakes in the New York City region of an intensity great enough to topple chimneys took place  in 1737, 1783 and 1884. That magnitude is considered the equivalent of 5.0 on the Richter scale.</p>
        <p>County Legislator Thomas J. Abinanti, who is also a member of the Board of Legislators' Committee on the Environment, is leading the charge against the pipeline in Westchester.</p>
        <p>''There is the potential for disaster,'' he said in a recent interview. ''And while we shouldn't be alarmists, we must be concerned.'' He called the Columbia Gas plan an ''absurd'' proposal, especially in light of recent reports, which say little has been done to toughen pipeline safety standards.</p>
        <p>In particular, investigators from the National Safety Transportation Board say that Department of Transportation regulators who oversee gas pipelines have failed to impose specific standards that the investigators recommended for pipeline toughness, for the frequency and types of inspections and for installation of equipment that would allow operators to shut off gas from a broken pipe.</p>
        <p>Last year, James E. Hall, Chairman of the safety board, which is an independent investigative agency, said regulators had ''a poor history of responding to our recommendations in a timely manner.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Archer, however, said that Columbia Gas ''either meets or exceeds D.O.T. standards.''</p>
        <p>And regulators from the Department of Transportation reported recently that the budget of the Federal Office of Pipeline Safety, which regulates the pipeline industry, nearly doubled after the Edison explosion -- to $37 million in 1995 and $32 million in 1996 and 1997 from $19 million in 1994. While the agency had 30 inspectors in 1994, there were nearly 60 by the end of last year.</p>
        <p>Yet those numbers do little to allay fears among those worried about the impact of the latest pipeline project. Mr. Abinanti said during the interview that Millennium would be boring under the Hudson River and under high rocks and low valleys in highly populated areas of Westchester -- at best a difficult, if not dangerous task, he said.</p>
        <p>And Cara Lee, director of Scenic Hudson, an environmental group in Poughkeepsie, worried in a recent interview that ''environmental corners would be cut in the rush to lay down the pipeline.''</p>
        <p>The project is to begin next year and be completed in 2000, when the spigots would be opened. Millennium is in the talking stages of negotiations with Consolidated Edison to lay pipe under its above-ground electric lines, James P. O'Toole, a Con Edison spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lee said she was worried that the blasting necessary for the project would denude trees and harm wetlands and streams. ''Millennium has a very big vision, and the Hudson Valley is just a little piece of its project,'' she said, ''but to us, it's our world. We're going to be taking a vigilant stance.''</p>
        <p>Currently Tennessee Gas Pipeline, the Algonquin Gas Transmission System, Iroquois Gas and Texas Eastern Pipeline have gas lines in Westchester. A proposal by Tenneco Gas Company to lay a pipeline through Dobbs Ferry to a co-generation plant in southwest Yonkers was defeated several years ago by Friends of the Old Croton Trailway, a residents' group. The pipeline was to have provided natural gas to the Yonkers plant, where it would be converted to electricity to sell to Consolidated Edison and steam for Refined Sugars and the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey's Industrial Park in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>At the meeting in White Plains, Mr. Archer observed that the company had developed methods to prevent pipeline ruptures during earthquakes. And in previous interviews, company officials said the consortium would install controls that could turn off gas valves from remote locations. In the Edison blast, it took workers several hours to reach the site and stop the flow of gas, which was feeding the fire.</p>
        <p>Legislator Kaplowitz has reassured Columbia Gas representatives that officials throughout the region would approach the proposal with, if not open arms, at least open minds.</p>
        <p>''Certainly, we'll be asking the questions that need to be asked,'' Mr. Kaplowitz said recently, ''but there's no cause for hysteria.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
