<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: Arms-Length Transactions; I'll Have Some Chitlins, Fries and an Oxygen Tank</title>
    <meta content="13SACK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1069405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morris, Lee (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3D71E3AF930A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: Arms-Length Transactions; I'll Have Some Chitlins, Fries and an Oxygen Tank</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>City Councilman Lee Morris of Atlanta, Ga, has proposed ordinance to ban construction of new drive-through windows in Atlanta, national leader in what he refers to as 'autodependency'; his bill would ban car-bound transactions at banks, fast-food eateries, dry cleaners, pharmacies, liquor stores and cappucino cafes; Morris claims autodependency is responsible for dirty air, traffic congestion, obesity, global warming, respiratory illness and epidemic of pedestrian deaths; Atlanta Regional Commission has concluded that Atlantans drive average of 33 miles per day, more than residents of any other major city, photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OPENING a debate here Tuesday night, City Councilman Lee Morris wanted to make one thing clear. ''I don't think drive-throughs are evil,'' Mr. Morris said. ''And I don't think that folks who use drive-throughs are evil.'' Then he admitted his own pathetic dependency: ''Uh, I use them myself -- because they're there.''</p>
        <p>The shame of it all.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OPENING a debate here Tuesday night, City Councilman Lee Morris wanted to make one thing clear. ''I don't think drive-throughs are evil,'' Mr. Morris said. ''And I don't think that folks who use drive-throughs are evil.'' Then he admitted his own pathetic dependency: ''Uh, I use them myself -- because they're there.''</p>
        <p>The shame of it all.</p>
        <p>So began Mr. Morris's plea for votes for his proposed ordinance to ban the construction of new drive-through windows in Atlanta, the national leader in what Mr. Morris refers to as ''autodependency.'' Under his bill, the city would effectively declare an end to more convenient but bloodless car-bound transactions at banks, fast-food eateries, dry cleaners, pharmacies, liquor stores and cappucino cafes. In Atlanta, you can even drive through for chitlins.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Morris's thinking, autodependency is responsible for dirty air, traffic congestion, obesity, global warming, respiratory illness, an epidemic of pedestrian deaths and the deterioration of community. The Atlanta Regional Commission, a coalition of local governments, has concluded that Atlantans drive an average of 33 miles a day, more than residents of any other major city, 52 percent more than those in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>After debate, and some lobbying by bankers and burger barons, the Council rejected Mr. Morris's admittedly modest proposal by an 8-to-5 vote. But the measure spoke to the desperation of this city, and so many others, that are trying to control problems like air pollution and sprawl.</p>
        <p>Metropolitan Atlanta has been on the go for nearly 30 years, emerging unscathed from the civil rights movement. And after more than doubling its population in that period, to 3.1 million, it suffers from severe traffic and environmental woes. The area's leaders, including Governor-elect Roy E. Barnes, are increasingly concerned that ozone days and creeping traffic are becoming an intractable part of Atlanta's international profile. A poll of Atlanta business and political leaders this year showed that air quality had replaced crime and public education as their greatest concern.</p>
        <p>With no mountains or oceans to block Atlanta's growth, farmland and forest have been swiftly paved into nondescript exurbia. And despite the relentless expansion of the road system, drivers have come to expect delays any time and anywhere. The recent addition of high-occupancy-vehicle lanes on the three Interstate highways converging in downtown Atlanta have had little noticeable impact.</p>
        <p>The city's air quality is considered so hazardous that Federal financing for new highway projects has effectively been frozen. Studies have found that more than half of the nitrogen oxides in Atlanta's air comes from cars, and environmental officials project that  pollution will worsen in the next century.</p>
        <p>EVER since Atlanta was founded as the terminus of the Western &amp; Atlantic Railroad in 1837, transportation has been central to its character. Although a few in-town neighborhoods like Midtown and Virginia Highlands have retained a pedestrian charm, the area's suburban design and personality have largely made it a driving city. While the Metropolitan Atlanta Rapid Transit Authority run clean, efficient trains, its service area remains limited. Many of those who do take the trains commute to the stations by automobile.</p>
        <p>Several smaller cities, including Burbank and Sierra Madre, Calif., and Carrboro, N.C., have imposed limits on drive-through windows in recent years, although usually to preserve their character rather than to reduce pollution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris understood that his proposal to ban the construction of new drive-throughs fell somewhat short of a panacea. Robert R. King, president of the Georgia Hospitality and Travel Association, called it ''a Band-Aid on a blowout.'' It is not even clear that an idling car at a drive-through pollutes any more than a car that is stopped and then started again. But with the hundreds of competing governments in the metropolitan area flailing in their efforts to improve air quality, Mr. Morris felt it was time to do something, anything, to get Atlantans out of their cars, to show some determination to change the city's culture.</p>
        <p>HE also understood that his measure would cause inconvenience, especially for the elderly, the handicapped and parents of young children. But he recalled that it was not so long ago that the culture deemed it inconvenient to toss soft-drink bottles and litter into trash cans rather than into rivers and gutters.</p>
        <p>His supporters noted that the city and its suburbs had to start somewhere. ''Everyone says that they're supportive of cleaning up the air,'' said Councilwoman Debi Starnes. ''Everyone says that they're supportive of making our city and the world more pedestrian friendly. And everyone says that they realize that in order to accomplish those two objectives that we're going to have to do a lot of little and medium things. There's no one big thing that will solve these problems. And almost every time one of these little or medium things comes up, people say, 'Well not this little or medium thing. This won't make that much difference.' ''</p>
        <p>In the end, however, the measure failed, with its opponents lauding Mr. Morris's intentions but condemning his methods. They argued that the ordinance would place an unreasonable burden on businesses, would put Atlanta at a competitive disadvantage with surrounding jurisdictions, would undercut its tax base and would inconvenience the disabled. Black members of the Council opposed it unanimously, with many arguing that it would stifle badly needed development on the city's predominantly black south side. Councilman Derrick Boazman took a shot at Mr. Morris's moralizing by observing that he had not noticed any donkeys or electric cars in the City Hall garage that day.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris, not surprisingly, found the outcome a bit frustrating. ''Atlanta is known for its rah-rah pro-business attitude,'' he said. ''And the pursuit of the almighty dollar tends to overwhelm good public policy.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
