<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Government Called A Shoreham Victim</title>
    <meta content="22NUKE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shoreham Nuclear Power Plant</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Lighting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nuclear Regulatory Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aron, Joan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Licensed to Kill? (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E5D91139F931A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="1340" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Government Called A Shoreham Victim</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joan Aron, author of Licensed to Kill?: The Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the Shoreham Power Plant, argues that government--Suffolk County, New York State and Nuclear Regulatory Commission--suffered huge loss of public trust in the $5 billion Shoreham debacle; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NINE years after the demise of Shoreham, a new analysis of America's largest dead-end industrial project has identified a victim beyond the obvious ones, the customers and shareholders of the Long Island Lighting Company and taxpayers around the United States, who will share a waste of more than $5 billion on the reactor.</p>
        <p>The other victim, according to a newly retired policy planner at the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, Joan Aron, is government. Suffolk County, New York State, the N.R.C. and the rest of the Federal Government suffered a huge loss, she argues, not of money but of trust. They lost not only the trust of the public but the trust of each other, according to Ms. Aron.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NINE years after the demise of Shoreham, a new analysis of America's largest dead-end industrial project has identified a victim beyond the obvious ones, the customers and shareholders of the Long Island Lighting Company and taxpayers around the United States, who will share a waste of more than $5 billion on the reactor.</p>
        <p>The other victim, according to a newly retired policy planner at the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, Joan Aron, is government. Suffolk County, New York State, the N.R.C. and the rest of the Federal Government suffered a huge loss, she argues, not of money but of trust. They lost not only the trust of the public but the trust of each other, according to Ms. Aron.</p>
        <p>In a new book, ''Licensed to Kill? The Nuclear Regulatory Commission and the Shoreham Power Plant'' (University of Pittsburgh Press, $18.95 paper, $45 cloth), Ms. Aron also argues that the true impact of the Shoreham debacle has not been felt yet, because one of its key products has not been tried yet, a ''reformed'' system for licensing future nuclear plants, designed by the commission to prevent future Shorehams. The new system calls for a single license to be granted before constructon begins, and not, as in Shoreham's case, a construction permit and then an operating license when construction is done. The new system will backfire and make nuclear power even less acceptable to the public, she argues, because it reduces the opportunity for public input.</p>
        <p>Ms. Aron has taken on a difficult subject -- the writing of contemporary history -- because so many of the people involved in the story have their own passionate perspectives. But in a review of the Shoreham saga, Ms. Aron, who joined the staff of the N.R.C. in 1976 and worked there on and off until early this year, makes a case that governments acted in ways that no one should be proud of and that will have future effects.</p>
        <p>''There's a large stake in making a decision that is perceived as 'correct' from all standpoints, including technical, economic, environmental, and policy considerations,'' she writes. ''None of the contending parties -- Lilco, the Nuclear Regulatory Commission, New York State or Suffolk County -- had confidence that the other participants were making an honest effort to achieve good public policy. Moreover, no party had confidence that the outcome would be 'right' or that the process would lead to the correct decision. Consequently, each party felt vindicated in departing from the customary rules governing the process and engaging and engaging in questionable practices to achieve its ends.''</p>
        <p>The Nuclear Regulatory Commisison refused to consider a 20-mile emergency planning zone in place of a 10-mile zone because the larger area might have doomed the plant, she said; Suffolk refused to seriously consider emergency planning because it might have been possible. Lilco plowed forward because it assumed, wrongly, that if it got a license to run the plant, the plant would run. The N.R.C. granted the plant a test license that resulted in radioative contamination and thus raised the eventual price of decmmissioning, because it could not cope with any other outcome, and nobody put the whole situation in context and cut a deal earlier that would have saved everyone time and money, she argues.</p>
        <p>Government, of course, is also the cause of the debacle, with one level launching the utility and its ratepayers on a vast industrial project, while another created obstacles that would insure it was all a waste. In a telephone interview, Ms. Aron said that in the end, another problem was that no one in government would take responsiblity for solving the problem, of a reactor inspired by the ''too cheap to meter'' thinking of the 1950's, reaching completion in the post-Three Mile Island, post-Chernobyl 1980's, when the dominant question was what would happen if an emergency required an evacuation.</p>
        <p>''Had anyone been willing to take responsiblity, you probably could have put an extra road on top of the L.I.E., or planned for some Dunkirk-like, imaginative way of getting away,'' said Ms. Aron, in a telephone interview. Building another roadway on top of the Long Island Expresway and then operating the reactor, she said, would have been cheaper than abandoning it. But the failure to take responsibility, she said, was ''partially what's wrong with the decision-making process.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Aron knows about governmental cooperation and the lack thereof. An associate professor of political science at New York University from 1969 to 1976, she is also the author of ''The Quest for Regional Cooperation: A Study of the New York Metropolitan Regional Council.''</p>
        <p>Shoreham is still very much a factor in Long Island's energy situation, giving the area the highest electric rates in the mainland United States and driving an effort that dates from the days of Gov. Mario M. Cuomo to re-structure Lilco. But events beyond the control of anyone on Long Island have rendered it less important than it might have seemed in April 1989, when shareholders of the company voted to accept a deal to kill the plant.</p>
        <p>Since that time, the technology for finding natural gas and the infrastructure for bringing it to market has improved markedly, and the price of oil has continued to decline. If Shoreham had run well, its uranium fuel might have replaced about 10 million barrels of oil a year, but over time, the importance of that oil has changed. In 1979, when opposition was strong but construction was well under way, that was worth about $400 million annually; today it is worth only about $150 million, and with the dollar worth less because of intervening inflation, the savings is much smaller than anyone had dared to predict.</p>
        <p>Now Gov. George E. Pataki's plan for a partial state takeover of Lilco is advancing, and rebates to customers in Nassau and Suffolk are expected to be sent before Election Day. Rate cuts of 20 percent are also expected.</p>
        <p>And with looser rules about who can make and sell electricity, the region continues to have plenty of power, even with the long-term shutdown of the three Millstone reactors across Long Island Sound in Waterford, Conn.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, with more than 100 nuclear plants operating around the country for the last nine years, not one of them has had an incident that resulted in orders to shelter or evacuate.</p>
        <p>None of the people who were members of the commission while Shoreham was an issue are still there, although some staff members endure. The book is not kind to the N.R.C., but Ms. Aron, who retired in January and lives in Washington, said that she had not received any reaction from anyone at the agency. She was assisted with the book by Leo Slaggie, who is still the deputy solicitor at the agency.</p>
        <p>Ms. Aron's conclusions about nuclear power may not matter, in the sense that it is not clear when any level of government will face a decision on opening a new reactor. She believes, though, that given certain turns in the energy market and concern about global warming and other forms of pollution, the question of how to regulate new reactors could indeed be important. But her conclusion about trust and government might apply to some other technical fields.</p>
        <p>If a second nuclear era begins, she writes, with better-designed plants about which there are fewer technical questions, ''there will remain a need for the N.R.C. to act -- and to be perceived by the public -- as a bold, vigorous regulatory body, with an aggressive approach to regulatory standards, safety analyses, quality assurance, and investigations of allegations of whistle-blowers (that is, those with safety concerns within and outside the agency), with ends of public health and safety paramount to all other considerations. In short, re-regulation instead of de-regulation.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
