<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Skirmishes Over Treaty On Warming</title>
    <meta content="Y11CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buenos Aires (Argentina)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina/Buenos Aires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DB1F3EF932A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Skirmishes Over Treaty On Warming</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional foes and supporters argue over whether Clinton Administration, which plans to eventually sign international accord to fight global warming, should do so during talks this week in Buenos Aires, Argentina; debate whether step, which Clinton favors as sign of commitment to controversial accord, would weaken or strengthen United States's bargaining hand (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As negotiators from around the world worked on details of an international agreement to fight global warming, the Clinton Administration faced an intense debate among lawmakers today over whether to sign the pact during talks this week in Argentina.</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that the Administration will sign the agreement eventually, even though it faces an uphill struggle for approval by the Senate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As negotiators from around the world worked on details of an international agreement to fight global warming, the Clinton Administration faced an intense debate among lawmakers today over whether to sign the pact during talks this week in Argentina.</p>
        <p>There is no doubt that the Administration will sign the agreement eventually, even though it faces an uphill struggle for approval by the Senate.</p>
        <p>But Congressional adversaries argued today whether signing it now, a step the White House favors as a sign of its commitment to the controversial accord, would strengthen or weaken the bargaining hand of the United States.</p>
        <p>Some Administration officials said today that no decision had been reached on signing the agreement, but others said that the Administration's envoy to the talks, Stuart E. Eizenstat, would announce in Buenos Aires that it would be signed.</p>
        <p>The agreement would commit the United States to reducing its emissions of carbon dioxide and other heat-trapping greenhouse gases, which scientists say threaten to warm the planet and disrupt its climate, by 7 percent below the 1990 levels over the next 10 to 15 years.</p>
        <p>Opponents have said that this would require cuts in the use of fossil fuel that would devastate the economy. The Administration insists that new technologies would insure a painless transition to a cleaner economy.</p>
        <p>For weeks, Administration officials have declined to say when the United States would sign the protocol, which was agreed to by more than 150 nations last year in Kyoto, Japan.</p>
        <p>The current round of talks is aimed at establishing a system of international emissions trading and at defining what role developing countries should play in cutting emissions of the pollution that scientists say may cause major changes in the planet's climate.</p>
        <p>As reports spread that the Administration would sign the agreement this week, Congressional opponents warned that this would be a political mistake, while those who favor the treaty said signing it now would increase the Administration's influence in the negotiations.</p>
        <p>Sen. Robert Byrd, a Democrat from West Virginia, where cuts on emissions of carbon dioxide from burning coal would damage the state's mining industry, warned President Clinton to ''resist making empty gestures that will only make the potential future approval of the protocol by the Senate more difficult.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Byrd is a leader of Congressional opponents of the treaty who contend that it must not be approved until developing nations, whose emissions of greenhouse gases are projected to surpass those of the United States in the next few decades, agree to join industrial nations in cutting emissions.</p>
        <p>But Sen. Joseph Lieberman, a Democrat from Connecticut, urged the White House to sign the agreement.</p>
        <p>''If we are not at the table, we cannot cajole or convince the developing nations to become part of the solution,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Representative F. James Sensenbrenner Jr., a treaty opponent in the House and a leader of the Congressional observers' delegation to the talks in Buenos Aires, called on the Administration not to sign the treaty.</p>
        <p>''Any global warming treaty devoid of developing country participation and credible evidence that America will maintain its economic health and vitality will be dead on arrival,'' said Mr. Sensenbrenner, a Republican from Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lieberman, as he left Washington to join the observers from Capitol Hill, called Mr. Sensenbrenner's plea ''a mistake, and a serious abdication of American responsibility to lead in this effort, and also an obstacle to our being able to shape the global response to the problem.''</p>
        <p>Fred Krupp, the head of the Environmental Defense Fund, an advocacy organization that favors the treaty, said that ''the people who oppose signing are the same people who have opposed the treaty from the beginning, and in fact they are really opposing protecting the planet. We feel very strongly that the time to sign has come.''</p>
        <p>But other environmentalists were not so enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''In my mind, this Administration has made expectations so low, that when they finally sign this weak agreement that they negotiated, people will mistake it for leadership,'' said John Passacantando, executive director of Ozone Action, an environmental group that follows climate issues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
