<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rich Leaders Turn Eye to Crime and Debt</title>
    <meta content="17SUMM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Birmingham (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/Birmingham</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDB1E30F934A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rich Leaders Turn Eye to Crime and Debt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>BIRMINGHAM, England, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leaders of eight major industrial countries attending economic summit in Birmingham, England, agree to cooperate more in battling international crime; pledge to do more to help world's poorest countries; focus on issues of common interest, including how to create more jobs and stop global warming; thousands of protestors surround site of meeting in central Birmingham, demanding more action by rich nations to relieve poorest countries of their debts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With concern over India and Indonesia lurking in the background, the leaders of eight major countries turned their attention today to other issues, agreeing to cooperate more in battling international crime and pledging to do more to help the world's poorest countries.</p>
        <p>Meeting in the quiet of a country estate 20 miles outside this industrial city, President Clinton and the leaders of Britain, France, Germany, Italy, Canada, Japan and Russia put aside the crises of the day to focus on longer-term issues of common concern, including how to create more jobs and stop global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With concern over India and Indonesia lurking in the background, the leaders of eight major countries turned their attention today to other issues, agreeing to cooperate more in battling international crime and pledging to do more to help the world's poorest countries.</p>
        <p>Meeting in the quiet of a country estate 20 miles outside this industrial city, President Clinton and the leaders of Britain, France, Germany, Italy, Canada, Japan and Russia put aside the crises of the day to focus on longer-term issues of common concern, including how to create more jobs and stop global warming.</p>
        <p>It is the sixth such gathering attended by President Clinton, and for the White House it offered a welcome opportunity to get away from the relentless grind of legal and political problems in Washington.</p>
        <p>After meeting one-on-one with President Boris N. Yeltsin of Russia on Sunday morning, Mr. Clinton will spend Sunday night as the guest of Prime Minister Tony Blair of Britain at his country home, Chequers. Mr. Clinton and Mr. Blair will go to London on Monday to discuss the relationship between the United States and the European Union.</p>
        <p>Before flying home to Washington, Mr. Clinton will stop in Geneva late Monday to address the World Trade Organization, where he is expected to call for further efforts to knock down trade barriers.</p>
        <p>As the leaders met today in the 17th-century manor at Weston Park in the village of Weston-under-Lizard, thousands of protesters encircled the convention center in central Birmingham that is the summit meeting's headquarters, demanding more action by rich nations to relieve the poorest countries of their debts.</p>
        <p>The issue has long been a vexing one for the industrial countries, leaving them trapped between pressure to help poverty-stricken counterparts and the risk that debt forgiveness would undermine the economic discipline they have urged developing nations to adopt.</p>
        <p>Many African countries in particular amassed huge debts to the International Monetary Fund, the World Bank and other governments and private lenders, and now find themselves unable to spend as much on health, education and economic development as they would like because of their huge repayment burden.</p>
        <p>Through a program agreed to by the seven largest industrial democracies, the I.M.F. and the World Bank have made seven countries eligible for a $5.7 billion package of debt relief -- Uganda, Bolivia, Guyana, Burkina Faso, Ivory Coast and Mozambique.</p>
        <p>But many poverty-fighting organizations have argued that the program is being carried out too slowly and that too many countries are being excluded.</p>
        <p>A study by the relief group Oxfam International said that in Africa, where only half of children go to school, governments spend four times as much on debt repayment as on health and education. In Ethiopia, Oxfam said, more than 100,000 children die each year from preventable diseases but the Government spends four times as much on debt as on health care.</p>
        <p>In response to today's protest here, Mr. Blair, as the summit meeting's host, issued a statement reaffirming the commitment of the leaders to ''speedy and determined implementation'' of the program.</p>
        <p>He made no commitment to speed up or expand the program, but American officials said the leaders had agreed to support a broad effort to insure that all African children had the opportunity to go to school and that infant mortality rates be reduced.</p>
        <p>On issues closer to home, the leaders discussed what policies can help create more jobs -- a topic of particular interest and sensitivity in France and Germany, which are plagued by double-digit unemployment.</p>
        <p>American officials said Mr. Clinton pointed to welfare-to-work programs and the earned income tax credit, which provides incentives to low-income working people, as initiatives that have helped in the United States.</p>
        <p>The leaders discussed efforts to curb global warming, a subject on which the United States has come under considerable criticism from European countries for its refusal to make ironclad commitments to reduce emissions of heat-trapping gases.</p>
        <p>And they spent considerable time discussing arrangements for international cooperation in fighting cross-border crimes like money-laundering, computer fraud and arms smuggling.</p>
        <p>In a communique, the leaders endorsed efforts to negotiate a United Nations agreement to provide law enforcement officials with more tools to fight international organized crime.</p>
        <p>They called for talks with the business community on an international legal framework for obtaining computer data as evidence in criminal cases, while preserving privacy protections.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
