<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Essay; Wondering How the World Will End? Some Mordant Thoughts from Physics</title>
    <meta content="14ESSA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980716T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Universe</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Essay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Universe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED81331F937A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Essay; Wondering How the World Will End? Some Mordant Thoughts from Physics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Malcolm W Browne Essay on scientists' mordant speculations about how universe will end; many of physicists' conceptions of Grand Unified Theory of life's ultimate demise are connected to decay and eventual death of a proton (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN contrast with the malevolent scientists of horror movies, most physicists are well-adjusted, friendly, attractive people whose conspicuous brain power is generally mixed with the milk of human kindness.</p>
        <p>It might therefore seem a little uncharacteristic that some physicists are eagerly hoping to see some tiny blue flashes streak through a cathedral-size water tank buried under a mountain: a signal that an inexorable process of annihilation is gnawing away at the universe. The universal rot, if it is real, will take untold eons to complete, but it will be thorough, leaving no stars, no people, no monuments, no cinders, no sonnets, no atoms, no memories.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN contrast with the malevolent scientists of horror movies, most physicists are well-adjusted, friendly, attractive people whose conspicuous brain power is generally mixed with the milk of human kindness.</p>
        <p>It might therefore seem a little uncharacteristic that some physicists are eagerly hoping to see some tiny blue flashes streak through a cathedral-size water tank buried under a mountain: a signal that an inexorable process of annihilation is gnawing away at the universe. The universal rot, if it is real, will take untold eons to complete, but it will be thorough, leaving no stars, no people, no monuments, no cinders, no sonnets, no atoms, no memories.</p>
        <p>Except for a faint and ever fading glow, the corpse of our universe would cease to exist.</p>
        <p>And yet, a harbinger of this dismal future would be welcomed by many theorists.</p>
        <p>For much of the 20th century, physicists have tried to construct a theory that would mathematically bring three of the four known forces of nature -- the electromagnetic force and the weak and strong nuclear forces -- into consonance. (A theoretical assimilation of the fourth force, gravity, poses many more formidable problems for theorists.)</p>
        <p>There are various candidates for the title Grand Unified Theory, but none has been validated by experiment or observation, and all of them seem to embody a disquieting requirement: the eventual death of every proton in the universe.</p>
        <p>So far, in nearly two decades of searching, no experiment has produced convincing evidence of the decay of even one proton, much less an appreciable fraction of the 10 to the 79th power protons the universe is estimated to contain. (That number is mathematical notation for the numeral one followed by 79 zeros.)</p>
        <p>This hasn't stopped scientists from continuing the search; in fact, there are hopes that the mighty Super-Kamiokande detector under a mountain near Kamioka, Japan, which contains 50,000 tons of water, will soon see the telltale flash signaling the death of a proton. This minuscule event, the theorists predict, would yield some decay products. In one possible decay route, the products would be an antielectron and a pi meson, which would almost instantly decay into two gamma-ray photons. In another proton decay mode, the debris would include a K meson with a specific energy associated with proton decay, and a virtually undetectable neutrino.</p>
        <p>The demise of a proton (or better, of several protons) would make it easier for theorists to build a Grand Unified Theory that would actually work. Frustrated scientists therefore feel a certain urgency in the quest for deceased protons. During a physics conference in Japan last month, Dr. Frank Wilczek of the Institute of Advanced Studies in Princeton, N.J., told an audience that ''if we don't see proton decay pretty soon, we'll be in serious trouble.''</p>
        <p>Of course, if scientists do detect a proton decay, the whole universe, not just theorists, will be in serious trouble. The death of just one proton would herald the eventual end of everything; if one proton can decay, all protons will decay, and without protons there can be no atoms, molecules, DNA, mountains, roses or concertos.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, even if a protonic funeral should occur in the coming months, the demise of the universe would not be imminent. In exquisitely sensitive experiments in Japan and elsewhere, physicists have determined that if protons decay at all, it must take them more than 2.5 times 10 to the 32d power years to die, on average. That's about 10 quintillion times the present age of the universe, which is believed to be about 14 billion years. (Although the average lifespan of a proton must be phenomenally long, a handful of them could be expected to have short lifetimes, some ending now rather than in the remote future. This is why the current search for proton decay is practical.)</p>
        <p>Of course, inhabitants of the surface of our terrestrial ball of iron and stone have many more immediate worries than proton decay, astrophysicists tell us. The devastating impact of a large comet or asteroid, for example, has furnished profitable grist for movie makers, and there are lots of other celestial catastrophes the entertainment industry has yet to mine.</p>
        <p>The nearby explosion of a supernova is one. There is no telling when or where a supernova will explode, but a few known candidates are uncomfortably close. The red supergiant star Betelgeuse, a mere 430 light years from the Earth, might be about ready to pop. Betelgeuse, a bright star at the shoulder of the constellation Orion, is close enough to us that its explosion could conceivably shower the Earth with potentially harmful radiation and disrupt the protective ozone layer.</p>
        <p>Another nasty possibility came to light during the past year -- roasting by a nearby gamma-ray burster.</p>
        <p>Since the advent of orbiting gamma ray telescopes in recent years, astrophysicists have been puzzled by gamma ray bursters -- spots in the sky that emit intense gamma-ray radiation for a few seconds or hours and then fade away without a trace, never to recur.</p>
        <p>But observations by a new gamma-ray satellite named BeppoSAX, built by Italy and the Netherlands, are so fast and so accurate that they can be used by optical, infrared and X-ray observatories to hunt for faint objects created by or left over from the fleeting gamma-ray bursts.</p>
        <p>Such objects have been found, and their distances from the Earth measured. This led to a sensational surprise last year: some gamma ray bursters appear to be vastly farther away than had been believed. To produce gamma rays of the intensity recorded from the vicinity of the Earth, these mysterious objects must be almost inconceivably powerful. One of them seems to have produced more energy in a few seconds than an entire galaxy generates during a year.</p>
        <p>Theorists surmise that such ''hypernovas'' may result from the violent merger of pairs of black holes or black holes with neutron stars. But no one knows how these great bombs are distributed throughout the universe; if one happened to go off relatively near the Earth, there could be dire consequences.</p>
        <p>Among the outlandish doomsday scenarios dreamed up by some scientists is the possibility that the energy density of ''empty'' space in our part of the universe represents a ''false vacuum''-- an emptiness pervaded by a certain amount of hidden energy. The menace is that there might be another vacuum with a lower energy level into which our part of the universe might tumble, losing all its protons and thereby obliterating our neck of the universal woods, ourselves included.</p>
        <p>It has been suggested by some non-physicists, led by Paul Dixon, a psychologist at the University of Hawaii, that the powerful Tevatron particle accelerator at Fermilab in Illinois (which collides particles together at a combined energy of two trillion electronvolts) might pack so much punch it could start a tear in our friendly space-time along with its false vacuum. Such a catastrophe, it is surmised, would propagate at the speed of light, plunging Batavia, Ill., the site of Fermilab, and the rest of the universe into non-existence.</p>
        <p>Physicists scoff at this notion, saying that the Earth is continuously peppered by cosmic rays that have energies up to 10 to the 19th power electronvolts -- about 10 million times more energy than the most potent accelerator collisions -- and yet our universe survives.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Fermilab is pestered often enough by doom-saying demonstrators that the editors of the laboratory's news letter devoted two pages last month to debunking the torn space-time threat.</p>
        <p>This seems to be the season for contemplating decay and doom, not only in movies but in such serious publications as Sky &amp; Telescope magazine. The August issue features an article entitled ''Future of the Universe,'' which paints a somber process of universal aging and decay, with the last stars winking out about 100 trillion years from now, and even the most massive black holes evaporating in around 10 to the hundredth power years.</p>
        <p>But although the long-term prognosis for our ''region'' of the universe is grim, physics offers some possibilities that could save us from the awful all-becoming nothing, to borrow a phrase from Asian philosophy.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alan Guth of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, whose revolutionary conjectures have strongly influenced cosmological thinking during the last two decades, envisions an eternal process, in which our stable region of the universe must run down to cold, dark death, but other unstable regions of the universe might undergo the same instantaneous process of ''inflation'' that our own region supposedly once underwent long ago. Inflation, in the cosmological sense, means not only instantaneous expansion of space-time, but the spontaneous creation of energy to fill the new space-time, providing the raw stuff of a new universe.</p>
        <p>A new generation of observatories and experiments now on the drawing board may provide some answers to human's most deep-seated questions about the texture and fate of universal existence. In any case, the quest will continue.</p>
        <p>The authors of the Sky &amp; Telescope article, Dr. Fred Adams of the University of Michigan and Dr. Gregory Laughlin of the University of California at Berkeley, put it this way:</p>
        <p>''Whether life can exist indefinitely, or whether the universe is structured to guarantee the final annihilation of all consciousness, purpose and meaning -- including any record that such things ever existed -- holds an inordinate fascination.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 16, 1998, Thursday  An article in Science Times on Tuesday about theories on the end of the universe misstated the name of the institute in Princeton, N.J., with which Dr. Frank Wilczek, a physicist, is affiliated. It is the Institute for Advanced Study, not the Institute of Advanced Studies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 16, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about theories on the end of the universe misstated the name of the institute in Princeton, N.J., with which Dr. Frank Wilczek, a physicist, is affiliated. It is the Institute for Advanced Study, not the Institute of Advanced Studies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
