<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Spending Bill Dictates Delay in Action on Climate Treaty</title>
    <meta content="T26ENVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1027464"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DF163FF935A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="608" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Spending Bill Dictates Delay in Action on Climate Treaty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Congressional opponents of a treaty to fight the threat of global warming are using the annual spending bills now before Congress to send a blunt message to the Clinton Administration: Don't even think about how to meet the treaty's goals before it wins Senate approval.</p>
        <p>As a House committee drafted a bill today to finance the Environmental Protection Agency, the treaty's foes won language warning that the money was not to be used ''for the purpose of implementation, or in contemplation of implementation, of the Kyoto Protocol.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Congressional opponents of a treaty to fight the threat of global warming are using the annual spending bills now before Congress to send a blunt message to the Clinton Administration: Don't even think about how to meet the treaty's goals before it wins Senate approval.</p>
        <p>As a House committee drafted a bill today to finance the Environmental Protection Agency, the treaty's foes won language warning that the money was not to be used ''for the purpose of implementation, or in contemplation of implementation, of the Kyoto Protocol.''</p>
        <p>The international pact, negotiated in Japan last year and supported by the Administration, is opposed by industries including oil, coal, automobile and public utilities, and faces an uphill fight in the Senate.</p>
        <p>The treaty's opponents in the House want to bar the Environmental Protection Agency from even holding seminars on the need to cut emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases like carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Administration officials warned that the E.P.A. spending bill might be vetoed, because of differences with Congress over climate policies, along with other objections to bill, which also finances housing programs, veterans' programs and others.</p>
        <p>The House Appropriations Committee fended off efforts today by Democrats to modify the disputed language. But the legislation still faces consideration by the full House and Senate. The disputed provisions were inserted by a subcommittee last week at the urging of Representative Joe Knollenberg, a Republican from the suburbs of Detroit.</p>
        <p>Treaty opponents have seized every opportunity to challenge the Administration. Representative John D. Dingell, Democrat of Michigan, recently objected when the E.P.A. paid for a study on limiting greenhouse gases through a system of trading emissions credits. The study, he said in a letter to E.P.A. Administrator Carol M. Browner, assumed that the Kyoto protocol would be ratified.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto treaty calls for industrial nations to reduce emissions of greenhouse gases, with the United States cutting 1990 levels by 7 percent over the next 10 or 15 years. Last year, United States emissions of carbon dioxide were about 10 percent higher than in 1990.</p>
        <p>The treaty is strongly opposed by the automobile industry and coal producers, among other industries. The Administration, faced with powerful opposition, has said it will not ask the Senate to approve the deal until further negotiations establish rules for participation by developing nations and for trading emissions-reduction credits among nations.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Administration's opponents in Congress have cut spending requests for existing programs, like energy conservation. The House spending bill would cut the E.P.A.'s request for climate-related programs by $106 million.</p>
        <p>The committee report accompanying the House bill said that the bill is intended to prohibit implementation of the protocol ''in any manner'' before it is approved by the Senate.</p>
        <p>The legislation prohibits any spending ''to develop, propose, or issue rules, regulations, decrees, or orders for the purpose of implementation, or in contemplation of implementation, of the Kyoto Protocol.''</p>
        <p>Administration officials said that might prevent them from setting energy-efficiency standards, encouraging industries to take such measures, or finding ways to give credit to companies that reduce emissions before the treaty becomes binding.</p>
        <p>The committee's report ordered the E.P.A. and the White House Council on Environmental Quality ''to refrain from conducting educational outreach or informational seminars on policies underlying the Kyoto Protocol until, or unless, the Protocol is ratified by the Senate.''</p>
        <p>The agencies, the report said, ''may be engaging in activity that is tantamount to lobbying in an effort to build public support for implementation of the Protocol.'' The language in the reports is usually not binding but carries weight with agencies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
