<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="15FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDA1031F936A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-20</p>
        <p>Iraqi President Retreats But U.S. Threat Remains  The government of President Saddam Hussein appeared to back down in the face of imminent American attack and said Iraq would resume cooperating with arms inspections. But he initially set conditions on his agreement, and American officials said they would procede with military preparations.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Air Attacks Called Off  The United States had prepared a broad campaign of air strikes on Iraq but called it off, at least temporarily, after the last-minute flurry of diplomacy.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-20</p>
        <p>Iraqi President Retreats But U.S. Threat Remains  The government of President Saddam Hussein appeared to back down in the face of imminent American attack and said Iraq would resume cooperating with arms inspections. But he initially set conditions on his agreement, and American officials said they would procede with military preparations.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Air Attacks Called Off  The United States had prepared a broad campaign of air strikes on Iraq but called it off, at least temporarily, after the last-minute flurry of diplomacy.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>'Carlos' on Hunger Strike  The terrorist who calls himself Carlos has been on a hunger strike for 11 days, protesting his four years of solitary confinement in a French prison, where he is serving a life sentence for murder.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>China's Economy Slogs Along  President Jiang Zemin of China can go with some pride to Malaysia for a summit meeting of Asian and Pacific leaders; Chinese economic growth is sluggish by recent standards but looks spectacular compared with the rest of Asia's economies.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Hunger in North Korea  Congressman Tony P. Hall, a Democrat from Ohio who visited remote parts of North Korea this week, said millions of North Koreans might have starved in the last few years.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>Climate Conference Ends  After an all-night session in Buenos Aires, negotiators from more than 150 countries set a deadline of two years for adopting rules for cutting emissions of waste industrial gases that are believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A22-34</p>
        <p>Con Artists Trading In College Scholarships  As the cost of a college education rises, and the cost of not having one soars, scholarship brokers have proliferated, many on the Internet. The Federal Trade Commission and other watchdog groups warn that the quest for scholarship money has produced new victims for con artists. Federal and Ohio authorities are investigating World Education Access, based in Dayton, Ohio, after students who said they were promised scholarships received invalid checks, or no checks at all.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Starr Revisits Whitewater  Less than a week before he is scheduled to testify before the House Judiciary Committee, Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, has apparently abandoned his inquiry into the President's sex life, the portion of his investigation that repulsed most Americans. But Mr. Starr has aggressively returned to his original mission, the Clintons' failed real estate venture named Whitewater.</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>Foreign Policy Is Foremost  A ruling against the Massachusetts Burma Law, which largely bars the state government from doing business with companies that trade with Myanmar, and the state's planned appeal could ultimately reach the Supreme Court and affect all such local sanctions. The judge said the Burma law infringed on the Government's control of foreign policy.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>Los Angeles Police Monitor  The first person to serve as a public watchdog over the Los Angeles Police Department resigned this week, criticized her bosses for undercutting her authority and touched off concerns that the city's commitment to overhauling the department was wavering.</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>37-45</p>
        <p>Remembering a Slain Doctor Who Was Stubbornly Dedicated  Everyone who knew Dr. Barnett A. Slepian, the obstetrician who performed abortions at a clinic in Buffalo until a sniper killed him on Oct. 23, knew that he endured a measure of stress that would exhaust, even break, most people. Strangers pawed through his garbage and growled ''murderer'' at him at the grocery store. Demonstrators assailed the pregnant patients at his private practice. Friends and relatives of the Buffalo doctor wondered how he held up so long under the strain.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>46-47</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>45</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
