<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes, Autocracy Breeds Freedom</title>
    <meta content="28KAPL$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaplan, Robert D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3DC143FF93BA15755C0A96E958260" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes, Autocracy Breeds Freedom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robert D. Kaplan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kaplan, Robert D</byline>
      <dateline>STOCKBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Robert D Kaplan says Americans who lecture Chinese about democracy should be understanding of culture vastly different from theirs; says personal freedoms are greater than they have been in decades in China, and political freedom may follow; says since 1989, China's one-party dictatorship has improved lives of its citizens far more than Russia's multiparty democracy; says not all people see freedom solely in terms of right to vote periodically and to demonstrate and express political views publicly; says they worry about finding job and decent place to live, and by these measures, millions of Chinese lives have improved; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Congressional Republicans and human rights advocates deride President Clinton for visiting China, they might ask themselves the following question: since 1989, which system has improved the lives of its citizens more, China's one-party dictatorship or Russia's multiparty democracy?</p>
        <p>Whether the measure is personal freedom or economic gain, the answer is China's dictatorship. China's rulers have overseen the formation of a capitalist society, where wealth is created at the bottom by individual entrepreneurs. A middle class of tens of millions is beginning to emerge, and along with that, personal freedoms have expanded for homosexuals, unmarried couples, young parents and entrepreneurs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Congressional Republicans and human rights advocates deride President Clinton for visiting China, they might ask themselves the following question: since 1989, which system has improved the lives of its citizens more, China's one-party dictatorship or Russia's multiparty democracy?</p>
        <p>Whether the measure is personal freedom or economic gain, the answer is China's dictatorship. China's rulers have overseen the formation of a capitalist society, where wealth is created at the bottom by individual entrepreneurs. A middle class of tens of millions is beginning to emerge, and along with that, personal freedoms have expanded for homosexuals, unmarried couples, young parents and entrepreneurs.</p>
        <p>In Russia, parliamentary democracy has led to neo-Communism, in the form of a new oligarchic class with its own media outlets and security apparatuses, as well as crime syndicates that have plundered state assets through cronyism, bribery and intimidation. More so than China's new wealth, Russia's belongs to a corrupt, political elite in a few cities.</p>
        <p>Although there was a decline in inflation and a return to growth last year, the Russian economy has consistently been on the brink of collapse. Throughout much of the 1990's, Russia's inflation rate galloped near 150 percent, while its gross national product declined by around 5 percent annually. In China, inflation has often remained in single digits while the gross national product has grown by as much as 13 percent annually. Despite the Asian crisis, China has come close to its goal of 8 percent economic growth this year.</p>
        <p>Russia today recalls its medieval past, in which the Muscovite city-state weakly presides over a vast, impoverished hinterland where highwaymen often govern the roads. The former Soviet Union has become such a disaster that Eastern Europeans now speak of a ''Second Iron Curtain'' -- meaning a curtain of misery on their eastern frontier.</p>
        <p>China's economic growth, meanwhile, has allowed hundreds of millions of its citizens to open bank accounts, buy books and videos, travel and, through television, join a global civilization. China's autocracy has enlarged the mundane, daily freedoms that matter most to ordinary people, even as Russia's democracy has led to near anarchy in the provinces. Whatever qualms Western investors may have about China, they pale in significance to their fears regarding Russia and many so-called democratic former Soviet republics. Indeed, China is now getting 10 times more American investment than Russia is.</p>
        <p>This doesn't mean China is stable. Many Chinese have outgrown the authoritarian institutions that ignited the boom in the first place. Calls for political freedom to match the economic openness will undoubtedly multiply. And the economic meltdown elsewhere in Asia means that China's dictators will be unable to placate their citizenry with the same level of growth as in the past.</p>
        <p>Ethnic unrest threatens in the westernmost province of Sinkiang, where Muslim Turkic Uighurs despise the Chinese. The economic boom has empowered regional political interests in the more prosperous south and coastal areas. Then there is the environment, whose degradation in the form of poisoned air and soil, water shortages, deforestation and acid rain has been estimated to cost China's economy the equivalent of its annual gross national product growth.</p>
        <p>But China's volatility is the consequence of economic energy brought about by increased freedoms. Russia's volatility is caused by economic and social failure. In Russia, the infliction of a parliamentary system on a society that lacked the prerequisites for democracy -- honest bureaucracies, a middle class, a moral code -- has led to lawlessness, unpredictability and ethnic clashes.</p>
        <p>Were China to have suddenly become a parliamentary democracy in 1989 at the time of the Tiananmen Square uprising, the average Chinese citizen would likely be worse off today, and dramatically so. Back then, with more poverty, a smaller middle class and far more ignorance about the outside world, parliamentary democracy in China would probably have ignited turmoil, particularly in areas with ethnic and regional divides.</p>
        <p>Order would have evaporated but corruption, always a scourge in China, would not have. Foreign investment would never have materialized. It is a fact of history that modern bourgeoisies have rarely been created under democratic conditions. It is the bourgeois spirit -- more than a particular system -- that provides for stability and civil society.</p>
        <p>The recent experiences of China and Russia show that the American definition of freedom has become narrow and abstract. The overwhelming majority of people everywhere are not obsessed with politics. They do not see freedom solely in terms of the right to vote periodically and to demonstrate and to express political views publicly. Rather, they worry about such things as finding a job and a decent place to live -- and by these measures, millions of Chinese lives have improved.</p>
        <p>When Americans lecture the Chinese about democracy, they forget their own history. As Tocqueville wrote, the development of American democracy depended on ''the practical experience, the habits, the opinions, in short . . . the customs of the Americans.'' He believed that the national culture led to the American system of government.</p>
        <p>We should therefore be understanding of a culture vastly different from ours, where personal freedoms are greater than they have been in decades, and where political freedom may follow.</p>
        <p>Recently, I visited the ''Chinese market'' on the outskirts of Budapest that provides cheaply priced necessities for Hungarians who cannot afford the fancier shops that have opened since the fall of Communism.</p>
        <p>Many of the merchants are from China. They came to Hungary after the Communists in Beijing loosened travel restrictions. The liberalizing policies of a one-party state have eased the hardships of a new democracy in Central Europe. The world is full of such paradoxes -- paradoxes that President Clinton is aware of, by virtue of his trip to China.</p>
        <p>Robert D. Kaplan, a contributing editor at The Atlantic Monthly, is author of ''The Ends of the Earth.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Robert D. Kaplan, a contributing editor at The Atlantic Monthly, is author of ''The Ends of the Earth.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
