<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NASA Readies a 'Mission to Planet Earth'</title>
    <meta content="17EART$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="996006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AM-1 (Earth Satellite)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DA163FF934A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="2485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NASA Readies a 'Mission to Planet Earth'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <dateline>VALLEY FORGE, Pa.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA engineers prepare new AM-1 craft to inaugurate new era in space science; AM-1 craft's surveillance target is not some distant world, but rather the home planet of those who built it; AM-1 is to be flagship of new generation of earth satellites called Earth Observing System, or EOS, which in turn is centerpiece of what until recently has been called Mission to Planet Earth: 15-year effort to subject interlinked workings of atmosphere, oceans and land surfaces to detailed scrutiny from space; drawings illustrate project (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN a small nondescript room in an equally ordinary low-rise structure just off the Pennsylvania Turnpike, a technician named Dave Banks was speaking into a headset.</p>
        <p>''Chamber, this is Control,'' he said. ''We are going to start the power-up sequence.'' With that, Mr. Banks typed a single line of characters into his computer, setting off a cascade of commands to one of the most important scientific space probes ever to be readied for launching.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN a small nondescript room in an equally ordinary low-rise structure just off the Pennsylvania Turnpike, a technician named Dave Banks was speaking into a headset.</p>
        <p>''Chamber, this is Control,'' he said. ''We are going to start the power-up sequence.'' With that, Mr. Banks typed a single line of characters into his computer, setting off a cascade of commands to one of the most important scientific space probes ever to be readied for launching.</p>
        <p>Twenty-two feet long and 10 feet in diameter, swathed in gold plastic wrap to insulate it in space, the craft is called simply AM-1. Today it is encapsulated in a 37-foot spherical vacuum chamber, where engineers and technicians are testing it in the simulated harshness of the void.  But this summer, if all goes well, AM-1 will inaugurate a new era in space science.</p>
        <p>The craft's surveillance target is not some distant world, but rather the home planet of those who built it. AM-1 is to be the flagship of a new generation of earth satellites called the Earth Observing System, or EOS, which in turn is the centerpiece of what until recently has been called Mission to Planet Earth: a 15-year effort to subject the interlinked workings of the atmosphere, oceans and land surfaces to detailed scrutiny from space.</p>
        <p>The goal of the project, now called simply the Earth Science enterprise, is to fill important gaps in knowledge that prevent scientists from achieving an adequate understanding of the global environment.</p>
        <p>At first, the main focus is to be on the earth's changing climate. Without the information that only satellites can glean, many scientists say, researchers will continue to be hobbled in their efforts to predict how the climate will respond to the combination of natural changes and those forced on the planet by human action -- emissions of heat-trapping gases from industrial waste, for instance.</p>
        <p>The road to this point has been long and contentious.  Attacked nearly a decade ago as an egregious example of big science gone wild, of distorted scientific priorities and overblown spending, EOS today has been sweated down to a cheaper, leaner, more flexible program that is perhaps  better attuned to scientists' actual needs. AM-1 is about a third the size of earlier conceptions, partly because of advancing miniaturization of parts, and the $6.6 billion that EOS itself will have cost by 2000 is about a third of what was originally to be spent.</p>
        <p>Even so, many experts, including top officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, say the $1 billion, five-ton craft, with five instruments aboard, is still too expensive, too big and too complex. They say it is carrying too many scientific eggs in one vulnerable basket.</p>
        <p>''I can tell you, this is a gripping launch,'' said Daniel S. Goldin, the Administrator of the space agency.  ''The loss of that spacecraft would be horrible; I don't want to contemplate the possibilities.''</p>
        <p>If Mr. Goldin has his way, there will never be another EOS satellite this big and complex. Although it was too late to change AM-1 when he took over the helm of the space agency in 1992, he says, the future will be different: EOS sensors will be distributed among many more smaller, cheaper, simpler satellites so that if one is lost, it will not deal such a big blow to what is widely recognized as a vital scientific undertaking.</p>
        <p>That, among other things, has helped the program weather the criticism directed at it in the past by scientists and politicians alike. While EOS ''didn't command a consensus five years ago that it was a good program, it does now,'' said John M. Logsdon, the director of the Space Policy Institute at George Washington University.</p>
        <p>So the way ahead appears clear for the launching of AM-1, now scheduled for June 30. And despite the nervousness of Mr. Goldin and others, an air of excitement is building at the Lockheed Martin Astro Space company's spacecraft construction and test site here.</p>
        <p>Putting AM-1 to the vacuum-chamber test is ''the proof of the pudding,'' said Eugene D. Keeling, who oversees the assembly and testing of the satellite. ''When you hit that, you know everything is coming together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>His boss, Michael Kavka, the director of the AM-1 program, who has been involved in building and launching satellites since the 1960's, bestowed a unique compliment, saying,  ''This is without a doubt the nicest-looking spacecraft I've ever seen.''</p>
        <p>Actually, it has lots of angles and protuberances, as a visitor learned firsthand by standing on a ladder at the bottom of the vacuum chamber before it was drained of air and peering upward at AM-1, where technicians in white coveralls were dusting everything to keep it spotless.  The angles and protuberances are the satellite's business end: five different remote-sensing instruments that will scan the earth continuously once AM-1 is launched from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California into a pole-to-pole orbit.</p>
        <p>The instruments go by their acronymic nicknames, and their functions indicate the scientific breadth of the research program that is about to begin. They include:</p>
        <p>*Modis (for Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer). This is the flagship instrument aboard the flagship satellite. It is designed to provide accurate surface temperature measurements of the entire globe; ground-based thermometers leave gaps and are subject to error. Modis will also measure biological changes in the ocean, changes in land vegetation, and changes in the properties of clouds and atmospheric aerosols. The latter are tiny droplets of sulfur that reflect sunlight and minute particles that serve as the nuclei for cloud-forming water droplets.</p>
        <p>*Ceres (Clouds and the Earth's Radiant Energy System) will measure incoming solar radiation, which drives the climate system, as well as radiation re-emitted by the earth, which, when trapped by greenhouse gases, warms the planet. The instrument will also measure cloud properties.</p>
        <p>*Aster (Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Reflection Radiometer) will make ''zoom'' images of terrestrial surface features and take finer readings of surface temperature and cloud cover.</p>
        <p>*Misr (Multi-angle Imaging Spectroradiometer) is designed to look at the three-dimensional structure of clouds and aerosol concentrations from several angles. It will also make fine-grained images of surface features -- for example, the heights of trees.</p>
        <p>*Mopitt (Measurements of Pollution in the Troposphere) will measure atmospheric carbon monoxide, to help better understand the earth's carbon cycle, and methane, a greenhouse gas.</p>
        <p>Japan contributed Aster to the mix, and Mopitt is a Canadian contribution. The other three instruments are American-made.</p>
        <p>If all the instruments work as designed, scientists will get the clearest picture they have ever had of how the earth-ocean-atmosphere system functions. For instance, two of the instruments will measure aerosols and four are to measure cloud properties. Lack of data about these two features is the biggest impediment faced by researchers who use computer models to simulate and predict the global climate's behavior. Without a realistic rendition of cloud and aerosol behavior, the models' predictions about any human-induced global warming will continue to be shrouded in a frustrating haze of uncertainty.</p>
        <p>While virtually everyone concerned agrees that the data to be provided by EOS are essential, there is also a consensus that satellites cannot do the whole job by themselves. Some data can be acquired only by measurements on the ground, at sea or in the air, with sensors aboard aircraft. In the early 1990's, EOS was severely criticized by those who believed it was drawing money away from these more prosaic means of observation. Critics back then also worried that EOS might suck up money that would otherwise support the work of scientists who would use the data.</p>
        <p>As conceived at the start of the 1990's, EOS was to consist of an elaborate array of six 15-ton satellites, each carrying 12 sensing instruments -- ''Battlestar Galacticas,'' Mr. Goldin calls these behemoths -- to be launched over a 12-year period beginning in 1998. A complementary series of smaller satellites was to be sent into orbit starting somewhat earlier. The cost of the program, including operational expenses, was projected at $17 billion by 2000 and $30 billion by 2020.</p>
        <p>But the project never found solid support. When Mr. Goldin became the NASA Administrator, he set out to make the space agency's programs ''smaller, cheaper, faster, better,'' and EOS was a prime target of his intended reforms. Mr. Goldin brought in Dr. Charles F. Kennel, a plasma physicist at the University of California at Los Angeles, as associate administrator for Mission to Planet Earth.</p>
        <p>Not long after Dr. Kennel arrived,  the program came under attack from Congressional Republicans who charged that its purpose was to push a global-warming agenda.</p>
        <p>EOS survived that challenge, but was redesigned in accordance with Mr. Goldin's philosophy.</p>
        <p>The next EOS satellites will all be smaller than AM-1. One of these, set for launching in 2000, would complement AM-1 by making many of the same measurements (plus some new ones) at a different time of day. (The second satellite is to be called PM-1, because it will cross the Equator in the afternoon instead of the morning, as AM-1 will.) Another satellite, to be launched in 2002, is called Chem-1 and will measure atmospheric trace gases, like water vapor, ozone and nitrous oxides, that play critical roles in regulating the earth's climate.</p>
        <p>Before the end of this year, the latest in the highly successful series of Landsat satellites, which make images and measure properties of the earth's land areas, is also to be launched. Landsat 7, as it is called, and its successors will be folded into the EOS program. A fifth EOS satellite now scheduled for launching, Icesat-1, is to go into orbit in 2001 to measure the growth and shrinkage of global ice sheets.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, a number of smaller, complementary satellites, each making a single type of measurement, are to be placed in orbit.  The first, launched last November, measures tropical rainfall.</p>
        <p>The space agency plans to hold off building EOS spacecraft for the period beyond 2001 as long as possible, both to take advantage of the newest technology and take into account any new research priorities that emerge once the first round of data has been analyzed. Smaller satellites, which can be built faster, make this flexibility possible, Mr. Goldin said.</p>
        <p>In further pursuit of flexibility, the whole program now undergoes a full-scale reassessment every two years.  As a result of the most recent review, last summer, NASA boiled down its earth-science research targets to five areas: seasonal-to-annual climate variability; climate change over years and decades; atmospheric chemistry and ozone; natural hazards like volcanoes, earthquakes, floods and hurricanes; and, changes in land use and land cover. All told, EOS is ultimately to make 24 separate kinds of measurements.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldin said the scaling-down has freed money to support the research of scientists who will use the EOS data. From about $136 million provided in the fiscal 1997 budget, he said, the total is scheduled to rise gradually until it approaches $200 million in 2002.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is totally happy with the balance in resources being allocated to satellites and the equally important conventional measurements. ''It is a continuing challenge to make sure we're doing both'' adequately, said Dr. Michael MacCracken, an official of the United States Global Change Research Program, the Federal office under which Mission to Planet Earth functions.</p>
        <p>Over all, the program ''has improved enormously,'' said Dr. Thomas M. Donahue, a professor of planetary science and physics at the University of Michigan, an early critic of what he called the original ''humongous'' EOS spacecraft. Criticism from scientists has died down, he said. ''I don't hear a lot of complaining now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Conservative Republicans in Congress say the program is still too big and should rely more on the private sector to perform remote sensing. Some say EOS remains a creature of Democrats and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Its ''driving force'' is the desire to ''prove global warming,'' said Representative Dana Rohrabacher, a California Republican. Mr. Rohrabacher, who heads the space and aeronautics subcommittee of the House Science Committee, said the space agency should rely more on the private sector and on smaller and cheaper satellites.</p>
        <p>NASA officials insist that science alone drives the program. Far from promoting any point of view about global warming, Dr. Kennel said, NASA wants to contribute information and be an ''honest broker'' in the debate on climate change.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Goldin said that ''we are really listening'' to the Congressional critics. ''We value criticism at NASA,'' he said. Mr. Rohrabacher responded, ''I think he has heard me.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kennel, for his part, said he believed that the worst of EOS's problems were behind it. But while the program is not in mortal danger, he said, it will always be under pressure from Congress and others.</p>
        <p>''I think that pressure is healthy,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
