<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FOOD CHAIN</title>
    <meta content="25CHAI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1DF1639F936A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FOOD CHAIN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELISSA CLARK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Flours: The Hard and the Soft</p>
        <p>Q: Often, recipes specify ''cake flour'' or ''bread flour.'' What are they? If I don't have them, can I substitute all-purpose flour? And what is ''hard'' flour, which is called for in some recipes? Is there such a thing as ''soft'' flour?</p>
        <p>A:  For all intents and purposes, bread flour and hard flour are the same thing. Ditto for cake flour and soft flour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Flours: The Hard and the Soft</p>
        <p>Q: Often, recipes specify ''cake flour'' or ''bread flour.'' What are they? If I don't have them, can I substitute all-purpose flour? And what is ''hard'' flour, which is called for in some recipes? Is there such a thing as ''soft'' flour?</p>
        <p>A:  For all intents and purposes, bread flour and hard flour are the same thing. Ditto for cake flour and soft flour.</p>
        <p>Before all-purpose flour became ubiquitous, recipes for baked goods often called for one specific type of flour, but that happens only occasionally now.</p>
        <p>White wheat flours are categorized by their protein content. Bread flour is ground from wheat that is especially high in proteins, including those that make up gluten.</p>
        <p>When bread dough is kneaded, the gluten in the flour forms an elastic network, or web, which traps the carbon dioxide gas given off by the yeast. That is what causes the dough to rise. The more gluten, the greater the bread dough's tendency to rise (provided there is sufficient yeast activity), and the lighter the finished loaf.</p>
        <p>Flour milled from low-protein strains of wheat has less gluten. It is called soft flour, and is often marketed as ''cake'' or ''pastry'' flour, since it is perfect for mixing into tender, delicate cake batter and pastry dough.</p>
        <p>All-purpose flour -- a mixture of hard and soft wheat flours -- has become a standard compromise in contemporary recipes. While it can be used for most baked goods, it excels in none. But when a recipe calls for all-purpose flour, it means that the recipe has been developed -- or at least tested -- using all-purpose flour, and it is best to follow the recommendation.</p>
        <p>But if a recipe calls for cake flour and all you have is all-purpose, you can make a fine substitute by mixing  1/4 cup cornstarch with  3/4 cup all-purpose flour for each cup of cake flour.</p>
        <p>If a recipe calls for bread flour and you have only all-purpose, adding a tablespoon of gluten powder for every cup will help the dough rise; it will also make multigrain breads lighter. (Gluten flour is available in health-food stores.)</p>
        <p>Another tip: When a recipe calls for cake flour, don't use the self-rising kind. The added salt and leavening will throw off the proportions and bake up into a tough-crumb cake.</p>
        <p>MELISSA CLARK</p>
        <p>Questions about food and cooking can be sent to Food Chain, the Dining section, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036-3959, or by E-mail to dining@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
