<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In and Out of a Mind Thought to Be Doomed</title>
    <meta content="12CANB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031122"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gets, Malcolm</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Danielle, Graciela</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canby, Vincent</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, William</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">New Brain, A (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DF113EF931A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In and Out of a Mind Thought to Be Doomed</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vincent Canby</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Canby, Vincent</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vincent Canby reviews William Finn chamber opera A New Brain starring Malcolm Gets and directed by Graciela Danielle at Lincoln Center, NYC; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NEW BRAIN,'' William Finn's latest chamber opera, is the composer-lyricist's attempt to deal with what was obviously a doomy, seriously traumatic experience: the preliminary diagnosis of an inoperable brain tumor, which he received in 1992 just two weeks after winning Tonys for his book and score for ''Falsettos.''</p>
        <p>In the program for ''A New Brain,'' which is now at the Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater in Lincoln Center, he reports that all he could think about in the days before the diagnosis was revised ''were the songs I had planned to write but hadn't finally written.'' The show we're now seeing, he says, is not meant to be a medical drama since what eventually happened was ''much worse than anything that's on the stage.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NEW BRAIN,'' William Finn's latest chamber opera, is the composer-lyricist's attempt to deal with what was obviously a doomy, seriously traumatic experience: the preliminary diagnosis of an inoperable brain tumor, which he received in 1992 just two weeks after winning Tonys for his book and score for ''Falsettos.''</p>
        <p>In the program for ''A New Brain,'' which is now at the Mitzi E. Newhouse Theater in Lincoln Center, he reports that all he could think about in the days before the diagnosis was revised ''were the songs I had planned to write but hadn't finally written.'' The show we're now seeing, he says, is not meant to be a medical drama since what eventually happened was ''much worse than anything that's on the stage.''</p>
        <p>Instead, ''A New Brain'' means to recall what it's like to spend five weeks thinking you're going to die, and then living. A Dostoyevskian experience full of dread, anger and hopelessness? Possibly, but in Mr. Finn's hindsight it also seems to have been therapeutic: a time to recognize priorities, the ephemeral nature of existence and the alternately sustaining and lacerating effects of the artist's merciless vision.</p>
        <p>Yet the show that has come out of all this is a major anticlimax. ''A New Brain'' is a peculiarly random collection of pale characters and unrevealing incidents that seem more like an exercise in composition than an urgent expression of the creative impulse restored.</p>
        <p>The new show is especially wan after the exuberant wit, originality and technical virtuosity of ''Falsettos,'' in which Mr. Finn explores the awakening of one of the musical theater's most charming heels. He is Marvin, an aggressively feckless fellow who's thunderstruck to realize that he can't put together a household of his ex-wife, his troubled adolescent son, his male lover and his shrink (who has fallen in love with and married the ex-wife).</p>
        <p>Gordon Michael Schwinn, the central character in ''A New Brain,'' could use a little of Marvin's redeeming chutzpah. Instead he's a passive character whose grand aspirations would seem quite unrealistic. Like Mr. Finn early in his career, Gordon is a composer and lyricist who dreams of writing great songs while turning out ditties for children's television programs, in this case for a loathsome man-size frog named Mr. Bungee.</p>
        <p>During most of the 100-minute ''New Brain,'' which is played without an intermission, we move in and out of Gordon's woozy mind as he deals with his mother, his agent,  his lover, Mr. Bungee and assorted doctors, nurses and other types found in hospital corridors. Hovering on the fringes of his awareness is a mysterious woman who wears rags and has a smudged face, identified in the program as Lisa, ''a homeless lady.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Finn's principal associates are Graciela Daniele, the show's director and choreographer, and James Lapine, who collaborated with him on the book. (Mr. Lapine earlier worked with Mr. Finn on ''March of the Falsettos'' and ''Falsettoland,'' which, combined, became the material for the Broadway production of ''Falsettos.'') Both Ms. Daniele and Mr. Lapine appear to have worked overtime to give this new project some sense of cohesion and energy, but it never takes off on its own. ''A New Brain'' seems always to be on artificial life support.</p>
        <p>Quite early in the show, not long after Gordon has been hospitalized, Ms. Daniele stages a big, energetic song-and-dance number (''Ya gotta have heart and music/Heart and music make a song''), enthusiastically performed by all the principal characters, including the dreaming Gordon. Yet because the number comes so early in the show, before the audience is aware of what the stakes are, it seems to have no point, either as a genuine anthem or as a send-up.</p>
        <p>In this way, the number reflects the weaknesses of Mr. Finn's entire score, which is never as evocative, pointed or diasarmingly cheeky as ''Falsettos.'' So much attention is devoted to subsidiary characters that Gordon remains no more than a puzzled ego. It's as if he sees everything through a squint, so that the show becomes as out-of-focus as he is.</p>
        <p>Especially disappointing are some of the lyrics, whose banality can't be excused as intentional. I think of the number (''I'd Rather Be Sailing'') sung by Gordon's lover, Roger, who, as imagined by Gordon, describes his joy at being on the sea by rhyming ''sailing'' with ''railing,'' which is the thing he leans against as he's ''inhaling'' the fresh salt air.</p>
        <p>One of the show's better songs is sung by a robustly gay male nurse, who rues his fate in ''Poor, Unsuccessful and Fat.'' Meanwhile, the mysterious homeless lady pops up from time to time as a kind of tough, streetwise psychiatrist prone to enigmatic pronouncements in song. As the show pushes doggedly on, Gordon himself becomes even more of a cipher than he was at the beginning. Perhaps Mr. Finn should have spent more time on the real horrors of Gordon's craniotomy and hospitalization rather than attempting to compose a half-heartedly upbeat musical testament to his survival.</p>
        <p>Ms. Daniele's production looks great and is well sung, especially by Malcolm Gets (Gordon), Penny Fuller (Gordon's mother), Liz Larsen (his agent), Michael Mandell (the nurse), Chip Zien (Mr. Bungee) and Mary Testa (the homeless lady).</p>
        <p>'The Skin of Our Teeth'</p>
        <p>Thornton Wilder's cosmic comedy, ''The Skin of Our Teeth,'' which triumphed on Broadway in 1942 under the direction of Elia Kazan, is still some kind of great play, but it's not easily revived today. That's clear in the earnest, jokey, sometimes colorful Joseph Papp Public Theater production that closes today at the Delacorte Theater in Central Park.</p>
        <p>When you read it, ''The Skin of Our Teeth'' is a free-form delight: the history of the world as experienced by Mr. and Mrs. George Antrobus, an average American couple from Excelsior, N.J. During their 5,000-year marriage, he invents the wheel and the alphabet, among other things, and she keeps the family together while he periodically threatens to run off with other women, all played by the Antrobus maid, Sabina. Plucky optimists that they are, the Antrobuses survive the Ice Age, the Flood, various depressions large and small, and World War II, which America was just getting into when Wilder wrote the play.</p>
        <p>In his autobiography, ''A Life,'' Mr. Kazan describes the form of the play ''as novel and constantly surprising,'' but says that ''the author's values'' are ''conventional and finally stuffy.'' He adds: ''Other plays I've liked were conceived out of the life experience of the dramatist; this play seemed to have been hatched in the library of a financially secure college campus.''</p>
        <p>That's a devastating though not inaccurate assessment. Wilder was a cerebral artist for whom the mind was the only logical locale for his Grand Tours. Part philosopher, part professor, part yarn spinner, he created tales that depended less on particular experience than on his imagination. He was a fantasist of the ideal.</p>
        <p>Whatever its conception, ''The Skin of Our Teeth'' is full of irresistible moments that are especially difficult to recreate in today's theater, which is far less bound by conventions than was the Broadway theater of 1942. In Wilder's script, the actress playing Sabina is constantly interrupting the performance, as if ad-libbing, to say she hasn't a clue as to what the play's about, to remember other, better roles, or to refuse to say a particular line of dialogue she finds distasteful.</p>
        <p>This was pretty lively stuff in 1942, especially when Tallulah Bankhead, at her most grandly volcanic, was playing the outspoken actress who plays Sabina.</p>
        <p>Today's audiences have grown up watching television comics step in and out of character, break up at their own jokes and make rude remarks about their material. Such badinage has become an accepted form of contemporary humor, almost obligatory. This may be why the Delacorte audience with which I saw the play accepted these interruptions as comic. It wasn't because the interruptions really were funny (which they weren't, at least not as played by these actors), but because it was recognized they were supposed to be funny. Television has taught us that intentions are enough.</p>
        <p>''The Skin of Our Teeth'' is showing its age these days, but there's nothing wrong with that unless, as sometimes happens in this staging, you have the feeling that the actors are patronizing their material, patting it on the head. What is more difficult to accept is Wilder's conviction that man will somehow muddle through.</p>
        <p>In this time of the Bomb, environmental pollution and global warming, such optimism seems utterly mad, until you understand that, in 1942, optimism was a patriotic duty.</p>
        <p>The Delacourt production, directed by Irene Lewis, has the great good fortune to have John Goodman playing Mr. Antrobus, which may be the best role he's had since his early years on ''Roseanne.'' Mr. Goodman is a fine, big stage performer, disciplined, commanding and unfussy.  His George Antrobus pats no one on the head. He's a salesman, traveling through the ages, meeting the eye of each person he's talking to. Frances Conroy is also stalwart as Mrs. Antrobus, not an easy assignment since it's almost entirely humorless.</p>
        <p>Kristen Johnston, of television's ''Third Rock From the Sun,'' looks stunning as Sabina, with a voluptuous figure that seems to have been sewn into her saucy maid's costume.  She also has the seductively husky voice required of a siren still operating at peak efficiency after 5,000 years on the job.</p>
        <p>What she lacks, however, is an apparent willingness to be the bitchy opportunist who might alienate the audience. She tries too hard to please, which is the manner of the entire production. This ''Skin of Our Teeth'' seems geared to convince the audience that it's a warm, cuddly teddy bear of a show.</p>
        <p>It was to guard against such interpretations that Wilder mocked his own highfalutin aims in Sabina's asides to the audience. If anyone was going to wink at the audience, Wilder would do the winking. The members of the cast were expected to play it straight.</p>
        <p>A NEW BRAIN: Especially wan after the wit, originality and virtuosity one expects from William Finn.</p>
        <p>THE SKIN OF OUR TEETH: Such optimism seems mad until you realize that in 1942 it was a patriotic duty.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
