<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Little Progress for G.O.P. and White House on Spending Bills</title>
    <meta content="Y09SPE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EFD6133BF93AA35753C1A96E958260" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Little Progress for G.O.P. and White House on Spending Bills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional Republicans and White House, with their deadline just hours away, make little progress toward resolving their differences over must-pass spending bills needed to keep Govt open (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With their deadline just hours away, Congressional Republicans and the White House made little progress today toward resolving their differences over the must-pass spending bills needed to keep the Government open.</p>
        <p>Aides said that up to 150 matters were on the table, about a dozen of them major but all of them needing attention, and that new issues were cropping up by the minute as the impeachment vote dominated the stage and members sought to slip in pet projects. These included such items as extending patent periods on various drugs, subsidizing importers of fine wool and increasing military pensions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With their deadline just hours away, Congressional Republicans and the White House made little progress today toward resolving their differences over the must-pass spending bills needed to keep the Government open.</p>
        <p>Aides said that up to 150 matters were on the table, about a dozen of them major but all of them needing attention, and that new issues were cropping up by the minute as the impeachment vote dominated the stage and members sought to slip in pet projects. These included such items as extending patent periods on various drugs, subsidizing importers of fine wool and increasing military pensions.</p>
        <p>''Today was a day that we slipped backwards,'' said one top Democratic aide.</p>
        <p>With the Senate's vote today to pass the bill financing the veterans affairs and housing programs, Congress has still cleared only 6 of the 13 spending bills in advance of the midnight Friday deadline, when temporary financing of the Government runs out. Both sides are expected to agree on Friday to extend the temporary financing for at least a day or two.</p>
        <p>Republican leaders in both the House and Senate were scrambling behind the scenes and in negotiations with the White House to piece together the remaining bills, while in public, the House voted to begin an impeachment inquiry of the President and the Senate addressed matters unrelated to spending.</p>
        <p>In a kind of surreal reminder of his power as President, Mr. Clinton, on the eve of the impeachment vote, set the appropriations back a notch by vetoing one of the six spending bills that Congress had cleared. This was the measure on agriculture matters and disaster relief for farmers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton said in his veto message that he wanted more money for farmers, but the veto, which he signed just before midnight Wednesday, was widely perceived as a last-minute attempt to please Democrats from farm states before they voted on impeachment.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said Mr. Clinton wanted to give Congress time to fix the matter before the Friday deadline. It struck Republicans as odd, though, that he would veto the bill since Congress had put more money into the agriculture bill than he had requested; it was only after Democrats said they wanted more that the President joined the cause.</p>
        <p>With time running out, Republican leaders said they would not try to override the agriculture veto but would roll the bill into the ever-expanding omnibus package that will contain other contentious issues.</p>
        <p>But they did agree tentatively to meet some of the President's more-publicized demands, including providing money for fuel assistance for low-income people, for summer jobs and for child care.</p>
        <p>For most of the day, House leaders were sequestered in closed-door sessions deciding what to include in the omnibus and what to exclude, leaving many members to gesture with futility toward the Speaker's office and say in a phrase repeated throughout the Capitol that all decisions were above their pay grade.</p>
        <p>The House, which has yet to act on six spending bills, voted on none today. The Senate, which has seven spending bills outstanding, easily passed the bill covering veterans affairs and housing but never got around to the next spending bill on its docket, the one covering the Treasury Department and the United States Postal Service.</p>
        <p>The fact that so many bills remain unmoved at this point in the process was a sign of how deeply divided Republicans are among themselves, between the two houses and from the Administration.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most contentious bill, despite some progress today, is the one financing labor, health, human services and education. This is the first time since Congress started funding these agencies together more than 40 years ago that both houses appeared unlikely to pass the labor and health bill.</p>
        <p>Hang-ups include millions of dollars that President Clinton wants for education, including 100,000 teachers and expanded after-school programs. The President also wants national testing for students, but the bill bars any steps toward that.</p>
        <p>Complicating the outlook for the bill is a proposal floating in the Senate to add a tobacco-related measure that would prevent the Federal Government from receiving any of the money that states receive from tobacco settlements.</p>
        <p>Another difficult bill is the one financing the Interior Department, which has passed the House but not the Senate. The President has warned for months that he would veto the bill if it retained the numerous ''riders'' that he calls anti-environmental.</p>
        <p>These include provisions to increase nationwide timber sales, to allow clearcutting in Alaska's Tongass National Forest, to allow roads to be built through wilderness in Alaska's Isembek National Wildlife Refuge and across wetlands in Alaska, to halt plans to reintroduce the grizzly bear into the Selway-Bitteroot system in Idaho and Montana and to mandate the renewal of grazing permits on land owned by the Bureau of Land Management.</p>
        <p>Potential roadblocks to agreements on other bills include a measure that the Administration says would weaken the background checks in purchases of handguns, bar the use of money to study global climate change and deny aid to international family-planning groups that use their own money to advocate abortion rights.</p>
        <p>Many Republicans said that while numerous problems loomed, especially over big topics like the census and the money for the International Monetary Fund, they expected to work them out rather than shut down the Government. With the impeachment vote over, members are increasingly anxious to get home to campaign for the November elections.</p>
        <p>Representative John Porter, Republican of Illinois and chairman of the labor subcommittee of the appropriations committee, said his committee still had 25 issues to resolve. But Mr. Porter said a Government shutdown was highly unlikely, mainly because of the negotiating skill of Erskine B. Bowles, the President's chief of staff.</p>
        <p>''A shutdown has receded as a possibility because of the way Erskine Bowles has approached the discussion,'' Mr. Porter said.</p>
        <p>Administration officials, including Jack Lew, the director of the Office of Management and Budget, and Lawrence Stein, the Administration's liaison with Congress, were meeting tonight with Speaker Newt Gingrich and others.</p>
        <p>In another part of the Capitol, Treasury Secretary Robert E. Rubin was trying to strike a deal under which Republicans would agree to full financing of the International Monetary Fund. Republicans want to impose conditions on the lending agency in exchange for $18 billion to shore up its reserves.</p>
        <p>Representative Sonny Callahan, Republican of Alabama and chairman of the foreign operations subcommittee of the appropriations committee, said a deal ''could materialize tonight or tomorrow.'' But this matter too is likely to be tossed into the omnibus package, which would be presented to the President on a take-it-or-leave-it basis.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
