<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Record Penalty Likely Against Diesel Makers</title>
    <meta content="22TRUC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E2DC103DF931A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Record Penalty Likely Against Diesel Makers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency nears accord with makers of heavy-duty diesel truck engines allegedly designed to evade clean air standards that calls for record $1 billion fine; deal would also force companies to speed introduction of cleaner engines, take other steps to offset excess emissions produced by up to million trucks with these engines; EPA reportedly plans to use some of money to pay for changes to engines when they wear out and have to be rebuilt; engines are programmed to run more cleanly in laboratory tests than on road, where they save on fuel but let pollution rise (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency is expected to impose its biggest civil penalty ever in a settlement with manufacturers of heavy-duty diesel truck engines for violating clean air standards, officials said today.</p>
        <p>For the past several days, lawyers for the E.P.A. and the Justice Department have been wrapping up a $1 billion settlement with several engine makers that would force the companies to pay large fines and speed the introduction of cleaner engines. The manufacturers are also expected to take other steps to offset the excess emissions produced by as many as a million trucks with engines that the Government says were designed to evade pollution standards of the Clean Air Act.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency is expected to impose its biggest civil penalty ever in a settlement with manufacturers of heavy-duty diesel truck engines for violating clean air standards, officials said today.</p>
        <p>For the past several days, lawyers for the E.P.A. and the Justice Department have been wrapping up a $1 billion settlement with several engine makers that would force the companies to pay large fines and speed the introduction of cleaner engines. The manufacturers are also expected to take other steps to offset the excess emissions produced by as many as a million trucks with engines that the Government says were designed to evade pollution standards of the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>One manufacturer, Cummins Engine Company, said today that the negotiations ''appear to be concluding'' and Government officials said they expected a settlement as early as Thursday.</p>
        <p>''We are working to conclude discussions as soon as possible so that we can reach an agreement that protects public health and the environment,'' said Loretta Ucelli, the E.P.A. spokeswoman. She said it would be inappropriate to discuss the details until the deal was completed.</p>
        <p>If approved, the settlement could cost the companies close to $1 billion before taxes and significantly reduce future pollution from diesel trucks, a major source of smog and acid rain, especially in the Northeast and California, where officials have been closely involved.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and Government officials say diesel engines were passed over in emission standards until the 1990's because they caused much less smog than did cars and smokestack industries. But since car emissions of hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxide began to be regulated in 1970, diesel engines have increasingly emerged as a greater problem.</p>
        <p>People who have been briefed on the settlement said it did not require that the trucks be immediately recalled and modified. Instead, the E.P.A. wants to use some of the money from the settlement to pay for changes to the engines when they wear out and have to be rebuilt, typically after several years or a few hundred thousand miles of operation.</p>
        <p>Agency officials decided that truck owners would be unlikely to comply with a recall, since fixing the pollution problem would cut fuel efficiency and significantly increase the costs of driving the trucks.</p>
        <p>As many as a million trucks are involved, some of them giving off as much as twice the allowable amount of pollution.</p>
        <p>They were built in the last 10 years by several companies, including Cummins, the Detroit Diesel Corporation, Mack Trucks, the Navistar International Transportation Company, Caterpillar , Renault and Volvo. It is not known which companies will be covered by the settlement.</p>
        <p>The Government believes that the companies used computerized controls built into the diesel engines to insure that the engines run as cleanly as possible in the laboratory during emissions tests required by the Federal law. But when the trucks are actually cruising on the highways, the controls are programmed to adjust how the engines operate, saving fuel but letting pollution rise.</p>
        <p>Typically, the computer controls alter the timing of fuel injection in the engine after monitoring the engine's operating speed over a period of time, effectively deactivating the main control that limits emissions, the agency has claimed.</p>
        <p>As a result, pollution experts say, these one million trucks are giving off as much smog-forming chemicals as about 50 million automobiles.</p>
        <p>The manufacturers have disputed the assertion that they evaded the pollution laws, saying that the engine tests designed by the E.P.A. simulate urban driving patterns and that the engine designs do indeed control pollution during stop-and-go driving on congested roads.</p>
        <p>In announcing its third quarter earnings today, Cummins said ''resolution of this matter could have a material effect on Cummins financial results.''</p>
        <p>Civil penalties are not tax deductible, but some of the steps the companies would have to take, like introducing clean engines sooner than planned, will be a normal cost of doing business and will lessen the companies' tax liabilities, cushioning the financial impact.</p>
        <p>The companies would also spend some of the settlement money to provide vehicles with clean-burning engines that they produce themselves for demonstration projects, like urban mass transit programs.</p>
        <p>The case, which has been under negotiation and in litigation since early this year, is being watched by state officials and environmental advocates. Truck operators and members of Congress have also been putting pressure on the agency.</p>
        <p>Some state officials, including New York and New Jersey authorities, were involved in the talks, and environmental advocates have filed a related lawsuit in California.</p>
        <p>The American Trucking Association wrote President Clintonto protest the deal, saying it would ''require significant changes in new engines and trucks in overly short and unreasonable time periods.''</p>
        <p>But Al Meyerhoff, a lawyer representing the Sierra Club and the Environmental Law Foundation, said the groups would challenge the deal in court because the agency was not demanding an instant recall of the trucks. ''Every year of delay is more cancer and more illness,'' Mr. Meyerhoff said.</p>
        <p>Even as the final details were hammered out, with some manufacturers still holding out, the outlines of the deal were described by several people involved.</p>
        <p>They said the civil penalty alone, expected to be about $100 million, would make the settlement as big as any ever reached by the agency.</p>
        <p>''Anything less would be absurd,'' said Jason Grumet, executive director of the Northeast States for Coordinated Air Use Management, a regional organization of pollution control authorities. ''This is far and away the biggest violation of air quality standards under the Clean Air Act.''</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. has estimated that hundreds of thousands of trucks may emit up to twice the permitted level of nitrogen oxides, a chemical that contributes to smog and to acid rain. In the Northeast, heavy-duty truck engines account for about a third of the emissions of nitrogen oxides. Rough calculations by state officials indicate that the faulty trucks may be emitting a million tons of nitrogen oxides a year. And the trucks that are already on the road are likely to remain in use for decades.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists objected to the lack of a recall. Others said they would wait to see how much of the pollution would be eliminated, and on what timetable, before making comments on any settlement.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
