<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Eye; Still Reaching for the Sun</title>
    <meta content="02EYE.$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Flanagan, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EFDE1E3FF931A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="778" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Eye; Still Reaching for the Sun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barbara Flanagan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Flanagan, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum mounts exhibition on the expanding design possibilities of solar energy technology; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOLAR-POWERED fiber optics? Photovoltaic cell-laminated tensile hyperbolic paraboloids? Today's visionary gibberish is tomorrow's plain English. The nifty thing about emerging technologies is the way they sneak up on you, then transform your life overnight.</p>
        <p>''Under the Sun: An Outdoor Exhibition of Light,'' a garden installation inside the wrought-iron fence of the Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum until Oct. 25, explains how solar technology has been sneaking up on civilization in the 20th century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOLAR-POWERED fiber optics? Photovoltaic cell-laminated tensile hyperbolic paraboloids? Today's visionary gibberish is tomorrow's plain English. The nifty thing about emerging technologies is the way they sneak up on you, then transform your life overnight.</p>
        <p>''Under the Sun: An Outdoor Exhibition of Light,'' a garden installation inside the wrought-iron fence of the Cooper-Hewitt National Design Museum until Oct. 25, explains how solar technology has been sneaking up on civilization in the 20th century.</p>
        <p>As for the transformation of daily life -- the one foretold in the 1970's, when solar-energy zealots worshiped clunky black panels and declared independence from fossil fuels -- it is once again in sight. This time around, the show declares, the design possibilities are endless. So are the global perks (cleaner air, fewer oil wars). No, really.</p>
        <p>Solar power as a source of electricity was discovered in 1839, refined for satellites in the 1950's, and lately has been engineered into glass panels for the rising office tower at Four Times Square designed by Fox &amp; Fowle Architects with Kiss &amp; Cathcart Architects.</p>
        <p>But only over the last few years have scientists figured out how to make photovoltaic material -- now a thin black film that can be attached to other materials -- turn sunlight into electricity affordably. The Energy Department and BP Solar (a subsidiary of British Petroleum, and a manufacturer of photovoltaics) helped sponsor this traveling exhibition to spread the news: this is not your father's solar energy.</p>
        <p>It is not your father's old museum fare either. Lucy Fellowes, who shaped the exhibition over four years, did more than the standard curatorial sweep. Yes, Ms. Fellowes, the museum's curator for special projects, created a time line of solar history and collected solar-powered products and prototypes (lawn mower, lantern, call box, computer, lights and so on). But there is plenty of innovation, too.</p>
        <p>She commissioned two forward-looking New York architects to design the exhibition and to create two original structures using photovoltaics in new ways. Early on, the exhibition and its message became a collaborative mission.</p>
        <p>Nicholas Goldsmith, of FTL Happold Architects and Engineers, designed the garden's most imposing structure: a 30-foot-high solar tensile pavilion, a fabric tent laminated with photovoltaic film five-thousandths of an inch thick. At night, the film electrifies a display of red lights.</p>
        <p>The show's timing is fortuitous. At the apex of a stock market that has financed a cavalcade of giant gas guzzlers and small electronic consumables, ''Under the Sun'' offers a change of perspective. Refreshingly, it involves no recycled garbage.</p>
        <p>Its wonders may be arriving just in time. After a decade of techno-ennui -- the fatigue of being startled by an onslaught of PC's, laptops, cell phones, satellites, lasers -- users are jaded. Cash-machine cards in hand, they stand ready to be wowed, then bored, then wowed again by the next barrage of personal gadgets in black or taupe. Is that all there is?</p>
        <p>What is missing is awe. It takes something like this exhibition to show off the poetry of solar energy. When designers express the link between earth and sky, between the sun and our insatiable need for power, the trick can be downright thrilling.</p>
        <p>Witness the Himawari, an intricate silver pod with a transparent dome tucked under one of the Cooper-Hewitt's windows. It is a solar lighting system making its first American appearance. Invented and produced in Japan, the Himawari (sunflower) tracks the sun with 36 moving lenses that gather energy into light-conducting (fiber-optic) glass strands. The light is transported indoors to six lamps that illuminate, poetically enough, some solar souvenirs, like a German pocket sundial of 1748. The room reflects the mood of the sky outside; clouds change the intensity of the lighting.</p>
        <p>In midgarden is a self-powered solar glass pavilion invented by Gregory Kiss and Mr. Goldsmith. The pavilion is made of photovoltaic-laminated glass panels that do triple work: structure, enclosure and electrical generator. Inside, visitors are cooled by a fan and lighted by fluorescent lights in the glowing glass floor. ''We want to make energy production palpable,'' Mr. Kiss said. ''We're trying to do sensual design.''</p>
        <p>Technology that warms the soul as it cools the body? Maybe there is such a thing as progress after all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
