<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="01FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E7DB1138F932A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="2496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A2-6</p>
        <p>New Assaults in Kosovo Prompt Flood of Refugees  Thousands of ethnic Albanian refugees in Kosovo fled fresh attacks a day after the Serbian Government declared its military offensive over. United Nations officials estimated that the latest round of fighting had displaced up to 50,000 people. A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL  A2-6</p>
        <p>New Assaults in Kosovo Prompt Flood of Refugees  Thousands of ethnic Albanian refugees in Kosovo fled fresh attacks a day after the Serbian Government declared its military offensive over. United Nations officials estimated that the latest round of fighting had displaced up to 50,000 people. A1</p>
        <p>I.M.F. Urges Aid to Ukraine  An International Monetary Fund team said it would recommend a $2.2 billion loan to Ukraine, where the United States has showered assistance but where the economy remains crippled by corruption and a lack of reform. A5</p>
        <p>Bank Admits Nazi Gold Dealings  Germany's biggest bank, Deutsche Bank, acknowledged that it dealt in Nazi gold during World War II and expressed regret for the ''injustices that occurred.'' But it declined to say if wartime officials knew that some of the gold might have come from concentration camp victims. A2</p>
        <p>Fast Start by Japan's Premier  Keizo Obuchi, on his first day as Prime Minister, named a new financial adviser, Toyoo Gyohten, as he sought to reassure the world that he would move swiftly to address Japan's economic problems. A3</p>
        <p>Former Hostage Meets Captor  A former hostage from the 1979 takeover of the American Embassy in Teheran met in Paris with one of his former captors. But about all the two men agreed on was that it would take many more talks like theirs to overcome the hostility of the last 20 years. A3</p>
        <p>Military Spending Approved  The Senate has approved a $252 billion military spending bill that includes an amendment barring the Pentagon from training missions with foreign troops who have committed human-rights abuses. A6</p>
        <p>Intimidation in Cambodia  A growing number of opponents of Cambodia's ruling party are fleeing villages for the capital, Phnom Penh, saying they have been threatened with reprisals for voting against the party of the incumbent leader, Hun Sen, in parliamentary elections. A3</p>
        <p>Burmese Police on Alert  Hundreds of police officers carrying assault rifles and heavy machine guns were deployed throughout the capital of Myanmar, formerly Burma, as tensions continued to mount between the military Government and its democratic opposition. A3</p>
        <p>India-Pakistan Talks Collapse  An effort to open regular talks between India and Pakistan on divisive issues like nuclear weapons and Kashmir collapsed in acrimony, with the two countries accusing each other of setting conditions that made a sustained dialogue impossible. A4</p>
        <p>Beijing Ex-Mayor Sentenced  Chen Xitong, the former Mayor and Communist Party boss of Beijing, was sentenced to 16 years for corruption and dereliction of duty. The sentence appears intended to show that China's leaders are serious about cracking down on corruption. A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A7-11, 14</p>
        <p>Clinton Promises Full and True Testimony  President Clinton declared that he would testify ''completely and truthfully'' in the Monica S. Lewinsky investigation on Aug. 17, but that until then he would have no public comment on the matter. F.B.I. technicians began examining a dress that Ms. Lewinsky gave prosecutors for signs of a stain that lawyers said could provide evidence of a sexual encounter with the President. A1</p>
        <p>The President and Mrs. Clinton flew to East Hampton, on Long Island, for a weekend of relaxation and fund-raising. A8</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Paula Corbin Jones asked a Federal appeals court to reinstate her sexual misconduct suit against President Clinton, arguing among other things that a lower court should not have excluded evidence of any relationship that he and Ms. Lewinsky might have had. A8</p>
        <p>Campaign Bill Holds Its Ground  A steady majority of the House voted repeatedly to shield a bipartisan campaign finance bill from a final onslaught of amendments, making it all but certain that the measure would win final House passage. A1</p>
        <p>I.B.M. Admits Illegal Shipment  An I.B.M. subsidiary pleaded guilty to illegally exporting 17 advanced computers to a Russian nuclear weapons laboratory, and the subsidiary, I.B.M. East Europe/Asia Ltd., agreed to pay an $8.5 million fine. It was believed to be the first criminal conviction against I.B.M. A1</p>
        <p>Medical Code Plan Delayed  The Clinton Administration has backed away from a plan to assign every American a computerized code to track medical records, saying the ''unique health identifier'' would be delayed until Congress adopted legislation to protect patients' privacy. A10</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration announced a privacy initiative intended to protect children and medical patients, among others. But the Administration can enforce few of the proposals without the consent of Congress or private industry. A10</p>
        <p>New Tactic on Global Warming  Paying other countries to cut their pollution could be the cheapest way to help control the heat-trapping gases that cause global warming, the Clinton Administration said. A8</p>
        <p>Capitol Police Officer Buried  Officer Jacob Joseph Chestnut of the Capitol Police, who was killed by a gunman last week, was buried in Arlington National Cemetery after a funeral attended by members of Congress and hundreds of police officers. A11</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Switching of Babies  The authorities in Virginia are investigating whether two girls born in 1995 at a Charlottesville hospital were deliberately switched and sent home with the wrong parents. A7</p>
        <p>Puerto Rican Plebiscite  A Senate committee chairman made public a draft of a bill defining the three options -- commonwealth, statehood or independence -- for a plebiscite that the Governor of Puerto Rico hopes to hold on Dec. 13. A14</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A7-11, 14</p>
        <p>Clinton Promises Full and True Testimony  President Clinton declared that he would testify ''completely and truthfully'' in the Monica S. Lewinsky investigation on Aug. 17, but that until then he would have no public comment on the matter. F.B.I. technicians began examining a dress that Ms. Lewinsky gave prosecutors for signs of a stain that lawyers said could provide evidence of a sexual encounter with the President. A1</p>
        <p>The President and Mrs. Clinton flew to East Hampton, on Long Island, for a weekend of relaxation and fund-raising. A8</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Paula Corbin Jones asked a Federal appeals court to reinstate her sexual misconduct suit against President Clinton, arguing among other things that a lower court should not have excluded evidence of any relationship that he and Ms. Lewinsky might have had. A8</p>
        <p>Campaign Bill Holds Its Ground  A steady majority of the House voted repeatedly to shield a bipartisan campaign finance bill from a final onslaught of amendments, making it all but certain that the measure would win final House passage. A1</p>
        <p>I.B.M. Admits Illegal Shipment  An I.B.M. subsidiary pleaded guilty to illegally exporting 17 advanced computers to a Russian nuclear weapons laboratory, and the subsidiary, I.B.M. East Europe/Asia Ltd., agreed to pay an $8.5 million fine. It was believed to be the first criminal conviction against I.B.M. A1</p>
        <p>Medical Code Plan Delayed  The Clinton Administration has backed away from a plan to assign every American a computerized code to track medical records, saying the ''unique health identifier'' would be delayed until Congress adopted legislation to protect patients' privacy. A10</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration announced a privacy initiative intended to protect children and medical patients, among others. But the Administration can enforce few of the proposals without the consent of Congress or private industry. A10</p>
        <p>New Tactic on Global Warming  Paying other countries to cut their pollution could be the cheapest way to help control the heat-trapping gases that cause global warming, the Clinton Administration said. A8</p>
        <p>Capitol Police Officer Buried  Officer Jacob Joseph Chestnut of the Capitol Police, who was killed by a gunman last week, was buried in Arlington National Cemetery after a funeral attended by members of Congress and hundreds of police officers. A11</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Switching of Babies  The authorities in Virginia are investigating whether two girls born in 1995 at a Charlottesville hospital were deliberately switched and sent home with the wrong parents. A7</p>
        <p>Puerto Rican Plebiscite  A Senate committee chairman made public a draft of a bill defining the three options -- commonwealth, statehood or independence -- for a plebiscite that the Governor of Puerto Rico hopes to hold on Dec. 13. A14</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
