<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report on the Sound: Good and Bad</title>
    <meta content="23SOUN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1041010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island Sound</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brenner, Elsa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oxygen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6DE123DF930A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report on the Sound: Good and Bad</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brenner, Elsa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oxygen levels in most sections of Long Island Sound drop as result of global warming; researchers find hypoxic conditions, detrimental to marine life, at several sites along Long Island and Connecticut; environmental efforts are helping to alleviate some other adverse conditions; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT used to be known as a jubilee, the summertime event when crabs ''walked'' out of the sea. For shellfish lovers, the phenomenon continues to be an occasion for a feast. For scientists, it is a cause for worry.</p>
        <p>So far this year, no mass exodus of oxygen-starved crabs from Long Island Sound has taken place, but signs of trouble abound. There are indications in many locations that water quality in the Sound has been steadily deteriorating, and, in part, global warming is to blame.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT used to be known as a jubilee, the summertime event when crabs ''walked'' out of the sea. For shellfish lovers, the phenomenon continues to be an occasion for a feast. For scientists, it is a cause for worry.</p>
        <p>So far this year, no mass exodus of oxygen-starved crabs from Long Island Sound has taken place, but signs of trouble abound. There are indications in many locations that water quality in the Sound has been steadily deteriorating, and, in part, global warming is to blame.</p>
        <p>''Weather conditions have been just right for a crash,'' said Steve Yergeau, research director for Save the Sound, an environmental group in Stamford and Glen Cove. ''The warm, wet winter primed the pump, and the hot, humid summer allowed the water to stratify.''</p>
        <p>Oxygen levels in most sections of the Sound are low, with some locations below three parts per million -- a condition known as hypoxia, which puts stress on marine life and can cause the shellfish to flee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yergeau and about 250 volunteers this summer sampled water quality along the shoreline in Westchester and by late July had come up with sobering findings: hypoxic conditions existed at Milton Harbor in Rye, Mamaroneck Harbor and Echo Bay in New Rochelle.</p>
        <p>''This could be fatal,'' Mr. Yergeau said, explaining that when striped bass, blue fish and bait fish are deprived of oxygen, they often charge en masse to harbors and become trapped.</p>
        <p>There are, however, some optimistic signs in the Sound -- indications that despite the unpredictability of weather trends, other factors affecting the Sound are being controlled.</p>
        <p>Rainy weather last week stirred the waters and helped oxygenate the Sound. But environmental efforts -- like sewer repairs, a cap on the amount of nitrogen flowing into the Sound from sewage treatment plants, restoration of streams and adoption of local ordinances -- may also be helping.</p>
        <p>''We're hoping our efforts are finally paying off,'' said Paul Stacey, chief environmental analyst with the Connecticut Department of Environmental Protection. ''Given the weather conditions during much of this summer, water quality has not fallen off as much as it might have.'' Mr. Stacey said he observed less decaying material in the Sound this year, a sign that the reduction in the amount of nitrogen going into the water may be helping. Nitrogen from fertilizer, which flows off lawns, and nitrogen in the effluent from treatment plants encourages the growth of algae, which, when it decays, consumes the oxygen that fish need.</p>
        <p>The Sound -- an estuary where salt water from the ocean mixes with freshwater from inland streams and rivers -- is bounded by Connecticut and Westchester to the north and Long Island to the south. In New York City, the Interstate Sanitation Commission also reported critical conditions in some parts of the East River and along sections of the north shore of Long Island. Howard Golub, executive director and chief engineer for the tri-state environmental agency, described the situation as very worrisome.</p>
        <p>There have been scattered reports of fish kills, Mr. Golub said, although those have not been officially substantiated. In Connecticut, the Department of Environmental Protection reported that the fish kills occurred in Hempstead Harbor on Long Island, and it reported that severe hypoxic conditions were recorded in Norwalk.</p>
        <p>But at Save the Sound, John Atkin, the president, observed that the policy of no net increase of nitrogen going into the Sound seems to be helping. ''Knock on wood,'' he said, ''although we certainly still have alot of work ahead of us.''</p>
        <p>Part of that work will take place in Westchester as part of an agreement signed last Monday between the county and the State Department of Environmental Conservation. Under continuing pressure from the state, Westchester agreed to correct longstanding inflow and infiltration problems in the county's sewer system to prevent unpermitted discharges from county sewage treatment plants to the Hudson River and Long Island Sound. John P. Cahill, Commissioner of the Department of Environmental Protection, called on the county to upgrade its sewer systems immediately.</p>
        <p>Under a consent order, the county will repair deteriorating sewage-collection systems in 30 municipalities served by treatment plants in Yonkers, New Rochelle, Rye and Mamaroneck. The purpose is to prevent ground water, which is rich in nutrients like nitrogen, from entering sewer systems -- a problem known as infiltration. The estimated cost of the improvements is $50 million.</p>
        <p>In addition, Westchester will also pay a $100,000 penalty to the state and pay for $500,000 in environmental projects on the river and the Sound. On the Sound, the projects include retrofitting storm water management basins in Rye and New Rochelle, stabilizing stream banks at the junction of the Mamaroneck and Sheldrake Rivers and restoring Beaver Swamp Wetland in Rye and Harrison and Pryer Manor Marsh Tidal Wetland in New Rochelle.</p>
        <p>The consent order also requires municipalities to disconnect all illegal sewer connections from the county's lines, which contributes to the problem known as inflow. Illegal hookups from private homes and businesses must be disconnected by 2002, the state said.</p>
        <p>The county initially agreed to attend to the problems in 1992, and again in 1996, but failed to comply with terms of the agreement and did not compel its municipalities to do so.</p>
        <p>In a separate effort to improve water quality in the Sound, five Westchester communities recently pledged to work together and with the county to reduce levels of nutrients entering the water.</p>
        <p>A committee made up of representatives from Harrison, Mamaroneck Village, Port Chester, Rye Brook and Rye City released a management plan earlier this summer to guide the communities in cleaning up the estuary and the many streams, ponds and wetlands within their borders.</p>
        <p>The document was released by what is known as a watershed advisory committee, a group of municipal representatives that studied an 11,755-acre area, including the watersheds of Blind and Beaver Swamp Brooks and Port Chester and Milton Harbors, all of which drain into the Sound.</p>
        <p>A citizens' group called the Committee on Nonpoint Source Pollution in Long Island Sound, established in 1992 by County Executive Andrew P. O'Rourke, set up six watershed advisory committees the next year to study intermunicipal planning efforts. One of the advisory committees, which studied more than 6,600 acres in New Rochelle, the town and village of Mamaroneck, Larchmont, Pelham and Pelham Manor, was the first to complete its plan -- in May 1997.</p>
        <p>A major focus of the remedial plans is on nonpoint- source pollution, a prime source of contaminants. The Rye City Council and the Boards of Trustees of Harrison, Mamaroneck Village, Port Chester and Rye Brook all adopted resolutions endorsing the plan's principles. In addition to providing official support for the plan, the resolutions will enable the communities and the county's Planning Department to seek grants and other funds to put the plan into effect.</p>
        <p>Nonpoint-source pollution is carried by storm water runoff into the Sound and can include anything that gets into the ground and is washed off by rain and melting snow and ice into streams, ponds and storm sewers. Those pollutants include petroleum, pesticides, antifreeze, road maintenance chemicals, fertilizer and animal waste.</p>
        <p>Gina D'Agrosa, the county's director of environmental planning, said that the findings of local watershed advisory committees would serve as models for future proposals in obtaining Federal grants and money from the state's Clean Water-Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>This year, the county received $3.8 million from the bond act for a demonstration project at the Mamaroneck Sewer District to remove nitrogen and other pollutants going into the Sound. The 1998 allocation also included $34,500 from the bond act to restore native vegetation in a marsh area in Mamaroneck, $50,000 for aquatic plantings to reduce runoff and sediment in one area of New Rochellle and $141,000 to reduce the amount of sediment washing into New Rochelle Harbor.</p>
        <p>Rob Doscher, a County Planning Department researcher, said the county had also received a $600,000 Federal grant to restore tidal marshes and other wetlands and freshwater streams in the watershed. Among them are the shoals and islands in and around the Echo Bay portion of New Rochelle Harbor. Although severely degraded by the late 1960's, the Bay has experienced a ''modest but encouraging'' colonization by shellfish and smooth cordgrass over the last five years, Mr. Doscher said.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Federal and state officials adopted a 15-year, $650 million plan to upgrade sewage treatment plants along the Connecticut and New York shorelines. Those initiatives are part of the Comprehensive Conservation and Management Plan for the Sound, first approved by state and Federal agencies in 1994.</p>
        <p>Lisa Holst, a spokeswoman for the division of marine resources for the state's Department of Environmental Conservation, said that in Connecticut alone, there has been a 70 percent loss of forests since the 1700's. Throughout the Sound, there has been a 30 percent loss of tidal wetlands. Loss of habitat, the department has shown, means a reduction in an area's natural ability to assimilate pollutants and flush them out.</p>
        <p>Just how much all of the early efforts are working to improve the water's quality is difficult to know yet, most scientists and researchers agree. Looking at Milton Harbor in Rye, where Mr. Yergeau at Save the Sound has been sampling water every year at six different stations throughout the summer, no pattern of improvement has emerged. ''We will need another decade to chart the long-term progress of our efforts,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Atkins, the president of Save the Sound, said, ''We may have come a long way, but it is clear that we're still not out of the woods.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
