<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Groups Ask Permission To Revive Hemp Farms</title>
    <meta content="22HEMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1004135"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hemp</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Office of National Drug Control Policy</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E2DD1538F931A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="558" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Groups Ask Permission To Revive Hemp Farms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coalition of agricultural, commercial and environmental groups urges lifting of Federal prohibition on cultivation of all Cannabis strains so that those that lack intoxicating properties of marijuana can again be grown; argue that hemp is an earth-friendly crop with extensive uses in fiber production that draws high praise fromn some manufacturers; Office of National Drug Control Policy rejects idea as a subterfuge for legalization (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A coalition of agricultural, commercial and environmental groups is pushing the Clinton Administration to overturn the prohibition on cultivation of all Cannabis strains so those that lack the intoxicating properties of marijuana can again be grown.</p>
        <p>Hemp has developed a reputation for being an earth-friendly crop with extensive uses in fiber products that draws high praise from some manufacturers. But officials at the White House drug office quickly dismissed that notion, branding it a subterfuge for legalization and they noted that the idea of allowing hemp farms had already been studied and rejected.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A coalition of agricultural, commercial and environmental groups is pushing the Clinton Administration to overturn the prohibition on cultivation of all Cannabis strains so those that lack the intoxicating properties of marijuana can again be grown.</p>
        <p>Hemp has developed a reputation for being an earth-friendly crop with extensive uses in fiber products that draws high praise from some manufacturers. But officials at the White House drug office quickly dismissed that notion, branding it a subterfuge for legalization and they noted that the idea of allowing hemp farms had already been studied and rejected.</p>
        <p>''Many of the people who are interested in hemp are interested solely as a means of legitimizing the production of marijuana for use,'' said David Des Roches, an official at the Office of National Drug Control Policy.</p>
        <p>Under the coalition's proposal, licensed farmers would be permitted to grow the crop and would have to use seeds genetically selected and Federally certified not to produce significant amounts of the mind-altering compound that turned the species from a commonplace cash crop years ago into a banned one.</p>
        <p>They said they would petition the Drug Enforcement Administration and the Department of Agriculture on Monday to write new regulations recognizing the difference between strains of the plant. But Federal officials said that was unlikely to happen unless Congress first changed the drug laws.</p>
        <p>The groups in the coalition are taking pains to distance themselves from those who would legalize marijuana for medical or recreational use, saying their goal is to revive industrial-grade hemp as a major domestic crop. To that end they have chosen a carpet manufacturing official, a Republican legislator from Hawaii, and a senior biologist from Indiana University to speak for their cause.</p>
        <p>The coalition includes representatives of the North American Industrial Hemp Council, which represents potential producers and consumers, and the Resource Conservation Alliance, an environmental group that favors alternatives to forest products.</p>
        <p>''The fiber is better than any other natural product for our commercial markets, even to include wool,'' said Ray Berard, senior vice president of technology at Interface Inc., a $1.2 billion carpet manufacturer. ''I would like to be able to buy the material here in this country.''</p>
        <p>The hemp advocates said the system they are proposing would accommodate law-enforcement concerns while allowing farmers to grow a crop that is harvested in dozens of countries, recently including Canada, Germany and Britain.</p>
        <p>Although marijuana and hemp are synonyms for the same plant species, the industrially useful strains have almost none of the psychoactive ingredient THC, or delta-9 tetrahydrocannabinol.</p>
        <p>The hemp plant, once widely cultivated in the United States, can be used for an array of commercial materials, like textiles, balms, paper, lumber, paints and oils.</p>
        <p>Typically grown without harmful chemicals, the plant is said to be environmentally benign, and its products, like industrial carpeting, are easily recycled and used in composts. Environmental advocates often see it as an alternative to conventional materials like wood pulp or cotton, or perhaps as a source of renewable energy.</p>
        <p>In recent years, a lively market for products made from hemp has emerged, from and natural-tone knitwear to ''Extra Strength Hemp Zap Vegan Analgesic Balm.''</p>
        <p>But law-enforcement officials said that hemp's true cachet comes not from its earth-friendly image but from the perception that hemp products are hip, especially when they carry the readily recognized logo of the Cannabis leaf.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
