<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; Energy Addicted in America</title>
    <meta content="01MYER$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1058653"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alaska</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4D9143FF932A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="1004" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; Energy Addicted in America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN R. MYERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myerson, Allen R</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Americans have gone back to using energy as if it were limitless, consuming far more per person than Asians or Europeans; low energy prices are regarded as a right, and politicians who try to tax or otherwise raise cost of fuel near levels in Europe are soundly rebuked; within country, energy use varies greatly; average Alaskan uses more than five times as much energy as New Yorker, who uses the least; presence of heavy industry acounts for greatest differences; photo; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was during the oil embargo era of the 1970's that Patricia Nelson Limerick, who is now a leading historian of the American West, announced to her students at Yale that Americans' outlook and behavior had gone through a momentous change. No more vistas of limitless resources. No more endlessly rising consumption. The Era of Scarcity had begun.</p>
        <p>To save fuel and emphasize her belief, Ms. Limerick got around by bicycle, train and bus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was during the oil embargo era of the 1970's that Patricia Nelson Limerick, who is now a leading historian of the American West, announced to her students at Yale that Americans' outlook and behavior had gone through a momentous change. No more vistas of limitless resources. No more endlessly rising consumption. The Era of Scarcity had begun.</p>
        <p>To save fuel and emphasize her belief, Ms. Limerick got around by bicycle, train and bus.</p>
        <p>But 25 years later, Americans are consuming about as much energy as ever. By next year, the Energy Department predicts consumption per person will come to within 2 percent of the 1973 peak. Americans are living in bigger homes crammed with more appliances and driving larger, more powerful cars and more light trucks.</p>
        <p>Ms. Limerick is still riding buses. But she admits she got the broader pattern wrong. ''I was quite a sucker,'' she says.</p>
        <p>The Land Grab</p>
        <p>Far from illustrating a transformation in American character, the nation's heavy and rising use of its most basic fuels illustrates consistencies. The distinctions between America and most other advanced nations endure. As the 19th-century American historian Frederick Jackson Turner famously said, the frontier set America apart from its European forebears. For Americans, there was always more land, food and fortune out there for the grabbing.</p>
        <p>Though the Census Bureau declared the frontier closed more than a century ago, in many ways it remains open. Americans have gone back to using energy as if it were limitless -- consuming far more per person than Asians or Europeans. Only Canadians, with more heavy industry and more chilblains, consume more. Low energy prices are regarded as a part of the Bill of Rights. Politicians who try to tax or otherwise raise the cost of fuel anywhere near the levels in Europe are summarily rebuked.</p>
        <p>The wide open frontier still lives in the naming and advertising of pickups and sports utility vehicles. Americans venture forth in their Blazers, Explorers and Durangos. In commercials these trucks rumble over endless stretches of Western highway.</p>
        <p>Revisionist historians like Ms. Limerick point out that Western settlement also included official repression of Indians and other minorities, the ravaging of the environment and a culture of violence. Revisionist Western states and cities that once welcomed mining and development are now trying to clean up pollution from those mines and control urban sprawl.</p>
        <p>America's pattern of settlement, more dispersed than in most other advanced nations, locks in the need for cheap, abundant energy.  But underneath the roar of factory machinery, home construction and expressway traffic is the clang of a moral clash.</p>
        <p>Half the nation's oil is imported. Scientists caution that emissions from rising energy use aggravate global warming. But ever since proto-environmentalists warned of timber depletion in the 1870's, Americans have learned to doubt the need for conservation.</p>
        <p>Within the country, energy use varies greatly. New Yorkers and Hawaiians are practically foreigners, merely sipping fuel while Alaskans and Texans guzzle it. The average Alaskan uses more than five times as much energy as the New Yorker, who uses the least; the Texan burns more than two and a half times as much.</p>
        <p>The presence of heavy industry accounts for the greatest differences. Louisiana and Texas, besides having plenty of oil wells, are home to the chemical and refining businesses. Alaska and Wyoming produce great quantities of oil, coal and natural gas, especially in proportion to their populations.</p>
        <p>In New York, smokestacks and drilling rigs are few but subway and taxi riders many. New Yorkers are also more apt than other Americans to live jammed into apartments whose energy demands are far lower than for houses. And with common walls, says Arthur Rypinski, a Department of Energy economist, ''You get to share your neighbor's heating and cooling.'' As for Hawaii, it counts more on tourism and pineapples than on petrochemical plants, and has far lower heating bills than Wyoming or Alaska.</p>
        <p>During the 1970's embargo era, Texans, who considered their state an honorary member of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries, were never shy about letting Northerners know who had the most fuel. Bumper stickers on their Lincoln Continentals and long-bed pickups said, ''Let the Yankees Freeze in the Dark.'' With oil prices so low, perhaps Texans should mount a gracious campaign assuring New Yorkers they are welcome to every drop Texas has.</p>
        <p>A Lowly Light Bulb</p>
        <p>In Washington, the conflict between the energy-hungry life style and energy-saving impulses extends to the White House. At his conference on global warming last October, President Clinton confessed his doubts about how much the nation could alter its ways. Or even how much he could change his own.</p>
        <p>''I'm plagued by the example of the light bulb I have in my living room of the White House that I read under at night,'' Mr. Clinton said, ''and I ask myself, 'Why isn't every light bulb in the White House like this?' '' The lighting in question was a readily available, compact fluorescent bulb whose longer life and energy efficiency pay for its initial high cost several times over. ''Why are we not all doing this?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>Faced with a battle many Americans agree is worth fighting but don't want to fight themselves, the Clinton Administration has proposed hiring hungry foreign mercenaries. Through trading in emissions rights, the White House plans to pay developing countries to achieve about three-fourths of America's reductions required under last year's Kyoto accord. Europe and Japan have howled that this plan violates that accord, at least in spirit. They must be cranky from having to drive such tiny cars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
