<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Power Deregulation: Shadow, Substance and Politics</title>
    <meta content="Y26POW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1004984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salpukas, Agis</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DC1F38F935A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Power Deregulation: Shadow, Substance and Politics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salpukas, Agis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of Clinton Administration's presentation of guidelines as to how it would like to see utility industry deregulated, including innovative way for consumers to easily compare deals offered by rival sellers of power; says it is unclear whether proposals will help expedite process of dismantling the industry; says under some of major guidelines, utilities would have to open themselves to competition by year 2003, a fund of $3 billion would be established to help low-income people with their electric bills, and old laws governing utility industry would be repealed (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration presented guidelines yesterday as to how it would like to see the utility industry deregulated, including an innovative way for consumers to easily compare deals offered by rival sellers of power. But it's unclear whether the proposals will help expedite the process of dismantling the economy's last major regulated monopoly.</p>
        <p>Under some of the major guidelines presented by Energy Secretary Federico F. Pena, utilities would have to open themselves to competition by the year 2003, a fund of $3 billion would be established to help low-income people with their electric bills, and old laws governing the utility industry would be repealed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration presented guidelines yesterday as to how it would like to see the utility industry deregulated, including an innovative way for consumers to easily compare deals offered by rival sellers of power. But it's unclear whether the proposals will help expedite the process of dismantling the economy's last major regulated monopoly.</p>
        <p>Under some of the major guidelines presented by Energy Secretary Federico F. Pena, utilities would have to open themselves to competition by the year 2003, a fund of $3 billion would be established to help low-income people with their electric bills, and old laws governing the utility industry would be repealed.</p>
        <p>Part of the reason Secretary Pena presented the guidelines at a news conference in Washington is that the drive to deregulate has stalled in Congress and in many states. Mr. Pena intends to get it going again.</p>
        <p>''There is limited time left,'' he said in an interview. ''We're going to press ahead as hard as we can to get something done this year.''</p>
        <p>But the Administration is still facing a clamor of divergent interest groups over how to proceed.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem is the enormous size of the utility industry, which sold more than $212 billion worth of electricity last year. Moreover, many utilities have never contended with competition and are nervous about how to make the transition.</p>
        <p>Consumers are already confused by a welter of offers in states like California, which soon plans to give residents a choice among electric utilities.</p>
        <p>There are battles between state regulators and legislators over who should lead the deregulation. The utility industry itself is split.</p>
        <p>Big utilities that have plenty of cheap power want to accelerate the process so they can sell outside their territory. Other utilities that sell expensive power want to slow the process, so they can make the transition without bankrupting themselves.</p>
        <p>The most divisive issue has become how to insure that residential and other small consumers get a fair share of the savings that are promised from competition. As it stands now, most of the savings are falling to the larger industrial and commercial customers, who are cutting deals with power companies in anticipation of deregulation.</p>
        <p>California had planned to give customers a choice as of Jan. 1, but was forced to delay that until March 31 because of computer glitches and concerns over transmission reliability. An announcement yesterday by the state's biggest utilities that more testing would be needed before the process could begin next Tuesday has not reassured the public either. Some already skittish consumers have said in surveys that they do not want to deal with more choices.</p>
        <p>Deregulation has also drawn criticism from environmentalists, who fear that competitive pressure to cut the cost of power means that utilities will rely more on coal-fired plants. Such plants produce most of the cheapest electricity, which could make it more difficult to reduce carbon dioxide emissions, a possible cause of global warming.</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration's proposal calls for more efficient burning of fuels to lower emissions and for a tripling of the amount of power to be generated from renewable sources like wind and solar energy by 2010. But environmental advocates called such a measure inadequate.</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, director of the air and energy program of the Natural Resources Defense Council, said it ''fails to deliver on the President's promise to make a significant down payment on reducing greenhouse gas emissions and other air pollutants.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pena, though, is optimistic that some kind of Federal legislation will result because states will have difficulty achieving common standards, such as a nationwide system that would enable consumers to compare what marketers are offering.</p>
        <p>As proposed by the Administration, that information would also disclose what fuel utilities use to generate electricity so that consumers can choose from sellers that offer power from renewable sources.</p>
        <p>''As consumers see more information and they get more clarity,'' he said, ''they will be able to compare apples to apples.''</p>
        <p>And as they get more comfortable and see savings, support for deregulation will grow, the Energy Secretary predicted. In an effort to impart some lightness to a heavy subject, Mr. Pena ended his news conference by playing John Lennon's ''Power to the People.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
