<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Views From the Greenhouse</title>
    <meta content="05BROADT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Philander, S George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Thomas Gale</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Is the Temperature Rising? (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Climate of Fear (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DA163FF936A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="1469" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Views From the Greenhouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William J. Broad</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William J Broad reviews following books: Is the Temperature Rising: The Uncertain Science of Global Warming by S George Philander and Climate of Fear: Why We Shouldn't Worry About Global Warming by Thomas Gale Moore (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Is the Temperature Rising?</p>
        <p>The Uncertain Science of Global Warming.</p>
        <p>By S. George Philander.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 262 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>Climate of Fear</p>
        <p>Why We Shouldn't Worry</p>
        <p>About Global Warming.</p>
        <p>By Thomas Gale Moore.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 175 pp. Washington:</p>
        <p>Cato Institute. $18.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Is the Temperature Rising?</p>
        <p>The Uncertain Science of Global Warming.</p>
        <p>By S. George Philander.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 262 pp. Princeton, N.J.:</p>
        <p>Princeton University Press. $29.95.</p>
        <p>Climate of Fear</p>
        <p>Why We Shouldn't Worry</p>
        <p>About Global Warming.</p>
        <p>By Thomas Gale Moore.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 175 pp. Washington:</p>
        <p>Cato Institute. $18.95.</p>
        <p>A secret of science is that its luminaries have always done the easiest things first, contrary to many claims and myths. Newton ignored the messiness of the real world. His gravitational law showed that two planetary bodies could grip each other invisibly. But his mathematical rigor failed to account for the mutual attractions of three bodies, like the earth, moon and sun. That took the efforts of many successors.</p>
        <p>Exploring problems of even greater complexity, Lavoisier, and then Mendeleev, helped reveal scores of chemical elements and their odd, recurring similarities. Darwin and Mendel shed light on the tangle of life. And in our own time, scientists are addressing such riddles as the substructure of the atom, the fate of the universe and the workings of the human brain.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to climate change, one of the knottiest scientific problems of all. What we lightly call the climate system is actually trillions of variables in flux over billions of years. The factors include wind, rain, ice, clouds, snow, storms, lightning, comets, asteroids, sunlight, land size, sea currents, magnetic fields, cosmic rays, volcanic dust and life itself. In ages past, the atmosphere had little oxygen. But plants arose and changed that. The only constant seems to be variability, as suggested by the planet's erratic cycles of cold and warmth.</p>
        <p>Can this turmoil be fathomed and its evolutionary path forecast? More important for world leaders, can we distinguish the natural changes in meteorological conditions from those induced by humans?</p>
        <p>Scientists face the riot of variables only with the help of vast simplifications and the world's most powerful computers. To complicate matters, the field itself is in transition as the science improves and experts grow in number. Climate change was once viewed as slow. But recent studies have disclosed past temperature swings so sudden that in theory New England could have Miami-like weather in as little as 25 years. On the other hand, methane, seen as a major spur to global warming, now appears to be accumulating in the atmosphere more slowly than predicted, seeming to reduce the risk of crisis. Moreover, conflicting data are often communicated to the public by environmental zealots at either end of the political spectrum, obscuring things still further.</p>
        <p>Into this wilderness comes S. George Philander, a geoscientist at Princeton who writes with skill and cool reserve. ''Is the Temperature Rising? The Uncertain Science of Global Warming'' is a careful, step-by-step look at confusing data and clarifying science. He is literate, quoting Shelley, Coleridge and Eliot. And he is reasonably sure we are digging our own grave, though he says so with such understatement that it is easy to overlook the doom and gloom.</p>
        <p>Rather adroitly, Philander explains why scientists worry about the global rash of fires, generating plants and factories that release carbon dioxide at a furious pace. When sunlight bathes the earth and reflects back into the sky as heat, he says, the radiations have ''so little energy that they are unable to interact with the diatomic molecules that account for most of the atmosphere.'' Such bypassed molecules are mainly pairs of oxygen atoms and pairs of nitrogen atoms. The trouble arises when the weak radiations are absorbed by triatomic and other complex gases, including carbon dioxide, ozone, methane and water vapor. These trap heat in the atmosphere, much like glass in a greenhouse. The question is whether the heat is rising and how much.</p>
        <p>To address that puzzle, Philander examines issues such as those raised by clouds. If greenhouse heat evaporates some of the sea and increases water vapor in the atmosphere, the planet may grow hotter still, since the mist is a major greenhouse gas. But, he adds, if the added vapor condenses widely, the earth may cool, since white, fluffy, abundant clouds reflect more sunlight back into space. An added twist is that individual clouds heat or cool the earth depending on their exact form. Clouds, Philander says, are the main wild card in the warming game. Driving the point home, he asks readers to imagine computer simulations ''as whimsical as clouds!''</p>
        <p>The book's science is clear but formidable. We meet latent heat, quantum theory, the photoelectric effect, the hydrological cycle and plate tectonics, some explained better than others. Equations dot the text and pervade 13 appendixes. Many illustrations aid comprehension. But they, too, tend to be esoteric, with temperatures, for instance, always given in the Celsius scale.</p>
        <p>Like a windy but stimulating uncle, Philander also takes us on detours, some tedious. Who cares why water is a poor thermometer fluid? But what fun to learn that weather experts around the globe release 700 balloons every noon and midnight Greenwich mean time and share the resulting data, friend and foe alike. People, he observes, are ''more truly united in this activity than any other.''</p>
        <p>For all its detail, the book makes no mention of such current research topics as the extent to which the air is warmed by the sun's variable brightness, newly discovered in the 11-year sunspot cycle and suspected to occur over longer periods. Nor does it adequately explore whether terrestrial reactions to atmospheric upsets can curb greenhouse warming. ''The carbon cycle amounts to a thermostat that keeps temperatures in a moderate range,'' it says provocatively, missing the obvious follow-up.</p>
        <p>At the book's close, Philander draws together some of his strands and concludes that humankind is playing with fire. The problem, he concedes, is ''enormously complex.'' But the balance of evidence, he warns, suggests that serious problems lie ahead unless we take drastic steps to curtail the buildup of greenhouse gases: ''The growth is exponential, a dangerous situation that calls for action long before there is clear evidence of impending trouble.''</p>
        <p>Thomas Gale Moore, an economist at the Hoover Institution in California, rejects such alarm. ''Climate of Fear: Why We Shouldn't Worry About Global Warming'' argues that any rise in temperatures is likely to help Americans, if not poor people in the tropics. Moore's optimism is similar to that of Svante August Arrhenius, the Swedish chemist who late in the 19th century first proposed that rises in industrial gases might produce ''ages with more equable and better climates.'' Of the greenhouse idea itself, however, Moore is skeptical: ''The theory is weak and the models on which the conclusions are based cannot even replicate the current climate.'' For the sake of argument, he nonetheless assumes that moderate warming may occur, and he explores possible costs and benefits.</p>
        <p>First, he reviews the growing literature on past climes and concludes that warm ones favored humans. For instance, balmy weather 800 to 1,200 years ago allowed people in Britain, Prussia and Norway to grow grapes and make wine. ''Mankind prospered during warm periods and suffered during cold ones,'' he writes. He then looks at global warming in the next century. He faults doomsayers as exaggerating woes and ignoring benefits. In sports, he says, pessimists see declines in skiing but overlook rises in golf, camping, tennis, canoeing, hiking and bicycling.</p>
        <p>His own tally for the United States from global warming estimates annual costs of $6 billion from such things as smog, wetland loss, hurricane damage and new dikes needed to hold back rising seas. On the plus side, he finds $99 billion in benefits from saved lives, improved health, new recreational and life-style amenities, lower heating bills, new construction and added water supplies.</p>
        <p>He ends with an analysis of the costs of greenhouse curbs like those spelled out in the recent accords reached in Kyoto, Japan, and judges them staggering and silly. Moore, who was a member of President Reagan's Council of Economic Advisers, concludes that ''the best strategy is to maintain the status quo, continue research on climate and help poor countries improve their economies.''</p>
        <p>Economics, perhaps no less than climatology and other disciplines that probe complexity, has a hard time foreseeing change. Its subject matter, after all, is people, whose behavior is famously at odds with expert prediction. Moore may be as unrealistic as the prophets of doom, perhaps more so. The truth is that we all live in a great climate experiment, the outcome of which, good or bad, no one is likely to forecast with any certitude.</p>
        <p>William J. Broad is a science reporter for The New York Times and author of ''The Universe Below: Discovering the Secrets of the Deep Sea.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William J. Broad is a science reporter for The New York Times and author of ''The Universe Below: Discovering the Secrets of the Deep Sea.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
