<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14MSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1024662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D6173DF937A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL 3-18</p>
        <p>Despite Nuclear Tests, Heads Are Cool in Kashmir  India and Pakistan have fought two wars over Kashmir and still have thousands of troops arrayed there along a line of control that divides the Himalayan region. But on the Indian side, at least, few seem worried about another war, much less one that would go nuclear. 1</p>
        <p>Poles Debate Press Freedom  A court-ordered ban in Poland of a documentary that takes a caustic look at the American direct-sales company Amway has set off a debate about press freedom. Amway argued that it needed to protect its reputation. But many Polish journalists said the action was reminiscent of the old days of Communism. 4</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL 3-18</p>
        <p>Despite Nuclear Tests, Heads Are Cool in Kashmir  India and Pakistan have fought two wars over Kashmir and still have thousands of troops arrayed there along a line of control that divides the Himalayan region. But on the Indian side, at least, few seem worried about another war, much less one that would go nuclear. 1</p>
        <p>Poles Debate Press Freedom  A court-ordered ban in Poland of a documentary that takes a caustic look at the American direct-sales company Amway has set off a debate about press freedom. Amway argued that it needed to protect its reputation. But many Polish journalists said the action was reminiscent of the old days of Communism. 4</p>
        <p>Bad Air in Beijing  Beijing has joined 38 other Chinese cities in providing weekly air quality reports that for the first time are giving citizens hard information on the air they breathe. The data have confirmed what many Western scientists have long believed: that the air in China's cities is among the most polluted in the world. 18</p>
        <p>Global Warming Pact Still Hot  Six months ago countries approved an agreement requiring industrialized nations to reduce emissions of gases believed to be warming the Earth's climate. Now, haggling over how to carry out the first cuts is proving to be as difficult as hammering out the original accord. 16</p>
        <p>Serbs Vow to Defend Kosovo  A top aide to the Yugoslav President says that his country does not want a conflict with NATO but that it will defend Kosovo province if the alliance intervenes. NATO said it would hold military exercises in the region on Monday. 13</p>
        <p>NATIONAL 20-33</p>
        <p>A New Force Emerges In California Politics  Ron K. Unz, the Californian who beat bilingual education in the nation's most populous state, is no slick demagogue or smooth revolutionary. At 36, he looks and lives like a harried graduate student, dressed in faded and fraying clothing, fueled by fast food and canned chili, fatigued by late nights in the glow of a computer screen. But by successfully promoting a statewide initiative that, if it withstands legal challenges, will essentially wipe out bilingual education in California, Mr. Unz has emerged as a new force and a new kind of figure in California politics. 1</p>
        <p>Starr Acknowledges Leaks  Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel investigating President Clinton, acknowledged in a magazine interview that he and his aides have given information on the Monica S. Lewinsky matter to reporters. But he insisted that the leaks were neither illegal nor a violation of Justice Department ethics. 1  A Citizen Under Suspicion  Behind the stock images of middle-American life, Mohammed Salah, a naturalized American citizen born in Jerusalem, has operated secretly as a high-ranking member of the Islamic terrorist organization Hamas, Federal authorities say. 20</p>
        <p>G.O.P. Hails the Traditional  A parade of prospective Presidential candidates converged in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, for a gala that the state's Republican Party billed as a showcase of ''ideas and visions'' for the next millennium. Instead, the event more resembled a celebration of the traditional nuclear family of the 1950's, but none of the top potential candidates showed up. 24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK 35-41</p>
        <p>Chinese Cinema Fades Out  For decades, Chinese immigrants flocked to Chinatown's eight or so Chinese-language movie theaters. The theaters provided not only entertainment, but a sense of community and comfort. Soon, New York City's last Chinese-language theater, the Music Palace, will take its final bow, its faded three-story structure to be demolished and replaced by a gleaming office building. The theater's passing is a small milestone in the story of the Chinese in America, representing a shift toward the new mainstream. 1</p>
        <p>The Unending Lilco Saga  The current furor over the revelation that Lilco had dished out $67 million in special payments to 26 executives before it went out of business is but the latest chapter in the seemingly unending saga of the utility. From the ill-fated Shoreham nuclear power plant to its recent takeover by the state, it made history right up to -- and beyond -- its demise. ''It's the old Lilco curse -- it never seems to go away,'' said Richard M. Kessel, who now heads the Long Island Power Authority. 35</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES 42-43</p>
        <p>Jeanette Nolan  The actress who began her film career 50 years ago playing Lady Macbeth opposite Orson Welles was 86. 42</p>
        <p>H. F. McCarty Jr.  A Mississippi entrepreneur who transformed a feed and seed store into one of the nation's biggest poultry operations, he was 76. 43</p>
        <p>FRESH AIR FUND 36</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote 36</p>
        <p>Weather 41</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
