<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Deregulation Of Utilities In California</title>
    <meta content="Y02POW$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1006727"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salpukas, Agis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4DC163AF931A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Deregulation Of Utilities In California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salpukas, Agis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California becomes first state to allow customers to bypass their local utilities and buy power directly from other sources; complex system that allows electricity to be auctioned to get lowest price for customers and then to be delivered to them by agency no longer controlled by state's major utilities functions flawlessly, serving 38,000 customers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a five-year effort to allow customers to bypass their local utilities and buy power directly from other sources, California became the first state to do so yesterday.</p>
        <p>A complex system that allows electricity to be auctioned to get the lowest price for consumers and then to be delivered to them by an agency no longer controlled by the state's major utilities functioned flawlessly yesterday, serving 38,000 customers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a five-year effort to allow customers to bypass their local utilities and buy power directly from other sources, California became the first state to do so yesterday.</p>
        <p>A complex system that allows electricity to be auctioned to get the lowest price for consumers and then to be delivered to them by an agency no longer controlled by the state's major utilities functioned flawlessly yesterday, serving 38,000 customers.</p>
        <p>In achieving utility deregulation, California brought together many groups, often with competing interests, and reached an effective compromise. Now, California is expected to serve as the model for other states, despite delays caused by computer glitches, attempts by some groups to gain support for referendums that would reduce the amounts that utilities should be able to recover for past investments and the very small number of the 9.9 million customers who decided to switch away from their utilities.</p>
        <p>''We breathed a sigh of relief,'' said Scott Gebhardt, the president of PG&amp;E Energy Services, the marketing division of the PG&amp;E Corporation, which owns the largest utility in the state, the Pacific Gas and Electric Company. ''Despite the scare tactics of consumer groups and other naysayers, everything went well.''</p>
        <p>''Many are saying that California could have done things differently or cheaper, but the fact is that it's been done,'' he added.</p>
        <p>About 16 states, including New York, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts and Rhode Island are well on their way to opening their utilities to competition and have adopted some of the concepts pioneered in California.</p>
        <p>The complicated process began when the California Power Exchange received bids from 19 other utilities in and out of state and from other generators of power.</p>
        <p>In two hours, about 510,000 megawatts of electricity, or 80 percent of that used in the state, was traded at an average price of $19.73 a megawatt-hour. In comparison, before there was competition, a megawatt-hour would have cost an estimated $24. Rates in California are among the highest in the country.</p>
        <p>The aim of the exchange is to drive the cost of power as low as possible and thus help cut customers' rates.</p>
        <p>An agency called the Independent System Operator, which took the state's transmission grid over from the utilities, was responsible for making sure that the system functioned smoothly.</p>
        <p>One customer who switched, Michael Allen, a financial analyst who lives in Torrance, a suburb of Los Angeles, has begun to get his electricity through Enron Energy Services, the group that markets electricity for Enron, the Houston-based energy company, His local utility, the Southern California Edison Company, however, still delivers the power over its transmission system.</p>
        <p>Originally he and others who decided to switch would have gotten their power from their new suppliers as of Jan. 1, but glitches in the Power Exchange software led to a three-month delay.</p>
        <p>He said that he decided to switch to Enron to buy what has been dubbed as green power, that generated from such sources as wind, solar and hydroelectric.</p>
        <p>''This is a way for people to help foster the development of renewable energy sources,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The savings in the first four years are expected to be small. Mr. Allen said that like all residential and smaller customers in the state his rates were cut 10 percent on Jan. 1. For him that is a saving of about $3 on his average monthly bill of $30.</p>
        <p>After the 10 percent rate cut, the 229 marketers that are trying to get customers to switch have had a hard time offering additional savings. Thus, they have resorted to offering incentives such as short periods of free electricity, often merely confusing customers.</p>
        <p>The delay also caused people to worry about reliability and provided ammunition for groups opposed to the current approach.</p>
        <p>Lou Pai, the chairman and chief executive of Enron Energy Services, said that yesterday was ''just the opening of a very long and protracted process.'' He added, ''It's not going to change the industry structure overnight.''</p>
        <p>He said that building up a base of customers would take time. Eventually Enron hopes to offer a range of services and ways for customers to use electricity more efficiently.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
