<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From a French Past, a Look at the Future</title>
    <meta content="22GAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="GAME THEORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cd-Rom (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rhinestone Publishing</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herz, J C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Game Theory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EFDA173DF931A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From a French Past, a Look at the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By J. C. Herz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herz, J C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Game Theory column evaluates Zero Zero, interactive CD-ROM from Rhinestone Publishing; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PINKEE was born far away, in Paris, at a time when a fire burned in every grate and smoke curled black and feathery like a horse's tail from a thousand chimney pots.''</p>
        <p>So begins the tale of a little girl in the City of Lights on New Year's Eve in 1899, ''the hinge upon which the century turned.'' Zero Zero, an interactive story on CD-ROM by Theresa Duncan, describes Pinkee's journey through the streets of Paris in the waning hours of the 19th century as she hops from rooftop to rooftop, explores the catacombs and slides down cartoon chimneys to ask whimsically drawn Parisians what the future has in store.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PINKEE was born far away, in Paris, at a time when a fire burned in every grate and smoke curled black and feathery like a horse's tail from a thousand chimney pots.''</p>
        <p>So begins the tale of a little girl in the City of Lights on New Year's Eve in 1899, ''the hinge upon which the century turned.'' Zero Zero, an interactive story on CD-ROM by Theresa Duncan, describes Pinkee's journey through the streets of Paris in the waning hours of the 19th century as she hops from rooftop to rooftop, explores the catacombs and slides down cartoon chimneys to ask whimsically drawn Parisians what the future has in store.</p>
        <p>Their replies, like Pinkee's Paris, are suffused with Gallic insouciance. ''I love the future!'' exclaims Antoinette, the pastry chef's assistant. ''It's very modern. Very chic!'' In Madame Grenouille's greenhouse, the flowers exclaim, ''Salut!''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, in the window of Quel Fromage, the French Revolution is staged with wedges of Camembert and wheels of brie. In a fashionable atelier, a couturier explains: ''Since all the great styles have already been invented in this century, and by Parisians, the only things for 20th-century designers to do will be to mix them up. You'll see faux nouvelle and French neoclassicism and machine-made utilitarian furniture all in the same room. There will be lots of stripes, and lots of blown glass! It will be fabulous!''</p>
        <p>The librarian, Benjamin Walter, scribbles in his book of ''20th Century Dreams,'' an album with pictures of robots and space travel with theremin music in the background. ''In the 20th century,'' he says, ''aeroplanes will scoop up snow from mountaintops and drop it over cities simmering with the heat of summer. In the future, we will stroll along the rings of Saturn on Saturday night.'' But of course, since the future is French, the robots carry baguettes and bottles of wine. Poodles wear astronaut helmets. Sleek spacecraft sport bumper stickers from Paris, and a tricolor flag flies on the moon.</p>
        <p>From pastries shaped like French philosophers to a hilarious send-up of Baudelaire, Zero Zero is filled with winking cultural references children may not catch. But they can surely relate to its heroine, with her soot-smudged face and insatiable curiosity about the future, her yen for faraway places and her enthusiasm for new technology. She, too, is a child at the end of a century, at a time when new visual technologies signify the future.</p>
        <p>Like modern-day Silicon Valley, turn-of-the-century Paris was brimming with revolutionary visual devices. Zoetropes, panoramas and motion pictures represented cutting-edge technology, as well as the latest form of entertainment. A coin could conjure the films of Georges Melies in 1899. A hundred years later, a  mouse click conjures those same films in Quick Time video, accompanied by the digital whir of an antique sprocket-and-reel projector. On screen, the cursor brings every object to life. Plus ca change.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the only obvious difference between 19th-  and 20th-century attempts to divine the future is our mood about it, and the people we designate as soothsayers. Visions of the future were once the province of novelists and philosophers. Now they are put forth by corporate consultants, advertising agencies and tabloid astrologers (in order of ascending accuracy). And whereas 19th-century oracles were generally optimistic, ours predict a world filled with messy crises if not outright doom.</p>
        <p>According to nearly everyone in the professional futurology racket, the 21st century is going to clobber us. First, all our computers will shut down, precipitating a crash of planes, trains and stock markets. The ozone layer will shortly disappear, leaving us all fried to a crisp when we're not being ravaged by loose nukes or terrorist germs.</p>
        <p>And of course, the future will be very American. There will be a McDonald's on every block, worldwide! Everyone will be drinking Coca-Cola and downloading from the World Wide Web (in English) on their Palm Pilots! They will have different skin tones and dress codes, but everyone will be American inside. And all the world's consumers will join hands and sing in unison, just like on the Small World ride at Disneyland.</p>
        <p>At the end of the 21st century, this is going to seem just as outlandish as robots with berets. Because this picture, like all visions of the future, is hyperbole, based on our present hopes and present fears. The only thing we can predict with absolute certainty is that the clock will turn, and there will be fireworks.</p>
        <p>''Zap! Zip! Wheee! Sparks spiraled up into the night, where they joined their cousins, the stars,'' we hear toward the story's end. ''Pinkee put on her rabbit pajamas and stood in front of the round window in the room she shared with her sisters. The seven sisters had awakened from their sleep and joined Pinkee at the window, where the last fireworks reflected pink and green on their sleepy faces. 'What time is it?' they asked as the last of the fireworks faded. 'It's the future,' said Pinkee. 'We're there.' ''</p>
        <p>Rhinestone Publishing, CD-ROM for Mac and Windows 95 and 98, $34.95; suitable for all ages. Available on line at www.rhinestonepublishing. com, in Virgin Megastores or by calling (888) 476-2789.</p>
        <p>GAME THEORY E-mail address: Herz@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail address: Herz@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
