<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Biography' Takes a Glossy Page From 'People'</title>
    <meta content="05GERS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1007366"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerston, Jill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Biography (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E6DD1E3BF936A35757C0A96E958260" item-length="1660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Biography' Takes a Glossy Page From 'People'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL GERSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gerston, Jill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on A&amp;E's series Biography, which has expanded to six nights a week; more than 550 biographies have been featured on series since its debut in 1987; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SAM WALTON. The Gambinos. And Kathie Lee Gifford.</p>
        <p>If the three top-rated documentary portraits on A&amp;E's ''Biography'' are any indication, there's no accounting for viewers' taste when it comes to devouring stories about other people's lives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SAM WALTON. The Gambinos. And Kathie Lee Gifford.</p>
        <p>If the three top-rated documentary portraits on A&amp;E's ''Biography'' are any indication, there's no accounting for viewers' taste when it comes to devouring stories about other people's lives.</p>
        <p>Why should the sagas of an ambitious dime-store merchant who became a billionaire (as the founder of Wal-Mart), a notorious organized-crime family and a saccharine talk-show host draw bigger audiences than the biographies of Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Colin Powell or Houdini?</p>
        <p>''We can't explain it,'' said Brooke Bailey Johnson, executive vice president and general manager of the Arts &amp; Entertainment Network. ''We are always surprised by who does well and who doesn't.''</p>
        <p>Not that it seems to matter whose life it is, anyway. Whether it is Sid Caesar's story or Julius Caesar's, ''Biography'' has become the cable network's top-rated series, as well as its signature show. Over the last four years, ratings have climbed 30 percent. Last year, ''Biography'' garnered its highest ratings ever.</p>
        <p>More than 550 biographies have been featured on the series since its debut in 1987. Originally an hourlong weekly show at 8 P.M., ''Biography'' expanded to five nights a week in 1994. A year later, the series added a Saturday episode, ''Biography: This Week,'' pegged to a person in the news. Now there is also ''Biography for Kids'' on Saturday mornings, ''Biography International'' on Sunday mornings and an occasional two-hour special on Sunday nights.</p>
        <p>The series and its offshoots have little in common with the original ''Biography,'' a half-hour CBS series from the early 1960's. That series, whose host was Mike Wallace, may have profiled the occasional actor or athlete but it focused much more on world leaders. Those were different times.</p>
        <p>The A&amp;E show's success has spawned a slew of ''Bio''-clones, including Lifetime's ''Intimate Portraits,'' the Nashville Network's ''Life and Times'' and E!'s ''Celebrity Profile,'' which are even more celebrity oriented. Think Shania Twain, not Mark Twain. And their approaches, unlike ''Biography's'' more balanced style, range from hagiographic to tawdry tabloid.</p>
        <p>In a world where Time and Newsweek sometimes have the same cover subject as People, Leonardo DiCaprio has more than 300 Web sites, made-for-television and feature-film biographies have been proliferating and four of the books on the New York Times nonfiction best-seller list are either biographies or memoirs, it is no surprise that audiences have become hooked on ''Biography.''</p>
        <p>Most viewers' lives would seem humdrum compared with those of Al Capone or the Princess of Wales. And what better way to avoid thinking about the ozone layer or the budget deficit than to channel the life of Eva Peron?</p>
        <p>It may even be reassuring to discover that superachievers like Mozart and Eleanor Roosevelt had dysfunctional childhoods. And historical events like the battle of the Alamo and the Normandy invasion become more vivid when personalized through the lives of Davy Crockett and General Omar Bradley.</p>
        <p>Call it voyeurism, escapism or just intellectual curiosity, but a certain amount of interest in others' lives is natural. And the craving for biographies may simply be that ''real people are often more interesting than fictional ones,'' said Michael Cascio, A&amp;E's senior vice president for programming.</p>
        <p>''Once you scratch the surface of anyone who has made a contribution of one form or another, you always find fascinating stuff,'' he said. ''We've occasionally done biographies of fictional characters like Sherlock Holmes and Betty Boop, but they don't do well in the ratings.''</p>
        <p>Which doesn't surprise Neal Gabler, the author of ''Winchell,'' a biography of the powerful gossip columnist and broadcaster Walter Winchell, who is completing a new book, ''Life the Movie: How Entertainment Conquered Reality.''</p>
        <p>''Biography is entertainment written in the medium of life,'' he said. ''There is the texture of actuality to things. There is no plausibility factor. The people are real. The events are real. The primary reason we're absorbed is because a life is entertaining.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, most ''Biography'' stories zip along from cradle to grave (or the present day), combining narration with period footage, archival tapes, film clips and interviews with the subject's friends, colleagues or even ex-spouses. In Judy Garland's story, for instance, her old friend June Allyson attributed Garland's terrible judgment about men to an insecurity so deep that she was amazed anyone would want to marry her. Jack Perkins and Peter Graves, the series' hosts, usually provide the narration.</p>
        <p>''The connective tissue of the show is the writing,'' said Peter Jones, an independent documentary filmmaker who produced the biographies of Judy Garland and Charlie Chaplin, among others, for the series. ''You don't want it to get lost in 'cocktail party' chitchat-type interviews where people just gas on about how wonderful so-and-so was. It has to help flesh out the subject.''</p>
        <p>Occasionally, five biographies are packaged together as a theme week. ''Attention, Shoppers!'' spotlighted merchants like J. C. Penney and the Woolworth family while ''Men Behaving Madly'' served up Caligula and the Marquis de Sade.</p>
        <p>What makes a person rate an episode of ''Biography''?</p>
        <p>''You have to have a life that is worth at least an hour,'' said Mr. Cascio. ''Donald Trump just barely makes the cut, but Marla Maples definitely does not. We thought about Tara Lipinski, but what is she, 15 years old? We did a little research on Tiger Woods, but the story would have been more about his upbringing and the pressures on him, making it something different than a biography.''</p>
        <p>As any ''Biography'' fan can tell you, the hallmark of the series is that each life story unfolds in a strictly chronological way.</p>
        <p>''You can't begin a biography in the middle,'' said Mr. Jones. ''For example, you can't begin Montgomery Clift's biography with the car accident that left him disfigured and changed his life.''</p>
        <p>Despite its linear approach, ''Biography'' sprinkles its stories with little personal details that might intrigue viewers and offer some insight into the subject.</p>
        <p>''Greta Garbo loved nothing better than to watch 'Hollywood Squares,' '' for example, said Mr. Jones. ''She was actually a very dull human being, yet there was this glamorous myth about her.''</p>
        <p>''Sidney Poitier learned how to speak English by listening to baseball announcers and newscasters on radio stations in New York,'' he continued. ''It is those details that tell so much about his ambition, his drive, his discipline. A life isn't just about major achievements.'' (Mr. Poitier grew up on Cat Island in the Bahamas and spoke a highly dialectal English.)</p>
        <p>NOR are ''Biography'' episodes always about household names. The series' range encompasses lesser-known achievers like Oscar Levant, the troubled musician and television personality (who chatted casually about his drug addiction on the air with Jack Paar) and Samuel Bronfman, the liquor magnate.</p>
        <p>''We're doing a biography of Lee Strasberg,'' said Mr. Cascio, referring to the creator of the Method school of acting, who died in 1982. ''I don't know how well it will do, but we'll try it. It may give people insight into another aspect of show business they don't necessarily know about.''</p>
        <p>''Biography'' has been applauded for its broad variety of subjects, its straightforward, comprehensive approach and its refusal to wallow in sensationalism. Although it may reveal the skeletons in a subject's closet, it doesn't drag out the bones and rattle them.</p>
        <p>''We put things in context,'' said Mr. Cascio. ''If you are John Kennedy and you had affairs in the White House, that is important to know, but it is also important to know what he was like as a kid, what influence his father had on him and how the death of his older brother affected him.''</p>
        <p>This evenhanded, encyclopedic style has been criticized for being too broad and formulaic, lacking an edge or an incisive point of view. All facts and little penetrating analyses do not an illuminating biography make.</p>
        <p>''I was disappointed with what they had done with Walter Winchell's life,'' said Mr. Gabler. ''They telescoped events and gave a distorted vision of how his life unfolded. And the linear narrative didn't tell you much about the cultural resonances of his life.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Bailey Johnson of A&amp;E believes the ''less critical and more encyclopedic'' approach is appropriate for a five-day-a-week format.</p>
        <p>''We provide context, depth, facts and accuracy,'' she said. ''We don't dodge controversy, but we don't take a position on it. We tend to be more 'just the facts, ma'am,' and let the viewers decide.''</p>
        <p>The viewers must approve, judging by the series' rapidly multiplying franchises. A ''Biography'' Web site, begun two years ago, has become the network's most popular. Last year a monthly magazine (named, of course, Biography) was introduced. There is also a series of ''Biography'' audiocassettes and hardcover books, published by Random House. A line of books geared to children is in the works, as is a series of music albums based primarily on personalities profiled on ''Biography.''</p>
        <p>Long before the series grew into a cottage industry, Mr. Cascio recalled that when A&amp;E decided to put it on five nights a week, ''people said, 'What are you, crazy?' ''</p>
        <p>''But it's such a natural for popular culture,'' he added. ''And you never have to worry about running out of subjects.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
