<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Air Pollution Within State Borders</title>
    <meta content="05LETT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1029523"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Godar, Thomas (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Swadosh, Jeanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DC1E3FF936A35754C0A96E958260" item-length="503" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Air Pollution Within State Borders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeanne Swadosh and Dr Thomas Godar letter responds to May 31 article on Connecticut's poor air quality (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The air in Connecticut is making us sick. More than 400 Connecticut residents will die as a result of air pollution in 1998. Many more, especially asthmatics, the elderly and children are being admitted to hospital emergency rooms because of poor air quality.</p>
        <p>The article (''Where the Bad Air Comes From,'' May 31) attempted to answer the obvious but did not tell the whole story behind Connecticut's air pollution woes. The article led readers to believe ancient coal and oil burning power plants in the Midwest and the South are the source of Connecticut's high air pollution levels. It failed to mention the presence of five such plants located in Connecticut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The air in Connecticut is making us sick. More than 400 Connecticut residents will die as a result of air pollution in 1998. Many more, especially asthmatics, the elderly and children are being admitted to hospital emergency rooms because of poor air quality.</p>
        <p>The article (''Where the Bad Air Comes From,'' May 31) attempted to answer the obvious but did not tell the whole story behind Connecticut's air pollution woes. The article led readers to believe ancient coal and oil burning power plants in the Midwest and the South are the source of Connecticut's high air pollution levels. It failed to mention the presence of five such plants located in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Five coal- and oil-burning power plants, located in Bridgeport, New Haven, Middletown, Norwalk and Montville have been allowed to operate under weaker standards for more than two decades because of a grandfather clause in the 1977 Clean Air Act. This is the same loophole cited in the article that permits out-of-state plants to pollute at excessive levels.</p>
        <p>These ''Filthy Five'' are responsible for over 50 percent of Connecticut's industrial air pollution. They are the largest industrial source of pollutants contributing to the smog and soot currently irritating our respiratory systems.</p>
        <p>It is just as likely that the air pollution causing asthma attacks, premature deaths, acid rain and mercury contamination is homegrown in Connecticut as it is that air pollution is coming from the Midwest and the South. According to Environmental Protection Agency studies, less than 5 percent of Connecticut's air pollution comes from Midwestern sources.</p>
        <p>Although it is laudable that we have made considerable progress in battling our air pollution problem, Connecticut needs to accept its own culpability for its high air pollution levels instead of placing blame on other states.</p>
        <p>Connecticut clearly needs to take further action, namely by getting stronger standards for our five grandfathered power plants. Gov. John G. Rowland has authority to upgrade these power plants. The Connecticut Coalition for Clean Air has been formed to urge Governor Rowland to make a commitment to reduce air pollution emissions from the five coal and oil power plants.</p>
        <p>It is deplorable that we should even have to think twice about sending our children outside on a hot summer day or worry about our senior citizens' well-being because of air pollution.</p>
        <p>As the prevalence of respiratory conditions such as asthma continues to rise, state residents need to contact Governor Rowland and persuade him to lead the way in cleaning up Connecticut's air.</p>
        <p>JEANNE SWADOSH  DR. THOMAS GODAR</p>
        <p>Ms. Swadosh is with the Toxics Action Center in New Haven and Dr.  Godar is with the American Lung Association of Connecticut.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
