<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q.&amp;A.</title>
    <meta content="04QNA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1021932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E1D9123BF937A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q.&amp;A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Leslie Land</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 'Magic Number'</p>
        <p>Q.  I tried to grow sweet corn several years ago and failed miserably. I have heard that you need a certain minimum number of plants so that they can cross-pollinate, a necessity for the plants to yield corn. Is this true? What is that minimum? Is it too late to plant this year?</p>
        <p>A.  No, it's not too late. Corn does best when planted in warm soil and grown in hot weather. Then, ideally, just as the ripening starts, nights will begin to cool off. Heat is great for vegetative growth, but the plant will produce ears that have more carbohydrates (including sugars) when temperatures are moderate.</p>
        <p>As far as pollination goes, your informant is on the right track but not great on the specifics. Cross-pollination between varieties usually results in starchy, bland corn, so different strains should be separated, either by large distances or staggered ripening times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 'Magic Number'</p>
        <p>Q.  I tried to grow sweet corn several years ago and failed miserably. I have heard that you need a certain minimum number of plants so that they can cross-pollinate, a necessity for the plants to yield corn. Is this true? What is that minimum? Is it too late to plant this year?</p>
        <p>A.  No, it's not too late. Corn does best when planted in warm soil and grown in hot weather. Then, ideally, just as the ripening starts, nights will begin to cool off. Heat is great for vegetative growth, but the plant will produce ears that have more carbohydrates (including sugars) when temperatures are moderate.</p>
        <p>As far as pollination goes, your informant is on the right track but not great on the specifics. Cross-pollination between varieties usually results in starchy, bland corn, so different strains should be separated, either by large distances or staggered ripening times.</p>
        <p>Yet, pollination itself is essential, and though each plant is both male and female, corn plants don't fertilize themselves because the two parts reach sexual maturity at slightly different times. The ear is the female part. Each corn kernel on it is attached to a strand of silk. A grain of pollen from a tassel, the male part,  must fall on it in order for that kernel to develop. The pollen is shed over a period of several days, but each grain is viable only for about four hours. So the trick is to be sure those grains get a good, wide distribution.</p>
        <p>You can't call in the bees for help; corn is pollinated by a combination of wind and gravity, and that's where the ''minimum number of plants'' comes in. It's not so much a matter of numbers as it is of how they're arranged -- the rows should be in blocks, not strung out in narrow lines.</p>
        <p>Plants should be 10 inches apart in rows 36 inches apart. The minimum is four rows, giving you about 40 plants in a square that's nine feet on each side. If you take advantage of prevailing winds, you can get away with something smaller, but since two ears per stalk is average, you probably won't want to.</p>
        <p>Greenery vs. Toxins</p>
        <p>Q.  I have read that certain houseplants are particularly effective at removing toxic substances from the air. (Those mentioned include the spider plant, English ivy and dracaena.) Is there any truth to this?</p>
        <p>A.  The most impressive tests of this hypothesis were conducted a decade ago by scientists of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration. They put plants and pollutants together in sealed containers and measured marked reductions in gases, including formaldehyde, benzene and carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, the sealed environment is central to the effect. Open a window, and the impressive results fly out of it. As skeptics, including Robert B. Axelrad, senior policy adviser in the indoor environments division of the Environmental Protection Agency, have pointed out, it would probably take hundreds of plants to refresh the air as well as proper ventilation does.</p>
        <p>Indoor air pollution is in large part caused by ''outgassing,'' the release of toxic substances by a host of common products. From plywood to permanent-press fabrics, the synthetic rug to the ceiling tiles, many furnishings of daily life constantly exude chemicals like formaldehyde, xylene, toluene, ammonia and benzene. Plants can remove small quantities of these from the air, but they cannot stop the outgassing itself; so control at the source should not be ignored. Score another point for natural fibers.</p>
        <p>Dr. B. C. Wolverton, an environmental engineer who worked on the NASA studies, has retired from the space agency but continues his research under the sponsorship of the nonprofit Plants for Clean Air Council in Davidsonville, Md., an organization supported by the houseplant industry. His enthusiastic but regrettably footnote-free ''How to Grow Fresh Air'' (Penguin, 1996) lists 50 houseplants recommended for their air-cleaning ability. He gives high marks for chemical vapor removal to the Areca palm (Chrysalidocarpus lutescens), the rubber plant (Ficus robusta) and the Gerbera daisy (Gerbera jamesonii), as well as English ivy (Hedera helix) and a couple of dracaenas. The spider plant is also in the book, but rather low on the list.</p>
        <p>Address questions to Garden Q.&amp; A., The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036, or by E-mail to gardening@nytimes .com. Those of general interest will be published. Unpublished questions cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
