<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AUTO MAKERS PLAN CUTS IN EMISSIONS OF SPORT VEHICLES</title>
    <meta content="06TRUC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sport-Utility Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recreation Vehicles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chrysler Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recreational Vehicles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E0DD1230F935A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AUTO MAKERS PLAN CUTS IN EMISSIONS OF SPORT VEHICLES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Jan. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co will begin selling sport utility vehicles and Windstar mini-vans that produce as little air pollution as cars; Chrysler, after initially expressing reservations, says it will match move in its most popular sport utility vehicle; Ford will install larger and more effective catalytic converters and fine-tune engines so all 1999 sport-utility models, or nearly a quarter-million vehicles, emit roughly 40 percent less pollutants that comparable 1998 models; Chrysler says all 1999 Jeep Cherokees and Grand Cherokees, which will have new engine designs, will be as clean as Ford's (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company announced today that this autumn it would start selling sport utility vehicles and Windstar mini-vans that would produce as little air pollution as cars. The Chrysler Corporation, after initially expressing reservations, said this evening that it would match that move in its most popular sport utility vehicle.</p>
        <p>Ford said it would install larger and more effective catalytic converters and fine-tune its engines so all of its 1999 model-year sport utility vehicles and Windstars -- nearly a million vehicles -- emit roughly 40 percent less in smog-causing gases like nitrogen oxide than the comparable 1998 models now on the market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company announced today that this autumn it would start selling sport utility vehicles and Windstar mini-vans that would produce as little air pollution as cars. The Chrysler Corporation, after initially expressing reservations, said this evening that it would match that move in its most popular sport utility vehicle.</p>
        <p>Ford said it would install larger and more effective catalytic converters and fine-tune its engines so all of its 1999 model-year sport utility vehicles and Windstars -- nearly a million vehicles -- emit roughly 40 percent less in smog-causing gases like nitrogen oxide than the comparable 1998 models now on the market.</p>
        <p>''On emissions, anyway, there will be nothing to feel apologetic about in driving a sport utility vehicle,'' said Alexander Trotman, chairman and chief executive of Ford, the world's second-largest auto maker. Mr. Trotman was addressing recent criticism that, because of special favors from Washington, sport utility vehicles are allowed to emit as much as 175 percent more nitrogen oxides than even the largest cars.</p>
        <p>Ford said it did not plan to charge extra for its cleaner vehicles, choosing instead to look for other cost savings, said Jacques Nasser, Ford's president of worldwide automotive operations.</p>
        <p>The Ford initiative initially drew little enthusiasm from rival auto makers. Thomas Stallkamp, Chrysler's president, said he doubted that Americans wanted cleaner vehicles enough to pay the $50 to $200 extra per vehicle that he estimated it would take to reduce emissions from existing engines. ''Keeping our manufacturing costs as low as possible is important to us,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But later in the day, Chrysler announced that all 1999 Jeep Cherokees and Grand Cherokees, which will have new engine designs, would be as clean as Ford's sport utility vehicles. Chrysler sold roughly 130,000 Cherokees and 260,000 Grand Cherokees last year.</p>
        <p>Michael A. Grimaldi, vehicle line executive for pickup trucks and sport utility vehicles at the General Motors Corporation, the world's largest auto maker, said his company had the technology to reduce emissions as much as Ford, in some cases for the 1999 model year. Executives are reviewing whether to do so, he added. G.M., Ford and Chrysler together produce five of every six light trucks, a category including sport utility vehicles, mini-vans and pickups.</p>
        <p>All of Ford's sport utility vehicles -- including the Ford Explorer and Expedition, the Mercury Mountaineer and the Lincoln Navigator -- will be cleaner next year. Ford sold 650,000 such vehicles last year, as well as 200,000 Windstars, and expects to sell even more sport utility vehicles in the coming years.</p>
        <p>Ford's 1998 model light trucks are already the cleanest in the industry because of recent advances in engine technology. Other auto makers produce sport utility vehicles that are far dirtier and could have a harder time following Ford's example. A Chevrolet Suburban, for example, produces three times as much in smog-causing nitrogen oxides as a Ford Expedition, which is only slightly smaller. G.M. is close to introducing more advanced engines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser of Ford declined to discuss the company's costs for the move, which will include some investments in new factory equipment and greater purchases of precious metals like platinum and palladium, which are used in catalytic converters.</p>
        <p>Industry experts estimated Ford's costs at a little over $100 per vehicle, or about $100 million in the first year, and possibly less thereafter. Ford earns up to $14,000 apiece on the Navigator and more than $3 billion a year in profits on light trucks but loses money on its cars.</p>
        <p>In addition to producing more air pollution than cars, sport utility vehicles typically burn a lot more gasoline. Because of that, they produce more gases that are thought to contribute to global warming. And because they weigh more than cars and ride higher off the ground, they tend to be particularly deadly to occupants of other vehicles in crashes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotman said Ford was working to develop lighter, fuel-efficient sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser said in a speech here that Ford's decision to build cleaner sport utility vehicles would do more to clean up the air in the United States than recent plans by the industry to offer cars running on electricity and other nontraditional fuels early in the next century. ''This year we'll offer cleaner, gasoline-powered vehicles that in the near term should have a greater impact on urban smog problems because of their much higher sales volumes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser made clear in an interview that Ford wanted to maintain the acceptability of sport utility vehicles as alternatives to cars, while gaining an advantage over rival auto makers in catering to environmentally aware families. ''Anybody who has concerns about the environment can set them aside,'' Mr. Nasser said, adding that Ford had also been influenced by recent articles in The New York Times on the environmental problems of light trucks.</p>
        <p>Ford is not planning to reduce emissions immediately for its slow-selling Mercury Villager mini-van, an old design, or for its pickup trucks, which are locked in a fierce competition on price with G.M. and Chrysler pickups.</p>
        <p>Federal emissions regulations on cars and light trucks are likely to be tightened, but not until 2004. Auto makers had also been considering unilateral improvements in emissions for cars and light trucks in exchange for a commitment from state governments not to impose even tougher standards in the future.</p>
        <p>Ford and Chrysler said they would proceed with their plans regardless of those talks but said they were not committing themselves to further improvements nationwide. Toyota, the largest foreign brand seller of sport utilities in the United States, said tonight that it would wait to see what became of those negotiations before changing its vehicles' emissions.</p>
        <p>Loretta M. Ucelli, an associate administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, welcomed today's move by Ford, while cautioning that the agency wanted to study the technical details.</p>
        <p>Ford said that no matter where in the nation these vehicles are sold, all will meet the stringent emissions standards being phased in by California for light trucks. Those standards are not as strict as the state's standards for cars. But the California light truck standards are similar to Federal standards for cars, and allow less than half as much pollution as Federal standards for light trucks.</p>
        <p>California proposed last month to require light trucks to meet its even stricter air pollution standards that will be in force for cars in 2004. Ford remains opposed to such a measure, said Kelly M. Brown, Ford's director of vehicle environmental engineering.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
