<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Panel Approves Deep Cuts in Programs Championed by Clinton</title>
    <meta content="24SPEN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1027079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E4D7103CF937A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Panel Approves Deep Cuts in Programs Championed by Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House subcommittee approves proposal to cut $2.6 billion from Pres Clinton's education and other programs and increase spending on popular health and research programs in fiscal 1999 appropriations bills; Clinton threatens veto; Democrats call cuts extreme and say Republicans may be setting state for confrontation that could again shut down Government; proposal, designed to appeal to conservatives, may alienate Republican moderates whose votes are needed to pass it (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Setting Congress on a collision course with President Clinton, a House panel today approved a proposal to cut back the President's education initiatives as well as eliminate the annual financing for home heating subsidies for the poor.</p>
        <p>The proposal provides substantial increases for the National Institutes of Health and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, underscoring the Republicans' emphasis on popular health and research programs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Setting Congress on a collision course with President Clinton, a House panel today approved a proposal to cut back the President's education initiatives as well as eliminate the annual financing for home heating subsidies for the poor.</p>
        <p>The proposal provides substantial increases for the National Institutes of Health and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, underscoring the Republicans' emphasis on popular health and research programs.</p>
        <p>At the same time, it takes a $2.6 billion bite out of Clinton Administration priorities, cutting the Goals 2000 education program in half, eliminating the Low Income Home Energy Assistance Program, terminating the Summer Youth jobs program and decreasing money for tutoring disadvantaged children.</p>
        <p>The energy assistance program, which costs $1.1 billion, pays for home heating for 4.4 million poor households. Two-thirds of the recipients earn less than $8,000 a year. The summer jobs program spends $871 million for employment of 530,000 young people.</p>
        <p>The proposal, passed by the subcommittee on Labor, Health and Human Services by a vote of 8 to 7, calls for the deepest cuts so far as the Republican-controlled Congress works its way through 13 appropriations bills that Congress must pass to keep the Government running in the fiscal year that begins on Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>Administration officials said tonight that the President would almost certainly veto the measure in its current form.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton himself, in a statement, called the cuts ''arbitrary'' and ''extreme.''</p>
        <p>''This bill is out of step with our values and the wrong vision for America's future,'' he said.</p>
        <p>House Democrats said the cuts were so extreme that the Republicans were setting the stage for a confrontation that could result in the kind of standoff that shut down the Government two years ago and damaged the Republicans' image with the public -- a gamble that some aides said Republicans might be willing to take this year because the President appeared to be politically weaker than he had in the past.</p>
        <p>Republicans said they were strait-jacketed by last year's budget agreement, which virtually froze discretionary spending, and they played down the need for social programs.</p>
        <p>''I regret that we don't have more money to throw at problems,'' said Representative Robert L. Livingston of Louisiana, chairman of the Appropriations Committee. ''But it's the real world.''</p>
        <p>But Republicans also acknowledged that the bill was constructed by House leaders to attract the maximum support of the House's vocal conservatives. This is part of the Republican strategy to activate the party's base of conservative voters in the November elections, when many other voters, content with the strong economy, may not be motivated to go to the polls.</p>
        <p>The problem is, the proposal is so appealing to conservatives that it may alienate Republican moderates, without whom it could not pass. This could deepen the factions within the party and weaken its chances of retaining control of the House.</p>
        <p>The full Appropriations Committee is to vote on the proposed cuts in mid-July, and then the bill will move to the House floor.</p>
        <p>The cuts in domestic social programs help Congress keep within the spending limits it agreed to last year with the Administration to balance the budget. They are not designed to make room for the tax cuts that Republicans are promoting as their main election-year agenda, but they could if Congress changes its rules to allow tax cuts to come from discretionary spending. At the moment, tax cuts can come only from entitlements, which are not discretionary.</p>
        <p>The President has asked for discretionary spending of about $538 billion for next year, up from $523 billion this year. The House has proposed spending $532 billion and the Senate about $534 billion, sums that because of inflation amount to a virtual spending freeze. For example,  the bill's $153 million increase for Head Start, which is $160 million below what the President requested, will not add up to much.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obey said the Republicans were cutting programs to come up with money for medical research that would have come from tobacco companies under a bill that died last week in the Senate.</p>
        <p>''By killing the tobacco bill, Republicans have made it much harder to fund the President's health initiatives,'' Mr. Obey said.</p>
        <p>The labor-education bill increases financing for the National Institutes of Health by $1.3 billion, up more than 9 percent from this year and $126 million more than the President has requested. It increases money for the disease control centers by $202 million over this year, $89 million more than the President sought.</p>
        <p>On policy matters, the bill bans the use of Federal money for research using human embryos, bans the distribution of needles and syringes for the injection of any illegal drug and prohibits Federal financing for a rerun of the teamsters election.</p>
        <p>Today's cuts in the labor-education subcommittee follow House votes on Monday to increase spending on local energy and water projects and on military building.</p>
        <p>The House approved $21.1 billion in energy and water programs, or about $700 million more than the President requested. These include about 200 local projects for flood control and stopping beach erosion, projects eagerly sought by lawmakers in an election year.</p>
        <p>But it sharply reduced Mr. Clinton's request for more money for research into solar power and other forms of renewable energy like wind. It also cut his request for more money to maintain the nation's nuclear weapons arsenal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
