<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. AUTO MAKERS SHOWING INTEREST IN FUEL EFFICIENCY</title>
    <meta content="05CARS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFD71430F936A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. AUTO MAKERS SHOWING INTEREST IN FUEL EFFICIENCY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Jan. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having fiercely but unsuccessfully opposed a global warming treaty and other environmental initiatives last year, American auto makers are stepping up their research into cleaner, more fuel-efficient cars and making ambitious plans for bringing their advanced designs to market.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation, until now skeptical about the demand for such vehicles, today unveiled several prototypes of mid-sized cars that would get 60 to 80 miles per gallon, and said that one of the designs would be ready for mass production in 2001 and another by 2004. The auto maker called for new Federal subsidies to speed the introduction of such vehicles, including tax credits and Government installation of equipment to recharge electric vehicles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having fiercely but unsuccessfully opposed a global warming treaty and other environmental initiatives last year, American auto makers are stepping up their research into cleaner, more fuel-efficient cars and making ambitious plans for bringing their advanced designs to market.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation, until now skeptical about the demand for such vehicles, today unveiled several prototypes of mid-sized cars that would get 60 to 80 miles per gallon, and said that one of the designs would be ready for mass production in 2001 and another by 2004. The auto maker called for new Federal subsidies to speed the introduction of such vehicles, including tax credits and Government installation of equipment to recharge electric vehicles.</p>
        <p>Harry Pearce, G.M.'s vice chairman, said in an interview today that while the new vehicles were likely to be introduced first in Europe, where high gasoline prices made them more attractive, the auto maker was prepared to support a modest increase in American taxes on gasoline and other fossil fuels to make high-mileage vehicles more popular.</p>
        <p>The Ford Motor Company plans a press conference on Monday morning to display its latest inventions, including a prototype for a mid-sized sedan weighing just 2,000 pounds -- 1,300 pounds less than a similar Ford Taurus. And the Chrysler Corporation plans on Tuesday to show off its latest design for a car powered by both diesel and electricity.</p>
        <p>''No car company will be able to thrive in the 21st century if it relies solely on internal combustion engines,'' said John F. Smith Jr., G.M.'s chairman and chief executive, adding that the company was stepping up its research spending and focusing it on bringing to market.</p>
        <p>Some of these moves may reflect a desire to answer criticism over the soaring sales of gas-guzzling sport utility vehicles. Selling more high-mileage, advanced-technology vehicles would allow auto makers to sell more low-mileage gas guzzlers and still meet federally mandated averages for the overall fuel economy of the vehicles they sell.</p>
        <p>The auto makers have been cautious, and Mr. Smith hedged a little today, about committing themselves to the massive production of fuel-efficient vehicles, insisting that they will not build advanced, high-mileage cars if no one wants to buy them.</p>
        <p>But the tone of Detroit executives in talking about high-mileage vehicles has nonetheless been shifting in recent weeks. After years of dismissing advanced-technology vehicles as impractical and too expensive to build, the executives are beginning to show genuine interest.</p>
        <p>The Detroit auto makers' sudden enthusiasm for cleaner cars partly reflects commercial realities. When the American auto makers joined forces last summer with oil and coal industries to set up a lobbying campaign against an international agreement to limit global warming, their Japanese rivals declined to participate. Then, in October, Japanese auto makers stunned the international auto industry by unveiling several very fuel-efficient, low-emissions cars at the Tokyo Motor Show. American and European manufacturers were caught flat-footed, still showing off high-performance gas-guzzling sports cars and sport utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said today that the Tokyo Motor Show had made a profound impression, leaving him with the conclusion that G.M. would have to be a leader in high-mileage cars with extremely low emissions. ''It crystallized in my mind we needed to do a good job on that,'' he said.</p>
        <p>William C. Ford Jr., the powerful chairman of the finance committee at Ford, said the auto maker that reached the market first with a reasonably priced, alternative-fuel vehicle would win a significant competitive advantage.</p>
        <p>''There's a compelling business case to be made,'' Mr. Ford said last month, after Ford announced that it would join Daimler-Benz of Germany in developing cars with fuel-cell engines, which produce power by chemical reactions rather than by burning fuel.</p>
        <p>G.M. announced today that it hoped to have a car powered by a fuel-cell engine ready for production by 2004, and a car powered by both gasoline and electricity by 2001.</p>
        <p>Thomas Gale, Chrysler's executive vice president for product strategy, said today that his company's latest prototype, to be unveiled on Tuesday at the North American International Auto Show here, would represent ''the most pragmatic approach yet to future power trains.'' But Chrysler, which is just half the size of G.M. and Ford, has not been able to devote the same resources as its larger rivals to the development of advanced vehicles.</p>
        <p>Cars produce gases that contribute to global warming in direct proportion to the gasoline they burn. So high-mileage vehicles produce few of these gases while gas-guzzlers produce a lot.</p>
        <p>Ford already holds 95 percent of the nation's small market for alternative-fuel vehicles that run on natural gas, propane, alcohol or electricity. Almost of the buyers are Government agencies, which buy them because of Federal mandates, and utilities that have virtually free supplies of electricity or natural gas; the general public has shown little interest and may shun the latest planned offerings as well.</p>
        <p>But G.M.'s decisions really set the pace for the global auto industry because the company remains the world's largest auto maker, selling a sixth of the world's cars and trucks. Even with heavy imports and growing production here, all of the European and Japanese auto makers combined still do not sell as many cars and trucks each year in the United States as General Motors, which holds nearly 31 percent of the American market. So G.M.'s increased interest in alternative-fuel vehicles could make a big difference in the long term.</p>
        <p>Toyota has just begun selling in Japan the Prius, a hybrid-engine small car that runs on gasoline and electricity and gets 70 miles to the gallon. Toyota is charging $17,000, but industry experts say that the auto maker is only covering half its costs at that price.</p>
        <p>G.M. has been leasing the world's first mass-produced electric car, the EV-1, with little success for the last year in Arizona and California. Robert Purcell, G.M.'s director of advanced vehicles, announced today that the company would introduce a battery this autumn that would double the car's range between rechargings, to 160 miles, and a new electric engine that would cost half as much and be half the size with a third fewer parts than the engine introduced a year ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
