<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="04DIAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980125T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFD71630F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="2023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL WELLMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROSY OUTLOOK  What? Us Worry?  Unruffled by Asia's crisis and buoyed by the promising job market, American consumers approached 1998 with more confidence about their economic future than they have expressed in almost three decades, according to the December survey by the Conference Board. Some 40.6 percent of the respondents to the monthly survey called jobs ''plentiful,'' up from 36.4 percent in November. The optimism was viewed as a strong signal that the economy would remain vibrant, partly because consumer spending accounts for a large portion of domestic growth. The Conference Board's overall confidence index jumped to 134.5 in December, from 128.1 a month before. As if to accent the positive feeling, the Conference Board's leading index of economic indicators rose one-tenth of 1 percent in November.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROSY OUTLOOK  What? Us Worry?  Unruffled by Asia's crisis and buoyed by the promising job market, American consumers approached 1998 with more confidence about their economic future than they have expressed in almost three decades, according to the December survey by the Conference Board. Some 40.6 percent of the respondents to the monthly survey called jobs ''plentiful,'' up from 36.4 percent in November. The optimism was viewed as a strong signal that the economy would remain vibrant, partly because consumer spending accounts for a large portion of domestic growth. The Conference Board's overall confidence index jumped to 134.5 in December, from 128.1 a month before. As if to accent the positive feeling, the Conference Board's leading index of economic indicators rose one-tenth of 1 percent in November.</p>
        <p>SOUTH KOREA  A Multiparty Bailout  The South Korean Government cleared a crucial hurdle in its effort to stabilize its battered economy, paying off or extending a large portion of its monthly debt to foreign banks. Two days before the due date, some of the world's largest commercial and investment banks -- in tandem with the regulators who oversee them -- had gotten together to push a plan to extend payment deadlines for up to $15 billion in troubled loans to strengthen South Korea's precarious financial position. But as the week wore on, it became clear that the plan was not a done deal. Many smaller banks with less money at stake felt that they had little to gain -- and maybe more to lose -- by rolling over the loans. Even among large banks, the plan was seen as an act of preserving the bottom line: ''The only reason the banks are rolling over the short-term debt is because they know if they call it, the loans will default,'' said David Durrant, an analyst with I.D.E.A., a financial advisory firm in New York.</p>
        <p>PHONE REGULATION  Happy New Year, Baby Bells  A Federal judge struck down major sections of the Telecommunications Act of 1996, saying the law unfairly kept the regional Bell telephone companies out of the long-distance market. Should the ruling survive the appeals process, it would allow the Bells to offer long-distance service for the first time since AT&amp;T was broken up in 1984. Not surprisingly, AT&amp;T was not amused, calling the ruling ''inexplicable and clearly erroneous.''</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY  A Disk for the Verbose  I.B.M. says it has broken the magnetic disk-drive storage barrier of 10 billion bits of data per square inch. The company said the new technology would first appear in products in 2001. A 2.5-inch disk drive will be able to hold 6.5 gigabytes of data, making possible ultraslim laptop computers that will nevertheless have vast storage capacity. A 3.5-inch platter will hold 12 to 13 gigabytes. A gigabyte is a billion bytes, equivalent to about 62,500 double-spaced, typewritten pages.</p>
        <p>BROWSER WARS  Click if You Dislike Microsoft  The Justice Department accused Microsoft last week of ''disobedience'' and of ''jerry-rigging its own products'' in response to a Federal judge's order to allow the makers of personal computers to license Microsoft's Windows operating system without being forced to also load its Internet browsing software. The comments were made in a filing in United States District Court in Washington, as the antitrust battle between the Justice Department and the Microsoft Corporation continued to escalate. In the filing, the Government also proposed what many computer users see as a quick solution for unbundling Microsoft's browser, Internet Explorer, from Windows -- simply use a Windows 95 feature for adding and removing programs, which is labeled ''Add/Remove Programs.'' The Government noted that on Nov. 18, on a page of Microsoft's Web site, the company itself said that removing Internet Explorer, or I.E., was not a daunting technical challenge that would cripple recent versions of Windows -- as the company told the court earlier this month.</p>
        <p>CLIMATE CHANGE  Nuclear-Power Economics  The nuclear industry's main lobbying organization, the Nuclear Energy Institute, has been arguing for months that global warming is a reason to build more reactors. But neither these arguments nor the Kyoto accords on global climate are likely to revive nuclear power. For better or worse, when a power plant is needed these days, the decision on what kind to build is generally made according to the availability and cost of fuel, not the potential output of carbon dioxide. And many experts argue that the cheapest way to make electricity now is to burn natural gas in combustion turbines, which are essentially giant jet engines bolted to the ground. In such ''combined cycle'' plants, 50 percent of the energy in the natural gas is turned into electricity, compared with about 30 percent in older plants running on fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>JOBS  Littler Town of Bethlehem  The Bethlehem Steel Corporation is shutting the last factory in its hometown, cutting the last 800 jobs in its coke division by the end of March. The last steelmaking furnace in Bethlehem closed two years ago. . . . Nationsbank expects to cut more than 6,000 jobs in Florida once it takes over Barnett Banks. . . . But even those numbers seem small potatoes compared with the situation in France, where the latest figures show that 12.4 percent of the labor force is out of work (compared with 4.6 percent in the United States in November). . . . The Toyota Motor Corporation is thinking about making luxury sport vehicles in the United States as early as 2000. A second assembly line might be built at a plant already under construction in Princeton, Ind. Toyota also announced that it would build a new plant in France.</p>
        <p>NEW VENTURES  Let's Talk Stopping Power  Smith &amp; Wesson, famous for its handguns, is turning to a new tool for law enforcement: bicycles. The company, the nation's largest handgun maker, has wheeled out a line of police bicycles complete with lights and sirens, The Associated Press reported. David Sargeant, business manager for Smith &amp; Wesson, estimated that more than 20,000 police officers across the country now patrol on bicycles, and their numbers are expected to increase sharply. Several bicycle companies, including Raleigh, Trek and BMW, already make special police models of their mountain bikes. But Smith &amp; Wesson sees its entry into the field as an expansion of a line of law enforcement equipment that includes everything from handcuffs to identification kits. The company's 24-speed mountain bikes range from $750 to $1,200.</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 25, 1998, Sunday  A report in the Business Diary column on Jan. 4 about the data storage capacity of new I.B.M. disk drives referred incorrectly to the size of a gigabyte. It is equivalent to about 512,000 double-spaced, typewritten pages of text, not 62,500. (A gigabyte is 1.024 billion bytes; the computation is based on 2,000 characters to a typewritten page.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 25, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>A report in the Business Diary column on Jan. 4 about the data storage capacity of new I.B.M. disk drives referred incorrectly to the size of a gigabyte. It is equivalent to about 512,000 double-spaced, typewritten pages of text, not 62,500. (A gigabyte is 1.024 billion bytes; the computation is based on 2,000 characters to a typewritten page.)</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
