<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In an Unusual Deal, U.S. Will Sell Stock In Its Uranium Mills</title>
    <meta content="30URAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United States Enrichment Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uranium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DA133FF933A05755C0A96E958260" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In an Unusual Deal, U.S. Will Sell Stock In Its Uranium Mills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Government, in unusual deal, will sell stock in United States Enrichment Corp, which provides most of nuclear energy fuel used in US; expects to raise $1.65 billion; decision to sell company in initial public offering comes after failure to sell it to any private bidder at acceptable price; company is widely viewed as inefficient manufacturer with antiquated technology, in business suffering declining demand; operates aging factories in Ohio and Kentucky and employes about 5,500; reported sales of $1.6 billion in 1997 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Government's uranium enrichment business, rooted in the development of the atomic bomb more than a half-century ago, will soon go on sale in the stock market.</p>
        <p>Federal officials said today that they would try to privatize the United States Enrichment Corporation, which provides most of the nuclear energy fuel used in this country, by selling it to investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Government's uranium enrichment business, rooted in the development of the atomic bomb more than a half-century ago, will soon go on sale in the stock market.</p>
        <p>Federal officials said today that they would try to privatize the United States Enrichment Corporation, which provides most of the nuclear energy fuel used in this country, by selling it to investors.</p>
        <p>The decision to sell the company in what's known as an initial public offering, more often used for start-up companies, came after the Government failed to sell United States Enrichment to any private company for an acceptable price. United States Enrichment is widely viewed as an inefficient manufacturer with antiquated technology, in a business suffering declining demand.</p>
        <p>Although it's unclear what investors would be willing to pay to own the business, the Treasury expects the stock offering to raise as much as $1.65 billion.</p>
        <p>The Government has never attempted anything quite like this before. In the short history of privatization in this country the only sale remotely similar, experts said, was that of Conrail, a collection of failing Northeastern railroads. The Government took them over in 1973 and subsequently sold the operation in a 1987 stock offering for $1.65 billion. The biggest privatization ever was the Government's sale of the Elk Hills petroleum reserve in California to the Occidental Petroleum Company last October for $3.65 billion.</p>
        <p>United States Enrichment operates aging factories in Piketon, Ohio, and Paducah, Ky., employs about 5,500 people and had 1997 sales of $1.6 billion. It is also trying to develop a modern, laser-based enrichment system at laboratories of the Energy Department, of which it was once a part.</p>
        <p>Two private consortiums, one including the contractors that now operate the company for the Government, submitted bids. People involved in the deal were reticent to speak about it because of the Securities and Exchange Commission rules limiting what can be said about businesses sold to the public, but some pointed out that the authorizing legislation, passed by Congress in 1992 and 1996, set a variety of requirements beyond price, including protecting public health and national security, and assuring a continued domestic enrichment industry.</p>
        <p>But some people in the industry said the Treasury's asking price was very high for an industry with uncertain prospects. Demand for nuclear reactor fuel is down, because fewer nuclear plants have been built than once expected and a surplus of enriched uranium now exists. The reason is that some weapons fuel, which is highly enriched, is diluted for reactor use.</p>
        <p>''The market is characterized by oversupply,'' said James C. Cornell, president of Nukem, a German-owned company involved in uranium enrichment. ''The million-dollar question is whether U.S.E.C. will be able to raise the kind of money they are looking for.''</p>
        <p>The company, with headquarters in Bethesda, Md., had its origins in the construction of the bomb that destroyed Hiroshima in World War II. Shifting to peaceful uses for nuclear fuel, it became part of the Atomic Energy Commission and then the Energy Department, but Congress established it as a separate enterprise in preparation for an eventual privatization mandated in a 1992 law.</p>
        <p>Two groups have made offers to acquire the business. One includes Lockheed Martin, which currently operates the Piketon and Paducah plants under contract, BWX Technologies, formerly Babcock &amp; Wilcox, a contractor involved in the laser development, and the Carlyle Group, an investment firm. The second includes General Atomics, a San Diego company that has been in the reactor and fuel-fabrication business, and Texas Pacific Group, an investment firm.</p>
        <p>The Treasury said a group of Wall Street investment bankers underwriting the stock sale, led by Morgan Stanley and Merrill Lynch, believe they can sell 100 million shares of United States Enrichment at $13.50 to $16.50 a share. The sale is expected to take place in about a month.</p>
        <p>The Treasury could cancel the sale if the shares could not be sold at $13.50, or it could accept a lower price, but doing so might result in a challenge from the corporate bidders rejected for submitting prices deemed inadequate.</p>
        <p>Another potential problem with the privatization is that some critics say it will jeopardize a deal made during the Bush Administration for the United States to buy surplus Russian weapons fuel. The company agreed to buy the fuel from the Russians for $110 to $120 per unit of enrichment work, called a ''separative work unit,'' but those units now have a market price in the $80 range, so keeping the contract is a guaranteed way to lose money.</p>
        <p>Senator Pete V. Domenici complained in a letter on Friday to Sandy Berger, the President's national security adviser, that it might be time to reconsider the deal because of the contracts with the Russians.</p>
        <p>But Robert E. Rubin and Federico F. Pena, the Treasury and Energy Secretaries, said in a letter to Senator John Glenn made public today that ''we expect U.S.E.C. to continue meeting its contractual obligations after privatization'' and that if it did not, the Energy Department could step in and buy the enriched Russian uranium.</p>
        <p>The sale would be ''one of the largest privatizations in U.S. history,'' they wrote, and would preserve more jobs at the company than if it were to remain Government owned.</p>
        <p>Some opponents have been struggling for months against the privatization because of the potential job impact. Representative Ted Strickland, whose southern Ohio district includes Piketon, said the Government had not adequately detailed how the privatization would maintain a viable domestic enrichment industry.</p>
        <p>The factories though, are confronting a number of problems. They use the oldest and most energy-gulping commercial technology for their business, which consists of taking in uranium that is seven-tenths of 1 percent of the type that splits easily in reactors, uranium 235, and raising that proportion to about 5 percent. The Government plants use a process known as gaseous diffusion; younger competitors abroad use centrifuges.</p>
        <p>The Government operation once held 90 percent of the world market, but the market expanded and aggressive competitors took a larger share. Now United States Enrichment has about 40 percent, including about 75 percent of the North American market.</p>
        <p>The plants are heavy users of chlorofluorocarbons, which deplete the earth's protective ozone layer. The biggest environmental problem, though, would stay in Government hands after the privatization: 1.25 billion pounds of uranium waste, which could cost $10 billion to put into stable form.</p>
        <p>The long-term prospect is for declining demand for enrichment work, as the reactor population dwindles.</p>
        <p>United States Enrichment's hope is a new technology, called Atomic Vapor Laser Isotope Separation, allows enrichment with one-tenth as much electricity. But it has not been commercialized and some people doubt it will be. The Federal Government has invested $2 billion in the technique, called Avlis.</p>
        <p>''In our industry we say you'll see Elvis before you see Avlis,'' said Mr. Cornell of Nukem. ''I don't think anybody will spend the money necessary to commercialize it, because it's in the billions, and when you get past the year 2010, even most optimistic demand forecasts call for decline in consumption.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
