<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A California Vote Could Rewrite U.S. Electric Bills</title>
    <meta content="25UTIL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Consumers Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salpukas, Agis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DE1F3DF936A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="3039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A California Vote Could Rewrite U.S. Electric Bills</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salpukas, Agis</byline>
      <dateline>CHICO, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on effort by Consumers Union and other groups to persuade California voters to pass Proposition 9, which would upend electric utility regulation and sharply cut rates for residential and small-commercial customers; photos; graphs (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS political rallies go, it wasn't much: a knot of about 20 people standing in front of a Pacific Gas and Electric Company office in this small city about 90 miles north of Sacramento. Passers-by ignored the signs they waved, placards that supported a proposition on the California ballot on Nov. 3 intended to upend deregulation of the state's utilities and sharply cut electric rates for residential and small-commercial customers.</p>
        <p>But television crews from two local stations recorded the event, and the activists who organized it welcomed the free publicity for their cause.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS political rallies go, it wasn't much: a knot of about 20 people standing in front of a Pacific Gas and Electric Company office in this small city about 90 miles north of Sacramento. Passers-by ignored the signs they waved, placards that supported a proposition on the California ballot on Nov. 3 intended to upend deregulation of the state's utilities and sharply cut electric rates for residential and small-commercial customers.</p>
        <p>But television crews from two local stations recorded the event, and the activists who organized it welcomed the free publicity for their cause.</p>
        <p>''We're reduced to stunts,'' acknowledged Harry M. Snyder, a senior advocate for Consumers Union, the nonprofit group that publishes Consumer Reports magazine.</p>
        <p>With little money for television commercials and an issue that confuses many voters, Consumers Union and other groups are trying to ignite a rate-payer revolt to pass Proposition 9 and rein in the state's utilities, which the groups say are failing to share enough of the benefits of deregulation with smaller customers.</p>
        <p>This is a long-shot effort, but one that the utilities and their allies are taking very seriously. Opponents of Proposition 9 are spending more than $30 million on a campaign to defend the deregulation plan that went into effect earlier this year. Although the utilities' barrage of television commercials has cut into support for the proposition, polls still show it with considerable support among a befuddled electorate.</p>
        <p>The stakes are high. Opponents of Proposition 9 say that if it ever took effect, it could cost utilities about $6 billion and put the state's credit at risk. More important, a victory for the measure -- even if it is tied  up in the courts, as so many California ballot propositions are -- could help stall plans to deregulate utilities in other states.</p>
        <p>''The effects would be devastating,'' said Scott Gebhardt, the president and chief executive of PG&amp;E Energy Services, a subsidiary of the PG&amp;E Corporation, the holding company for Pacific Gas and Electric, the largest utility in the state. ''It would have a chilling effect across the nation.''</p>
        <p>Backers of Proposition 9 certainly hope so. The California battle comes as the early enthusiasm for deregulation is running into opposition in a few states.</p>
        <p>Massachusetts will vote next month on a ballot initiative that, like Proposition 9, challenges the mechanism by which utilities can recover the costs of nuclear plants they built and high-priced power contracts they signed in the days of strict state regulation. In New Hampshire, deregulation is stalled in the courts.</p>
        <p>California, which has moved further than other states to deregulate its utilities, has become the flashpoint for consumer discontent. Since residential power service was opened to competition earlier this year, the electric bills received by California households have shown a state-mandated 10 percent discount. But the bills now also include a variety of additional charges -- including one for those nuclear plants and high-cost contracts -- and consumer groups are arguing that smaller customers are actually saving very little, perhaps only 1 to 3 percent.</p>
        <p>''They give us a rate cut, but then the utilities are using fees to get that back,'' said George West, a retired savings-and-loan executive who, along with his wife Jan, was one of the handful of people who showed up for the rally in Chico. ''Something's not right.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, big industrial customers  may end up cutting their power costs by a third within four years, according to energy marketers. The expected competition among electricity suppliers is taking place mostly for these big customers; as a result, it is utilities and industry that are providing most of the money for the campaign to defeat Proposition 9.</p>
        <p>AT issue is a compromise reached two years ago by the state's three big utilities, environmental groups and others that enabled the Legislature to unanimously pass a law making California the first state to deregulate its utility industry.</p>
        <p>As part of the deal, the utilities agreed to open themselves to competition from power suppliers outside California; electricity customers, meanwhile, would foot most of the bill for what are called stranded costs.</p>
        <p>These include the costs California utilities incurred building nuclear plants that were much more expensive than anticipated. They also include the costs of long-term contracts for high-priced electricity from outside suppliers. In California, these stranded costs total a staggering $28 billion according to an estimate two years ago, which is to be paid off in about four years. Then, smaller customers are also expected to see larger savings, of 20 percent or more, as more marketers begin competing to serve them.</p>
        <p>The Utility Reform Network, an activist group that has long battled the state's utilities on rate matters, took part in the talks over the 1996 deregulation plan and ultimately adopted a neutral stance, easing the deal's passage in Sacramento. But now, the  group, known by the acronym Turn, has joined Consumers Union and others, including the League of Women Voters and the Sierra Club, to promote Proposition 9.</p>
        <p>The groups, which have raised just $1.2 million to back the initiative, contend that Proposition 9, if passed, would quickly cut residential electric bills by 20 percent, basically by shifting $6 billion in stranded costs to the utilities and their shareholders.</p>
        <p>It would also prevent the utilities from imposing fees on rate payers to pay off a separate $6 billion bond issue that enabled the power companies to give the rate payers a 10 percent rate cut this year. In effect, the initiative's backers say, it would stop the utilities from taking back with one hand the discount they extended with the other.</p>
        <p>But if Proposition 9 is approved by the voters, the utilities say that bondholders would be left in limbo, endangering the credit rating of every public borrower in California. They are also threatening to go to court to uphold their right to be reimbursed for costs they incurred when rates were regulated. If that happens, the implementation of the proposition -- and possibly of utility deregulation here over all -- could be tied up for years.</p>
        <p>''You will have to fight it all over again,'' said Robert D. Glynn Jr. chairman, president and chief executive of PG&amp;E, which is based in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>That prospect could inhibit other states from proceeding with their own deregulation plans. ''People will be more inclined to wait and see,'' said Robert K. Johnson, executive director of the Electric Consumers Alliance, which represents about 260 consumer groups nationwide.</p>
        <p>The other states that have adopted deregulation plans are Pennsylvania, New York, Connecticut, Rhode Island, New Hampshire, Maine, Illinois and Montana; 15 others are putting plans together.</p>
        <p>Here in California, the three major electric utilities -- Pacific Gas and Electric;  Southern California Edison, which is owned by Edison International, and the San Diego Gas and Electric Company, owned by the Sempra Energy Corporation -- have spent heavily to saturate the state with prime-time commercials opposing Proposition 9.</p>
        <p>The utilities have wide and formidable support, not only from such expected allies as associations for large industrial customers and local chambers of commerce, but also from labor unions, which worry about job losses because of high power rates; environmental groups like the Environmental Defense Fund and the Natural Resource Defense Council, which favor the deregulation plan's incentives for using renewable energy and encouraging efficiency, and education groups like the California School Boards Association, which do not want to see borrowing costs rise.</p>
        <p>Statewide polling on the initiative indicates that prospective voters are confused and divided. Three respected polls put support for Proposition 9 at anywhere from 43 percent of those questioned to just 19 percent; the undecideds range from 23 percent to 43 percent.</p>
        <p>In their efforts to sway the result, both sides are making simplistic appeals to voters' pocketbooks and their sense of fair play.</p>
        <p>In one anti-Proposition 9 TV spot, Thomas Hayes, a former state Treasurer, warns that after conducting an in-depth study he concluded that passage of the proposal  would cause a default on the deregulation bonds, ''leaving California taxpayers liable for about $6 billion.'' Such a default, he warns, would force California municipalities and schools to pay higher interest rates when they borrow money.</p>
        <p>The other side relies on news interviews with spokesmen, like Harvey J. Rosenfield, the consumer activist who in 1988 spearheaded Proposition 103, an initiative that led to rebate checks for many of the state's auto insurance customers.</p>
        <p>Interviewed this month by KRON, a San Francisco television station, Mr. Rosenfield assailed the utilities for persuading politicians to require rate payers to ''pay 100 percent of the utilities' bad debts.''</p>
        <p>''This outrageous corporate welfare will cost every family in California $2,000,'' he said. An hour later, at another station, he struck out again, comparing the full recovery of stranded costs to the ''utility mafia calling in all their chits.''</p>
        <p>But this lively debate has not made either utility deregulation or Proposition 9 much  clearer to many people, who say in interviews that they remain unsure how to vote.</p>
        <p>For example, Salah Atshon, a clerk at a small delicatessen near Union Square in San Francisco, has seen many of the ads. ''They tell me to say 'no,' '' he said, standing behind the counter, ''but they tell me little about what exactly the proposition says.''</p>
        <p>Dan Davis, who owns a film processing business in Chico and follows utility deregulation for the Chico Chamber of Commerce, said he was unsure what Proposition 9 would do. ''And I've read it twice,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As a result, he is reluctant to tamper with the existing deregulation plan, especially because it has only begun to take hold. Indeed, the Chico chamber decided to oppose the proposition rather than disrupt deregulation at this point.</p>
        <p>''Most small-business people want to take a wait-and-see approach and let things evolve,'' Mr. Davis said.</p>
        <p>THE utility business was deregulated  here in March, after a three-month delay. That wait was because of glitches in the software used to run a power pool in which electricity could be bought and sold by competing marketers, utilities and independent power producers, much as on a commodity exchange.</p>
        <p>An $89 million statewide publicity campaign raised expectations that customers would be able to choose a supplier other than their established utility and that the competition would help drive down rates.</p>
        <p>Smaller customers, however -- whether homeowners, renters or small-business owners -- found that there were few choices. Since the smaller customers were already guaranteed a 10 percent discount, most power suppliers could offer little in the way of savings and still cover their expenses, let alone eke out a profit.</p>
        <p>The Enron Corporation, for example, tried offering two weeks' worth of free electricity to entice smaller customers. But after spending millions of dollars and months of effort, Enron, based in Houston,  attracted only 30,000 customers. So it withdrew from the consumer market in April.</p>
        <p>All together, only about 100,000 customers out of a potential 10 million statewide have switched away from their utilities. (Municipal systems, like the one that serves most of the city of Los Angeles, are exempt from the deregulation law unless they choose to compete outside their service area.)</p>
        <p>But utilities and outside power suppliers like Enron are competing vigorously for large industrial customers, the market that, with its economies of scale, offers the greatest potential for profits.</p>
        <p>For example, PG&amp;E Energy Services is spending about $100 million pursuing manufacturers and other big businesses. Among other things, the company is providing staff to help customers find ways to conserve energy, change processes and shift power use to off-peak times, when it is cheaper.</p>
        <p>Such steps, together with a decline in industrial electric rates because of the increased competition, are expected to save some large customers hundreds of millions of dollars, cutting their power costs by a third or more over about four years, according to Mr. Gebhardt of PG&amp;E Services.</p>
        <p>Numbers like these, the initiative's backers say, show that the fruits of deregulation are not being shared equitably. Moreover, in June, when various deregulation-related charges were broken out on bills for the first time, some smaller customers began to realize that even their 10 percent discount did not come without strings.</p>
        <p>They saw, for instance, a charge labeled ''Trust Transfer Amount,'' which is being collected to pay off the $6 billion of bonds that were sold on behalf of the utilities by agents to help make the 10 percent rate cut possible. On many residential bills, the charge is actually larger than the discount.</p>
        <p>Some customers look at the two amounts and wonder where the savings are, even though the utilities insist that the two figures are not comparable.</p>
        <p>The mathematics of California rate payers' bills underscore a big reason that most states have been slow to deregulate utilities: it is difficult to keep electricity rates from going up in the early years, because the utilities' stranded costs must be paid. Otherwise, the long-established power companies are stuck with plants that cannot compete once the shield of monopoly is lifted and cheap power begins to flow freely.</p>
        <p>In California, that challenge was made a bit less formidable by the fact that many of the utilities' contracts for higher-priced power from independent suppliers were about to run out; that meant the price that the utilities were paying for power would drop quickly.</p>
        <p>Normally, such savings would have been passed on to customers by the California Public Utilities Commission in rate reductions estimated at 8 to 12 percent.</p>
        <p>Instead, the negotiators who cobbled together California's deregulation plan in 200 hours of marathon meetings agreed to allow the utilities to freeze rates. On the surface, that looked like a good deal for consumers used to regular increases in power costs. In reality, it was a huge source of revenue for the utilities to apply toward paying off their stranded costs.</p>
        <p>''It was a very creative and pragmatic way to get to competition,'' said Mr. Gebhardt, who had gone through the slow process of deregulation of the natural gas industry when he was an Enron executive. ''You keep the utilities whole while you open up competition.''</p>
        <p>Later, the 10 percent discount was insisted upon by legislators and advertised as a further inducement for popular support.</p>
        <p>Consumer advocates like Mr. Snyder of Consumers Union see the compromise differently, complaining that no strong voice for rate payers was represented in the negotiations. ''The person paying the bill was left out of the room,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Besides forcing the utilities to pay about $6 billion of stranded costs -- those for building and operating nuclear plants --  Proposition 9 would also eliminate the Trust Transfer Amount from customers' bills, by prohibiting utilities from charging rate payers for the costs of retiring the $6 billion in bonds sold to finance the 10 percent rate cut.</p>
        <p>Both sides agree, though, that any cost-shifting to the utilities will be borne by their investors and that the companies' stock prices are likely to fall.''The shareholders will have to pay,'' Mr. Snyder said.</p>
        <p>Californians reached this point in part because Turn, the rate-payer activist group, blinked during negotiations over the 1996 deregulation plan.</p>
        <p>Nettie Hoge, Turn's executive director,  said in an interview that she had misgivings about the agreement from the start but  believed it was the best deal that could be reached. Businesses tired of paying some of the highest rates in the country were threatening to move plants to other states with cheaper power, and there was a sense that the state needed to act quickly.</p>
        <p>While Turn lobbied to protect consumers during the negotiations, she said, ''I did not have the courage to say, 'This doesn't meet our bottom line.' ''</p>
        <p>Since then, the group has been actively seeking to change California's program. ''I don't think this is the best thing for residential customers,'' Ms. Hoge said. ''I think the utilities got a windfall.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
