<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Gives Its First Grants From Big Ted Turner Gift</title>
    <meta content="Y20NAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980521T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1018418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations Children's Fund</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations Population Fund</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wirth, Timothy E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Ted</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E0DA1439F933A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Gives Its First Grants From Big Ted Turner Gift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, May 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First round of grants from Ted Turner's $1 billion gift to UN will be announced on May 20, with nearly three-quarters of the initial $22 million going to help women, children and victims of war in poor countries; recipients of largest grants--and more than half of initial $22 million--will be UN Population Fund and UN Children's Fund; Turner fund president Timothy E Wirth comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first round of grants from Ted Turner's $1 billion gift to the United Nations will be announced on Wednesday, with nearly three-quarters of the initial $22 million going to help women, children and victims of war in poor countries, the president of the fund, Timothy E. Wirth, said today.</p>
        <p>Among the varied targets of the grants will be the control of intestinal parasites in Vietnam, the eradication of diseases that kill children in several African nations and the disarming of child soldiers in Sierra Leone. Programs to combat violence against women in Latin America, provide better reproductive health services in Asia and Africa and aid victims of land mines in six countries are also included.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first round of grants from Ted Turner's $1 billion gift to the United Nations will be announced on Wednesday, with nearly three-quarters of the initial $22 million going to help women, children and victims of war in poor countries, the president of the fund, Timothy E. Wirth, said today.</p>
        <p>Among the varied targets of the grants will be the control of intestinal parasites in Vietnam, the eradication of diseases that kill children in several African nations and the disarming of child soldiers in Sierra Leone. Programs to combat violence against women in Latin America, provide better reproductive health services in Asia and Africa and aid victims of land mines in six countries are also included.</p>
        <p>The fund, formally established in January as the United Nations Foundation, plans to disburse $100 million a year over the next decade from the sale of up to 18 million shares of Mr. Turner's Time Warner stock, acquired when his company, Turner Broadcasting System, Inc., merged with Time Warner in 1996.</p>
        <p>The grant, announced last year, is the largest gift the United Nations has ever received from a private source. United Nations agencies and programs compete for the money by submitting proposals.</p>
        <p>The recipients of the largest grants -- and more than half of the  initial $22 million -- will be the United Nations Population Fund and Unicef, the United Nations children's fund.</p>
        <p>The biggest single award -- $3 million -- is to the population fund in Bolivia for developing bilingual Spanish-Quechua literacy among rural women to improve their understanding of their reproductive health options. A grant of $860,000 goes to a Unicef project supplying vitamin supplements to mothers in Indonesia's province of West Timor, an extremely poor area lost in the shadow of East Timor, the disputed territory with which it shares an island.</p>
        <p>''We set four broad priority areas: Women and population stabilization, sustainable environment and climate change, children's health, and strengthening the U.N. system,'' said Mr. Wirth, a former Democratic Senator from Colorado and Under Secretary of State for Global Affairs.</p>
        <p>The areas generally reflect the interest of Mr. Turner and Jane Fonda, his wife. But environmental projects are noticeably absent from the larger grants.</p>
        <p>''The environmental group isn't as strong as we would like it to be,'' Mr. Wirth said. ''Some of the projects that were recommended were basically infrastructure projects, which is not the sort of things we ought to be doing in terms of preventive and innovative programs.''</p>
        <p>In one of only three environmental projects of 22 supported in the first round of grants, the United Nations Foundation allocated $900,000 for a joint one-year project of the United Nations Development Program and the World Resources Institute to help China, the world's second-largest source of greenhouse gases, consolidate information about policies to reduce carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>Two other environmental grants totaling about $520,000 go to an assessment of the global environment by young people to encourage them to focus on the future, and to a United Nations task force studying environment in relation to human settlements.</p>
        <p>Last week, the United Nations Foundation chose its international board of directors, of which Mr. Turner is the chairman. Other directors are Ruth Cardoso of Brazil, an anthropologist who works in anti-poverty programs; Graca Machel, a former education minister of Mozambique who produced a United Nations study on children at war; Emma Rothschild, director of the Center for History and Economics at King's College, Cambridge, and a fellow at the Harvard Center for Population and Development Studies; Maurice Strong, a Canadian businessman who was Secretary General of the Rio Earth Summit; Andrew Young, former mayor of Atlanta and now co-chairman of Good Works International, a consulting group, and Muhammad Yunus, founder of the Grameen Bank of Bangladesh, which pioneered small-scale credit programs for women. Mr. Wirth is also a member of the board.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 21, 1998, Thursday  A headline yesterday about the first round of grants from Ted Turner's $1 billion gift to the United Nations referred imprecisely to the donor of the grants. It is the United Nations Foundation, an independent group, not the United Nations itself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 21, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>A headline yesterday about the first round of grants from Ted Turner's $1 billion gift to the United Nations referred imprecisely to the donor of the grants. It is the United Nations Foundation, an independent group, not the United Nations itself.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
