<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="02FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984626"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D61E31F931A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Israel's Foreign Minister Threatens to Resign Post  Foreign Minister David Levy threatened to resign in the midst of a dispute over the 1998 budget, creating a crisis for Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and forcing him to delay the budget vote until Monday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Israel's Foreign Minister Threatens to Resign Post  Foreign Minister David Levy threatened to resign in the midst of a dispute over the 1998 budget, creating a crisis for Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and forcing him to delay the budget vote until Monday.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>One Dead in Belfast Shooting  Tensions rose in Northern Ireland, after a Catholic man was shot dead and five others were wounded when masked Protestant paramilitaries opened fire on a crowded pub in Belfast. The Loyalist Volunteer Force, a breakaway group opposed to peace talks, claimed responsibility and promised more violence in retaliation for the killing of Billy Wright, the group's founder. Talks aimed at ending nearly 30 years of conflict are to resume on Jan. 12.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Zapatistas Mark Anniversary  Members of the Zapatista National Liberation Army celebrated the fourth anniversary of their invasion of four towns in southern Mexico, which was motivated by their drive for autonomy for the nation's Indians. The Zapatistas have expressed disappointment that little has changed in the four years.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Rebels Attack Burundi Village  Rebels attacked a village and military camp on the outskirts of Burundi's capital, killing at least 160, in what officials called the biggest rebel assault in that country in recent years. According to the head of security forces in Burundi, the rebel group attacked a village and killed civilians who refused to accompany the guerrillas. The attackers were repelled when they tried to seize the capital's airport.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Controversy in Kenyan Vote  The situation surrounding the presidential election in Kenya remained explosive as the slow counting of ballots continued. With more than half the constituencies counted, Democratic Party candidate Mwai Kibaki, a former Vice President, was putting up a strong fight against President Daniel arap Moi. Mr. Kibaki and another opposition candidate said they would not accept the results if Mr. Moi were to win, accusing officials of rigging the election.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Congo to Organize Elections  President Laurent Kabila of Congo said his Government would organize national elections early in 1999. Mr. Kabila made the pledge in a nationally broadcast New Year's address, despite opposition within his own Government and at a time of widespread popular disenchantment with his rule.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Russia Gets Another New Ruble  Russia introduced new rubles, worth 1,000 times as much as the old ones, marking the third time in less than a decade that the Government has tried to strengthen its battered currency. Old rubles will be accepted along with the new ones for a year, but many Russians have converted their money into dollars, and plan to hold onto the dollars for several weeks out of fear that the change will not be painless.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-14</p>
        <p>Michael Kennedy Died Playing Football on Skis  Michael L. Kennedy, the 39-year-old son of Robert F. Kennedy, who died in a skiing accident in Aspen, Colo., on Wednesday, had been playing football on skis, a game that Kennedys have engaged in for generations on the slopes this time of year, witnesses and family members said.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Hatch Answers Rehnquist  Responding to the unusually pointed complaint of Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist about the Senate's slow pace in confirming Federal judges, the chairman of the Judiciary Committee, Orrin G. Hatch, defended the Senate's performance and said the courts themselves were partly to blame for their heavy caseloads.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Southern Tradition Imperiled  The city of Wilson, N.C., is expected sometime early this year to ban old sofas, recliners and other indoor furniture from porches and yards in what many people see as a clash of the classes and an assault on the rhythms of Southern life.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Balloonist Heads for Europe  Steve Fossett continued his attempt to circle the world by balloon, soaring at about 80 miles an hour, 22,000 feet over the Atlantic Ocean, more than 225 miles east of Bermuda. Mr. Fossett, who left from St. Louis, was expected to reach Europe by Saturday. A competitor who took off at about the same time had to abort his flight because of a burst helium container.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Officer's Verdict Overturned  A new trial was ordered for former Detroit police officer Larry Nevers, 57, who was found guilty of second-degree murder in the 1992 slaying of Malice Green, a 35-year-old unemployed steel worker. The conviction of another police officer in the same case had been overturned earlier. Judge Lawrence Zatkoff, who overturned the verdict in the Nevers case, said prejudicial pretrial publicity and errors during the proceedings, such as allowing jurors to see the film ''Malcolm X,'' which opens with video footage of the Rodney King beating -- prevented the police officer from obtaining a fair trial.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Judge Rules Against Author  A Florida judge ruled that the state may seize money an author made by marketing the confessions of a serial killer, co-writing a book with him and selling his art and autographs.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>New Painkiller Discovered  Taking a clue from a deadly poison found in the skin of a South American frog, researchers have discovered a powerful new painkiller that seems to have all of the benefits of morphine, but none of the damaging side effects.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Hay Airlifted to Cattle  With the announcement on Wednesday of $2 million in disaster aid for ranchers, the New Mexico National Guard was airlifting hay to 181,000 head of livestock stranded by snow. The Federal Department of Agriculture estimated that some 5,000 cattle had already died.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Giuliani Calls for Adding 1,600 Police Officers  Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, delivering the inaugural speech for his second term, said he wanted to add 1,600 officers in New York City to what is already the country's largest municipal police force and vowed to use his second term to build on the successes of the first.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Police Gunfire Comparably Low  F.B.I. statistics show that New York City police officers shoot civilians far less frequently than their counterparts in other major cities.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>The Day After in Times Square  On the morning after Times Square hosted a New Year's Eve party for 500,000 revelers, the neighborhood seemed subdued, but hardly hung over. The neighborhood's rapid recovery was aided by the Times Square Business Improvement District and the city's Department of Sanitation, which planned a huge, synchronized clean-up effort. Twenty-five minutes after the ball dropped, mechanical brooms were whirring down the avenues. Police made just 30 arrests during the festivities.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-35; E37-46</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>D7</p>
        <p>Richard Elman  A novelist, poet and critic who taught for many years at the Bennington College Summer Writing Workshops in Vermont, he was 63.</p>
        <p>D7</p>
        <p>Floyd Cramer  A pianist who played piano on Elvis Presley's ''Heartbreak Hotel'' and had his own hit, ''Last Date,'' which became an instrumental classic, he was 64.</p>
        <p>D7</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Michigan Takes Rose Bowl  Michigan beat Washington State, 21-16, in the Rose Bowl, most likely securing a national championship.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ewing Assesses His Recovery</p>
        <p>Patrick Ewing, in his first public appearance since suffering a dislocated bone and torn ligaments in his right wrist 12 days ago, said that he believed he would be back at full strength next season and expressed hope that he could be back for this year's basketball playoffs -- if the Knicks can reach the postseason.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Cubans Seek Bahamas Asylum  Joe Cubas, an agent for a number of Cuban baseball players, said that Orlando Hernandez, half brother of the Florida Marlins' Livan Hernandez, and Alberto Hernandez, no relation, have requested asylum in the Bahamas, where their escape from Cuba led them last weekend. Just in case their request is not honored, Cubas said, he is working to get the players into another country, possibly Costa Rica.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-6, D8</p>
        <p>South Korea Clears Hurdle</p>
        <p>South Korea has cleared a crucial hurdle in its effort to stabilize its battered economy, paying off or extending a large portion of debt it owes foreign banks. But the Korean Government was forced to repay some of the debt because smaller lenders have been unwilling to extend their loans.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Stallkamp Leads Chrysler  Thomas T. Stallkamp became the president of Chrysler. He had been one of several contenders for president, and his promotion last month caught some people by surprise. He wants to streamline the entire process of building and selling cars and trucks at the company.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Outlook on Nuclear Power  The Kyoto accords on global climate change will probably not revive the nuclear power industry: Nuclear reactors produce no carbon dioxide, but they are expensive and pose environmental risks. It might be preferable, experts say, to use the same money to build a much larger number of plants running on natural gas, which produce very little carbon dioxide.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Heart Attacks and the Street  The heart attack death rate during business hours for the 5,000 people who work at the New York Stock Exchange is 60 percent higher than the national rate for men between 18 and 65, according to the National Center for Health Statistics.</p>
        <p>D2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: The Mayor's second term; hurdles for South Korea; environmental tasks in 1998.</p>
        <p>Column: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E46</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>B7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
