<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AUTOS ON FRIDAY/Technology; Cleaner Cars, No Magic Required</title>
    <meta content="06CARS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="993250"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Monoxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DA153DF935A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AUTOS ON FRIDAY/Technology; Cleaner Cars, No Magic Required</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Autos on Friday column assesses Big Three auto makers' promise to produce cleaner vehicles than Federal regulations now require, in exchange for agreement by eight states not to adopt California's even stricter standards; sees little impact on car buyers, since companies can make cars far cleaner without resorting to new components, by refining existing parts; photo; tables showing emissions standards for various classes of vehicles (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOW that the Big Three auto makers have agreed to a compromise under which they will produce cleaner vehicles than Federal regulations now require, cars will have new hardware, beginning next year in the Northeast and in 2001 in the rest of the country outside of California. But the differences under the hood are likely to be minor.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the General Motors Corporation, the Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler Corporation agreed to sell cleaner cars nationwide in exchange for an agreement by eight states not to adopt California's even stricter standards. The car makers had sought a standard for all states except California, but settled for a deal that allowed New York, Maine, Massachusetts and Vermont to enforce California's rules.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOW that the Big Three auto makers have agreed to a compromise under which they will produce cleaner vehicles than Federal regulations now require, cars will have new hardware, beginning next year in the Northeast and in 2001 in the rest of the country outside of California. But the differences under the hood are likely to be minor.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the General Motors Corporation, the Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler Corporation agreed to sell cleaner cars nationwide in exchange for an agreement by eight states not to adopt California's even stricter standards. The car makers had sought a standard for all states except California, but settled for a deal that allowed New York, Maine, Massachusetts and Vermont to enforce California's rules.</p>
        <p>What does this mean to car buyers? Not much, because the manufacturers can make cars far cleaner without resorting to major new components. Instead, they have refined the existing parts, tweaking the catalytic converter and the fuel injectors. As a result, the changes have mostly been inexpensive and smooth. And some of these alterations may also improve a car's fuel economy and its performance.</p>
        <p>Both the California standard and the new 45-state standard are fleet averages, goals that each car company can reach through different mixes of car categories established by the State of California. The categories, in increasing order of cleanliness, are ''transitional LEV,'' LEV, ''ultra LEV,'' and ZEV, for zero-emission vehicles. ZEV's would have to be electric-powered.</p>
        <p>The changes needed to make a Federal-certifed car meet LEV standards are invisible to the customer. ''Except for the price, there doesn't seem to be much difference,'' said Pete Iwanowicz, a clean air specialist in Albany with the Resource Renewal Institute, a nonprofit environmental group. Auto industry executives point out, though, that multiplied by millions of car sales, the aggregate expense would be billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>One tool is to add to the catalytic converter a little more palladium, rhodium and platinum, metals called ''catalysts'' that foster chemical reactions without being consumed themselves. This would increase the efficiency with which the converter takes carbon monoxide, unburned hydrocarbons and nitrogen oxides and turns them into carbon dioxide, water and nitrogen. The added quantities are so small that the added cost is well under $100.</p>
        <p>Another approach is to build a catalytic converter with slightly more surface area. These converters are typically about the size of a one-pound coffee can, but they have several square feet of surface area because the inside is crammed with a honeycomb.</p>
        <p>By making the walls of the honeycomb thinner, more chambers can be squeezed in. And if the walls are thinner, the converter heats up more quickly to the operating temperature.</p>
        <p>It is a big challenge to get the converter to operating temperature as quickly as possible. Cold starts are the source of most hydrocarbons, which are unburned fuel, and carbon monoxide, which is partly burned fuel. Unless the catalyst comes up to operating temperature quickly, ''you'll fail the test in the first few seconds, and the rest of it is a waste of time,'' said Kelly M. Brown, director of the vehicle environmental engineering program of the Ford Motor Company.</p>
        <p>California officials said they originally thought that car makers would need electrically heated catalysts to meet the low-emission standards. But the manufacturers have found simpler, cheaper ways.</p>
        <p>Some have moved the converter closer to the engine. This is a balancing act, because the converter needs to reach 1,500 to 1,600 degrees Fahrenheit to work well, but at 1,800 or 1,900 degrees it will be damaged. Moving it too close to the exhaust manifold increases the chance that it will be destroyed someday, perhaps when accelerating up a steep grade or while towing.</p>
        <p>So, on some cars, engineers have built a small, heat-resistant converter that is installed close to the engine for quick warm ups, leaving a larger converter farther down the exhaust path.</p>
        <p>Sam Leonard, an emissions expert at General Motors, said his company was considering another approach: attaching an air blower to the exhaust system. The air-fuel mixture is very rich on start-up -- too rich for the catalyst to handle -- but adding air would allow the hydrocarbons and carbon monoxide to burn up completely inside the catalyst. In the 1970's, some of the earliest cars with catalytic converters used that method, until catalyst technology improved enough to allow cars to meet Federal standards without the devices.</p>
        <p>Another approach is to make the exhaust cleaner before it reaches the catalyst. With computer-controlled fuel injection, most cars are very good at staying at the perfect ratio of fuel and air for full combustion -- called stoichiometric -- when engine speed is constant. But to burn cleanly, the ratio must stay within 1 percent of stoichiometric, and most cars cannot do that as the engine speed changes rapidly; they go through brief periods of lean air, which causes engine hesitation, hotter combustion and production of nitrogen oxides, or rich periods, which hurt fuel economy and result in carbon monoxide and unburned hydrocarbons. Solutions include using more and better exhaust gas sensors, individual fuel-air controls for each cylinder, and fuel injectors that are assisted by air pumps, to atomize the fuel better.</p>
        <p>All these changes come down mostly to money. In 1996, California estimated that the cost to take a Federal car to transitional LEV standards was $72; to the LEV level, $120, and to ULEV status, $145.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leonard of General Motors said that $72 was about right for the transitional level; to reach LEV, he said, was an additional $100 to $200, and to reach ULEV, from $100 to $1,500 above that, depending on whether it was a small, four-cylinder car, which would require few changes, or an eight-cylinder vehicle that would have to be converted to natural gas or some other cleaner fuel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
