<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Garden for Children Opening in the Bronx</title>
    <meta content="BOTAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Botanical Garden</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Singer, Penny</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E3DF173FF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="1325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Garden for Children Opening in the Bronx</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Singer, Penny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Everett Children's Adventure Garden is set to open on May 2 at New York Botanical Garden in Bronx; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT'S a herbarium? Why are plants green? What lives in a pond?  Many mysteries of the plant kingdom will be revealed when the Everett Children's Adventure Garden opens on May 2 at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''It's a first, the only indoor-outdoor museum of plant science for children and families in the country,'' John E. Rorer, executive vice president of the Botanical Garden, said. ''It has been built on a 12-acre site, which includes 8 acres of exploration activities for children. Designed as a kid's wonderland, it has such things as boulder mazes, 40 hands-on nature-discovery activities, trails, a picnic area, topiaries, galleries, plazas and more.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT'S a herbarium? Why are plants green? What lives in a pond?  Many mysteries of the plant kingdom will be revealed when the Everett Children's Adventure Garden opens on May 2 at the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>''It's a first, the only indoor-outdoor museum of plant science for children and families in the country,'' John E. Rorer, executive vice president of the Botanical Garden, said. ''It has been built on a 12-acre site, which includes 8 acres of exploration activities for children. Designed as a kid's wonderland, it has such things as boulder mazes, 40 hands-on nature-discovery activities, trails, a picnic area, topiaries, galleries, plazas and more.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Rorer joined the staff of the Botanical Garden in 1989, his most pressing task was to develop the garden's financial goals, strategies and policies.</p>
        <p>''The first order of the day was to put the garden on a businesslike basis,'' he said. ''Financial issues were dealt with immediately, and by 1990, we were ready to start working on an overall strategic plan for the future of the garden.''</p>
        <p>The result was a 7-year, $200 million master plan, begun in 1993, resulting in a renaissance in every part of the garden.</p>
        <p>''The concept and construction of the Everett Children's Adventure Garden was one of the major projects included in the master plan,'' said Mr. Rorer, who commutes from his home in New Rochelle. ''We felt that kids needed more than the garden was giving them. My daughter Kate, who was 7 when I first took her with me to the garden, summed up the experience by remarking. 'This is not a place for kids.' And kids are a huge market.</p>
        <p>''In the New York City area alone, 1.4 million households have children ages 5 to 13. And although the entire garden with its 40 acres of original forest in the middle of the Bronx is an amazing resource, we still didn't have enough activities geared to kids and families. Today's kids want experiences that are interactive and fun. And that's what we asked our team of designers to come up with:  hands-on activities, imaginative exhibits and fanciful designs that would make the Adventure Garden both an inviting place to play and a structured learning environment.''</p>
        <p>The Everett Children's Adventure Garden, endowed at a cost of $9 million, is the centerpiece of the $15 million Children's Adventure Project at the Garden, Mr. Rorer said, adding: ''It responds to a need to improve general science education for children and integrates environmental education into the school curriculum. Our programming was developed to meet the requirements of the New York State science curriculum for kindergarten through grade 6.''</p>
        <p>It may be educational, but it will certainly be fun. Once children pass through the archway of the Adventure Garden they find themselves on a winding path, which leads to a free-form Boulder Maze, with winding trails and to Beth's Maze, a geometric labyrinth of shrubs. From there, the path swings around to the first of the galleries, the Sun, Dirt and Water Gallery, donated by the Vincent Astor Foundation.</p>
        <p>''Here is the place where kids will be able to find the answer to the question: 'Why are plants green?' ''  Mr. Rorer said, adding that children will learn how plants use sunlight, water and carbon dioxide to make their own food. ''A set of oversize test  tubes, a huge rhubarb leaf with a see-through stem, Sun Power Boxes, and a hands-on lean Green Food machine have been installed to make the learning process fun,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Next, on the tour, is the William and Lynda Steer Discovery Center, where two discovery rooms, equipped with laboratory specimens and research tools, allow children to perform experiments, use microscopes on a diverse number of plants and press and mount their own plant specimens with help provided.</p>
        <p>Two giant caterpillar topiaries and a monarch butterfly mark the way to the Heckscher Foundation for Children's Wonder Gallery. ''Here, kids can marvel at the amazing diversity of plants,'' Mr. Rorer said. ''While  looking for plants, they'll go under a vine-covered arch, over a tiny bridge, around a mini pond and begin to see how the basic parts of plants can take an amazing variety of forms.''</p>
        <p>The path  winds through flowers and grasses of the Arthur Hays and Iphigene Ochs Sulzberger Meadow Gallery, where children can pollinate giant flowers, see flowers through the eyes of a bee and disperse seeds.</p>
        <p>Next and last is the Con Edison Pond Gallery. At the Pond Cafe, children can play at being animals that live in and around a pond, searching for a tasty lunch. Pond dipping lets the children examine water samples to see what lives in the water. They can also assemble a giant bird's nest, using plant parts, straw and other plant materials.</p>
        <p>''In a city where nature may not be obvious to a child's eyes, our new indoor-outdoor wonderland will put the marvels of our environment at children's fingertips and under their fingernails,'' Gregory Long, president of the Botanical Garden, said. ''Kids can use their physical energy and their imagination to discover why it's exciting to explore the natural world. We hope our garden will serve as a model for other communities.''</p>
        <p>Raising money for the Adventure Garden was relatively easy, Mr. Rorer said. ''Donors were genuinely interested and loved the idea of getting children excited about science  and the natural world,'' he said. ''Many became actively involved in the planning. The garden has been made possible by the leadership and generosity of Edith and Henry Everett, who have made a multimillion-dollar commitment. The Everetts are interested in causes that benefit children.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Everett said the education of young children has been ''a primary philanthropic passion of ours.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''And what better way to fulfill that passion than through a beautiful, entertaining, enlightening garden, situated in one of the most glorious settings in any city of the world, the New York Botanical Garden?''</p>
        <p>The new botanical adventure land has won approval from the most demanding of critics, four sisters, 6 to 12. They are the daughters of  Benny Bulfamante, a principal in Mario Bulfamante &amp; Sons, landscape contractors in New Rochelle. The Bulfamantes started construction of the Adventure Garden last June. ''We've had 8 to 10 men working steadily on the project,'' Mr. Bulfamante said. ''It's a big job, and we were very happy to get it. We've worked for the botanical garden since 1990, but this has been our biggest project for them. We've been lucky in the weather, but still it has taken us seven days a week from 8 to 5 to get the place ready for opening day.''</p>
        <p>One of the most difficult parts of the job, Mr. Bulfamante said, was building the boulder maze. ''Placing those tremendous rocks just so took some doing,'' he said. ''But it's a favorite with my girls. I brought them with me often, and they watched the place take shape, which was nothing, when we started, but rubble. All the girls love the Adventure Garden, and they're asking their teachers to make it a school trip.''</p>
        <p>Admission to the Everett Children's Adventure Garden is $2 and $1 for children 3 to 5. Admission to the grounds is extra. A snack bar and  areas for picnics and birthday parties are available.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
