<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Just How Green Can a Middle School Get?</title>
    <meta content="08DONA$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Natural World" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19990113T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portland (Ore)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donohue, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon/Portland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oregon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reading and Writing Skills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DA1F3BF93BA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1273" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Just How Green Can a Middle School Get?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL DONAHUE</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Ore.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>just how green can a middle school get**Bill Donohue article on environmental-based education, such as the kind practiced at Environmental Middle School in Portland, Ore, where study of environmental problems is integrated into all lessons; students at Environmental, a public magnet school whose students come from neighborhoods throughout the city, score above average on writing and math tests; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MATH class begins as a stocky boy in a ski parka chucks a stick into the muddy, cool water of Johnson Creek. The stick bobbles over rapids and collides with a waterborne leaf.</p>
        <p>On the grassy bank, sixth, seventh and eighth graders from the Environmental Middle School watch raptly, clipboards in hand. ''Ten seconds,'' one yells the instant the stick has traveled 50 feet. The students calculate stream velocity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MATH class begins as a stocky boy in a ski parka chucks a stick into the muddy, cool water of Johnson Creek. The stick bobbles over rapids and collides with a waterborne leaf.</p>
        <p>On the grassy bank, sixth, seventh and eighth graders from the Environmental Middle School watch raptly, clipboards in hand. ''Ten seconds,'' one yells the instant the stick has traveled 50 feet. The students calculate stream velocity.</p>
        <p>They measure Johnson Creek's dissolved oxygen content, and their familiarity with this twisting brown current -- this workaday stream that snakes past oil lube shops and low-rent apartments -- grows deeper.</p>
        <p>With John Richter, their teacher, the eighth graders at Environmental, a public magnet school, have been visiting Johnson Creek regularly for three years. They have assiduously drawn pictures of the leaves of the cottonwoods on the shoreline, planted willows and taken notes on resident creatures, including squirrels and a bird that one student said ''sounds like a cat choking.''</p>
        <p>Inevitably, lessons have become political.</p>
        <p>Johnson Creek is inhabited by a species of salmon, the steelhead, that the National Marine Fisheries Service regards as endangered in many streams in the Northwest. The Service is asking citizens to help shape a steelhead recovery plan, which will likely curtail logging and development beside the stream, and Mr. Richter wants his students to speak out. Last month, he took three of them to a conference about the steelhead. ''They weren't there to observe,'' he stresses. ''They were there to participate.''</p>
        <p>It was not the first time Mr. Richter had veered into real controversies. In 1996, he took 15 students to a protest. They spent 90 minutes picketing a United States Forest Service office; they bore signs that begged ''Stop Clear-cutting,'' and they incited outrage. So many loggers wrote to Environmental that the school began keeping what it calls a ''hate file.'' Portland's daily newspaper, The Oregonian, editorialized against the protest, and one letter to the editor called the protest a ''mass tantrum.''</p>
        <p>The concept of environmental education was being called into question again. Increasingly, critics are saying that environmental education is really propaganda aimed, in the words of a political scientist, Michael Sanera, at ''convincing kids that the sky is falling.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Sanera, who is a senior fellow at the Center for the New West in Denver, wrote ''Facts Not Fear,'' which argued that acid rain, water pollution and deforestation are ''trendy'' myths promoted by a mass media hungry for sensation. He attacked textbooks like the one that suggested that when global warming occurred, New York City would be underwater.</p>
        <p>BUT the sound-bite debate over environmental education is misguided. Environmental education might once have been about simple proselytizing -- about, say, venting outrage at Dow Chemical on Earth Day. But it has become a far broader -- and less pointed -- endeavor.</p>
        <p>The movement's biggest grantor, the Pew Charitable Trust, which gives away $200 million annually, recently embraced ''using the environment as an integrating context for learning.'' It hasn't financed Environmental, but it has begun championing schools that, like Environmental, are green at the core and apt to take a multidisciplinary approach to ecological studies.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, about 100 public schools practice environmental-based education. Three-year-old Environmental may be the most nontraditional. Each morning at the school starts with Mr. Richter strumming his guitar as the 180 students sing songs like ''Blowing in the Wind.'' Students call teachers by their first names, and the office is, according to Environmental's founder and coordinator Sarah Taylor, ''modeled after a kitchen in a big family's home.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Taylor sits at a classroom-style table, sipping herbal tea as students drop by for math help or gardening instructions. She is 50, a child of the 1960's who discovered as a teen-ager that she learned best in nature. ''Often,'' she said, ''I'd stay home from school and sit by the creek and write or daydream and draw. This school was born out of that experience.''</p>
        <p>Lessons are tied to annual themes. Two years ago, the focus was forests; last year, mountains. Now, Environmental students are studying rivers. They are doing math problems about their home water use and compiling a poetry anthology called ''A River of Words.'' Nearly every class includes some contemplation of moving water, but no class, Ms. Taylor insists, is designed to mint protesters. ''John went to that protest,'' she said, ''because the kids wanted to, and we won't go to a protest again. I don't think you change anything with one-time protests. You have to eliminate the cause of environmental problems, which is greed.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Sanera dismisses such reasoning as ''ignorant of the economic system.'' (He argues, ''Richer is cleaner and healthier. Just look at pollution in developing countries.'') He's skeptical, too, of a recent morning assembly at which Ms. Taylor helped students compile a ''Bill of Rights'' for rivers. One sixth grader said that rivers have a right not to be dammed.</p>
        <p>''They're probably not being taught to think critically,'' Dr. Sanera charged. ''Did anyone point out that the power at their school is generated by dams' turbines?''</p>
        <p>No one did, but standardized tests suggest that Environmental is academically effective. Last spring, when Portland's eighth graders were tested on writing and math, Environmental students, who come from neighborhoods throughout the city, scored above average in all 10 categories tested.</p>
        <p>''They're doing well,'' Mr. Richter speculates, ''because they're happy in their learning environment.'' Science class is about to begin, and today Mr. Richter's students will ponder an imaginary river -- and an imaginary downpour.</p>
        <p>''Folks,'' Mr. Richter announces, gesturing toward an elaborate diorama on the back wall, ''there's been a tremendous rain storm over our river here.'' The students scoot their chairs toward Mr. Richter, 47, a gentle outdoorsy fellow, a sort of Mr. Rogers in fleece. Each student is role-playing a Northwest animal this year, and Mr. Richter wants to know how the ''animals'' are enduring the storm.</p>
        <p>''I'm a salmon,'' one boy says, ''and I wouldn't have a place to lay my eggs. Salmon need clean water for that and, in the storm, the river would be full of silt.''</p>
        <p>Another child says: ''I'm a great horned owl, and I'd benefit because the rains would wash all the little animals, my prey, out of their holes.''</p>
        <p>Gradually, a lesson emerges: Nature is not a fragile victim; it is instead a sturdy web, an intricate system in which death for one animal can mean lunch for another. Mr. Richter does not spell this out. Rather, he guides the students toward it. The room is aswarm with children stabbing their hands desperately into the air, and he spends 40 minutes directing the verbal traffic. Then the class ends and the students stream out to the gym, for murderball.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to get past good guy versus bad guy,'' the teacher says in the ensuing silence. ''The kids usually view issues as environmentalists, but that's the way kids are. They aren't directly using resources like lumber yet. But they will be, and we want them to ask, 'Am I being respectful of the environment? Is there any way to do this that pollutes less?' If those questions are asked, I think it's a great thing.''</p>
        <p>Bill Donahue has written for The New York Times Magazine and The New Yorker.</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 13, 1999, Wednesday  A picture caption on Dec. 8 in The Natural World, a special section, with an article about environmental education, misidentified a student shown on a field trip to Johnson Creek in Portland, Ore. He was Alex Thomson, not Jared Blackwell. A teacher mentioned the error to the writer about two weeks ago, but word was delayed in reaching the editors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 13, 1999, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption on Dec. 8 in The Natural World, a special section, with an article about environmental education, misidentified a student shown on a field trip to Johnson Creek in Portland, Ore. He was Alex Thomson, not Jared Blackwell. A teacher mentioned the error to the writer about two weeks ago, but word was delayed in reaching the editors.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bill Donahue has written for The New York Times Magazine and The New Yorker.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
