<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="09FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04EED91F30F93AA35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Former Pakistan Leader Linked With Corruption  Benazir Bhutto, the former Prime Minister of Pakistan who has spoken out against avaricious politicians, and her husband, Asif Ali Zardari, have been linked to more than $100 million in foreign bank accounts and properties as part of a widening corruption inquiry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Former Pakistan Leader Linked With Corruption  Benazir Bhutto, the former Prime Minister of Pakistan who has spoken out against avaricious politicians, and her husband, Asif Ali Zardari, have been linked to more than $100 million in foreign bank accounts and properties as part of a widening corruption inquiry.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Algerian Conflict Intensifies  As many as 1,000 people have been killed by Islamic guerrillas as the onset of Ramadan brought its annual intensification of the Algerian conflict. Well-planned attacks against singers, writers and other representatives of Western culture have given way to mass murders of ordinary people. The death toll has already eclipsed that of Ramadan last year, when an estimated 400 were slain.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mediator Presses Israel  Dennis Ross, the American mediator for the Middle East, continued to search for a new formula to bridge the gap between Israeli and Palestinian politicians. American officials have insisted that Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel make a withdrawal of more than 10 percent of the West Bank. Mr. Netanyahu evidently would do this only if the Palestinians agreed to forgo a third withdrawal, a notion they have rejected.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Mexican Judge Criticized  Mexico City's District Attorney called on the Judiciary Council to discipline Judge Maria Claudia Campuzano for releasing five men who had confessed to kidnapping and killing an American businessman, Peter Zarate, a New York real estate executive. The judge had ordered their release after finding multiple contradictions in their confessions, and concluded that they were scapegoats who had been arrested and forced to confess by the police. The judge's order provoked considerable anger in a city panicked by a wave of kidnappings, killings and armed robberies and the case has become the latest symbol of Mexico's crippled criminal justice system.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Kenya Disease Is Not Ebola  Medical researchers said that a disease that has killed 300 people in Kenya is not the deadly Ebola virus as doctors had feared, but Rift Valley Fever. The virus, which attacks both livestock and humans, has swept through dozens of remote villages, and has symptoms similar to those of the Ebola virus. World Health Organization officials said some of the deaths may have been caused by other diseases triggered by massive flooding in the area.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Poland Improves Ties to Church  Poland's new parliament, dominated by center-right parties, ratified a treaty with the Vatican that had been stalled for years by the previous leftist legislature. The concordat governs relations between the state and the Roman Catholic Church, to which about 90 percent of the population at least nominally belong. The new government said the treaty posed no danger of imposing church influence on daily life.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-17</p>
        <p>Judge Orders Mental Exam For Unabom Suspect  After apparently trying to hang himself on the eve of this trial, Theodore J. Kaczynski asked to be allowed to represent himself. His request, the latest rebellion against his lawyers' plan to cast him as mentally ill, led the trial judge to order an examination into whether he is competent to stand trial.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Universe Expanding Steadily  Astronomers, by examining the distant light from stars that exploded before the Sun was born, have determined that the universe has apparently been expanding at a slow, steady rate since the beginning and is destined to expand forever.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Haitians Still Face Deportation  The Government's immigration lawyers and judges are continuing to pursue deportation cases against Haitian immigrants, despite a Presidential order issued two weeks ago aimed at exempting up to 20,000 Haitians from strict new deportation rules for at least a year.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Earth Is Warmer Than Ever  The vast pool of warm Pacific water called El Nino, coming on top of an underlying global warming trend, boosted the earth's average surface temperature in 1997 to the highest levels ever recorded, Government scientists reported.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Substance Abuse a Path to Jail  Illegal drugs and alcohol helped lead to the imprisonment of 4 out of 5 inmates in the nation's prisons and jails, a study has found.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Cisneros Pleads Not Guilty  Henry G. Cisneros, President Clinton's first Housing Secretary, pleaded not guilty to 18 felony counts of conspiracy, false statements and obstruction of justice at Federal court in Washington. The charges stem from more than $250,000 in payments that Independent Counsel David M. Barrett said Mr. Cisneros gave to a former mistress to buy her silence about their relationship.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-7</p>
        <p>Yousef Sentenced to Life For Trade Center Bombing  Ramzi Ahmed Yousef, the man who masterminded the World Trade Center bombing five years ago, was sentenced to spend life plus 240 years in prison.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Clinton Asked to Share Funds  Judith Hope, the chairwoman of the New York Democratic Party, asserted that President Clinton's frequent fund-raising trips to New York were undermining her efforts to prepare her party for a critical election year, and asked that national Democrats either begin sharing the bounties of Mr. Clinton's trips or stay out of the state this year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>NEEDIEST CASES</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Kwan Receives Perfect Marks  Seven of the nine judges at the U.S. national skating championship rated Michelle Kwan's presentation on her short program as perfect. No American woman had ever received one perfect mark of six at the national championships. Tara Lipinski, the 15-year-old defending champion, fell to fourth place at the competition, which concludes this weekend.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Banned Hormone Suspected  Luggage belonging to a Chinese swimmer was seized by Australian custom officials who said it contained a substance labeled as human growth hormone. If the label is correct, the incident would reinforce the widely held belief that China's female swimmers have been using banned bodybuilding drugs.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7-8</p>
        <p>Jack F. Grimm  A West Texas wildcatter who found his share of oil but had less luck searching for Sasquatch in the Pacific Northwest, the Abominable Snowman in Nepal and the Loch Ness Monster, he was 72.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-18</p>
        <p>Fears Shake Indonesia  Fears of economic collapse and political turmoil shook Indonesia, with the currency and stock market suffering their worst one-day losses and with a wave of panic buying that emptied grocery shelves. The panic was sparked by worries that the International Monetary Fund might cut off its $40 billion assistance package following the unveiling of a new Indonesian budget this week that failed to address many of the country's urgent needs.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>December Sales Were Strong  American retailers, in a remarkable turnaround from a weak season, reported strong December sales, aided in huge part by shopping that occurred after Christmas. The Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company same-store sales index reported that retail sales were up 4.4 percent in December, compared with a meager 2.9 percent gain in December 1996.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-32; E33-46</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A18-19</p>
        <p>Editorials: Freezing the Schiele paintings; Algeria's unending civil war; the bad seed; two promising picks in Mexico.</p>
        <p>Column: Russell Baker.</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E46</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>C7</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
