<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Humanoids Make Scientists Paranoids</title>
    <meta content="15JAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="987731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Prey (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6D91139F936A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="466" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Humanoids Make Scientists Paranoids</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews Prey, ABC-TV's science-fiction series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the news according to ''Prey,'' there is one small ecological detail that slipped by the global warming conference in Kyoto, Japan, last month. Warming has caused a new species of beings to evolve. They look human, but their brains work faster than the fastest computers. And, quite inconveniently, most are serial killers determined to wipe out humankind and become the dominant species. That is how this surprisingly lively new series came by its droll promotional slogan, ''You've just been bumped down the food chain.''</p>
        <p>To make the game more interesting, the only way to distinguish the new species from humans is by a DNA test. There you have a minor legacy of the O. J. Simpson trial: DNA testing as a pop culture accessory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the news according to ''Prey,'' there is one small ecological detail that slipped by the global warming conference in Kyoto, Japan, last month. Warming has caused a new species of beings to evolve. They look human, but their brains work faster than the fastest computers. And, quite inconveniently, most are serial killers determined to wipe out humankind and become the dominant species. That is how this surprisingly lively new series came by its droll promotional slogan, ''You've just been bumped down the food chain.''</p>
        <p>To make the game more interesting, the only way to distinguish the new species from humans is by a DNA test. There you have a minor legacy of the O. J. Simpson trial: DNA testing as a pop culture accessory.</p>
        <p>Silly at its core and straight-faced in its delivery, ''Prey'' is also effective as a thriller and a sly science-fiction story. Though it is reminiscent of the movie ''Species'' in its racing, up-against-them action, the show's real strength is its creepy ''X-Files'' paranoia. Anyone who looks human, after all, could be out to kill you.</p>
        <p>The heroine is a young bio-anthropologist named Sloan Parker (Debra Messing) who makes an unlikely discovery while testing the DNA of a convicted murderer. ''Oh, my God, he's not human,'' she says to the computer screen, and soon to her loyal colleague, Dr. Ed Tate (Vincent Ventresca). This discovery, of course, puts her in danger. From then on, in the classical tradition of smart-but-stupid suspense heroines, Sloan tends to walk into dark, scary places alone. But she is befriended by a kindly nonhuman, Tom Daniels (Adam Storke), who sometimes comes out of the shadows to save her.</p>
        <p>''Prey'' tosses in every element the genre can bear. The F.B.I. knows more than it's telling. A police detective (Frankie R. Faison) believes Sloan's story. The weak link is the new head of Sloan's lab (Larry Drake), played so ominously he would appear to have a nonhuman connection even if Sloan hadn't discovered a new life form.</p>
        <p>It is easier for a story like this to work once than to sustain its surprise, so there's no telling where ''Prey'' will go. If it develops any humor, Sloan might turn her thoughts to practical matters. Saving humanity is fine in the long run, but for now shouldn't she be working on a portable DNA test that will let you enter a cocktail party and avoid making small talk with a killer nonhuman?</p>
        <p>PREY  ABC, tonight at 8</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
