<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ice Storm Takes Its Toll on Vermont's Maple Syrup Industry</title>
    <meta content="24MAPL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maple Syrup and Sugar</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maple Trees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Vermont</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Vermont</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E6DA173EF937A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ice Storm Takes Its Toll on Vermont's Maple Syrup Industry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>January ice storm in New England destroys countless sugar maple trees, injuring Vermont's maple syrup industry; is expected to reduce maple syrup production in Vermont alone by 10 percent; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR most of the tens of thousands of Canadians and New Englanders left without power after last month's crippling ice storm, life has nearly returned to normal. But for sweet-tooths around the world addicted to the unique flavor of maple syrup and ''Indian sugar,'' the storm is expected to raise the cost of maintaining their expensive habit.</p>
        <p>Few agricultural products are more sensitive to the vagaries of nature than maple syrup, and the destruction of countless sugar maple trees by the ice storm is expected to reduce production in Vermont alone by about 10 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR most of the tens of thousands of Canadians and New Englanders left without power after last month's crippling ice storm, life has nearly returned to normal. But for sweet-tooths around the world addicted to the unique flavor of maple syrup and ''Indian sugar,'' the storm is expected to raise the cost of maintaining their expensive habit.</p>
        <p>Few agricultural products are more sensitive to the vagaries of nature than maple syrup, and the destruction of countless sugar maple trees by the ice storm is expected to reduce production in Vermont alone by about 10 percent.</p>
        <p>From Brattleboro to Burlington, Vermonters owning ''sugar bushes'' -- stands of sugar maple trees -- are drilling tap holes and waiting for the clear white sap to drip from the wounds into collecting buckets. In hundreds of ''sugar houses'' across the Northeast, maple harvesters will soon begin boiling down the sap to about one-fiftieth of its starting volume to produce the delectable syrup.</p>
        <p>But maple trees throughout the region suffered a staggering beating during the freakish January storm, which stripped trees of branches, uprooting and killing many trees outright.</p>
        <p>Bruce Martell of the Vermont Department of Agriculture, who supervises the state's maple inspection program, estimates that the reduction in syrup production caused by the storm will cause a corresponding increase in price of about 10 percent. (The price of one gallon of Vermont syrup is ordinarily about $30.)</p>
        <p>The state's 1997 syrup output, 395,000 gallons, already represented a decline from 550,000 gallons in 1996, and the total production in the United States was down 17 percent.</p>
        <p>The Vermont production decline will have especially widespread effects because Vermont produces more syrup than any other state; it accounts for nearly one-third of the United States' production. The destruction of maple trees elsewhere was also widespread, however; New York State, which normally produces 21 percent of the national total, will suffer a 45 percent production decline because of the storm, agricultural experts predict.</p>
        <p>Canada, the world's leading maple syrup and sugar producer, suffered losses even greater than those of New England.</p>
        <p>''Sugaring'' is a chancy business, dependent partly on outguessing the weather. If a maple harvester taps a tree too early in the late-winter season the tap hole will quickly dry up and heal, shutting off the flow of sap from the tree's xylem -- its equivalent of upward-flowing blood vessels. Ideally, there should be a hard freeze every night and days with temperatures above freezing for good tapping.</p>
        <p>Harvesters must be careful to avoid over-tapping trees. In an average year a harvester drills two or three three-inch-deep tap holes in a tree, and when there are too many holes the tree dies, just as if it had been ''girdled'' -- circled by a continuous cut that severs its circulatory system.</p>
        <p>Maple growers are also keeping an eye on the effects of global warming, Mr. Martell said. When spring arrives too early the sap flows too short a time for a good harvest. If global warming trends continue, botanists said, the production of maple syrup will shift farther to the north, giving Canada an even larger share. Depending on seasonal variations, Canada generally produces between three and five times as much syrup as the United States.</p>
        <p>Timothy Wilmot, a maple expert at the University of Vermont's Proctor Maple Research Center, said that insect infestation periodically interrupts good syrup production. During the 1988-89 season, he said, an invasion of thrips -- four-winged insects of the order Thysanoptera -- descended on New England, severely damaging maple buds, defoliating trees and throttling sap production.</p>
        <p>American Indians taught European settlers the trick of extracting sugar from maple trees, and methods have not changed much in three centuries.</p>
        <p>In a modern innovation, some syrup manufacturers use reverse osmosis to remove most of the water in raw sap before boiling it down. In reverse osmosis, the sap is forced under high pressure through tubes lined with a special membrane that allows water to flow through but blocks molecules of sugar. The sugar is thereby concentrated on the high-pressure side of the membrane.</p>
        <p>Most producers, however, simply  boil the sap down until the sugar concentration reaches 66.5 percent. The syrup is then filtered and bottled. To make the pure maple ''sugar cake'' molded into various shapes and sold as gourmet candy, the syrup is further heated to 240 degrees Fahrenheit, cooled with stirring to about 210 degrees, and poured into candy molds. Increasing the temperature of syrup to 250 degrees reduces it to the dry powder known as Indian sugar, used in desserts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
