<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hurricane Rumbles Ashore on Anxious Cape Fear</title>
    <meta content="27STOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1042055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricane Bonnie</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cape Fear River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Carolina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sack, Kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DA133CF934A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hurricane Rumbles Ashore on Anxious Cape Fear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEVIN SACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sack, Kevin</byline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, N.C., Aug. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hurricane Bonnie comes ashore near mouth of Cape Fear River in North Carolina, bringing winds of up to 115 miles per hour to region that is still recovering from back-to-back hurricanes in summer of 1996; there are no reports of deaths or serious injuries from category 3 hurricane, but state officials and weather forecasters say worst could be ahead as slow-moving storm continues to move up North Carolina coast; diagram; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A vast, plodding Hurricane Bonnie rumbled ashore near the mouth of the Cape Fear River this afternoon, bringing whipping winds and horizontal squalls through a region that was still recovering, both physically and emotionally, from back-to-back hurricanes in the summer of 1996.</p>
        <p>As midnight approached, there were no reports of deaths or serious injuries in the region from the category 3 hurricane, and its maximum sustained winds had declined to 105 miles an hour from 115 m.p.h. But state officials and weather forecasters worried that the worst could be ahead as the slow-moving storm, with hurricane-force winds extending 115 miles from its eye, continued its northerly stroll up the North Carolina coast tonight and on Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A vast, plodding Hurricane Bonnie rumbled ashore near the mouth of the Cape Fear River this afternoon, bringing whipping winds and horizontal squalls through a region that was still recovering, both physically and emotionally, from back-to-back hurricanes in the summer of 1996.</p>
        <p>As midnight approached, there were no reports of deaths or serious injuries in the region from the category 3 hurricane, and its maximum sustained winds had declined to 105 miles an hour from 115 m.p.h. But state officials and weather forecasters worried that the worst could be ahead as the slow-moving storm, with hurricane-force winds extending 115 miles from its eye, continued its northerly stroll up the North Carolina coast tonight and on Thursday.</p>
        <p>A particular concern for residents of the Outer Banks, a narrow and ecologically fragile chain of barrier islands, was that the hurricane would move straight up Pamlico Sound, creating surging flood waters that could cut new inlets and submerge the islands' single highway.</p>
        <p>Forecasters predicted that damage assessments of the Outer Banks, and of much of the rest of the North Carolina coast, would not be possible until well into Thursday.</p>
        <p>As the storm finally made land after two days of anxious expectation, residents here seemed fatalistic about the weather currents and terrible luck that have brought three hurricanes to their quaint, well-mannered city in only two years. In 1996, a mild hurricane named Bertha struck in July, only to be followed two months later by a devastating category 3 storm named Fran. That hurricane resulted in 24 deaths in North Carolina, and 34 total, and caused an estimated $6 billion in property damage, including hundreds of downed trees in Wilmington.</p>
        <p>The impact of that storm was symbolized by the destruction of the 197-foot-tall steeple at the First Baptist Church, a local landmark that is still being rebuilt.</p>
        <p>''My first thought when we heard about this one was that it couldn't happen again, that you just can't have three in a row,'' said C. Bruce Williams 3d, a spokesman for the emergency management team in New Hanover County. ''I guess it's just one of those things.''</p>
        <p>Gary Green, a 37-year-old cook who was waiting out the storm at a shelter at M. C. S. Noble Middle School here, said he liked the area enough to put up with the enduring threat of wicked weather.</p>
        <p>''Where are you going to run on this planet?'' Mr. Green asked. ''If you go to the Midwest, you put up with tornadoes. You go to the West Coast and you put up with earthquakes. You choose your poison as best you can.''</p>
        <p>The National Hurricane Center in Miami said the hurricane's speed had gradually decreased throughout the day to 8 m.p.h. from nearly double that on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>''Bonnie will be persisting over eastern North Carolina for at least another day, creating a serious flood threat from rain,'' the forecasters said in their 5 P.M. advisory. ''Rainfall totals of 6 to 12 inches are possible. Totals could be much larger, possibly in excess of 15 or 20 inches if the forward speed of Bonnie decreases further.''</p>
        <p>Richard H. Moore, North Carolina's Secretary of Crime Control and Public Safety, said the storm could churn north toward the Virginia border until about 2 A.M. Friday. There could be two to three inches of rain an hour almost as far west as Raleigh, Mr. Moore said. Gale-force winds hit that city today and flash-flood warnings were issued.</p>
        <p>Max Mayfield, the deputy director of the National Hurricane Center, said the eye of the storm moved lethargically from Cape Fear this afternoon to a point just off Wrightsville Beach about 8 P.M. Mr. Mayfield said the hurricane was expected to move in a north-to-northeast direction. But he said the storm's slow speed made it difficult to predict whether it would hug the coast or take a more inland path.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, he said, the storm should move out to sea near the border of North Carolina and Virginia. A hurricane warning remained in effect tonight from Cape Romain, S.C., to the North Carolina-Virginia border, while a tropical storm warning was in effect from Chincoteague, Va., to Cape Henlopen, Del.</p>
        <p>More than half a million residents and tourists evacuated coastal areas of North Carolina and South Carolina on Tuesday and this morning, filling makeshift emergency shelters in schools and government buildings.</p>
        <p>Curfews were declared across the region and most bridges from the mainland to barrier islands were blocked by police cars. An estimated 97,500 households were without electricity along North Carolina's southern coast. In Supply, N.C., about 30 miles south of here, the hurricane's winds destroyed part of the roof at Brunswick Hospital, forcing officials to move 34 patients to another unit. Here in Wilmington, a gust blew out a 40-foot section of windows at New Hanover High School.</p>
        <p>On Bald Head Island, N.C., near the point of the hurricane's landfall, 47 people were stranded after missing the last ferry on Tuesday night and some took shelter in the island's lighthouse after breaking its lock.</p>
        <p>''It certainly would be better than even the more modern houses,'' said Andy James, a spokesman for the state's emergency management team. ''It's been there a long time and weathered a lot of storms.''</p>
        <p>The lighthouse squatters were not the only ones trapped by the storm. On North Topsail Beach this afternoon, two young men stranded on the island ran through the blinding rain when they saw a sheriff's car stopped on a road. The men, Mitch Fowler, of Burlington, N.C., and Dennis Poythress of Sneads Ferry, N.C., had spent the day trying to repair Mr. Fowler's car. But after getting the car going, it became buried in the sand and was eventually flooded by rising sea water, Mr. Poythress said.</p>
        <p>''I didn't care if it was the Pope,'' said a soaking Mr. Poythress as he crawled into the sheriff's car. ''I was ready to get off the island. I'm about to starve. I want some dry clothes and a dry cigarette.''</p>
        <p>Here in Wilmington, the storm splintered some of the oak trees that help give this city of 60,000 people its grace. Power lines all across town drooped from poles, and debris-littered streets became obstacle courses for the few drivers braving the roads. The almost-universal power failures forced the daily newspaper here, The Morning Star, to send its eight-page Thursday edition to Fayetteville to be printed.</p>
        <p>Although local officials warned that it was too early to make broad assessments, the damage to trees and property here seemed far milder than that caused two years ago by Hurricane Fran.</p>
        <p>''We've had some air views of damage and some scouting around by people,'' David Paynter, a spokesman here for the New Hanover County Emergency Management Agency, said late this afternoon. ''It seems the hurricane has not created that much damage, but we've got at least seven more hours before the main part of the storm leaves this area.''</p>
        <p>While thousands of people along the coast fled the storm, at least one family drove here deliberately to witness it. Doug Shales and his daughter, Sarah, 21, detoured to Wilmington while returning from Tampa to their home in Columbia, S.C.</p>
        <p>''I've wanted to experience a hurricane for a long time,'' Mr. Shales said. ''We just came on the spur of the moment. It's very special for us to happen to land somewhere where you're going to be in the eye.''</p>
        <p>The Shales spent the day watching the hurricane through the picture windows in their room at a Holiday Inn. Mr. Shales noted that his family spent time in 1993 in a historic blizzard atop Beech Mountain, N.C. ''We just kind of really enjoy weather extremes,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But many people here remained exasperated that they had been struck by another hurricane before finishing repairs from the last one.  Kathy J. Rackley, 39, a homemaker from Wilmington, said she still had trees in her yard that had been felled by Fran. ''It's kind of depressing,'' she said. ''You want to see everything done before something else comes along and blows it all down.''</p>
        <p>Jack Goodhue, who fled a barrier island to take shelter in a Wilmington motel, summed up the mood of many. ''What has happened here?'' he asked. ''Have they pinned a target on Wilmington?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
