<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="02FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981103T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1059001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA133FF931A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="2147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-14</p>
        <p>Hurricane Toll Exceeds 1,000 in Central America  Intense and widespread flooding in the wake of Hurricane Mitch has killed more than a thousand people in Central America, with hundreds more still missing, their villages buried under huge mudslides, relief and government officials said. A1</p>
        <p>Memorial for Yitzak Rabin  Israel held its first nationwide memorial for Yitzak Rabin, the former Prime Minister, three years after his assassination, signaling a concerted effort to transform him from a partisan hero into a figure of consensus -- a national symbol of peace. A12</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL A3-14</p>
        <p>Hurricane Toll Exceeds 1,000 in Central America  Intense and widespread flooding in the wake of Hurricane Mitch has killed more than a thousand people in Central America, with hundreds more still missing, their villages buried under huge mudslides, relief and government officials said. A1</p>
        <p>Memorial for Yitzak Rabin  Israel held its first nationwide memorial for Yitzak Rabin, the former Prime Minister, three years after his assassination, signaling a concerted effort to transform him from a partisan hero into a figure of consensus -- a national symbol of peace. A12</p>
        <p>Hamas Warns Arafat's Officers  The armed wing of the militant Islamic group Hamas warned for the first time that it may turn its guns on Yasir Arafat's police force. The Palestinian chief of police vowed that his men would respond, and he issued orders from his Gaza office to shoot at suspected assailants. The Hamas threat was a departure in its longstanding position that it would never be drawn into a civil war and signaled a deepening crisis for the Palestinian Authority. A12</p>
        <p>New U.S.-Israeli Pact  President Clinton and Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu signed an agreement that officials in both countries described as a significant intensification of the American commitment to safeguard Israel's security in a post-Soviet world. A13</p>
        <p>U.S. Demands Iraqi Compliance  The Clinton Administration said it would consider military strikes against Iraq if President Saddam Hussein did not back down from his decision to halt all cooperation with United Nations weapons inspectors. President Clinton said Iraq's move clearly violated United Nations Security Council resolutions. A12</p>
        <p>Treaty Faces Tough Battle  International negotiators will resume talks today in Buenos Aires over details in the treaty to fight global warming, but with their expectations sharply lowered. Little progress has been made since the Kyoto Protocol was approved last year, and it appears unlikely that an agreement on the details will be reached in time for the United States Senate to vote on ratification before the elections in 2000. A6</p>
        <p>Distress in South Korea  Growing numbers of ''economic orphans,'' though still very rare, are just one symptom of the psychological distress tearing at families as South Korea's economy descends in a tailspin. A14</p>
        <p>Adams Seeks I.R.A. Restraint  Gerry Adams, the president of Sinn Fein, the political wing of the Irish Republican Army, said he would appeal to the overwhelmingly Roman Catholic guerrilla organization not to retaliate for the killing, apparently by Protestants, of a Catholic man in Belfast on Saturday. A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL A16-23</p>
        <p>Clinton Leads a Drive To Galvanize Black Voters  President Clinton invoked Speaker Newt Gingrich, the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and Rosa Parks in an impassioned plea that was part of a drive by Democrats to spur turnout by black voters in the election on Tuesday. Mr. Clinton appeared at a predominantly black church in Baltimore in his final barnstorming trip of the campaign year. A1</p>
        <p>In scores of tight House and Senate races across the country, campaign workers are applying the personal touch and powers of persuasion to rally supporters. In a non-Presidential election year like this, with the economy humming and no national issues stirring passions, only committed voters -- less than 4 in 10 of those eligible -- are expected to vote on Tuesday. A20</p>
        <p>Voters across the nation this week face measures that would allow direct citizen lawmaking through a process generally known as ''initiative and referendum,'' with the battles around some of them so intense that they have generated at least as much attention as Congressional races. A22</p>
        <p>Democratic Governors in the 14-state interior West risk falling in status from endangered to nearly extinct. In the three states with Democratic Governors -- Colorado, Nebraska and Nevada -- Republican candidates approach the elections with leads in opinion polls. A22</p>
        <p>Glenn Talks of Faith  Senator John Glenn said his return to space aboard the shuttle Discovery has strengthened his religious faith and illustrates the benefits of cooperating with other nations in space instead of competing with them, as was the case during his first flight three decades ago. A16</p>
        <p>Citigroup President to Resign  Jamie Dimon, president of Citigroup, the world's largest financial services concern, said that he would leave the company, a surprising move that raises questions about a successor. A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION B1-10</p>
        <p>Old-Style Politicking Colors a Senate Race  Representative Charles E. Schumer campaigned for the Senate in black, Jewish and Hispanic neighborhoods across New York City, bringing in Vice President Al Gore in an effort to rally support in the election. His opponent, Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, went to Orthodox Jewish communities in Brooklyn, portraying himself as an underdog in the final weekend of the bruising race. A1</p>
        <p>The Democratic and Republican Parties are using a new technique -- calls to potential voters that feature recorded messages from the candidates and political celebrities -- along with the customary mailings, fliers and telephone banks to get their voters to the polls. A1</p>
        <p>Peter F. Vallone, the Democratic candidate for Governor, debated what he called ''an empty chair,'' participating in a televised forum without his Republican opponent, Governor Pataki, who skipped the event and stumped upstate. B5</p>
        <p>B. Thomas Golisano's decision to spend $20 million of his fortune on a third-party campaign for governor may turn out to have been another smart investment. The stock price of Mr. Golisano's payroll processing company, Paychex, has jumped, just as it did when he ran for governor in 1994. B5</p>
        <p>ARTS E1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES B11</p>
        <p>Bulldog Turner  A Chicago Bears Hall of Fame center and linebacker who played on four National Football League championship teams in the 1940's, he was 79. B11</p>
        <p>Peter Griffin  An algebra teacher with such a winning way with numbers that he unlocked the mathematics of blackjack with a wink and became a cult figure to a generation of casino card counters, along the way writing the authoritative ''Theory of Blackjack,'' he was 61. B11</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY C1-10</p>
        <p>Part-Timers as Full-Timers  A new class of part-timers, mostly women, is emerging and working what used to be considered full-time hours -- 35 or 40 hours a week. The employees want to cut back their official hours so they can spend more time with their children or deal with other responsibilities. A1</p>
        <p>$1 Billion Software Deal  BMC Software, a software company based in Houston, is expected to announce today that it is acquiring Boole &amp; Babbage, one of Silicon Valley's older companies, for nearly $1 billion in stock. C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest C1</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY D1-10</p>
        <p>Jets Win, 20-17  John Hall kicked a winning field goal with 2 seconds remaining. D1</p>
        <p>THE MARATHON F1-10</p>
        <p>Marathon Winners  John Kagwe of Kenya repeated as champion of the New York City Marathon. Franca Fiacconi became the first Italian woman to win the New York race. F1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: New chill in China; vote no on New York City ''reform''; vote yes for open space in New Jersey; Brent Staples on Jefferson.  Columns: William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge E6</p>
        <p>Metro.Diary B2</p>
        <p>Crossword E8</p>
        <p>Weather B8</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 3, 1998, Tuesday  The News Summary yesterday included an entry erroneously in some copies for an obituary of Rudolph J. Melone, founder of the Gilroy, Calif., Garlic Festival. It appears today, on page B11.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 3, 1998, Tuesday</p>
        <p>The News Summary yesterday included an entry erroneously in some copies for an obituary of Rudolph J. Melone, founder of the Gilroy, Calif., Garlic Festival. It appears today, on page B11.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
