<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Scientists are Disputing The Fate of the Grizzly</title>
    <meta content="23GRIZ$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grizzly Bears</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yellowstone National Park</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Fish and Wildlife Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mattson, David J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wyoming/Yellowstone National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01EFDE123CF930A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Scientists are Disputing The Fate of the Grizzly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM ROBBINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>YELLOWSTONE NATIONAL PARK, Wyo.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David J Mattson and Craig Pease, respected wildlife biologists, report that number of grizzly bears in and around Yellowstone National Park may be much lower than previous estimates; warn that outlook for critical elements of grizzly bear habitat, including whitebark pine nuts, is poor; report runs contrary to widely accepted belief that grizzly bear numbers in park have increased since bear was listed as threatened under Endangered Species Act in 1975; Fish and Wildlife Service contends that grizzly population is healthy enough to begin process of removing bear from list of threatened species (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NEW report by two respected wildlife biologists warns that the number of grizzly bears in and around Yellowstone National Park may be much lower than previous estimates.</p>
        <p>Moreover, one of the report's authors, David J. Mattson, a wildlife biologist with the United States Geological Survey Biological Resources Division, warns that the outlook for critical elements of grizzly bear habitat, including whitebark pine nuts, is poor. ''The odds are not good that we will see a stable to increasing population of bears over the next 100 years,'' he said in an interview.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NEW report by two respected wildlife biologists warns that the number of grizzly bears in and around Yellowstone National Park may be much lower than previous estimates.</p>
        <p>Moreover, one of the report's authors, David J. Mattson, a wildlife biologist with the United States Geological Survey Biological Resources Division, warns that the outlook for critical elements of grizzly bear habitat, including whitebark pine nuts, is poor. ''The odds are not good that we will see a stable to increasing population of bears over the next 100 years,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The report, which will be published this year in the journal Ecology, is controversial, because it runs contrary to the widely accepted belief that grizzly bear numbers in the park have increased since the bear was listed as threatened under the Endangered Species Act in 1975. And it comes at a time when the Fish and Wildlife Service says the population is healthy enough to begin the process of removing the bear from the  list of threatened species.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mattson began collecting data for the report in 1979. He and his co-author, Craig Pease, a zoologist at the University of Texas, have spent the last five years analyzing data. Using a counting method that differs from past studies, they concluded there has been little gain in total bear numbers in the last 20 years.</p>
        <p>''We haven't had as much of an increase in the population as many people would like to think,'' Mr. Mattson said. He said that in 1975 ''the best guess is there were something in excess of 300 bears.''</p>
        <p>''At this point,'' he continued, ''we still have something in excess of 300, perhaps as many as 400.'' Further,  he said, any increases in the population are the result of fluctuations in food supply and not management of the population, placing the future further in doubt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mattson said his method does not rely on random sampling, as past models have.</p>
        <p>But Chris Servheen, the Grizzly Bear Recovery coordinator for the United States Fish and Wildlife Service in Missoula, Mont., said the numbers are ''totally wrong.''</p>
        <p>''There are between 400 and 500 bears in the system,'' he said, ''and we're seeing them in places we've never seen them.</p>
        <p>''Things are going well now and we should take advantage of that'' by removing the grizzly from the threatened list, he added. ''If all goes well, we'll propose a status change next year.''</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists fear removing the bear from the list would offer it less protection, allowing, for example, more logging and oil and gas development on Federal land.</p>
        <p>Mr. Servheen, who predicts the bear could be removed from the list  by the year 2000, expects to release a draft of a document this fall that will spell out how the grizzly will be managed by Montana, Wyoming and Idaho once the bear is off the list.</p>
        <p>A battle is expected because the  bear is one of the most charismatic animals in the American West, and it arouses fierce emotions on both sides of the issue. ''De-listing is premature,'' said Louisa Wilcox, a coordinator of the Sierra Club Grizzly Bear Ecosystem Project. ''It's going to be a classic Yellowstone knock-down, drag-out fight.''</p>
        <p>At the core of the debate are the numbers. Grizzly bears are secretive and unpredictable, making a truly random sample extremely difficult. Complicating the issue further is that the greater Yellowstone ecosystem is an ecological ''island'' with no link to other grizzly bear populations. And there are many opinions on how many bears are necessary to assure long-term survival.</p>
        <p>It is not the present population level alone that concern Mr. Mattson. The outlook for critical elements of the bear's habitat is poor on almost every count, he said.</p>
        <p>Whitebark pines are the cause of most concern. Not only are their nuts  a critical fall food for the bears, but  they draw the bears to higher elevations and keep them away from people. Conflicts between bears and people are the leading cause of bear mortality in the Yellowstone ecosystem, and there is a direct correlation between bad pine nut crops and mortality rates, Mr. Mattson said.</p>
        <p>A disease called blister rust, which kills whitebark pines, has made its way into areas north and west of Yellowstone, destroying most of the trees. At the same time, some studies indicate that global warming is causing the range of the pines to shrink. Moreover, Yellowstone lost roughly 27 percent of its whitebark pines in the 1988 fires, and the trees  will take about 100 years to replace.</p>
        <p>Global warming may also affect another prime food source, the army cutworm moth. These moths feed on the nectar of high altitude flowers at night. During the day, grizzlies find them under the rocks in talus slopes. Biologists have seen as many as 50 bears eating moths at one time. Alpine areas are sensitive to global warming, and there is concern the moth's food source could disappear.</p>
        <p>The shooting of hundreds of bison outside the park by Montana livestock officials could also have an impact on bears. The state fears that the bison harbor a disease that could be passed on to cattle, and hauls the carcasses away, effectively removing a critical source of protein.</p>
        <p>Damage to the fishery in Yellowstone Lake could also affect the bear. Lake trout were discovered in the lake in 1994, probably illegally introduced by fishermen. The huge fish prey on the cutthroat population which spawns in the lake's tributaries where as many as 30 or 40 bears may feed on them. Lake trout spawn in deep water in the lake, and therefore don't provide food for the bears.</p>
        <p>Habitat loss may be the single biggest threat to the grizzly. The Yellowstone and Grand Teton parks  make up only half of the six million-acre grizzly bear ecosystem. In the mix of other land ownership there are large tracts of private property. Some counties around the park are among the fastest growing in the country. Farms and homes can attract bears with garbage and dog food, and when a bear becomes habituated, or loses its fear of humans, it often needs to be moved out of the ecosystem or ends up being shot. Elk hunters who find a grizzly, and shoot it in self-defense, also account for a large share of grizzly deaths.</p>
        <p>Mr. Servheen believes that Mr. Mattson and environmental groups opposed to removing the bears from the list are exaggerating possible threats to food supplies.</p>
        <p>''He's saying there might be declines, and there might be,'' said Mr. Servheen. ''We'll monitor all these foods and have a response protocol.''</p>
        <p>Even if the bear is taken off the list, Mr. Servheen said, the three states around the park, the Park Service and the Forest Service must agree to a plan to protect the bear. If numbers drop or a food source seems imperiled, the bear can be placed back on the list.</p>
        <p>''There's a misperception that de-listing means there's an open season, with timber cutting and oil drilling in the forests around the park,'' Mr. Servheen said. ''That's far from the case.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
