<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Argentina Takes a Lead in Setting Goals on Greenhouse Gases</title>
    <meta content="Y12CLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Buenos Aires (Argentina)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Menem, Carlos Saul (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina/Buenos Aires</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E6DD1731F931A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Argentina Takes a Lead in Setting Goals on Greenhouse Gases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Carlos Saul Menem, at conference in Buenos Aires on global warming, says that Argentina will become first developing country to adopt binding targets for controlling emissions of industrial waste gases that are believed to cause global warming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an important breakthrough, Argentina signaled yesterday that it would become the first developing country to adopt binding targets for controlling emissions of industrial waste gases that are believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>Until now, developing countries have presented a united front in resisting specific limits on their emissions of such gases, which are produced by the burning of coal, oil, wood and natural gas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an important breakthrough, Argentina signaled yesterday that it would become the first developing country to adopt binding targets for controlling emissions of industrial waste gases that are believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>Until now, developing countries have presented a united front in resisting specific limits on their emissions of such gases, which are produced by the burning of coal, oil, wood and natural gas.</p>
        <p>Rich countries agreed last December in Kyoto, Japan, to reduce emissions by an average of about 5 percent below 1990 levels in the period 2008 to 2012, but poorer nations have refused to follow suit until industrial countries actually show results.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, at a follow-up conference in Buenos Aires, President Carlos Saul Menem said Argentina would establish goals for carbon-dioxide emissions and in about a year would announce its commitment to those goals for 2008-10.</p>
        <p>But Maria Julia Alsogaray, an Argentinian who is presiding over the Buenos Aires meeting, later described the goals as limitations on the growth of emissions, not as reductions.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Menem's speech was somewhat general, Stuart Eizenstat, the head of the United States delegation, said he had been told by Mr. Menem that Argentina would spend the next year analyzing its emissions to produce a binding target. ''This is a major, major move,'' Mr. Eizenstat said, ''truly historic.''</p>
        <p>There were indications that other developing countries might follow now that Argentina has led the way, some participants in the Buenos Aires talks said. ''No one wants to be the first one out of the box,'' said Connie Holmes, the chairwoman of the Global Climate Coalition, which represents fossil-fuel producers and users. She called Argentina's action ''great,'' if it can follow through.</p>
        <p>But she pointed out that it may be difficult for Argentina to be brought into the international process under the Kyoto Protocol because no developing countries are covered by it.</p>
        <p>Argentina wants to pursue its emissions program by taking advantage of some of the protocol's cost-cutting mechanisms like trading of emissions rights, Mr. Eizenstat said he was told. This, President Menem said, implies the creation of a ''new way'' under the 1992 treaty to involve his country and others like it. How that will happen remains to be worked out over months or even years.</p>
        <p>Moreover, said Ms. Holmes, Argentina's shift will not in itself satisfy the United States Senate, which has made participation by key developing countries a condition for ratifying the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists hailed the development. ''It is a major breakthrough,'' said Michael Oppenheimer of the Environmental Defense Fund. ''I don't think there's any doubt about it.'' He called the Argentine move ''a significant first step'' in satisfying the Senate's requirements.</p>
        <p>The move also represented ''a clear break'' from the developing countries' past insistence that binding limitations would put a cap on their economic growth, said Alden Meyer, a spokesman for the Climate Action Network, an environmental coalition.</p>
        <p>President Menem said Argentina's economy had grown 6 percent a year in the last decade while greenhouse gases per capita had grown by only 1 percent, and he said his country's purpose was to erase ''the false option between economic growth and environmental protection.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
