<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Rich nation, poor nation. Is anyone even looking for a cure?</title>
    <meta content="Y13SCEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Economic Scene (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E6D6153AF930A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Rich nation, poor nation. Is anyone even looking for a cure?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Economic Scene column by Peter Passell on bounty of America's economic growth going to educated, enterprising and already-affluent in last quarter of century; says since 1970's, economists have learned that while labor still captures about two-thirds of national income, only skilled workers have benefited; holds phenomenon of 'winner take all' has increased gaps between successful and also-rans in diverse occupations; says little is being done to right imbalance; suggests some ways to correct trend; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST economists are most comfortable thinking and writing about what is, or will be. Would cutting the capital gains tax to 15 percent transform couch potatoes into software entrepreneurs? Would 4 percent unemployment lead to inflation? Just ask you friendly, neighborhood Ph.D.</p>
        <p>And, truth be known, most economists have a weakness for clever fixes that exploit free markets. Want to prevent the overfishing of coastal waters? Privatize the rights to fish. Want to curb global warming for a fraction of the cost of conserving energy at home? Let Western consumers pay the Chinese and Russians to cut their emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST economists are most comfortable thinking and writing about what is, or will be. Would cutting the capital gains tax to 15 percent transform couch potatoes into software entrepreneurs? Would 4 percent unemployment lead to inflation? Just ask you friendly, neighborhood Ph.D.</p>
        <p>And, truth be known, most economists have a weakness for clever fixes that exploit free markets. Want to prevent the overfishing of coastal waters? Privatize the rights to fish. Want to curb global warming for a fraction of the cost of conserving energy at home? Let Western consumers pay the Chinese and Russians to cut their emissions.</p>
        <p>But efficiency isn't an end in itself: making more stuff for less gets you only part of the way to the economist's nirvana. And maybe, just maybe, economists -- and other Americans -- are worrying too little about dividing up the spoils.</p>
        <p>America's economic system does work better than the obvious alternatives. After all, the socialist utopias collapsed under the cumulative weight of their internal contradictions. Asia's crony capitalism has proved that it isn't ready for prime time. Europe's mixed economies perch on a powder keg of 20 percent youth unemployment -- and can't think of any way out, save for the risky strategy of following the advice of Alexander Hamilton and adopting a common currency.</p>
        <p>But the celebration may be getting out of hand. For while the American system is doing many things right, most economists would agree that it is doing one big thing wrong: for the last quarter century, virtually all the bounty of growth has gone to the educated, enterprising and already-affluent.</p>
        <p>Not so long ago, growth was seen as the solution to all problems. Competitive markets, the not-so-dismal scientists reminded us, had insured that two-thirds of all income had gone to wages as far back as the division between capital and labor could be measured. Hence, a growing, fully employed economy would mean rising living standards for all.</p>
        <p>But since the 1970's, economists have learned that a very nasty devil lurks in the details. While labor still captures about two-thirds of national income, only skilled workers have benefited. And even within this elite, the phenomenon of ''winner take all'' has increased the gaps between the successful and the also-rans in occupations as diverse as law, plumbing and basketball.</p>
        <p>Defenders of business-as-usual argue that the consequences are less than meet the eye. Inequality of consumption, they note, is less extreme than inequality of wages or incomes. Social mobility allows some of the poor to make the leap to the comfortable middle. The earned-income tax credit -- a negative income tax for the working poor -- has offset some of the wage decline of the unskilled. And the elderly, the people traditionally at greatest risk, are generally shielded from poverty by Social Security and Medicare.</p>
        <p>But such rationalizations get you only so far in an economy that has grown steadily less egalitarian over the last quarter century. The most comprehensive estimate of income distribution, by Lynn Karoly of the Rand Corporation, shows that the real income of the bottom 10th of American families fell by 13 percent between 1973 and 1995. And Brooks Pierce, an economist at the Bureau of Labor Statistics, has found this growing inequality has been magnified by the decline of company-wide medical and pension benefits.</p>
        <p>What could be done to right the imbalance without damaging the engine of economic growth? Probably plenty.</p>
        <p>The earned-income tax credit could be expanded. State and Federal tax systems could be tilted, effectively eliminating taxes on the bottom third of the income distribution and making up the lost revenue with modest increases on the top third. Government could take some of the sting out of private income inequality by increasing outlays for communal services -- day care, early childhood education, mass transit, recreation.</p>
        <p>What is being done? Precious little. Virtually all recent tax changes have had the effect of allowing the rich to keep more of their earnings. President Clinton's acclaimed effort to make college affordable has funneled the greatest share of the tax breaks to the middle class.</p>
        <p>Surprising the skeptics, welfare reform has been successful in cutting dependence. But it is safe to say that tough love gets you only so far. Even its most optimistic supporters concede that the social infrastructure of day care and medical benefits is sorely lacking -- and that roughly one-third of the welfare caseload is hopelessly unprepared for gainful employment.</p>
        <p>A decade hence, will hindsight show that American capitalism, too, was drifting toward the ashcan of history? Probably not. But history rarely looks kindly on societies that trumpet their virtues and ignore their failings.  This is Peter Passell's final Economic Scene column. He is leaving the staff of The New York Times to become editor of the public policy quarterly for the Milken Institute.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This is Peter Passell's final Economic Scene column. He is leaving the staff of The New York Times to become editor of the public policy quarterly for the Milken Institute.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
