<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Says Trading Pollution Permits Would Be Economical</title>
    <meta content="Y01CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White House Council of Economic Advisers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Global Climate Coalition</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dingell, John D (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yellin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holmes, Connie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DF1138F932A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Says Trading Pollution Permits Would Be Economical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Study by White House Council of Economic Advisers says that paying other countries to cut their pollution could be cheapest way for US to help control heat-causing gases; adviser Janet Yellin has told Congress that US could meet targets of Kyoto protocol at modest cost of as little as $70 per year per American household; Connie Holmes of Global Climate Coalition and Repr John Dingell, who opposes global warming treaty, reject projections (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paying other countries to cut their pollution could be the cheapest way for the United States to help control the heat-trapping gases that cause global warming, the Clinton Administration said in a new economic analysis released today.</p>
        <p>A system of buying and selling pollution permits internationally, as proposed by the Administration, would cut the costs to the United States at least in half and possibly by as much as 85 percent, according to a study by the White House Council of Economic Advisers. Many economists favor the trading of pollution permits as a free-market mechanism that reduces the costs of pollution controls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paying other countries to cut their pollution could be the cheapest way for the United States to help control the heat-trapping gases that cause global warming, the Clinton Administration said in a new economic analysis released today.</p>
        <p>A system of buying and selling pollution permits internationally, as proposed by the Administration, would cut the costs to the United States at least in half and possibly by as much as 85 percent, according to a study by the White House Council of Economic Advisers. Many economists favor the trading of pollution permits as a free-market mechanism that reduces the costs of pollution controls.</p>
        <p>''The world is filled with unbelievably cheap opportunities to reduce emissions abroad,'' said Janet Yellin, President Clinton's top economic adviser.</p>
        <p>The study was intended to substantiate Ms. Yellin's recent testimony before Congress that the United States could meet the targets of a new international climate change protocol, negotiated last year in Kyoto, Japan, at a modest cost. She has estimated that the typical household's annual energy bill might rise as little as $70 per year, although others insist the amount would be far higher.</p>
        <p>With the Senate balking at approving any treaty that does not include a substantial role for developing countries in the control of emissions, the Administration has struggled for more than a year to produce a comprehensive analysis of its proposals.</p>
        <p>The study released today was attacked by critics on several sides of the climate debate.</p>
        <p>Connie Holmes, the chairwoman of the Global Climate Coalition, a group representing large companies that oppose the treaty, called the report ''smoke and mirrors.'' The Administration, Ms. Holmes said, had not faced up to the fact that many foreign nations oppose the idea of pollution trading.</p>
        <p>Representative John D. Dingell, a Michigan Democrat who opposes the global warming treaty, said the report ''gives every appearance of being a post hoc rationalization, full of tautologies and self-fulfilling, unrealistic or unprovable assertions and assumptions.''</p>
        <p>Some environmental groups strongly criticized the Administration, saying the study suggested that the United States, which emits more heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide than any other country, is seeking to avoid much of its responsibility for solving the problem of climate change.</p>
        <p>''Their plan is to buy reductions abroad,'' said Gary Cook, legislative director for the climate campaign at Greenpeace. ''We need to take the first steps largely at home.''</p>
        <p>The Administration's study was based on sophisticated computerized economic models, including one developed by the Battelle Laboratory in Ohio to estimate the economic costs of actions to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide, the principal heat-trapping gas produced when fossil fuels are burned.</p>
        <p>The models suggested that the United States could meet its emissions targets, which require reductions of 7 percent below the 1990 level over the next 10 to 15 years, at an annual cost of $7 billion to $12 billion.</p>
        <p>Energy prices would increase by amounts equivalent to about 5 cents per gallon of gasoline, according to these projections.</p>
        <p>The models suggested that about one-fourth of the reductions in emissions would actually be accomplished within the United States. The rest of the reductions would be bought from other countries that were cutting emissions more than the treaty required, and therefore had surplus pollution permits to sell.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yellin and Todd Stern, the White House's senior aide on climate issues, said today that these projections underestimated how much the Administration's policies would reduce emissions at home.</p>
        <p>Ms. Yellin said the model did not take into account any of several initiatives the Administration favors to reduce domestic emissions of carbon dioxide. Among these are elements of its proposal to restructure the electric utility industry, to provide tax incentives for energy-saving investments, and to subsidize research into new technologies like solar power and fuel-efficient automobiles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
