<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saving Salmon In the Atlantic Makes Sense</title>
    <meta content="Y25OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="990340"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Salmon</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Nelson</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900EED9143BF936A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saving Salmon In the Atlantic Makes Sense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nelson Bryant</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bryant, Nelson</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nelson Bryant Outdoors column on his personal vow not to take any more Atlantic salmon until species is well on road to recovery; warns that Atlantic salmon populations of North American origin are at lowest points in history; reports some anglers are already releasing all or most of salmon they catch; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A few days ago, I thawed out a small Atlantic salmon that I caught in Caribou Pool on the Upsalquitch River in Canada last summer, and poached it for supper.</p>
        <p>Handsomely bedecked with sliced cucumbers, sliced hard-boiled eggs and served cold with a fresh dill, lemon juice, caper and sour cream sauce, it received the reverential treatment Ruth and I always accord one of its kind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A few days ago, I thawed out a small Atlantic salmon that I caught in Caribou Pool on the Upsalquitch River in Canada last summer, and poached it for supper.</p>
        <p>Handsomely bedecked with sliced cucumbers, sliced hard-boiled eggs and served cold with a fresh dill, lemon juice, caper and sour cream sauce, it received the reverential treatment Ruth and I always accord one of its kind.</p>
        <p>There was poignancy in our traditional ''thanks to salmon and the gods of the chase'' invocation because it was, I had resolved, the last Atlantic salmon I would kill until I am persuaded that the species is well on the road to recovery.</p>
        <p>Atlantic salmon populations of North American origin -- the only ones for which I fish -- are at their lowest points in history. This situation developed after nearly three decades of conservation efforts that until about three years ago seemed to be working. Those efforts included severely curtailing the daily and seasonal bag limits for recreational anglers, ending most netting of the species off Canada, and establishing, through an international organization, quotas for salmon fisheries off Greenland and the Faeroe Islands, locations to which the salmon travel while at sea.</p>
        <p>My decision not to kill salmon was triggered by a November 1997 resolution of the Atlantic Salmon Federation that asked anglers to release all of the salmon they catch, even if keeping them is legal. The World Wildlife Fund and the Salmon Trust of Scotland have endorsed this proposal. Even if anglers agree to this, it isn't very likely that the salmon's plunge toward erasure will be halted, but it is one way to immediately reduce the attrition on this glorious fish.</p>
        <p>Some anglers are already releasing all or most of the salmon they catch. And even now in eastern Canada, which accounts for almost all the wild salmon of North American origin, Quebec and Labrador are the only places where anglers may keep a large salmon, one that has been at sea for more than one year and produces more eggs than a grilse, a salmon that returns to its natal stream to spawn after only a year in the ocean.</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in Canada, only grilse may be kept -- no more than seven of them at the most -- during an entire season. Salmon conservationists have also successfully promoted salmon farming. Today more than 95 percent of the salmon sold in the world market are farmed fish.</p>
        <p>There is a twist to this success story, however. Farmed salmon that escape from their cages are mating with wild salmon and producing strains with inferior spawning capabilities.</p>
        <p>Why, given the plight of the salmon, would reasonable anglers be reluctant to release all of the salmon that they catch? Some might reason that commercial fishermen, American Indians under special dispensation and many recreational anglers are killing salmon, so why shouldn't we? Still others, and I was one of them until recently, are enmeshed in a food-gathering mystique that, in the case of salmon or any other similarly threatened species, cannot be justified.</p>
        <p>As one whose childhood was spent in rural surroundings in the late 1920's and early 30's, fishing -- whether for trout, perch, striped bass or bluefish -- was fun, but it was also for food. For me, cleaning, cooking and eating the catch brought the endeavor full circle, and lifted it beyond the mere pursuit of recreation. For decades I felt that luring, hooking, playing and releasing all fish, presumably to demonstrate one's skill and to observe and experience the quarry's antics, was silly.</p>
        <p>Today I no longer feel this way and realize that I was carrying old attitudes into a new era, an era in which there are too many of us pursuing too few fish. I was failing to comprehend that angling without food in mind can be both honorable and pleasurable. If a species of fish is in deep trouble and laws do not provide for its adequate protection, why shouldn't thinking anglers impose a no-kill restriction on themselves and hope that others will emulate them?</p>
        <p>Studies have shown that, if warming water has not placed them under stress, nearly all salmon survive the trauma of catch and release if brought to shore as swiftly as possible and handled properly during release.</p>
        <p>Thus it would be possible to sustain the thriving sport fishing industry for salmon in Canada without a single fish being killed intentionally, an all-important consideration for a country that is plagued by unemployment.</p>
        <p>The greatest threat to the salmon is commercial fishing in salt water for mixed stocks of the species. Such salmon could be from several rivers, and there is no way for the fishermen to identify their origin as they tumble on board.</p>
        <p>There are other problems: proliferation of salmon-eating seals; the degradation of salmon rivers by bad logging practices and acid rain, and the disruption of the oceanic food chain by overfishing. A bizarre example of a potential disruption is the Danes' fishery for sand eels in the North Sea. These ubiquitous little forage fish, which are near the bottom of the food chain, are being processed for use, among other things, as fuel oil.</p>
        <p>So to the salmon angler I say go forth and hone your skills, return your precious quarry to the water, and perhaps there will come a time when -- with a clear conscience -- you can bear a wild fish to the table triumphantly.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
