<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="22FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1011554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803EFD81F3CF931A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Seoul Won't Press Japan On Compensation Issue  South Korea said it would end its efforts to get compensation from Japan for South Korean women forced into Japanese military brothels in World War II and will instead pay the pensions itself.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Seoul Won't Press Japan On Compensation Issue  South Korea said it would end its efforts to get compensation from Japan for South Korean women forced into Japanese military brothels in World War II and will instead pay the pensions itself.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Africa Killing Spurs Anger  Thousands of South African mourners gathered for the funeral of a baby girl shot by a white man who opened fire on three black children in his field. Many South Africans are upset that the police did not arrest the man in this latest example of racially divisive confrontation.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Rebuffed on Cuba  The United Nations Human Rights Commission voted down an effort led by the United States to rebuke Cuba for its human rights practices.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>French Hearing on Rwanda  Four former French Government ministers, including the former conservative Prime Minister Edouard Balladur, testified before a parliamentary hearing on France's military role in Rwanda. In defending their actions, they said they had tried to stop the killings of more than 500,000 people there in 1994.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Burma Opposition Figure Jailed  The military Government of Myanmar, formerly Burma, has sentenced a prominent opposition leader, San San, to 25 years in prison, dissidents said.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>U.S. May Ease China Sanctions  The United States is offering to lift some sanctions imposed on China after the 1989 crackdown in Tiananmen Square if China makes more concessions on human rights, trade and the export of dangerous technologies.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Stance on Indonesia Explained  The Clinton Administration defended its decision to support a multibillion-dollar bailout for Indonesia despite a poor record on human rights.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Buddhist Shrine Destroyed  The Taktsang Monastery in Bhutan, one of the oldest and best known shrines in the Himalayan Buddhist world outside Tibet, was reported destroyed by fire on Sunday.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Colombia Crash a Puzzle  Investigators searched in the mountains near Bogota for clues as to why a Boeing 727 crashed on Monday, killing 53 people. Officials said that the route was familiar, the crew was experienced and the pilot had been warned that he was off course before the plane flew straight into a mountain. The passenger jet was leased to Air France by the Ecuadorean military-run carrier TAME.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>Northern Ireland Killing  A 29-year-old Roman Catholic man was shot and killed in the largely Protestant town of Portadown, Northern Irish police officials said. No group claimed responsibility. The town has been a trouble spot in the decades of tension that the recent peace agreement for Northern Ireland is intended to resolve.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-24</p>
        <p>Administration Asks Court To Block Agent Testimony  The Clinton Administration asked a judge to block Whitewater prosecutors from questioning Secret Service agents about what they learned as bodyguards for the President, law-enforcement officials said.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The Birth of a Planet?  Astronomers said they were seeing strong evidence of planets forming around young adult stars.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mayor Makes His Own Choice  Mayor Kurt L. Schmoke of Baltimore, left, broke with the Democratic Party by endorsing a challenger to Maryland's Governor, Parris N. Glendening, a fellow Democrat.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Hackers Tap Into Pentagon  A group of hackers has penetrated a military computer system that serves as ''a telecommunications backbone for the Defense Department,'' the Pentagon said.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Dispute Over Global Warming  The National Academy of Sciences took the extraordinary step of disassociating itself from a statement and a petition circulated by one of its former presidents that attacked the scientific conclusions underlying international efforts to control emissions of industrial waste gases believed to cause global warming.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Drug-Tobacco Linkage  Republican leaders in Congress suggested the linking of legislation to keep teen-agers from smoking with an anti-drug bill.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Race and Grand Juries  The Supreme Court ruled that white criminal defendants indicted by grand juries from which blacks were excluded could challenge the constitutionality of the indictment.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Toxicity Testing Sought  The Clinton Administration asked chemical companies to test thousands of common chemicals and disclose their toxicity, threatening to require the tests if the companies did not comply voluntarily.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Small Airlines Win Approval  Two small airlines got permission to fly to La Guardia in New York, and three airlines can add 20 flights at O'Hare Airport in Chicago.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Rise in Cigarette Smoking Is Linked to Marijuana Use  Teen-agers and some experts who have studied adolescent smoking say that in addition to advertising, the decision to take up smoking was fostered by a belief that cigarettes prolonged the effects of marijuana.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Limits on Health Care Rates  The Pataki administration said it would bar health insurance companies from raising rates for tens of thousands of New Yorkers who buy their own health insurance, saying the state would turn over $110 million to the companies to offset costs.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>West Side Stadium's Benefits  The Giuliani administration said a new West Side stadium for the Yankees would have an economic impact worth at least $1 billion a year, more than 10 times that of a renovated or new stadium in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>City Is Put on Notice  The New York Stock Exchange has told city officials that it is prepared to leave its historic headquarters on Wall Street and move to a new building in Battery Park City.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Crossing Party Lines  Mayor Giuliani, the city's most high-profile Republican, attended a fund-raiser for Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Con Ed to Rebuild Church  Con Ed will pay more than $3 million to help rebuild a Flushing church destroyed in a 1996 gas explosion.</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>Reversal at Georgetown  The president of Georgetown, responding to protests from alumni, faculty and students, has backed down from a decision to replace the dean of the law school.</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Linda Schele  A onetime studio art teacher who did pioneering work in decoding inscriptions on Mayan monuments, she was 55.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Gardner Dickinson  A founder of the Senior PGA Tour and a seven-time winner on the PGA Tour, he was 70.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-22</p>
        <p>New Rule on Options  A new S.E.C. rule lets companies listed on the New York Stock Exchange add a stock option plan if it meets two tests for a broad-based plan: at least 20 percent of employees must be eligible for options, and at least half of those employees must be below the level of company officer.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Big Penalty for 'Slamming'  The F.C.C. took its strongest action against the illegal practice of switching people's long-distance service without permission.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Job Hunting at the Mall  The Simon DeBartolo Group has created an alliance with Olsten, the temporary-employment business, to create employment centers in malls.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-10</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: The rush to finance stadiums; holding students back; campaign reform countdown; topics.The rush to finance stadiums; holding students back; campaign reform countdown; topics.</p>
        <p>Columns: Maureen Dowd, Frank Rich.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E10</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>B10</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
