<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long Boom or Bust; A Leading Futurist Risks His Reputation With Ideas on Growth And High Technology</title>
    <meta content="01FUTU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1021324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Peter Schwartz</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Global Business Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schwartz, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yankelovich, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E4DC163BF932A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="1977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long Boom or Bust; A Leading Futurist Risks His Reputation With Ideas on Growth And High Technology</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Schwartz, respected futurist and chairman of Global Business Network, is at center of spirited debate about technology and future since predicting what he calls Long Boom, global economic boom on scale never experienced before, driven by waves of fundamental technological change and free-market economics; he sees it lasting through about 2020; his vision of almost unabashed technological optimism about future has its critics; he recently debated merits of Long Boom with Daniel Yankelovich, public opinion analyst, who feels Long Boom betrays 'remarkable naivete' about technology and about working of market economics; Schwartz's Global Business Network has impressive list of corporate clients who value GBN's ability to offer scenarios built on in-depth research of demographic, political and technology trends; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peter Schwartz is a professional marketer of big, brow-furrowing ideas. By 2020, he says, the internal combustion engine will probably have gone the way of the dodo bird as conventional automobiles are replaced by hybrid cars powered by fuel cells that mostly use hydrogen.</p>
        <p>A telecommunications revolution, Mr. Schwartz believes, is coming even sooner. Thanks to big satellite projects, connections for high-speed Internet, telephone and video will be commonplace in six years or so. The world will be wired, inexpensively. By 2005, teen-agers in villages in developing countries will be chatting on video phones as they surf the Net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peter Schwartz is a professional marketer of big, brow-furrowing ideas. By 2020, he says, the internal combustion engine will probably have gone the way of the dodo bird as conventional automobiles are replaced by hybrid cars powered by fuel cells that mostly use hydrogen.</p>
        <p>A telecommunications revolution, Mr. Schwartz believes, is coming even sooner. Thanks to big satellite projects, connections for high-speed Internet, telephone and video will be commonplace in six years or so. The world will be wired, inexpensively. By 2005, teen-agers in villages in developing countries will be chatting on video phones as they surf the Net.</p>
        <p>By 2010, Mr. Schwartz predicts, breakthroughs in biotechnology and gene therapy may enable science to reverse aging and extend life. The prospect here, he insists, is not merely a prolonged old age but living for decades in one's biological 40's.</p>
        <p>Yet these are mere ingredients of Mr. Schwartz's biggest idea, which he calls the ''Long Boom.'' Its thesis is that the world is witnessing what Mr. Schwartz calls ''the beginnings of a global economic boom on a scale never experienced before,'' driven by waves of fundamental technological change and free-market economics.</p>
        <p>The Long Boom, which he sees running through about 2020, is a vision of almost unabashed technological optimism about the future from Mr. Schwartz, a leading futurist and chairman of the Global Business Network, a research and consulting firm. His manifesto first appeared as a cover story last summer in Wired magazine, whose pages generally celebrate the virtues of technology.</p>
        <p>Ever since, he has found himself at the center of a spirited debate about technology and the future. Bearded, affable and articulate, Mr. Schwartz is a skillful salesman who has won supporters for his ambitious idea, but he has been roundly criticized as well.</p>
        <p>In March, a loose-knit group calling itself the ''Technorealism Project'' emerged. Among the tenets proclaimed on its Web site at www.technorealism.org is the assertion, ''The Internet is revolutionary, not utopian.''</p>
        <p>Andrew L. Shapiro, a fellow at the Harvard Law School's Center for the Internet and Society and a founder of the Technorealism Project, said, ''We're just skeptical of the kind of sheer boosterism that Peter Schwartz is promoting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz recently debated the merits of the Long Boom with Daniel Yankelovich, the public opinion analyst and president of Public Agenda, a research organization, at a conference in San Diego. In Mr. Yankelovich's view, the Long Boom betrays a ''remarkable naivete'' not only about technology but also about the working of market economics. ''The market is great at distributing economic goodies,'' Mr. Yankelovich said, ''but it doesn't have all these moral virtues that Peter Schwartz attributes to it.''</p>
        <p>Such reactions, Mr. Schwartz says, are precisely why he wrote the Long Boom. It has provoked thought and, he insists, changed the debate about the future. The Long Boom, he asserts, represents ''a better vision of what could be if we make the right choices; it is what I think could and should happen.''</p>
        <p>As a futurist, Mr. Schwartz has impressive credentials. An alumnus of the Stanford Research Institute, now SRI International, he led a planning team at the Royal Dutch/Shell Group in London from 1982 to 1986. One of three possibilities drawn up in 1982 by Mr. Schwartz and his team was that oil prices would collapse.</p>
        <p>That possibility was taken seriously by Shell's senior management, which piled up cash to prepare. After prices fell precipitously, Shell began a $3.5 billion buying spree in 1986, buying oilfields and locking in a long-term cost advantage over most of its rivals.</p>
        <p>The Shell legacy gave Mr. Schwartz and four colleagues a head start in attracting corporate clients when they founded the Global Business Network in 1988. ''Everybody wanted the Shell magic,'' he recalled.</p>
        <p>The Global Business Network, known as GBN, is no ordinary consulting firm. Based in Emeryville, Calif., where it occupies a converted factory in the shadow of the Bay Bridge, GBN is eclectic if not eccentric. Its character is evident in the backgrounds of its five founders. Besides Mr. Schwartz, they are Jay Ogilvy, a former philosophy teacher at Yale University who headed values and life styles research at SRI International; Napier Collyns, who spent 30 years in Shell's planning group; Stewart Brand, creator of the Whole Earth Catalog and a founder of the Well computer network, and Lawrence Wilkinson, former president of Colossal Pictures.</p>
        <p>Today, GBN is a small but thriving specialist firm. Compared with mainstream consultants like McKinsey &amp; Company or Andersen Consulting, GBN is minuscule. Its revenues are running at $10 million a year, about double the level in 1994, while its staff has also doubled, to 55 people. (McKinsey says it has 4,500 consultants in 81 countries.)</p>
        <p>GBN has roughly 100 clients, about half of which sent executives to the company's four-day annual conference in San Francisco last month. The client list is as eclectic as the firm, ranging from I.B.M. and AT&amp;T to the Pentagon, the Government of Singapore and the National Education Association.</p>
        <p>The conference concluded with an advance screening of the Dreamworks SKG movie ''Deep Impact,'' which has since become a box-office hit. GBN worked with Dreamworks on developing the film, and Mr. Schwartz and a few other GBN members are mentioned in the film's credits.</p>
        <p>The narrative spine of ''Deep Impact'' is how people behave in the months after they learn that a comet is going to collide with Earth. The movie, in essence, illustrates the fulcrum of scenario building -- a what-if question. And creating scenarios is GBN's specialty.</p>
        <p>At the San Francisco conference, four scenarios for the next decade were presented as narratives for the participants to read and debate. They ranged from crisis and decline to an equivalent of the Long Boom, all rendered in imaginative detail.</p>
        <p>In the gloom-and-doom scenario, for example, the year 2000 computer bug and global warming are culprits in the tailspin. The European Union is shattered, the Middle East has water shortages, oil prices surge and inflation is ignited. In 2003, the scenario said, ''the Dow plummeted from 10,000 to 6,000 in a matter of months.'' In Mexico, the economy crumbles, South American drug cartels move in, guerrilla wars flare and refugees flood north. ''In 2010,'' the scenario asserted, ''President Wilson sent in the U.S. Army to establish order in Mexico.''</p>
        <p>Certainly provocative and undoubtedly more entertaining than most business reading, but what use is this kind of thing to corporations? Most companies say the GBN scenarios -- whether broad ones, like those presented at the San Francisco conference, or ones tailored for specific industries or nations -- are useful mainly as complementary planning tools.</p>
        <p>The scenarios are built upon in-depth research of demographic, political and technology trends. Daniel McGrath, a business strategy consultant at I.B.M., said the scenarios then sketched out ''causative chains that stretch your imagination and broaden your thinking.''</p>
        <p>GBN tries to broaden its own thinking through a network of about 100 people in diverse fields. They include Francis Fukuyama, the political scientist; Bruce Sterling, a science fiction writer, and Donella Meadows, an environmentalist. Yet the membership roster is heavy with technophiles including Danny Hillis, a computer scientist and research fellow at Walt Disney; Esther Dyson, an author and newsletter publisher, and John Gage, chief scientist at Sun Microsystems.</p>
        <p>Another GBN member is Kevin Kelly, the executive editor of Wired. Both GBN and Mr. Schwartz personally were original investors in Wired, a fact not mentioned in the magazine when it published Mr. Schwartz's Long Boom article. ''It's very incestuous in some ways,'' Mr. Schwartz allowed.</p>
        <p>For $35,000 a year, corporate clients get to join the GBN network members on the company's private Web site to discuss all sorts of subjects, from the future of the car to computing's millennium bug.</p>
        <p>In addition, clients are mailed two books a month, selected by Mr. Schwartz and Mr. Brand. ''We've basically solved the problem of executives' reading guilt,'' Mr. Schwartz observed. Recent selections include ''Remaking Eden,'' about cloning by Lee M. Silver, and ''The Commanding Heights,'' a history of the triumph of free-market policies, by Daniel Yergin and Joseph Stanislaw.</p>
        <p>GBN has prospered in recent years, partly because so many corporations, observing developments like the end of the cold war to the rise of the Internet, sense that change is accelerating. Divining traits of an uncertain future, more than ever, seems an essential corporate survival skill.</p>
        <p>But GBN has also done a deft job of marketing its mainstay business of scenario building. ''Scenarios have become the leading tool in thinking about the future, and GBN is the best at it,'' noted Michael Marien, editor of the Future Survey, a monthly newsletter.</p>
        <p>A central tenet of the discipline, Mr. Schwartz wrote in his 1991 book, ''The Art of the Long View,'' is that ''scenarios are not predictions.</p>
        <p>''It is simply not possible to predict the future with certainty,'' he wrote. ''Rather, scenarios are vehicles for helping people learn.'' Scenarios are typically presented in groups of three or four, not alone.</p>
        <p>Yet the Long Boom concept appears to be more a prediction than a scenario. And Mr. Schwartz, planning experts say, is taking a real risk with his reputation by championing the Long Boom. Professionals in the field of forecasting will talk cautiously about reducing uncertainty, while predictions suggest the hucksterish world of crystal balls, soothsayers and shamans.</p>
        <p>''I think you are moving down a dangerous slope in this business if you become identified with one view of the future,'' said Paul Saffo, a director for the Institute of the Future, a research organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schwartz acknowledges that risk, but he feels it is worth taking. ''I wanted to influence the future,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Schwartz is an inherent optimist -- a trait reinforced by his personal life and his professional experience. His parents were survivors of Nazi concentration camps. Mr. Schwartz was born in a refugee camp in 1946, outside Stuttgart, Germany, and lived until he was 5 in a Norwegian refugee camp. His family then immigrated to New Jersey, living in one room of a brownstone.</p>
        <p>His father, Benjamin, a self-trained engineer, quickly became a model of postwar upward mobility, steadily increasing his skills and income. He ended up designing advanced computer systems, and the family moved to a wealthy suburb of Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Professionally, Mr. Schwartz said, he has missed trends most often because of a failure to grasp the forces behind positive outcomes. In the early 1980's, he said, he consistently misread the outlook for the American economy because he failed to imagine the entrepreneurial effect of new industries led by the personal computer business.</p>
        <p>''It was a big miss, and that was a real learning experience for me,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
