<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Appearances; Germ Warfare</title>
    <meta content="31BEAUTYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="56" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020862"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tannen, Mary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DD1438F932A05756C0A96E958260" item-length="819" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Appearances; Germ Warfare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary Tannen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tannen, Mary</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mary Tannen article suggests that fear of germs and taste for extreme sports, two phenomena being targeted by cosmetics' industry, may both arise from axiety associated with the millennium; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A friend of mine -- beautiful, well traveled and healthy -- fears to take yoga class because the teacher's correcting touch may spread contagion from other students, yet she dares to climb hundreds of feet up vertical rock faces. Her problem is not multiple-personality disorder but exquisite sensitivity to millenarian anxiety, the underlying link joining fear of germs and attraction to high-risk sport.</p>
        <p>Because the cosmetics industry never tires in its quest to fulfill our needs almost before we are aware of them, its output now limns the footprint of apocalyptic dread. Today we can buy antibacterial soaps that promise not only to clean but also to kill more germs. Of course, there were disinfectant soaps before, but they smelled of hospitals and had no sex appeal. The new ones, like those from Bath and Body Works, are in fun colors and smell of raspberry, apple, vanilla. They spell death to a long list of micro-organisms, including Escherichia coli, Streptococcus epidermidis and Staphylococcus aureus. Barbara Jorgensen, a spokeswoman for Bath and Body Works, says the products have been enormously popular, especially in New York and other urban areas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A friend of mine -- beautiful, well traveled and healthy -- fears to take yoga class because the teacher's correcting touch may spread contagion from other students, yet she dares to climb hundreds of feet up vertical rock faces. Her problem is not multiple-personality disorder but exquisite sensitivity to millenarian anxiety, the underlying link joining fear of germs and attraction to high-risk sport.</p>
        <p>Because the cosmetics industry never tires in its quest to fulfill our needs almost before we are aware of them, its output now limns the footprint of apocalyptic dread. Today we can buy antibacterial soaps that promise not only to clean but also to kill more germs. Of course, there were disinfectant soaps before, but they smelled of hospitals and had no sex appeal. The new ones, like those from Bath and Body Works, are in fun colors and smell of raspberry, apple, vanilla. They spell death to a long list of micro-organisms, including Escherichia coli, Streptococcus epidermidis and Staphylococcus aureus. Barbara Jorgensen, a spokeswoman for Bath and Body Works, says the products have been enormously popular, especially in New York and other urban areas.</p>
        <p>Liquid soap is a $400 million business and 75 percent of that is now in antibacterials, according to Sheila Hopkins, a vice president at Colgate-Palmolive. While Colgate's Softsoap, which represents 45 percent of the liquid-soap market, has offered an antibacterial choice since 1985, business has recently been growing -- about 10 percent a year. Softsoap now has antibacterials with moisturizers as well as a hand gel for disinfecting when no water is available. In focus groups, Colgate found that women with children are the most concerned about ''the invisible health threat'' that pathogens present. Taking the cue, Formica has been working on antimicrobial countertops.</p>
        <p>For the young woman I found trapped in the ladies' room at a trendy sushi bar because she wouldn't touch the doorknob, there's Jao, which the publicity release says is ''the first upscale antibacterial hand refresher.'' It includes lavender, geranium, eucalyptus and tea tree, as well as a meaningful dose of ethyl alcohol. Bacteria are everywhere, warns the release, even on ''doors to the most exclusive hotels.'' It goes on to say that the TV crew for ''Nash Bridges'' ''goes through a bottle a day!''</p>
        <p>Why should people who have been inoculated against most serious diseases, whose sewage is treated and water supply protected, now have a need to not only feel clean, but also sanitized? Our embrace of super soaps can probably be understood in light of a general foreboding that crystallizes around the new millennium. As the world gets smaller, there is the fear of a deadly disease -- to which we do not have the antibodies -- sweeping out of some remote enclave and decimating whole populations. There is the additional menace of bioterrorism, and though antibacterial hand washes would prove feeble against an Ebola outbreak in Cleveland, they provide a comforting illusion of safety.</p>
        <p>Doom by germs is only one of many end-of-the-world scenarios hitting us daily, even hourly. We may perish from global warming, a sudden chilling or even fall-</p>
        <p>ing skies. Since there is little the average person can do to prevent Armageddon, some are training to survive it. Extreme sports -- jumping over barricades on dirt bikes or skateboards, scaling walls with fingers and toes -- are all skills that will be useful for getting through the rubble of ruined cities. New men's fragrances enhance this feeling of engagement. Ralph Lauren has Extreme Polo Sport for men, with a black-pepper top note and cool spice accord. Tommy Hilfiger weighs in with Hilfiger Athletics, smelling of crushed wet greens and invigorating citrus.</p>
        <p>Beyond those fragrances explicitly tied in with sports, others try to convey the spirit of energy -- a catchword for forces we sense but cannot name. Decorators from Scarsdale take courses in feng shui so they can block negative energy. Fragrances want to be seen as elixirs of positive energy shielding the wearer from hostile influences.</p>
        <p>Over at International Flavors and Fragrances, five choices are sprayed onto the arms of a volunteer who holds them out for the perfumer to sniff. The dominant note is of freshly mowed grass. ''This one has more energy,'' approves the perfumer, pointing to a spot on the volunteer's wrist. Clinique has had resounding success with Happy, launched last fall, and is adding Body Wash and Body Smoother in the same bouquet of mandarin, boysenberry and mimosa. In ads for the fragrance, models display industrial-strength happiness, tough enough to vanquish the most insidious negative energy of all, that which comes from within.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
