<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Smallest Octuplet Dies; Others Remain Critical</title>
    <meta content="Y28OCT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981231T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1073028"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Octuplets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Houston (Tex)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chukwu, Nkem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chukwu, Chijindu Chidera</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Altman, Lawrence K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas/Houston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Multiple Births</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01EED9173FF93BA15751C1A96E958260" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Smallest Octuplet Dies; Others Remain Critical</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE K. ALTMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Altman, Lawrence K</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chijindu Chidera Chukwu, smallest of octuplets born to Nkem Chukwu, Houston resident, dies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The smallest of the week-old octuplets, born to a Houston woman, died early today after the infant's heart and lungs gave out and mechanical respiration failed, according to Texas Children's Hospital in Houston.</p>
        <p>The baby, Chijindu Chidera Chukwu, nicknamed Odera, took a sudden and critical turn for the worse on Saturday night, after doctors moved her from a standard ventilator to a different type known as an oscillator in an effort to increase the amount of oxygen-rich blood in her body.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The smallest of the week-old octuplets, born to a Houston woman, died early today after the infant's heart and lungs gave out and mechanical respiration failed, according to Texas Children's Hospital in Houston.</p>
        <p>The baby, Chijindu Chidera Chukwu, nicknamed Odera, took a sudden and critical turn for the worse on Saturday night, after doctors moved her from a standard ventilator to a different type known as an oscillator in an effort to increase the amount of oxygen-rich blood in her body.</p>
        <p>Odera was the fifth of the octuplets born this month to Nkem Chukwu and her husband, Iyke Louis Udobi, who are from Nigeria and are United States citizens. Odera's condition began to deteriorate about the time that her mother visited all eight babies for the first time.</p>
        <p>The surviving seven babies remain in critical condition in a neonatal intensive care unit at the hospital. The youngest, Gorom, is recovering from abdominal surgery performed on Saturday to repair a hole in her intestines. Two of the babies are on mechanical ventilators, and the remaining four are breathing on their own.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chukwu's condition was reported as stable.</p>
        <p>Odera's name translated to ''God has my life,'' the hospital said. Through the hospital, the parents said they were ''very saddened'' by Odera's death and thanked people for their prayers and donations.</p>
        <p>Odera weighed 10.3 ounces and was 9.75 inches long when she was born at Texas Children's Hospital, which describes itself as the largest pediatric hospital in the United States. All of the babies weighed less than two pounds at birth. The largest weighed 1 pound 11 ounces. The first child was delivered on Dec. 8 and the rest on Dec. 17.</p>
        <p>Last week, The Associated Press reported that doctors at the hospital had given the babies an 85 percent chance of survival. But that level of optimism has surprised many doctors not connected with the octuplets' case.</p>
        <p>One, Dr. Ayman A. El-Mohandes, an attending neonatologist at George Washington University Hospital in Washington, said that he thought the odds were ''less than 50 percent'' and that 20 percent was a more reasonable figure.</p>
        <p>''We do not have very many babies in the United States that have survived at a similar weight,'' Dr. El-Mohandes said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The odds of such a baby's survival depend on many factors.</p>
        <p>The fact that all eight babies weighed less than two pounds ''showed how retarded growth was from the environment they had to endure'' in the womb, Dr. El-Mohandes said.</p>
        <p>Doctors call the condition ''in utero growth retardation,'' meaning that the baby weighs less than its gestational age would indicate. Yet some such babies do better than others of the same weight but of a younger gestational age. One theory is that ''the stress of surviving in utero leads to increased production of steroids and chemicals known as catecholamines that help the lungs mature a little more than the baby's gestation would indicate,'' Dr. El-Mohandes said.</p>
        <p>In such babies, Dr. El-Mohandes said, ''we worry about how much nutrition and oxygen the body organs received.''</p>
        <p>Another variable in the odds of survival is the location of the placenta in the womb, because certain parts of the womb have a better blood supply. Some of the eight placentas in Nkem Chukwu's uterus had a better opportunity to grow simply because of the overcrowding on the uterine wall, Dr. El-Mohandes said.</p>
        <p>After birth, ''lung function is the initial stumbling block in survival,'' Dr. El-Mohandes said.</p>
        <p>A standard ventilator inflates the lungs a specified number of times a minute, but pumps air in under pressure, which can cause lung damage.</p>
        <p>Because Odera failed to respond to a standard ventilator, doctors had to switch her to an oscillator. It vibrates air at high frequencies to try to increase the amounts of oxygen in the lungs and remove more carbon dioxide. It does so without using the very high pressures that are necessary to inflate the lungs completely with every breath.</p>
        <p>Another survival factor is the difficulty that small babies have regulating the amount of fluids and salts, like sodium and potassium, that their bodies need. Normally, the kidneys automatically regulate such amounts but those organs are often not fully developed in babies with low birth weights.</p>
        <p>''The smaller they are, the more difficult it is to control their fluid'' and chemical balance, Dr. El-Mohandes said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 31, 1998, Thursday  An article on Monday about the death of one of the octuplets born to a Houston woman misstated the date on which seven of the children were born. The first child was delivered on Dec. 8 and the rest were born on Dec. 20, not Dec. 17.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 31, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Monday about the death of one of the octuplets born to a Houston woman misstated the date on which seven of the children were born. The first child was delivered on Dec. 8 and the rest were born on Dec. 20, not Dec. 17.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
