<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Second Time Around, and Around; Remanufacturing Is Gaining Ground in Corporate America</title>
    <meta content="Y14REUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031746"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Copying Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Xerox Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recycling of Waste Materials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Copying Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE6DC1031F937A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Second Time Around, and Around; Remanufacturing Is Gaining Ground in Corporate America</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Remanufacturing--method of re-using old parts in new machines--is gaining ground in corporate America; companies of all types and technologies are looking to remanufacturing as premier way to hold costs down and keep products out of landfills; many companies are beginning to design products with eventual remanufacturing in mind; Federal Trade Commission, Environmental Protection Agency, and Congress have recently embraced remanufacturing, with money, technological support and new rules; numerous universities are studying it and teaching it; development of remanufactured components for copiers at Xerox Corp plant in Webster, NY, detailed; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dig inside the Xerox Corporation's newest stand-alone digital copier and the nuts and bolts of a big shift in manufacturing swing into view.</p>
        <p>Parts that were welded are now fastened, and easy to take apart. Components that were scattered throughout the machine are arranged on subassemblies that can easily be lifted out. The fuser roll, which fixes the toner to the paper, is no longer made of an aluminum core that is tossed out when its rubberized coating wears off; the core is now a combination of aluminum and steel that can be recoated again and again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dig inside the Xerox Corporation's newest stand-alone digital copier and the nuts and bolts of a big shift in manufacturing swing into view.</p>
        <p>Parts that were welded are now fastened, and easy to take apart. Components that were scattered throughout the machine are arranged on subassemblies that can easily be lifted out. The fuser roll, which fixes the toner to the paper, is no longer made of an aluminum core that is tossed out when its rubberized coating wears off; the core is now a combination of aluminum and steel that can be recoated again and again.</p>
        <p>Why all the changes -- particularly since some of the new parts are more expensive to make? Because they add a re-use option to the ''recycle or dump it'' choice for disposing of used or obsolete products.</p>
        <p>''In the long run, it is cheaper to re-use a part than to recycle it,'' said Jack C. Azar, Xerox's director of environment, health and safety.</p>
        <p>Once the purview of myriad small companies that eked out a living refurbishing carburetors, printer cartridges and other used parts, remanufacturing -- a method of re-using old parts in new machines -- has hit corporate America in a big way.</p>
        <p>From Xerox to Saturn, from Lucent to DuPont, from Kodak to Steelcase, companies of all types and technologies are looking to remanufacturing as a premier way to hold costs down and keep products out of landfills. No longer happy to let their small-company forebears breathe new life into their discarded machines, many are stepping up their collection methods and re-use technologies to bring older products home.</p>
        <p>But they are not content just to salvage parts from old products. Now, they are beginning to design products with eventual remanufacturing in mind.</p>
        <p>''We're finally convincing designers that it doesn't matter if a part is twice as expensive, if you can use it again and again,'' said Cavan Kelsey, manager of design for health, safety and environment at the Eastman Kodak Company, which recently replaced some plastic parts in its high-speed copiers with more expensive, but reusable, stainless steel.</p>
        <p>Designers are not the only converts. The Federal Trade Commission, the Environmental Protection Agency, and even Congress have recently embraced remanufacturing, with money, technological support and new rules. And numerous universities are studying it and teaching it.</p>
        <p>In fact, interest is running so high that some manufacturers are using design changes and sometimes lawsuits to keep the independent remanufacturers at bay. Some are fearful that the remanufactured versions of their products will eat too deeply into sales of new ones. Others just want to do the remanufacturing themselves.</p>
        <p>Although they have similar environmental goals, recycling and remanufacturing are not at all alike. Recycling generally involves destroying something so that its materials can be re-used. remanufacturers remove parts, test them, refurbish them and re-use them.</p>
        <p>Recycling methods -- melting down steel or dissolving paper -- can be energy intensive and polluting, and often yield lower-grade materials. And they do not recapture the value that was added through processing or assembling.</p>
        <p>By contrast, ''remanufacturing is an affordable way to get the highest value out of parts,'' said Nabil Nasr, director of the Rochester Institute of Technology's National Center for remanufacturing and Resource Recovery. That realization, said Stuart L. Hart, professor of strategic management at the Kenan-Flagler Business School of the University of North Carolina, is yielding ''tremendous corporate interest in, and sophistication about, remanufacturing.''</p>
        <p>Universities are fanning the embers. Kenan-Flagler just hired a professor of reverse logistics -- getting products back and remanufacturing them. The Rochester Institute sponsored a conference on remanufacturing in June. Gary A. Davis, director of the Center for Clean Products and Clean Technology at the University of Tennessee, said his group was  about to study remanufacturing for the automobile industry ''because it is infinitely superior to any type of recycling.''</p>
        <p>And numerous schools now preach remanufacturing in industrial design courses. ''We are teaching students that it is silly to think one-time use when they design products,'' said Steven Derby, associate professor of mechanical engineering at the Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute.</p>
        <p>remanufacturing is no panacea. The logistics of getting products back can be daunting. So can putting in tracking systems to insure that a part with a 10-use life is not on its 11th go-round. And some customers eschew remanufactured products, no matter how rigorously tested and warrantied.</p>
        <p>''Some people will always believe that if something isn't brand new, it isn't high quality,'' said Michael J. Best, a product manager for Steelcase Inc., which makes new and remanufactured furniture.</p>
        <p>Still, a growing number of manufacturers think the pluses outweigh the drawbacks. Computer companies, including the International Business Machines Corporation, are retrieving chips from old machines. Telecommunications equipment companies, including Lucent Technologies, are remanufacturing switching equipment. Lexmark International, which remanufactures its own printer cartridges, is looking ''on a test basis'' at whether it should use remanufactured parts in printers, a spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation's Saturn division is working with the University of Tennessee to develop a software program that tracks the energy and environmental impact of every part of a car, from manufacture to disposal. One major use for the program: letting designers run ''what if'' scenarios to see whether tinkering with certain parts will make them easier to recycle or remanufacture. ''We want designers to look at the environmental component of all their decisions,'' said William R. Miller 3d, Saturn's manager of environmental affairs.</p>
        <p>Even chemical companies, which deal with vats of materials rather than discrete parts, are learning to remanufacture. Instead of melting down old polyester film -- which degrades the fiber -- or burning it for fuel, DuPont now ''unzips'' the polyester molecule down to its atoms, and remanufactures the polyester. DuPont is ''scouting around for a similar chemistry for nylon,'' said John B. Carberry, director of environmental technology. ''Billions of pounds of nylon carpeting is going into landfill that we should be able to re-use.''</p>
        <p>Collins &amp; Aikman Floor Coverings Inc. has noticed that, too. It has a new technology, which falls between recycling and remanufacturing, for grinding up old carpets and, without any chemical processing, using them as backing for new ones. ''You can do this forever, without the fiber degrading in any way,'' said Lee H. Schilling, senior vice president.</p>
        <p>Remanufacturing as a separate industry has been around for more than 50 years. Remanufactured parts dominate the aftermarket for cars and trucks. Remanufactured office furniture and printer cartridges have also been available for years.</p>
        <p>The United States military, the largest remanufacturer in the world, routinely uses remanufactured parts in vehicles and weapons. And ''disposable'' cameras are a misnomer: since the early 1990's, Fuji and Kodak have retrieved them from photofinishers and re-used the flash and other parts in new cameras.</p>
        <p>''It didn't take long to realize how much value was left in those so-called throwaways,'' said Stephen C. Rumsey, Kodak's manufacturing manager for single-use cameras.</p>
        <p>Indeed, remanufacturing is a good-sized industry in its own right. Robert T. Lund, a professor of manufacturing engineering at Boston University, said that in 1996, the last year for which he gathered figures, companies that rebuild parts comprised a $53 billion business employing 480,000 people.</p>
        <p>But until recently, manufacturers and regulators barely acknowledged them. ''This industry has grown and grown, yet it's been completely overlooked,'' Professor Lund said.</p>
        <p>Now, remanufacturing is being promoted by its proponents -- including several state legislators in New York, which is home to many cartridge remanufacturers -- as the answer to everything from global warming (it requires less energy, and thus reduces greenhouse gases) to welfare reform (it provides jobs for low-skilled workers). Congress just granted the Rochester Institute's remanufacturing center $10 million over five years to develop new technologies.</p>
        <p>The F.T.C., whose Green Guide to products with recycled content is widely followed by corporate and government procurement departments, amended its guidelines in May to embrace remanufactured products. The E.P.A. is financing some studies on remanufacturing. ''It's an environmentally friendly solution for businesses looking to hold down costs,'' said Jane Bare, a chemical engineer in the E.P.A.'s office of research and development.</p>
        <p>Remanufacturing companies are trying to capitalize on their new fame. Last year they formed the Remanufacturing Industries Council International, which is lobbying Congress to make remanufacturing equipment eligible for a 25 percent capital investment tax credit.</p>
        <p>''As George Burns used to say, 'Hang around long enough, and you'll get discovered,' '' said William Gager, chairman of both the Automotive Parts Rebuilders Association and the new council.</p>
        <p>But what may be old hat for Mr. Gager is brand new for primary manufacturers. Many are under pressure from shareholders to meet environmental goals, and from customers who, facing their own environmental pressures and leery of rising landfill charges, want them to take back used items.</p>
        <p>The pace of technology and the robust economy together encourage companies to upgrade old equipment, creating a steady flow of products to be remanufactured. And the pressure to keep costs down, combined with the growing number of start-up businesses that cannot afford all-new products, has created a growing market for remanufactured goods like office furniture or cartridges, which, unlike remanufactured copiers or cameras, are generally sold at a discount.</p>
        <p>The battle lines between primary manufacturers and the independent remanufacturers are being drawn. Several printer companies have redesigned their cartridges to make them harder to refill. And they have aggressively sued remanufacturers -- and sometimes each other -- for trademark infringements when the packaging on the remanufactured cartridges looks too much like that on their new ones.</p>
        <p>Furniture manufacturers may be playing hardball, too. Bill Davies, owner of Davies Office Refurbishing in Albany, says it used to be simple to remove fabric from the frames of office panels; now, he says, Steelcase and other manufacturers are laminating the fabrics ''solely to make them hard to remanufacture.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Best of Steelcase says that is nonsense -- particularly since his company has a thriving remanufacturing business of its own. ''The new design makes it easier to route cable through the panels,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Maybe so. But it also brings more of the panels home to Steelcase itself for remanufacturing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
