<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing the American-Opposition-to-Big-Government 2-Step</title>
    <meta content="05REGU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="985397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="OUTLOOK '98: ECONOMY &amp; INDUSTRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEEDB1730F936A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing the American-Opposition-to-Big-Government 2-Step</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER PASSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Taxpayer Bill of Rights passed in 1997 with reluctant support of Pres Clinton is symptomatic of broader revolt against intrusive goverment; there is much evidence that Americans have lower expectations of what government can accomplish and less tolerance of its abuses; but opposition to big government is less tidy than it might appear; environmental regulation is still building momentum, and same Congress that brushed aside White House plans for broadening medical insurance coverage and heavily regulating delivery of services rushed to defense of mothers of newborns when insurers refused to pay for extra day in hospital (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Americans have long complained about abuses by the Internal Revenue Service. Taking aim at an easy target, in 1997 Washington finally did something about the complaints: With the reluctant support of President Clinton, the House passed, 426 to 4, a ''Taxpayer Bill of Rights,'' setting the stage for what is likely to be an equally lopsided vote in the Senate in 1998.</p>
        <p>By most accounts this ritual slaying of Big Brother is symptomatic of a broader revolt against intrusive government that has been gaining momentum since Jimmy Carter unleashed ''supersaver'' airline fares. And there is plenty of evidence -- everything from revised welfare laws to the current drive to deregulate electricity -- to buttress the idea that Americans have lower expectations of what government can accomplish and less tolerance of its abuses.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Americans have long complained about abuses by the Internal Revenue Service. Taking aim at an easy target, in 1997 Washington finally did something about the complaints: With the reluctant support of President Clinton, the House passed, 426 to 4, a ''Taxpayer Bill of Rights,'' setting the stage for what is likely to be an equally lopsided vote in the Senate in 1998.</p>
        <p>By most accounts this ritual slaying of Big Brother is symptomatic of a broader revolt against intrusive government that has been gaining momentum since Jimmy Carter unleashed ''supersaver'' airline fares. And there is plenty of evidence -- everything from revised welfare laws to the current drive to deregulate electricity -- to buttress the idea that Americans have lower expectations of what government can accomplish and less tolerance of its abuses.</p>
        <p>Look closer, though, and the picture clouds. The impact of apparently popular environmental regulation on daily life is growing by leaps and bounds. Efforts to contain the cost of Medicare guarantee that Uncle Sam will be a party to the most private interactions of patients and doctors. And even the cathartic attack on the tax collector could have unintended consequences. ''Taking the I.R.S. down a peg may lead to more exacting record-keeping and reporting standards for taxpayers,'' argued Joel Slemrod, an economist at the University of Michigan's Business School.</p>
        <p>The nation's always tumultuous relationship with New Deal-style government has been on the rocks at least since the 1970's. Washington, once seen as the champion of the weak and a catalyst for economic and social progress, has come to be reviled as the agent of special interests.</p>
        <p>Elaborate regulations governing the airline, trucking, railroad, long-distance telephone, natural gas and oil industries were dismantled over the last two decades, while the burden shifted to government to show whether or why corporate mergers and aggressive business practices restrained commerce. Big tax cuts, followed by a decade of budget deficits, ended the era in which Washington was inclined to define aspirations -- eliminating poverty, moving the disabled into the mainstream, saving family farms, assuring the survival of passenger trains -- and throw money at them.</p>
        <p>An ideologically driven Republican Congress beat back the Clinton Administration's effort to provide universal health insurance, and it ended welfare as millions of single mothers knew it. Emboldened by skepticism about the welfare state, mainstream research organizations and advisory commissions have broached the idea of taming Social Security deficits by privatizing the system. Even Democrats are talking the talk, calling for tax simplification and revisions in entitlement spending and emphasizing the need to use market incentives to ease the burden of regulation.</p>
        <p>But the opposition to big government is less tidy than it might first appear. For starters, a tsunami of environmental regulation is still building momentum. If Congress agrees, the United States could be forced to double energy prices in the next decade to meet its commitment at the recent conference in Japan on cutting greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Even without new legislation, big changes are coming. Open-ended requirements in the Clean Air Act require the Environmental Protection Agency to identify hazardous pollutants and then set standards that eliminate health effects. And despite protests from White House and Treasury economists, the E.P.A. has just reduced tolerances for ozone and fine soot particles to levels that would almost certainly require wrenching changes in transportation, energy use and the details of daily life.</p>
        <p>''People don't yet realize the new standards will affect everything from gasoline lawn mowers to the way the neighborhood bakeries vent their pastry ovens,'' said Lester Lave, an economist at Carnegie Mellon University.</p>
        <p>Or consider medical care. Congress brushed aside White House plans for broadening medical insurance coverage and heavily regulating delivery of services. But what a difference a few years can make: in equally high dudgeon, legislators last year rushed to the defense of the mothers of newborns, whose insurers had refused to pay for an extra day in the hospital.</p>
        <p>The inclination by Congress to micro-manage private health care may be beaten back, in part by heftier campaign contributions from the insurance lobby. But paradoxically, Washington's determination to cut Federal spending leaves little doubt that older Americans will have to jump through new hoops to get Government-financed medical care.</p>
        <p>Under the accord reached last year, fully half of the Federal budget savings over the next decade will come from slowing the inevitable growth in Medicare spending. This will require the ratcheting down of both the costs of individual services and the volume of services delivered -- all of which translates into a larger say by both Government and insurance company bureaucrats into who gets what treatment.</p>
        <p>''With unconstrained fee-for-service insurance, no one stands between doctor and patient,'' said Robert D. Reischauer, former director of the Congressional Budget Office. But with tightly constrained managed care, he added, the Government will surely be sucked into the dialogue as both the gatekeeper to access and as a defender of patients' rights.</p>
        <p>By the same token, Judy Gueron, president of the Manpower Development Research Corporation in New York, suggested that extracting Washington from its traditional welfare-state role might well mean a greater government presence in maintaining the remnants of the social safety net. The least intrusive public assistance program, after all, is a monthly check or a book of food stamps. By contrast, successful welfare reform will probably turn on the states' willingness to push, plead and train people off the dole -- and then provide child care and medical insurance.</p>
        <p>And then there is the aforementioned Taxpayer Bill of Rights, evidence that Washington is listening to the pleas of citizens to get government off their backs. Should the bill become law, the burden of proof in tax disputes that reach Tax Court would shift from the taxpayer to the I.R.S. But in becoming obliged to prove that taxpayers have cheated, the I.R.S. must fall back on greater disclosure to deter fraud. A likely result will be demands that honest taxpayers keep better records and file more forms.</p>
        <p>Tax policy is a perfect example of Americans' deep ambivalence about the proper role of government. Soon before the House voted on the I.R.S. bill, Congress passed legislation that includes tax credits for college tuition. And Mr. Slemrod notes that with the new benefits will come -- you guessed it -- bigger government in the form of new tax-reporting requirements for both beneficiaries and colleges.</p>
        <p>OUTLOOK '98: ECONOMY &amp; INDUSTRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
