<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Wait for the Y2K Problem?</title>
    <meta content="15BORO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1069879"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nineteen Hundred Ninety-Nine</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Borowitz, Andy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DA143DF936A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Wait for the Y2K Problem?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andy Borowitz</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Borowitz, Andy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andy Borowitz Op-Ed article warns that all the talk about Year 2000 Problem affecting computers obscures the Year 1999 Problem: the flood of millennium-related hype we will have to endure in coming year (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>We have been so preoccupied with the Year 2000 Problem that we have all but ignored the Year 1999 Problem -- at our peril, experts say.</p>
        <p>Simply put, the Year 1999 Problem is this: In 1999, we will experience a sudden, frightening surge in the number of articles printed about the Year 2000 Problem. Some of these articles will suggest that computers will fail to recognize the number 2000, putting a stranglehold on global communication. Other articles will assert that computers will in fact recognize the number 2000, since they deal with numbers all day and have a pretty good idea what they look like.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>We have been so preoccupied with the Year 2000 Problem that we have all but ignored the Year 1999 Problem -- at our peril, experts say.</p>
        <p>Simply put, the Year 1999 Problem is this: In 1999, we will experience a sudden, frightening surge in the number of articles printed about the Year 2000 Problem. Some of these articles will suggest that computers will fail to recognize the number 2000, putting a stranglehold on global communication. Other articles will assert that computers will in fact recognize the number 2000, since they deal with numbers all day and have a pretty good idea what they look like.</p>
        <p>All of these articles, however, will have one thing in common: they will be very boring. Unless we can find a way to make the Year 2000 Problem a much more interesting topic, the authorities fear, 1999 threatens to be the most annoying year ever.</p>
        <p>Even if that problem is somehow fixed -- and let us all hope that it will be -- there is ample evidence to suggest that 1999 will still be an unspeakable endurance test. While many have expressed concern that the year 2000 will bring with it a deluge of tedious millennium-themed books, records and calendars, experts have now moved up that timetable: the year 2000 is when those items will be remaindered.</p>
        <p>In 1999, it will be impossible to enter a Barnes &amp; Noble without being assaulted by jacket copy that reads, ''Four members of the Yale Class of 1975 -- a dreamer, a cynic, a saint and a sinner -- find their paths crossing once again . . . on the brink of the millennium.''</p>
        <p>While it is possible to avoid reading -- and most Americans do -- experts are concerned about another, more intractable problem for which there is no known solution: the expected upswing in use of the song ''(Party Like It's) 1999,'' by the artist formerly known as Prince. The once catchy dance track will become unbearably ubiquitous, and will inevitably be co-opted by do-gooder types to lame effect. (''Come and party like it's 1999 -- for world literacy!'')</p>
        <p>The resurgence of this song will bring with it another, equally serious problem, experts warn -- a resurgence of jokes in the form of, ''the Something Formerly Known as Something,'' making late-night comedy monologues unsafe for the balance of the year.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Year 1999 Problem will manifest itself in alphanumeric overload: because of the endless use of Y2K as shorthand for the Year 2000, every other serious worldwide problem will be given a cute abbreviation.</p>
        <p>Global warming will be called 2HOT4U, Saddam Hussein will be TROUBLE/24-7, and asteroids plummeting toward the earth will be O-NO-O-NOOO-AAIII-EEEE.</p>
        <p>It would be tempting to stick our heads in the sand and say that the Year 1999 Problem will not affect us, but experts warn against such complacency. Here is just one of the ''doomsday scenarios'' these authorities have described to rouse us to action:</p>
        <p>Time: Jan. 1, 1999. Place: A local television news studio. Two anchors, BEN and JAN, trade quips.</p>
        <p>BEN: So, Jan, I heard you partied like it was 1999 last night.</p>
        <p>JAN: I'll say -- and I'm afraid I enjoyed myself a little more than I should.</p>
        <p>BEN: Oh, the old 2MUCH4U problem!</p>
        <p>JAN: Well, moving on to tomorrow's forecast, here's the Weatherman Formerly Known as Ryan Larsen. How's the millennium treating you, Ryan?</p>
        <p>RYAN: Well, this week it's going to be snowing like it's 1999. . . .</p>
        <p>Given such gloomy predictions, one might ask, who is looking forward to 1999? With the exception of Barbara Feldon, whose portrayal of Agent 99 on ''Get Smart'' may, experts say, entitle her to a modest career resurgence, perhaps no one.</p>
        <p>But there may be a silver lining in all of this. True, 1999 will be a miserable year for magazines, newspapers, books, radio and television. But on Jan. 1, 2000, computers will fail to recognize the number 2000, putting a stranglehold on global communication. And not a moment too soon.</p>
        <p>Andy Borowitz co-produced the movie ''Pleasantville.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andy Borowitz co-produced the movie ''Pleasantville.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
