<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suit Demands Ban on Logging in U.S. Forests</title>
    <meta content="17FORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1070389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Forest Service (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Friends of the Earth</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Forest Guardians</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E3DB103DF934A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="790" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suit Demands Ban on Logging in U.S. Forests</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coalition of environmentalists plans to sue Forest Service, demanding end to logging in national forests on novel grounds: Federal timber program causes more economic harm than good; environmental groups, led by Friends of Earth and Forest Guardians, assert that Forest Service routinely ignores laws and regulations that require it to calculate economic costs of logging and to weigh them against benefits (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A coalition of environmentalists plans to sue the Forest Service on Thursday, demanding an end to logging in national forests on novel grounds: the Federal timber program causes more economic harm than good.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups, led by Friends of the Earth and Forest Guardians, assert that the Forest Service routinely ignores laws and regulations that require it to calculate the economic costs of logging, like damage to water resources or tourism, and to weigh them against the benefits, like the value of the timber that is sold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A coalition of environmentalists plans to sue the Forest Service on Thursday, demanding an end to logging in national forests on novel grounds: the Federal timber program causes more economic harm than good.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups, led by Friends of the Earth and Forest Guardians, assert that the Forest Service routinely ignores laws and regulations that require it to calculate the economic costs of logging, like damage to water resources or tourism, and to weigh them against the benefits, like the value of the timber that is sold.</p>
        <p>In one sense, the lawsuit upends the typical dispute between business groups who say that environmental regulations cost more than they are worth and environmentalists who usually argue that the benefits of strict environmental rules cannot be expressed in dollars. For years, the environmentalists have been fighting attempts in Congress to require cost-benefit tests. Now they are in court seeking exactly that.</p>
        <p>The lawsuit has been joined by recreation, hunting and fishing organizations, owners of small forest lots, tourism enterprises and others who say they have been harmed economically by the logging program.</p>
        <p>It is supported by some prominent natural resource economists who contend that the worth of forests that are not logged can be measured -- and that these values probably far exceed the worth of the timber they hold and the jobs that are created by logging.</p>
        <p>The suit is to be filed in Federal District Court for Vermont, in Burlington, said Brian Dunkiel, a staff lawyer for Friends of the Earth. It follows a yearlong campaign in which the environmentalists filed administrative appeals with the Forest Service challenging hundreds of individual timber sales by the service, including in the Green Mountains National Forest in Vermont, on similar grounds, only to be rebuffed repeatedly.</p>
        <p>''The law requires the Forest Service to account for net economic and social values,'' Mr. Dunkiel said. ''It is almost as though the Congress had hired the Forest Service to serve as the public's accountant, to manage these assets. What has become clear is that the Forest Service has failed terribly.''</p>
        <p>James Lyons, the Under Secretary of Agriculture for natural resources, said he had not seen the complaint and could not address its specifics.</p>
        <p>''As an organization we are certainly moving in a direction that takes into account all the resources,'' Mr. Lyons said. ''We are seeking to improve, if not maximize, net public benefits. Our analysis is not focused solely on timber production.</p>
        <p>''It's not what we take out of the woods, it's what we leave behind that really matters.''</p>
        <p>The coalition's lawsuit relies on a new but increasingly influential theory among ecologists that it is possible to put a monetary price on the public benefits that flow from healthy ecosystems, like providing a home for commercial species and protecting drinking water reserves, providing recreation and helping control global warming.</p>
        <p>It comes at a time when the Federal timber program, in which the Forest Service auctions off its trees to commercial companies, is under challenge on many fronts. The Clinton Administration is considering sweeping new forest policies aimed at protecting the last pristine stands of trees in roadless areas, and anti-logging forces have proposed Federal legislation that would restrict logging and road construction in tens of millions of acres in national forests.</p>
        <p>But some conservationists have complained that the Administration's approach exempts major forests from protection, and the legislation has virtually no chance of being enacted because pro-logging lawmakers control the committees in the House and Senate that have jurisdiction over forests.</p>
        <p>Instead, the plaintiffs in the suit are seeking to force the Forest Service to stop logging until it obeys what they say are the requirements of existing laws and rules.</p>
        <p>In documents prepared for the  suit, John Talberth, the executive director of Forest Guardians, presents the results of a broad review he conducted of the professional literature describing what he calls generally accepted standards for measuring the values of forests and the costs of logging them.</p>
        <p>He also presents results of a survey of hundreds of timber sale documents obtained from the Forest Service, which he said demonstrated that the agency ''has failed to incorporate significant information about the socio-economic values of unlogged national forests into timber sale program decisions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
