<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="03DIAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1014371"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0D7103EF930A35756C0A96E958260" item-length="2122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN M. ROSEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE ECONOMY  Growth Without Inflation  Instead of slowing down because of Asia's recession, the American economy has picked up speed. It grew at an unexpectedly strong 4.2 percent annual rate in the first quarter, up from a 3.7 percent rate the previous quarter. And the broadest measure of inflation, instead of drifting higher as Washington and Wall Street had feared, dipped below 1 percent, to its lowest rate since 1964. ''We keep expecting a slowdown and it never comes,'' said Jeffrey A. Frankel of the Council of Economic Advisers, citing instead ''a remarkable combination of strong growth without inflation.'' But consumers see no slowdown. The Conference Board reported that its consumer confidence index approached a three-decade high, rebounding to 136.7 in April, from 133.8 in March.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE ECONOMY  Growth Without Inflation  Instead of slowing down because of Asia's recession, the American economy has picked up speed. It grew at an unexpectedly strong 4.2 percent annual rate in the first quarter, up from a 3.7 percent rate the previous quarter. And the broadest measure of inflation, instead of drifting higher as Washington and Wall Street had feared, dipped below 1 percent, to its lowest rate since 1964. ''We keep expecting a slowdown and it never comes,'' said Jeffrey A. Frankel of the Council of Economic Advisers, citing instead ''a remarkable combination of strong growth without inflation.'' But consumers see no slowdown. The Conference Board reported that its consumer confidence index approached a three-decade high, rebounding to 136.7 in April, from 133.8 in March.</p>
        <p>MARKETS  Battered, Then Buoyant  Displaying the stability of a windsock, the stock market soared on the buoyant economic news. The Dow Jones industrial average tacked on more than 100 points on Thursday, its second consecutive day of gains, and erased the vestiges of its 146.98-point tumble on Monday. That plunge followed a report that the Federal Reserve had adopted a bias favoring higher interest rates -- a report that some in Washington viewed as having been planted by the Fed itself as a signal to investors. But the latest economic data largely erased any lingering fears of a rate increase soon, and the yield on the long bond fell back below 6 percent. The Dow average ended the week up 82.45, at 9,147.07, while the Nasdaq composite index edged up 4.48, to close at 1,873.44.</p>
        <p>SOCIAL SECURITY  Doomsday Delayed  Young adults have been given a reprieve -- three more years to hone their survivalist skills, learning to prepare meals of berries and bark, say, or build shelter from tender young saplings. Thanks to the nation's booming economy, the Administration reported, the Social Security system's solvency has been extended by three years from the date projected last year, 2029. Even with the new projections, Social Security would be able to pay only three-quarters of promised benefits after the system exhausts its reserves in 2032. The Government reported that Medicare, the health care program for the elderly, would remain financially sound until 2008.</p>
        <p>DEALS  BMW Captures Rolls  Vickers P.L.C. formally accepted a $566 million takeover offer for Rolls-Royce Motor Cars from BMW, subject only to shareholder approval. But BMW's German rival, Volkswagen, vowed to fight on, promising a sweeter price for Rolls, Britain's premier luxury-car maker. . . . United Airlines and Delta Air Lines agreed on a broad marketing alliance, subject to approval by pilots. The deal would link the airlines' frequent-flier programs, allow each carrier to sell seats on the other's flights and give United passengers access to 39 new cities and Delta passengers access to 17 more. . . . Lucent Technologies agreed to acquire Yurie Systems, a maker of devices to send data and video over the Internet, for $1 billion. . . . Times Mirror will sell its legal publishing business to the British-Dutch publishing giant Reed Elsevier for $1.65 billion in cash.</p>
        <p>HEALTH CARE  Limits for Viagra  Fearing huge payouts to millions of American men, large insurers, including Wellpoint Health Networks and Cigna Healthcare, are adopting strict reimbursement policies for Viagra, Pfizer Inc.'s new pill for impotence. The insurers require proof of a medical cause for the problem, and Cigna will pay for only six pills a month. Kaiser Permanente plans a similiar policy. Since its introduction in late March, Viagra has had one of the most successful debuts in pharmaceutical history, with some 20,000 prescriptions written daily.</p>
        <p>EUROPE  Locking Exchange Rates  The dollar, after reigning supreme in global finance for the better part of this century, will soon face a new rival that could prove much more powerful than the German mark or Japanese yen: a single European currency, the euro. This weekend, 11 of the European Union's 15 member nations -- those that have chosen to participate in the first stage of monetary union -- will lock their exchange rates together. ''The euro has the potential to reshape European and international financial markets,'' the I.M.F. said, and to transform the world monetary system.</p>
        <p>MICROSOFT  States Slam Windows  Attorneys general from 13 states are preparing a joint antitrust action against Microsoft, seeking to block the company's release in June of Windows 98, the next version of its ubiquitious operating system for personal computers. Several said they would rather act with the United States Department of Justice, which has been conducting its own antitrust investigation, but they fear that the Federal agency is acting too slowly. Any lawsuit would become much more complicated, they added, once the software goes on sale.</p>
        <p>PEOPLE  Honda's New Driver  Honda's president and chief executive, Nobuhiko Kawamoto, will retire. An engineer, he led the company to record profits and market share in the United States and Japan over the last eight years, after making his mark in 1974 as a member of the team that designed the first engine to meet Federal clean air regulations without a catalytic converter. Mr. Kawamoto has infuriated Detroit executives by contending that global warming is a serious problem that the auto industry should address. He will be succeeded by Hiroyuki Yoshino, Honda's head of research and vehicle development and a close associate. . . . Mario J. Gabelli, the mutual fund manager, wants to sell part of his fund and investment empire to the public. But he plans to keep control of the company -- and, perhaps, many of his best investment ideas. . . . Pepsi-Cola, stung by the lagging performance of its flagship brand, said its chief global marketing officer, Brian Swette, would leave at the end of the month and would be replaced by a three-executive marketing council.</p>
        <p>UTILITIES  Pollution Sale Halted  At the urging of New York State, the Long Island Lighting Company said it would stop selling, to polluters in the Midwest and South, pollution credits it earned by cleaning its own smokestacks. The 1990 Federal Clean Air Act established the marketplace trading of the right to pollute as an inexpensive way to clean up the environment. But as New York State and its neighbors have learned, the marketplace cannot stop the wind from blowing pollution eastward. . . . Texas Utilities won Energy Group P.L.C., one of Britain's last remaining independent utilities, after another American utility company, Pacificorp, said it would not try to beat a $7.4 billion bid. . . . Two fast-growing Nevada utilities, Nevada Power and Sierra Pacific Resources, agreed to a $1.2 billion merger.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
