<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DIARY</title>
    <meta content="23DIAR3" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1041146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E1DA113DF930A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="2279" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL WELLMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RUSSIA  Floating Like a Butterfly Or Sinking Like a Stone?  The Russian Government moved hastily last week to avert financial collapse with a series of drastic measures, including delaying payments for 90 days on foreign debt owed mostly by banks, a restructuring of Government bonds and the sacrifice of the ruble to market forces. The value of the Russian currency is now free to float as low as 9.5 to the dollar, a risky step -- tantamount to devaluation -- that many people fear could prompt a new round of inflation. It could also wipe out as much as a third of the ruble's purchasing power in an economy heavily dependent on imports. The decision came after a request for $22.6 billion from the West was turned down. Standard &amp; Poor's cut Russia's long-term foreign-currency debt rating by two notches. For this beggar at a McDonald's in Moscow, the collapsing ruble was not of immediate concern.</p>
        <p>THE MARKET  A Roller-Coaster Ride  The global economic crisis and the aftermath of United States strikes on Afghanistan and the Sudan ravaged Wall Street stocks on Friday. After rising strongly early last week, the Dow fell slightly on Wednesday, more than 80 points on Thursday, and another 77.76 points on Friday, to close the week at 8533.65. Earlier on Friday the Dow had been down more than 200 points. The ups and downs over the week left some traders holding their heads.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RUSSIA  Floating Like a Butterfly Or Sinking Like a Stone?  The Russian Government moved hastily last week to avert financial collapse with a series of drastic measures, including delaying payments for 90 days on foreign debt owed mostly by banks, a restructuring of Government bonds and the sacrifice of the ruble to market forces. The value of the Russian currency is now free to float as low as 9.5 to the dollar, a risky step -- tantamount to devaluation -- that many people fear could prompt a new round of inflation. It could also wipe out as much as a third of the ruble's purchasing power in an economy heavily dependent on imports. The decision came after a request for $22.6 billion from the West was turned down. Standard &amp; Poor's cut Russia's long-term foreign-currency debt rating by two notches. For this beggar at a McDonald's in Moscow, the collapsing ruble was not of immediate concern.</p>
        <p>THE MARKET  A Roller-Coaster Ride  The global economic crisis and the aftermath of United States strikes on Afghanistan and the Sudan ravaged Wall Street stocks on Friday. After rising strongly early last week, the Dow fell slightly on Wednesday, more than 80 points on Thursday, and another 77.76 points on Friday, to close the week at 8533.65. Earlier on Friday the Dow had been down more than 200 points. The ups and downs over the week left some traders holding their heads.</p>
        <p>COMPUTERS  An iMac Moment  Shares of Apple Computer climbed to near a three-year high after the company's debut of its iMac personal computer, being scrutinized here by a potential buyer in New York. Apple said it had advance orders for 150,000 of the new computers, which, the company says, will get users onto the Internet very quickly. Dell Computer is also flying high, reporting a 62 percent gain in earnings for its second fiscal quarter, exceeding Wall Street analysts' estimates. Dell also cited market research showing that it had moved into the No. 1 position in the United States in desktop computer sales, and the No. 2 position over all, behind Compaq Computer.</p>
        <p>JAPAN  Honda's Global Dividend  After years of taking grief from its Japanese rivals for its overseas emphasis, Honda Motor is now benefiting more than ever from that globalization. Even with the domestic market shrinking rapidly, Honda, Japan's No. 3 auto maker behind Toyota and Nissan, reported a 26 percent profit gain for the latest quarter, largely because of sales in Europe and in Honda's largest market, the United States. Other Japanese car makers did not have such a good week. Moody's Investors Service cut its rating of Toyota Motor's long-term debt, citing concern that falling sales in Asia would eat into profits. The downgrading followed an earlier announcement by Moody's that it had lowered the credit ratings of Nissan Motor and Mitsubishi Motors. Still, Toyota's credit rating remains well above those of General Motors, Ford Motor and Volkswagen.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY  This New House  Housing construction jumped last month for the second straight month -- its fastest pace in more than a decade. New housing units were going up at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 1,718,000 units in July, the heaviest activity since 1987. The Federal Reserve did its part to help that boom by deciding to leave short-term interest rates at 5.5 percent. Given that United States consumer prices rose a seasonally adjusted 0.2 percent in July after a 0.1 percent increase in June, the Fed's action was not unexpected. . . . The trade deficit narrowed slightly, to $14.2 billion in June, but was still not far from the record high as deficits with troubled Asian nations continued to soar. The June deficit was off 8.9 percent from the record $15.5 billion in May, marking the first decline since January.</p>
        <p>GLOBAL WARMING  It's Melting, It's Melting  Alaska is thawing, and much of northern Russia and Canada with it. And many scientists say the warming of these cold regions is one of the most telling signals that the planet's climate is changing. Experts have long said that in an era of global warming, this bellwether region should warm more and faster than the Earth as a whole, and that is just how things are turning out, to the consternation of walruses and people alike. According to a 1997 study, longer summers have allowed Alaska's tourism industry to grow and should expand shipping in the region, too. But the warmer weather is taking a heavy toll on forests, and by extension, eventually the forestry industry. The warming has promoted a buildup of tree-eating insects in general and has prompted some species, like the spruce budworm, to move farther north. Across southern Alaska, some of the forest is more than sick; it is dead or dying, and spruce bark beetles are the killers. Scientists estimate that a third to half of Alaska's white spruce have died the last 15 years.</p>
        <p>JOBS  Downsizing With Less Gusto  The country's most comprehensive survey of permanent layoffs found that in the last three years, downsizing affected a smaller percentage of the work force than in any other period this decade. But the layoff rate is still significantly higher than in the 1980's, and women now get pink slips almost as often as men. Eight million people were pushed out of their jobs involuntarily in the 1995-97 period, the Labor Department said in its report, or one out of every 15 adult job holders. That was down from 8.4 million in the previous three years, or one in 12 workers, the decade's worst performance. But downsizing is still occurring at a faster rate than in the late 1980's. Then the displacement rate was one out of every 18 job holders. (Article, page 11.)</p>
        <p>SEMICONDUCTORS  The Chips Are Down  Two computer chip makers said they expected sharply lower quarterly results because of Asia's economic crisis, and a third said its quarterly net earnings fell 81 percent. The warnings from LSI Logic and National Semiconductor, coupled with the results from Analog Devices, suggested that any talk of a recovery in the chip manufacturing industry might be premature. Chip companies are finding that they are much more vulnerable to Asia's problems than they had thought. ''When something like Asia happens, it doesn't really matter how good your products are or how well managed your company is, you're going to feel it,'' said Drew Peck, an analyst at SG Cowen &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>SWEDEN  Business@ArcticCircle.com  A mouse pad made of reindeer hide? Well, maybe that's a bad example of a high-technology business with a big future. But Sweden has a few other ideas up its reindeer coat-covered sleeve, including extreme telecommuting. In an effort to slow the flight of people from what is already one of the world's most sparsely settled areas, the Government is encouraging businesses to set up computerized telephone-call centers in remote Arctic Circle villages -- such as Arvidsjaur, where Sara Andersson, above, is director of trade -- and to staff them with young people who otherwise would be scouting for work in the population centers to the south, or abroad. The companies benefit from special Government subsidies, and they find that outlying parts of Sweden have a supply of educated, keyboard-literate young people with the Swedes' noted ability to function comfortably in several languages. Swedes and telephones have a cozy relationship: The country has the highest number of lines per person in the world -- 70 for every 100 inhabitants -- and 44 percent of Swedes have mobile phones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
