<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pushing the Limits Of an Irreplaceable Resource</title>
    <meta content="08INTR$16" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Natural World" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="WATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7DC173AF93BA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pushing the Limits Of an Irreplaceable Resource</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William K Stevens article surveys man's effects on the earth's water cycle and progress toward mitigating some of the harm he has done; photos; map; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE earth came into being, according to the ascendant view among scientists, when chunks of rocky matter that had coalesced from the particles of an interstellar nebula, the same one from which the sun materialized, began clumping together under the force of mutual gravity about 4.6 billion years ago. More chunks along with comets continued to bombard the planet's growing mass, according to this view, bringing with them one of the earth's most basic materials: water.</p>
        <p>Oceans formed. A few of the rocky chunks crashing into the nascent planet might have been so big that the heat of their impact temporarily vaporized the young seas. But eventually the period of heavy bombardment ended, things more or less settled down, and within about 800 million years after its birth, the earth had assumed its identity as the Watery Planet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE earth came into being, according to the ascendant view among scientists, when chunks of rocky matter that had coalesced from the particles of an interstellar nebula, the same one from which the sun materialized, began clumping together under the force of mutual gravity about 4.6 billion years ago. More chunks along with comets continued to bombard the planet's growing mass, according to this view, bringing with them one of the earth's most basic materials: water.</p>
        <p>Oceans formed. A few of the rocky chunks crashing into the nascent planet might have been so big that the heat of their impact temporarily vaporized the young seas. But eventually the period of heavy bombardment ended, things more or less settled down, and within about 800 million years after its birth, the earth had assumed its identity as the Watery Planet.</p>
        <p>All or most of the water the earth has today was here then, and it may be about all the planet will ever have.</p>
        <p>Of this supply, 97.5 percent resides in the oceans and seas as salt water. Most of the remaining 2.5 percent, the planet's entire ration of fresh water, is imprisoned in glaciers and ice caps, unavailable for use by people and other living things. In all, less than 1 percent -- the actual figure is put by some experts at .77 of 1 percent -- is in lakes, rivers, swamps, aquifers and other such receptacles, or floating as clouds or invisible vapor in the atmosphere or locked up in soils and plant tissues.</p>
        <p>Even that overstates water's true availability. The renewable freshwater supply on land, constantly replenished as part of a perpetual cycle in which water evaporates from the oceans and falls as saltless precipitation, has been estimated to represent a microscopic eight-thousandths of all the water on earth.</p>
        <p>This small, finite supply is the water that actually supports human existence. Except for oxygen, it is the most vital substance on the planet for people.</p>
        <p>In pursuit of this indispensable elixir, humans have in recent history multiplied their impact from the significant to the enormous.  Population expansion and the inexorable march of industrial technology and urbanization have pushed people to use 35 times as much water as they did three centuries ago. One recent study concluded that more than half of all accessible water is now diverted for human use.</p>
        <p>The amount appropriated by people continues to grow as the human population expands. In some places serious water shortages loom, even as the world as a whole wastes water extravagantly. While there is some cause for encouragement in the overall picture, there is also serious concern that some regions will have enough water for everyday needs, or to produce enough food -- but not both.</p>
        <p>People are not only dependent on water, but have been at its mercy. Ancient civilizations from the Middle East to Latin America, possibly including the fabled Maya, have expired for lack of it. Floods have been a fearsome occurrence throughout history; the deaths last month of more than 10,000 Central Americans from floods caused by Hurricane Mitch are a fresh example.</p>
        <p>Virtually every culture has its flood myth, and water has long been an object of awe and of verse and story, from Samuel Taylor Coleridge's Ancient Mariner (''Water, water, everywhere/Nor any drop to drink'') to the cowboy songs of the Sons of the Pioneers (''Cool, clear water''). People have prayed for water and fought over it. Sometimes they have used it as a weapon; in 1938, for instance, China dynamited dikes on the Yellow River to destroy part of an invading Japanese army.</p>
        <p>But it is at the mundane level of day-to-day use that the relationship between humans and water has acquired new dimensions.  People trap water, tap it, rechannel it, transfer it, pollute it, consume it, feed it to livestock, ladle it onto farm fields (by far the biggest single use) and flush it through factories, power plants and toilets.</p>
        <p>In this way, people have significantly altered the earth's life-giving water cycle; indeed, humans are now an important part of it. They have drastically upset the workings of freshwater ecosystems, with a consequent loss of biological variety and vitality. By closely corseting rivers and streams, they have denied water to flood plains, and in the process have often squeezed flood water into faster, deeper, more dangerous sluices.</p>
        <p>Yet the biosphere never really runs out of water. Only a minor part of what is withdrawn from nature is consumed; most is released back into the water cycle to be used again. Even the water consumed by living creatures finds its way back into the cycle when the creatures excrete, exhale or die. Because of this capacity for renewal, some experts believe there is probably enough water to meet burgeoning humanity's basic drinking, cooking and sanitation needs for some time. That is the theory. In reality, more than a billion people do not have access to clean drinking water now. The reason, critics say, is that many developing countries, along with international aid agencies, have not provided community-level drinking water and sanitation systems. Plenty of water may be stored behind big dams, but it does as much harm as good there, and sometimes maybe more, when it becomes as polluted as it has in many parts of the world.</p>
        <p>Even if the pollution disappeared and everyone on the earth had enough good water for everyday living, experts say, many countries would still run out of water in the future -- if they insist on producing all their own food. The vagaries of the atmosphere declare that some regions are rain-rich and others rain-poor. The Middle East, Northern Africa and the American Southwest are prime examples of rain-poor regions. There, water means wealth and lack of it means relative poverty. So a sometimes-bitter competition has arisen between expanding urban populations -- which are exploding especially in the developing world -- and agricultural interests.</p>
        <p>The amount of water used for irrigation has dropped somewhat around the world as the big cities have siphoned off more for their own use. Eventually, some experts believe, some dry areas will not be able to serve both the needs of farming and those of the ballooning cities. If these regions are to meet everyday water requirements, they might have to permanently import all or most of their food. This raises the prospect that lack of water will make some countries chronically dependent on others, or on the international community at large.</p>
        <p>Water has long been a source of conflict between regions, cultures and countries. In California in the 1920's, the Los Angeles Valley aqueduct and pipeline were bombed repeatedly by those who wanted to prevent diversions of water from agricultural land to Los Angeles. Diversion of river waters between India and both Pakistan and Bangladesh was a chronic source of tension for decades. In the 1967 Arab-Israeli war, Israel destroyed Arab diversion works on the Jordan River and occupied the West Bank, under which lies a major aquifer. In 1988, when Boutros Boutros-Ghali, who would later become the United Nations Secretary General, was Egypt's foreign affairs minister, he predicted that ''the next war in our region will be over the waters of the Nile, not politics.''</p>
        <p>Tensions caused by the clash between scarce water and ever more abundant populations are likely only to intensify. The study that concluded that people are using half the world's accessible water supply also noted that new dam construction might increase that supply by only about 10 percent over the next 30 years. Meanwhile, population is expected to grow at about four times that rate.</p>
        <p>In the face of these increasing pressures, there are some encouraging signs. The conventional belief, for years, has been that water use unavoidably rises with population and economic growth. That was true in the United States when its industrial economy was expanding most rapidly. In the first eight decades of the 20th century, growth in water use by Americans outstripped population growth by about 5 to 2.</p>
        <p>But recently, developed countries, possibly charting a path for poorer ones, have begun using water more efficiently. In the United States, water use has actually declined -- by about 20 percent ar person from 1980 to 1995, according to the United States Geological Survey. Experts attribute the decline to new water-saving technologies and practices ranging from less wasteful irrigation gear to water-stingy toilets.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, as in the Western states, the switch was inspired by the prospect of water shortages and the increasing costs of irrigation. At the same time, the best sites for dams had long since been exploited, and building new ones had become increasingly costly. Dam construction was also inhibited by growing concern about their negative ecological impact. So the emphasis, at least in the United States, has shifted from scrambling to expand water supplies to using water more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Water in the industrial world has also become cleaner in the last three decades. Many once-polluted rivers, lakes and streams have been cleared of industrial wastes, and treatment plants have long since made water universally drinkable in the developed countries. The Hudson River, like many American streams, was once given up for dead but today abounds with life. People can even swim in it -- unthinkable 30 years ago.</p>
        <p>Another ecological disruption is also being remedied. All across the country, from Maine to the Grand Canyon to California, the flow of water from dams is being readjusted and in some cases dams are being removed to accommodate aquatic ecosystems once again.</p>
        <p>The millennium is not here, however. The change in humans' handling of water has only begun even in the United States, where it is probably the farthest advanced. The continuing runoff of millions of tons of nitrogen from farm fields into rivers and streams alone, could negate many of the constructive efforts by choking the water with too many nutrients. And big dams are still being built, mainly in the developing world, as witnessed most strikingly by the biggest of all, the gigantic Three Gorges project under construction on the Yangtze River in China.</p>
        <p>There is a major wild card in all of this. Most climate scientists believe that emissions of gases like carbon dioxide will raise the earth's average global temperature by about 3.5 degrees over the next century. A warmer planet, many scientists say, would intensify the water cycle: Floods might become worse. But the land would dry out more and faster between rain storms, and where it seldom rains, the warmth would make droughts more severe.</p>
        <p>For now, at least, the big question is whether humanity can learn to use an irreplaceable but maybe adequate resource in a way that can slake everyone's thirst without continuing to damage the natural order.</p>
        <p>WATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
