<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Most Reliable Dinner Mate: German Riesling</title>
    <meta content="30WINE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1050338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="WINE TALK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Prial, Frank J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Wine Talk</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E5DA1E39F933A0575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Most Reliable Dinner Mate: German Riesling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank J. Prial</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Prial, Frank J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank J Prial Wine Talk column on German rieslings, reputed to be best wines to have with food; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Burg Landshut, a ruined castle high above medieval Bernkastel, the best known of the Mosel wine towns of Germany, offers one of the most spectacular views of vines in Europe. The vineyards sweep southward toward Brauneberg and west past Graach and Wehlen to Zeltigen, all of them legendary German wine villages, too. The view is never more stunning than a few weeks from now when summer is truly past, the leaves are turning and the river's steep banks are carpeted a bright yellow gold.</p>
        <p>I visit this magical place when I can, which is not often enough, but always with mixed feelings of anticipation and guilt. Anticipation because of the unmatchable wines, the beauty of the area, the overwhelming sense of history it imparts. And guilt for having failed, over the years, truly to convey the profound pleasures these wines can give. The wines are rieslings, the elegant, complex, long-lived white wines from the steep-sloped banks of the Rhine river and its equally famous tributary, the Mosel; from the Pfalz region, and from Alsace, in France.</p>
        <p>What has the unending search for something new in wine brought us in the United States in recent years? Domestic merlot, sangiovese and viognier, mostly pale imitations of their European counterparts. Domestic rieslings have been around longer than those three, but they, too, rarely approach the wines of Germany and Alsace. Might it be time for the real thing?</p>
        <p>What prompt these ruminations are some recent observations by David Rosengarten of the Food Network and by Willie Gluckstern, the wine writer and consultant, in his new book, ''The Wine Avenger'' (Fireside, $11). Both agree: German rieslings are the best wines to have with food, more flexible than any chardonnay or merlot.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Burg Landshut, a ruined castle high above medieval Bernkastel, the best known of the Mosel wine towns of Germany, offers one of the most spectacular views of vines in Europe. The vineyards sweep southward toward Brauneberg and west past Graach and Wehlen to Zeltigen, all of them legendary German wine villages, too. The view is never more stunning than a few weeks from now when summer is truly past, the leaves are turning and the river's steep banks are carpeted a bright yellow gold.</p>
        <p>I visit this magical place when I can, which is not often enough, but always with mixed feelings of anticipation and guilt. Anticipation because of the unmatchable wines, the beauty of the area, the overwhelming sense of history it imparts. And guilt for having failed, over the years, truly to convey the profound pleasures these wines can give. The wines are rieslings, the elegant, complex, long-lived white wines from the steep-sloped banks of the Rhine river and its equally famous tributary, the Mosel; from the Pfalz region, and from Alsace, in France.</p>
        <p>What has the unending search for something new in wine brought us in the United States in recent years? Domestic merlot, sangiovese and viognier, mostly pale imitations of their European counterparts. Domestic rieslings have been around longer than those three, but they, too, rarely approach the wines of Germany and Alsace. Might it be time for the real thing?</p>
        <p>What prompt these ruminations are some recent observations by David Rosengarten of the Food Network and by Willie Gluckstern, the wine writer and consultant, in his new book, ''The Wine Avenger'' (Fireside, $11). Both agree: German rieslings are the best wines to have with food, more flexible than any chardonnay or merlot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosengarten said: ''The white wine I select for food more than any other is dry German riesling. This is no accident. I believe it to be the most flexible white wine in the world for food.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gluckstern writes: ''Nothing, I repeat, nothing, marries better with more foods than riesling. Whereas other white wine varieties might be generally serviceable with food, German rieslings fairly sing at the table.'' Mr. Gluckstern is not given to half measures. Of the pairing of red meat with one of the richer German rieslings, he writes: ''What's truly astounding is how perversely delicious they taste together.'' But he advises: ''Keep your eyes closed. The concept of white wine with red meat might short-circuit your neural transmitters.''</p>
        <p>I'm not so sure about red meat -- at least, not our steaks and chops. But in northern climes, even in Scotland and Scandinavia, great rieslings have always been paired with game: venison, wild boar and the pungent flesh of game birds like pheasants and wild ducks. With fine German wines so unfashionable in this country, it might be a mistake to plunge directly into the most extreme combinations. But there is no reason not to enjoy good Rhine wines or Mosels with roast chicken and farm-bred ducks and turkeys. A rich riesling could turn this year's Thanksgiving dinner into a memorable event.</p>
        <p>Riesling is king in Germany, and there are not many princes. Chardonnay is an interloper, and lesser white varieties like sauvignon blanc, chenin blanc and the upstart viognier are dismissed out of hand. What's more, in the best vineyards here and along the Rhine, so are other German grapes, even though many of them, like Kerner and Muller-Thurgau, are related -- some closely, some less so -- to the riesling.</p>
        <p>In an attempt to cater to the worldwide trend to dry wines, both red and white, the German vintners have begun in recent years to turn out trocken (dry) and halbtrocken (semidry) wines. Some of them are quite good.</p>
        <p>But the glory of great riesling is the relationship between sweetness and acid; they are the yin and the yang of the best German white wines. Alcohol is less important in German wines; they rarely exceed 11 percent and most range from 9 to 10. This makes them easier to drink than most French wines and some of California's alcoholic monsters.</p>
        <p>German wines are ranked by ripeness at the time the grapes are picked. Ripeness is determined by the grape's sugar content. The rules are complicated, and the language even more so. Suffice it to say that the levels most often encountered in quality table wines, in increasing levels of natural sugar, are kabinett, spatlese and auslese.</p>
        <p>These wines are usually fermented dry -- that is, until all the sugar has been turned into alcohol and carbon dioxide. Then a small quantity of unfermented grape juice called susswein is added to them. Some grapes with exceptionally high levels of sugar are turned into sweet dessert wines known as beerenauslese and trockenbeerenauslese.</p>
        <p>My own preference is for the traditionally made wines with a touch of sweetness. When the sugar is perfectly balanced by the wine's acidity, it doesn't seem sweet at all -- just extra rich and complex.</p>
        <p>I recall a lunch a few years ago in a kitschy old Bernkastel restaurant with the winemaker Karl-Heinz Lauerburg and his son Patrick. We had spent the morning in the Lauerburg cellars, sampling rieslings going back to 1949. Lunch was a handsome trout, poached briefly with a few herbs, accompanied by a riesling from the Sonnenuhr vineyard in nearby Wehlen. Among Mosel vineyards, the Wehlener Sonnenuhr is almost as famous as the Doctor vineyard in Bernkastel, the source of some of Lauerburg's finest wines.</p>
        <p>''Sonnenuhr'' means ''sundial'' in German and indeed, a huge sundial graces the upper reaches of the vineyard that bears its name. It was supposed to tell the vineyard workers when the day was ended.</p>
        <p>Mosel wines -- you can tell them by their green bottles -- are usually a bit more delicate and drier than wines from the Rhine vineyards, which are identified by brown bottles. It is the richer, more assertive Rhine wines, from communes like Hochheim, Eltville, Johannisberg and Rudesheim, that are most often associated with heavier dishes.</p>
        <p>Two hundred years ago, German wines, called Hock by the English, who were their best customers, were highly prized. And Thomas Jefferson was particularly fond of the wines of Schloss Johannisberg. As late as the 1920's, wines of the best German estates, like Marcobrunn and Scharzhofberg on the Rhine and Brauneberg on the Mosel, were even more expensive than the first growths of Bordeaux.</p>
        <p>There are a few encouraging signs today. At Union Pacific, one of New York's better new restaurants, Urs Kaufmannis, the sommelier, has assembled a wine list that includes a good selection of German wines to go with Rocco DeSpirito's inventive cooking. At Lutece, Eberhard Muller has extended the wine list to include attractive German wines. Lutece has a fine selection of Alsatian wines, a legacy of its former owner. Andre Soltner, himself an Alsatian.</p>
        <p>Germany has a long list of Michelin-starred restaurants, and in them, German wines are once again associated with the finest food. Perhaps, one day, it will happen here.</p>
        <p>Unfamiliarity Breeds Bargains</p>
        <p>BECAUSE German wines are relatively unfamiliar in this country, and even the rarest bottles have yet to attract the attention of collectors, prices are still reasonable -- often remarkably so. It is true, the strange names can be an obstacle, but not an insurmountable one.</p>
        <p>Here are a few examples of good rieslings that are available in this country, or will be soon. Availability is often limited because the market is so small. Some of the best wine shops in New York don't even list German wines in all their catalogues. The 1996 vintage was an excellent one in Germany, but there has not been a really poor year in the last decade. Three other particularly good years were 1990, 1992 and 1994.</p>
        <p>Alsace, on the western bank of the Rhine, is French, but its vineyards produce rieslings that always rival and occasionally best those of their German neighbors. Alsatian rieslings are almost always drier than the German versions, and the producer's name usually precedes the description of the wine on the label.</p>
        <p>KABINETT</p>
        <p>Bernkasteler Badstube 1996, from Kesselstatt; about $15.</p>
        <p>Urziger Wurzgarten 1996, from Christoffel Erben; about $20.</p>
        <p>Ayler Kupp 1996 from Carl Graff; about $10.</p>
        <p>SPATLESE</p>
        <p>Wachenheimer Goldbachel 1996, from Josef Biffar; about $30.</p>
        <p>Wehlener Sonnenuhr 1996, from Kerpen; about $20.</p>
        <p>Niersteiner Orbel 1996, from J. Strub; about $16.</p>
        <p>Brauneberger Juffer 1996, from Willi Haag; about $25.</p>
        <p>AUSLESE</p>
        <p>Maximin-Grunhauser Abtsberg 1996 from von Schubert; about $30.</p>
        <p>Deidesheimer Paradiesgarten 1995 from von Buhl; about $27.</p>
        <p>ALSACE</p>
        <p>Trimbach Clos Ste.-Hune 1992; about $55.</p>
        <p>Hugel Jubilee Reserve Personnelle 1995; about $30.</p>
        <p>Marc Kreydenweiss Wiebelsberg Grand Cru 1996, about $25.</p>
        <p>WINE TALK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
