<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y07BRI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1060120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05EEDA153EF934A35752C1A96E958260" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Christopher S. Wren</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: CRITICIZED ON ECONOMIC RETREAT -- Deputy Secretary of State Strobe Talbott attacked Russia's retreat from free-market economics and warned that financial decline could lead to ''political drift, turmoil and even crack up'' there. Help from the International Monetary Fund, Mr. Talbott said in a speech at Stanford University, ''must wait until the Russian Government shows itself willing and able to make the difficult structural adjustments necessary for recovery and growth.'''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: CRITICIZED ON ECONOMIC RETREAT -- Deputy Secretary of State Strobe Talbott attacked Russia's retreat from free-market economics and warned that financial decline could lead to ''political drift, turmoil and even crack up'' there. Help from the International Monetary Fund, Mr. Talbott said in a speech at Stanford University, ''must wait until the Russian Government shows itself willing and able to make the difficult structural adjustments necessary for recovery and growth.'''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>RUSSIA: THE TRUTH IS NOW THE WORD -- Pravda, once the official organ of the Soviet Communist Party, was forced by court order to change its name. The newspaper, whose name means ''the truth,'' has now appeared on newsstands as Slovo, the word. The change resulted from a battle between editorial factions, one of which began publishing a new version of the paper in 1994 with the same name, in virtually the same typeface. (The old Pravda is shown at top above, with its competitor.)</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: U.S. LAWYER PRESSES SLAVE-LABOR CASE -- An American lawyer who has sued companies over slave labor in World War II demanded that the new Government include his group in talks about a compensation fund. The lawyer, Edward Fagan, said he would never agree to a Government-run fund.</p>
        <p>Edmund L. Andrews (NYT)</p>
        <p>YUGOSLAVIA: INSPECTORS' VISAS SOUGHT -- Richard C. Holbrooke, the United States special envoy, said in Berlin that President Slobodan Milosevic clearly agreed last month to allow United Nations war-crimes investigators access to Yugoslavia, including Kosovo. But Belgrade has refused to give the visas.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: PINOCHET EXTRADITION REQUESTED -- The Government agreed to seek the extradition from Britain of Gen. Augusto Pinochet, a move that could send the general, the ex-dictator of Chile, to trial on a charge of genocide. The Chilean Government immediately recalled its ambassador, and the Spanish Foreign Minister, Abel Matutes, conceded that the case ''inevitably has important political repercussions.''</p>
        <p>(NYT)</p>
        <p>TURKEY: NEW RULES ON THE BOSPORUS -- Turkey imposed new navigation rules for the Bosporus, moving to eliminate competitors in the race to carry Caspian Sea oil to world markets. Turkey, which says increased traffic would lead to collisions and oil spills, is seeking a pipeline to skirt the Bosporus. Turkey can stop traffic when currents are unfavorable, stop any ship on legal grounds and require increased use of local pilots.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>INDONESIA: SUPPORT FROM THE I.M.F. -- The lending agency approved a $960 million loan to the Government and urged it to speed the pace of banking reform and of refinancing corporate debt. But it also praised the direction of the economy. Michel Camdessus, the I.M.F.'s managing director, said, ''Due to good policy implementation, the Indonesian economy is showing welcome signs of stabilization.''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>JAPAN: 4 SPY SATELLITES BY 2003 -- The Government announced it would launch four intelligence-gathering satellites, increasing its military abilities in ways that are widely expected to cause unease at home and regionally. The Cabinet approved the launchings by the spring of 2003. Japan became alarmed when North Korea launched a rocket over its territory in September.</p>
        <p>Nicholas D. Kristof (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHINA: CONTROLS ON MIXED MARRIAGES -- Shanghai has moved to control the increasing number of marriages between residents and foreigners, BBC World News reported. Starting next month, the BBC said, Chinese in Shanghai who want to marry a foreigner have to register with city authorities, who will rule in a month on allowing or prohibiting marriages. Shanghai had 3,000 mixed marriages last year.</p>
        <p>TAJIKISTAN: RESISTANCE TO WARLORD'S THREATS -- Tajik and former opposition groups joined forces to combat a warlord, Makhmud Khudoberdyev, who threatens to blow up a dam and flood large areas. Government troops and their allies retook control of Khudzhand, but still faced pockets of resistance.  (Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>LEBANON: ISRAEL CURBS TOPSOIL THIEVES -- The Israeli Army has taken measures to stop its citizens from stealing topsoil in southern Lebanon and taking it back, a United Nations spokesman said. The army confirmed that Israelis were removing soil from an Israeli-occupied zone, said the spokesman for the United Nations peacekeepers in Lebanon, Timur Goksel.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>UNITED NATIONS: U.S. IS SPURNED AGAIN -- The United States was again denied a seat on a financial watchdog committee because it owes the United Nations more than $1 billion, despite having paid $197 million this week to avoid forfeiting its vote in the General Assembly. The United States, which was voted off the panel, the Advisory Committee on Administrative and Budgetary Questions, in 1996, finished last in a field of four candidates.</p>
        <p>Barbara Crossette (NYT)</p>
        <p>COLOMBIA: REBELS GIVEN A WIDE AREA -- Rebel commanders began taking control of 15,000 square miles in the southeast that the Government ceded in an effort to clear the way for the first peace talks in six years. President Andres Pastrana ordered 2,000 members of his security forces to pull out of five municipalities that straddle Caqueta and Meta Provinces for at least three months.  (Reuters)</p>
        <p>ARGENTINA: AFRICA WARNED ON WARMING -- Africa is more likely to suffer from global warming than other regions largely because of its limited ability to react to climate change, a United Nations committee predicted at a conference. The rest of the world will not be spared,  either, the panel said, with the North and South Poles, as well as the Pacific and Caribbean, also badly affected.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>Compiled by Christopher S. Wren</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
