<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EXXON AND MOBIL ANNOUNCE $80 BILLION DEAL TO CREATE WORLD'S LARGEST COMPANY</title>
    <meta content="02OIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981203T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066598"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BIG OIL: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exxon Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mobil Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Exxon Mobil</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myerson, Allen R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raymond, Lee R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Noto, Lucio A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DE153BF931A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EXXON AND MOBIL ANNOUNCE $80 BILLION DEAL TO CREATE WORLD'S LARGEST COMPANY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN R. MYERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myerson, Allen R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exxon, nation's largest oil company, agrees to buy Mobil, next largest, for $80 billion in stock, to form world's biggest corporation; antitrust regulators will scrutinize merger and probably force sale of some gas stations and refineries; so great are doubts over whether companies will win approval or accept required divestitures that investors send stock prices of both companies down; companies say they would save $2.8 billion annually; about 9,000 workers out of 123,000 worldwide would likely lose their jobs; Exxon chmn Lee R Raymond would add title of president in combined company; Exxon Mobil, as company would be called, would have sales of $204 billion; Mobil chief exec Lucio A Noto would be vice chairman; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Exxon, the nation's largest oil company, agreed yesterday to buy Mobil, the next largest, for $80 billion in stock, to form the world's biggest corporation.</p>
        <p>While the merger is not likely to have any immediate effect on prices at the pump, antitrust regulators will  certainly scrutinize it and probably force the sale of some gas stations and refineries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Exxon, the nation's largest oil company, agreed yesterday to buy Mobil, the next largest, for $80 billion in stock, to form the world's biggest corporation.</p>
        <p>While the merger is not likely to have any immediate effect on prices at the pump, antitrust regulators will  certainly scrutinize it and probably force the sale of some gas stations and refineries.</p>
        <p>So great are the doubts over whether the companies will win approval or accept the required divestitures that investors sent the stock prices of both companies down yesterday. Shares of Exxon dropped $3.375, to $71.625, and Mobil fell $2.25, to $83.75, well below Exxon's offer of $99.01 a share, based on Monday's closing Exxon stock price.</p>
        <p>The agreement would reunite the two largest pieces of John D. Rockefeller's Standard Oil Trust, broken up in 1911 in the nation's most celebrated antitrust case.</p>
        <p>The companies contended yesterday that they now confront global competitors and plunging energy prices, making their combination and the resulting savings a necessity. But while the companies foresee savings of $2.8 billion annually, the greatest costs would be paid by employees. About 9,000 workers out of 123,000 worldwide are likely to find themselves without jobs, the companies said.</p>
        <p>Lee R. Raymond, the chairman and chief executive of Exxon, who would add the title of president in the combined company, said repeatedly that further efficiency, not brute size, was his goal. ''This is the case of the whole being greater than the sum of the parts,'' he said at a news conference, later adding: ''I have always had the view that the objective is to be best. If in being best you also have to be biggest, that's fine.''</p>
        <p>Exxon Mobil, as the company would be called, would have sales of $204 billion, surpassing General Motors as the world's largest company and Royal Dutch/Shell Group as the largest oil company. It would still appear to motorists as the familiar separate chains, with gas stations and oil cans bearing the distinct brand names.</p>
        <p>Officials of the Federal Trade Commission, saying they held their first discussions with the companies yesterday, had no comment. Antitrust experts said the regulators were likely to review the effects city by city and region by region, probably requiring the sale of at least some gas stations and refineries. ''If large divestitures are required, it could be that the deal doesn't make sense,'' said Eleanor M. Fox, who teaches antitrust law at New York University.</p>
        <p>But many industry analysts agreed with Mr. Raymond and Lucio A. Noto, Mobil's chief executive, who would be the combined company's vice chairman, that the corporations and their shareholders would fare better if united.</p>
        <p>The proposed deal comes as mergers are also welding many of the world's largest banks, auto makers and telephone companies. The companies said that they would have about a 13 percent share of the gasoline market in the United States, compared with about 14 percent for the partnership between Shell and Texaco and 10.5 percent for British Petroleum should it complete its planned $48.2 billion purchase of the Amoco Corporation.</p>
        <p>Analysts praised the latest combination, saying that other industry mergers would follow. ''To create lower costs and greater efficiencies, they had to go outside their own organizations,'' said Frederick P. Leuffer of Bear, Stearns. ''That same question is now before the other major oil companies.''</p>
        <p>He and other analysts said they considered Mobil's $80 billion price  to be fairly high but reasonable, considering the benefits. Mr. Raymond said the purchase would have no effect on profitability in the first year and would begin adding to earnings per share after that.</p>
        <p>Exxon would trade 1.32 of its shares for each Mobil share, leaving Exxon shareholders owning 70 percent of the resulting company in a deal expected to close by mid-1999. The company would be based at Exxon's headquarters in Irving, Tex., a suburb of Dallas. Mobil's headquarters in Fairfax, Va., would become the center for refining and sales, while Houston would be home to exploration, production and chemicals.</p>
        <p>The contrasting strengths and styles of the companies and their chief executives were on display yesterday at their meetings on Wall Street with analysts and reporters. Mr. Raymond, a South Dakotan with a doctorate in chemical engineering, has a reputation as a blunt cost-cutter and technician. Pruning his work force year by year, he has already made his company a model of efficiency. His shareholder returns at Exxon usually match the performance of market indexes whose advances have been paced by companies making computer software or chips.</p>
        <p>Mr. Noto, whose company has slimmed down, too, is better known as a salesman and international diplomat. While Exxon is cautious about developing new oil and natural gas sources abroad, Mobil has expanding interests ranging from Indonesia to the Persian Gulf and the Caspian Sea.</p>
        <p>In an age when chief executives  carefully tend their images, Mr. Raymond avoids attention and dismisses questions he deems redundant or dumb. ''I'm not interested in your views of how we ought to deal with the F.T.C.,'' he told a reporter yesterday who questioned why his company had not begun by telling the agency what operations it would sell.</p>
        <p>So if Mr. Raymond took the lead in reciting the merger's particulars, it fell to Mr. Noto to set forth the imperatives in more human terms. ''This is not a combination based on desperation,'' he said, his accent showing his roots a subway ride and a world away in Bensonhurst, Brooklyn. ''It is one based on opportunity. But we need to face some facts. The world has changed. The easy things are behind us. The easy oil, the easy cost savings, they're done. So all of us are now looking for some way to make a jump, to make a quantum leap, to be able to deliver more value to our shareholders, and our employees and customers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Noto was likewise the one who explained that while managers could not offer more details of the job cuts: ''They are not cold and indifferent. They understand that jobs are important, and they understand the impact on communities.'' About 40 percent, or 50,000, of the companies' employees are in the United States.</p>
        <p>The executives bemoaned oil prices that are low and getting lower since the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries finished its recent meeting without doing much more than agreeing to meet again. But they said their deal was based far more on their views of where their business was going over the longer term.</p>
        <p>In a consolidating industry, they said, they see powerful state-owned oil companies expanding to other countries. They spoke of the need for huge amounts of capital and deep technological expertise to produce oil and natural gas from beneath Arctic ice and unexplored seas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Raymond's restiveness in public and Exxon's history of dealing with the media may hamper efforts to sell the agreement to the public. Exxon's handling of the 1989 grounding of its Exxon Valdez tanker off Alaska has come to be known as one of the industry's worst environmental and public relations disasters. Parting company with European competitors like British Petroleum and Royal Dutch/Shell, Exxon and Mobil are opposing a treaty meant to slow global warming.</p>
        <p>Since news of their talks broke last Wednesday, antitrust experts and consumer advocates have been picking at it. ''Rockefeller's revenge,'' is how Heat USA, a buying cooperative for heating oil in the New York area, put it. ''There's little question in my mind that if you have industry consolidation on this magnitude, you're going to see energy prices controlled by fewer people,'' said Andrew Heaney, the group's president.</p>
        <p>At gasoline stations, consumers had mixed views. Some, like Juanita Purner of Santa Monica, Calif., suspect that the deal will raise prices.  ''To me, that says monopoly, big business, more control,'' she said at a Mobil station in Los Angeles. ''I may have to take the bus.''</p>
        <p>But others, like Wayne E. Daniels of Farmingville, N.Y., seemed more concerned about the workers. ''I've heard that thousands of jobs will be lost in the merger,'' he said at a Mobil station in Riverhead, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Mobil has been far more ardent in seeking partners, allies and acquisitions, combining its European refineries and gas stations with British Petroleum's. Exxon has stood aloof, assuming it was large enough to fend for itself.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Raymond said yesterday that he had been pondering how much more profitable his company could become in league with Mobil.</p>
        <p>The flirtation began last June after an American Petroleum Institute committee meeting, when a possible partnership in Japan was suggested.</p>
        <p>''Maybe we should talk about that,'' Mr. Raymond said.</p>
        <p>''That and other things,'' Mr. Noto responded. About three weeks later, they began merger talks in earnest.</p>
        <p>Those who have been briefed on their discussions said that agreements on price came easily and early. Sorting through the potential antitrust obstacles and deciding who should get what job took longer. The boards held their own separate discussions as well, especially on the antitrust questions.</p>
        <p>BIG OIL: THE OVERVIEW  Correction:  December 3, 1998, Thursday  A front-page article yesterday about the merger agreement between the Exxon Corporation and Mobil Corporation misattributed a statement disclosing the first discussions held by the companies with the Federal Trade Commission. The disclosure was made at a news conference by Lee R. Raymond, the chairman and chief executive of Exxon, not by Federal Trade Commission officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 3, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>A front-page article yesterday about the merger agreement between the Exxon Corporation and Mobil Corporation misattributed a statement disclosing the first discussions held by the companies with the Federal Trade Commission. The disclosure was made at a news conference by Lee R. Raymond, the chairman and chief executive of Exxon, not by Federal Trade Commission officials.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
