<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>El Nino Finally Meets Its Meteorological Match: El Spring</title>
    <meta content="30NINO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1006102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980330T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DA133BF933A05750C0A96E958260" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>El Nino Finally Meets Its Meteorological Match: El Spring</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists say peak of El Nino weather phenomenon has passed and that its effects on North American are being progressively weakened by even more powerful climatic force, namely, arrival of spring; say, even though remnants of El Nino are still altering atmospheric circulation patterns, normal seasonal forces are superseding it and are once more reordering atmosphere; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>El Nino has led the United States on a not-always-merry weather chase this year. But scientists say that the peak of its influence has passed and that its effects on North America are being progressively weakened by an even more powerful climatic force, the seasonal change known as spring.</p>
        <p>The high sea-surface temperatures in the eastern Pacific Ocean that define El Nino are still there, and they are still affecting weather by altering atmospheric circulation patterns. But as spring warms the Northern Hemisphere, the experts say, normal seasonal forces are superseding El Nino and reordering the atmosphere again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>El Nino has led the United States on a not-always-merry weather chase this year. But scientists say that the peak of its influence has passed and that its effects on North America are being progressively weakened by an even more powerful climatic force, the seasonal change known as spring.</p>
        <p>The high sea-surface temperatures in the eastern Pacific Ocean that define El Nino are still there, and they are still affecting weather by altering atmospheric circulation patterns. But as spring warms the Northern Hemisphere, the experts say, normal seasonal forces are superseding El Nino and reordering the atmosphere again.</p>
        <p>In the New York metropolitan region, a result has been a more or less typical mercurial March, now colder (see last weekend's snow), now warmer (see this weekend's abnormally high temperatures in the 70's and 80's), now in between, after an almost uniformly mild and nearly snowless El Nino winter.</p>
        <p>Government forecasters got it right when they predicted last year that El Nino would bring a warm, wet winter to much of the United States and that California and the Gulf Coast were in for unusually heavy rainstorms. The winter turned out to be the second warmest and seventh wettest on record for the country.</p>
        <p>California was battered, and the Southeast had the most rain in 103 years of record keeping.</p>
        <p>The climax may have been in the last week of February, when the strongest Pacific rainstorm of the winter, generated by El Nino, pounded California while lethal tornadoes spun off from an extra strong subtropical jet stream linked to El Nino ripped central Florida.</p>
        <p>A few days later, some sort of climatic switch flipped. The pattern changed. California's weather improved, and the regime of uniform warmth in the East disappeared.</p>
        <p>Now, said Vernon Kousky, of the Climate Prediction Center of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration in Camp Springs, Md., it is clear that ''as far as the impacts on the United States are concerned, El Nino is past its peak.''</p>
        <p>California, Mr. Kousky said, will continue to be wetter than normal this spring, but ''it looks like we're out of the woods on big California storms.''</p>
        <p>For the period from April through June, the National Weather Service, relying largely on its reading of El Nino, predicts above-normal temperatures for the West Coast and Northwestern quadrant of the country, below-normal temperatures in most of the South and Texas and normal readings elsewhere.</p>
        <p>That three-month forecast calls for above-normal rainfall in the West and Southwest, below-normal rainfall around the Great Lakes and in northern New England and normal rainfall everywhere else.</p>
        <p>Longer-range forecasts, for July, August and September, necessarily extremely tentative, call for above-normal temperatures on the East and West Coasts, below-normal in the midsection, above normal precipitation in the Great Lakes and Northern Plains and normal elsewhere.</p>
        <p>It is too soon to know whether the 1997-98 El Nino will end up eclipsing the 1982-83 edition as the strongest on record, Mr. Kousky said. But it did live up to its billing as a weather maker. Well-above-normal rains fell in a broad swath from San Francisco and Los Angeles to New Orleans to Tampa, Fla. Los Angeles had more than 13 inches of rain in February, a record for the month.</p>
        <p>More generally, Mr. Kousky added, El Nino's effects have been mixed. Australia was spared a feared drought, although an Indonesian drought fed forest fires. The Indian monsoon, which is essential for agriculture, was not aborted, as had been feared. But Peru and eastern equatorial Africa were drenched.</p>
        <p>Closer to home, strong westerly winds spawned by El Nino last summer sheared apart most Atlantic hurricanes before they developed.</p>
        <p>The primary direct effect on North America is that El Nino creates an extra-strong jet stream, a high-level river of eastward-flowing air in which storms are embedded, and sends it coursing across California and the southern tier and then, sometimes, up the East Coast.</p>
        <p>The stronger jet stream results from an increased difference in temperature between the tropics and colder regions farther north. At the same time, more water evaporates from the warmer tropical waters, and the stronger jet stream transports more precipitation to the United States.</p>
        <p>As the subtropical jet stream strengthens, the normal northern branch of the jet stream weakens and shifts northward. A result this year was that cold Arctic air stayed penned up in Canada, making for a warm American winter.</p>
        <p>Parts of the East and Midwest had their warmest winter on record. The East Coast was wetter than normal.</p>
        <p>Close to the ocean, as in New York, the extra precipitation fell almost entirely as rain. But where it did grow cold enough to snow from time to time, as in northern New England, the additional moisture in the air led to a good season for skiers.</p>
        <p>There were also some ''freakish snowfalls,'' said Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist in the Weather Communications Group at Pennsylvania State University, including ''one of the great snowfalls of all time in Louisville, Ky.''</p>
        <p>Some experts attributed the unusual wetness and warmth to a combination of El Nino and global warming. A warmer atmosphere usually contains added moisture. ''This year,'' said Ants Leetma, director of the Climate Prediction Center, ''the strong El Nino, on top of the continuing gradual increase of temperature and precipitation, set the stage for many all-time state records.''</p>
        <p>El Nino is starting to weaken, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Jet Propulsion Laboratory reported last week. The warm pool of tropical water is starting to dissipate.</p>
        <p>For now, the sea surface remains abnormally warm, and it is expected to continue that way at least through May. The sea surface is expected to cool gradually, however, and it should be ''more or less normal in the tropics next winter,'' Mr. Kousky said.</p>
        <p>For next winter in North America and everywhere else outside the tropics, he said, that means only one thing: ''Anything goes.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
