<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A/Joel Gordes; Insurers, Risk and the Global Climate</title>
    <meta content="GORDES$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1010704"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dubrow, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordes, Joel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDC1F3DF93AA25757C0A96E958260" item-length="1461" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A/Joel Gordes; Insurers, Risk and the Global Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT DUBROW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dubrow, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Joel Gordes, energy consultant, on his effort to persuade insurance industry to help stem global warming and resulting rise in insurance risk; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOEL GORDES, an energy consultant, believes that Connecticut's multibillion-dollar insurance industry has a choice: face possible financial ruin from losses due to more frequent and severe storms, droughts and wildfires or commit some of the industry's considerable resources to efforts to stem global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes is a consultant to Dr. Jeremy Leggett, formerly of Greenpeace International, and now of Solar Century in Britain. Dr. Leggett began the discussions about climate change between insurers and environmentalists in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOEL GORDES, an energy consultant, believes that Connecticut's multibillion-dollar insurance industry has a choice: face possible financial ruin from losses due to more frequent and severe storms, droughts and wildfires or commit some of the industry's considerable resources to efforts to stem global warming.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes is a consultant to Dr. Jeremy Leggett, formerly of Greenpeace International, and now of Solar Century in Britain. Dr. Leggett began the discussions about climate change between insurers and environmentalists in Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes now engages in similar  discussions with Connecticut and other United States insurers, proposing products he feels would both increase insurers' bottom lines and reduce emission of climate-changing gases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes has been involved in energy-related work since 1975, when he was hired by a solar energy company in Waterbury. He was vice chairman of the Connecticut General Assembly's energy committee when he served as a State Representative from 1987 to 1991.</p>
        <p>A lifelong Connecticut resident, Mr. Gordes, 51, lives in Colebrook. In a recent interview, he discussed global warming and the insurance industry. Following are excerpts from that conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. Why should the insurance industry be concerned about global warming?</p>
        <p>A. The insurance industry is based upon stability of weather within certain types of boundaries.</p>
        <p>There has to be an actuarial experience to be able to say, ''This is what the premium should be for this property in this place.'' If climate is changing, the probability of risk changes, and that's not good. There could be more flooding, hail storms, intense wind storms, intense precipitation events.</p>
        <p>Some recent research from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration says that climate change may make hurricanes worse. Brushfires could become urban firestorms if they come off the ridges and go into Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>It's going to be erratic and volatile, and that's not a great situation to base insurance premiums on.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the magnitude of losses from these kinds of events?</p>
        <p>A. If Hurricane Andrew had hit a more populated and wealthy area, like Miami, it would have been a $50 billion loss rather than the $16.5 billion loss it was. If a similar event hit metropolitan New York, New Jersey and then went into Connecticut, it could be as much as $110 billion.</p>
        <p>Q. Have insurance losses been increasing in the 1990's?</p>
        <p>A. Of the 25 largest weather-related insurance losses in the United States, 21 have occurred in the past decade. There has been a remarkable increase in billion-dollar catastrophic losses. Two primary reasons are greater wealth and people building more in harm's way. However, even when you normalize for that, it appears there are other factors at work.</p>
        <p>Q. With all the uncertainty involved in projecting the future of global climate, why should the insurance companies take this seriously?</p>
        <p>A. Absence of certainty does not mean absence of risk. If you wake up at the end of the day and say, ''What if I'm wrong, what if there really is climate change?'' it may be too late by then to do anything about it. The insurance industry is the first in line to be bankrupt if climate change is real.</p>
        <p>Q. What should the insurance industry do about climate change?</p>
        <p>A. European insurers usually have staff climatologists on board. The United States industry, with the exception of Employers Reinsurance of Kansas, generally does not.</p>
        <p>They need to start looking at the probabilities of what could happen.  Then they can ask what they can do to help mitigate climate change that at the same time will increase their bottom line -- for instance, making their own facilities more energy efficient. They own tremendous amounts of property. It will make it lower cost to maintain, at the same time they are reducing emissions.</p>
        <p>The other thing is reducing property-casualty losses through energy types of upgrades.</p>
        <p>A few winters ago we had all the huge icicles, called ice dams, forming along the edges of roofs. They are caused by heat escaping from poorly insulated ceilings, melting the snow on the roof from below, the water running down over the unheated eaves, refreezing, working its way back under the shingles and causing water damage inside the home. Insulating the ceiling correctly and ventilating the air above it stops ice dams.</p>
        <p>So here's a case where saving energy, which is saving emissions, saves future claims for the insurance industry. The insurance industry could say, ''We're going to give you 10 percent off your insurance for three years, if you will insulate your ceiling.''</p>
        <p>Q. Did the insurance industry have a presence at the December global  warming conference in Kyoto?</p>
        <p>A. The European and Asian insurers certainly did, and they came out with some very, very strong statements calling for emission reductions. Even as far back as 1995, Lloyd's of London, Munich Reinsurance and Swiss Reinsurance were calling for reductions. The American industry has not been there.</p>
        <p>Seventy-one insurers have signed a United Nations accord, pledging to  consider the issues of climate change and other environmental problems in all business practices. Employers Reinsurance is the only United States company to sign.</p>
        <p>Q. Have the European and Asian insurers been involved in encouraging energy efficiency?</p>
        <p>A. They've gone even further. They've started to invest in renewable energy. Swiss Reinsurance has put money into a fund to help people in the third world with photovoltaics. There are a number of English insurers joining the campaign called Solar Century.</p>
        <p>Q. Why can't insurance companies simply not insure vulnerable areas instead of trying to mitigate global warming?</p>
        <p>A. Then you don't have much of a business. And you are going to have to have the insurer of last resort take over, which is usually the government. In the long run that usually doesn't work too well. Somebody has to pay somewhere. If you're an insurer, you calculate the risks and do your business. There are a lot of other tools they are developing to manage those risks, financial tools mostly, but that ignores what may be the biggest threat.</p>
        <p>Q. Why can't insurance companies simply raise their rates as their response to global warming?</p>
        <p>A. They have been doing that -- in Florida, in certain other prone areas. But remember, it's a regulated business, and the minute you start raising rates, people start squawking to  their state senators and representatives and insurance commissioners.  It's a politically driven process.</p>
        <p>Q. Are there precedents for the insurance industry advocating social policy changes that would reduce risks?</p>
        <p>A. Absolutely. What about the support they've given to Mothers Against Drunk Driving? What about seat belt safety and air bag safety? In one case they took some pension funds and invested them in businesses that created jobs for union members from whose pension funds the money came.</p>
        <p>Why should insurance companies, if there is a solid link to climate change from fossil fuel emissions, be investing in fossil fuel projects? It's like a health insurance company investing in tobacco.</p>
        <p>Q. What has been the response of United States insurance executives to your arguments?</p>
        <p>A. They are, as insurers usually are, very cautious. They want to see more ironclad links before they begin to take action. However, a few are starting to make some statements, one that will be putting something in their annual report.</p>
        <p>We've come up with certain reasons why the United States insurers have not followed in the footsteps of the European Community. The Europeans have more global exposure to losses. The Europeans do not have a massive disinformation campaign going on by their fossil fuel industry, as we do.</p>
        <p>United States companies don't want to scare their stockholders and customers by saying climate change is imminent. Many also sell auto insurance. And one of the things we're going to have to do, if we want to stop emissions, is get a lot of people out of their autos.</p>
        <p>Q. How important is this issue for Connecticut?</p>
        <p>A. Connecticut's economy is still heavily invested in the insurance industry. Some statements were made by Republican State Chairman Chris DePino about how Democratic Senator Joseph I. Lieberman's support for climate change legislation and the Kyoto treaty holds a risk for him. I don't think the Republican chairman has reckoned with the threat that climate change could present to the insurance industry in his home state. So I think he's barking up the  wrong tree.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
