<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FIGURE IN SCANDAL ASSERTS SHE HEARD CLINTON ON PHONE</title>
    <meta content="31CLIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980201T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subpoenas</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Secret Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Susan Webber (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Paula Corbin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lieberman, Evelyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tripp, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ginsburg, William H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jordan, Vernon E Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E6DB133AF932A05752C0A96E958260" item-length="1510" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FIGURE IN SCANDAL ASSERTS SHE HEARD CLINTON ON PHONE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former White House worker Linda E Tripp, whose tape recordings have led to investigation of sex scandal involving Pres Clinton and former White House intern Monica Lewinsky, breaks silence with angry statement defending her credibility and accusing White House of engaging in smear campaign; claims knowledge of every detail of alleged affair; describes overhearing early-morning telephone call in November 1997 that Clinton allegedly made to Lewinsky; says she was present on many occasions over space of 15-month friendship with Lewinsky when she made and received numerous phone calls with White House officials that were of volatile and contentious nature; says she saw numerous gifts Clinton and Lewinsky exchanged and heard several of Lewinsky's tapes of Clinton; Lewinsky's lawyer, William H Ginsburg, says Tripp was never privy to phone calls between President and Lewinsky; says occasional calls made by Lewinsky were of business nature and were in no way fraught with sexual innuendo; White House maintains its no-comment policy; independent counsel, Kenneth W Starr, presses criminal inquiry; is seeking corroborating witnesses to allegations that there was affair and that Clinton, or confidante Vernon E Jordan Jr, may have urged Lewinsky to lie about it under oath; Bob Weiner, spokesman for Clinton's drug control policy office, testifies before grand jury; angrily accuses prosecutors of engaging in witch hunt and of trying to intimidate him because he called Maryland Democratic officials to raise questions about Tripp's possible violations of wire-tap laws; Evelyn Lieberman, former White House deputy chief of staff who transferred Lewinsky out of White House job to Pentagon, also testifies; tells news conference she knows of no improper relationship between Clinton and Lewinsky; Clinton wins round in sexual harassment suit by Paula Corbin Jones as Federal Judge Susan Webber Wright rules Secret Service agents who guard him at White House cannot be subpoenaed to testify about what they saw in course of their work (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal worker whose furtive tape recordings caused the investigation of sex-scandal charges against President Clinton broke her silence today to tell of an early-morning phone call she said Mr. Clinton made to the White House intern at the heart of the alleged affair.</p>
        <p>Linda R. Tripp, the former White House worker who made 20 hours of secret tapes of the accounts of the intern, Monica S. Lewinsky, told of overhearing one end of the Presidential call in an angry two-page statement defending her credibility and accusing the White House of a ''smear'' campaign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal worker whose furtive tape recordings caused the investigation of sex-scandal charges against President Clinton broke her silence today to tell of an early-morning phone call she said Mr. Clinton made to the White House intern at the heart of the alleged affair.</p>
        <p>Linda R. Tripp, the former White House worker who made 20 hours of secret tapes of the accounts of the intern, Monica S. Lewinsky, told of overhearing one end of the Presidential call in an angry two-page statement defending her credibility and accusing the White House of a ''smear'' campaign.</p>
        <p>Claiming knowledge of ''every detail'' of the alleged affair, Ms. Tripp described a 2 A.M. phone call last November to Ms. Lewinsky's Watergate apartment. She said that Ms. Lewinsky later identified the caller as Mr. Clinton and said that the two of them talked into the night about the alleged sexual affair.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewinsky's lawyer, William H. Ginsburg, laboring to protect his client from criminal indictment, insisted in an interview with ABC News tonight that Ms. Tripp was ''never privy'' to phone calls between the President and Ms. Lewinsky. ''I do know she had conversations with the President of the United States,'' he said of his client. ''By telephone. Absolutely.'' He said they were very occasional business calls between the Chief Executive and a subordinate.</p>
        <p>''As far as I know, they were in no way fraught with sexual innuendo,'' Mr. Ginsburg said.</p>
        <p>The White House, citing the ongoing investigation, maintained its no-comment policy when asked about the phone call described by Ms. Tripp, who said she had been staying overnight with Ms. Lewinsky. The President has denied any sexual relationship with Ms. Lewinsky and declined to discuss the charges in detail.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tripp said that, across a 15-month period of close confidences with Ms. Lewinsky, she also had been present when the 24-year-old former intern ''made and received numerous phone calls'' with White House officials, which were of ''a volatile and contentious nature'' and focused on the accusations involving the President. Defenders of Ms. Tripp said these calls went beyond Betty Currie, the President's secretary, to higher ranking officials.</p>
        <p>''I have also seen numerous gifts they exchanged and heard several of her tapes of him,'' Ms. Tripp added, without specifying the nature of the tapes.</p>
        <p>The inquiry spilled further into the public arena when an Administration witness emerged from the grand jury empaneled by the independent counsel, Kenneth W. Starr, and denounced it as ''Big Brother at its worst.'' The witness, Bob Weiner, a spokesman for the President's drug control policy office, accused prosecutors of trying to intimidate him because he had called Maryland Democratic officials and urged them to raise questions about whether Ms. Tripp might have violated wire-tap laws in tape-recording Ms. Lewinsky without her permission.</p>
        <p>''We have just experienced the witch hunt and the partisanship that more and more of the American people resent about this case,'' Mr. Weiner declared. His attack reflected the Administration's rising confidence, with the President enjoying record-high approval ratings in the polls despite the sensational inquiry.</p>
        <p>For the second day in a row, The President won a point in Little Rock, Ark., where he is defending himself in a sexual harassment civil suit brought by Paula Corbin Jones. Judge Susan Webber Wright ruled that Secret Service agents who guard the President in the White House cannot be subpoenaed to testify about what they have witnessed in the course of their work. On Thursday, in a significant victory for the President, Judge Wright barred all evidence of the Lewinsky investigation from being used in the Paula Jones case.</p>
        <p>Forcing Mr. Clinton's bodyguards to testify, Judge Wright declared today, might ''provide those with hostile intent toward the President with important information to use in piercing the Secret Service's protection.''</p>
        <p>Her ruling did not affect the separate question of whether Mr. Starr has the power to compel Secret Service agents to testify in his criminal inquiry. He is seeking to find corroborating witnesses for the accusations that there was an affair and that the President or his confidant, Vernon E. Jordan Jr., sought to have Ms. Lewinsky lie about it under oath. Ms. Lewinsky has flatly denied the material on the Tripp tapes in a sworn deposition submitted in the Paula Jones case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr moved ahead with his grand jury inquiry with the fate of Ms. Lewinsky apparently still unsettled. Her lawyers have been seeking immunity from criminal prosecution in return for cooperating with Mr. Starr, but the two sides have been struggling to come to terms over precisely what Ms. Lewinsky will have to disclose.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Weiner, the grand jury heard today from Evelyn Lieberman, the former White House deputy chief of staff who, in April, 1996, ordered Ms. Lewinsky transferred out of the White House to a job across the Potomac in the Pentagon, citing ''inappropriate and immature behavior'' and poor job performance.</p>
        <p>Emerging from the grand jury after three-and-a-half hours, Ms. Lieberman, grasping the hand of her husband, Ed, stepped up to a throng of microphones and declared: ''I want to make one point clear. I know of no improper relationship between the President, Monica Lewinsky or anyone else, for that matter.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Starr pressed his inquiry, political fallout continued in the newly returned Congress. Senator John Ashcroft, Republican of Missouri, called for the President to resign if the accusation is true. In contrast, Representative John Conyers, Democrat of Michigan, called for an investigation of the methods of Mr. Starr, whose original Whitewater inquiry into the President's Arkansas business dealings began in 1994.</p>
        <p>With the President's job approval ratings rising, the White House claimed a busy day devoted to official duties, not preoccupation with  defending the President. Mr. Clinton had a breakfast meeting with members of the U.S. Conference of Mayors and attended to such topics as the tense situation with Iraq, a new aviation trade agreement with Japan and proposals to invest more research money in the fight against global warming, according to the White House.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Weiner emerged from the grand jury, he offered the first glimpse of the tooth-and-claw politics that suffuse the charges and countercharges in the inquiry. Decrying a ''scary'' abuse of prosecutorial powers, Mr. Weiner, who Republicans noted used to be press secretary to Representative Conyers, said he had been questioned about personal phone calls he made last Sunday night from his home.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr had no comment. But some of his defenders said that the independent counsel had been informed of Mr. Weiner's telephoned attempts to stir questions about the legality of Mrs. Tripp's tapings by a Republican criminal justice official in Howard County, Md. Ms. Tripp resides there, and the local angle on the scandal inquiry was instantly being gossiped about by rival party politicians.</p>
        <p>With her veracity in question and her methods drawing more criticism, Ms. Tripp began sending out a defense statement to news organizations across the country late last night through her lawyer, Jim Moody. Excerpts of the statement appeared in late editions of The New York Times on Friday. She praised Mr. Starr for ''fairness, thoroughness and integrity'' and accused the White House of making ''vicious personal attacks against me.''</p>
        <p>''I am disturbed by the smear campaign that maligns Monica,'' she asserted, explaining that she decided to secretly tape her friend's revelations because, Ms. Tripp said, she knew her veracity would be challenged by the White House when she testified in the Paula Jones case.</p>
        <p>''She was not a stalker,'' she said of Ms. Lewinsky, rebutting critics' suggestions that the former intern was calculating in her alleged promiscuity. ''She was invited; she did not embellish. The truth is sensational enough.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ginsburg, the lawyer fighting to keep Ms. Lewinsky from criminal charges, said Ms. Tripp's statement sounded ''like the pre-publicity for a book.'' But the lawyer, who has been on national television every day for the past week, waxed philosophical in declining to accuse Ms. Tripp of outright lying.</p>
        <p>''No one ever lies,'' he said to Barbara Walters, his interviewer. ''People often do what they have to do to make their story sound right. Ms. Tripp is no more lying than Monica Lewinsky was lying when she had the taped phone conversations and the taped wire conversations with Ms. Tripp.''</p>
        <p>Lucianne S. Goldberg, a New York literary agent and open critic of President Clinton, has said she suggested the tapings to her friend Ms. Tripp as a legal precaution, not for publication. Ms. Tripp, saying she was a political independent, maintained in her statement that ''whatever political agenda Ms. Goldberg may have is not mine.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Tripp noted that she did not volunteer to testify in the Paula Jones trial but was subpoenaed and then encountered an Administration climate of ''threats, intimidation,'' and denial. ''Because I have chosen the path of truth, I have been vilified,'' she said.</p>
        <p>THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE OVERVIEW  Correction:  February 1, 1998, Sunday  Headlines yesterday about a statement by Linda R. Tripp that she was present when Monica S. Lewinsky received a late-night phone call from President Clinton misstated what Ms. Tripp said she heard. She said she heard Ms. Lewinsky's end of a conversation and was later told by Ms. Lewinsky that it was the President; she did not tell of hearing the President speaking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 1, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>Headlines yesterday about a statement by Linda R. Tripp that she was present when Monica S. Lewinsky received a late-night phone call from President Clinton misstated what Ms. Tripp said she heard. She said she heard Ms. Lewinsky's end of a conversation and was later told by Ms. Lewinsky that it was the President; she did not tell of hearing the President speaking.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
