<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; It's not easy to know when and how to act to protect the planet.</title>
    <meta content="Y01SCEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Models (Simulations)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Club of Rome</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Passell, Peter</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E0D91031F932A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; It's not easy to know when and how to act to protect the planet.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Passell, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Passell (Economic Scene) column recalls 1972 report entitled The Limits to Growth, prepared by mostly European group of business leaders who called themselves Club of Rome; says report warned that world was about to run out of essential commodities; also says report became holy writ of environmental movement; notes that since that time, global economic output has tripled without any indication that end is in sight; also notes world markets are currently glutted with commodities and that prices of most natural resources have fallen in real terms; says 1972 report looks foolish largely because computer experts who simulated resource use failed to incorporate market forces in their model; says technology, guided by market forces, has made it possible for huge population to live better than would ever have been guessed in 1972 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT a difference a quarter-century can make.</p>
        <p>In 1972 a mostly European group of business leaders who called themselves the Club of Rome forecast that Spaceship Earth was about to run out of fuel and other essential commodities. A ''rapid, radical redressing of the present unbalanced and dangerously deteriorating world situation is the primary task facing humanity,'' the group concluded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT a difference a quarter-century can make.</p>
        <p>In 1972 a mostly European group of business leaders who called themselves the Club of Rome forecast that Spaceship Earth was about to run out of fuel and other essential commodities. A ''rapid, radical redressing of the present unbalanced and dangerously deteriorating world situation is the primary task facing humanity,'' the group concluded.</p>
        <p>The group's report, ''The Limits to Growth,'' sold nine million copies and transformed the fuzzy concept of sustainability into the holy writ of the environmental movement. Since then, however, global economic output has roughly tripled without any indication that the end is nigh. Indeed, world markets are currently glutted with commodities and the prices of most natural resources have fallen in real terms.</p>
        <p>The easy lesson here is that forecasts are no better than the underlying assumptions. But for all its apparent silliness, the Club of Rome did touch a nerve. Markets alone, most experts concede, may be insufficient to protect the planet from unacceptable environmental damage. The catch, as the divisions over global warming suggest, is that it's hard to know how or when to act on the insight.</p>
        <p>First the easy part. ''The Limits to Growth'' looks foolish largely because the computer experts who simulated resource use failed to incorporate market forces in their model. In market economies, scarcity leads to higher prices, which in turn sets off a variety of compensating responses. If copper prices rise, consumers make do with fewer copper products. More important, producers search for way to do the same job with cheaper materials -- here, replacing copper with aluminum in wiring, or shifting to solid-state electronics that barely make use of expensive metals.</p>
        <p>The denouement of the 1973-74 oil shock, which at the time lent credibility to the Club of Rome's jeremiad, proves the point. After oil prices quadrupled in the mid-1970's, the world shifted to cheaper fuels and developed energy-saving technology for vehicles that could run only on petroleum. Today the industrial West burns less oil to produce twice as much as it did in 1972. And, thanks to financial incentives, accessible reserves are considerably larger.</p>
        <p>''You can't underestimate the value of price signals when it comes to nonrenewable resources,'' said Robert Stavins, an economist at the Kennedy School of Government at Harvard.</p>
        <p>What happens, though, with resources that are not private property and not directly subject to the hidden hand of the market? Ocean fisheries, for example, typically belong to everybody -- and therefore nobody. It doesn't pay any individual to conserve breeding stocks because others will be happy to reap the profit today.</p>
        <p>That's why most of the world's great fisheries have been decimated over the last few decades. And why consumers have turned to aquaculture -- an expensive technological fix -- to satisfy their appetite for everything from salmon to oysters.</p>
        <p>But with as little help from regulation, public fisheries could mimic the incentives of private markets. Setting a maximum allowable level for the total catch, then auctioning or giving away rights could -- and in a few cases, has -- served as a substitute for the market. Clamming off the mid-Atlantic coast, for example, is now efficiently limited with quotas on individual catches.</p>
        <p>By the same token, economists have fought to conserve environmental resources by effectively privatizing access. Tradable permits for sulfur emissions from power plants, mandated by Congress in 1990, promise to limit total emissions at minimum total cost to electric utilities. And if the Clinton Administration has its way, a similar system of market-based permits will someday be used to limit global emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>All this adds up to a potent counterargument to the pessimism of the Club of Rome: technology, guided by the hidden hand of the market, has made it possible for a huge population to live better than Malthus's modern-day prophets would ever have guessed in 1972. And most apparently scarce environmental resources -- air, water, natural habitat -- could be stretched a lot further by applying a little economic sense to the problem.</p>
        <p>To give the pessimists the benefit of the doubt, though, it is still conceivable that economic activity will overshoot and produce irreversible damage. Catch too many fish, and it takes years to rebuild the fishery. Catch way too many fish, and the species never comes back. There's plenty of precedent. ''The passenger pigeon is extinct,'' Mr. Stavins of the Kennedy School noted.</p>
        <p>Likewise, it is conceivable that allowing greenhouse gases to reach some threshold concentration will cause irreversible reactions, leading to a rapid warming that will make everyone sorry they didn't heed the warnings.</p>
        <p>But how are policy makers supposed to cope with the unmeasurable probability of disastrous environmental consequences? A little knowledge may not be a bad thing, but it is certainly an uncomfortable thing.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
