<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Conservative, D'Amato Learned to Adapt</title>
    <meta content="23DAMA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056282"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: RACE FOR THE SENATE -- THE INCUMBENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Alfonse M. D'Amato</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Amato, Alfonse M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981023T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0DF1E3DF930A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="2720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Conservative, D'Amato Learned to Adapt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Analysis of Sen Alfonse M D'Amato's campaign to turn back Democratic challenger, Repr Charles E Schumer; finds that D'Amato, three-term Republican running hard for a fourth, is seen dancing away, in his campaign, from a Republican Party that seems anathema to many New Yorkers; but a review of D'Amato's most recent term shows that, for all his shifting on the edges, he remains a fundamentally conservative politician--among most conservative senators New York State has had since World War II; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent evening, a crowd of elegantly dressed people, many of them Democrats, gathered at the Hilton Hotel in Manhattan to honor a Brooklyn housing group founded by one of the state's most famous liberals, Senator Robert F. Kennedy. And there, seated near the front, was an unlikely guest of honor: Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, the three-term Republican running hard for a fourth.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato had just completed another day of attacking his Democratic challenger, Representative Charles E. Schumer, as being a Brooklyn liberal. But this evening, the Senator accepted an award for his work on behalf of the nonpartisan group, the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, and then started into a speech peppered with phrases Mr. Kennedy would have appreciated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a recent evening, a crowd of elegantly dressed people, many of them Democrats, gathered at the Hilton Hotel in Manhattan to honor a Brooklyn housing group founded by one of the state's most famous liberals, Senator Robert F. Kennedy. And there, seated near the front, was an unlikely guest of honor: Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato, the three-term Republican running hard for a fourth.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato had just completed another day of attacking his Democratic challenger, Representative Charles E. Schumer, as being a Brooklyn liberal. But this evening, the Senator accepted an award for his work on behalf of the nonpartisan group, the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation, and then started into a speech peppered with phrases Mr. Kennedy would have appreciated.</p>
        <p>''This group is about investing back in people,'' Mr. D'Amato said, his voice rising in volume and pitch. ''It is about fighting to take back our communities and our homes and our schools, about empowering youngsters, empowering the community.''</p>
        <p>To his critics and supporters alike, this was Alfonse Marcello D'Amato doing what he seems to do best these days: dancing away from a Republican Party that seems anathema to many New Yorkers, and surgically slicing at the grand coalition that has sustained New York's Democratic Party from the days of Franklin D. Roosevelt.</p>
        <p>But a review of Mr. D'Amato's most recent term shows that, for all his shifting on the edges, he remains a fundamentally conservative politician -- among the most conservative senators the state has had since World War II.</p>
        <p>He staunchly opposes abortion and gun control, regularly advocates tougher penalties for criminals and has rarely met a tax cut he did not like. He endorsed major portions of Newt Gingrich's Contract With America in 1995 and hailed the Republican takeover of Congress as a stinging repudiation of liberalism. And he continues to receive among the highest ratings in the Northeast from conservative groups like the Christian Coalition.</p>
        <p>It is a good bet, though, that many New Yorkers are not familiar with Mr. D'Amato's conservative credentials; a New York Times/CBS News poll taken from Oct. 1 to Oct. 6 showed, for instance, that 71 percent of voters did not know his position on abortion and only 39 percent considered him a conservative.</p>
        <p>That is in part because for the last three years, facing what he expected to be a difficult re-election campaign, and recognizing that the conservative revolution of 1994 had fallen precipitously from favor, Mr. D'Amato has worked harder than ever to clothe his conservative core in the gauzier attire of a moderate.</p>
        <p>One of the wiliest pragmatists in Congress, he has done this in signature D'Amato style: grabbing a few high-profile, emotional and mostly nonideological issues that appeal to targeted constituencies, and then fighting for them in tenacious, and sometimes showy, fashion.</p>
        <p>He has championed the cause of breast cancer victims, repeatedly threatening to hold up legislation on the Senate floor to get what he wants. He has chided his own majority leader, Trent Lott, for equating homosexuality with a sin -- and has won the endorsement of a major gay and lesbian group for his troubles. He has demanded that Swiss banks release the stolen assets of Holocaust victims -- and has won accolades within a constituency that Democrats consider a fundamental part of their base. And he has been silent on President Clinton's problems in the Monica Lewinsky affair, just a few years after he grabbed headlines with his aggressive investigation of Mr. Clinton as chairman of the Senate Whitewater committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato says he takes positions based on conviction, not politics. His supporters add that he has never been a rigid ideologue and has always been able to work with Democrats. Indeed, his advisers say what could make or break his re-election chances is that so many beneficiaries of his work as ''Senator Pothole'' have been Democrats.</p>
        <p>Even an old nemesis, former Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, who was ousted in 1994 by Mr. D'Amato's protege, George E. Pataki, acknowledged that ''when I asked for help as Governor, he was there.''</p>
        <p>But, Mr. Cuomo added in the next breath: ''There is no question he will deliver little packages the way old politicians did with bags of coal in the winter. But we also need an intelligent position on gun control, on abortion, on helping with education and H.M.O.'s and all of this. And he's nowhere on that stuff.''</p>
        <p>In his 1995 autobiography, ''Power, Pasta and Politics,'' Mr. D'Amato, now 61, talks of two major movements that shaped his political thinking: the rise of Barry M. Goldwater and the Republican Party's conservative wing in the early 1960's, and the emergence of the bloc of conservative working-class voters who became known as Reagan Democrats in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Recalling how he gave out American flags during his 1970 campaign for receiver of taxes in the town of Hempstead in Nassau County, Mr. D'Amato described his attempts to reach those conservatives: ''I won because patriotism wasn't just a gimmick, it was something that my generation and my parents' generation knew to be fundamental about being an American.''</p>
        <p>Ten years later, when he was Presiding Supervisor of Hempstead, Mr. D'Amato stunned the political world by handily defeating the state's liberal Republican Senator, Jacob K. Javits, in the primary. With Mr. Javits drawing votes on the Liberal Party line from the Democratic candidate, Elizabeth Holtzman, Mr. D'Amato won the general election with just 45 percent of the vote, carried along on Ronald Reagan's coattails.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. D'Amato's leadership, the state Republican Party proceeded to marginalize the Rockefeller moderates who had dominated it for decades, refashioned itself in his hard-edged image and forged close alliances with the Conservative and Right to Life Parties, which have endorsed Mr. D'Amato in all his Senate races.</p>
        <p>In style, Mr. D'Amato is only slightly more buttoned down than he was in those early years. He still screams at aides in his office, particularly when guests are present, calls men he does not know ''buddy'' and ''big guy,'' and kisses women on the hand. The epithets flow as freely as ever, as evidenced in his calling Mr. Schumer ''putzhead'' during a meeting with Jewish leaders earlier this week. In public, he is a whirling dervish of energy, alternately overbearing and charming. ''Hey, Chollie,'' he bellowed at Representative Charles B. Rangel, a Manhattan Democrat, before bear-hugging him outside the Senate chamber recently.</p>
        <p>But if Mr. D'Amato's style remains much the same, the political ground has shifted dramatically beneath him.</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton's election in 1992 gave new vitality to a more centrist wing of the Democratic Party. And the rise of the Christian right created unease among many moderate New York Republicans, many of them suburban voters crucial to Mr. D'Amato's political calculus.</p>
        <p>The Republicans' midterm victory in 1994  seemed to vindicate Mr. D'Amato's more conservative positions, at least briefly.</p>
        <p>But by 1996, polls showed that Mr. Gingrich and his Contract With America were deeply unpopular in New York. Mr. Clinton trounced Mr. D'Amato's candidate for President, Bob Dole. Mr. D'Amato's role as chairman of the Whitewater committee was panned in New York. His approval ratings plummeted into the low 30's.</p>
        <p>By 1997, the repositioning of Mr. D'Amato was well under way. He stopped attacking the President -- a trend that continues today, with Mr. D'Amato refusing to condemn Mr. Clinton's relationship with Ms. Lewinsky or to take a public position on impeachment. And he seized on a host of traditionally Democratic issues, from the environment to reforming health insurance to restore welfare benefits to immigrants.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato's supporters contend that his work on many of those issues was not related to political trends. His efforts on breast cancer, for instance, began in 1990 when the group One in Nine approached him about getting Federal funds to study the high incidence of the disease on Long Island.</p>
        <p>They also note that long before he began hectoring Swiss banks to release the assets of Holocaust victims, he was a strong supporter of Israel.</p>
        <p>And when Mr. D'Amato first announced to the world his support for civil rights for homosexuals -- a floor speech supporting homosexuals in the military in January 1993 -- he had just won re-election and was not under political pressure to adopt Democratic stances, his allies contend.</p>
        <p>''That was a year he could have coasted,'' an adviser said.</p>
        <p>Fluctuations In Voting Record</p>
        <p>But to many Democrats, Mr. D'Amato's leftward march has been a cynical, poll-driven effort to rebuild his low approval ratings, something they say he did before his last campaign, in 1992. To defend their assertion, they point to the significant changes in the grades he has received from some of the more liberal special interest groups in recent years.</p>
        <p>In 1992, for instance, Mr. D'Amato's scores from the A.F.L.-C.I.O., the League of Conservation Voters and the Consumer Federation of America all rose above his lifetime averages. But those scores dropped sharply in 1995, largely because of his votes for the Contract With America. By last year, though, his ratings from all three groups had climbed back up.</p>
        <p>Though such scorecards rarely sway blocs of voters, they are used by interest groups to decide endorsements. That may be one reason, analysts say, that for the last three years Mr. D'Amato has been championing high-profile issues and bucking his leadership more often. Indeed, the number of times he voted with the Republican majority fell from 90 percent in 1995 to 67 percent last year.</p>
        <p>''He has a real feel for how to capitalize on symbolically important issues to key constituencies,'' said Thomas Mann, director of governmental studies at the Brookings Institution, a policy research organization.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. D'Amato voted with the minority to raise the minimum wage. The vote may have helped prevent the state A.F.L.-C.I.O, usually a Democratic bastion, from endorsing Mr. Schumer this year, union officials said.</p>
        <p>He also sponsored legislation intended to reduce acid rain and testified at Senate hearings on the subject last month. The move won him accolades from a number of conservation groups in the Adirondacks at a time when other organizations, like the Sierra Club, were harshly criticizing Mr. D'Amato's lifetime environmental record.</p>
        <p>On the Banking Committee, Mr. D'Amato has pushed hard for a number of consumer rights measures, including legislation to prevent mortgage insurance companies from overcharging customers, and rules that require banks to make loans in their communities. Those efforts have helped counter Democratic assertions that he uses the committee to do favors for banks and securities firms that give him large campaign contributions, analysts say.</p>
        <p>''He's much more pro-consumer than any other Republican on that committee,'' said Ed Mierzwinski, director of consumer programs for the United States Public Interest Research Group, an advocacy organization.</p>
        <p>Master of the Art Of Appropriations</p>
        <p>Congressional experts say Mr. D'Amato has never had a major impact on domestic or foreign policy, or been known for his skills in writing legislation. But on one thing, many Democrats and Republicans agree: the Senator is an expert at getting things out of the Federal bureaucracy and bringing those things home.</p>
        <p>As soon as he arrived in Washington, Mr. D'Amato became a master of the appropriations process, which requires a horse trader's sense, good personal relations and a lot of badgering. He was soon dubbed Senator Pothole, a title of derision that he now wears as a badge of honor.</p>
        <p>This year, Mr. D'Amato helped lead a fight to prevent Senators from the South and West from sharply reducing Federal mass transit spending. Though he was slow to enter the battle, Mr. D'Amato's threats to block a huge highway spending bill and his influence with Senator Pete V. Domenici, the chairman of the Budget Committee, helped win a major increase in New York's transit funding, negotiators said.</p>
        <p>''There were a lot of Senators from the Northeast who would stop by and say, 'D'Amato's told us to do this,' '' said Mr. Domenici, a New Mexico Republican who is one of Mr. D'Amato's closest friends in the Senate. ''D'Amato was ginning up all these guys to talk to me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato's resourcefulness also led to one of his major legislative triumphs: using the defense budget to finance breast cancer research. Mr. D'Amato devised the financing scheme, which has provided $900 million since 1992, to get around the spending restrictions then in place on other Federal departments.</p>
        <p>For politicians across the state, Mr. D'Amato has become known as the go-to Senator. And in Congress, Democratic officials say Mr. D'Amato always returns their calls promptly. ''I would think a lot of Democrats would have a difficult time campaigning hard against D'Amato because of their good relations with him,'' said the chief of staff to a Democratic member of Congress. ''If you need anything done, you've got to go to D'Amato. Distasteful or not, you've got to do it.''</p>
        <p>In Some Ways, A Bit Like Clinton</p>
        <p>For a man who has spent much of the last six years attacking, investigating and trying to unseat the President, there is something oddly Clintonesque about Mr. D'Amato.</p>
        <p>Both men have been the subject of repeated inquiries by Congress and prosecutors. Both men are considered consummate politicians and deal makers. And both have had to use every ounce of their political skills to recover from lapses in judgment.</p>
        <p>And like Mr. Clinton's detractors, Mr. Schumer clearly believes that the weight of Mr. D'Amato's past will bring him down.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Schumer has not made ethics a central campaign issue, his aides are not shy about recounting the Senator's past problems. In 1991, the Senate Ethics Committee rebuked the Senator for allowing his brother, Armand, to write a letter on behalf of a law client on Senate stationery. In 1992, a Puerto Rican developer was charged with funneling $32,000 in illegal contributions to his campaign; the charge was dismissed. In 1993, he made a $37,125 profit in one day of stock trades with a firm that had been repeatedly investigated by securities regulators. In none of those cases was Mr. D'Amato found to have broken any laws.</p>
        <p>The Schumer camp also likes to suggest that New Yorkers are embarrassed by their junior Senator, from his singing ''Old MacDonald had some pork'' during a floor debate in 1994 to his heavily accented imitation of Lance A. Ito, the judge in the O. J. Simpson murder trial, on the Don Imus radio program in 1995.</p>
        <p>But what Mr. D'Amato may have going for him, some Democrats say, is precisely what Mr. Schumer is hoping will be his Achilles' heel: people already know much about him. He has been thoroughly investigated. His Senate record has been pored over. And, Mr. D'Amato's handlers contend, just enough voters are comfortable with what they see, warts and all.</p>
        <p>For that reason, an embattled Alfonse D'Amato will still be tough to beat, many Democrats acknowledge.</p>
        <p>''Clinton is not as good as D'Amato,'' Mr. Cuomo said. ''D'Amato swims at the tops of waves."</p>
        <p>THE 1998 CAMPAIGN: RACE FOR THE SENATE -- THE INCUMBENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
