<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Be Fruitful and Subtract</title>
    <meta content="14HULBURT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1024233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DC103BF937A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Be Fruitful and Subtract</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ann Hulbert</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE ONE</p>
        <p>A Personal and Environmental</p>
        <p>Argument for Single-Child Families.</p>
        <p>By Bill McKibben.</p>
        <p>254 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE ONE</p>
        <p>A Personal and Environmental</p>
        <p>Argument for Single-Child Families.</p>
        <p>By Bill McKibben.</p>
        <p>254 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
        <p>It has become a bipartisan habit to turn vexing public problems into child-centered causes whenever possible. Poverty, health care policy, budget priorities, tobacco companies: the list of issues we must address out of concern for the fate of children keeps growing. Bill McKibben now urges us to address the fate of children out of concern for the issue he cares about most, the environment. In ''Maybe One,'' he brings anxiety about global warming down to earth -- right to your hearth -- by casting it in terms of an intimate childbearing choice. We have until 2050 or so, he gauges, to ''stabilize climate at the current level of disruption'' and prevent a precariously balanced world from getting utterly out of whack. Since ''cleverer technologies and more humble aspirations'' may not do the job fast enough, stabilizing the population can serve as a safeguard. If more Americans stopped at a single child, he proposes, we might buy time to ''salvage what we can of our relationship with the earth, keep things from getting any worse than they have to be.''</p>
        <p>McKibben once again proves himself an expert recycler. Ever since he left The New Yorker a decade ago, he has plowed events in his simple Adirondack life into his ecological writing, and plowed elements of each book into the next one. He recently had a daughter, and a vasectomy. Hence this repackaged variation on the ''think small'' theme of both ''The End of Nature'' (1989) -- in which he and his wife, worrying about global warming, tried ''very hard not to think about how much we'd like a baby'' -- and ''The Age of Missing Information'' (1992), a hymn to rustic, television-free life.</p>
        <p>A hair-shirt alarmist in his youth, McKibben has acquired some Snugli-inspired optimism that an ecological consciousness need not be apocalyptic. ''It is possible that we face unavoidable calamity,'' he still fears; ''but it's also possible that we'll see remarkable change,'' he now hopes. McKibben tucks his ecological case for a lower birth rate, slower economic growth and reduced immigration into the middle of his slim book. It won't win over ''cornucopians'' convinced that there are no limits to the earth's carrying capacity. But readers unnerved by the weird weather, and by the recent invasion of sport utility vehicles, are well primed to nod at green sentiments served up so gently -- and to nod off at the big statistics he sprinkles here and there. Who on earth can say whether McKibben's dream scenario for the United States -- a birth rate of 1.5 children per woman, combined with annual immigration of 400,000, for a population of 230 million in 2050 -- is the answer? He himself only ventures that it ''could be crucial, I think, in reducing our environmental damage.''</p>
        <p>In fact, he's counting on his readers not to trouble their heads too much with the math. One paradox of the think-small creed is that much of its authority rests on the kind of large, abstract calculations that it deems properly beyond human ken. But McKibben's smallest number, that 1.5 birth rate (down from the current 1.9), merits a closer look, since it's the linchpin of the rest of his book. Given the proportion of women the Census Bureau reports as already having zero or one offspring, there's an easier way to arrive at McKibben's goal than to concoct a campaign to persuade -- not, he emphasizes, coerce -- a large portion of the rest to have only one child. He could just urge women who have three or more children to stop at two. (In fact, his campaign for one threatens to undermine his own cause. It's a good way to guarantee that the environmentalist ethic wanes as green-minded nurturers, who are likely to rear little recyclers in their own image, produce a minority of America's children.)</p>
        <p>But the just-say-two line is old hat, and would deprive McKibben of the ''personal'' part of his argument. In it, he employs intimate confession (he bares all in detailing his vasectomy) and parenting advice -- two popular genres -- to sell an environmental message of restraint that Americans, despite his best efforts in the past, have failed to take to heart. His marketing sense is that it's ''easier to change fertility than life style. For better or for worse, we live in a culture that can say 'that's enough' in regard to children at least as easily as it can regarding cars.''</p>
        <p>He could well be onto something: a new baby's gas problems, unlike those of a new Ford Bronco, can keep an owner up at night. McKibben now appreciates that an effective call to conscience, in America at least, should not entail too much inconvenience. It's even better, of course, if the ecologically enlightened path is an upscale alternative of sorts. According to the ruminations on family matters with which McKibben begins and ends ''Maybe One,'' that's just what the one-child choice turns out to be for both child and parents.</p>
        <p>In the stroll through psychological literature about only children that opens the book, he has fun showing how they have been unfairly stigmatized as spoiled, lonely oddballs. The child study enthusiast G. Stanley Hall and his disciples planted the stereotype just before the turn of the century in ''A Study of Peculiar and Exceptional Children,'' which McKibben judges ''anecdotal, lamebrained and meaningless,'' and unduly influential. Actually, as he later admits, these conventional prejudices may not have been so misplaced back in an era when many families were very isolated. And by the 1920's, ''reputable studies'' began challenging anxieties about onlies. McKibben rounds up the data with a zeal Dr. Hall would have approved of, allowing himself only a passing giggle over such sophisticated modern measurements as an Anomie Index and an Index of Richness of Past Experience. But challenging the bias against singletons by showing that they seem basically indistinguishable from other children -- no more anomie than average -- isn't quite enough for this proudly solicitous father of one. The exceptionalist stereotype lives on as McKibben somewhat immodestly hints now and then that such intensively nurtured children may have a leg up in life.</p>
        <p>He spends the last section of the book rescuing the parents of only children from the reputation of being selfish, soulless, immature hedonists. McKibben (a Sunday-school teacher in his spare time) tours centuries of religious, especially Christian, arguments about celibacy and fecundity more reverentially than he does the psychological findings about onlies, but emerges equally satisfied with both journeys. His conclusion is that the earth being full enough, thank you, those who selflessly, maturely and soulfully choose to be less fruitful and multiply only once can consider themselves holier than thou. They have more precious time to devote to their child, to their careers and to good causes. ''The technologies of contraception,'' McKibben informs his readers, ''can be used as technologies of indulgence and self-obsession, but they can be the technologies of humility as well.''</p>
        <p>McKibben's real accomplishment in ''Maybe One,'' appropriately enough, is humbler than his sometimes sanctimonious tone suggests. He's highly unlikely to start a one-child trend (or, let's hope, a vogue in vasectomy memoirs). As he himself acknowledges, index-laden psychological studies of family health and success won't clinch the case for most people, unless, like McKibben, they've already made up their minds. Such generalizing misses the chastening yet also inspiring wisdom the second child brings: the daily reminder that no two children, or their relations with their parents, are alike. In any case, the great bulk of McKibben's natural audience of fellow baby boomers is already well embarked on childbearing. His best shot is to sway choices at the margins -- forestall that ''afterthought'' third child, those post-40 fertility treatments to give No. 1 a sibling. By reminding us that an only child is only and completely a child, not a freak or part of an unfinished family, he makes two children seem like a lucky luxury. A small revelation, it is all McKibben's own case for cutting back requires.  Ann Hulbert is the author of ''The Interior Castle: The Art and Life of Jean Stafford.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ann Hulbert is the author of ''The Interior Castle: The Art and Life of Jean Stafford.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
