<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Study Says Emissions Cut Will Raise Fuel Costs</title>
    <meta content="09CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052664"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Information Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D7133BF93AA35753C1A96E958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Study Says Emissions Cut Will Raise Fuel Costs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Dept's official forecasting arm produces extraordinarily pessimistic forecast of steeply rising energy prices if United States fights global warming by clamping down on emissions of heat-trapping gases that come from burning fossil fuels; under various outcomes, forecasting arm, Energy Information Adm, projects gasoline prices would rise to $1.91 a gallon and electricty prices could also rise sharply by 2010 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Energy Department's official forecasting arm has produced an extraordinarily pessimistic forecast of steeply rising energy prices if the United States fights global warming by clamping down on emissions of heat-trapping gases that come from burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Under various outcomes, the forecasting arm, the Energy Information Administration, projected gasoline prices would rise to $1.39 to $1.91 a gallon, and electricity prices would rise 20 percent to 86 percent by 2010. Natural gas prices would rise significantly, and coal prices would soar, the forecast said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Energy Department's official forecasting arm has produced an extraordinarily pessimistic forecast of steeply rising energy prices if the United States fights global warming by clamping down on emissions of heat-trapping gases that come from burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>Under various outcomes, the forecasting arm, the Energy Information Administration, projected gasoline prices would rise to $1.39 to $1.91 a gallon, and electricity prices would rise 20 percent to 86 percent by 2010. Natural gas prices would rise significantly, and coal prices would soar, the forecast said.</p>
        <p>Under an international agreement negotiated last year in Kyoto, Japan, the United States would have to reduce emissions of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases significantly in 10 to 15 years. But the treaty is in trouble in Congress, where opponents often say it would wreck the economy.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department's forecast is sharply at odds with the Clinton Administration's previous assertions that the United States can meet the targets set by the treaty without significant economic disruption. The forecast is to be presented on Friday at a Congressional hearing.</p>
        <p>The new study plays directly into the hands of treaty opponents, but those who favor the treaty said it is deeply flawed.</p>
        <p>Energy conservation advocates said the forecast, produced using the Energy Information Administration's standard economic models, had relied on absurd assumptions and improper analysis to reach ridiculous conclusions.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the most flawed, biased, intellectually dishonest analyses ever produced by an supposedly unbiased analytical organization,'' said Joseph J. Romm, a former Assistant Energy Secretary. Mr. Romm is an expert on energy technologies like solar power and conservation that would help control greenhouse gas emissions.</p>
        <p>He and other critics said the study discounted many of the policies, like tax incentives and research subsidies, that the Administration had proposed for enforcing the treaty if the Senate approved it. They said it used computer models that were unreliable for long-term forecasting.</p>
        <p>They said it did not account for the lower costs that would result from a key feature of the Administration's climate change policy: international emissions trading, which would allow the United States to meet the treaty's targets largely by paying other countries to reduce their output of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Critics also said the forecast assumed that businesses would be slow to adopt new energy technologies although, under the forecast's own projections, the costs of not acting would be high.</p>
        <p>Many such computer models have been used for projecting the costs of the Kyoto agreement protocol on climate change. Because so much depends on the assumptions of the models, their predictions may not be reliable. And critics noted that the Energy Department had a long track record of making bad predictions about long-range trends in energy prices and pollution control costs.</p>
        <p>Even so, the new study is certain to fuel criticism of the treaty. The study is scheduled to be presented on Friday at a hearing of the House Science Committee, whose chairman, Representative F. James Sensenbrenner Jr., a Wisconsin Republican, is a leading critic of the treaty.</p>
        <p>The study's projections of the costs of controlling the emissions of greenhouse gases are significantly greater than the predictions of several similar studies, even the gloomy forecasts paid for by industry opponents of the treaty that predicted extraordinary costs.</p>
        <p>And it predicts that the costs would be much higher than predicted by Janet L. Yellen, chairwoman of the Council of Economic Advisers, in a study released in July.</p>
        <p>Eileen Claussen, a former senior State Department official who helped negotiate the Kyoto agreement, said that just as Dr. Yellen's analysis was wildly optimistic, this one was wildly pessimistic.</p>
        <p>''Both of these forecasts are totally unrealistic,'' Ms. Claussen said. ''It is the most bizarre thing. They haven't put out a single bit of analytical work on the costs that has any credibility at all.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Claussen now directs the Pew Center on Climate Change, which has drawn together major corporations pledging early actions to cut their  emissions of greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romm, who now consults with businesses on how to cut greenhouse gas emissions, criticized the report's assertions that emerging technologies like solar power and fuel cells would gain little over 20 years although costs of traditional fuels were likely to rise.</p>
        <p>He ridiculed the study's finding that even with coal prices soaring, power plants would not install any measurable cogeneration equipment, which uses waste heat to generate extra electricity from coal.</p>
        <p>Although the new study predicts slowing economic growth as a result of higher energy costs, over the long run this amounts to just tens of billions of dollars in an economy that grows to more than $10 trillion.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
