<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Leaves Washington Controversy Behind to Talk Policy in the Midwest</title>
    <meta content="Y29CLI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991347"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">State of the Union Message</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">La Crosse (Wis)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Champaign (Ill)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">State of the Union Message (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DB173AF93AA15752C0A96E958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Leaves Washington Controversy Behind to Talk Policy in the Midwest</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bennet, James</byline>
      <dateline>LA CROSSE, Wis., Jan. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton speaks in La Crosse, Wis, and Champaign-Urbana, Ill, about issues he raised in his State of Union Address, but he does not mention accusations that he had affair with White House intern Monica S Lewinsky (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Setting aside certain slight if metaphorically inconvenient mishaps -- notably when Air Force One got stuck in the Illinois mud -- President Clinton had a politically comforting day today after a very bad week.</p>
        <p>With his last national election behind him but perhaps his toughest political fight ahead, Mr. Clinton returned to the campaign style that he loves, trying as he has in past crises to substitute public excitement about his policies for any suspicions about his personal conduct.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Setting aside certain slight if metaphorically inconvenient mishaps -- notably when Air Force One got stuck in the Illinois mud -- President Clinton had a politically comforting day today after a very bad week.</p>
        <p>With his last national election behind him but perhaps his toughest political fight ahead, Mr. Clinton returned to the campaign style that he loves, trying as he has in past crises to substitute public excitement about his policies for any suspicions about his personal conduct.</p>
        <p>Introduced by a revved-up Vice President Al Gore and showered with cheers by the biggest crowds he has seen since his second Inaugural Address, President Clinton spoke here and in Champaign-Urbana, Ill., about fixing the Social Security system, fighting global warming, and improving education.</p>
        <p>He did not take questions. And he did not mention accusations boiling over back in Washington -- and on the minds of many in his audiences -- that he had had an affair with an intern, Monica S. Lewinsky, and then urged her to lie about it under oath.</p>
        <p>''It feels good to be back in God's country tonight,'' Mr. Clinton shouted at the rally here, on his first trip out of Washington since the disclosure of the accusations against him a week ago. Thousands of people packed the plaza outside the La Crosse Center and spilled back down the streets leading to it.</p>
        <p>As he listed the economic accomplishments of his Administration, Mr. Clinton predicted for the first time tonight that the budget would be balanced this year. ''I think it'll be balanced before the year's out,'' he said. His aides had previously indicated that they expected the deficit to all but disappear this year, for the first time in three decades.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore delivered growling stemwinders in urging the audiences to stand by the President, although he never mentioned the charges against Mr. Clinton. By contrast, the President rambled a bit, as he often does before smaller crowds. He extolled the virtues of the Internet, and, as he discussed Social Security in Illinois, he grew wistful about his youth. ''I thought I would live forever, always young,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Keep your eyes on the future,'' he urged the crowd of more than 10,000, which filled the University of Illinois Assembly Hall up to its ceiling. Then, because his whole audience could not fit into the Assembly Hall, Mr. Clinton addressed two overflow crowds of thousands more in other auditoriums.</p>
        <p>Today's trip had been carefully planned by Mr. Clinton's aides -- who picked friendly towns with strong economies -- to produce enthusiastic crowds for a reprise of policies Mr. Clinton outlined in his State of the Union Message Tuesday night. But the timing and venues, Mr. Clinton's aides said, turned out to be perfect to showcase the President going about the people's business, the image his aides want to project in this crisis.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Clinton left the University of Illinois to travel here, the White House's plans went slightly awry. As Mr. Clinton's 707 attempted a right turn onto the main runway, one wheel rolled off the tarmac onto grass, and the plane stopped dead.</p>
        <p>The President was delayed for more than an hour while a substitute airplane rushed to Champaign-Urbana. His aides sadly shook their heads over an embarrassing image that they believed would dominate television newscasts. They were right.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also confronted less figurative reminders of his difficulties. Directly across the Mississippi River from the rally here, carved into the snow piled on the western bank, was a one-word message: ''Impeach,'' in gigantic letters. The same message, in similar dimensions, appeared in a field near here under the President's flight path.</p>
        <p>White House advance teams in both locations had been drumming up crowds for days. At the University of Illinois only two previous Presidents had ever spoken -- Gerald R. Ford in 1976 and William Howard Taft in 1911. The line to see Mr. Clinton started forming at 2 o'clock this morning, in frosty air redolent of nearby hog farms.</p>
        <p>Opinions about Mr. Clinton and the scandal were as varied as the rumors dogging the President. But among Democrats at least, the general sentiment was captured by one of the rock songs played by the school band as Mr. Clinton arrived at the stadium in Illinois: ''Carry On, My Wayward Son,'' by the band Kansas.</p>
        <p>''That's his own business, between him and his wife,'' said Betty Williams, 61, of Urbana.</p>
        <p>Michelle Palmer, 24, said that she did not vote for Mr. Clinton in 1996. But she said that people made too much of his private life. ''If it didn't directly have anything to do with the way this country's ran, I don't think it's any of my business,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her father, John S. Palmer, who called himself a die-hard Republican, disagreed. ''Sure it's our business,''' he said. ''He's the President of the United States.'' Mr. Palmer, a disabled veteran, said that he was concerned about accusations that Mr. Clinton had lied and obstructed justice. But, he said, if he could just resolve his personal troubles, Mr. Clinton would ''be a damn good President.''</p>
        <p>THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
