<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Blasts Shake Foundation of Effort to Limit Nuclear Arms</title>
    <meta content="Y03NUK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1021771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Tests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Tests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E6D8153BF930A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Blasts Shake Foundation of Effort to Limit Nuclear Arms</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH MILLER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts say Indian and Pakistani nuclear tests have undermined accords and assumptions that form basis for efforts to stop spread of nuclear arms; says tests have all but doomed prospects for Senate approval of Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty; say tests have revived fierce debate over how to get nations to keep their commitments not to develop nuclear arms and how to stop India and Pakistan from plunging into nuclear arms race; arms control advocates disagree on how much tests have changed prospects for halting spread of weapons and how United States and other nations should respond (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The nuclear tests by India and Pakistan have undermined the agreements and assumptions on which efforts to stop the spread of nuclear weapons have been based for the last 30 years, a range of officials, analysts and diplomats say.</p>
        <p>They say the tests have also helped to all but doom prospects this year for Senate approval of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, which the Clinton Administration has made a high priority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The nuclear tests by India and Pakistan have undermined the agreements and assumptions on which efforts to stop the spread of nuclear weapons have been based for the last 30 years, a range of officials, analysts and diplomats say.</p>
        <p>They say the tests have also helped to all but doom prospects this year for Senate approval of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, which the Clinton Administration has made a high priority.</p>
        <p>The tests have also revived a fierce debate about how to get countries to keep their commitments not to develop nuclear weapons and how to stop India and Pakistan from plunging into a nuclear arms race.</p>
        <p>''The nuclear tests are the most significant and damaging proliferation event in years,'' said Lawrence Scheinman, who until August was assistant director of the United States Arms Control and Disarmament Agency and is now director of the Washington office of the Monterey Institute of International Studies, an arms control research center.</p>
        <p>But arms control advocates disagree about how much the tests have changed the prospects for halting the spread of the weapons and how the United States and other nations should respond.</p>
        <p>Some analysts say the amount of damage to efforts to stop the spread of nuclear weapons will depend on whether India and Pakistan are forced to pay a high price for their tests. They say that would mean getting other countries to join the United States in imposing tough sanctions to discourage similar tests.</p>
        <p>Other experts warn that while the tests have undermined American efforts, the Administration should acknowledge that neither India nor Pakistan is as potentially dangerous as countries like Iraq or Iran. Isolating India and Pakistan with tough sanctions, they say, may only complicate efforts to keep them from putting nuclear warheads atop missiles and from sharing their nuclear know-how with other countries.</p>
        <p>''American policy has always placed India, Pakistan and Israel in an unstated, special category -- the de facto weapons state,'' said Richard N. Haass, director of foreign policy studies at the Brookings Institution. ''So we need to continue distinguishing, in fact, if not in arms control theory, between them and rogue states.''</p>
        <p>''An all-out isolation campaign is a mistake,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some arms control advocates say the Administration has not put sufficient emphasis on nuclear disarmament in general. Paul Leventhal, president of the Nuclear Control Institute, a Washington-based nonprofit group that lobbies for arms control, said the Administration had inadvertently encouraged the tests by making trade a higher priority.</p>
        <p>Others cite the relative lack of progress in disarmament by the two countries with the most nuclear weapons -- the United States and Russia -- noting that treaties and agreements between them permit each side to have 3,500 long-range nuclear missiles and unlimited tactical nuclear weapons. But most analysts give the Administration relatively high marks for its efforts to stop the spread of the weapons.</p>
        <p>In 1996, the Administration claimed a major arms control achievement -- helping to draft the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty, which bans all test explosions, and persuading reluctant Governments in China and France to sign.</p>
        <p>In an effort to counter opposition in the United States, the Administration  agreed to spend $45 billion over the next 10 years to enable weapons laboratories here to develop ways to check the reliability of bombs without detonating them, by using computer simulation, for instance.</p>
        <p>But even before the Indian and Pakistani tests, the treaty was already on life support in the Senate. Conservative Republicans, including Senator Jesse Helms, the influential chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, said adherence to the treaty could not be verified and vowed to block Senate approval.</p>
        <p>In January, Mr. Helms wrote President Clinton that he would not consider the test ban treaty until the Senate voted on the Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty and the global warming treaty. In practical terms, that meant the test ban treaty had virtually no chance of coming to a vote in the Senate this year.</p>
        <p>Now, some arms control analysts say, the Indian and Pakistani tests may have lessened the chances even further.</p>
        <p>Ten prominent members of the Union of Concerned Scientists -- including Adm. William Crowe, former Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff; Hans Bethe, the Nobel Prize-winning physicist; and Herbert York, a former founding director of the Livermore National Laboratories -- sent letters to the Senate urging action on the treaty now.</p>
        <p>Mr. Haass of Brookings, who worked in the Bush White House, said: ''Even if India and Pakistan do sign the test ban, which India has hinted it may do, the tests make the treaty something of a mockery. To push for it now says: Get your testing done and then sign. Why should we reinforce this cynical message when the problem is not so much further testing as stopping the deployment, use and transfer of nuclear technology.''</p>
        <p>So far, however, the Administration maintains that it has ''redoubled'' its commitment to the treaty. The Indian and Pakistani tests, a senior White House official said, ''demonstrate the urgent need for such a treaty now.''</p>
        <p>''Don't write the treaty's epitaph just yet,'' the official said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
