<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lilco Is to Stop Selling Credits to Upwind Polluters</title>
    <meta content="30AIR.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1013550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal Clean Air Act</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Lighting Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E2DE153EF933A05757C0A96E958260" item-length="1020" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lilco Is to Stop Selling Credits to Upwind Polluters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Lighting Co, in move that could help reduce amount of air pollution that drifts from Midwestern and Southern states to New York, announces that it will stop selling pollution credits it earned by cleaning its its own smokestacks to polluters in these states; decision underscores limitation of major strategy enshrined in 1990 Federal Clean Air Act: that market place trading of right to pollute is inexpensive way of cleaning up environment without setting inflexible Government rules (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move that could help reduce the amount of air pollution that drifts from Midwestern and Southern states to New York, the Long Island Lighting Company announced today that it would stop selling pollution credits it earned by cleaning its own smokestacks to polluters in those states.</p>
        <p>The decision, coming at the urging of New York State, underscores a limitation of a major strategy enshrined in the 1990 Federal Clean Air Act: that marketplace trading of the right to pollute is an inexpensive way of cleaning up the environment without setting inflexible Government rules. But as New York State and its neighbors have learned, the marketplace cannot stop the wind from blowing pollution eastward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a move that could help reduce the amount of air pollution that drifts from Midwestern and Southern states to New York, the Long Island Lighting Company announced today that it would stop selling pollution credits it earned by cleaning its own smokestacks to polluters in those states.</p>
        <p>The decision, coming at the urging of New York State, underscores a limitation of a major strategy enshrined in the 1990 Federal Clean Air Act: that marketplace trading of the right to pollute is an inexpensive way of cleaning up the environment without setting inflexible Government rules. But as New York State and its neighbors have learned, the marketplace cannot stop the wind from blowing pollution eastward.</p>
        <p>Under the act, any company that cut its emissions below Federal standards could earn pollution credits that it could then sell to other companies that were having a hard time meeting those standards. Thus, the companies that did improve would be rewarded for doing it, while the laggards had to, in essence, buy the right to keep polluting.</p>
        <p>But environmentally sensitive areas like the Adirondacks and the Catskills have suffered immensely under the free-market approach, experts say, as major polluters in the South and the Middle West have found it cheaper to buy pollution credits instead of cutting toxic emissions that eventually blow back into New York and contribute to its acid rain problem.</p>
        <p>The move by Lilco marks the first time a company has agreed to tailor the sales of its pollution credits to prevent them from falling into the hands of out-of-state polluters whose emissions might harm the company's home state, according to environmental experts and state officials.</p>
        <p>Even so, there is no guarantee that the move by Lilco will reduce pollution or acid rain in New York State, since polluters in the South and the Midwest could turn to other companies to buy the credits. But experts say Lilco's move reduces their flexibility in gathering credits and may force them to purchase credits in smaller parcels from many different companies.</p>
        <p>The move represents a striking reversal for Lilco, which has been harshly criticized in recent years for selling hundreds of thousands of pollution credits to dozens of utilities and coal companies scattered throughout states that are upwind of New York, including West Virginia, Ohio, Michigan, Illinois, Kentucky and Indiana.</p>
        <p>The decision is also significant because Lilco is among the most aggressive sellers of pollution credits in the state, state officials say.</p>
        <p>The company has sold 260,000 credits since 1994, the vast majority of them going to polluters in the upwind states. The credits cost about $140 each and allow polluters to emit one ton of sulfur dioxide, a major contributor to acid rain and smog. Lilco's credits account for about one-half of one percent of all the sulfur dioxide emitted in the United States.</p>
        <p>Lilco estimates that it would be entitled to 1.2 million credits over the next 30 years.</p>
        <p>The announcement today was hailed as a victory by state officials and environmentalists. They said it ought to send a strong message to Federal officials that pollution-credit trading has allowed utilities in regions like the Midwest to continue burning high-sulfur coal at the expense of states like New York that have laws and regulations forcing such companies to reduce their own emissions.</p>
        <p>''This is a principled act on behalf of Lilco,'' said John P. Cahill, the State Commissioner of Environmental Conservation. ''This is the first time in the nation that any state has acted on the recognition that these trades create regional inequities.''  John F. Sheehan, spokesman for the Adirondack Council, said the agreement was particularly important because it could help reduce acid rain in environmentally fragile areas like the Adirondacks. He noted that state and Federal officials estimate that by the year 2040, nearly half of that region's 2,800 lakes and ponds will be too acidic to sustain the fishes and plants that now live in them if the acid rain problem persists unabated.</p>
        <p>''This is a significant deal because Lilco is a major player in the pollution credit market,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But even as environmental groups praised the deal, they insisted that it did not diminish the need for either Federal or state legislation that would prevent pollution-credit sales that help polluters in one region at the expense of another.</p>
        <p>''This is a Band-Aid approach that doesn't address the larger problem,'' said Assemblyman Richard L. Brodsky, a Westchester Democrat who is chairman of the environmental conservation committee. ''There is still a need to pass legislation that regulates the other utilities.''</p>
        <p>The pollution-credit trading system was approved by Congress at the urging of economists and some environmentalists, who said it would improve efficiency in pollution reduction. The intent is to encourage that reductions be made in the cheapest way possible while not affecting the amount of emission reduction nationwide.</p>
        <p>The act gave Lilco a windfall because a New York State law had forced it to reduce emissions in the 1980's to levels below what the Federal law requires. As a result, Lilco has 70,000 pollution-credit allowances a year to sell.</p>
        <p>Under the deal announced today, Lilco would not sell credits to companies in 10 Southern and Midwestern states. They are Virginia, North Carolina, Tennessee, West Virginia, Ohio, Michigan, Illinois, Kentucky, Indiana and Wisconsin. Nor would Lilco be allowed to sell credits to companies in New York and four nearby states, including New Jersey, Pennsylvania and Delaware, according to the deal.</p>
        <p>The deal also contains a provision that would prohibit any company that does buy credits from Lilco from turning around and selling those credits to polluters in states that Lilco is not permitted to trade with directly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
