<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Global Warming, or Hot Air?</title>
    <meta content="Y03WAR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1050998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE AD CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Global Climate Information Project</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E5D61238F930A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="968" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Global Warming, or Hot Air?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Global Climate Information Project, a coalition of business, labor and farm groups, sponsors two television commercials opposing agreement reached in Kyoto, Japan, in December 1997 to reduce emissions of industrial waste gases that are blamed for global warming; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A coalition of business, labor and farm groups called the Global Climate Information Project has been sponsoring two television commercials for the last month opposing an agreement reached in Kyoto, Japan, last December to reduce emissions of industrial waste gases believed to cause global warming. One commercial is a 30-second spot called ''In Common.''</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Goddard Claussen</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A coalition of business, labor and farm groups called the Global Climate Information Project has been sponsoring two television commercials for the last month opposing an agreement reached in Kyoto, Japan, last December to reduce emissions of industrial waste gases believed to cause global warming. One commercial is a 30-second spot called ''In Common.''</p>
        <p>PRODUCER -- Goddard Claussen</p>
        <p>ON THE SCREEN -- A pair of scissors slices developing countries like India, Algeria, Thailand, Mexico and Brazil out of the world map. In a broader shot, the entire third world dissolves to white.</p>
        <p>THE SCRIPT -- Female voice: The United Nations climate treaty cuts 134 countries out of the picture. Together, these countries' greenhouse gas emissions are growing five times faster than the rest of the world's, and the U.N.'s treaty will allow them to produce even more. So while America and a few other countries are forced to drastically cut energy use, countries like China, India and Mexico will continue to produce even more emissions. This U.N. treaty isn't global, and it won't work.</p>
        <p>ACCURACY -- All 175 countries that have ratified the 1992 United Nations climate treaty are obligated, in general, to control emissions of heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide, which is produced by the burning of fossil fuels like coal and oil. But 39 industrialized nations including the United States, meeting in Kyoto, added a provision to the treaty that requires them to make specific cuts in emissions totaling about 5 percent below 1990 levels during the next 10 to 14 years. These 39 countries now produce most of the world's greenhouse emissions, even though poorer countries' emissions are growing and may exceed those of the richer countries in a decade or two. The poorer countries, arguing that the rich countries got wealthy by burning fossil fuels, have long refused to bind themselves to specific cuts until the richer countries lead the way. It is not clear that the Kyoto accord would require America to cut energy use drastically; many experts believe that eliminating energy waste by using fuel more efficiently would go far toward achieving the cuts.</p>
        <p>SCORECARD -- Many of the commercial's sponsors fear that they would be hurt by action to reduce emissions, and they are trying to convince viewers that the Kyoto agreement would be unfair and costly to Americans. The American Automobile Manufacturers Association took the lead in organizing the campaign, according to Karen Kerrigan, the sponsoring coalition's chairwoman. Among the reasons why the spot is running now, she said, are these: Delegates from around the world are to meet in Buenos Aires in November to try to work out details of the Kyoto accord. The Kyoto agreement must still be approved by the Senate. (It has not yet been submitted by the White House.) And the Clinton Administration has recently been lobbying for urgent action to control emissions in the face of rising global temperatures.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM K. STEVENS</p>
        <p>THE AD CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
