<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED7103FF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-17</p>
        <p>E Pluribus Euro: The Next Big Step  Germany, France and nine other European countries are soon to surrender a central pillar of national sovereignty: control over their currencies. The first big step comes this week, when European leaders are to set the exchange rates at which currencies will be locked together.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Threat of Germ Weapons  The Federal Government is taking a new look at the terrorist threat of germ weapons. And officials are disturbed to find that the United States is not prepared for a devastating new type of biological terror.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-17</p>
        <p>E Pluribus Euro: The Next Big Step  Germany, France and nine other European countries are soon to surrender a central pillar of national sovereignty: control over their currencies. The first big step comes this week, when European leaders are to set the exchange rates at which currencies will be locked together.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Threat of Germ Weapons  The Federal Government is taking a new look at the terrorist threat of germ weapons. And officials are disturbed to find that the United States is not prepared for a devastating new type of biological terror.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>In Poll, Deep Support for Israel  As Israel prepares for its 50th anniversary, most Americans continue to have a positive view of the country, a poll indicates, saying that Israel is vital to American interests.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>No Jewish lobbying group in Washington is as influential -- or as feared -- as the American Israel Public Affairs Committee.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Iraq Sees Cracks in Its Isolation  Sanctions against Iraq are likely to be extended next week, but Iraq's Foreign Minister said Baghdad's isolation is eroding ''whether the Americans like it or not.''</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>Cleaning Up Thai Corruption  A corruption-fighting general is leading a campaign to reform the political system. Many Thais say that regulators who are paid off to overlook rule-breaking are partly responsible for the nation's economic turmoil.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Burmese Dissident Is Isolated  Any hopes that the Burmese military regime was becoming more tolerate have been ended, and the opposition leader, Daw Aung San Suu Kyi, is still kept isolated.</p>
        <p>9</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>18-28</p>
        <p>Group Plans to Fight Global Warming Treaty  Opponents of a treaty to fight global warming have proposed to spend millions of dollars to convince the public that the environmental accord is based on shaky science. Opposition to the climate treaty is a daunting public relations task; the treaty's advocates, including the Clinton Administration, present the science on global warming as essentially settled and unchallengeable.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Hillary Clinton Testifies  Hillary Rodham Clinton was questioned at the White House about her Arkansas legal work by Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, and other prosecutors from his office, Administration officials said. The session was videotaped to be shown to a Federal grand jury in Arkansas.</p>
        <p>22</p>
        <p>I.R.S. Charges Repudiated  Most of the accusations of abuse of taxpayers that an Internal Revenue Service agent made at Senate hearings last September are unfounded or cannot be substantiated, the Treasury Department's Inspector General said in a report.</p>
        <p>23</p>
        <p>Fears Along the Bay  After last year's outbreaks of a toxic microbe in Chesapeake Bay, watermen, business owners and farmers along the bay are feeling anxious as another summer approaches.</p>
        <p>18</p>
        <p>'Midget' Remark Controversy  The Houston Mayor has suspended his director of affirmative action after she used the term ''midget'' to refer to a city councilman who is a dwarf. The director, whose comments set off a controversy, was suspended for three days and ordered to develop a new sensitivity-training program for city employees.</p>
        <p>19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>29-36</p>
        <p>A Local Media Mogul  Dick French Jr. is the Ted Turner of the Hudson Valley -- in four years, he has expanded Regional News Network, a 24-hour news operation based in Kingston, N.Y., from a station that broadcast to 250,000 homes upstate to one that reaches 2.4 million homes through cable systems in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut. Now he has gone to court to expand WRNN into New York City.</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>The Gotti Tapes  Movie-like dialogue is typical of the remarks captured on 7,000 surveillance tapes that are the heart of the racketeering case against John A.Gotti, sometimes called Junior, that prosecutors are preparing to bring to trial here. They say the son of the dapper Mafia leader who is in prison for life is the new Gambino boss. From what is known about the tapes, it is clear they include enough expletives, veiled threats and sarcasm to seem like a mob-movie parody. On the tapes, people actually use names like Tommy Sneakers.</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>Rabbi's Case Is Reviewed  Federal prosecutors are examining whether state officials gave lenient treatment to a Hasidic rabbi imprisoned in a widely publicized kidnapping case after appeals were made on his behalf by a fund-raiser for Gov. George E. Pataki, officials and others involved in the inquiry say.</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>39</p>
        <p>George Masters  A high school dropout turned master hairdresser and stylist who worked for almost half a century at the pinnacle of his profession. He traveled from salon to salon bringing his uncanny sense of color and composition, but was best known as the makeup artist who transformed Dustin Hoffman into Tootsie for the 1982 movie. He was 62.</p>
        <p>39</p>
        <p>Cong. Vote</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>36</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
