<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Conversation: With Tyler Volk; Using Flows and Fluxes to Demythologize the Unity of Life</title>
    <meta content="11GAIA0AE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Volk, Tyler (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neimark, Jill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biology and Biochemistry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E1DB163AF932A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Conversation: With Tyler Volk; Using Flows and Fluxes to Demythologize the Unity of Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JILL NEIMARK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Neimark, Jill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dr Tyler Volk, biologist and member of board of directors of Gaia: The Society for Research and Education in Earth Systems Science who sees world as interconnected whole--or as symphony of biochemical guilds; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes science and myth merge to make a kind of chimerical beast, and perhaps the most magical of those Chimeras is the Gaia hypothesis, developed a quarter century ago by James Lovelock, a British atmospheric chemist, and Lynn Margulis, an American microbiologist.  The notion that our planet's surface functions like a giant organism, one interconnected whole, was named after the Greek earth goddess, and it has attracted not just pagans and mystics but also atmospheric chemists, ecologists, oceanographers, microbiologists and geologists.</p>
        <p>Tyler Volk, 47, is an associate professor of biology at New York University and a member of the board of directors of Gaia: The Society for Research and Education in Earth System Science, which was formed to inspire interdisciplinary research into the Gaia hypothesis. Dr. Volk is a principal investigator with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration who studies crop growth in closed systems. He divides his time between New York City and New Mexico, where he spends summers in a trailer in the Mogollon mountains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes science and myth merge to make a kind of chimerical beast, and perhaps the most magical of those Chimeras is the Gaia hypothesis, developed a quarter century ago by James Lovelock, a British atmospheric chemist, and Lynn Margulis, an American microbiologist.  The notion that our planet's surface functions like a giant organism, one interconnected whole, was named after the Greek earth goddess, and it has attracted not just pagans and mystics but also atmospheric chemists, ecologists, oceanographers, microbiologists and geologists.</p>
        <p>Tyler Volk, 47, is an associate professor of biology at New York University and a member of the board of directors of Gaia: The Society for Research and Education in Earth System Science, which was formed to inspire interdisciplinary research into the Gaia hypothesis. Dr. Volk is a principal investigator with the National Aeronautics and Space Administration who studies crop growth in closed systems. He divides his time between New York City and New Mexico, where he spends summers in a trailer in the Mogollon mountains.</p>
        <p>He wrote the recently published Gaia's Body: Toward a Physiology of Earth (Copernicus).</p>
        <p>Q. When Lovelock first discussed the Gaia hypothesis, he admitted it was at the outer bounds of scientific credibility and he had a hard time even finding a journal to publish his ideas.  What do you think of the original theory?  A. Gaia started with a stupendous metaphor and a unique scientific insight, and I think Lovelock has a special charisma. In a simple sentence, traditional Gaia theory postulates something called ''comfortable conditions for life,'' and asserts that the Gaian system maintains those conditions. It looks at the constancy of temperature, climate, gasses, the ocean environment.</p>
        <p>The million-dollar question that Lovelock first asked was, Why is atmospheric oxygen constant at 21 percent, the level needed to maintain complex life? But I think there's been too much emphasis on the ill-defined idea of comfort and on environmental stability. I think the key is almost the opposite: the flow and flux of life, of the chemical processes of organisms over the entire planet. The sheer, raw power of life.  Q. How do you actually measure something as diverse as life spread across an entire planet?  A. I'm looking at chemical, global productivity. I study the ratio at which different elements crucial to life are recycled, or passed from organism to organism. The cycling ratio of an element instantly reveals the power of life. Take carbon, the heart of life on our planet. If all that was available was the amount shed from rocks and volcanoes, a carbon atom might be released into the environment, utilized just once by an organism, and then buried. But that's not what happens. Carbon is taken up into an organism and then recycled, either because the organism dies and becomes part of the biosphere's resources again, or because it's eaten by another organism, or because it sheds carbon as waste. A single atom of carbon is actually recycled 200 times before it is buried. So you can see the power of the flow of life.  Q. So the cycling ratio of an element is kind of like a basketball team that keeps passing the ball, and after 200 passes finally retires it? We know that life is carbon-based, but how important are the cycling ratios of other elements?  A. The fluxes of all the elements are profoundly revealing, because they tell us what life needs. Nitrogen's cycling ratio can be as high as 1,300, which is a huge amplification. And it's no coincidence that the fluxes of the dozen or so most important elements in our environment are in rough proportion to the fluxes of those same elements in our own living bodies. That shows the unity of life. What's also interesting is how these amplitudes vary across the planet. I had an epiphany when I was working on the equatorial belts of the ocean, trying to understand why they outgassed so much carbon dioxide. I was turning a globe, and I remember suddenly ''seeing'' this huge loop of carbon dioxide flowing from the Pacific Ocean to the North Atlantic, and understanding that the two are one coupled system.  Q. What does the notion of a global breath tell us?  A. In part, how much respiration (breathing out carbon dioxide as waste) and photosynthesis (utilizing carbon dioxide as fuel) is occurring in both places. And that tells us about the different organisms there, and about the fact that there is indeed a global metabolism, with one ocean coupled to the other. And once we can build this large, coherent kind of picture, we can start to formulate questions about the planet and how it works.  Q. Will understanding the global metabolism give us a window into the possibility of life on other planets?  A. It might. We know, for instance, that oxygen could not exist at its  current level on the planet without life -- it's far too reactive a gas, and would on its own combine with other elements and quickly plunge to low levels. In the case of life, photosynthesis constantly pours out oxygen and maintains it at high levels. So the proportion of gasses in a planet's atmosphere may give us a clue to organisms hundreds of light years away. We may be able to look at the spectrum of light reflected off a planet, as Lovelock originally pointed out, and translate that wobble of light waves into knowledge about the proportion of gasses we're seeing. And then we'd know if organic life was driving them.  Q. What else do the cycling ratios of elements tell us about our own planet?  A. They show us the fundamental mechanism of Gaia, which is that waste equals resource. We're more than just predator and prey. Eating is only one form of chemical transfer. When an organism's waste goes out into the world, it can become part of the atmosphere, ocean, or soil, and become part of a vast chemical web. The carbon dioxide you exhale while walking in your back yard has almost as much chance of being taken in by a tree in a forest in China as by local photosynthesis.</p>
        <p>The fluxes of chemicals also give us a whole new way of classifying life forms by their actual functions rather than as species or even kingdoms.  I think of the world as a symphony of what I call biochemical guilds. Plants, algae and many bacteria are members of different kingdoms, but they can be classed as a single biochemical guild of photosynthesizers. Then there's the guild of the respirers, which breathe out carbon dioxide and include everything from frogs to amoeba. There is the guild of nitrogen fixers, which take gaseous nitrogen and transform it. Nitrogen fixers are all microbes, although certain kinds of plants like legumes and some trees harbor the microbes in their roots. If you order our global metabolism by these guilds you can instantly see the unity of Gaia. One of the neatest proofs of the existence of the biochemical guilds is the universal molecular mechanisms shared by their members, the common metabolic machinery down at the molecular level.  Q. Can you give an example of a universal molecule?  A. The green of chlorophyll in all photosynthesizers. I remember when I first saw this guild, in California. I was looking across a lake and suddenly the thicket of trees, shrubs and grasses blended into a single entity. Green. Chlorophyll is the molecule of our most visible guild. Now wherever I go, this guild speaks to me of its presence, even in the winter in the desert in New Mexico. It's as if the guild is saying to me, ''Green is forever.'' The individual parts aren't as important.  Q. What guild are we part of? The respirers?  A. I call us the guild that knows all other guilds. We're not only respirers. We're alchemists, too; we can actually fix nitrogen without the help of bacteria. They use enzymes.  We use heat in factories, and manufacture fertilizers that way. And we take fossil fuel carbons like coal and oil and burn them. We're the first guild that is adding to the chemical fluxes with devices set up outside our bodies.  Q. This use of technology to augment or replace natural processes sounds like a monumental shift. Or are we just doing what life always does, and amplifying cycling ratios?  A. That's the classic question. I think we've taken over the planet in many ways, and, though we will probably never wipe out the microbes, we need to think about what kind of world we want, and the disruption we may cause by changing our ecosystems.  Q. We're losing species at a tremendous rate, and, it seems, drastically altering the climate through the greenhouse effect. Can Gaian science help us preserve ourselves? It sounds like the whole system is hinged together in an exquisitely subtle way.  A. We can measure the biomass of algae and launch satellites to monitor ozone and pull up sediment from lakes to learn which trees lived during the last Ice Age. And then we can start to understand the critical points where the system would collapse. So we can learn, for instance, how to apply nitrogen fertilizer at the proper times and doses, to limit the runoff that endangers ecosystems.  Or we can phase out the release of chlorofluorocarbons. Gaia shows that our actions affect all other life and always come back to us.  Q. Your Gaia sounds almost as romantic and mythic as Lovelock's. Do you really feel you've stripped the metaphor from the science, or are you still seduced by it?  A. I've tried to be more exact with the phrase ''global metabolism'' rather than ''global organism.'' But I may have only partly succeeded. I was walking in a canyon the other day and listening to the thunder, and I thought to myself, ''There's Zeus talking.'' And recently I stopped a truck from running over a rattlesnake, and as the snake crawled off into the bush I thought, ''Well, now all the rattlesnakes will know I'm a good guy and I'll have a little bit of coinage next time I hike in the canyons.'' That way of thinking is so deep and so important to us. This mixing human qualities into nature runs deep in civilization.  Q. It's our way of connecting to the world by seeing and feeling it as self,  rather than other.  A. It's why we painted lions' heads on human bodies, why we turned rain and wind into gods. If I really feel I'm living inside Gaia, if the whole body of the biosphere becomes my self, then I'm truly part of the world. It's important to loosen up the concept of self because if you extend it into the world you're more likely to want to engage with the world, to play in it, not just to see it as a resource for food.  Q. So in that sense, the Gaia metaphor is as powerful a siren song as ever.  A. Yes. As is the science. If you want to worship mystery, studying the global metabolism is a great way to go.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
