<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mosquitoes Are Out To Get Us. But We're Out to Get Them.</title>
    <meta content="21MOSQ$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Suffolk County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kannapell, Andrea</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980621T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7DF113DF932A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="3143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mosquitoes Are Out To Get Us. But We're Out to Get Them.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA KANNAPELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kannapell, Andrea</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on $2 million mosquito control program in Suffolk County, NY, in light of early spring rains; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A WHINE in the air. A sudden silence. That unmistakable stinging moment.</p>
        <p>It is a sequence that has not changed, scientists say, for more than 100 million years, since the early descendants of the tropical Ur-mosquito were buzzing the Cretaceous era, enjoying a bit of Tyrannosaur tartare.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A WHINE in the air. A sudden silence. That unmistakable stinging moment.</p>
        <p>It is a sequence that has not changed, scientists say, for more than 100 million years, since the early descendants of the tropical Ur-mosquito were buzzing the Cretaceous era, enjoying a bit of Tyrannosaur tartare.</p>
        <p>This year, the stinging, slapping and complaining have been gaining momentum. An El Nino-induced early spring gave the breeding season a jump start, and it has also been repeatedly drenched in mosquito-friendly rains. Whether the plague will continue is largely a matter of day-to-day weather conditions, the experts say, with occasional heavy rain promoting mosquitoes. But the indications are all extremely favorable. For the mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>''It's hard to see how we're going to get out of this without a whole lot of mosquitoes,'' said Dominick Ninivaggi, who heads Suffolk County's $2 million mosquito control program, the largest in New York State with several thousand acres of its extensive salt-marshes known to be breeding sites.</p>
        <p>North America counts about 170 species of mosquito, of which Long Island has 42. Not all of them bite humans. In fact, mosquitoes live on a diet of nectar. They pollinate flowers. In an adaptation that is usually mentioned to the accompaniment of bitter male laughter, only the females need blood. They use the protein for their eggs.</p>
        <p>Researchers who identify species get to name them, which, it turns out, is an opportunity to exercise their senses of humor. Among the best-represented in this area is the genus Aedes, which includes the species excrucians, intrudens, provocans, sticticus and vexans. In the genus Coquillettidia, one species is named perturbans.</p>
        <p>The counteroffensive has mobilized. Mondays and Tuesdays, inspectors in Suffolk and Nassau hunt for larvae. Tuesdays and Wednesdays, they check their traps for adults. Thursdays, from trucks and helicopters, workers fling larvacide pellets into the standing pools of brackish water hiding among the dunes along Jones Beach, into Long Island's vast stretches of salt marsh, and into the freshwater red maple swamps of Suffolk County. If all else fails, they fog adult mosquitoes with toxic mist.</p>
        <p>But the whats and the whens and the whys of mosquito control are all different from -- and far more environmentally sensitive than -- what they used to be.</p>
        <p>Prevention is the first order of business, and it takes the form of year-round wetlands management so environmentally friendly that nature conservancy agencies and groups have become willing partners. ''The mosquitoes are in the wetlands, and the mosquito people work in wetlands, and we're interested in improving the quality of the wetlands for wildlife, and we find it's to our mutual benefit to work together,'' said Harry Knoch, regional wildlife director of the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>Last winter, 1,300 acres of sensitive salt marsh was restored in the first year of a decade-long, $10 million cooperative effort involving the state conservation department, the Suffolk County mosquito unit, the Long Island National Wildlife Refuges and Ducks Unlimited, a wetlands preservation group. Another 700 acres are being considered for restoration next winter, some of them in Nassau County, as part of the same effort, known as the Long Island Wetlands Restoration Initiative.</p>
        <p>Workers have removed dikes from abandoned salt-hay farms, encouraging daily tidal flow, and have plugged ditches that drained the marshes twice daily. Although it increases the amount of standing water, this process helps to assure that fish can penetrate breeding areas. Workers even dig ponds so the fish can stay in mosquito-friendly spots even when water levels are low. The fish eat the larvae. The returning shore birds eat the fish. An ecological system gets healthier.</p>
        <p>The wetlands management also discourages an invader weed called phragmites, which edges out the native wetlands grass, spartina, and is a better host to mosquito larvae.</p>
        <p>''Some of us have money, some have equipment, some have manpower,'' Mr. Knoch said. ''Collectively, we can do much more than any of us could do individually.''</p>
        <p>Nassau County mosquito inspectors don't even sample the water in nesting areas of the endangered piping plover without the company of a plover steward. It's a surprising twist for a field whose image, if it exists in the public imagination at all, is that of a huge, governmentally wielded can of Raid.</p>
        <p>It was not always so. When Long Island's mosquito control started in the 1930's, before the era of DDT, cutting-edge technology meant ditches, and W.P.A. workers dug thousands of miles of them to drain salt marshes. Nassau County alone has nearly 1,000 miles of such ditches.</p>
        <p>''The concept behind their work was that if you take the water off the marsh, you take out the mosquitoes,'' explained Craig Kessler, who heads the Long Island branch of Ducks Unlimited. ''And that worked. But it also took out the food chain.''</p>
        <p>That resulted in a loss of habitat for the indigenous black duck and a ''whole host of species,'' Mr. Kessler said, which are now being re-established in the restored marshes. Ducks Unlimited, an international group with 700,000 members, was founded in 1937 by Joseph Knapp, a hunter who realized that waterfowl breeding habitats were being destroyed by the encroachment of farms throughout the midwestern prairies. His great-grandaughter, Mr. Kessler noted, is Sibby Penny, a Southold resident. ''She's quite active in our Peconic Bay chapter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last winter's Restoration Initiative project included 470 acres at the Wertheim National Wildlife Refuge in Shirley, 90 acres at the Seatuck National Wildlife Refuge in Islip, and 100 acres of Suffolk County parkland in Sayville, according to Robert W. Parris, a project leader for the wildlife refuge.</p>
        <p>The Restoration Initiative has focused on salt marshes so far, but the mosquito agencies have been quietly using similar procedures in freshwater swamps. Meandering ditches can reduce sheetwater, where larvae, which must breathe at the surface and feed on the bottom, flourish. But the ditches can be engineered not to dry the areas out, leaving the habitat intact for birds and other creatures. And standing water can be deepened into ponds and stocked with the guppy-sized mosquitofish, Gambusia affinis, a larval vacuum.</p>
        <p>The mosquitofish has also proven useful for some manmade breeding grounds: those early drainage ditches meant to control mosquitoes, left untended, can fill and become new breeding areas.</p>
        <p>Mosquito agencies try to spread the word to municipalities and homeowners that even tiny amounts of standing water can serve as breeding areas for some species. They tell stories of larvae in forgotten pails, swimming pool covers, even bottle caps.</p>
        <p>Careful, thorough monitoring means that larvacides and other chemicals are only used when problems are documented. Inspectors drive around, sampling water for larvae and checking traps for adults. They count the take and identify the species in the lab. They send some to the state laboratory in Albany to be tested for disease. They take  ''landing counts,'' in which inspectors stand still for one minute and count how many mosquitoes land on them. Only when a portrait of a local mosquito population is complete is it time to prescribe a pesticidal treatment.</p>
        <p>Expensive biorational agents -- substances that interfere with the life cycle of the mosquito, but with virtually nothing else -- are the weapons of choice for spraying. Some are preparations of bacteria that attack only larvae of a certain age. For instance, the helicopters buzzing Jones Beach in the early morning are usually spreading  B.T.I. (Bacillus thuringiensis israelensis), which, when ingested by a larva, destroy its stomach. That, and a longer-acting biorational, Bacillus sphaericus, are accepted by even the most cautious environmentalists.</p>
        <p>Other compounds mimic the mosquito's growth hormone, preventing larvae from emerging as adults, but leaving them alive and well as fish food.</p>
        <p>The point is to get the mosquitoes as early as possible, before they take wing and spread out.</p>
        <p>''If we can't control them in the early phase, with fish, or using environmental means, or chemical larvacides,'' said Greg Terrillion, who heads Nassau County's mosquito agency, ''then we're upland fogging. And those materials just aren't as specific to mosquitoes.''</p>
        <p>On Long Island, the preferred ''adulticide,'' as the fogging chemicals are known, is resmethrin, a synthetic version of a chrysanthemum derivative that attacks insects' nervous systems. It's a powerful material, sold under the brand name Scourge. But even it is used in an environmentally friendly compound, which evaporates entirely in minutes. Organophosphates, which are still used in neighboring states to kill adult mosquitoes, are not allowed in New York.</p>
        <p>It's a far cry from the early methods, which, besides extensive ditching, included spraying sheetwater with heavy oil to smother larvae. And of course, DDT, a chlorinated hydrocarbon, was a popular pesticide, until evidence of its pervasive and long-lasting toxicity became widely known in the early 60's.</p>
        <p>New York has some of the most restrictive pesticide regulations in the nation. Every use of pesticide must be reported to the state, in part so that researchers can see if there is any connection to Long Island's cancer level, which has been found to be high. When pesticides are used, only a person licensed by the state to apply them is allowed to handle and disperse the materials. ''We need a full-time staff person just to make sure that we comply with all the laws,'' said Mr. Ninivaggi, the Suffolk mosquito man.</p>
        <p>In terms of biting, some of Long Island's most troubling species are Culex pippians, the common house mosquito; Aedes vexans, the floodwater mosquito, and Aedes sollicitans, the salt-marsh mosquito. This mosquito lays its eggs at the rack line, the inland reach of the twice-monthly lunar tides. Untouched by the daily tides that would wash them away, the eggs go through a necessary drying phase, and then, at the new moon or the full moon, are soaked, enabling larvae to hatch. The biting will begin about a week later, perhaps 10 or 12 days later if the weather remains cool.</p>
        <p>Left uncontrolled, the experts say, much of the South Shore would be uninhabitable.</p>
        <p>A recent example in Nassau County proved the case. The mosquito problem had been reduced by the end of the 80's, thanks in part to the installation of sewers, which helped eliminate standing water. In 1992, with the recession hitting full force, Nassau County reduced its payroll by 3,000 workers, and the mosquito control unit was essentially eradicated.</p>
        <p>Then, in 1996, one of the wettest summers on record, the mosquitoes took over Jones Beach, the county's most prolific mosquito breeding area.</p>
        <p>''There were signs saying, 'No refunds due to insects,' '' recalled Mr. Terrillion. ''You'd see mom and dad, with the kids and the coolers, getting out of the car in the parking lot. And in the time it took them to walk to the sidewalk, they turned around and went back to the car.''</p>
        <p>In both Nassau and Suffolk, the mosquito agencies are divisions of the Department of Public Works, where there is enough equipment and manpower to do wetlands management. But, in testament to lingering fears of mosquito-borne diseases, which kill millions in less-developed areas of the world, both divisions work cooperatively with their county health departments.</p>
        <p>''Just because people are not getting sick here doesn't mean we can relax,'' said Mr. Ninivaggi. ''We're not just abating a nuisance.''</p>
        <p>The salt-marsh mosquito is widely believed to be a carrier of eastern equine encephalitis. It has been found in Long Island mosquitoes four of the last five years, Mr. Ninivaggi said, but the deadly disease is usually only a problem during long, hot summers in which the disease overruns birds, its host population, and begins spreading to horses. Humans are also susceptible, but such cases are rare.</p>
        <p>Only one genus, Anopheles, carries malaria, and its only local species, quadrimaculatus, is not common on Long Island. Malaria is caused by a protozoan that mosquitoes ingest with blood and then inject into victims as part of their blood-thinning saliva. (The complex demands of the transfer process insure that H.I.V. cannot be spread by mosquito bite.)</p>
        <p>Malaria hasn't been evident on the island since the 30's. But it has come as close as New Jersey, as recently as 1991. New Jersey state health officials say that two people were infected after local mosquitoes bit people who had come from the tropics with untreated malaria.</p>
        <p>There is even a sort of killer bee of mosquitoes threatening to invade Long Island: Aedes albopictus, the Asian tiger mosquito. An aggressive daytime biter that breeds easily in urban settings, it has been spreading through the United States since its arrival from Asia, where it is an active disease carrier, in a boatload of used tires in 1985. Identified in New Jersey in 1995, the mosquito seems to have paused in its expansion. But ports and marinas on Long Island are being carefully watched.</p>
        <p>''We've been looking for two years, but we haven't found any tigers yet,'' Mr. Ninivaggi said.</p>
        <p>These days, watching is a crucial part of mosquito control. Inspectors have identified exactly which areas mosquitoes breed in. In Suffolk County, records of the locations are being painstakingly transferred into a computerized mapping system that will include complaint and treatment histories for each site. The ''Service Request'' computer screen has a little box marked ''Compliments'' next to the ''Complaints'' entry, but Mr. Ninivaggi just laughed. ''We don't need a computer to keep track of compliments,'' he said.</p>
        <p>SKEETER EATERS: FACT AND FICTION</p>
        <p>Some predators of mosquitoes get little credit and some get way too much. Dr. Wayne Crans, chief entomologist of the New Jersey Agricultural Experiment Station, sets the record straight.</p>
        <p>GAMBUSIA AFFINIS  This inchlong freshwater fish eats hundreds of larvae an hour. It bears live young -- 120 to 400 a year -- and so requires no special environment to spawn. And unlike most fish, it tolerates warm, shallow standing water, making it ideal for adding to stormwater basins, ditches and freshwater marshes.</p>
        <p>KILLIFISH  Like Gambusia, these fish eat mosquito larvae, but are generally less tolerant of fetid water.</p>
        <p>BATS  Mosquitoes make up a very small percentage of insectivorous bats' natural diets. Research that suggested otherwise was based on 1950's echo-location studies, in which bats were released in rooms full of nothing but mosquitoes. Those bats ate up to 10 mosquitoes a minute. That finding has been extrapolated to suggest that an average-sized colony of 500 bats would remove at least a quarter million mosquitoes an hour. In fact, bats usually vastly prefer moths, beetles and other non-pest insects.</p>
        <p>PURPLE MARTINS  There is a bit of utterly false popular wisdom that says this bird can eat 2,000 to 14,000 mosquitoes a day. But that is based on the calculation of the number of insects it would take to maintain the purple martin's body weight. In fact, purple martins will eat a few mosquitoes, but they prefer dragonflies and other insects. And dragonflies eat mosquitoes.</p>
        <p>DRAGONFLIES  Immature dragonflies stand at the edge of ponds and pounce on mosquito larvae. Mature dragonflies fly ''patrols'' over ponds, catching mosquitoes in midair and eating them in flight. Dragonflies will even follow mosquito broods into fields.</p>
        <p>ANDREA KANNAPELL</p>
        <p>The Repellent Truth</p>
        <p>ONLY female mosquitoes bite, and only because they need a meal of blood to acquire the protein necessary to lay their eggs. These critters find their quarry by detecting the carbon dioxide from the animals' breath, as well as lactic acid and other, less studied byproducts of metabolism.</p>
        <p>Scientists have confirmed that some people are much more attractive to mosquitoes than others: Sweaty people are more appealing than non-sweaters, adults more than children, men more than women, and larger people more than smaller people.</p>
        <p>But the scientists don't know why this is so; if they did, they might have devised a truly effective mosquito repellent. Meanwhile, we're stuck with repellent wannabes and impostors, and some that actually are slightly more noxious to mosquitoes than they are to humans.</p>
        <p>Some plants supposedly repel mosquitoes, but in ''Mosquitoes and Mosquito Repellents: A Clinician's Guide,'' published in the June 1 edition of Annals of Internal Medicine, Mark S. Fradin writes that the best-known repellent plant, the Citrosa, a genetically engineered hybrid of lemon grass and geraniums, has been shown to be ineffective. So have bug zappers, which electrocute other varieties of insects but not mosquitoes, and novelty electronic devices that emit high-frequency sound waves.</p>
        <p>That leaves topical repellents, which work by evaporating at the skin surface, creating a ''fog'' that wards off the insect. The most common is DEET (N,N,-diethyl-3-methylbenzamide) -- the active ingredient in commercial sprays like Off -- which was patented by the United States Army in 1946. The chemical can be toxic, particularly to children. Products with 10 percent to 35 percent concentrations of the chemical are considered adequate under normal conditions. High temperatures and sunscreen reduce its effectiveness.</p>
        <p>Citronella, the oil of a grass, can be an effective but short-lived repellent, requiring frequent reapplication. It is the most common active ingredient in repellents marketed as ''natural,'' like Buzz Away (5 percent), Herbal Armor (15 percent) and Green Ban for People (5 and 10 percent).</p>
        <p>Several years ago, Avon Skin-So-Soft, a bath oil reputed to function as a repellent, was tested in laboratory conditions and found to provide 30 to 40 minutes' worth of protection against at least two mosquito species. (And there's the rub: Mosquito species are many and mobile, so you have no way of knowing which types are in your yard.) Avon has since added trace amounts of citronella oil to its Skin-So-Soft products.</p>
        <p>A plant-based repellent that is new to the United States, Bite Blocker, combines soybean oil with geranium and coconut oil. Canadian studies show that it gave nearly 100 percent protection from some mosquito species for more than three hours.</p>
        <p>A final category of repellent is a contact insecticide. Permethrin, a synthetic form of an African chrysanthemum, is the active ingredient in lice treatments as well as in aerial sprays that kill adult mosquitoes. It is applied to clothing and gear, like tents and sleeping bags, rather than to skin.</p>
        <p>ANDREA KANNAPELL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
