<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q &amp; A</title>
    <meta content="28QNA.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1088293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Q and A</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4DC133DF93BA15751C0A96F958260" item-length="1125" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q &amp; A</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL FREIREICH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Driving at Age 70 and Over</p>
        <p>Q. My wife and I are in our early 70's and are planning a trip to Ireland and Wales. A friend cautioned us about restrictions that some car rental companies have on providing cars for septuagenarians. Are we likely to be refused because of our age? -- Stanley Myers, Blue Hill, Me.</p>
        <p>A. Because age restrictions vary from one company to another, there is a chance you could be rejected. To avoid having a monkey wrench thrown into your plans at the last minute, it's best to tell your car rental company, travel agent or broker before you leave your age, especially since limits in the same company may differ. The reason for the age restriction, the car rental companies say, is a limit set by insurers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Driving at Age 70 and Over</p>
        <p>Q. My wife and I are in our early 70's and are planning a trip to Ireland and Wales. A friend cautioned us about restrictions that some car rental companies have on providing cars for septuagenarians. Are we likely to be refused because of our age? -- Stanley Myers, Blue Hill, Me.</p>
        <p>A. Because age restrictions vary from one company to another, there is a chance you could be rejected. To avoid having a monkey wrench thrown into your plans at the last minute, it's best to tell your car rental company, travel agent or broker before you leave your age, especially since limits in the same company may differ. The reason for the age restriction, the car rental companies say, is a limit set by insurers.</p>
        <p>Here, listed alphabetically, are the policies of major car rental companies and brokers. Brokers use cars provided by several companies and can direct you to a company that will accept a driver your age.</p>
        <p>AutoEurope, (800) 223-5555. The  suppliers in Ireland are Hertz, with an upper age limit of 79, and Europcar, which has a maximum of 75. (The limit for Hertz cars is, indeed, higher than if rented directly from Hertz.) In Wales the suppliers are Europcar, which has a limit of 69, and Avis, which has no limit.</p>
        <p>Avis, (800) 331-1212. In Ireland, drivers from 66 to 74 years old can rent the company's less expensive cars, from, say, a Nissan Micro to a midsize automatic like a Toyota Carina; age 74 is the maximum. In Wales, there is no age restriction.</p>
        <p>Budget, (800) 527-0700, has corporate and licensee owners, all under the name Budget, with varying age limits. In Ireland, the maximum ranges from 75 to 80 and in Wales from 65 to 70.</p>
        <p>Hertz, (800) 654-3131. In Ireland, the maximum is 74. In Wales, there is no limit.</p>
        <p>Kemwel Holiday, a broker, uses two suppliers in Ireland: Eurodollar, with a maximum of 70, and Sixt, with a maximum of 75. In Wales, the cars come from National/Alamo, which has a maximum of 80.</p>
        <p>Thrifty, (800) 367-2277. In Ireland and Wales, the oldest a driver can be is 70.</p>
        <p>Bugs in the Caribbean</p>
        <p>Q. Because we were being eaten alive by bugs, my husband and I stopped going to Guadeloupe after a January vacation about 15 years ago. My husband was intensely allergic, and none of the usual bug repellents seemed to have any effect. Are there new, more effective repellents? Or are there other islands where we would encounter no bug problems? -- Carolyn W. Sanger, Potomac, Md.</p>
        <p>A. Actually, the high season in the Caribbean, generally from around December to mid-March or so, is when one is least likely to encounter bugs. And the problem is hardly limited to Guadeloupe since the same species of bugs are common throughout the coastal tropics of the Western Hemisphere, according to Dr. Paul Reiter, chief of the entymology section of the dengue branch of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in San Juan, P.R.</p>
        <p>Even so, he said, there may have been very good reasons you encountered bugs, which, broadly speaking, includes biting flies. One is that you were probably out when the bugs do their most intense biting -- starting 30 to 45 minutes after sunset and continuing for 30 to 45 minutes. ''At that time, it's best to have your rum and Coke in a screened place,'' Dr. Reiter suggested.</p>
        <p>Another possibility, he said, is that you had the bad luck to be vacationing after a heavy rainfall and high tides. That is when some of the most voracious offenders breed in salt marshes and mangrove swamps.</p>
        <p>Or perhaps smell may also have played a role. Scientists have found that mosquitoes are attracted to some people by such things as carbon dioxide and lactic acid.</p>
        <p>Dr. Reiter, who has lived in Puerto Rico for a dozen years, offers these suggestions: Stay out of the way at the wrong time of day; wear a long-sleeved shirt, which he concedes may be unrealistic for people on vacation in a warm climate, and apply a repellent containing DEET, which is widely regarded as the most effective repellent and which has been used for more than 40 years.</p>
        <p>As helpful as DEET is, remember that perspiration and swimming diminish its effectiveness. DEET is available in varying concentrations. Ten to 35 percent -- with 10 percent being the maximum for children -- usually suffices.</p>
        <p>Barging in Belgium</p>
        <p>Q. I would like information about river or barge cruising on a trip to include Bruges and to end in Brussels. I read that a barge called the Rembrandt might offer such a trip.  -- G.K. Bellis, The Woodlands, Tex.</p>
        <p>A. A number of companies offer the basic barge trip aboard the Rembrandt, which carries 18 to 20 passengers, plus transportation to and from Brussels. At least one has a more inclusive package.</p>
        <p>Among the stops are Bruges, for a visit to the market square, the Basilica of the Holy Blood (parts of which date from the 12th and 15th centuries) and the Memling Museum; Oudenaarde, to see 14th-century tapestries; Ghent, to see the St. Bavo Cathedral and ''The Adoration of the Mystic Lamb'' by Jan and Hubert van Eyck, and Antwerp, to visit the diamond center and the Rubens House. Crossing into the Netherlands, the barge stops at the fortress town of Willemstad; Gouda, for visits to St. John's Cathedral and a cheese shop, and Terneuzen.</p>
        <p>Note that dates of availability may change and that the itinerary runs from Bruges to Terneuzen and sometimes the reverse. Brussels is about an hour's drive from Bruges and about 90 minutes from Terneuzen.</p>
        <p>A package that includes two nights in Brussels at the start plus a half-day tour of Brussels led by an expert is available from IST Cultural Tours, 225 West 34th Street, New York, N.Y. 10122; (800) 833-2111 or (212) 563-1202. In addition, the expert provides commentary, from a historical or architectural perspective, on the day of arrival. The cost between May 30 and Aug. 1 is $1,575, based on double occupancy. This price and the one below include all meals aboard the barge and all admissions.</p>
        <p>Among the companies offering the barge component, at $1,690 a person, for double occupancy, are these:</p>
        <p>Abercrombie &amp; Kent, 1520 Kensington Road, Oak Brook, Ill. 65023; (800) 323-7308 or (630) 954-2944.</p>
        <p>Barge Broker prefers to deal through a travel agent; 2321 30th Street, Boulder, Colo. 80301; (800) 275-9794, fax (303) 447-2487.</p>
        <p>The Barge Lady, 101 West Grand Avenue, Suite 200, Chicago, Ill. 60610; (800) 880-0071 or (312) 245-0900, fax (312) 245-0952.</p>
        <p>PAUL FREIREICH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
