<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Natural Gas Has Many Selling Points, but Few Buyers</title>
    <meta content="20NEIL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1146853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neil, Dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DA1031F933A15753C1A96F958260" item-length="1638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Natural Gas Has Many Selling Points, but Few Buyers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN NEIL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Neil, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dan Neil article on recent history of natural gas as object lesson in difficulties facing alternative transportation energy, and how hard it is to displace gasoline as fuel of choice; notes natural gas vehicles typically can go about half distance of gasoline cars between refueling and have few places to fill up; holds fuel is best suited to large fleets of buses, cabs and delivery trucks, which can be fueled at central site; photos (Special Section: Cars) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT if there was a fuel that was cheap, limitless and clean-burning? A fuel whose supply and price were strategically secure, free from the caprice of oil-producing nations? A fuel that relied on engineering fundamentally no more esoteric than that of a restaurant stove?</p>
        <p>It sounds like an environmentalist's giddiest daydream. Yet such a fuel is natural gas -- simple, guileless methane, the perfume of the plains. It even comes in two flavors: compressed natural gas (C.N.G. for short) and its cryogenic cousin, liquefied natural gas (L.N.G.). It is a fuel with a host of attributes, a seemingly elegant solution to issues as diverse as air pollution and trade imbalances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT if there was a fuel that was cheap, limitless and clean-burning? A fuel whose supply and price were strategically secure, free from the caprice of oil-producing nations? A fuel that relied on engineering fundamentally no more esoteric than that of a restaurant stove?</p>
        <p>It sounds like an environmentalist's giddiest daydream. Yet such a fuel is natural gas -- simple, guileless methane, the perfume of the plains. It even comes in two flavors: compressed natural gas (C.N.G. for short) and its cryogenic cousin, liquefied natural gas (L.N.G.). It is a fuel with a host of attributes, a seemingly elegant solution to issues as diverse as air pollution and trade imbalances.</p>
        <p>Yet even its most ardent supporters concede that compressed natural gas will probably never be more than a niche source of energy, one best suited to large fleets of buses, cabs and delivery trucks, which can be fueled at a central location. The Natural Gas Vehicle Coalition, which speaks for the industry, has all but given up hope that large numbers of compressed natural-gas stations will ever be built.</p>
        <p>At best, it appears, C.N.G. vehicles will account for a small part of America's rolling stock in the next decade. At worst, they may be stalled for the foreseeable future.</p>
        <p>Either way, the recent history of compressed natural gas is an object lesson in the difficulties facing alternative transportation energy, and how hard it is to displace gasoline as the fuel of choice.</p>
        <p>Certainly, recent events have seemed favorable for an alternative fuel. Two years ago, Congress approved the Environmental Protection Agency's plan to ratchet up pollution standards on oxides of nitrogen and diesel particulate matter, the city-choking residue of automobiles and trucks burning gasoline and diesel fuel.</p>
        <p>Last spring, the E.P.A. proposed new tailpipe-emission standards that would essentially federalize California's stringent  standards. The agency's so-called Tier Two rules also call for refineries to produce cleaner-burning low-sulfur gasoline, a provision opposed by the petroleum industry.</p>
        <p>Diesel fuel, gasoline's grimy sibling, is also under attack. In a move that could have far-reaching consequences, both California and the E.P.A. have declared diesel particulate -- a k a soot -- a toxic substance.</p>
        <p>Natural gas, by comparison, is clean. Compared with gasoline vehicles, C.N.G. vehicles emit 70 percent less carbon monoxide, 87 percent less nitrogen oxide (a principal culprit in smog) and 87 percent less nonmethane volatile organic compounds. Because natural gas contains less carbon than other fossil fuels, it contributes significantly less carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases to the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, gasoline is becoming more vulnerable on price. Oil-exporting nations crimped the petroleum pipeline to the United States just in time for the summer travel season. From a historic low of $9.84 a barrel in December 1998, crude oil prices had risen to $22.78 in early October.</p>
        <p>In California, where supply problems this year have added to the price increase, gasoline was up $1.48 a gallon in early October; a gasoline gallon equivalent of compressed natural gas is about $1.</p>
        <p>ASIGNIFICANT price disparity should be good news for natural-gas advocates. So should the Alternative Fuel Promotion Act, which Senator John D. Rockefeller 4th, Democrat of West Virginia, and Senator Orrin G. Hatch, Republican of Utah, introduced in early May. (A similar bill was introduced in the House of Representatives in June.) If the act is passed, it would give sellers of clean-burning fuels a tax credit of 50 cents a gasoline-gallon equivalent, radically changing the economics of alternative fuels, particularly natural gas. The legislation has been caught up in the tax-cut dispute between the White House and Congress and is still pending. ''If we get that, it's very likely that we'll see prices in the range of 55 cents'' a gasoline-gallon equivalent, said Richard R. Kolodziej, the president of the Natural Gas Vehicle Coalition. ''Then I think you are going to see people say: 'I like this. I want to do it.' ''</p>
        <p>The Rockefeller-Hatch bill is opposed by the petroleum industry, which has defeated similar initiatives in state legislatures. ''We feel that no fuel ought to be disadvantaged or advantaged by tax subsidies,'' said Bill O'Keefe, the executive vice president of the American Petroleum Institute. ''Let the market decide.''</p>
        <p>But the bill, should it pass, would signal a renaissance in vehicles that burn natural gas.</p>
        <p>So, what could be wrong? One word: range. Most gasoline cars can go 300 miles or more on a tank of fuel. When they run low, they pull into a gas station to fill up.</p>
        <p>Natural-gas vehicles typically can go about half that distance, and when they run out of fuel, there are few places to fill up. That's why these vehicles work best -- indeed, almost exclusively -- for fleets, like buses, cabs and delivery trucks, in which high-mileage users travel regular, local routes and return to a central refueling point.</p>
        <p>''We recognized that our business will be built up not by going after a few vehicles in a large population, but a larger percentage of a small population,'' Mr. Kolodziej said. ''It doesn't mean that others are going to be ignored -- early adopters, environmentalists and so on.''</p>
        <p>But that is often the message. In January, I was part of a team from Car and Driver magazine that tried to cross the country in a compressed natural-gas vehicle using the Natural Gas Vehicle Coalition's guide to refueling stations. Many stations, listed as public, were inaccessible, or had no means to measure out quantities of gas or accept payment for it, or kept irregular hours, or had been abandoned.</p>
        <p>While companies in the West and Northeast have built chains of C.N.G. refueling stations, real growth awaits a better market or Government incentives. Stations, it seems, are costly to build and operate, primarily because they require large compressors capable of supplying the industry standard of 3,000 pounds a square inch of pressure on demand, around the clock.</p>
        <p>The Rockefeller-Hatch bill offers a $30,000 tax deduction toward the installation costs of alternative fueling stations. ''For too long, we have been caught in a chicken-and-egg cycle, with the infrastructure not available to support alternative-fuel vehicles and consumers not interested in the vehicles because there is no support infrastructure,'' Senator Rockefeller said.</p>
        <p>For determined environmentalists, there is another way. Fuelmaker, a Canadian company, sells home fueling stations that can be plumbed directly into a home's natural-gas supply. C.N.G.-powered cars can then be refueled in the driveway. Fuelmaker units cost about $2,500, and some manufacturers offer rebates on purchases. The Rockefeller-Hatch bill would grant the same tax credit to home refuelers, who could deduct costs up to $100,000 from their Federal taxes.</p>
        <p>But the oil industry, which controls 60 percent of America's natural-gas reserves, is the least interested in building a C.N.G. infrastructure. On the face of it, it seems odd that the industry would not be eager to sell its wares to the public. Why not build the C.N.G. stations, and let them come?</p>
        <p>It doesn't work that way, said Mr. O'Keefe of the American Petroleum Institute. ''My members are in the business of providing what consumers want,'' he explained. ''Right now the consumers want S.U.V.'s, not C.N.G.'s. Supply follows demand.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kolodziej said the institute's members ''would like to sell more natural gas, but not to cannibalize their transportation market.'' They have billions tied up in refineries, pipelines and service stations designed to deliver a liquid petroleum product, he said.</p>
        <p>For their part, auto makers are wading into the C.N.G. market, despite lackluster consumer demand. The reason? The E.P.A.'s Corporate Average Fuel Economy rule, in which every alternative-fuel vehicle sold is calculated to get 120 miles a gallon. This gives car makers considerable slack on their big-selling low-mileage vehicles. More than a dozen light-duty compressed natural-gas models are on the market, and more are on the way. At the North American International Auto Expo in Detroit in January, DaimlerChrysler displayed a 325-horsepower Dodge Charger concept car that employed a new compact storage system and a range, it said, of up to 300 miles.</p>
        <p>A sister project using the Plymouth Breeze/Dodge Stratus as a platform yielded a C.N.G. car virtually indistinguishable from its gasoline-powered twin. ''Our goal was to find C.N.G. technology that was transparent to the driver, so he wouldn't even be aware that he was driving a C.N.G. vehicle,'' said John Wozniak, the project manager for the Applied Physics Laboratory. ''That's the only way C.N.G. is going to make real progress.''</p>
        <p>But there have been unexpected complications. In Seattle, government administrators abandoned plans to expand the city's C.N.G. fleet after determining that such an expansion would require extensive garage renovations.</p>
        <p>THE course of any technology never did run true. By the time compressed natural-gas technology sorts itself out, it may be superseded by another technology, the hydrogen-driven fuel cell, which has the petroleum industry's support. Fuel cells catalyze fuels instead of burning them,  so they produce only oxygen and water as byproducts.</p>
        <p>Dave Lefever, the executive director of the National Association of Fleet Administrators, said that what car manufacturers are telling the fleet managers ''is that all these alternative and flex-fuel approaches are basically interim approaches until they get the fuel-cell technology up and running,'' perhaps in 10 years' time.</p>
        <p>But compressed natural-gas advocates remain hopeful. Noting that hydrogen and C.N.G. are both compressed gases, Mr. Kolodziej of the Natural Gas Vehicle Coalition  said: ''The same infrastructure that delivers C.N.G. can deliver hydrogen in the future. We are the logical bridge between petroleum and hydrogen.''</p>
        <p>Dan Neil is a contributing editor at Car and Driver magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dan Neil is a contributing editor at Car and Driver magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
