<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Did He Inhale?</title>
    <meta content="25BERKET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1102474"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zelnick, Bob</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Gore: A Political Life (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EFDD153BF936A15757C0A96F958260" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Did He Inhale?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard L. Berke</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard L Berke reviews book Gore: A Political Life by Bob Zelnick (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GORE</p>
        <p>A Political Life.</p>
        <p>By Bob Zelnick.</p>
        <p>384 pp. Washington:</p>
        <p>Regnery Publishing. $29.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GORE</p>
        <p>A Political Life.</p>
        <p>By Bob Zelnick.</p>
        <p>384 pp. Washington:</p>
        <p>Regnery Publishing. $29.95.</p>
        <p>Al Gore presents the ultimate challenge to a biographer, and not just because he is hardly a scintillating politician. He has been a public fixture for so long that the story lines about him are so well established that they are practically cliches: he is animated in private but wooden in public; his father, the Senator, so groomed him to be President that Gore is out of touch with ordinary people; he is trustworthy and reliable, but the accusations about his fund-raising practices in 1996 exposed his need to indulge in the political games that he expects will carry him to the White House.</p>
        <p>In ''Gore: A Political Life,'' Bob Zelnick offers a useful and comprehensive survey of the highs and lows of Gore's political career as he embarks on his quest for the Democratic Presidential nomination. But the book falls short in offering readers any sense of Gore that is more textured or revealing than what has already appeared in newspaper and magazine articles.</p>
        <p>While the book lauds Gore on several points -- his service in Vietnam, his knack in Congress for identifying hot new issues, his intimate, hands-on role in the White House -- there are many areas where Zelnick interprets Gore's actions in the most deprecatory way possible. The book starts on a positive note but, as the chapters progress, turns increasingly critical.</p>
        <p>For example, while some environmentalists describe Gore's book ''Earth in the Balance'' as an impressive work that incorporates his knowledge of global warming and other issues, Zelnick dismisses it as ''pathetically one-dimensional in its view of Western civilization, shabby in its ignorance of economics, simplistic in its approach to problem solving.''</p>
        <p>In describing Gore's participation at a White House session with several leading conservatives, Zelnick is clearly put off by his blunt defense of racial preferences. While many Democrats were impressed by Gore's outspokenness, Zelnick sees it another way. ''Clinton's reputation for empathy, analysis and nuance was put on dazzling display,'' he writes, while ''Gore's reputation for stiff-necked condescension was also very much in evidence.''</p>
        <p>And while many politicians in both parties cheered Gore's performance in debating Ross Perot on the North American Free Trade Agreement, Zelnick ridi-</p>
        <p>cules him for offering ''anecdotal nonsense, a list of treaty endorsements and some rather nasty ad hominem attacks on Perot.''</p>
        <p>Zelnick does little to dispel accusations from Gore loyalists that his was the latest conservative-tinged book from Regnery Publishing. The book was controversial even before it was published. Zelnick resigned last year as a correspondent for ABC News after the network said that for him to write a book about Gore and cover national politics constituted a conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>One frustration is that Zelnick provides no footnotes. That makes it hard to separate fresh reportage from material that has already been published. That is a particularly important matter because the book cries out for new insights or revelations, especially since Gore did not cooperate.</p>
        <p>Even if he did not uncover much, Zelnick does provide some tantalizing tidbits. He recounts, for instance, that Gore liked to smoke marijuana at Harvard and that he and his wife, Tipper, used the drug recreationally for a decade. He explores how Gore was an ardent foe of spending Federal money on abortion -- until he hooked up with Bill Clinton. And he offers evidence that the image of Gore as superorganized and disciplined may not be so accurate.</p>
        <p>In his years as a reporter for The Nashville Tennessean, Zelnick recalls, there was ''little passion, humor, calculated irony or human insight in Gore's journalism.'' Zelnick's prose at times seems to share a certain lifelessness. His is a somewhat disjointed book that lacks overarching themes and whose writing is serviceable but hardly graceful.</p>
        <p>Even so, as the first in a parade of biographies of the Vice President, this book is likely to become a resource for Gore watchers as the campaign unfolds -- at least until another biographer takes a stab at coming up with a new story line.</p>
        <p>Richard L. Berke is the national political correspondent of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Richard L. Berke is the national political correspondent of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
