<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="27BRIE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1156477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Visas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Panama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez Balladares, Ernesto</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Panama</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DD153FF934A15752C1A96F958260" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled by Joseph R. Gregory</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Panamanian Pres Ernesto Perez Balladares, who is accused of participating in ring that sold illegal United States visas to Chinese immigrants, has his tourist visa revoked; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>PANAMA: U.S. REVOKES EX-LEADER'S VISA -- Former President Ernesto Perez Balladares, who is accused of participating in a ring that sold illegal United States visas to Chinese immigrants, has had his tourist visa revoked, according to the Panamanian newspaper La Prensa. In August Samantha Smith, the former head of Panama's National Security Council, accused Mr. Perez Balldares of selling some 140 visas for as much as $15,000 apiece. Mr. Perez Balladares, who left office in September, has denied any involvement.</p>
        <p>David Gonzalez (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>PANAMA: U.S. REVOKES EX-LEADER'S VISA -- Former President Ernesto Perez Balladares, who is accused of participating in a ring that sold illegal United States visas to Chinese immigrants, has had his tourist visa revoked, according to the Panamanian newspaper La Prensa. In August Samantha Smith, the former head of Panama's National Security Council, accused Mr. Perez Balldares of selling some 140 visas for as much as $15,000 apiece. Mr. Perez Balladares, who left office in September, has denied any involvement.</p>
        <p>David Gonzalez (NYT)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: DEPOSITS FOR U.S. CARS -- Mexico will begin on Wednesday to collect deposits of up to $800 for United States-registered cars crossing the border. Officials said the new system would avoid fraud and corruption, and tried to reassure people residing in the United States that their money would be safe. Under the program, any driver with American license plates will need to leave a cash or credit-card deposit at the border when they enter Mexico. They will recover their deposits when they leave.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>MEXICO: RECONCILIATION -- Eighteen days after the governing party's presidential primary, President Ernesto Zedillo was the host at a reconciliation meeting between the winner, Francisco Labastida Ochoa, and his closest rival, Roberto Madrazo Pintado. The candidates had traded insults during the campaign, but they embraced during the meeting. Mr. Madrazo said he would return to the governorship of Tabasco, from which he had taken leave.</p>
        <p>Sam Dillon (NYT)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>ITALY: EX-PREMIER FACES TRIAL -- Silvio Berlusconi, a media tycoon who heads the center-right opposition, was ordered to stand trial in Milan, his second indictment on corruption charges this week. Since leaving office in 1994, he has been convicted of bribing tax inspectors and false accounting. Now he is charged with trying to bribe judges over a sale involving a holding company. Mr. Berlusconi sued the judge who ordered him to stand trial, claiming he is biased.</p>
        <p>Alessandra Stanley (NYT)</p>
        <p>BRITAIN: BACK IN OFFICE -- Michael Portillo, the former defense secretary who lost his parliamentary seat and the chance to become Conservative party leader in the Labor landslide of 1997, is back in the Commons, victor in a London by-election. He pledged his loyalty to the current Tory head, William Hague, whose troubled leadership has raised questions about his future.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: BUDGET CUTS APPROVED -- The lower house of Parliament approved a budget for 2000 that includes cuts in Germany's generous social welfare system. The cuts have set off protests by pensioners, public  employees and others. Chancellor Gerhard Schroder, who heads a center-left coalition, said the aim was to balance the budget by 2006 and slash the $780 billion debt run up while rebuilding the formerly communist East Germany.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: EX-OFFICIALS CHARGED -- Two former interior ministers, Jose Luis Corcuera and Jose Barrionuevo, who served under the former Prime Minister Felipe Gonzalez, face jail terms of 10 and 7 years respectively if convicted of embezzling $8 million in government funds.</p>
        <p>Al Goodman (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>AFGHANISTAN: DANGEROUS MUSEUM -- The world's most dangerous museum has been defused, the United Nations office in Islamabad, Pakistan, reported. The museum was set up in Zendajan, in Harat province, to educate Afghans about the hazards of land mines, and contained 463 unexploded weapons, from aircraft bombs to mortar shells. Peter LeSoeur, a technical adviser in charge of the Afghan ordnance disposal team, said one accidental detonation in the museum, which adjoined two schools, would have destroyed everything within a half mile.</p>
        <p>Christopher S. Wren (NYT)</p>
        <p>CHINA: 4 FOREIGNERS RELEASED -- Four foreigners who were detained as followers of the banned Falun Gong spiritual movement were released. The police raided a meeting in the southern city of Guangzhou on Thursday and held 15 followers, including a Chinese-American, two Chinese-Australians and a Swedish student. The Swede was sent back to the school she is attending in the northeastern city of Dalian, and the other three were deported.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>PAKISTAN: EX-LEADER FACES COURT DELAY -- For the second time, the antiterrorism court has allowed a delay in the bringing of formal charges against the ousted prime minister, Nawaz Sharif, giving prosecutors until Dec. 4 to file official papers. During a brief hearing, Mr. Sharif met his brother Shahbaz for the first time since the Oct. 12 coup. The two embraced. ''We are innocent,'' the former prime minister told reporters. ''Gen. Pervez Musharraf has made this a personal vendetta against us.'' Mr. Sharif was referring to allegations that he and others conspired to hijack the general's airliner and kill all those aboard.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>MOROCCO: EXILES TO RETURN -- The family of Mehdi Ben Barka, the opposition leader who disappeared in France in 1965, are to return to Morocco today after decades of banishment, his son, Bachir Ben Barka, said on French television. The family's return follows the death this year of King Hassan II, whose son Muhammad VI has taken steps to allow prominent exiles to return. The elder Mr. Ben Barka, an outspoken opponent of King Hassan II, disappeared after being picked up by the French police on Oct. 29, 1965. His body was never found.</p>
        <p>(Agence France-Presse)</p>
        <p>ETHIOPIA: EX-DICTATOR SOUGHT -- Ethiopia called on South Africa to extradite the former dictator, Mengistu Haile Mariam, to face charges of human rights violations. Mr. Mengistu fled to Zimbabwe in 1991 when he was overthrown after 16 years in power, but recently sought treatment in South Africa for a heart  ailment.</p>
        <p>Ian Fisher (NYT)</p>
        <p>TANZANIA: AFRICA'S TALLEST PEAK -- Mount Kilimanjaro is 10 feet shorter than previously thought, scientists said. Tanzanian and German scientists scaled the mountain earlier this year and, with the aid of the Global Positioning System, set the peak's height at 19,442.8 feet. Rising sea levels, compression of the mountain over the years and previous errors account for the 10-foot difference, they said. In May, American mountaineers measured Mount Everest's height at 29,035 feet -- 6.6 feet higher than officially recognized for 45 years.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
