<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Report Finds Power Plants Dirtier in '98</title>
    <meta content="21POWE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1101807"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990421T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0D7173AF932A15757C0A96F958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Report Finds Power Plants Dirtier in '98</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report released by several environmental groups finds that air pollution from 21 aging power plants across New York State rose significantly last year; although New York State environmental officials do not dispute report's findings, they say state had reduced overall power plant pollution by half from level of 1990 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Air pollution from 21 aging power plants across New York State rose significantly last year, according to a report released yesterday by several private environmental, health, and consumer groups.</p>
        <p>Although New York State environmental officials did not dispute the findings on these plants, they said that the state had reduced overall power-plant pollution by half from the level in 1990.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Air pollution from 21 aging power plants across New York State rose significantly last year, according to a report released yesterday by several private environmental, health, and consumer groups.</p>
        <p>Although New York State environmental officials did not dispute the findings on these plants, they said that the state had reduced overall power-plant pollution by half from the level in 1990.</p>
        <p>At the plants, which use decades-old technology and burn mainly oil or coal, there was a 21 percent rise last year in emissions of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain and respiratory problems, and a 12 percent rise in releases of nitrogen oxides, which cause acid rain and smog, according to the report.</p>
        <p>The study said that the persistent problems at these plants, the state's most polluting, could cause health problems for communities downwind in New York and New England, which receives some of New York's pollution along with the flow from more highly polluting plants in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The plants cited in the report are scattered across the state, from Port Jefferson on Long Island and Astoria, Queens, to the Hudson Valley and Niagara County. They were highlighted because they all produce at least 100 tons more nitrogen oxides annually than the Federal standard allowed for new plants burning coal, said Cori Traub, an author of the report and director of air and energy projects for Environmental Advocates, a private lobbying group in Albany. The other organizations publishing the study were the New York Public Interest Research Group and the New York chapter of the American Lung Association. The data were provided by the Federal Environmental Protection Agency.</p>
        <p>New York State environmental officials said the state was a national leader at cutting power-plant pollution, by focusing efforts on newer plants, where major improvements can be made at a low cost, instead of forcing expensive improvements at old plants. Samuel Thernstrom, a spokesman for the State Department of Environmental Conservation, said that the drop in the state's total emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides since 1990 was due mainly to a shift to cleaner fuels, like natural gas, and improved pollution-capturing gear for smokestacks.</p>
        <p>He added that by far the biggest air problem for New York still lay to the west. In fact, he said, some individual coal-fired power plants in the Ohio River Valley produce more sulfur and nitrogen pollution than all New York's industries combined. This pollution drifts east, damaging forests and lakes and causing health problems like asthma.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the authors of the report said that more must be done to clean up what they called the dirty 21. The 21 plants are responsible for half the total emission of the nitrogen oxides and sulfur dioxide released by all industries in the state, according to the analysis.</p>
        <p>If they are not forced to clean up to the same standard as other plants, Ms. Traub said, they will have a competitive advantage over newer plants that are required to install costly pollution-control gear. ''With deregulation happening,'' Ms. Traub said, ''it's unfair that these plants have this competitive advantage, that they're able to run more cheaply under outdated standards.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Thernstrom said that if New York clamped down too hard on its dirtiest plants, utility companies might simply close them and buy power from even dirtier ones in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The study comes as most of the state's plants are being sold off by utilities like Consolidated Edison and Niagara Mohawk under new state regulations aimed at ending monopolies in the power industry.</p>
        <p>Carol Murphy, the executive director of the Independent Power Producers Association of New York, said that the rise in emissions last year was unlikely to be repeated, because many of the new owners are planning to modernize the plants, either switching to a cleaner fuel, natural gas, or installing more efficient equipment that reduces pollution.</p>
        <p>Also in the background is an intensifying fight between the Midwest and the Northeast over cutting pollution from old plants that rely on coal and oil. Several bills that would curtail pollution, sponsored by legislators from eastern states, are making the rounds in Congress.</p>
        <p>But environmental groups say that New York could spur improvements by passing a state law requiring that any electricity sold in the state, whether it is generated here or elsewhere, be produced at plants using the cleanest standard, said Ashok Gupta, an economist who conducted a similar study two years ago for the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
