<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="23FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1155744"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991123T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DE113CF930A15752C1A96F958260" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Iraq Cuts Oil Exports To Protest Sanctions Policy  Iraq unexpectedly began cutting off exports of the oil it is allowed to sell under post-gulf-war sanctions to pay for food and other humanitarian purposes, United Nations officials said. The Iraqis said they were protesting the Security Council's decision to extend the oil-for-food program for only two weeks, instead of the usual six months.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israeli Officer Disciplined  An Israeli Army lieutenant, who is an Orthodox Jew, was suspended after telling a class of soldiers that the Reform and Conservative movements of Judaism were ''worse than the Holocaust.'' It was an unusually swift and resolute response, in which the Israeli Army drew a clear boundary between acceptable and unacceptable discourse on religious pluralism, a very sensitive issue in Israeli society.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>Iraq Cuts Oil Exports To Protest Sanctions Policy  Iraq unexpectedly began cutting off exports of the oil it is allowed to sell under post-gulf-war sanctions to pay for food and other humanitarian purposes, United Nations officials said. The Iraqis said they were protesting the Security Council's decision to extend the oil-for-food program for only two weeks, instead of the usual six months.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Israeli Officer Disciplined  An Israeli Army lieutenant, who is an Orthodox Jew, was suspended after telling a class of soldiers that the Reform and Conservative movements of Judaism were ''worse than the Holocaust.'' It was an unusually swift and resolute response, in which the Israeli Army drew a clear boundary between acceptable and unacceptable discourse on religious pluralism, a very sensitive issue in Israeli society.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Islamic Leader Slain in Algeria  Abdelkader Hachani, a senior leader of an Islamic group, was shot to death in Algiers, and President Abdelaziz Bouteflika denounced the killing as an effort to subvert his drive to put an end to nearly eight years of violence.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Clinton in Bulgaria  President Clinton, making the first visit by an American president to Bulgaria, thanked the former East Bloc country for letting NATO fighter planes use its air space in the Kosovo campaign, and he urged the struggling nation to stay its course of economic change.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Observations in Timor  Richard C. Holbrooke, the chief United States delegate to the United Nations, said militias linked to the Indonesian military were using intimidation tactics to prevent tens of thousands of East Timorese refugees from returning home from camps in West Timor. Mr. Holbrooke, who spoke during a tour of the region, also said international relief experts were losing a crucial information battle to the roving gangs.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Rwanda Blocks U.N. Visit  Rwandan officials, angered that charges against a top genocide suspect were dropped, have refused to grant a visa to the prosecutor of the international war crimes tribunal investigating the massacres of at least 500,000 people in Rwanda in 1994.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-25</p>
        <p>Pentagon Study Tracks Races' Different Views  A Pentagon survey found that despite decades of effort to promote equal opportunity and good race relations, wide gaps remain among the races in their perception of their treatment in the military.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Helping the Blind With TV  The F.C.C. is proposing that broadcasters be required to adopt technology that lets blind people follow the action on television programs by listening to a narrator describe it.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Child Seat-Belt Enforcement  The Transportation Department said the police would be stepping up enforcement of child seat-belt laws around the country this week.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>Debate Over Workplace Rules  New federal rules intended to prevent on-the-job injuries from repetitive motion touched off a wide-ranging debate over how such injuries occur, what they cost businesses and how they could be avoided.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Relief Pilot Still the Focus  Federal investigators remain focused on the actions of a reserve pilot who they believe may have deliberately crashed EgyptAir Flight 990, government officials said.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Rebuke to Vice President  Bill Bradley, citing Vice President Al Gore's use of White House perquisites in his campaign, asserted that Mr. Gore had no interest in changing the nation's campaign-finance system.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Women Arrested as Abusers  New laws and police attitudes on domestic abuse have had an unexpected consequence: in some places, one-quarter or more of arrests for domestic assault are of women.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Booklet on Gay Students  A coalition of medical, mental health, educational and religious groups plans to send school superintendents a booklet stating that there is ''no support among health and mental health professional organizations'' for the idea that homosexuality is abnormal or mentally unhealthy.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Museum Cancels Exhibition  The Detroit Institute of Arts canceled an exhibition after two days because the director was concerned that some works -- like a toy Jesus wearing a condom, and a brazil nut labeled with a racial epithet -- would offend the community.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Health Programs May Gain From Tobacco Settlement  New York lawmakers are moving toward a consensus that most if not all of the state's share of money from the settlement with tobacco companies should be spent on health.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Brick Victim Improving  Nicole Barrett, who was attacked with a brick in Midtown, has begun to speak and ask about what happened to her, her family said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Commercial License Scheme  Two employees of a truck-driving school were charged with renting watches containing answers to the state commercial driver's test.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>U.S. Says Salon Lied on Visas  Federal prosecutors said the French beauty care company Jacques Dessange had lied on visa applications so Paris-trained stylists and colorists could work illegally in New York.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Bowling Alley Killing Confession  Dominique Livingston, 20, of Jamaica, in Queens, confessed to fatally stabbing an 18-year-old teacher's assistant, the police said.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Regents Enact CUNY Standards  The State Regents, voting 9 to 6, decided that CUNY could begin excluding students from bachelor's degree programs who do not demonstrate that they are ready to begin college-level work in math and English.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-12</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>A Sudden Burst of Warming  American and Australian scientists say there is evidence that the biggest global warming in the last 100 million years may have been touched off by a blowout of greenhouse gases from the ocean floor. The effect wiped out many marine life species and helped the rise of mammals.</p>
        <p>F3</p>
        <p>Toxins and Ground Water  Industrial solvents and related chemicals are present in ground water used to provide drinking water for millions of Americans.</p>
        <p>F8</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-28</p>
        <p>Big Loss for Japan Automaker  Nissan reported a $3.05 billion loss for the first six months of its fiscal year and said it expected an annual loss of more than $5.5 billion.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Examining Online Brokers  Securities regulators in Washington and New York issued weighty reports on the industry, identifying lapses in investor protection at many online operations and offering suggestions -- though no new rules -- about how to correct them.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>U.S. Seeks Boxing Monitor  Federal prosecutors in Newark asked a judge to appoint a monitor to run the International Boxing Federation, whose leaders are accused of racketeering and bribery.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>N.F.L. Mulls Banning Gesture  The National Football League is taking steps toward banning a throat-slashing gesture players are increasingly making after scoring a touchdown.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B11</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Mr. Barak's summons to peace; a solid remedial plan for CUNY; the Teamster case.</p>
        <p>Columns: Anthony Lewis, Gail Collins.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>E12</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
