<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Return of the Native: A Brook Trout Project</title>
    <meta content="24OUTD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1079537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFDC1739F937A15752C0A96F958260" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Return of the Native: A Brook Trout Project</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nicholas Karas</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tired of catching stunted brook trout? A movement is afoot to return bigger, wild brook trout to their original streams. Anyone who has ever caught a brook trout wants to bring back the natives. Now, they can.</p>
        <p>Over the past century, the conditions these fish demand for survival have returned. As new-growth forests have reclaimed the uplands, stream conditions have improved.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tired of catching stunted brook trout? A movement is afoot to return bigger, wild brook trout to their original streams. Anyone who has ever caught a brook trout wants to bring back the natives. Now, they can.</p>
        <p>Over the past century, the conditions these fish demand for survival have returned. As new-growth forests have reclaimed the uplands, stream conditions have improved.</p>
        <p>While brook trout populations have declined in every watershed in the United States and southern Canada, they have never become extinct. They have been driven to upper extremes of streams to survive rising water temperatures, silted spawning sites and exotic species. Also, brook trout stocks were so altered by hatchery managers -- who strove for quantity not quality -- that they changed the character of the fish. Brook trout today in the United States only faintly resemble the fish Priscilla Mullins discovered in November 1620 in Town Brook, next to Plymouth Rock, when she went to fetch a pail of water.</p>
        <p>Many biologists now are promoting the use of ''wild'' trout in restocking efforts. Nowhere is this concept more important than in brook trout management. But the right stock is only part of the answer. The other part of the equation is habitat. It's impossible to reestablish all past forests or original fish habitat. There is one area, however, where this can be done to some degree.</p>
        <p>The Canadian biologist David Craig evolved one solution that's working. To replace lost spawning sites, he invented a river!</p>
        <p>During his college years, Craig found that catching a limit in southern Quebec was impossible though many domesticated brook trout were stocked. Craig saw the problem as two-fold: high pH levels from acid rain and marginal spawning beds on the Brule Lake's feeder streams.</p>
        <p>After Craig's graduation from college, he returned to the area. In 1992, he founded the Gesti-Faune Research Center, a nonprofit organization to study brook trout, and persuaded Dr. Pierre Magnan of Quebec University to join him.</p>
        <p>''We called it 'the Invented River,' '' Craig said, ''because we did just that.''</p>
        <p>In creating the new, milelong outlet to Brule lake, they exaggerated stream features that would enhance spawning. Magnan began directing graduate students in investigating different aspects of the brook trout's life, using the Invented River as their laboratory. The students looked into water velocity, gravel sizes, stream carrying capacity and redd (nest) destruction by later nest builders, larval survival and migration.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Magnan received a $1.3 million grant from Quebec to help gather brook trout data. Researchers began by building spawning beds. Craig trucked in 115 tons of washed, nut-size gravel. Strategically, they added boulders to turn the flow and create small pools to further enhance spawning sites.</p>
        <p>To protect newly hatched larvae and fry from bigger brook trout, students built sanctuary cages that allowed in only fry. To protect them from fish-eating birds, Craig used the pulp company's heavy equipment and brought in large tree trunks and temporarily laid them across the stream. The total cost of the project, including planning, machinery, gravel and labor, was only $12,500.</p>
        <p>''The results were almost immediate,'' Craig said. ''We've developed a density of 120 fry per square yard. That's well above average. By 1996, the lake catch increased 10 fold, from 300 to 3,000. We've stopped stocking the lake. We've hit on a winning combo: wild trout and near-perfect spawning sites.''</p>
        <p>Magnan added: ''What we've done can be duplicated wherever brook trout are in trouble.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
