<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Law Opening Research Data Sets Off Debate</title>
    <meta content="31FOI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1127212"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Information Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hilts, Philip J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shelby, Richard C (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DE1331F932A05754C0A96F958260" item-length="1675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Law Opening Research Data Sets Off Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP J. HILTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hilts, Philip J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists are alarmed by new law law under which anyone can write a request to Government under Freedom of Information Act and get 'all data produced' by a published study paid for with any public dollars, and potentially receive everything from a summary of findings to a scientist's notebooks or E-mail or, in some cases, information about patients; Sen Richard Shelby sponsored amendment, which passed quietly, without debate; scientists and university administrators fear that corporate or political interests will use law to hamper research on controversial subjects, tie up scientists in red tape, circumvent confidentiality agreements and thwart Government regulations (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The proposition is simple enough: Public dollars pay for a lot of scientific research, so data from that research should be available to the public.</p>
        <p>At the request of Senator Richard C. Shelby, Republican of Alabama, a measure saying just that passed quietly one evening last October, without hearings or debate, as a one-sentence amendment to the 4,000-plus-page appropriations bill. Under the amendment, anyone can write a request to the Government under the Freedom of Information Act and get ''all data produced'' by a published study paid for with any public dollars, and potentially receive everything from a summary of findings to a scientist's notebooks or E-mail or, in some cases, information about patients.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The proposition is simple enough: Public dollars pay for a lot of scientific research, so data from that research should be available to the public.</p>
        <p>At the request of Senator Richard C. Shelby, Republican of Alabama, a measure saying just that passed quietly one evening last October, without hearings or debate, as a one-sentence amendment to the 4,000-plus-page appropriations bill. Under the amendment, anyone can write a request to the Government under the Freedom of Information Act and get ''all data produced'' by a published study paid for with any public dollars, and potentially receive everything from a summary of findings to a scientist's notebooks or E-mail or, in some cases, information about patients.</p>
        <p>''Experience has shown that transparency in government is a principle that has improved decision-making and increased the public's trust in government,'' Mr. Shelby stated in explaining the law's premise.</p>
        <p>For too long, he said, Americans ''have been unable to access federally funded research data despite the significant impact of this data in the policy-making process.''</p>
        <p>The law has the United States Chamber of Commerce delighted. ''In the regulatory reform arena there may never be a more important issue,'' its Web site reads. It says that companies would be better able to scrutinize the data that policy makers use when they issue regulations, and it adds, ''This would be the first time the business community has ever been provided with the basis for the bureaucracy imposing $700 billion in annual regulatory costs on us.''</p>
        <p>The conclusion: ''If implemented properly, this rule will do more for regulatory reform than all the legislation passed in the last 10 years!''</p>
        <p>But scientists and university administrators, who took some time to notice the law, are alarmed. They fear that corporate or political interests will use the law to hamper research on controversial subjects, tie up scientists in red tape, circumvent confidentiality agreements and thwart Government regulations. While they agree with the general notion of giving the public access to research data, they assert that data from any study, no matter how rigorous, can be made to appear questionable if examined by hostile experts and publicists.</p>
        <p>''We have now concluded that the legislation constitutes a broad political attack on both science and on the Federal regulatory apparatus,'' Nils Hasselmo, president of the Association of American Universities, said in a letter to Vice President Al Gore on Wednesday. He added that ''we are very concerned that such an effort could involve actions designed to discredit scientists and discourage researchers from addressing controversial topics.''</p>
        <p>At a hearing about the law before a House subcommittee on government management and technology earlier this month, scientists recalled previous clashes between science and industry and said they feared that the law would increase such cases.</p>
        <p>In one example, Dr. Paul Fisher at the Medical College of Georgia published a study in 1991 of what small children know about tobacco brands. He found that Joe Camel was a figure known just as well as Mickey Mouse by 6-year-olds, and that they knew the brands of cigarettes in some detail.</p>
        <p>The cigarette maker R.J. Reynolds decided it wanted to see Dr. Fisher's data and do its own analysis. The company wanted not only all the raw data, but also the names and addresses of the children who were interviewed so the company could go back to ''re-interview'' them. Dr. Fisher fought the case in court, but ultimately the college's own president agreed that the company should have access to the data. Dr. Fisher resigned from the college, and Reynolds got most of the data it wanted, although it did not contact the children. The litigation dragged on for years and made Dr. Fisher decide not to do research on tobacco issues ever again.</p>
        <p>Supporters of the law dismiss the possibility of harassment. But critics point out that Senator Shelby started work on the amendment after Harvard researchers, citing confidential patient information, declined to give Congress their raw data in a two-decade-long pollution study. The study, sponsored by the Environmental Protection Agency, was instrumental in creating a 1997 Federal regulation that required stronger controls on sources of small particle emissions, including cars and power plants. Among the companies that opposed the regulation was the Alabama Power and Light Company.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Harvard compromised by giving the data to a bipartisan group, funded by both the E.P.A. and the auto industry, which is auditing the data and conclusions.</p>
        <p>After that episode, Senator Shelby recommended that businesses be able to get the raw data themselves for analysis and re-interpretation.</p>
        <p>''I strongly believe that federally funded research data that is used to drive public policy should be available to the taxpayers who paid for it,'' he said in a statement today.</p>
        <p>But Kevin Casey, who as senior director of Federal and state relations at Harvard University was involved in the dispute over the pollution study, called the Shelby amendment a backdoor attack on regulations like the emissions rule.</p>
        <p>''This is not about getting the public information,'' he said. ''It is about attacking regulations on pollution and other areas.''</p>
        <p>Through the new rule, Mr. Casey asserts, Republicans are able to attack environmental laws under the guise of sunshine laws and not lose public support, as they have for their more open challenges in recent years.</p>
        <p>''The Shelby amendment is a backdoor way to achieve the same goal,'' Mr. Casey said. ''It allows company lawyers to harass scientists collecting data on the most sensitive and controversial issues -- such as environmental health and pollution -- to slow down the research used to make policy.''</p>
        <p>The real impact of the amendment will not be known until it goes into effect later this year; it is now being formulated into regulations by the Office of Management and Budget. Among the questions facing the office is how to define ''data'' -- does it mean blood samples and archeological finds as well as written work?</p>
        <p>Under a draft of the regulations, those who want data must ask for it under the Freedom of Information Act, by submitting a request to the agency that gave the grant to the scientist. The scientist then would turn over all data -- including names and addresses of patients and other private and commercially secret information -- to the agency. Then, the F.O.I.A. office of that funding agency would determine what must be given to the requester and what must be withheld. The information act carries protections against giving out some kinds of information, including commercial trade secrets or financial data, and private information such as medical records.</p>
        <p>Administrators at the National Institutes of Health, the agency that finances the largest percentage of biomedical research, said they were  concerned about the cost of collecting and storing all the raw data. As it is, in the fiscal year 1998, the institutes' F.O.I.A. office had 20 full-time employees answering 1,200 requests at a cost of $500,000. And despite the legal protections, administrators say they worry, too, about the confidentiality of patient records.</p>
        <p>''Even if they redact the name and address, there are other ways to identify the patients -- if it was a female patient at a certain hospital with a particular diagnosis, that might be enough to identify them,'' said Wendy Baldwin, the institutes' deputy director for extramural affairs.</p>
        <p>Members of Mr. Shelby's staff said that while they understood the scientists' worries, they believed that the F.O.I.A. rules would prevent disclosure of private or trade secret information. And, if problems do occur,  ''we can address those. We will be alert to those.''</p>
        <p>In most areas of science, the way to test the mettle of a study is not to examine data, but to do another study, said Carol Scheman, vice president for governmental affairs at the University of Pennsylvania, but for some kinds of studies, she said, ''Senator Shelby is right. There are real issues of how to share data.''</p>
        <p>For example, in the pollution studies by Harvard's School of Public health, thousands of subjects were followed for more than two decades. That kind of work is unlikely to be copied. So some other method must be used to review the data behind the scientists' final conclusions, she said.</p>
        <p>Industry is not uniformly in favor of the new rule. Pharmaceutical and biotechnology companies, for example, fear that the rule will jeopardize university-industry agreements. If a scientist's data can be fetched through F.O.I.A., so can information they have shared with the scientist. This means, potentially, that competitors could learn much about the progress of their commercial work through the new rule.</p>
        <p>The Washington watchdog group OMB Watch also points out that the rule is aimed at nonprofit groups while leaving the corporations who work with government funds untouched. The amendment applies to hospitals and other nonprofit groups that get grants from the government, but excludes other groups that get contracts from the Government. ''Thus, it applies to a Y.M.C.A. that receives a Federal grant, but not to Boeing that is doing a range of research through contracts,'' Gary D. Bass, a spokesman for the group, said in a July 15 statement.</p>
        <p>But other business and advocacy groups are enthusiastic. Those on the record in favor of the Shelby amendment include Gun Owners of America, which has complained about research that shows guns in the home are several times more likely to kill family members by accident than intruders on purpose. In Washington, several dedicated anti-regulatory groups have lined up in favor of the Shelby rule, including the Competitive Enterprise Institute and Citizens for a Sound Economy.</p>
        <p>In its Web site, the Chamber of Commerce, notes that huge masses of data can be fetched from scientists -- data to challenge E.P.A. regulations on clean air and water, data supporting the global warming agreement called the Kyoto Protocol. ''This list is virtually limitless and can be extended into areas other than health and safety,'' it says.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
