<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Letter to Environmental Groups, Clinton Firmly Defends Gore Record</title>
    <meta content="Y17GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1100736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EEDE103BF934A25757C0A96F958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Letter to Environmental Groups, Clinton Firmly Defends Gore Record</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton sends environmental groups letter that defends Vice Pres Al Gore's record on their issues--unusual move that underscores Clinton's commitment to promoting Gore's Presidential prospects; Clinton responds to recent letter to Gore from several environmental groups that accused Clinton and Gore of breaking their pledge to reduce pollutants that cause global warming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton sent environmental groups a letter today that aggressively defends Vice President Al Gore's record on their issues -- a highly unusual move that underscores the President's commitment to promoting Mr. Gore's Presidential prospects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was responding to a letter to Mr. Gore earlier this week from several environmental groups who accused the President and Vice President of breaking their pledge to reduce pollutants that cause global warming. White House aides said they could not recall a similar instance in which Mr. Clinton felt so moved to publicly aid Mr. Gore.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton sent environmental groups a letter today that aggressively defends Vice President Al Gore's record on their issues -- a highly unusual move that underscores the President's commitment to promoting Mr. Gore's Presidential prospects.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was responding to a letter to Mr. Gore earlier this week from several environmental groups who accused the President and Vice President of breaking their pledge to reduce pollutants that cause global warming. White House aides said they could not recall a similar instance in which Mr. Clinton felt so moved to publicly aid Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>''No one has done more over the past decade to mobilize action against climate change than Vice President Gore,'' Mr. Clinton wrote in his three-page letter. ''And no one can more effectively lead this effort in the decade ahead. We must not allow our frustration over the real obstacles we face to distract us from our common goals.''</p>
        <p>He continued, ''We must pursue sound strategies, not proposals that risk eroding the support so vital to our success.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's effort demonstrates the degree to which he is determined to help his Vice President by trying to smooth relations with environmental groups on what could be an important issue in the Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>The timing of Mr. Clinton's letter is particularly helpful. Next Thursday is Earth Day, when the Administration is bound to draw significant attention to its environmental record.</p>
        <p>The environmental groups' letter to Mr. Gore, who has long cast himself as an environmental champion, was surprisingly combative. ''We are writing,'' it complained, ''to voice deep disappointment with the lack of an Administration proposal to require significant reductions in global warming pollution. We are particularly frustrated that the Administration has not sought meaningful emission reductions from either power plants or passenger vehicles.''</p>
        <p>In his reply, Mr. Clinton recited the Administration's environmental accomplishments in the face of ''the most anti-environmental Congress ever.'' Throughout the letter, he lauded Mr. Gore's ''vision and leadership.'' He said Mr. Gore had ''led the charge'' on a number of fronts. He also wrote, ''The Vice President and I have sought at every opportunity to highlight the mounting scientific evidence that global warming is a threat to this and future generations.''</p>
        <p>A treaty intended to reduce global emissions was negotiated in Kyoto, Japan, in 1997 and signed by the Administration last year. But it was not presented to the Senate for ratification because it faced strong opposition from industry groups.</p>
        <p>Carl Pope, executive director of the Sierra Club, one of nine groups that signed the original letter, said of the response, ''It is a valid defense of what the Administration has done to date. The letter is fundamentally silent on the question of when the Administration will take the next step: insisting that the auto industry and the public utilities start cleaning up their greenhouse emissions.''</p>
        <p>Paul Hansen, executive director of the Izaak Walton League of America,  another signer of the environmental groups' letter, said, ''The President makes a good point -- that we need to try to work together.'' Even so, he said, it does not take away from the deficiencies in the Administration's record.</p>
        <p>Another signer of the letter, Philip E. Clapp, president of the National Environmental Trust, said Mr. Clinton ''feels it necessary to cast his and the Vice President's inaction in the best political light.'' He added: ''This is calculated to defend the Vice President from potential criticism between now and the election.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hansen said he was disturbed that a colleague had given the environmental groups' letter to reporters. ''I'm extremely unhappy about that,'' he said. ''We thought this was an exchange of views -- not a political stone-throwing contest.'' But Mr. Clapp insisted that ''this letter was quite specifically a public letter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
