<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Environmental Group Backs Bradley and Criticizes Gore</title>
    <meta content="Y15BRA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1138002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Friends of the Earth</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E0D7163CF936A2575AC0A96F958260" item-length="492" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Environmental Group Backs Bradley and Criticizes Gore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Friends of the Earth Political Action Committee endorses Bill Bradley's bid for Democratic Presidential nomination, dealing blow to Vice Pres Al Gore's efforts to cast self as choice of environmentally minded voters; group officials cite frustration with Clinton Administration's environmental policies; other environmental groups call move premature (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Former Senator Bill Bradley picked up the endorsement of a national environmental organization today, dealing a blow to Vice President Al Gore's efforts to cast himself as the clear choice of environmentally minded voters in the Democratic Presidential primaries.</p>
        <p>Officials with the group, the Friends of the Earth Political Action Committee, said they had decided to back Mr. Bradley this early in the campaign -- the Iowa caucuses are still more than four months away -- largely out of frustration with the environmental policies of the Clinton Administration, particularly on global warming and international trade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Former Senator Bill Bradley picked up the endorsement of a national environmental organization today, dealing a blow to Vice President Al Gore's efforts to cast himself as the clear choice of environmentally minded voters in the Democratic Presidential primaries.</p>
        <p>Officials with the group, the Friends of the Earth Political Action Committee, said they had decided to back Mr. Bradley this early in the campaign -- the Iowa caucuses are still more than four months away -- largely out of frustration with the environmental policies of the Clinton Administration, particularly on global warming and international trade.</p>
        <p>''We had very high hopes for Al Gore, and we've been disappointed,'' said Mark Whiteis-Helm, a spokesman for the group. ''He's talked the talk but he has simply been unable to walk the walk.''</p>
        <p>With 20,000 members in the United States, Friends of the Earth is significantly smaller than other major environmental groups, and it lacks the financial resources to provide much campaign help to Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>The announcement also appears unlikely to sway the two other national environmental groups that endorse candidates, the Sierra Club and the League of Conservation Voters. Officials of both groups called today's move premature.</p>
        <p>''None of these candidates have even outlined their positions or programs,'' said Deb Callahan, president of the League of Conservation Voters.</p>
        <p>Both candidates, Ms. Callahan said, have strong environmental records.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore, the author of a 1992 best seller about the dangers of global warming, ''Earth in the Balance,'' has been widely viewed as the leading environmental voice in the Administration. So today's endorsement raises questions about the depth of his support within an important Democratic constituency that might have once been safely considered in his camp.</p>
        <p>''This is going to remind a lot of people who care about the environment about how good Bradley's record was,'' said Eric Hauser, a spokesman for Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>Kiki Moore, a spokeswoman for the Vice President, said, ''Al Gore will continue to work for a balanced approach and fight for a clean and healthy environment for America's working families.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Whiteis-Helm criticized the Administration -- and by extension Mr. Gore -- for not pushing to reduce use of chemicals that are believed to contribute to global warming and for negotiating trade agreements that let foreign companies skirt American environmental rules.</p>
        <p>The League of Conservation Voters, which grades members of Congress on their environmental votes, has given Mr. Bradley a lifetime score of 84 percent for the 18 years he represented New Jersey in the Senate. The group has given Mr. Gore, who represented Tennessee in the House and the Senate for 16 years, a 64 percent lifetime score.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
