<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reviving Quest to Tame Energy of Stars</title>
    <meta content="08FUSI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1113570"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fusion (Nuclear Reaction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fusion (Nuclear Reaction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Energy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D81339F93BA35755C0A96F958260" item-length="2296" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reviving Quest to Tame Energy of Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <dateline>PLAINSBORO, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Specialists in field of hydrogen fusion band together to pursue research in face of discouragements and spending cuts; put their hope in lean, selective financing of small-scale experiments as well as large the large ones that have dominated field's history, increased cooperation between longstanding competitors, and a lot of patience; say main obstacle to accelerated research fusion is the disincentive created by low fossil fuel prices; drawing; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In its heyday it was a palace among physics laboratories, with an enviably fat budget, ample support staff and the prestige that comes to research institutions working at the cutting edge in solving global problems. But today, the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory, still a leader in hydrogen fusion research, is so short of cash that it can no longer afford even a receptionist.</p>
        <p>However, a dry spell of discouragements and spending cuts for fusion research may be ending. With their backs to a financial wall, specialists in the field are banding together to pursue the elusive goal of harnessing thermonuclear fusion, the process that drives the sun and hydrogen bombs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In its heyday it was a palace among physics laboratories, with an enviably fat budget, ample support staff and the prestige that comes to research institutions working at the cutting edge in solving global problems. But today, the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory, still a leader in hydrogen fusion research, is so short of cash that it can no longer afford even a receptionist.</p>
        <p>However, a dry spell of discouragements and spending cuts for fusion research may be ending. With their backs to a financial wall, specialists in the field are banding together to pursue the elusive goal of harnessing thermonuclear fusion, the process that drives the sun and hydrogen bombs.</p>
        <p>Leaders in the field say the new spirit calls for lean, selective financing of small-scale experiments as well as the large ones that have dominated the field's history, increased cooperation between long-standing competitors, and a lot of patience.</p>
        <p>Proponents of hydrogen fusion, the joining together of hydrogen nuclei to produce useful energy, have suffered too many frustrations over the years to hope for too much too soon. Fusion energy will not come tomorrow. But it could become a reality in the mid-21st century, believers say, and slow the carbon dioxide pollution of the atmosphere by the burning of fossil fuels -- a problem that may be leading to disastrous global warming.</p>
        <p>Pressed by tight budgetary constraints imposed by Congress, competing fusion laboratories have begun sharing and coordinating their research to a greater extent than ever and have drafted guidelines for allocating their limited resources as they would an investment portfolio, giving major financing to the most promising projects but gambling some funds for high-risk but potentially fruitful experiments.</p>
        <p>Next month fusion scientists and engineers from around the world will hold a meeting in Snowmass, Colo., to discuss all the devices and proposals currently on the table. It will be the first meeting of its kind, according to its co-chairman, Dr. Michael E. Mauel of Columbia University, and it signals a growing realization that if fusion energy is ever to become a reality it will require global cooperation rather than endless competition between nations and individual laboratories.</p>
        <p>The main obstacle to accelerated research fusion, many scientists say, is the disincentive created by low fossil fuel prices.</p>
        <p>''Right now,'' said Dr. Robert J. Goldston, director of the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory in New Jersey, ''a bottle of table water costs more than a bottle of gasoline. But cheap oil won't last forever, and in any case, the burning of fossil fuels may be contributing to global warming. Fusion, which could produce enormous amounts of energy at reasonable cost with only negligible amounts of radioactive waste and no pollution of the atmosphere, may be our only practical alternative to fossil fuels.''</p>
        <p>No one doubts that hydrogen fusion can be achieved. Huge pulses of fusion power have already been generated by experimental fusion reactors in the United States and Europe. The trouble is that until now, conventional generating plants have had to supply more energy to kindle a thermonuclear pulse than the pulse itself produces. No one has yet been able to squeeze thermonuclear fuel tightly enough and long enough to ignite a self-sustaining fusion reaction.</p>
        <p>In the sun, energy is produced when hydrogen nuclei fuse to produce helium, a heavier element. But for hydrogen nuclei to overcome their mutual electrostatic repulsion and get close enough to fuse, they must have very high velocities, that is to say, they must be very, very hot. Scores of different reactor designs have been built, tested and abandoned over the years, most of which belong to one of two main categories: magnetic confinement, the squeezing of plasma by magnetic fields; and inertial confinement, the squeezing of hot gas by the implosion of miniature hydrogen bombs.</p>
        <p>A magnetic confinement device uses powerful interlocked magnetic fields to contain and compress hot, electrically charged plasma (a kind of gas) within a vacuum chamber. The plasma must never touch the solid walls of its container; otherwise, it instantly loses its heat and can never be coaxed into undergoing fusion. Everything depends on keeping the plasma's magnetic bottle tightly stoppered, which is no easy task.</p>
        <p>Most of the stars of magnetic fusion experiments have been devices called tokamaks. One of the largest and most successful of these machines was the Princeton laboratory's big Tokamak Fusion Test Reactor, which in 1994 produced a record-breaking pulse of 10.7 million watts of fusion power. It was shut down two years ago for lack of money.</p>
        <p>The device's lineage goes back to the early 1950's, when the Soviet scientists Andrei Sakharov and Igor Tamm proposed the design and named it tokamak -- the Russian acronym for ''toroidal magnetic chamber'' -- a doughnut-shaped machine that compresses fusion fuel magnetically.</p>
        <p>Since then, however, the seemingly simple tokamak idea proved to conceal endless pitfalls and complications, and despite great progress in understanding the behavior of plasmas, commercial fusion power by magnetic confinement is still only a dream.</p>
        <p>A competing approach to fusion is inertial confinement, in which hydrogen bombs the size of small BB pellets would be detonated in a target chamber, transferring their energy to a metal ''blanket.''</p>
        <p>In an inertial confinement reactor, each hydrogen-filled pellet would be the target of batteries of high-powered lasers, particle beams or X-rays. A blast of this radiation would vaporize the plastic outer layer of the tiny fusion pellet. The resulting implosion would drive the plasma formed from the vaporized pellet inward on itself, compressing and heating the fusion fuel inside it until a thermonuclear explosion occurs.</p>
        <p>The thermonuclear pop of each pellet, yielding energy equivalent to the blast of 100 pounds of TNT, could simulate a thermonuclear weapon explosion -- a similarity that has important implications for both science and thermonuclear weapons programs. The Lawrence Livermore Laboratory in California is a leader in this approach to fusion.</p>
        <p>Livermore is a crucial player in the Science-Based Stockpile Stewardship and Management Program, which monitors the health of the nation's nuclear weapons. Fusion experiments using the gargantuan laser array Livermore is building as the National Ignition Facility will help the laboratory evaluate the nuclear stockpile without having to detonate nuclear explosions banned by treaty.</p>
        <p>Because their research has both scientific and military purposes, Livermore and the other two weapons laboratories supported by the Department of Energy, Sandia and Los Alamos National Laboratories, receive financing for both categories of research. This makes them richer than laboratories like the Princeton Plasma Physics Laboratory, which receive only science financing.</p>
        <p>Competition for funding has always been a source of friction between rival partisans of magnetic and inertial fusion, and the sharing of ideas, experimental data and equipment was often minimal. Experiments by rival camps sometimes wastefully duplicated research.</p>
        <p>But a new spirit of closer cooperation has developed. In an interview, Dr. Mauel, a Columbia University fusion expert, praised leaders of the magnetic and inertial confinement fields for healing many of their long-standing differences.</p>
        <p>''Dr. E. Michael Campbell, the laser director at Livermore, and Rob Goldston, the Princeton director, are doing a wonderful job bringing us all together as a team,'' Dr. Mauel said. ''As a co-chairman of the big fusion meeting we're holding in Snowmass next month, I know that there's still competition among us. But we're working together more than we used to.''</p>
        <p>A center of interest in the fusion race is the National Ignition Facility that Livermore is building -- a $1.2 billion array of 192 lasers packed into a building that could contain a football stadium. When it begins operating in 2003, its scientists hope that progress toward sustained power-producing fusion will be greatly accelerated.</p>
        <p>At Princeton, financing will remain much less lavish. The laboratory will have to spend $48 million in the next three years just to demolish its decommissioned Tokamak Fusion Test Reactor, which still contains traces of the radioactive tritium it used as fuel. The big machine's reaction chamber will be filled with concrete and then sawed into pieces for disposal, safely isolating the tritium until it decays harmlessly.</p>
        <p>At its peak in the 1980's, the Princeton center employed about 1,300 people. Today it has about 400.</p>
        <p>But the laboratory has retained most of its senior scientists and is still doing important experiments.</p>
        <p>Dr. Goldston and his colleagues believe magnetic fusion research in the United States will need a bit more than $300 million a year to regain momentum -- a substantial increase from its present level of $223 million. At its peak, magnetic confinement research received as much as $370 million.</p>
        <p>But fusion physicists are learning to live within tight budgets.</p>
        <p>In the spirit of no-frills research that has followed the closing of its big tokamak, Princeton has already completed a much more modest fusion reactor called a spherical tokamak, which resembles an apple with a thin core rather than a doughnut. The $23.8 million machine incorporates a highly efficient magnetic confinement system and will begin full operation in August. (By comparison, Princeton's big tokamak shut down two years ago cost more than $1.4 billion.)</p>
        <p>Other magnetic fusion projects in the United States are under way at the General Atomics Company (which operates its big DIII-D tokamak in San Diego), the Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, the Naval Research Laboratory, the University of Rochester, the University of Wisconsin, Oak Ridge National Laboratory and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Time and again, however, multimillion-dollar tokamaks, stellarators, spheromaks, inertial confinement systems and other devices with unfamiliar names have fallen far short of the conditions needed to sustain a thermonuclear ''burn'' -- the continuous joining-together of hydrogen nuclei into helium.</p>
        <p>Taxpayers, members of Congress and many scientists outside the fusion research community have grown weary with the ever-receding goal and the huge cost of many fusion experiments.</p>
        <p>Moreover, many of the heady predictions during the early years of fusion research proved to be wildly overblown. Enthusiasts used to claim that hydrogen, the most abundant of all substances in the universe, could power the world cheaply and forever. However, ordinary hydrogen is not viewed as a fusion fuel that could be used in the foreseeable future. Commercial reactors of the near future, if such are built, will almost certainly require fuel mixtures of two hydrogen isotopes -- deuterium and tritium, not common hydrogen. Tritium, which is radioactive, is produced only at great expense from reactors that burn uranium.</p>
        <p>Another impediment is that the fusion of deuterium and tritium can be ignited only at a temperature around 100 million degrees Celsius (180 million degrees Fahrenheit) after being compressed to a density 20 times that of lead. These conditions are difficult to create.</p>
        <p>Confining a dollop of super-hot compressed plasma has proved to be harder than compressing and shaping a blob of jelly using only rubber bands. Each clever idea of the plasma physicists for solving this problem has been matched by a new challenge.</p>
        <p>Since 1996, Federal support for the fusion energy has program declined by 40 percent, and last year the United States withdrew from a partnership with Russia, Japan and Europe intended to create a gigantic fusion research machine -- the International Thermonuclear Experimental Reactor. It was a heavy blow to fusion prospects.</p>
        <p>''It was just too expensive,'' Dr. Goldston said. ''We simply have to choose a path consistent with national priorities. It will take longer, but we'll get there. We must get there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
