<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Take Hundreds of Epochs And Digest in Two Hours</title>
    <meta content="22GOOD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1162915"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">National Geographic Specials (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE2DE1639F931A15751C1A96F958260" item-length="567" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Take Hundreds of Epochs And Digest in Two Hours</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Goodman reviews National Geographic Special: Adventures in Time; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>So if you're in need of another millennium-season fix, here's a two-hour special from good old reliable National Geographic. ''Adventures in Time,'' made up mainly of material that fans have seen before, offers little by way of fresh ideas or incisive thought, but it is a picturesque grab bag. The notion of packaging billions of years of happenings in two hours is a television conceit, so don't take too seriously the pretense that the program has much to do with time, except the timeouts for commercials.</p>
        <p>The viewing family may enjoy these quick looks at some favorites like the 80-million-year-old fossil of an Oviraptor, ''that fearsome carnivore of the Gobi.'' So much for dinosaurs, and it's briskly on to the water chevrotain, an ancient flower eater related to antelopes and pigs that can resist the horned lizard, which in turn owes its survival to its ability to squirt a nasty stream of blood into the face of a predatory coyote.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>So if you're in need of another millennium-season fix, here's a two-hour special from good old reliable National Geographic. ''Adventures in Time,'' made up mainly of material that fans have seen before, offers little by way of fresh ideas or incisive thought, but it is a picturesque grab bag. The notion of packaging billions of years of happenings in two hours is a television conceit, so don't take too seriously the pretense that the program has much to do with time, except the timeouts for commercials.</p>
        <p>The viewing family may enjoy these quick looks at some favorites like the 80-million-year-old fossil of an Oviraptor, ''that fearsome carnivore of the Gobi.'' So much for dinosaurs, and it's briskly on to the water chevrotain, an ancient flower eater related to antelopes and pigs that can resist the horned lizard, which in turn owes its survival to its ability to squirt a nasty stream of blood into the face of a predatory coyote.</p>
        <p>Before you know it, the program has reached primates, those new arrivals, in the form of the famous skull discovered by Louis and Mary Leakey of a young male creature who lived in Africa about two million years ago.</p>
        <p>The narrator makes a strained segue from primitive life to an obsession with death as evidenced by the ancient sarcophagus discovered not long ago near the pyramids of Giza. If you conclude that the subjects are driven by the available pictures, you are onto something.</p>
        <p>The camera speeds from New Guinea to the Indian subcontinent to central Borneo, ostensibly for glimpses of the ways different peoples see or ignore the passage of time. Although it's a random collection, the material has its fascination. As much cannot be said for the familiar references to 20th-century explorers including Robert Peary and Matthew Henson, Richard Byrd, William Beebe and Otis Barton. And then for no particular reason except the photographs there's an interlude devoted to the perennially popular pastime of climbing Mount Everest: ''You don't conquer it, you survive it.''</p>
        <p>So much for Earth. Suddenly we are transported to outer space, a slightly discouraging journey considering the recent failure of the latest Mars probe.</p>
        <p>But the narrator holds out the hope of establishing an outpost on Mars by 2050, by which time, some expert assures us, gene research should be producing humans without cavities or colds or inherited disease who will live almost forever. That is, of course, if the millennium does not live up to the expectations or wishes of people who are planning on an end to the world.</p>
        <p>But National Geographic is no more a proponent of miraculous expiration than of creationism. The fears with which the program leaves us are of ''a doomsday asteroid'' that could strike almost anytime or global warming or depletion of ocean life or pollution or overpopulation; you name it. Happy millennium.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL GEOGRAPHIC SPECIAL  Adventures in Time  NBC, tonight at 8  (Channel 4 in New York)</p>
        <p>Written by Kevin McCarey. Nicolas Noxon, executive producer; Nicholas Stein, producer; Emmanuel Mairesse, co-producer and editor; Teresa Koenig, senior producer. Music by Jay Chattaway. Barry D. Nye, series supervising producer and editor; Andrew Carl Wilk, executive vice president, programming and production; Tim Kelly, president; C. Richard Allen, president and chief executive, National Geographic Ventures, John Lithgow, narrator.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
