<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beginning a Bargain-Basement Invasion of Mars</title>
    <meta content="21MARS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19990924T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1139361"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Climate Orbiter (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Polar Lander (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA1E3CF932A1575AC0A96F958260" item-length="1851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beginning a Bargain-Basement Invasion of Mars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two American spacecraft are approaching Mars; Mars Climate Orbiter, scheduled for arrival on Sept 23, will orbit planet and study its atmosphere, prospect for water and generally observe weather through seasons of a full Martian year; Mars Polar Lander will land Dec 3 at edge of south polar ice cap, where terrain is thought to hold layered record of planet's climate history; missions are integral steps in long-term strategy of sending small spacecraft to Mars at each 26-month opportunity in effort to map the entire planet and its resources and scout out clues to conditions there in an earlier, more temperate epoch; drawings (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two American spacecraft are approaching Mars, the second wave of economy-class robotic orbiting and landing parties in an ambitious revival of exploration of the red planet.</p>
        <p>One spacecraft, scheduled for arrival on Thursday, is to orbit the planet and study its atmosphere, prospect for water and generally observe weather through the seasons of a full Martian year (687 days). The second craft is on course for a landing on Dec. 3 at the edge of the south polar ice cap, where the terrain is thought to hold a layered record of the planet's climate history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two American spacecraft are approaching Mars, the second wave of economy-class robotic orbiting and landing parties in an ambitious revival of exploration of the red planet.</p>
        <p>One spacecraft, scheduled for arrival on Thursday, is to orbit the planet and study its atmosphere, prospect for water and generally observe weather through the seasons of a full Martian year (687 days). The second craft is on course for a landing on Dec. 3 at the edge of the south polar ice cap, where the terrain is thought to hold a layered record of the planet's climate history.</p>
        <p>Mission officials at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., said yesterday that both spacecraft, Mars Climate Orbiter and Mars Polar Lander, are in excellent condition and ready for their arrival. Last week, the orbiter fired thruster jets to fine-tune its aim on the planet.</p>
        <p>Though relatively modest in cost and scope, the missions are integral steps in a long-term strategy of sending small spacecraft to Mars at each 26-month opportunity when the orbital relationship is right. Orbiters, landers, roving surface vehicles, balloons and miniaturized airplanes -- at all times over the next decade or more there should be a robotic presence on and over Mars. Their objectives are to map the entire planet and its resources and scout out clues to conditions there in an earlier, more temperate epoch.</p>
        <p>Eventual objectives are to return samples of rock and soil, perhaps by 2008, and someday send astronauts for a long visit. Behind this methodical approach is the enduring question of whether life ever emerged on Mars and left some fossil traces, and whether it still exists in some moist recesses of this cold, arid world.</p>
        <p>This is a far cry from the fictional travels to Mars that once fired the human imagination. In the marvelous tales of Edgar Rice Burroughs, also creator of Tarzan, the gentleman-adventurer John Carter simply closed his eyes and wished himself all the way to Mars (Barsoom in the novels), where he found spired cities, eight-legged beasts of burden and, not least, the beautiful Dejah Thoris, the princess he wooed and won.</p>
        <p>Real-life exploration of Mars has proved to be tame stuff by potboiler standards. Long after the Martians of legend vanished, two spacecraft landed there in 1976 in search not of a princess but of the merest trace of microbial life in the red dust. Finding nothing, and under tighter budget limits, scientists have turned to the even more plodding operations of today.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to do a whole lot more with less,'' said Dr. Sam Thurman, flight operations manager of the current missions. ''The public and Congress have told us, 'Space is neat, but it's got to be done at less than a billion dollars a pop.' ''</p>
        <p>That was the price tag on the Mars Observer spacecraft, which failed just before reaching the planet in 1992. The failure was particularly devastating because the National Aeronautics and Space Administration had put all its eggs in one basket, and was left with nothing. The Viking life-seeking missions in 1976, though operational successes, cost more than $2 billion, a figure no longer acceptable.</p>
        <p>By contrast, as a result of NASA orders to develop ''cheaper, better, faster'' science missions, the complete cost of the present Climate Orbiter and Polar Lander missions has been kept to $327.5 million, Dr. Thurman said. This represents a further paring of expenditures over the first two missions in the current program. The Pathfinder spacecraft, which landed with its little Sojourner rover two years ago, cost $270 million. Another $300 million went for the orbiting companion, Global Surveyor.</p>
        <p>Global Surveyor is still going strong, returning the most detailed pictures ever for mapping the planet. The pictures of widespread water erosion and magnetic data showing that in an early period the planet churned with internal heat have further encouraged planetary geologists in their view that ancient Mars was a more Earthlike place, with abundant water, and could have supported the beginnings of life.</p>
        <p>''We want to understand the history of that planet from a biological perspective,'' Dr. Charles Elachi, director of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory's space and earth-science programs, said in an interview with Sky &amp; Telescope magazine. He has been in charge of developing the current Mars exploration strategy.</p>
        <p>In an effort to answer some of the life and climate questions, the orbiter is equipped to examine the temperatures, dust and clouds in the planet's atmosphere, composed mainly of carbon dioxide, and especially look for water vapor.</p>
        <p>''That's a very important part of trying to understand Mars's climate,'' said Dr. Richard W. Zurek, the chief mission scientist. ''We want to learn how water gets into the atmosphere, where it comes from and where it goes.''</p>
        <p>Launched last December, the 1,387-pound Climate Orbiter is approaching the northern half of Mars. A 16-minute firing of the craft's main rocket should slow it down to enter a wide-ranging elliptical orbit. The spacecraft will loop around Mars once every 14 hours, at first dipping in no closer than 130 miles from the surface.</p>
        <p>Then the craft will be maneuvered to a closest approach of 60 miles to use friction from the upper atmosphere to bring its orbit down to a low circular course. This technique, known as aerobraking, was first demonstrated by Mars Pathfinder in 1997. Its advantage is economic: the reduction in the amount of fuel needed for rocket braking means the spacecraft weighs less and could be launched on its journey by a smaller, less expensive rocket.</p>
        <p>By the middle of November, the spacecraft should be settled in a 262-mile-high orbit and ready to support the Polar Lander's planned 90-day operations on the surface. During that time, the orbiter is to serve as a communications satellite, relaying radio transmissions between the lander and Earth.</p>
        <p>The 1,270-pound Polar Lander, 3.5 feet tall and 12 feet wide, is targeted to touch down on a broad, gently rolling plain near the south pole. Specifically, the landing site is a rectangular area 125 miles long and 12 miles wide, at 76 degrees south latitude, 195 degrees west longitude.</p>
        <p>At landing time, it will be the end of spring in the planet's southern hemisphere. The site will be in 24-hour daylight, critical to operations of the solar-powered craft's systems. The thick polar ice cap, in seasonal retreat, will be farther south. But drilling into the frozen surface, the spacecraft should be able to investigate subterranean water ice and the details of the layers of dust and ice deposited there.</p>
        <p>''We believe this layered terrain is a record of climate change on Mars,'' Dr. Zurek said. ''In a sense, digging into the surface will be like reading tree rings or layers in an ice core.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Ronald Greeley of Arizona State University, a member of the lander science team, said a study of the thickness and geometry of the polar layered terrain should test ''some of our ideas of how the layers relate to the planet's climate history'' over millions of years.</p>
        <p>The lander's 6.5-foot-long digging arm will probably take two days to scoop up soil samples and deliver them to an oven. Gases from the heated samples will be analyzed for any evidence of water vapor, among other things. Then the lander's cameras and other instruments are expected to collect data on atmospheric conditions and weather patterns. A microphone is designed to capture the sounds of Mars, perhaps the whistling of winds on the robot arm's digging operation.</p>
        <p>To supplement some of its own explorations, the lander is supposed to release two projectiles about 10 minutes before touchdown. These probes are to crash at 400 miles an hour and bury themselves beneath the surface, where they will draw soil samples for heating and another search for vaporized water ice.</p>
        <p>By March, when the lander's operations should be ending in the approaching polar darkness, the Climate Orbiter is scheduled to begin its own primary mission. One of its two science instruments is an infrared radiometer for measuring temperatures, dust, water vapor and clouds in the atmosphere from the surface to an altitude of 50 miles.</p>
        <p>The orbiter also carries a color imaging system, combining digital wide-angle and medium-angle cameras, developed by Dr. Michael Malin of Malin Space Science Systems in San Diego. The wide-angle camera will be used for daily global pictures of the Martian atmosphere and surface. The medium-angle instrument should provide more detailed pictures of surface changes related to weather and seasonal conditions.</p>
        <p>Because temperatures on the planet rarely rise above freezing, most water there is probably stored in the ground, chemically and physically bound to the soil or as ice. This may be especially true in the polar regions. Wherever water is, the orbiter's mission is to investigate its distribution and search for possible surface and subsurface reservoirs.</p>
        <p>Now, as the Climate Orbiter cruises toward its encounter, all is quiet for flight controllers. Their simulations are completed. All instructions for maneuvers have been radioed to the spacecraft's computers. And Polar Lander, with another two and a half months to go before its arrival, is essentially flying on autopilot.</p>
        <p>Soon enough, the controllers will be busy operating two vehicles at once, and the Global Surveyor as well. As another concession to the budget crunch, said Dr. Thurman, the flight operations manager, the ground support team has been trimmed to 80 people. Seven years ago, Mars Observer had a team of more than 200. And in the 1970's, the Vikings had 500.</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 24, 1999, Friday  An article in Science Times on Tuesday about missions to Mars misidentified the craft that first used atmospheric friction, or aerobraking, to achieve orbit around a planet. It was the Mars Global Surveyor. (The Mars Pathfinder made a direct descent to the planet's surface, also in 1997.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 24, 1999, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about missions to Mars misidentified the craft that first used atmospheric friction, or aerobraking, to achieve orbit around a planet. It was the Mars Global Surveyor. (The Mars Pathfinder made a direct descent to the planet's surface, also in 1997.)</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
