<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Threatened but Unruffled, a Persistent Beauty in Sea, Sky and Sand</title>
    <meta content="25GOLD$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1118278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Center of Photography (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Vicki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E2D6173AF936A15755C0A96F958260" item-length="1217" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Threatened but Unruffled, a Persistent Beauty in Sea, Sky and Sand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VICKI GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Vicki</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicki Goldberg reviews contemporary seascape photographs, at International Center of Photography; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the sea, by the sea: That's where city dwellers long to go for renewal and inspiration, for play and the sweaty joys of a little publicly sanctioned voyeurism. It was not always so. For centuries the sea was a far cry from frolic and a close call with fear. The Lord destroyed all creatures once, by making the ocean rise up. The sea remained fearsome to journey on, fearsome to live near and home to monsters, one of which swallowed Jonah whole. Centuries later, some suspected that if Columbus ventured too far out he might sail off the edge of the earth into oblivion.</p>
        <p>The shore as vacation paradise is a social construct. The 19th-century French historian Jules Michelet said the sea was invented in 1750, not long after medicine had decided that sea bathing could cure melancholy. So writes James Hamilton-Paterson in ''Sea Change: The Seascape in Contemporary Photography,'' the catalogue of an exhibition with the same name at the International Center of Photography Uptown. Trudy Wilner Stack, curator of exhibitions and collections at the Center for Creative Photography at the University of Arizona in Tucson, was curator of this show for the center, which organized it. With 65 works by 19 photographers, the show has moments that are nearly as lovely as the south shore of Long Island, with the great advantage that you need not brave the Expressway on Friday to get there.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the sea, by the sea: That's where city dwellers long to go for renewal and inspiration, for play and the sweaty joys of a little publicly sanctioned voyeurism. It was not always so. For centuries the sea was a far cry from frolic and a close call with fear. The Lord destroyed all creatures once, by making the ocean rise up. The sea remained fearsome to journey on, fearsome to live near and home to monsters, one of which swallowed Jonah whole. Centuries later, some suspected that if Columbus ventured too far out he might sail off the edge of the earth into oblivion.</p>
        <p>The shore as vacation paradise is a social construct. The 19th-century French historian Jules Michelet said the sea was invented in 1750, not long after medicine had decided that sea bathing could cure melancholy. So writes James Hamilton-Paterson in ''Sea Change: The Seascape in Contemporary Photography,'' the catalogue of an exhibition with the same name at the International Center of Photography Uptown. Trudy Wilner Stack, curator of exhibitions and collections at the Center for Creative Photography at the University of Arizona in Tucson, was curator of this show for the center, which organized it. With 65 works by 19 photographers, the show has moments that are nearly as lovely as the south shore of Long Island, with the great advantage that you need not brave the Expressway on Friday to get there.</p>
        <p>There are no crowds on these beaches, either, at least not in the photographs, where no living creature, whether clad in bikini or armored with scales, strays into view. These photographs concentrate on waves and sky, horizon, pattern and color (though the majority are black and white, and oddly, they are the most beautiful). Painters long preferred the beaches populated, if only sparsely. Early in the 19th century a number of artists painted the sea with a solitary figure contemplating the vastness of the ocean, the immensity of the universe.</p>
        <p>Turner struggled with the titanic battle of ships against angry oceans. Boudin, Manet and the Impressionists regarded the beach as a holiday where fashionable strollers dotted the sand with color. At I.C.P., however, the ocean is sad, lovely, frightening, perhaps the embodiment of heaven-sent visions, but not a human habitation, not a site of temporary triumph by sail or steam, and not, most definitely not, a playground. It is instead a lonely place that lends itself to art and at times to thought.</p>
        <p>By the beautiful sea: The sea is the landscape at its most reductive -- ''ground'' below, horizon line in the middle, sky above. Yet it is infinitely changeable, and artistic responses to it, at least in this show, are almost as various as artists. Robert Adams traps for a moment the slippery, silver quality of light that jitters over dancing water. Tom Baril, whose toned prints look like images of metal, turns the ocean into Art Deco sculpture at its most rigorous.</p>
        <p>Thomas Joshua Cooper, photographing the largest whirlpool in Europe, focuses on the dark continuity and unfathomable forces that abide in long, slow revolutions of current and wisps of spume. Lynn Davis investigates the dramatic potential of an environment at once limited (nothing but sky and sea confined within a frame) and limitless.</p>
        <p>Tom Millea finds apocalypse hovering over the deep, Hiroshi Sugimoto examines the way that light rearranges an almost primitive memory of water below and sky above, Hiroshi Yamazaki studies the passage of time and light together across the sea. The images here document not so much the way the ocean looks as the way a few sensibilities wish to see it. The sea is converted into visions of isolation, preternatural calm, glory, agitation.</p>
        <p>Since fairly early in this century, photographers tended to look on the sea as an invitation to modernism. Edward Weston isolated linear patterns in the surf and the kelp on the shore. Ansel Adams, in one of his most brilliant works, a five-part sequence of the surf seen from above, injected time into abstraction. Harry Callahan went to the seaside to investigate ''the edge of nothingness,'' the endless emptiness of sky and sea and sand. ''Sea Change'' is about more contemporary reactions to ocean and shore.</p>
        <p>It is lucky for us that the oceans that so dominate the earth are so beautiful. (Brassai, the photographer, said that beauty is not the intent of creation but the reward.) Unfathomable and unconquerable the seas are too, yet, as the catalogue for ''Sea Change'' points out, they are in great danger. If man succeeds in conquering them with rising temperatures, pollution, garbage and overfishing, we will have conquered the planet and lost it. Sea levels could rise like the biblical flood. Sea life from plankton to coral to fish is already in trouble.</p>
        <p>Photographers who photograph the landscape today find no shortage of ugliness to photograph -- strip mines, clear cuts, overdevelopment, eyesores. Yet the sea remains lovely in decline, and even ecologically minded photographers are forced to confront its persistent beauty. Oil spills are the obvious exception and black-slicked sea birds the obvious signs, but no one can photograph the decrease in plankton or oxygen in the water. Beauty is suffering but shining still.</p>
        <p>You and I, you and I: Even the Hamptons know that the sea can vent its wrath on the land; still, no one ceases to love the beach. Surely one reason is that life long ago crawled out of the sea and began the land voyage that ultimately brought about human beings. The sea is the ancient mother; the 84 mineral elements in the human body are the same as the 84 in the ocean. The human body shelters its own sea, being about 65 percent water, while the earth's surface is about 70 percent. What's more, the body's saline content is comparable to the ocean's, another bit of evidence of a long-ago relationship.</p>
        <p>Oh how happy we'll be: One thing is certain, though not susceptible to scientific proof: the ocean is awesome, beautiful and eternally capable of provoking an emotional response. Photographs of it therefore start with an advantage, and much of ''Sea Change'' takes off from there. No breeze, no sound of surf, no sand flies or dangers of ultraviolet radiation either; just the sea at some pared-down level of purity and grace. Not, distinctly not, as beautiful as the ocean itself, ''Sea Change'' is still a day at the beach.</p>
        <p>''Sea Change: The Seascape in Contemporary Photography,'' organized by the Center for Creative Photography, University of Arizona in Tucson, is at the International Center of Photography, 1130 Fifth Avenue, at 94th Street, (212) 860-1777, through Sept. 26.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
