<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Adds Bars to Make a Large Sport Vehicle Safer</title>
    <meta content="Y27TRU$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1088203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Motoring</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Safety Features and Defects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E5DD153CF934A15751C0A96F958260" item-length="1314" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Adds Bars to Make a Large Sport Vehicle Safer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich., Feb. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co, in first design change to make rising number of huge sport utility vehicles safer in crashes with cars, will mount hollow steel bars below front and rear bumpers of its new Excursion model to keep vehicle from riding over cars; Ford says its largest SUV ever, set to go on sale in fall, will meet California's criteria for low-emission light trucks; safety and environmental advocates are still critical of model, noting it is likely to do tremendous damage in crash and has gas mileage as low as 10 miles per gallon; photos; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company today introduced the first design change to make the rising number of huge sport utility vehicles a little safer in crashes with cars. It said its newest sport utility vehicle, a behemoth that would be the tallest and heaviest yet, would be equipped with hollow steel bars mounted below the front and rear bumpers to prevent it from riding over cars during collisions.</p>
        <p>The horizontal steel beams hang down six inches from the high-riding steel frame of the vehicle, the Ford Excursion, which is nearly seven feet tall and weighs more than three tons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company today introduced the first design change to make the rising number of huge sport utility vehicles a little safer in crashes with cars. It said its newest sport utility vehicle, a behemoth that would be the tallest and heaviest yet, would be equipped with hollow steel bars mounted below the front and rear bumpers to prevent it from riding over cars during collisions.</p>
        <p>The horizontal steel beams hang down six inches from the high-riding steel frame of the vehicle, the Ford Excursion, which is nearly seven feet tall and weighs more than three tons.</p>
        <p>Priya Prasad, Ford's top safety researcher, said that if an Excursion without the steel beams collided with the front of a Ford Taurus when both  vehicles were traveling at 30 miles an hour, the Excursion would ride up over the Taurus's hood, crushing it. The Excursion's grille would then strike the base of the Taurus's windshield, causing tremendous damage to the passenger compartment, as Mr. Prasad illustrated with a videotape of a computer simulation of such a crash.</p>
        <p>But with the steel beam in front, the Excursion would crush the Taurus's front end only as far back as the front wheels and would not ride over it, leaving the passenger compartment of the Taurus relatively intact, Mr. Prasad said.</p>
        <p>The hollow steel beams are designed to bend and absorb energy in a crash, and are mounted about 18 inches from the ground, the height of a car bumper as well as the strongest part of a car's body. They should also reduce somewhat the risk that the Excursion will ride over a car that it hits in the side or the rear and reduce the risk of a car sliding under the vehicle when it is hit.</p>
        <p>Any family car hit by an Excursion is still likely to have heavy damage. Collisions between mismatched vehicles are unusually deadly, and Mr. Prasad said in an interview last April that weight differences caused 60 percent to 90 percent of the extra deaths and injuries in collisions between mismatched vehicles. But British researchers have estimated that height differences, which Ford is trying to address, account for three-quarters of the extra damage.</p>
        <p>All Excursions sold in the United States will also meet California's criteria for labeling as low-emissions light trucks, Ford officials confirmed today. This air pollution standard is roughly comparable to current Federal standards for tailpipe emissions from cars.</p>
        <p>Ford announced in January 1998  that it would voluntarily build all current and future sport utility vehicle models, including the Excursion, to meet the California standard rather than continue to use a loophole in Federal regulations that allows sport utility vehicles to pollute nearly three times as much as cars.</p>
        <p>Safety and environmental advocates today were still critical of the Excursion, which will go on sale in the fall. Safety experts said that the vehicle weighed twice as much as a midsized car and was still likely to do tremendous damage in a crash. The Excursion is also built on a stiff, unyielding, pickup-truck underbody  originally designed to carry cargo.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists said the Excursion's low gas mileage -- as little as 10 miles per gallon in the city with the V-10 engine -- would contribute to global warming and oil exploration in fragile wildernesses. The Excursion, which has a 44-gallon fuel tank, has three rows of seats that can seat nine, along with as much cargo room behind the third row as the combined trunk space of three average cars.</p>
        <p>The Excursion is not only long and tall but wide -- 80 inches wide, 3.3 inches wider than a Chevrolet Suburban. If the Excursion were even a fraction of an inch wider, it would be required by Federal regulations to carry special running lights on the roof and the sides as an extra-wide vehicle, said Dan Holden, the vehicle's body engineering manager.</p>
        <p>Ford has not yet set a price for the Excursion, but auto analysts expect it to cost close to $50,000.</p>
        <p>The Excursion's steel bars and low tailpipe emissions represent a sharp shift over the last two years in safety and environmental policies at Ford, the world's leading maker of sport utility vehicles. In an interview in October 1997, eight Ford managers contended that sport utility vehicles did not pose extra safety or environmental hazards.</p>
        <p>Paul Mayer, the engineering supervisor who oversaw the development of the steel beams, said today that the design for the rear beam had been approved in late 1997, and the front beam's design was completed during the first quarter of 1998. Ford also lowered the front end of the Excursion an inch by adjusting the suspension, making it less dangerous to cars and easier to enter, he said.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Flake, a Ford spokeswoman, said the company decided in the fall of 1997 that something had to be done to reduce the risk that the Excursion would ride over cars. Helen Petrauskas, Ford's vice president for safety and environmental issues, said articles in The New York Times in 1997 about the safety of sport utility vehicles and other light trucks  played a large role in persuading Ford to act. ''I've got to believe it gave it a big impetus,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Excursion's front bar is new, while the rear bar is a trailer-hitch bar from existing pickup trucks that will be lowered for safety reasons.</p>
        <p>Ford's announcement today came three days before a conference in Detroit at which safety regulators are expected to blame mismatches between cars and sport utility vehicles and other light trucks for thousands of deaths.</p>
        <p>According to Federal safety regulators, a sport utility vehicle is nearly three times as likely as a car to kill the other driver in a crash. But this does not mean sport utility vehicles are safer for their own occupants: According to the Insurance Institute for Highway Safety, which is supported by insurers trying to reduce accident costs, sport utility vehicles actually have a higher death rate for their occupants than cars of similar weight, because the sport utility vehicles roll over more often when they hit curbs, guardrails and other vehicles. Only the biggest and heaviest sport utility vehicles have roughly the same death rates for their occupants as large cars and mini-vans.</p>
        <p>Today's announcement marks an extraordinary shift in how American auto makers approach the design of sport utility vehicles, their most profitable product. Until now, most auto engineers focused only on making each vehicle as safe as possible for its own occupants and did not look at minimizing injuries to occupants in other vehicles during crashes.</p>
        <p>Ford officials said they would consider mounting similar steel beams on other models. But they added that even the Ford Expedition and Lincoln Navigator, both full-sized sport utility vehicles, did not ride as high as the Excursion and therefore might not need the new devices.</p>
        <p>Robert Lange, vehicle safety director for General Motors, said  G.M.'s Suburbans, currently the biggest sport utility vehicles on the road, rode lower than an Expedition or Navigator and did not require special devices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
