<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Unbuttoning of Al Gore: Act 1</title>
    <meta content="Y15GOR$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1115558"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EED71038F936A25755C0A96F958260" item-length="1952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Unbuttoning of Al Gore: Act 1</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>CONCORD, N.H.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series The Contenders: Running Toward 2000 focuses on Vice Pres Al Gore's Presidential drive; notes Gore, despite switch to more casual attire on Pres Clinton's instructions, still seems formal and stiff and oddly unprepared for role; Gore is largely unknown to voters, even though he has taken stands on far more topics than other candidates; his supporters see official announcement of candidacy giving him chance to emerge from Clinton's shadow and begin to define himself; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore is walking up the path to a home here where 40 people have gathered to listen to his pitch. He has shed his blue suit (as per President Clinton's instructions) for a green polo shirt, khakis and cowboy boots. Spotting his host, who is wearing a tie and sports jacket, Mr. Gore calls out, ''I hope I'm not too informal!''</p>
        <p>That may be wishful thinking. Even in his casual, earth-tone clothes, Al Gore seems pressed and starched. His language has that same formal quality. ''I want to engage in a dialogue with you,'' he begins, then jumps straight to what he alerts his audience is ''my punch line: I want to be President and I need your support.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore is walking up the path to a home here where 40 people have gathered to listen to his pitch. He has shed his blue suit (as per President Clinton's instructions) for a green polo shirt, khakis and cowboy boots. Spotting his host, who is wearing a tie and sports jacket, Mr. Gore calls out, ''I hope I'm not too informal!''</p>
        <p>That may be wishful thinking. Even in his casual, earth-tone clothes, Al Gore seems pressed and starched. His language has that same formal quality. ''I want to engage in a dialogue with you,'' he begins, then jumps straight to what he alerts his audience is ''my punch line: I want to be President and I need your support.''</p>
        <p>As he sets the stage for the official announcement of his candidacy on Wednesday in Tennessee, Vice President Gore still seems to be painting by numbers, following the chalk while he is learning to dance, telling his audience as much as reminding himself exactly what he is doing and why.</p>
        <p>For all of his years of practice for the 2000 election -- he was groomed in a political family in Washington, has already run for President once and has understudied with a political master for the last seven years -- Mr. Gore seems oddly unprepared for it.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Mr. Gore probably has a more extensive record on issues than anyone else running for President. From his votes in 16 years in Congress, his authorship of a book on global warming and more than six years as Mr. Clinton's Vice President, Mr. Gore has had to take specific stands on hundreds of topics -- abortion rights, ethanol subsidies, trade with China (he favors them all) -- in a way that few other candidates have.</p>
        <p>Still, voters do not know who Mr. Gore is and what he is about -- his pollster Mark Penn calls him ''famous but unknown.''</p>
        <p>His campaign hopes to change that on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The Gore camp views the announcement speech as an opportunity for Mr. Gore to emerge from Mr. Clinton's shadow and begin to define himself. The speech also gives him the chance to try to close the book on a period in which most of the information seeping out about Mr. Gore has been negative: his exaggerated claims about creating the Internet, his questionable money-gathering at a Buddhist temple, his steadfastness toward Mr. Clinton during the impeachment proceedings.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most important, it gives him a chance to present himself in human terms -- he will talk a lot about himself and his family -- and to try to overcome the perception that he is a wooden technocrat, or, in the word that most people said in a Pew poll was the one that immediately came to mind when asked about Mr. Gore, ''boring.''</p>
        <p>''With our announcement, we are now in the next phase of our campaign,'' Tony Coelho, the former California Congressman now in the saddle at Gore headquarters, said in an interview. ''The Vice President will be dealing directly with the American people on specific issues.''</p>
        <p>It is highly unusual for a Presidential candidate to get as specific as Mr. Gore intends to this early in a campaign. But Gore aides believe this will help the Vice President separate himself from Mr. Clinton and show up the weaknesses in the two rivals he is most worried about, former Senator Bill Bradley of New Jersey on the Democratic side and  Gov. George W. Bush of Texas  among the Republicans.</p>
        <p>While he has adhered to President Clinton's policies, Mr. Gore is starting to put his own stamp on certain issues. He has given a speech on education and called for universal preschool. He wants to increase the Federal Government's reliance on religious institutions to help with social programs, like drug treatment. He wants to revive the fight for health-care coverage for people without insurance. He wants to limit suburban sprawl and traffic jams as part of what he calls his ''livability agenda.'' And he will be giving policy speeches regularly from here on out.</p>
        <p>''The most important thing,'' Mr. Coelho said, ''is for Al Gore to say who he is before the Republicans say who he is and before Bradley says who he is, and to have the American people relate to him.''</p>
        <p>The strategy is also intended to smoke out Mr. Bush, whose inaugural speeches this week have been broadly thematic. By being specific on issues like gun control and abortion, the theory goes, Mr. Gore will force Mr. Bush to take positions that might reveal him to be more conservative than swing voters are willing to tolerate. If Mr. Bush avoids being specific, the Gore camp says, he will appear inexperienced and unprepared to lead the country.</p>
        <p>Specificity also helps Mr. Gore distinguish himself from President Clinton, which is a tricky task. He wants to bask in Mr. Clinton's successes but distance himself from the President's failures.</p>
        <p>The glaring Clinton success is the economy. Mr. Gore is running as the man who can continue the prosperity of the Clinton years. ''We know what works,'' he assures audiences.</p>
        <p>The glaring Clinton failure is the character issue, including the extramarital activities that led to his impeachment. Pollsters say that ''Clinton fatigue,'' a weariness with the  scandals, has been sapping energy from the Gore candidacy.</p>
        <p>To counteract that, Gore advisers said the Vice President would emphasize his family-man credentials -- married 29 years, father of four, expectant grandfather. To reinforce the message, Mr. Coelho said, Mr. Gore is to appear on the ABC News program ''20/20'' on Wednesday, the day of his announcement speech, and make it clear that he disapproved of Mr. Clinton's personal behavior.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was once hesitant to criticize his boss in public. Forced by reporters to confront the issue of the President's behavior in September, Mr. Gore would use only Mr. Clinton's own words, ''I agree with him that it's indefensible.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is perhaps best remembered for declaring Mr. Clinton a great President on the December day that the House voted to impeach him. The Gore campaign would like to erase that image and make it clear that Mr. Gore condemns the behavior that led to it.</p>
        <p>Marla Romash, the deputy campaign manager, said that most people do not know much about Mr. Gore and that at the top of her list of qualities was this: ''He's a loving father.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is mentioning his wife, Tipper, at every turn. This helps him solidify the family image, puts some personality on his blank slate and is intended to help him connect with women. As Mr. Gore told his audience here, he had to cancel their anniversary dinner last month because he needed to break a tie vote in the Senate on a gun-control measure -- which, he added, was fine with his wife. ''She is, if anything, more anti-gun than I am,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In its increasingly extensive use of Mrs. Gore, the campaign is also presenting her, subliminally, as the anti-Hillary. She has said she would not be the same kind of First Lady as Hillary Rodham Clinton. She has acknowledged a bout of depression, giving her an air of vulnerability and casting the Gore family as close-knit and caring. The Gores have let it be known that in the impeachment ordeal, while Mr. Gore was backing the President, Mrs. Gore was unforgiving.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton may be a drag on the character issue, but oddly, his widely acknowledged political skills have also taken a toll on his Vice President. The concern goes beyond Vice Presidentialitis, an infectious disease usually caught by standing in the draft of a Commander in Chief. Most people appear clumsy next to Mr. Clinton, and Mr. Gore is no exception. A recent joint engagement in Texas proved such a disaster for Mr. Gore that the campaign is now on high alert to keep him and his mentor from sharing a stage.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers say that his difficulty in establishing a persona has been aggravated by his running in a vacuum, against himself rather than an identifiable opponent with vulnerabilities to be exploited.</p>
        <p>''Not only has Gore been running in a vacuum, but you have the reflection of Bill Clinton,'' one Gore adviser lamented. ''We're being compared to the absolute best.''</p>
        <p>Doug Sosnick, a senior adviser to Mr. Clinton, put it a little differently. ''Gore has been running so far against two perfect people -- Clinton, whose skills as a candidate are taking on mythic proportions, and Greta Garbo,'' he said, referring to Governor Bush's ability to appeal to voters without saying much.</p>
        <p>The campaign has been reluctant so far to acknowledge Mr. Bradley, Mr. Gore's only rival for the Democratic nomination. But this is proving harder as Mr. Gore finds he still needs to court certain audiences, including union workers and Iowa Democrats, who are pleased to have an alternative.</p>
        <p>''They're struggling with whether to engage Bradley,'' said Bill Carrick, a Democratic consultant based in Los Angeles. ''Do you raise his stature, or ignore him and hope he doesn't get traction? That causes some indecisiveness.''</p>
        <p>Gore aides take solace in his strong showing in early polls testing him against Mr. Bradley. But the picture turns darker when Mr. Gore is matched against Mr. Bush. Voters know little about Mr. Bush, but he leads Mr. Gore in public opinion polls. A recent Newsweek survey found that Mr. Bush was favored by 54 percent of voters, compared with  36 percent for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>By large margins, voters say Mr. Bush is more of a leader than Mr. Gore, more inspiring, has a better moral character and is more able to get things done. The Governor polls ahead of the Vice President across every category of voter, most alarmingly among the elderly and women, two bedrock Democratic constituencies without whom the Democrats cannot win.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats worry that Mr. Bush's talk of ''compassionate conservativism'' will blur the ideological lines and magnify Mr. Gore's weaknesses.</p>
        <p>''The biggest problem facing Al Gore is the fact that people see him as a politician, through and through,'' one Democratic consultant said. ''It's not that he's not smart or doesn't understand where America is at,'' the consultant said.</p>
        <p>Senator Charles E. Schumer, Democrat of New York, said he had told Mr. Gore he was putting too much emphasis on things like endorsements from elected officials. ''People see him as more of a politician than he really is,'' Mr. Schumer said. ''But he's a substantive, policy-oriented guy, and I think that's going to come through.'' Mr. Coelho also dismisses the personality factor, saying the public is not looking for ''a drinking buddy'' but someone with experience. Still, he said he was considering enlisting Michael Sheehan, a debate coach for numerous Democratic politicians, including Mr. Clinton. ''I'm trying to bring Michael back in,'' Mr. Coelho said. ''He's good at identifying certain situations. But I want Al Gore to be Al Gore. If you start to let the computer in your head dictate what you should do, then you lose your heart.''</p>
        <p>It is Al Gore's heart, his campaign says, that will be on display this week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
