<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Offers a More 'Livable World' With Some Tinkering</title>
    <meta content="16GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1092858"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iowa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Iowa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E6D9113EF935A25750C0A96F958260" item-length="1185" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Offers a More 'Livable World' With Some Tinkering</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>DES MOINES, March 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, who is not expected to announce his Presidential candidacy until later in year, visits New Hampshire and Iowa in his first official campaign trip paid for by his election committee; Gore lays out platform for his candidacy, appealing to harried suburbanites and promising to create more 'livable world' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore began laying out a platform today for his all-but-announced Presidential candidacy, appealing to harried suburbanites and promising to create a more ''livable world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore offered a continuation of President Clinton's policies, with only minor tinkering. He said, for example, that he wanted to hire enough teachers to reduce the size of classes in all grades through high school, not just through eighth grade as Mr. Clinton has proposed. He also said that he wanted to make preschool education available in all public schools.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore began laying out a platform today for his all-but-announced Presidential candidacy, appealing to harried suburbanites and promising to create a more ''livable world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore offered a continuation of President Clinton's policies, with only minor tinkering. He said, for example, that he wanted to hire enough teachers to reduce the size of classes in all grades through high school, not just through eighth grade as Mr. Clinton has proposed. He also said that he wanted to make preschool education available in all public schools.</p>
        <p>But he did little to separate himself from his political benefactor today as he took one more step in his long, slow march toward a Presidential candidacy by taking his first official campaign trip, paid for by his election committee. He is not expected to announce his candidacy officially until later this year.</p>
        <p>''I want to build on the wisdom that we've all gained in the last several years,'' he said at a rally in snowbound New Hampshire before flying here, paying homage to the two states that vote the earliest in the primary process.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore put special emphasis on what he calls quality-of-life issues -- easing traffic congestion, for example -- that some have ridiculed as un-Presidential because they are local issues, but that he defends as integral to strengthening families by creating more free time. They are also aimed squarely at an important bloc of swing voters, especially frazzled parents, who live in the suburbs and could decide the next election.</p>
        <p>''The person who deserves to be our next President is the one who understands how tired working parents are,'' Mr. Gore said.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing the daily commutes get longer and longer,'' he said. ''And for people who don't think that it's a problem that parents are caught in traffic jams that are lengthening each day, I'll tell you, they haven't been in traffic jams and they don't know what it does to the desire to balance work and family.''</p>
        <p>He referred to the cultural battles that his wife, Tipper, fought over obscene song lyrics and said, ''The V-chip is just the beginning.'' As he told a crowd of about 100 people here, ''Let's be sensitive to the problems that real families have.''</p>
        <p>In an apparent response to criticism that he has focused too exclusively on upscale suburbanites, he made a pledge today on behalf of women and minorities. Citing the commitment of his late father, a Senator, to civil rights and of his mother to women's independence, he vowed to carry those crusades into the next century.</p>
        <p>For all of Mr. Gore's identification with the Clinton Administration, particularly the nation's economic prosperity, he seemed quite ambiguous about how strongly to associate himself with it. He did not mention Mr. Clinton by name, and he seemed to want to create distance by describing not a policy divide but an epochal divide -- a natural break in the calendar in the year 2000 that would leave Mr. Clinton in the past and put Mr. Gore in the future.</p>
        <p>''It's not only the beginning of a new century and a new millennium,'' Mr. Gore said. ''It's the beginning of a whole new era in human history.'' He said that posed a new set of challenges with ''new approaches for the new century.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has spent years building up an extensive financial, political and policy network across the country, and that in-place apparatus has gone a long way toward clearing the field of primary challengers.</p>
        <p>Today he was accompanied by Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the House Democratic leader, who formally endorsed him in what the two billed as a strong sign of party unity. Bill Bradley, the former Senator from New Jersey, is the only Democrat who has entered the race, and the polls strongly favor Mr. Gore over him for the party's nomination.</p>
        <p>But the polls are less encouraging for Mr. Gore in hypothetical match-ups against various Republicans, suggesting serious vulnerabilities in the Gore candidacy. The latest NBC/ Wall Street Journal poll showed him 18 points behind Gov. George W. Bush of Texas and 15 points behind Elizabeth Dole, the two leading Republicans.</p>
        <p>Judith Hope, the Democratic chairwoman in New York, last week openly questioned whether Mr. Gore would be the party's best nominee, noting that Democratic Vice Presidents who have sought the Presidency have tended to lose.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's media consultant, Bob Squier, said that Mr. Gore was flagging in the polls because he was still being perceived as Vice President. ''He is not thought of in Presidential terms,'' Mr. Squier said, suggesting that campaign forays like today's, which drew the biggest press contingent of Mr. Gore's tenure, would start to change that perception.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore sidestepped questions about whether he was too closely linked with the impeached President. He said the campaign would be about ideas, not polls.</p>
        <p>But Gore aides admit that he is using a series of narrowly focused, poll-tested initiatives, reminiscent of some of Mr. Clinton's micro-proposals in 1996, to appeal to voters.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Clinton off in Central America last week, the Vice President used the empty stage of the White House almost every day to discuss topics including traffic jams, drug labels and lost bags at airports.</p>
        <p>Aides even imitated the Clinton strategy of targeting their announcements to certain media venues to insure maximum, and sympathetic, exposure. For example, at last week's announcement on ways to ease traffic congestion, they invited  traffic reporters, those who ride the choppers and describe road conditions. This guaranteed the Vice President media coverage in local markets across the country and on drive-time radio, much as Mr. Clinton in 1997 insured heavy attention for his conference on global warming by inviting more than 100 local weather forecasters to cover it.</p>
        <p>Republicans have poked fun at Mr. Gore for directing a Presidential campaign to such seemingly small issues as lost bags at airports and such seemingly local issues as traffic congestion. Jim Nicholson, chairman of the Republican National Committee, has been particularly scathing, accusing Mr. Gore of trying to ''do away with the internal combustion engine, the automobile,'' and calling him ''an apologist for the President; he's a wasteful dreamer.''</p>
        <p>Even an airline passenger, Jim Corsetty of Rockville, Md., whose plane was stranded on a runway and who found himself on stage with the Vice President last week, expressed his astonishment that he had become an anecdote in the Presidential campaign. He introduced the Vice President as ''my own personal consumer advocate.''</p>
        <p>But some Republicans think Mr. Gore might be on to something.</p>
        <p>Bill McInturff, a Republican pollster who is working for the Presidential campaign of Senator John McCain of Arizona, said that even if Mr. Gore was talking about ''microscopic'' issues and sounded as if he were running for town manager rather than President, he was still controlling the policy debate.</p>
        <p>''It's working,'' Mr. McInturff said with some exasperation. ''You're writing a story about Gore talking about lots of popular issues. But have we really so dumbed down the office that he can be talking about traffic?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
