<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Backtalk; Sports And Sex Are Always Together</title>
    <meta content="Y11LIPS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1122646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women's World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipsyte, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Cup (Soccer)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E3D7153CF932A25754C0A96F958260" item-length="805" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Backtalk; Sports And Sex Are Always Together</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT LIPSYTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipsyte, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert Lipsyte column on selling of</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In another time, I pitched a proposal on the sexual implications of sports to a magazine called Eros. The rejection letter came swiftly; the editor said there were no such implications because, as any fool could see, sports was pure sex in the first place.</p>
        <p>At the time (this was before two Yankee pitchers switched wives), I thought he overstated the situation. But now I'm wondering if he was on to something. At the least, sex has sold sports as subliminally as it has sold cars and beers, which in turn are sold by sports. More directly, if you start in this century with the promotion of the hypermasculine Babe Ruth and go on through the sexually ambiguous Babe Didrikson, the current selling of the American World Cup team as the babes of soccer seems like a logical arc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In another time, I pitched a proposal on the sexual implications of sports to a magazine called Eros. The rejection letter came swiftly; the editor said there were no such implications because, as any fool could see, sports was pure sex in the first place.</p>
        <p>At the time (this was before two Yankee pitchers switched wives), I thought he overstated the situation. But now I'm wondering if he was on to something. At the least, sex has sold sports as subliminally as it has sold cars and beers, which in turn are sold by sports. More directly, if you start in this century with the promotion of the hypermasculine Babe Ruth and go on through the sexually ambiguous Babe Didrikson, the current selling of the American World Cup team as the babes of soccer seems like a logical arc.</p>
        <p>Sexuality may be so intrinsic to sports that unless the audience is sexually comfortable, the game just won't sell.</p>
        <p>This doesn't mean that the players have to be sexually alluring. It just means that they can't be threatening. A lovely lesbian may be bad for business if you are pushing a traditional family package. Forget a gay man. Meanwhile, a female shot-putter who uses steroids that give her manly muscles and a mustache may so reinforce gender stereotypes that she threatens only her drug-free competitors. And the same goes for a wife-beating linebacker who feels whole only in the midst of a 'roid rage.</p>
        <p>There is a wonderful midland Babbittry to the selling of the World Cup team. The enthusiastic complicity of the players evokes the car washes and bake sales that many of them once ran to raise money for their youth traveling teams. They are on a mission, for their sport and for themselves, and if that means a little cheesecake (or a lot in at least one case), sacrifice is the name of the game.</p>
        <p>The implications here are not that the players are sexually available, but that they are ''normal,'' that they are proper role models for all the girls who will buy shoes and gear (and eventually cosmetics that won't run or cake late in the match?). For the World Cup team to crack into the male-dominated merchandising mart as a group and as individuals, they must dispel the aura of homosexuality that was hung on women's athleticism as a way of stifling their emerging physical and political power.</p>
        <p>There is, of course, a Faustian bargain here. Women's tennis had to sell cigarettes to survive; let another generation decide how many lung cancer casualties were worth that important cultural victory. Also, there is a betrayal of all the lesbians whose enormous contributions to many sports should not be forgotten in the hetero happy hours where soccer babes entertain potential sponsors; the so-called ''meet the shooters at your local Hooters'' syndrome.</p>
        <p>All this bubbles up in the same season that 18-year-old Alexandra Stevenson, who may be the future of tennis as well as of interracial relations, wowed us by becoming not only the first female qualifier to reach the semifinals at Wimbledon but also the first whose father was a legendary basketball player. After a Florida newspaper printed Alexandra's birth certificate, Julius Erving issued a statement acknowledging paternity.</p>
        <p>O.K., Editor Eros, there must have been sex here, too. And, naturally, there were agitated, if not hysterical reactions. There was justifiable concern that Erving's relationship with Samantha Stevenson, a pioneering sportswriter whose work has appeared in The New York Times, would be used as evidence against women's access to male games. There is no question that sleeping with a subject is unethical, a conflict of interest, although it seems healthier, at least more human, than many of the relationships between dominating male sports figures and sycophantic male sportswriters and broadcasters.</p>
        <p>It was these sycophants, more than athletes and coaches, who fought hardest to keep women out of press boxes, much less locker rooms. They were afraid that women would adulterate their testosterone moments, the mutual masculinity they fantasized in their same-sex access. Tell me there isn't sex in all this, too.</p>
        <p>Ah, well, having lusted in vain for Billie Jean King in the late 60's, I can take no moral high ground here. People who live in glass columns should probably not even turn over stones, much less throw them. And like any healthy sports fan of any gender or sexual orientation, I say the more flesh the better. What do you think male or female basketball, volleyball and ice skating are about? If the World Cup soccer babes are hot, let another generation worry about their impact on the sporting ozone layer.</p>
        <p>It's progress. The magazine Eros went out of business years ago, probably done in by Sports Illustrated.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
