<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="16OBSE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1092778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iron (Nutrient)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Scripps Institution of Oceanography</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Diet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oils and Fats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Age</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990316T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EFDF153EF935A25750C0A96F958260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article comments on technique for converting vegetable oil into diesel fuel; Japanese researchers report way of increasing iron content of rice that could help solve serious worldwide problem of iron deficiency; reseachers at Scripps Institution of Oceanography at University of California report warming preceeded increase in carbon dioxide in earth's atmosphere during transition period at end of last three ice ages; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From Fries to Fuel</p>
        <p>Diesel engines are hardly picky eaters. In addition to petroleum-based fuel, they will run, relatively cleanly, on just about any kind of vegetable oil. But a driver can't simply pour a bottle of Mazola into the tank. A bit of chemistry has to take place first.</p>
        <p>And there, alas, is the rub. Converting vegetable oil into diesel fuel takes time, can be done only in batches and creates a waste water problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From Fries to Fuel</p>
        <p>Diesel engines are hardly picky eaters. In addition to petroleum-based fuel, they will run, relatively cleanly, on just about any kind of vegetable oil. But a driver can't simply pour a bottle of Mazola into the tank. A bit of chemistry has to take place first.</p>
        <p>And there, alas, is the rub. Converting vegetable oil into diesel fuel takes time, can be done only in batches and creates a waste water problem.</p>
        <p>Now, researchers at the Idaho National Engineering and Environmental Laboratory, part of the Energy Department, have developed a technique that streamlines the process and results in less waste and what should be less expensive fuel.</p>
        <p>Like the older technique, it uses an acid or a base to catalyze the reaction of the oil and an alcohol, producing the diesel fuel and a byproduct, glycerol. But the acid or base in the new process is solid, not liquid, remaining separate from the reaction products and easy to recover. The new process can also run continuously, and the high quality glycerol produced is  valuable in its own right.</p>
        <p>For the researchers, who tested the technique on used vegetable oil from a local producer of french fried potatoes (this being Idaho, after all), the next step is to create a pilot project. They foresee a day when a food producer is able to convert its waste oil into diesel fuel for its trucks.</p>
        <p>Supercharged Rice</p>
        <p>It won't power an engine, but a way to give rice more of a kick for humans in the form of increased iron content has been figured out by researchers in Japan.</p>
        <p>Iron deficiency is a serious problem worldwide, particularly for people whose diet consists mostly of vegetables and grains.</p>
        <p>The researchers, reporting in the journal Nature Biotechnology, re-engineered the rice, transplanting a soybean gene responsible for producing ferritin, a complex compound that stores thousands of iron atoms in a central cavity. They also found a way to control production of the ferritin so that it ended up in the endosperm, the starchy part of the rice grain. The new rice contains up to three times the iron of ordinary rice, and a meal-sized portion may provide 30 to 50 percent of the adult daily requirement.</p>
        <p>Which Came First?</p>
        <p>The transition period at the end of an ice age is something of a dance, where a rise in world temperatures fox-trots with an increase in the greenhouse gas, carbon dioxide. The question has always been, which of the partners is leading?</p>
        <p>Researchers from the Scripps Institution of Oceanography at the University of California at San Diego think they know. Analyzing the carbon dioxide content in tiny air bubbles trapped in ancient Antarctic ice, and comparing the results with a temperature record, they have determined that the warming begins first.</p>
        <p>The researchers, reporting in the journal Science, studied transition periods of about 10,000 years at the end of the last three ice ages, 18,000, 135,000 and 240,000 years ago. They found that during the ice ages, carbon dioxide concentrations were about 180 to 200 parts per million. As the Earth warmed, the concentrations increased to 280 parts per million, but lagged behind the temperature rise by about 400 to 1,000 years.</p>
        <p>The warming, scientists believe, was touched off by changes in the earth's position relative to the sun. As the warming proceeded, organisms flourished, producing carbon dioxide through respiration and decay. The carbon dioxide trapped more heat in the atmosphere and amplified what would otherwise have been a relatively small warming.</p>
        <p>When the warmer periods ended and temperatures started cooling again, higher carbon dioxide levels persisted for a shorter or longer time, depending on the length of the warmer period.</p>
        <p>The longer the warm period, the scientists suggest, the more organisms flourish, and thus the more carbon dioxide there is to keep the levels high even as temperatures begin dropping again.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
