<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Briefing</title>
    <meta content="Y26BRI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1148305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E5D91438F935A15753C1A96F958260" item-length="982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">Compiled By Terence Neilan</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: EX-TERRORIST TO MOVE -- At Yasir Arafat's request, Prime Minister Ehud Barak is permitting the former terrorist leader of a militant Palestinian political faction to move from Damascus to the Palestinian-governed Gaza Strip and the West Bank. Nayef Hawatmeh, 63, left, who as head of the Democratic Front for the Liberation of Palestine was held responsible for the killing of 24 Israeli schoolchildren in 1974, says he has renounced violence and wants to take part in politics in the Palestinian Authority.</p>
        <p>William A. Orme Jr. (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MIDDLE EAST</p>
        <p>ISRAEL: EX-TERRORIST TO MOVE -- At Yasir Arafat's request, Prime Minister Ehud Barak is permitting the former terrorist leader of a militant Palestinian political faction to move from Damascus to the Palestinian-governed Gaza Strip and the West Bank. Nayef Hawatmeh, 63, left, who as head of the Democratic Front for the Liberation of Palestine was held responsible for the killing of 24 Israeli schoolchildren in 1974, says he has renounced violence and wants to take part in politics in the Palestinian Authority.</p>
        <p>William A. Orme Jr. (NYT)</p>
        <p>TUNISIA: PRESIDENT RE-ELECTED -- In a result that was never in doubt, President Zine al-Abidine Ben Ali won a third five-year term with nearly 100 percent of the vote, official results showed. Mr. Ben Ali, 62, won 3,269,000 out of 3,287,000 votes cast, Interior Minister Ali Chaouch said. For the first time, two token opposition candidates took part. They got a combined total of just over one half of 1 percent of the votes cast.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>IRAQ: U.S. JETS ATTACK -- American jets patrolling the no-flight zone over northern Iraq bombed an Iraqi missile storage center south of Mosul in response to Iraqi antiaircraft fire, the United States military said. According to an Iraqi spokesman, two people were killed and seven were wounded.</p>
        <p>(AP, Agence France-Pressse)</p>
        <p>EUROPE</p>
        <p>NORTHERN IRELAND: RENEWED OPTIMISM -- Intensified talks in Belfast to break the impasse that has blocked progress in putting the peace accord into place produced guarded expressions of hope for a breakthrough this week when former Senator George J. Mitchell returns to finish his formal review. An Ulster Unionist negotiator, Alan McFarland, said, ''There is a degree of trust creeping in'' between his party and Sinn Fein, the political wing of the I.R.A.</p>
        <p>Warren Hoge (NYT)</p>
        <p>SPAIN: KEY BASQUE DETAINED -- The French police arrested Belen Gonzalez Penalva, whom authorities say represented the Basque separatist group E.T.A. at the only peace talks, held last May, with the Spanish Government since they declared a cease-fire 13 months ago. Her arrest came a day after the rebels announced tougher demands for resuming the stalled peace talks, insisting that Madrid must first agree to Basque self-determination and the withdrawal of all state security forces from the region. The Government dismissed the initiative as propaganda.</p>
        <p>Al Goodman (NYT)</p>
        <p>GERMANY: 'GREENHOUSE' MEETING -- Representatives from 168 countries opened a two-week conference in Bonn intended to cut emissions of so-called greenhouse gases blamed for global warming. They will discuss a timetable for carrying out the agreement reached at the 1997 United Nations conference in Kyoto, Japan, which set global standards for reducing pollution, including a cut in greenhouse emissions by 5.2 percent for industrialized nations from 1990 levels by 2008-2012.</p>
        <p>Victor Homola (NYT)</p>
        <p>BOSNIA: SUSPECT SEIZED -- NATO-led peacekeeping troops in Bosnia detained a suspected Bosnian Serb war criminal, Damir Dosen, who is under indictment for crimes against humanity. A NATO statement issued in Brussels said Mr. Dosen would be transferred to the International Criminal Tribunal for the Former Yugoslavia at The Hague. It said he was shift commander in 1992 at a camp outside Prijedor, where detainees were ''killed, sexually assaulted, tortured, beaten and otherwise subjected to cruel and inhuman treatment.''</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>AFRICA</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA: NOT GUILTY PLEA -- Dr. Walter Basson, the head of chemical warfare under the apartheid-era Government, pleaded not guilty to 61 criminal charges, including conspiracy to murder, fraud and drug dealing. Six murder charges against him have already been dismissed because those killings took place outside South Africa. Dr. Basson still faces 16 counts of murder and his trial is expected to last two years.</p>
        <p>Rachel L. Swarns (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE AMERICAS</p>
        <p>MEXICO: TOP REBEL SEIZED -- The recently-formed federal police said it captured the top commander of a guerrilla group operating in the violence-torn state of Guerrero. Jacobo Silva Nogales, known as Commander Antonio, was arrested in the state capital, Chilpancingo, along with three other people accused of leading the Revolutionary Army of the Insurgent People. The year-old group has carried out a string of armed attacks on Government troops.</p>
        <p>Julia Preston (NYT)</p>
        <p>VENEZUELA: CONTENTIOUS CLAUSE -- The assembly drawing up a new constitution expected to significantly expand the powers of President Hugo Chavez has approved a clause that would require all news organizations to publish only ''truthful and impartial'' information and guarantee anyone mentioned in a news report the right to a rebuttal. Critics in Venezuela and abroad have condemned the measure, saying it would give Mr. Chavez and his followers the power to silence opponents and could lead to censorship.</p>
        <p>Larry Rohter (NYT)</p>
        <p>ASIA</p>
        <p>HONG KONG: IMMIGRATION REVISITED -- Five months after it was reversed by Beijing on a landmark immigration ruling, the highest court in Hong Kong began hearing an appeal by 17 mainland Chinese who claim they have the right to live in the territory. The mainland Chinese claim their right under a January ruling by the court. That ruling was overturned by Beijing, and legal experts said the court will have to rule on the validity of that action in deciding on those claims.</p>
        <p>Mark Landler (NYT)</p>
        <p>INDIA: PARLIAMENT OPENED -- President K. R. Narayanan opened Parliament with a pledge that ''bold strategy'' would be used in economic reforms, pledging the creation of 10 million jobs each year. Among a broad outline of policies, he mentioned speedier disinvestment of state-owned companies, improved infrastructure and banking reforms.</p>
        <p>Barry Bearak (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
