<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Big Heat</title>
    <meta content="11RYBCZYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1122383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rybczynski, Witold</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Christianson, Gale E (Prof)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Greenhouse: The 200-Year Story of Global Warming (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD6173DF932A25754C0A96F958260" item-length="666" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Big Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Witold Rybczynski</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rybczynski, Witold</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Witold Rybczynski reviews book Greenhouse: The 200-Year Story of Global Warming by Gale E Christianson</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GREENHOUSE</p>
        <p>The 200-Year Story</p>
        <p>of Global Warming.</p>
        <p>By Gale E. Christianson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 305 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Walker &amp; Company. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GREENHOUSE</p>
        <p>The 200-Year Story</p>
        <p>of Global Warming.</p>
        <p>By Gale E. Christianson.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 305 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Walker &amp; Company. $25.</p>
        <p>Gale E. Christianson, who has written biographies of Loren Eiseley and Edwin Hubble, calls his interesting new book ''the biography of an idea.'' The idea is global warming. Can such a topical subject really have a biography? Christianson makes a convincing case that it can. He traces the evolution of both the scientific thinking that slowly led to an understanding of the phenomenon of global warming and the technologies that were, and are, its cause.</p>
        <p>''Greenhouse'' spans 200 years in an epic sweep, with a cast of characters to match -- from Baron Jean-Baptiste-Joseph de Fourier, the French mathematician who in 1824 hypothesized that the earth's atmosphere was a thermal envelope that he likened to a bell jar, to the American chemist Charles Keeling, who in 1955 accidentally discovered that carbon dioxide levels in the atmosphere were rising. It was another chemist, Svante August Arrhenius, the winner of the Nobel Prize in 1903 for his work on electrolysis, who coined the term ''hothouse.'' He speculated that burning fossil fuels would eventually cause atmospheric carbon dioxide to double, leading to warmer weather. The Swede viewed the prospect without alarm: an increase in temperature would ''allow our descendants, even if they only be those of a distant future, to live under a warmer sky and in a less harsh environment than we were granted.''</p>
        <p>A fascinating aspect of Christianson's account is the way that the evidence of global warming is differently understood at different times. It's a reminder that while science may be objective, the interpretation of science is not. Moreover, interpretation is usually conditioned by the technological alternatives at hand. This is the other side of global warming -- the supply side, so to speak. It is represented by King James I of England, who popularized anthracite (a clean-burning alternative to bituminous coal); Abraham Darby, who discovered how to use coke in blast furnaces; Thomas Newcomen, who built the first successful steam engine; and of course Henry Ford, who popularized the premier fossil fuel-burning device, the automobile.</p>
        <p>Christianson, who teaches history at Indiana State University, resists the temptation to demonize. Many inventions that drew mankind closer to the environmental brink seemed, at first, to improve our living condition. Thomas Midgley Jr. was a chemist with the General Motors Research Corporation whose ''genius for benign invention'' was celebrated. During World War I, Midgley developed a tetraethyl lead antiknock agent that raised compression ratios in airplane engines; subsequently, lead was routinely added to automobile gasoline. Midgley was not done. Seeking a replacement for poisonous sulfur dioxide, then used as a cooling agent in refrigerators, he discovered a new family of compounds that he called chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's. Decades later, scientists identified the effects of lead on humans, and of CFC's on stratospheric ozone.</p>
        <p>The final chapters of ''Greenhouse'' are the least captivating. Perhaps we are simply more familiar with the destruction of the Brazilian rain forest, El Nino and the shrill political and scientific debates over global warming. Christianson, who comes down firmly on the side of urgency, is an evenhanded guide who does not preach. ''No matter which way the dice fall,'' he writes, ''it is science and not personal conviction that will have the last word.''</p>
        <p>This is an oddly stimulating book that sometimes suggests a public television documentary. Images flit by, historical characters make sudden entries and equally sudden exits. There is a chilling chapter on the effect of climate change on the Anasazi of the Southwest, the vikings and the Dust Bowl Okies. We learn about London fog and Los Angeles smog, about climatological modeling and about the Victorian technology of building tall chimneys. But if you can get beyond this jumpy format, you will be rewarded by a fascinating if alarming story.</p>
        <p>Witold Rybczynski's latest book is ''A Clearing in the Distance: Frederick Law Olmsted and America in the Nineteenth Century.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Witold Rybczynski's latest book is ''A Clearing in the Distance: Frederick Law Olmsted and America in the Nineteenth Century.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
