<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spacecraft Speed to Mars, High Hopes on Board</title>
    <meta content="05MARS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1074738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Climate Orbiter</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Polar  Lander (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Life, Extraterrestrial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E5DB173EF936A35752C0A96F958260" item-length="1601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spacecraft Speed to Mars, High Hopes on Board</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two new spacecraft are heading for Mars as part of 16-year effort to determine once and for all if life ever arose on red planet; Mars Climate Orbiter was launched from Florida from Dec 11, and Mars Polar Lander followed on Jan 3; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fresh off the launching pad, two new spacecraft are heading for Mars as part of a 16-year effort to determine once and for all if life ever arose on the red planet. The two probes make up a second wave of inquiry, the first having begun in 1996.</p>
        <p>The question of whether Mars harbors life was first asked centuries ago when astronomers turned increasingly powerful telescopes on the heavens and found that the reddish planet has seasons, icy poles and other Earthlike features. Such similarities have made Mars the main place in the solar system to look for signs of extraterrestrial life. So far, however, no convincing evidence has come to light.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fresh off the launching pad, two new spacecraft are heading for Mars as part of a 16-year effort to determine once and for all if life ever arose on the red planet. The two probes make up a second wave of inquiry, the first having begun in 1996.</p>
        <p>The question of whether Mars harbors life was first asked centuries ago when astronomers turned increasingly powerful telescopes on the heavens and found that the reddish planet has seasons, icy poles and other Earthlike features. Such similarities have made Mars the main place in the solar system to look for signs of extraterrestrial life. So far, however, no convincing evidence has come to light.</p>
        <p>The Mars Climate Orbiter was launched from Florida on Dec. 11, and the Mars Polar Lander followed on Sunday. Both were designed by the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif. The pair, which cost the National Aeronautics and Space Administration $357 million to build, launch and run, are to arrive at the red planet this September and December.</p>
        <p>While unlikely to top the Mars Pathfinder rover in terms of action and spectacle, which riveted millions of computer and television viewers in July 1997, the pair of spacecraft are meant to advance the exploratory hunt in important ways. For instance, the lander spacecraft is to probe deep beneath the Martian surface in search of water, which is considered the crucial ingredient for life.</p>
        <p>Over at least 16 years, and perhaps longer, the new explorations of Mars are to involve more than a dozen spacecraft, thousands of scientists and billions of dollars.</p>
        <p>Only once before has the United States fixed its powers so intently on a single planetary body -- the Moon. That series of spacecraft included the Rangers, Surveyors and Apollos, each one more ambitious than its predecessor. The effort culminated in manned landings from 1969 to 1972.</p>
        <p>In contrast, exploration of the planets evolved haphazardly over the decades as American probes flew to Mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn and beyond.</p>
        <p>The piecemeal nature ofthese projects caused designers to make each craft big and costly, and that often inadvertently left them vulnerable to political whims and uncertainties.</p>
        <p>''The people involved thought they'd never go again, so they'd put on every possible instrument,'' said Dr. Bruce C. Murray, a former director of the Jet Propulsion Laboratory and now a scientist at the California Institute of Technology. ''Missions got too complicated, and cost too much, because there was a feeling there was no tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>''We were the victim of the next program we had to sell,'' Daniel S. Goldin, the NASA Administrator, said of previous decades. ''Now we have a vision and a strategy.''</p>
        <p>The new Mars undertaking involves a series of relatively low-cost probes compared with earlier spacecraft, which cost roughly $1 billion each.</p>
        <p>The new probes are to be launched in waves every two years or so if money for the series continues. Their Investigations are to build upon one another to form a scientific foundation for finally answering the life riddle.</p>
        <p>Pathfinder studied rocks. Mars Polar Lander will look for water by digging into icy terrain near the planet's south pole. Later craft are to collect rocky samples from promising sites and return them to Earth. Scientists will then search for signs of microscopic life, either fossil or extant.</p>
        <p>''It has become the intellectual centerpiece of NASA's space exploration program,'' said Dr. Bruce Jakosky, a planetary scientist at the University of Colorado who does research for NASA. A series of science breakthroughs in the past decade, he added, have made the discovery of life on Mars ''very plausible.''</p>
        <p>The concerted push to solve the life puzzle has prompted Japan, France and the European Space Agency to add their own spacecraft to the Mars fleet, at times in partnership with the United States.</p>
        <p>Relatively warm and wet in its early days billions of years ago, the surface of Mars is now an icy red desert etched by old river beds and flood plains that bespeak torrents of water. Scientists see the planet as a possible home for microbial life, especially if the planet's interior is still warm and if water is still flowing through rocky regions down below, as it does on Earth in aquifers.</p>
        <p>Mars Polar Lander, the most recent craft to join the hunt, is to zoom across 470 million miles of space, traveling about 2,000 times farther than the distance between Earth and the Moon. It is remarkably compact, as was evident last month inside a cavernous building at Cape Canaveral, Fla.</p>
        <p>Nothing of the squat bundle being readied for launching suggested that the spacecraft would be able to extend tripod legs, solar panels, a camera mast and a long arm to form a gangly robot some 12 feet long.</p>
        <p>Dr. John McNamee, program manager for the lander and orbiter, moved around the folded craft in a clean suit, booties, plastic gloves and a face mask meant to keep his germs from making the trek to Mars and contaminating the planet.</p>
        <p>The compact lander, he said, is a good example of NASA's resolve to do more with less.</p>
        <p>''It's about half the price, half the mass and able to do much more science'' than its forerunner, Mars Pathfinder, Dr. McNamee said.</p>
        <p>The relentless push for lower costs, Dr. McNamee added, means the lander will use regular rockets to slow its descent rather than innovative air bags, as Pathfinder did when it repeatedly bounced on the rocky surface before coming to a halt. Air bags weigh more, and thus cost more to hurl into space.</p>
        <p>Bulging outward from the craft were two spheres about the size of basketballs. These were microprobes, hitchhikers that will be fired from the lander just before it enters the Martian atmosphere.</p>
        <p>''The microprobes will get there faster because they don't have parachutes or rockets,'' Dr. McNamee said. ''They just go right in.''</p>
        <p>In a first for the exploration of space, and thus somewhat risky compared to tried and true landing techniques, the microprobes are to slam into Mars at about 400 hundred miles per hour, shattering their protective shells.</p>
        <p>The wide upper part of each probe, with antenna, circuits and batteries, will stop abruptly at the surface. But an inner, bullet-shaped projectile, linked to the upper part by a cable, will crash through soil, rock and ice as deep as three or four feet.</p>
        <p>The projectile is laden with sensors. An accelerometer will measure how fast it comes to rest, telling of soil hardness and revealing any layers of dust, rock and ice. Temperature sensors will tell how well the Martian soil conducts heat, giving clues to its composition.</p>
        <p>Finally, a tiny drill will emerge from the side of the projectile to sample the soil, heat it and look for water vapor. That finding would be a first, greatly improving the odds that microbes might thrive in the alien soil.</p>
        <p>About a minute or so after the probes hit, the lander is to settle down gently some 60 miles away but still near the icy south pole. A stereo camera atop a five-foot mast will scan the surrounding landscape.</p>
        <p>The lander's flexible arm is more than six feet long and can dig down as much as two or three feet to retrieve soil samples . In eight tiny ovens on the lander, soil will be heated and analyzed for the presence of icy water and carbon dioxide, the main component of the thin Martian atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Ice at the poles, never before sampled, is thought to be a mix of water and carbon dioxide in a sort of frozen seltzer.</p>
        <p>The lander is to operate for up to 90 days, and the microprobes for a few hours or days. Their downward probing is expected to reveal layered terrain that, like tree rings, sheds  light on the seasonal variations of Mars, its climatic past and whether conditions there were ever favorable for the maintenance of life.</p>
        <p>Readings from the microprobes and the lander will be relayed to Earth by the Mars Climate Orbiter and the Mars Global Surveyor, an orbiting craft that reached the planet during the first exploratory wave. Both orbiters are to map the planet and search for good landing sites.</p>
        <p>The surveyor craft has already discovered a region some 300 miles wide that contains large deposits of the mineral hematite, a rock consisting of tiny crystals of iron oxide that on Earth typically originate in hot or standing water. Scientists consider the region a good place to look for evidence of life and are discussing whether to send a lander there, and possibly one of the missions meant to return rocky samples to Earth.</p>
        <p>Some scientists say that Mars, despite its deserts and hostile surface, may ultimately be found to harbor regions aswarm with alien microbes.</p>
        <p>''I'm a big believer that there is life elsewhere,'' Dr. McNamee said. ''Out of the billions of places that there are in this entire universe, I don't believe that this is the one lucky place where it happened.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
