<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1133308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905EFDA173BF935A1575BC0A96F958260" item-length="1353" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>U.N. Rejects Serb Plea For Enclaves in Kosovo  The United Nations Special Representative for Kosovo, Bernard Kouchner, rejected pleas by the Serbs to formally partition Kosovo into ethnic cantons, at a heated meeting with Albanian and Serbian representatives. He said the peacekeeping force intended to protect the Serbs where they live, even if that meant guarding individual houses.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-10</p>
        <p>U.N. Rejects Serb Plea For Enclaves in Kosovo  The United Nations Special Representative for Kosovo, Bernard Kouchner, rejected pleas by the Serbs to formally partition Kosovo into ethnic cantons, at a heated meeting with Albanian and Serbian representatives. He said the peacekeeping force intended to protect the Serbs where they live, even if that meant guarding individual houses.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The chief of staff of the Bosnian Serb army, Gen. Momir Talic, was arrested while visiting Vienna, unaware that he had secretly been indicted by an international tribunal for crimes against humanity during the 1992-95 Bosnian war. He is the highest-ranking Bosnian Serb official to be arrested.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>U.S. Troops to Leave Haiti  The Administration will withdraw the last American troops stationed in Haiti, even though peace there remains tenuous, officials said. In the future, the Pentagon will send small contingents of reservists and National Guard members on short temporary assignments.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Dagestan Conflict Ends  The fighting in Dagestan, in the Russian Caucasus, appeared to be over as federal troops raised the Russian flag over villages seized three weeks ago by Islamic militants. But the Russian Defense Minister said the threat posed by the Islamic militants remained.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Seizures at Bank of New York  About $20 million has been seized in two Bank of New York accounts linked to what authorities believe is a major money-laundering operation involving Russian organized crime, law enforcement officials said.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Accused of Distorting His Past  Edward W. Said, a literary critic who has been one of the most eloquent proponents of the Palestinian cause, has been accused by an Israeli scholar of misrepresenting his early childhood in order to lend poignancy to his political stance. Mr. Said denied the accusation.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Turkey Defends Quake Aid  Reacting to what he called ''demoralizing'' coverage in the news media, Prime Minister Bulent Ecevit continued to defend his Government's response to the earthquake, which has been widely criticized as tardy and disorganized.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>U.S. and North Korea to Meet  North Korea and the United States agreed to meet in Europe next month, a sign that a resolution might be closer in the standoff over North Korea's suspected preparations to test a long-range ballistic missile.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>A United States Congressman criticized Japan for cutting off food aid to famine-stricken North Korea, as millions of tons of surplus rice sit in Japanese warehouses.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Holbrooke Assumes U.N. Post  Richard C. Holbrooke made his first appearance at the United Nations as the chief representative of the United States.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A11-14</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Rescinds Denial Of Devices Used at Waco  The F.B.I., in a reversal, acknowledged that it used ''pyrotechnic'' tear-gas canisters on the final day of the standoff in 1993 with the Branch Davidian cult near Waco, Tex. But a senior official asserted that the devices did not cause the fire that consumed the cult's headquarters, where about 80 people died.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Airline-Smuggling Arrests  Federal agents arrested more than 50 American Airlines baggage handlers and food contract workers in Miami, charging them with conspiracy, importation and distribution of drugs, and weapons trafficking. Two I.N.S. agents and a Customs inspector were also arrested.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Gay Legislator-Soldier Inquiry  The Pentagon is investigating a conservative Republican legislator in Arizona who is also an officer in the Army Reserves, following his declaration during a legislative debate that he is gay.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Effect of Voucher Ruling  Parents of 4,000 students in Cleveland are hastily weighing their options following a Federal judge's decision to suspend the city's four-year-old tuition voucher program while he considers a lawsuit challenging its constitutionality.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Israel Defends Plea Deal  Israeli officials vigorously defended a plea agreement they reached with Samuel Sheinbein, a teen-ager accused of murder in Maryland who fled to Israel to take advantage of its extradition laws.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Martian Landing Site Picked  NASA chose a broad, gently rolling plain near the south pole of Mars, where layered accumulations of ice and dust preserve a history of planetary climate change, as the landing site for the Mars Polar Lander, which is to arrive on Dec. 3.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Harvard-Boston Spat Ends  Harvard and Boston have reached an accord on the university's plans to expand across the river from its Cambridge campus.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Dispute Over Atlanta Sign  Urban designers and architects in Atlanta are aghast at construction of a giant six-story sign for Ted Turner's new sports arena.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-10</p>
        <p>Congressman Urges Boycott of Youth Rally  Representative Charles B. Rangel, Harlem's leading political figure, called for a boycott of the Million Youth March on Sept. 4. He said racially charged statements by organizers and violent clashes with the police at last year's rally had proved that ''it is impossible for any good'' to come out of the event. Other prominent black politicians also denounced the march and its organizers.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Backs Suit on Schools  The United States Justice Department has filed a brief supporting the right of a coalition of New York City advocacy groups to challenge the way the state finances public schools. The coalition says in its suit that the state's formula for financing education violates Federal civil rights law by providing city schools with less than their fair share of aid, thus discriminating against black and Hispanic children, who make up the majority of public school students in New York City.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Anti-Corruption Effort  State Attorney General Eliot L. Spitzer said he had created a team of prosecutors to investigate local and state government corruption.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Deadline for Apollo Deal  Time Warner officials were said to have notified Representative Charles B. Rangel that they would abandon their plans to take control of the struggling Apollo Theater unless he stepped down as its chairman by the next board meeting.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-14</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Alexandre Lagoya  A guitarist known for the elegance and textural clarity of his performances, both as part of a duet with his first wife, Ida Presti, and later as a soloist, he was 70.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-20</p>
        <p>Cisco in Deal to Expand  Cisco Systems, the leading maker of hardware for computer networks, is expected to announce today that it is acquiring two privately held Internet equipment makers, Cerent and Monterey Networks, for $7.4 billion.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Bank's Stock Drops 23%  Shares of Bank One, the fifth largest bank in the nation, plunged following the company's warning that intense competition in the credit-card business would cause profits to fall short of expectations.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>After-Hours Trading Session  Two on-line brokerage firms, Discover Brokerage and Dreyfus Brokerage Services, opened their electronic doors to small investors between 6 P.M. and 8 P.M. Eastern time.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Overhauling an Icon  Campbell's, whose business has slowed, will unveil a new design for its classic soup cans today.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Ecuador Deferring Payment  Ecuador said it would delay payment on $94 million in Brady bond interest due on Saturday, a decision that could produce ripple effects in the international debt markets. President Jamil Mahuad said the nation would use a 30-day grace period after the deadline to work out a restructuring agreement with creditors.</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A16-17</p>
        <p>Editorials: Japan discovers defense; what the Apollo means for Harlem; Tina Rosenberg on Toms River's Little League champions.  Columns: Bob Herbert.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E10  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>D5  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
