<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Cheaper Power to the People; In Germany, a Radical Deregulation Benefits Households</title>
    <meta content="Y28POW$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1148817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Electricite De France</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7D91038F93BA15753C1A96F958260" item-length="1903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Cheaper Power to the People; In Germany, a Radical Deregulation Benefits Households</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>FRANKFURT, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Impact of deregulation of electric power industry has been staggering in Germany; wholesale electricity prices have plunged as much as 60 percent in last year; corporate customers are getting reductions of 30 percent and more, often without even switching providers; but most surprising competition has been for ordinary household consumers; turmoil is all more unusual because Germany has been known for rigid regulation; Germany's central location in Europe has made it magnet for imports of cheap power from France, Scandinavia and Central Europe; competition in Germany has ignited several huge mergers, and more are on the way; Electricite de France, owned by French Government, is aggressively exporting electricity to Germany from its low-cost nuclear plants and is seeking to acquire German utilities; Germany's big power producers are setting up shop in neighboring countries and hunting for foreign companies to buy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until last month, Michael Loebl greeted his monthly electricity bill in much the same way as his taxes: too high, yet beyond his control.</p>
        <p>Not anymore. After being bombarded by television commercials and billboards from aspiring competitors, he dropped Frankfurt's long-time electric monopoly, Mainova A.G., and signed up with an upstart, Yello Strom. He expects the annual power bill for his modest row house to drop from about $860 to less than $700.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until last month, Michael Loebl greeted his monthly electricity bill in much the same way as his taxes: too high, yet beyond his control.</p>
        <p>Not anymore. After being bombarded by television commercials and billboards from aspiring competitors, he dropped Frankfurt's long-time electric monopoly, Mainova A.G., and signed up with an upstart, Yello Strom. He expects the annual power bill for his modest row house to drop from about $860 to less than $700.</p>
        <p>But that is peanuts compared with the possible savings at his sporting goods store, Sport Loebl, in downtown Frankfurt. Hamburg's city-owned utility, as part of a direct attack on rivals in Frankfurt and other cities, is promising to slash the store's annual bill by around 40 percent, from $18,000 to $11,000.</p>
        <p>Germany is not the first country to open its electricity market to competition. But nowhere has the deregulation been as radical or the resulting price wars as fierce as here.</p>
        <p>A number of American states, including California and New York, have deregulated electric power in ways that primarily benefit big corporate customers, but competition for residential customers remains minimal.</p>
        <p>And while most countries that have opened their markets have done so gradually, Germany abolished all its restrictions in a single move, in February.</p>
        <p>''This is by far the most brutal and maybe chaotic development in the marketplace I have ever seen,'' said Heinz Dieter Waffel, a managing director at Preussen Elektra, a unit of Veba A.G. and Germany's second-largest utility.</p>
        <p>The impact has been staggering.</p>
        <p>Wholesale electricity prices -- the prices that local utilities pay for power -- have plunged as much as 60 percent in the last year. Corporate customers are getting reductions of 30 percent and more, often without even switching providers. But the most surprising competition has been for ordinary household consumers like Mr. Loebl. Electric companies are marketing electricity in department stores, on television and over the Internet.</p>
        <p>The turmoil is all the more unusual because Germany has been known for rigid regulation.</p>
        <p>To be sure, prices here had a long way to fall. Before the price cuts began, electricity in Germany was more than twice as expensive as in the United States and more costly than in any other European country except Italy.</p>
        <p>The price wars have been compounded by other factors. For one thing, Germany is awash in excess generating capacity. And its central location in Europe has made it a magnet for imports of cheap power from France, Scandinavia and Central Europe.</p>
        <p>''Germany is like a copper plate -- electricity flows in all directions, and there are no bottlenecks,'' said Lynn Reinhardt, an energy analyst at Merrill Lynch in Frankfurt.</p>
        <p>Though customers receive electricity over only one set of electric lines, they can order their power from more than a dozen companies, which pay transmission fees to various electrical grids and deliver it from their generating plants to specific customers.</p>
        <p>The competition in Germany has already ignited several huge mergers, and more are on the way. Veba is merging with Viag of Bavaria, the nation's third-largest utility, in a $14 billion deal. RWE, Germany's biggest power company, is negotiating to acquire a big regional provider, VEW. Both Veba and RWE are on the prowl for more acquisitions in Germany and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>The shockwaves are reverberating across Europe. Electricite de France, owned by the French Government, is aggressively exporting electricity to Germany from its low-cost nuclear plants and is seeking to acquire German utilities.</p>
        <p>Germany's big power producers are returning the favor. Desperate to offset steep price declines with higher exports, they are setting up shop in neighboring countries and hunting for foreign companies to buy.</p>
        <p>Industry analysts predict a painful shakeout.</p>
        <p>''It is ruinous competition,'' said Ms. Reinhardt of Merrill Lynch. ''They are all talking about increasing revenues and market share, but market share is irrelevant to shareholders. What matters to shareholders are profits.''</p>
        <p>The turmoil will almost certainly force utilities to shut some of their unneeded power plants, and labor union leaders have warned that as many as 40,000 jobs could be eliminated.</p>
        <p>The competition may also accelerate a shift from coal-fired plants to natural gas and other sources. German coal, still protected by subsidies, is more expensive than many other resources.</p>
        <p>One particular problem is eastern Germany, where the Government prodded western German utilities to build huge ultra-clean coal-fired power plants after the fall of the Berlin wall in 1989. But those plants are being financed in part by higher electricity prices, which are now unsustainable. In a compromise reached this week, the big western German utilities pledged to buy up excess eastern electricity while the eastern plants pledged to cut costs and workers.</p>
        <p>The competition also complicates the country's desire to abandon nuclear energy. Although the Government has vowed to shut down nuclear plants at some point, the deregulation appears to have been a bonanza for imports of cheap electricity from French nuclear plants.</p>
        <p>Even Germany's biggest power companies are scrambling.</p>
        <p>RWE predicts that its prices will decline 10 percent next year; that translates into a $1 billion reduction in revenue. Just to make up lost revenue on the household side of the business, analysts estimate, RWE would have to add six million customers.</p>
        <p>''There is overcapacity in the German market of about 30 percent,'' said Michael Zerr, chief executive of Yello Strom, a new consumer-marketing subsidiary formed by Energie Baden-Wurttemberg, the nation's fourth-largest power company. ''At that level, you have two possibilities: you can hold on as long as possible with higher prices and just let the business decline, or you could be proactive.''</p>
        <p>Smaller utilities are worried that they will be forced out of business. Many have already urged both the courts and the government to shield them -- so far without success.</p>
        <p>At a street protest in Duisburg last month, utility workers donned skeleton masks to dramatize their fears.</p>
        <p>The big producers have been worrying, too.  Aghast that rivals were wooing some of its biggest industrial customers, RWE offered all its midsize customers an automatic price reduction of 30 percent in July.</p>
        <p>Industry executives and analysts say Germany's deregulation was more radical than that in any other country.</p>
        <p>Though American consumers have far lower rates than their German counterparts, prices in states proceeding with deregulation continue to be inflated by surcharges demanded by state regulators. The surcharges, which have been applied in most other countries, too, are intended to let utilities recover ''stranded costs'' -- the costs of power plants built when prices were regulated that could not operate profitably in an open market. By contrast, German officials did not bother, deciding instead to let all utilities sink or swim on their own.</p>
        <p>The German utilities' first big battle was for big industrial customers, much like what had occurred in the United States, Britain and Scandinavia.</p>
        <p>But then something very different took place: an outbreak of competition for ordinary household consumers as bloody as the battle in the United States for long-distance telephone customers.</p>
        <p>RWE, based in Essen, introduced the first nationwide sales campaign for household consumers on Aug. 1, offering a flat rate of 22.3 pfennigs (12.1 cents) a kilowatt-hour for those willing to pay a monthly fee of 9.97 marks ($5.42). This was a small reduction for RWE, but well below the going rates for some of the new territories it hoped to enter.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zerr, who had quietly begun organizing Yello Strom in April, fired back a few days later, offering a rate of 19 pfennigs a kilowatt-hour with a 19-mark monthly fee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zerr also started an eye-catching advertising blitz proclaiming that the ''color'' of electricity was yellow. Playing off the English word ''yellow,'' Mr. Zerr promoted Yello's image as a bright, quirky upstart that would also deliver a good deal.</p>
        <p>RWE responded with advertisements contending that the color of electricity was blue -- the color of its logo.</p>
        <p>The German word for blue -- ''blau'' -- is also slang for ''drunk,'' however, and Yello gleefully responded with ads that essentially said: ''I know the color of electricity is yellow. I'm not yet drunk.''</p>
        <p>Since August, other utilities have dropped their prices and started rival offers that quickly became as confusing as the claims of American long-distance companies.</p>
        <p>Several companies are offering ''green'' electricity, which costs more but is supposed to come exclusively from renewable energy sources like hydroelectricity and windmills.</p>
        <p>Mainova, which serves Frankfurt, is among those offering a ''green plan''; it also has a ''classic'' plan for light users and a ''plus'' plan for heavier users. Elektra Direkt, a new retailing arm of Preussen Elektra, offers both a ''family'' plan and a ''single'' plan.</p>
        <p>Early evidence suggests that only a small percentage of household and commercial customers are switching electric companies. But that is partly because of the pre-emptive price cuts.</p>
        <p>''No one can tell where the money will be made -- in households, industrial or commercial establishments,'' Mr. Waffel of Preussen said. But ''to optimize your portfolio, you have to be present in all those segments.''</p>
        <p>Several American companies have taken an active interest in all this. One is the Enron Corporation, a big wholesale trader of electricity in Europe that helps procure power for industrial customers and utilities.</p>
        <p>''Those who have really taken advantage of the choice in the market have seen prices fall by well over 30 percent and frequently as much as 50 percent,'' said John P. Thompson, Enron's general manager in Frankfurt. ''Everybody, even us, has been surprised by how swiftly this market has moved.''</p>
        <p>So, in the search for salvation through expansion into other markets, the fierce race is on among big German companies to buy up private and state-owned utilities, both inside and outside the country. And the rush is on to set up sales offices in countries like Poland, Italy and the Netherlands.</p>
        <p>A major source of tension is France, which actively exports inexpensive electricity but has so far defied a directive from the European Union to open its own market to competition.</p>
        <p>That is not likely to last long. Most analysts expect that cross-border competition in electricity will only increase. ''This is not just a German issue,'' Mr. Thompson of Enron said.  ''This is now very much a European picture.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
