<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="05FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1090011"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990305T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E6D6173FF936A35750C0A96F958260" item-length="1241" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Mexican Leader Proposes U.S.-Style Nominations  President Ernesto Zedillo called on his governing party to break with 60 years of authoritarian tradition and elect its presidential candidate this year through a series of state primaries culminating in an American-style party convention.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Effort on Kosovo Peace  The Clinton Administration is mounting what it hopes will be a speedy diplomatic offensive to salvage the Kosovo peace proposal. In Kosovo, two separate incidents nearly flared into violence.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-9</p>
        <p>Mexican Leader Proposes U.S.-Style Nominations  President Ernesto Zedillo called on his governing party to break with 60 years of authoritarian tradition and elect its presidential candidate this year through a series of state primaries culminating in an American-style party convention.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>U.S. Effort on Kosovo Peace  The Clinton Administration is mounting what it hopes will be a speedy diplomatic offensive to salvage the Kosovo peace proposal. In Kosovo, two separate incidents nearly flared into violence.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Power Struggle in Moscow  President Boris N. Yeltsin demanded that Boris A. Berezovsky, one of Russia's most prominent and cocksure tycoons, be ousted from a prominent diplomatic post.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Ukrainian Hopeful on Asylum  Pavlo Lazarenko, the former Ukrainian Prime Minister who faces corruption charges, said he had cleared the first procedural hurdle toward winning political asylum in the United States.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Ugandan Soldiers Seek Killers  Hundreds of Ugandan troops spread out through the dense rain forests of eastern Congo in a huge manhunt for the Rwandan rebels who killed eight foreign tourists this week. At least 15 rebels were reported killed. Rebel leaflets promised more attacks.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Progress in U.S.-China Talks  China and the United States, after two days of meetings, have ''made important progress'' in defining terms for China to join the World Trade Organization, the senior United States trade official said. But the official cautioned that there were still significant differences.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Zhu Rongji, addressing the opening session of Parliament, declared that ''despite a grim economic picture'' China would push ahead with economic and social reforms, and would continue ''opening our country wider to the outside world.''</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Balloonists' Quest  Two British balloonists seeking to become the first to circle the world nonstop have surpassed some of their biggest hazards, and were reported over the South China Sea, nearing Taiwan and the voyage's halfway point.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A10-16</p>
        <p>Republican Budget Plan Seals Off Social Security  Senior House and Senate Republicans agreed on the broad outline of a budget plan that they said would immediately wall off Social Security funds to prevent their use for tax cuts or new Government spending. The plan would provide for a relatively small tax cut next fiscal year, growing into a tax cut of as much as $800 billion over a decade.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Republicans in both houses agreed to to provide nearly $1 billion in emergency aid to storm-stricken Central Americans, provided President Clinton cut an equal amount from programs like food stamps and welfare assistance</p>
        <p>conditions that Mr. Clinton found unacceptable.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Dole to Test G.O.P. Waters  Elizabeth Dole will announce next week creation of a committee to explore a Presidential candidacy.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Marine Court-Martial Acquittal  Capt. Richard Ashby, the pilot of a jet that cut a gondola cable in Italy, killing 20 people, was cleared of homicide and manslaughter charges.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Italians reacted with shock and outrage. Prime Minister Massimo D'Alema, visiting Boston, said he would bring the issue up in a meeting with President Clinton today.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>New Los Angeles Quake Threat  Scientists have identified a major new fault under downtown Los Angeles, one that they say is capable of producing a big earthquake.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Melting of Greenland Ice Sheet  Greenland's ice sheet has shrunk in the last five years, but it is unclear if that is the result of natural or human causes or both. If the world's big ice sheets melt even partly, seas will rise and currents that modulate climate may be disrupted.</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>Promising Gene Research  New research sustains but does not yet fulfill the hope that manipulation of a gene will provide treatments for cancer, heart disease and other maladies of aging human tissues.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Anti-Gay Bias Cited in Killing  Two men told Alabama authorities that they killed a man and burned his body last month because he earlier made a homosexual advance.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>National Reading Test Scores  No state lost ground and some made significant gains on the nationwide exams that measure how well fourth- and eighth-grade public school students are reading.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-13</p>
        <p>Mayor Pushes Vouchers Despite Crew Threat to Quit  Mayor Giuliani intensified efforts to push a publicly financed tuition voucher program through the Board of Education and brushed aside Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew's threat to resign over the issue. The Mayor met with the board member most likely to cast the deciding vote, Terri Thomson, and her patron, the Queens borough president.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Contender Forgoes the Race  Robert E. Menendez, left, a four-term Congressman from New Jersey, said he would not seek to replace Senator Frank R. Lautenberg, who is retiring. Mr. Menendez was widely seen as the leading Democrat.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Diallo Inquiry Extended  A judge extended the term of the Bronx grand jury hearing evidence in the Amadou Diallo case. New divisions emerged between Mr. Diallo's family and the United African Congress, which has met with the Mayor and the Police Commissioner on behalf of African immigrants.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>U.N. Shift on Spousal Support  The Secretary General, Kofi Annan, announced a policy change that would allow for the garnishing of wages of United Nations employees who failed to pay spousal and child support ordered by local courts.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>WEEKEND</p>
        <p>E1-40; E41-54</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>Cable Company Looks at Mets  Cablevision, which tried to buy the Yankees, is now said to be discussing a deal to buy the Mets.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Appearance by Ailing Ex-Yank  The Hall of Fame pitcher Catfish Hunter attended a Yankee game in Tampa, Fla., his first public appearance outside his hometown since doctors diagnosed amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, Lou Gehrig's disease.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A17-19</p>
        <p>Harry A. Blackmun  The retired Supreme Court Justice who was the author of the Roe v. Wade decision on abortion was 90.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>Casualties of Trade War  Scores of companies were caught in a bitter trade war between the United States and Europe in which the businesses have no direct stake and over which they have no control.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>I.B.M. Selling Parts to Dell  I.B.M. said it expected to sell $16 billion worth of disk drives and other components to a rival, Dell Computer, signaling that I.B.M.'s future may depend as much on computer parts as on entire machines.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Merrill Lynch Goes on Line  Merrill Lynch, the country's largest brokerage house, switched on the firm's long-awaited Internet trading option for a select group of customers, allowing them for the first time to buy and sell listed stocks without calling one of the firm's 15,000 brokers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Grumbling Over Olivetti Bid  Large British and American investment funds with big stakes in Telecom Italia are expressing some misgivings over aspects of Olivetti's effort to buy its rival Telecom for $60 billion.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Action on Banking Bills  House and Senate committees took action on sharply conflicting bills to eliminate Depression-era barriers between banks, securities firms and insurance companies, diminishing the chances that Congress would pass major banking legislation this year.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Rudy versus Rudy; the rules of Monica's game; unstable autocracies in Central Asia; Justice Blackmun's journey.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E54</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>E39</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>D4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
