<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Plumbing Black Sea for Proof of the Deluge</title>
    <meta content="05FLOO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1074732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Black Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ryan, William B F (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pitman, Walter C 3d (Dr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bible</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Floods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DC173EF936A35752C0A96F958260" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Plumbing Black Sea for Proof of the Deluge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two Columbia University marine geologists, Dr William B F Ryan and Dr Walter C Pitman 3d, say they have more archelogical, geological and climate data to support their thesis that a catastrophic flood of Black Sea 7,600 years ago could have played a pivotal role in spread of early farming into Europe and much of Asia; deluge also may have cast such a long shadow over succeeding cultures that it inspired flood account in Babylonian epic of Gilgamesh and, in turn, story of Noah in Book of Genesis; say flood occurred when rising oceans sent salt water breaking through a lang barrier into Black Sea; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two Columbia University marine geologists, inviting incredulity, came forward in 1996 with astonishing evidence suggesting that a catastrophic flood of the Black Sea 7,600 years ago could have played a pivotal role in the spread of early farming into Europe and much of Asia. The deluge also may have cast such a long shadow over succeeding cultures that it inspired the flood account in the Babylonian epic of Gilgamesh and, in turn, the story of Noah in the Book of Genesis.</p>
        <p>Now the geologists, Dr. William B. F. Ryan and Dr. Walter C. Pitman 3d of Columbia's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory in Palisades, N.Y., say they have even more archeological, geological and climate data to support their provocative thesis. They argue their case in ''Noah's Flood: The New Scientific Discoveries About the Event That Changed History,'' a book being published next week by Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two Columbia University marine geologists, inviting incredulity, came forward in 1996 with astonishing evidence suggesting that a catastrophic flood of the Black Sea 7,600 years ago could have played a pivotal role in the spread of early farming into Europe and much of Asia. The deluge also may have cast such a long shadow over succeeding cultures that it inspired the flood account in the Babylonian epic of Gilgamesh and, in turn, the story of Noah in the Book of Genesis.</p>
        <p>Now the geologists, Dr. William B. F. Ryan and Dr. Walter C. Pitman 3d of Columbia's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory in Palisades, N.Y., say they have even more archeological, geological and climate data to support their provocative thesis. They argue their case in ''Noah's Flood: The New Scientific Discoveries About the Event That Changed History,'' a book being published next week by Simon &amp; Schuster.</p>
        <p>While the authors have yet to win over skeptics of the Black Sea flood's possibly sweeping influence on history, other scientists have weighed in with new findings that seem to confirm the fact of the flood itself. In about 5600 B.C., with rising global sea levels, salt water from the Mediterranean and Aegean seas apparently burst into the Black Sea, then a landlocked freshwater lake. The Black Sea rose with terrifying swiftness, inundating more than 60,000 square miles of coastal plains and giving the body of water its current size and configuration.</p>
        <p>The thesis, however it is ultimately judged, has already inspired a wave of archeological and other scientific research in the previously neglected Black Sea region.</p>
        <p>''It has captured the archeological community's attention and enthusiasm,'' Dr. Ryan said in a recent interview. ''The atmosphere has changed in just two years. People from many countries are keen to take part in exploring the idea in many ways.''</p>
        <p>Working on Turkey's Black Sea coast at Sinop, Dr. Fredrik T. Hiebert, a University of Pennsylvania archeologist, has detected possible ruins of a Stone Age village that was submerged in the flood. He is planning an expedition this summer to expand the search for preflood settlements. One objective is to determine if the people were farmers and so, as refugees from the deluge, might have spread the practice of agriculture into Europe for the first time.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robert D. Ballard, the oceanographer who used modern underwater technologies to find and explore the Titanic wreck, is preparing an ambitious survey of submerged Black Sea archeological sites this summer. Dr. Ballard, formerly with the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution on Cape Cod, is president of the Institute for Exploration in Mystic, Conn.</p>
        <p>Until Dr. Ryan and Dr. Pitman advanced their hypothesis, archeologists had little reason to believe the preflood Black Sea shore was particularly hospitable.</p>
        <p>In the last two years, moreover, new cores from the Greenland ice cap have revealed that the world underwent a cold, arid period, beginning in 6200 B.C. and ending about two centuries before the flood. Archeological digs in the Middle East appear to show many Neolithic settlements' being abandoned during this drought.</p>
        <p>''We speculate that this cold and arid period may have driven people to the Black Sea as an oasis,'' Dr. Pitman said. ''They would have brought farming with them to this water hole, so to speak, and also exchanged ideas and languages.''</p>
        <p>The timing of the flood, Dr. Pitman said, happened to coincide with archeological evidence of newcomers in the Balkans and in northeastern Europe and with some of the earlier signs of agriculture in these regions. Some pottery at these sites is similar to that found near the Sea of Marmara in Turkey from around the time of the flood.</p>
        <p>Making connections between people displaced by the flood and the rise of agriculture in Europe -- even in Egypt and Central Asia -- is the most controversial aspect of the Ryan-Pitman thesis. In a review of the book in the current issue of Archaeology magazine, Mark Rose, the managing editor, said the farming connection ''is predicated on a huge archeological assumption'' that there was a drought and it did force Middle Eastern farmers to find refuge on the preflood Black Sea coast. He also noted that some farming had already begun to appear in parts of Europe 500 years before the putative flood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rose concluded: ''If Ryan and Pitman are right about the inundation of the Black Sea, they have made a real advance in our understanding of the region's past. But making it Noah's flood and claiming it was the 'event that changed history' was a mistake.''</p>
        <p>In other recent research, Dr. Gilles Lericolais, a French oceanographer, led an expedition last spring that conducted more seismic and echo-sounding probes of the submerged shelf off the Black Sea coast. He discovered deep underwater canyons where the Danube and Dnieper rivers had once cut deep to reach the declining waters of the preflood Black Sea.</p>
        <p>Turkish geologists recently reported evidence that, contrary to most assumptions, the Bosporus Strait was cut at the time of the flood and not before. At the end of the last ice age, more than 12,000 years ago, the outlet connecting the freshwater Black Sea to the Mediterranean was probably a channel through the Sakarya River to the Gulf of Izmit, an eastern arm of the Sea of Marmara. But this passageway had closed well before the flood, leaving no outlet for Black Sea's steadily evaporating and diminishing waters.</p>
        <p>''We have no way of knowing what caused the change,'' Dr. Ryan said. The Sakarya outlet ''is on the Anatolian fault, so a slip of the fault may have choked it up,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In any event, where the Bosporus flows today by Istanbul, separating Europe and Asia, there was a low valley just before the flood. Dr. Ryan and Dr. Pitman propose in their book that a natural dam across the valley kept the ocean waters, rising since the melting of ice-age glaciers, from entering the Black Sea basin.</p>
        <p>This, they said, would explain why the world ocean did not make contact sooner with the lowered Black Sea and why, when it did break through, the event was so catastrophic and left such a deep scar as the Bosporus Strait.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
