<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cola Makers Leave Their Bottlers Flat</title>
    <meta content="12SODA$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1160410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pepsico Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DA1531F931A25751C1A96F958260" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cola Makers Leave Their Bottlers Flat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shareholders of big soft-drink bottling companies have suffered sharp losses this year, in part because of rising concentrate prices; Coca-Cola and PepsiCo have increased concentrate prices by 7 percent; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COCA-COLA, the soft drink, is based on a closely guarded secret formula. But the arithmetic that results when Coca-Cola, the company, decides to squeeze more profit from its complex relationships with its bottlers was laid bare last week.</p>
        <p>On Friday, shares of Coca-Cola Enterprises, in which Coca-Cola holds a 39 percent stake, closed at $18.375, less than half their 52-week high of $37.50. The share price of Coca-Cola Consolidated, the No. 2 Coke bottler in the United States, closed at $49.75, down 13.5 percent for the year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COCA-COLA, the soft drink, is based on a closely guarded secret formula. But the arithmetic that results when Coca-Cola, the company, decides to squeeze more profit from its complex relationships with its bottlers was laid bare last week.</p>
        <p>On Friday, shares of Coca-Cola Enterprises, in which Coca-Cola holds a 39 percent stake, closed at $18.375, less than half their 52-week high of $37.50. The share price of Coca-Cola Consolidated, the No. 2 Coke bottler in the United States, closed at $49.75, down 13.5 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>This had already been a bad year for the bottling stocks, but it became worse last month. That was when an executive of Coca-Cola Enterprises disclosed that Coca-Cola was raising the price it charges for concentrate -- the powder or syrup that is mixed with water and carbon dioxide to become soft drinks -- by 7 percent, twice the usual rate. The move was seen as Coke's attempt to capture some of the profit that the bottlers were anticipating from a price increase they initiated earlier this year at the wholesale level.</p>
        <p>For Summerfield Johnston Jr., the chairman and second-largest shareholder of Coca-Cola Enterprises, a result has been this: In early June, his 28.6 million shares were worth about $1.07 billion; the value of that stake has been whittled down to about $525 million.</p>
        <p>''I would say he's not a happy camper on this whole thing,'' said Emanuel Goldman, an analyst at Merrill Lynch. The unhappiness of bottlers like Mr. Johnston -- whose opinions carry some weight at Coca-Cola -- may have been a factor in the departure of M. Douglas Ivester, Coca-Cola's chief executive. Mr. Ivester stunned investors last week with the news that he was stepping down in April.</p>
        <p>The concentrate price increase was imitated over at Pepsi-Cola a short time later.  And for the Pepsi system, it has been the same story: shares in Pepsi Bottling, the company spun off from PepsiCo earlier this year, are now at $16, after trading as high as $25.25 in July. And the Whitman Corporation, another major Pepsi bottler, now trades at $13.125, down 48 percent for the year.</p>
        <p>The stock prices of the concentrate companies, however, have fared better. Coca-Cola closed on Friday at $63.25, down just 5.6 percent for the year, while PepsiCo closed at $36.9375, down 9.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Does all this mean that investors should avoid bottling stocks? Not necessarily, say some money managers and analysts.</p>
        <p>''The upside isn't limited if you are a long-term value player,'' said Scott Black, the president of Delphi Management, which is among the top five stakeholders in Coca-Cola Consolidated and has a stake in Pepsi Bottling. ''You're getting exclusive territorial franchises, a business that generates lots of cash, and very low multiples.'' With cash flow growth of 10 percent or so in good times, the stocks are attractive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldman said he thought all the bottling stocks had been oversold. He has 12-month price targets of $40 on Coca-Cola Enterprises, $31 on Pepsi Bottling and $16 on Whitman.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Pepsi Bottling, which announced the Pepsi-Cola concentrate price increase last month, said the timing was right as long as PepsiCo made marketing-support payments to the bottler. ''Consumers have to want what we make, sell and deliver,'' said the spokesman, Larry Jabbonsky.</p>
        <p>The relationship between the concentrate companies and their bottlers has been a concern on Wall Street. Many investors want to see a more equitable distribution of profits between the two sides; historically, more of the profit has accrued to the concentrate makers, whose margins are extremely high. Returns on invested capital have also been far higher for the concentrate companies than for the bottlers.</p>
        <p>STILL, there seems to be some confusion, said Paul Rissman, a senior vice president at Alliance Capital Management, who recently added to stakes in Coca-Cola Enterprises and Pepsi Bottling, both of which he calls ''incredibly cheap.''</p>
        <p>''If the concentrate companies were to intend to rob some of the profits from the bottlers, they'd just be cutting off their noses,'' he said. ''We think they know that. We think they are trying to reach agreements with the bottlers where they can both make money.''</p>
        <p>Companies like Coca-Cola have urged ever-higher volume from their bottlers, and stand to benefit from increased concentrate sales. But there has been a big cost to bottlers around the world, said Andrew J. Conway, an analyst for Morgan Stanley.</p>
        <p>In a note to investors published last week, Mr. Conway assessed Mr. Ivester's contributions and generally gave him high marks. However, he said volume growth targets of 7 to 8 percent -- which Mr. Ivester's successor, Douglas N. Daft, said he planned to pursue -- had a distinct downside.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Ivester's targets have led to an unprecedented rate of bottler investment in plants, trucks, machinery and coolers,'' Mr. Conway wrote. ''Given the global economic slowdown, this rate of investment was well ahead of the volume curve that has emerged. In turn, this has left many global bottlers with subpar returns on invested capital.''</p>
        <p>INVESTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
