<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Gore and Bradley, A Search for Distinction</title>
    <meta content="Y26REC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1148353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4DE1538F935A15753C1A96F958260" item-length="1532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Gore and Bradley, A Search for Distinction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore and former Senator Bill Bradley have lot more in common than either would like to admit to Presidential primary voters; each will try to emphasize differences that matter to voters when they debate for first time in New Hampshire on October 27; both have spent bulk of public service careers as generally liberal members of Congress, with quite similar approach to job; their similarities and differences discussed; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore and former Senator Bill Bradley have a lot more in common than either would like to admit to Presidential primary voters.</p>
        <p>Each will try to emphasize differences that matter to those voters when they debate for the first time in New Hampshire on Wednesday night. But in fact, the two Democrats have spent the bulk of their public service careers as generally liberal members of Congress, with a quite similar approach to the job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore and former Senator Bill Bradley have a lot more in common than either would like to admit to Presidential primary voters.</p>
        <p>Each will try to emphasize differences that matter to those voters when they debate for the first time in New Hampshire on Wednesday night. But in fact, the two Democrats have spent the bulk of their public service careers as generally liberal members of Congress, with a quite similar approach to the job.</p>
        <p>Their likenesses start with their voting records, during Mr. Bradley's 18 years in the Senate and Mr. Gore's 8 years there, after serving 8 years in the House. Mr. Bradley, plainly seeking to run to Mr. Gore's left on issues from health insurance to gun control, was a bit more liberal in the eyes of old-fashioned liberals and environmentalists. But to some groups, like the A.F.L.-C.I.O. and conservative groups, their records were almost identical.</p>
        <p>But a Congressional record, if it means anything at all, is more than a compilation of votes, and the Bradley-Gore similarities extended well beyond the yeas and nays.</p>
        <p>Each was effective in learning a complex, ''eyes glaze over'' issue and putting it on the national agenda.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Gore, there was global warming, arms control questions and computer technology. ''I think my work on arms control made a contribution at a critical time toward the creation of a new consensus on strategic stability,'' Mr. Gore said in a recent interview. And he said his work on environmental issues also helped to generate a consensus, both for the Superfund program to clean up toxic waste sites and for addressing global environmental problems.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Bradley, there was third world debt, international trade and tax simplification. He was central to the 1986 tax reform act that lowered tax rates and closed loopholes, which he pursued with ''a single-mindedness that was sometimes irritating to my family,'' he said in an interview. But in the end, he added, ''it became the symbol of doing very big things in a bipartisan way.''</p>
        <p>Neither man was known in Congress as an orator. But Mr. Gore rose to a dramatic occasion to explain his vote to authorize war in the Persian Gulf in 1991, when he broke with almost all other Democrats, including Senator Sam Nunn of Georgia, chairman of the Armed Services Committee. Mr. Bradley was unaccustomedly eloquent the next year in warning of deteriorating race relations.</p>
        <p>Neither was especially chummy with colleagues, though Mr. Gore had more friends in the House than both of them put together had in the Senate. Mr. Gore's run for the Presidency in his first Senate term made him seem presumptuous to some senators, and he was snidely labeled Prince Albert.</p>
        <p>That lack of loyal allies may be one reason why neither had a striking record of getting laws passed, though each had a few accomplishments. A more telling reason may be that neither served long enough to head a committee, though Mr. Bradley dealt impressively with Western water rights as a subcommittee chairman. In a similar position, Mr. Gore first began warning of global warming and the greenhouse effect.</p>
        <p>In a campaign, each will try to make an issue out of past votes, especially as proof of comparative constancy and sincerity, as reasons to trust their promises for the future.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, for example, has criticized Mr. Bradley for voting in 1992, 1994 and 1996 for school vouchers that parents could use to pay private and parochial school tuition. The New Jersey Senator said he supported only an ''experiment,'' and today he opposes vouchers. That quarrel is intended to attract the votes of public school teachers.</p>
        <p>Similarly, Mr. Bradley's insistence that he has been ''a consistent and unwavering supporter of a woman's right to choose'' whether to have an abortion is directed at another important Democratic primary constituency: voters for whom abortion rights are the prime issue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's current position is indistinguishable from Mr. Bradley's, but before he first ran for President in 1987 it was generally anti-abortion.</p>
        <p>In the House, he generally opposed Federal funding for abortions for poor women on Medicaid. In the mid-1980's, the Tennessee Representative regularly wrote constituents who asked his views: ''I have strongly opposed Federal funding of abortions. In my opinion, it is wrong to spend Federal funds for what is arguably the taking of a human life.''</p>
        <p>But by the time he was seeking votes in Democratic Presidential primaries in 1988, Mr. Gore was equivocating, and by 1992 he supported his party's position in favor of Medicaid financing for abortions.</p>
        <p>The environment is an important point of comparison. Mr. Gore has built much of his reputation in that area, although when it came to voting records, the League of Conservation Voters judged him ''right'' just 64 percent of the time, compared with 84 percent for Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore is best known for big concepts, like global warming and the threat to the ozone layer. The legislative results were not always dramatic, although he led a successful effort to limit CFC's in the 1990 Clean Air Act and was deeply involved with the Superfund program in the House. But since the Clinton Administration has not been as dedicated to those concerns as Mr. Gore was as a lawmaker, they sometimes seem to do him little good today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley is known more for specifics -- for filibustering an effort to undo Federal protection of millions of acres in Utah, for securing the Sterling Forest preserve in New Jersey and New York and, most of all, for the 1992 California water rights legislation. That law forced farmers to pay more than a token price for Central Valley water and made the water available for urban use.</p>
        <p>That legislation began as an issue that Mr. Bradley said ''I knew nothing about'' but was his to deal with when he became a subcommittee chairman. He studied it, held hearings, found allies and maneuvered the bill into law, using election year pressures to get President George Bush to sign it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was among an influential band of House Democrats who threatened in 1983 to oppose deployment of the MX missile unless the Reagan Administration would start talking to Moscow about arms controls. In the Senate he was among the advocates of reducing the use of multiple warheads.</p>
        <p>One successful legislative effort that brought Mr. Gore recent grief was technology. In March he said he ''took the initiative in creating the Internet.'' Republicans laughed him off the political stage for that one, with Dan Quayle saying if that was true, he had invented spell-check. In fact, Mr. Gore's efforts to promote supercomputing and high-speed communications networks are acknowledged by the developers of the process to have played an essential role.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Gore makes his Internet boast in more convoluted language: ''My work on technology included efforts to promote funding for the technologies that were used by people who expanded early prototypes of the Arpanet that later became the Internet.'' He grinned and added, ''I hope I have buffered that adequately.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley's greatest Senate accomplishment was the 1986 tax reform act that ''nobody in Washington thought would really happen,'' as he put it in the interview.</p>
        <p>Tax fairness was an issue he brought to Washington. ''I had always been upset by a system where people who were able to use loopholes paid less than people who did not,'' he said. He put the idea in a book, pestered colleagues, worked with the Reagan Administration and Senator Bob Packwood, chairman of the Finance Committee, and ultimately lobbied the House by playing basketball with members in the House gym -- an activity he had avoided since his election in 1978.</p>
        <p>But that was 13 years ago. Since 1986, he said, ''billions of loopholes have come back in and rates have gone back up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley argues that his work on various trade measures, from the Uruguay Round to the North American Free Trade Agreement, played important roles in strengthening the economy. And he was an early critic of Moscow's economic policies in the last days of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>One issue central to his Presidential campaign on which he was almost invisible in Congress is health insurance. In the 1993-94 fight over President Clinton's plan or various alternatives, the Finance Committee on which he served was a central battleground. He explained his inactivity by saying he followed the lead of Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan of New York, the committee chairman, who waited in vain for Republicans to compromise.</p>
        <p>To one longtime observer of Congress, Norman J. Ornstein of the American Enterprise Institute, what made both Mr. Gore and Mr. Bradley ''considerably better than average Senators'' was their ability to bring issues to national attention. ''Other than Pat Moynihan,'' he said, ''I couldn't pick someone better in the House or Senate to put an issue into play.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
