<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's Eating America? Weeds</title>
    <meta content="16WEED$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1138143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raver, Anne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flowers and Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5D9173CF935A2575AC0A96F958260" item-length="2000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's Eating America? Weeds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raver, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exotic plants like the arundo are wreaking havoc with habitats of America's native species, and about half of the invaders are escapees from the garden; governments on Federal and state level are moving to control distribution of non-native species, but exotics are the lifeblood of horticultural world; nurseries are pressing for voluntary, regional controls, arguing that an exotic that may be invasive in one part of the country could be perfectly docile in another; photos; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOBODY can remember the exact moment the giant cane, Arundo donax, went from being a nuisance to a state of emergency, but the day it lifted up a bridge in Norco, Calif., might do for starters. Sudden rains in 1993 had sent flood waters roaring down the Santa Ana river.</p>
        <p>''The arundo breaks off like monstrous celery stalks that jam up against the bridge and work like a dam,'' said Paul Frandsen, the general manager for Riverside County parks, standing on the banks of the river early last spring. ''As the water rose, it lifted the bridge right off its pylons.'' It did the same thing again last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOBODY can remember the exact moment the giant cane, Arundo donax, went from being a nuisance to a state of emergency, but the day it lifted up a bridge in Norco, Calif., might do for starters. Sudden rains in 1993 had sent flood waters roaring down the Santa Ana river.</p>
        <p>''The arundo breaks off like monstrous celery stalks that jam up against the bridge and work like a dam,'' said Paul Frandsen, the general manager for Riverside County parks, standing on the banks of the river early last spring. ''As the water rose, it lifted the bridge right off its pylons.'' It did the same thing again last year.</p>
        <p>The magnificent 30-foot plant has been used for everything from fencing by the Spanish conquerors to an ornamental grass. But over 20 years, it has muscled out the native cottonwoods and willows that once thrived along the banks of the Santa Ana. Slurping up nutrients pouring into the river from seven sewage treatment plants, arundo can grow seven inches a day, said Mr. Frandsen, who is battling 8,000 acres of it.</p>
        <p>And while the state of California spends millions to remove arundo from the watershed, Greenlee Nursery, in Pomona, Calif., continues to sell it.</p>
        <p>Arundo is one of about 300 exotic, or non-native plants invading natural habitats in the 49 continental states. And about half of them are escapees from the garden, said Janet Marinelli, a co-editor of ''Invasive Plants: Weeds of the Global Garden'' (Brooklyn Botanic Garden, 1996).</p>
        <p>Baby's breath, that pretty little white flower in bridal bouquets, is wreaking havoc in the dunes by Lake Michigan. ''It has a 15-foot taproot, about as big around as your thigh,'' said Sherri Laier, an ecologist at the Point Betsie Preserve, in Michigan, run by the Nature Conservancy. The plant stabilizes the dunes, which is disastrous for species like the threatened Pitcher's thistle, which depends on shifting sand to reproduce.</p>
        <p>Norway maples are out-competing the native sugar maples. Purple loosestrife is killing the native reeds and sedges in wetlands. Tall fescue, touted by the lawn industry as a drought-tolerant, disease-resistant grass, never goes dormant on the prairie. So farewell, native grasses.</p>
        <p>''Invasive plants are causing about $123 billion a year in damage,'' said William Y. Brown, the science adviser to Secretary of the Interior Bruce Babbitt. Controlling them is now on the Presidential agenda. For centuries, plant hunters have freely traded plants, from lilacs and magnolias to tomatoes and figs, with virtually no regulations. But those golden days are numbered, as exotics from other countries have spread over about 100 million acres and are continuing to grow at a rate of 3 million acres a year (that's twice the size of Delaware).</p>
        <p>HOW did such glorious, useful plants start eating America? Through our own doing, mostly, scientists say: acid rain, polluted water, heavy metals in the soil, nitrogen overloads, soil compaction, fragmentation by development are just a few of the human disturbances that can weaken a natural ecosystem, opening it up to disease -- and opportunistic weeds.</p>
        <p>''Because of what people have done,'' Mr. Frandsen said, ''we have created a monster.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the World Conservation Union  cited exotic species as the second-biggest threat to biodiversity, next to habitat loss.  And early this year, President Clinton issued an executive order charging the Agriculture, Commerce and Interior Departments with developing a plan for controlling invasive species and preventing the introduction and spread of new ones. At the same time, a bill is making its way through the Senate that would increase the Agriculture Department's authority to screen or even ban plants from commercial trade.</p>
        <p>Such controls, after thousands of years of free exchange -- since that first gardener carried seeds to another campfire -- has the nursery industry worried about everything from seeds brought back from Siberia to promising ornamentals in their greenhouses right now. There are about a dozen plants on the Federal noxious weed list, but horticulturists say the regulations are poorly enforced. And though 18 state agriculture departments have drawn up invasive plant lists, compliance is voluntary. As countries like Australia, where exotic plants overrun more than half of its wildlands, set up strict requirements before a non-native plant can cross its borders, the Federal Government is considering a similar model.</p>
        <p>But a plant that may be invasive in sunny California could be perfectly docile in the cold Northeast. ''One of my biggest concerns about regulation is that it will be national, while invasive plant issues are usually regional,'' said Barry Yinger, a Pennsylvania nurseryman, who has made about 40 collecting trips to Japan. ''Lantana is a horrible pest in Hawaii, but a great bedding plant in Pennsylvania. Yet, under national regulation it would be unavailable to everyone.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yinger advocates regional boards, which could monitor exotics and serve as a local early warning system for invasives.</p>
        <p>Craig Regelbrugge, a senior director at the American Nursery and Landscape Association, would like to see voluntary compliance, if only out of the sheer impossibility of regulating plants in a global economy,  where orders fly across the Internet and gardeners are constantly crossing borders (with seeds and cuttings in their bags). ''The last thing the nursery industry wants is an absolutely balkanized marketplace,'' he said, ''where every little village has its own plant list and the marketplace becomes so fragmented you can't even keep up with it and do business.''</p>
        <p>Many growers feel that they -- and their plants -- are being scapegoated by a culture unable to face up to its own mess.</p>
        <p>''These plants aren't big, evil villains that have invaded pristine nature,'' said John Greenlee, the Pomona nurseryman who insists on his right to sell arundo in California. ''They are indicators of disturbance. The river has already been trashed and turned into a channel. Native plants have already been removed.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frandsen, the arundo warrior, paints the same scenario, with the opposite conclusion ''You can't reverse this,'' he said. ''You can't ship the people out and take it back.''</p>
        <p>So you weed.</p>
        <p>Seven years ago, Mr. Frandsen assembled a coalition of about 20 groups usually at war with one another -- from the Nature Conservancy to the herbicide maker Monsanto to firefighters and flood control officials -- to declare war on arundo. And all spring and summer, youth workers from the California Conservation Corps were wacking back the weed with almost military zeal.</p>
        <p>But as soon as these teams turn their backs, the giant reed resprouts -- like something from ''The Day of the Triffids.'' So they nuke it with herbicides.</p>
        <p>''We can't ever stop doing it,'' said Mr. Frandsen, who is pushing for a state water bond issue that would funnel $20 million to control the cane. In 10 years, Team Arundo has brought 500 acres back to cottonwoods and willows, and the least-billed vireo, an endangered bird, has a place to nest again.</p>
        <p>The Nature Conservancy fights the same battle on 14,000 preserves around the country. ''If we are going to protect the diversity of native plants and animals, we have to do weed control or weed prevention,'' said Dr. John M. Randall, the group's invasive plant specialist. ''We cannot simply fence these properties off and walk away.''</p>
        <p>Like many conservationists, he says it is important to focus the limited time and money available on saving the most diverse, rare habitats, and also on preventing the entry of new invasive species.</p>
        <p>But new plants are the lifeblood of the horticultural world, say growers who fear that regulations will discourage new plant introductions and hurt the industry.</p>
        <p>It's the very qualities of exotic plants -- the ability to thrive in the dry, salty conditions of a tree pit, for example -- that send plant hunters roaming the Siberian steppes.</p>
        <p>''It is unfortunately true that the plants that are best adapted to our unnatural landscapes in cities and suburbs are often not native plants,'' said Mr. Yinger, who has a research nursery in central Pennsylvania. ''Native plants did not evolve for our current disturbed landscapes, and it is romantic nonsense to claim that they are the answer to all our landscape problems.''</p>
        <p>In the long view of many biologists, no amount of weeding is going to keep a disturbed forest full of dogwoods and trillium.</p>
        <p>''Conservationists are trying to preserve the remnants of what once was,'' said Dr. Peter Del Tredici, the director of living collections at the Harvard University Arnold Arboretum. ''It's a form of creationism. It denies the existence of change, which is about evolution.''</p>
        <p>New Yorkers can see evolution taking place right in the 200-year-old forest at the New York Botanical Garden. The hemlocks are dying, the dogwoods and ashes are sick. The forest is struggling with acid rain, amd heavy metals from road runoff. The Bronx River is polluted.</p>
        <p>Dr. Charles Peters, a forest ecologist at the garden, stood in a little grove of Aralia spinosa -- a thorny tree called devil's walking stick -- seeding itself in the sunny gaps created by fallen trees. ''As the natives die,'' he said, ''these highly invasive species come in, and say, 'Oh yeah, we can live here.' '' He led the way along the banks of the polluted Bronx River, where Japanese knotweed has covered the eroded banks.</p>
        <p>''Nature itself is fixing this,'' said Dr. Peters, trying to like the invaders. ''These plants are photosynthesizing, they're taking water up, they're cleaning the air.''</p>
        <p>They're doing the job of the forest, in other words. ''And once you start pulling out those Norway maples and knotweed,'' he said, ''you'll have to do it forever.''</p>
        <p>So where does all this debate leave the poor gardener?</p>
        <p>In a political state, that's where -- because simply putting an invasive plant in your garden might be hurting your local ecosystem. Or not, depending on your view.</p>
        <p>Experts hope that people will educate themselves by reading information published by local botanic gardens and conservancies, or by attending conferences, like the one coming up at Swarthmore College in Swarthmore, Pa., -- ''Invasive Exotic Plants: Current Management Strategies'' -- on Nov. 3 and 4 (215-247-5777, ext. 156). Gardeners can find out what plants are the top offenders in their states by calling local plant councils. The Invasive Plant Council of New York (518-273-9408, ext. 221), for example, lists Norway maple as the top offender. So plant a sugar maple, to give the native a leg up.</p>
        <p>Watch the plants in your own garden, especially those lovely self-seeders, like Verbena bonaniensis, a tall, airy purple flower that comes back every year, then shows up in cracks in the sidewalk. Or across the street in your neighbor's yard. These are the sure signs of an invader.</p>
        <p>''If you see it doing this in the garden, it's not a good species to distribute,'' said Dr. Sarah Reichard, a biologist at the University of Washington in Seattle, who is developing a screening model for letting plants into the country.</p>
        <p>And if a little Arundo donax should pop up in your garden, take a look in the mirror.</p>
        <p>''We have to admit that part of being an American in the 21st century is disturbance and pollution,'' Dr. Del Tredici said. ''And these are the plants that flourish in the company of people.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
