<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shaping Restless Planet Earth</title>
    <meta content="11EART$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1114304"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Museum of Natural History (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDD1638F932A25755C0A96F958260" item-length="1916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shaping Restless Planet Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American Museum of Natural History creates new exhibition illustrating 4.5 billion years of earth's history; exhibition addresses questions of how the planet evolved, why there are ocean basins, continents and mountains, how scientists read rocks, what causes climate and climate change and why earth in habitable; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over more than a century, scientists and explorers from the American Museum of Natural History have searched the world and returned with arresting examples of life in all its diversity: dinosaurs from Montana to Mongolia, birds and butterflies, artifacts of exotic cultures from here to the South Sea. For the last four years, their quest has been to collect the stuff of Earth itself and bring it back for a new exhibition illustrating the planet's 4.5 billion-year history.</p>
        <p>On 28 acquisition expeditions, museum teams collected 82 tons of rock and ore ranging from granite and sandstone to gold and platinum. The oldest, a zircon crystal from Australia, is nearly 4.3 billion years old. The youngest, a chunk of sulfur, was picked up the same day it solidified in an Indonesian volcano. The rarest and most intriguing to scientists are sulfide chimneys that rise from volcanic vents on the sea floor, where some of the first forms of life may have emerged.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over more than a century, scientists and explorers from the American Museum of Natural History have searched the world and returned with arresting examples of life in all its diversity: dinosaurs from Montana to Mongolia, birds and butterflies, artifacts of exotic cultures from here to the South Sea. For the last four years, their quest has been to collect the stuff of Earth itself and bring it back for a new exhibition illustrating the planet's 4.5 billion-year history.</p>
        <p>On 28 acquisition expeditions, museum teams collected 82 tons of rock and ore ranging from granite and sandstone to gold and platinum. The oldest, a zircon crystal from Australia, is nearly 4.3 billion years old. The youngest, a chunk of sulfur, was picked up the same day it solidified in an Indonesian volcano. The rarest and most intriguing to scientists are sulfide chimneys that rise from volcanic vents on the sea floor, where some of the first forms of life may have emerged.</p>
        <p>Now the collections have been studied, winnowed and arranged for display in the museum's newest permanent exhibition, the Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth, which opens tomorrow.</p>
        <p>Showing off the exhibition, Ellen V. Futter, the museum president, bragged that this was a ''never-before assembled global array'' of specimens integrated with ''the most innovative multimedia technology ever created for a museum hall.''</p>
        <p>Anyone expecting to find the usual drab pieces of rock under glass should be pleasantly surprised. Huge slabs of stone, highly polished and touchable, draw attention to the ingrained beauty and surging dynamism of geology. Video and other graphics offer crisp explanations. A result is an awakening to the motions and changes of the restless world underlying and supporting life.</p>
        <p>The intent, Ms. Futter said, was ''to convey both the majesty of earth and its dynamic, seething innards that yield such cataclysmic explosions as earthquakes, volcanoes, tornadoes, hurricanes and the like, while also presenting the latest, still emerging theories of the origins of life on earth and the possibilities of life beyond.''</p>
        <p>To this end, as Dr. Edmond A. Mathez, a geologist and the chief curator of the hall, explained, the exhibition is organized around five fundamental questions: How has earth evolved? Why are there ocean basins, continents and mountains? How do scientists read rocks? What causes climate and climate change? Why is earth habitable?</p>
        <p>Gazing at the Blue Planet</p>
        <p>In the center of it all, for rest, contemplation and perspective, is a 30-seat granite amphitheater where visitors can look up at an enormous earth globe. It appears to be rotating slowly as a projection system inside the globe shows the planet's surface as seen from space. Stay for 12 minutes and see the familiar landscapes change. The clouds disperse, then continental vegetation disappears, and finally all the blue water of the oceans drains away. The bare, rugged earth stands revealed.</p>
        <p>Off to one side is the ''Earth Event Wall.'' This is an electronic bulletin board bearing news of recent storms, earthquakes and volcanic eruptions, illustrated with television and computer-generated animation. The display is to be updated regularly, providing expert interpretations of how these events illustrate the world's geologic forces.</p>
        <p>At the north end of the hall is another focal point, a large video screen exploding with scenes of rampaging lava, rivers overflowing and glaciers carving terrain. The experience can be visceral. As the sounds of an earthquake fill the hall, those sitting on nearby benches feel the rumble. From one bench it is possible to see the consequences in the face of a crystalline rock. Its layers are offset more than a foot by the slippage of a fault during a major quake.</p>
        <p>Children and not a few grown-ups will enjoy stamping their feet and seeing the tremor, their own ''earthquake,'' recorded as a jagged spike on a seismograph.</p>
        <p>On display also is one of the world's best records of climate change, an ice core from Greenland. The ice is a 115,000-year archive of atmospheric gases, dust and other chemicals from the time the snow first fell. A chart shows the effects in the ice of the eruption of Vesuvius in A.D. 79 and the Clean Air Act in the United States, beginning in 1974.</p>
        <p>Some of the rock specimens can be viewed as a natural art form as well as a lesson in geology. The rippling folds exposed in one rock cutaway are a graceful show of how seemingly brittle material can flow, given enough time and heat. The rock is in easy, tempting reach.</p>
        <p>''You can touch,'' Dr. Mathez said. ''This is a very tactile hall.''</p>
        <p>One approaches a polished specimen of banded iron from Ontario, 2.7 billion years old, with the same impulse. Fingers run over the dark red streaks of jasper. Helpful labels explain the deeper meaning. When single-celled organisms began supplying oxygen to the earth's atmosphere, iron and silica minerals emerged out of the ocean. The red bands in the rock stopped forming once the atmosphere and ocean were saturated with free oxygen. Here, then, were rocks telling of this fateful transition in an evolving earth.</p>
        <p>Another display brings together two sandstones that were, so to speak, separated after birth. They were deposited at the same time near each other, but then the spreading Atlantic Ocean came between them, with one rock ending up in Scotland and the other near Monticello, N.Y.</p>
        <p>It was a striking illustration of continental drift through the shifting of crustal plates, the process known  as plate tectonics.</p>
        <p>Life Under Pressure</p>
        <p>''The present is the key to the past,'' said James Hutton, the 18th-century Scotsman who was among the first to recognize the principles of modern geology. His contributions are acknowledged and explained in one corner of the hall.</p>
        <p>The museum advertises that the rock specimens and 11 full-scale models of classic outcroppings were gathered from 25 countries. But geologists take special pride in some tall heaps of rock, resembling smelting slag, that they sent a robotic vehicle to the bottom of the Pacific Ocean to collect.</p>
        <p>These are the sulfide chimneys, also known as black smokers because they are formed as dark, mineral-laden hot water billows from vents in the sea floor. The museum said these are the first such chimneys ever collected while they were still hot and teeming with strange life. An expedition by the museum and the University of Washington brought them to the surface last summer off the coast of British Columbia.</p>
        <p>It is the microbial and other forms of life found thriving on the chimneys that especially intrigue scientists. These organisms flourish in the absence of sunlight, living on chemicals at crushing pressures. Scientists theorize that early life on earth could have arisen at such places, and life on other planets just might exist in similarly harsh environments.</p>
        <p>Standing before the stark columns of dark rock, Dr. Mathez said, ''This is where the biosphere and geosphere meet in a profound way.''</p>
        <p>The Hall of Planet Earth was developed with the financial support of David S. and Ruth L. Gottesman and was designed by Ralph Appelbaum Associates. It is the first half of the Rose Center for Earth and Space, designed by Polshek Partnership Architects. A new planetarium and hall devoted to cosmology are scheduled to open early next year.</p>
        <p>For the American Museum of Natural History, today the world, next year the universe.</p>
        <p>Outcroppings of Films, Lectures and Tours</p>
        <p>Special activities are planned this weekend to celebrate the opening tomorrow of the David S. and Ruth L. Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth at the American Museum of Natural History, Central Park West at 79th Street, Manhattan. ''Earth, Wind and Cinema,'' a series of films and videos, begins tonight at 7  and runs through Sunday; some of the filmmakers will speak after the screenings. Admission for tonight's screenings is $4 a program, but is free tomorrow and Sunday. Events tomorrow begin at 11 A.M. with a free outdoor celebration featuring the ''eruption'' of a 10-foot volcano, followed by performances of jazz, Dixieland, rock and Latin music, and magic and puppet shows and juggling demonstrations. Unless noted, admission to all events is included in museum admission: $8; $4.50 for children ages 2 to 12; $6 for students and the elderly. Museum hours: Sundays through Thursdays, 10 A.M. to 5:45 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays, 10 A.M. to 8:45 P.M. Information: (212) 769-5100. Tickets: (212) 769-5200. Tour and lecture information: (212) 769-5304. Here is a sampling of weekend events:</p>
        <p>Films</p>
        <p>PROGRAM 1, with ''Rain'' (1929), a silent film directed by Joris Ivens and Mannus Franken, and ''A Tale of the Wind'' (1988, French with English subtitles), directed by Mr. Ivens and Marceline Loridan, tonight at 7.</p>
        <p>PROGRAM 2, with ''Frozen Heart'' (1998), by Stig Andersen and Kenny Sanders, tonight at 9.</p>
        <p>FLEISCHER SUPERMAN CARTOONS (1942), featuring ''The Electric Earthquake,'' ''The Arctic Giant'' and ''Volcano,'' tomorrow at 11:45 A.M.</p>
        <p>''JOURNEY TO THE CENTER OF THE EARTH'' (1959), by Henry Levin, tomorrow at 12:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>''EVEREST -- DEATH ZONE'' (1998), by David Breashears and Liesl Clark, tomorrow at 3 P.M.</p>
        <p>''STROMBOLI'' (1950, English with some Italian), by Roberto Rossellini, tomorrow at 4:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>''UMBRELLAS'' (1996), by Henry Corra, Grahame Weinbren and Albert Maysles, tomorrow at 6:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>''MAN FALLING IN LAVA'' (1999), by Max Rosenthal, and ''THE DAY THE EARTH MOVED'' (1997, Japanese with English subtitles), by Toshio Goto, Sunday at 1:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>''WILD RIVER'' (1960), by Elia Kazan, Sunday at 3:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>Lectures</p>
        <p>''BLACK SMOKER EXPEDITION,'' lecture by Edmond A. Mathez, chief curator of the Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth, with screening of the ''Nova'' film ''Volcanoes of the Deep.'' June 22 at 7 P.M. Admission: $12; $10 for students, the elderly and museum members.</p>
        <p>''PLANET EARTH VIDEO SERIES AND HALL VIEWING,'' Monday lectures by Dr. Rosamond Kinzler, co-curator of the Gottesman Hall of Planet Earth. Mondays through June 28, 6 P.M.</p>
        <p>''ANTARCTIC GEOLOGY AND FOSSILS,'' a lecture by Scott G. Borg, program director at the National Science Foundation. Wednesday night at 7.</p>
        <p>''ANTARCTIC METEORITES: SIFTING THE SANDS OF THE SOLAR SYSTEM,'' lecture by Ralph P. Harvey, assistant professor at Case Western Reserve University. June 23 at 7 P.M.</p>
        <p>''GLACIOLOGY AND CLIMATE,'' lecture by Paul A. Mayewski, a professor at the University of New Hampshire. June 30 at 7 P.M.</p>
        <p>''LIFE AT THE POLE,'' lecture by Helleary D. Everist, deputy director at the National Science Foundation. July 7 at 7 P.M.</p>
        <p>Tours</p>
        <p>''ON THE TRAIL OF THE MANHATTAN SCHIST,'' a look at the Earth's geological processes through an examination of rocks in Central Park. July 8 at 5 and 7 P.M.. Fee: $12; $10 for students, the elderly and museum members.</p>
        <p>''BUILDING -- STONE GEOLOGY,'' an examination of the museum's building stones followed by a discussion of mountain building, lost seas and extinct animals. July 15 at 5 and 7 P.M. Fee: $12; $10 for students, the elderly and museum members.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
