<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 'Bonus' From Mars: Evidence Of Its Past; Glitch Gives a Spacecraft More Time for Photographs</title>
    <meta content="09MARS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1091016"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Global Surveyor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mars (Planet)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DB103FF93AA35750C0A96F958260" item-length="1493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 'Bonus' From Mars: Evidence Of Its Past; Glitch Gives a Spacecraft More Time for Photographs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft snaps hundreds of pictures of landscape, 20 to 40 times as detailed as anything obtained by previous explorations, during year of orbital maneuvering to get it into right position for its primary mission of mapping entire planet; most revealing pictures are taken when craft dips within 100 miles of Martian surface, much closer than its prescribed mapping orbit; photos show towering mountains, layered canyon walls and meandering channels, traces of planet's early history three billion years ago, when conditions on Mars seemed much more hospitable to life than today's cold desert environment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mars is coming into much better focus, so clearly that scientists think they now see in the towering mountains, layered canyon walls and meandering channels telling traces of the planet's early history, when volcanoes belched gases into a denser, warmer atmosphere and rivers flowed across the russet plains. It was a time, more than three billion years ago, when conditions on Mars seemed much more hospitable to life than today's cold desert environment.</p>
        <p>Over the last year, the Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft has looked down from orbit and snapped hundreds of pictures of the landscape that are 20 to 40 times as detailed as anything obtained by previous explorations. And this was not even part of the original mission plan, but an example of a constructive response to adversity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mars is coming into much better focus, so clearly that scientists think they now see in the towering mountains, layered canyon walls and meandering channels telling traces of the planet's early history, when volcanoes belched gases into a denser, warmer atmosphere and rivers flowed across the russet plains. It was a time, more than three billion years ago, when conditions on Mars seemed much more hospitable to life than today's cold desert environment.</p>
        <p>Over the last year, the Mars Global Surveyor spacecraft has looked down from orbit and snapped hundreds of pictures of the landscape that are 20 to 40 times as detailed as anything obtained by previous explorations. And this was not even part of the original mission plan, but an example of a constructive response to adversity.</p>
        <p>When Surveyor reached Mars orbit in September 1997, a malfunction had left its solar-power panels vulnerable to excessive vibrations. The spacecraft had to be maneuvered gingerly into its planned circular orbit for the primary mission of mapping the entire planet. Only now, a year late, has Surveyor reached its intended orbit, ready to start the two-year mapping operation this week.</p>
        <p>Flight controllers at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., checked out all of the spacecraft's systems and scientific instruments last week and reported they were in excellent health and performing normally.</p>
        <p>As eagerly as scientists await the improved maps, which will be used in selecting future landing sites, the delay was made more than bearable by the photographs and other scientific data transmitted while Surveyor was slowly getting into position. The most revealing pictures were taken when the craft dipped within 100 miles of the Martian surface, much closer than its prescribed mapping orbit.</p>
        <p>''We've gotten a bonus mission,'' exulted Dr. Arden L. Albee of the California Institute of Technology, the mission's 72-year-old chief scientist,  who put off retirement twice to be around for this moment. ''You wouldn't design a mission this way, spending so much time before getting to the major objective, but we couldn't be happier with the results.''</p>
        <p>Commenting on the results in a recent issue of the journal Nature, Dr. Maria T. Zuber, a planetary scientist at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said the Surveyor photography provided a spectacular new view of the geological processes that shaped the Martian surface.</p>
        <p>''These images, combined with observations from other orbital sensors and with local views from surface landers, offer the hope of piecing together a self-consistent view of Mars's early climate -- with implications for the development, or not, of early life on the planet,'' Dr. Zuber concluded.</p>
        <p>Some of the pictures revealed unsuspected aspects of familiar landmarks, like Valles Marineris, the canyon stretching 2,400 miles just south of the Mars equator. Shot at oblique angles, the pictures showed for the first time sharply defined horizontal layers in the chasm walls. The dark and bright banding represented layers, each 15 to 165 feet thick, reaching to depths of five miles.</p>
        <p>In an analysis of the pictures, a team of planetary geologists led by Dr. Alfred S. McEwen of the University of Arizona in Tucson concluded that the most likely explanation for the layering was periodic lava flows from repeated volcanic eruptions over much of the history of Mars. The geologists estimated that volcanoes spread 10 times as much lava onto the Martian surface as previously thought, enough to cover an area the size of the United States to a depth of four miles.</p>
        <p>''We conclude that volcanism on early Mars has probably been much more extensive than previously documented, and it must have affected the climate and near-surface environment,'' Dr. McEwen's team reported.</p>
        <p>Such volcanic activity would help explain why Mars appears to have had a thick, warm atmosphere in earlier epochs. Today, the atmosphere there is too cold and thin for liquid water to exist on the surface. But observations by Mariner 9 and two Viking spacecraft in the 1970's surprised scientists with ample examples of deep channels, dry riverbeds, flood plains and other signs of water erosion. This implied a thicker, warmer atmosphere in the past.</p>
        <p>Volcanism would have released substantial amounts of water to the surface and also gases to sustain a significant atmosphere. If the principal gas was carbon dioxide, Mars could have developed greenhouse conditions to retain atmospheric heat and maintain a relatively warm climate.</p>
        <p>Carbon dioxide is the main constituent of today's tenuous Martian atmosphere, but the Surveyor scientists said it had not yet been confirmed that the Martian crust contained sufficient carbonates for volcanoes to have expelled significant amounts of atmospheric carbon dioxide in the past.</p>
        <p>The new findings, Dr. Zuber said, provide more reasons to believe that ''Mars is a superb and arguably unique natural laboratory for the study of climate in the early stage of evolution of the terrestrial planets.''</p>
        <p>Scientists also said the Surveyor pictures showed extensive lava flows near the volcanoes of the Tharsis plateau that appeared to be no older than 40 million to 100 million years. Perhaps the planet still has some volcanic heat churning in its interior.</p>
        <p>The findings provided other clues to the planet's watery past. From previous photography, showing valleys that appeared to start abruptly at almost full size and without tributary channels, it was assumed that flash floods of upwelling ground water were mainly responsible for surface erosion. This left open the question of whether the early Mars environment could sustain flowing surface water for long periods.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael C. Malin of Malin Space Sciences Systems in San Diego and Dr. Michael H. Carr of the United States Geological Survey in Menlo Park, Calif., reported that the new pictures supported the view that ground water, rather than rainfall, played an important role in the formation of most of the water-eroded landscapes. Many of the dry channels appeared to be the result of short-duration floods, presumably fed by frozen reservoirs just beneath the surface. Other scientists suggested that volcanism could have melted these reservoirs and brought the water to the surface.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Malin and Dr. Carr also found the first strong evidence that in some places water had flowed for extended periods over great distances. A prime example is a narrow, meandering valley in Nanedi Valles. Surveyor pictures detected a 600-foot-wide trough at the bottom of the 1.6-mile-wide canyon, indicating to the scientists that flowing water had steadily eroded the channel deeper and deeper over a long period of time.</p>
        <p>Dr. Albee, the chief scientist, said Surveyor's nonphotographic results had also produced important findings. The magnetometer revealed large remnant magnetic fields in the Martian crust, indicating that at one time Mars had a global magnetic field presumably generated by convections in a molten core.</p>
        <p>An analysis of radio signals has shown that the planet's gravity field is lumpy, which may mean that an ancient cratered terrain lies buried under the present crust. And the spacecraft's laser altimeter, measuring variations in surface elevations, has given scientists a more detailed view of the terraced landscape of the north polar cap.</p>
        <p>For its mapping mission, the Surveyor is orbiting Mars from pole to pole, passing over a given part of the planet at the same local time on each orbit. Mapping pictures are to be taken repeatedly of the entire planet from a 250-mile altitude over almost two Earth years, the equivalent of one Mars year.</p>
        <p>Although the global map is mainly intended for interpreting the planet's geologic history and planning future missions, Surveyor will be directed to take special pictures of the borders of the southern polar ice cap in May. The pictures will be used in selecting a safe and interesting landing site for the Polar Lander spacecraft, already on its way for a scheduled landing in December.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
