<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Space Station Astronauts Report Illnesses</title>
    <meta content="Y07STA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1128831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discovery (Space Shuttle)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0D81230F934A3575BC0A96F958260" item-length="1088" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Space Station Astronauts Report Illnesses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>National Aeronautics and Space A</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the last mission to the new International Space Station, several astronauts suffered nausea, headaches and other symptoms that have NASA scrambling for solutions to a suspected air-quality problem before another crew visits the growing outpost.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the crew of the shuttle Discovery did not report the difficulties until debriefings two weeks after their landing, a delay that, some NASA authorities acknowledge, has hampered the search for possible solutions and caused a review of crew procedures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the last mission to the new International Space Station, several astronauts suffered nausea, headaches and other symptoms that have NASA scrambling for solutions to a suspected air-quality problem before another crew visits the growing outpost.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the crew of the shuttle Discovery did not report the difficulties until debriefings two weeks after their landing, a delay that, some NASA authorities acknowledge, has hampered the search for possible solutions and caused a review of crew procedures.</p>
        <p>The seven-member crew returned from the 10-day supply mission on June 6.</p>
        <p>Officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration say they believe unexpected buildups of carbon dioxide, fumes from chemicals used in some components and restricted air circulation may have been the sources of the problem.</p>
        <p>Frank Culbertson, NASA's space station operations manager at the Johnson Space Center in Houston, said that the problems were not serious but that the agency was taking steps to see that they did not recur on future missions.</p>
        <p>NASA did not disclose the health concerns when it became aware of them, but appointed what it calls a ''tiger team'' of agency experts to assess the problem quickly and make recommendations. The agency would not release a preliminary report by the team, citing the crew's medical privacy. But NASA Watch, a private Internet site that follows space issues, posted a copy of a summary report by the group.</p>
        <p>Without naming the specific crew members involved, the report said ''several'' of them experienced symptoms including headaches, burning and itching eyes, facial flush, nausea and one incidence of vomiting while working in the station. Symptoms improved when crew members retreated to the shuttle or used personal ventilator fans while working aboard the station.</p>
        <p>Astronauts, as planned, took air samples as they entered the station and before closing hatches to leave after six days. But, mission managers said, if they had been aware of potential air-quality problems, they would have asked for additional samples.</p>
        <p>''The crew did all the right things and there were no serious effects,'' Mr. Culbertson said. ''Everybody got rid of the symptoms they had very quickly and there were no major problems.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Culbertson acknowledged that lack of timely reporting of problems by the crew made it more difficult to diagnose and fix them. But he said it was the prerogative of each commander and crew to report problems to mission control as they occurred, depending upon how they judged the severity of the issue.</p>
        <p>''The crew felt they understood the problem and handled it appropriately,'' Mr. Culbertson said. ''Every commander is different. Some are more talkative with the ground than others and we are used to that. This isn't an issue.''</p>
        <p>But, he said, NASA managers reviewed agency procedures after the flight and have told crews to take more air samples and inform ground control if such problems surface again on flights.</p>
        <p>The Discovery's mission was led by Comdr. Kent V. Rominger of the Navy, and Lieut. Col. Rick D. Husband of the Air Force was the pilot. The other members of the international crew were three NASA astronauts, Daniel T. Barry, Tamara E. Jernigan and Ellen Ochoa; Julie Payette of Canada, and Col. Valery I. Tokarev of the Russian Air Force.</p>
        <p>Dr. David Robertson, director of the Center for Space Physiology and Medicine at Vanderbilt University, said air quality in spacecraft was important and something that could easily be addressed.</p>
        <p>Dr. Robertson said that timely reporting of health problems in space was ''very desirable and very important'' and that astronauts sometimes had to be reminded of this.</p>
        <p>''Astronauts need to keep mission control fully informed of health events, and I think they are doing that pretty well now,'' he said, ''This was not the case 20 or 30 years ago when some people tried to suppress problems because they had a test-pilot mentality and didn't want to disclose something that might be considered a weakness.''</p>
        <p>The International Space Station, which is to grow into a $60 billion complex the size of a football field, now consists of two of an expected score of modules and major components. The Russian-made Zarya work module is attached to the American Unity connecting hub, forming a unit 77 feet tall and weighing 70,000 pounds. The Discovery flight delivered more than 4,300 pounds of equipment and water for future crews, and allowed astronauts to repair equipment.</p>
        <p>The third component is the Russian Zvezda service module, which is to provide living quarters and laboratory space during the early stages of station construction. This module is to be launched in November, followed by an American shuttle mission in December to perform more station outfitting.</p>
        <p>The Zvezda module contains filters and other air circulation and cleaning equipment that should eliminate unwanted buildups of carbon dioxide and fumes in the station, NASA officials said.</p>
        <p>The NASA experts investigating the Discovery incident said most symptoms were reported by crew members working in the Zarya unit when two or more worked closely for long periods and wall panels to components were open, possibly blocking the circulation of fresh air from the shuttle. Under conditions of weightlessness when there is no normal air convection to help carry away gases, experts said, carbon dioxide breathed out by the astronauts and fumes from solvents and other construction materials could have built up to unhealthy levels.</p>
        <p>For the next shuttle mission to the station, NASA's assessment team  suggested, the crew should carry personal air monitors and do more sampling. In addition, it said, NASA should re-evaluate the station's air circulation system design, consider the possibility of sending up temporary duct work with the shuttle to force more fresh air through the station, look into installing an extra carbon dioxide scrubber or filter in the complex and look at the potential of flushing old air out of station modules as they are activated.</p>
        <p>The team noted that there was a potential longer-term impact to the air-quality question. When the first permanent crew of three astronauts arrives in a Russian Soyuz space capsule next year, it said, there will be no American shuttle attached to act as a haven in case something goes wrong with the air supply.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
