<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Across a Parched Land, Signs of a Hotter Era</title>
    <meta content="01WARM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1127710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle Atlantic States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DB1031F932A3575BC0A96F958260" item-length="1327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Across a Parched Land, Signs of a Hotter Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts say heat wave and drought engulfing much of US do not measure up to those of 1988 but that in parts of Middle Atlantic States the drought is of a severity occurring only about twice in a hundred years; heat appears to extend what scientists say is national trend toward more extreme summer temperatures since World War II; that trend, in turn, accompanies a warming of American climate that in some places, including northern tier and parts of Middle Atlantic region and Northeast, has amounted to 2 to 5 degrees over the last century; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In this season of heat and drought, with New York sweltering through the hottest July on record, the Middle Atlantic States turning brown and scores of people dying across the country, the question arises again:</p>
        <p>Is something new and different going on with the weather?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In this season of heat and drought, with New York sweltering through the hottest July on record, the Middle Atlantic States turning brown and scores of people dying across the country, the question arises again:</p>
        <p>Is something new and different going on with the weather?</p>
        <p>Clearly, experts say, the heat wave and drought of 1999 do not yet rival some of the great bake-offs of the past, most recently that of 1988, which seared most of the country for weeks. That one made global warming a byword, even though it was brought about by a case of natural atmospheric gridlock that held the heat and dryness in place.</p>
        <p>A similarly intractable natural pattern has locked into place this time, and although it has not yet reproduced the vast scale and long duration of 1988's heat and drought, it has nonetheless made a mark on climatic history. In parts of the Middle Atlantic region, the drought is of a severity occurring only about twice in a hundred years, on average.</p>
        <p>And in July, there were 11 days when the temperature reached 95 degrees or more in Central Park. Never had it been so hot so often in any one month since records were first kept in 1869. ''That's incredible,'' said Lee Grenci, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University.</p>
        <p>High temperatures like those in New York and elsewhere this summer appear to extend what Federal scientists say is a national trend toward more extreme summer temperatures since World War II. That trend, in turn, accompanies a warming of the American climate that in some places, including the nation's northern tier and parts of the Middle Atlantic region and the Northeast, has amounted to 2 to 5 degrees over the last century, on an annual average, according to scientists at the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C.</p>
        <p>Nationally and globally, the warming trend is smaller, as some areas of both the country and the rest of the world have cooled. The average annual surface temperature of the earth has risen by about 1 degree or a little more in the 20th century, and that of the contiguous 48 states by a little less, according to the climatic data center. The warming is greater at night and in the winter. By comparison, the earth is 5 to 9 degrees warmer now than in the depths of the last ice age some 18,000 to 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>Mainstream scientists project that the average surface temperature of the globe will rise 2 to 6 more degrees in the 21st century if emissions of heat-trapping waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide are not reduced. If that happens, the scientists say, summer heat waves will probably become more frequent, with nights becoming especially hot and droughts becoming worse.</p>
        <p>For all that, few if any experts go so far as to attribute any individual heat waves like the recent one -- or even the observed trend toward more extreme summer heat -- directly to global warming. The most they say is that the heat records are in line with what is to be expected in a warming atmosphere. Much clearer, they say, are the immediate causes of the 1999 heat and drought.</p>
        <p>Though heat and drought often go together, they are in some sense separate phenomena. Large-scale patterns of atmospheric circulation determine where it rains and does not, and these are what have decreed crop destruction and brown lawns from northern Virginia through eastern Pennsylvania. The drought began a year ago and intensified over the winter, thanks to a circulation pattern associated with La Nina, a natural occurrence of abnormally cool water in the tropical Pacific that sets off a characteristic pattern of atmospheric chain reactions.</p>
        <p>One consequence of La Nina was that winter storm tracks in North America shifted westward, making the Middle Atlantic region already relatively dry before summer arrived. When it did, the jet stream, the high-altitude, west-to-east river of air that carries storms and precipitation across the landscape, moved unusually far to the north, said Mark Svoboda of the National Drought Mitigation Center at the University of Nebraska in Lincoln. Its path missed most of the country, further depriving it of moisture.</p>
        <p>Finally, a semipermanent atmospheric feature over the Atlantic Ocean, called the Bermuda High, has settled in this summer in such a position that it has directed unusually hot tropical air into the Middle Atlantic states and the Northeast, said Fred Gadomski, another Penn State meteorologist.</p>
        <p>The convergence of drought and heat in the region has made both worse. Heat intensifies drought by increasing evaporation from the soil. Where there is no water left, the heat that would be spent in evaporation instead goes into warming the surface. Completing a destructive feedback loop, the warmer surface heats the air even more.</p>
        <p>Until about mid-July, most of the super heat was confined to the Northeast and Middle Atlantic states. But then the Bermuda High expanded greatly, moving well into the country's midsection and even the north-central United States. Yet another high-pressure area, in the Pacific, created what Mr. Grenci called an immovable ''phalanx'' of linked weather systems. The result was to  pump tropical air into the Northeast, Midwest and upper Plains, sending temperatures into triple digits in city after city and causing more than 100 deaths in the last two weeks.</p>
        <p>In the summer of 1988, a similar continent-sized mass of hot air, also coupled with a jet stream displaced unusually far to the north, cast the eastern two-thirds of the nation into drought and extreme heat. Then, 35 percent of the country was in extreme drought, said Mr. Svoboda, compared with around 15 percent now. The scope of the present drought ''pales in comparison to the great droughts'' of the past, said Mr. Gadomski. But Mr. Svoboda said the Middle Atlantic drought is now rivaling a major drought experienced by the region in the early 1960's.</p>
        <p>One consequence of this summer's heat and drought has been the record string of hot days in Central Park. The city is closing in on the record of 16 95-degree days for an entire summer, set in 1955.</p>
        <p>A notable aspect of the heat wave, said Mr. Gadomski, is that nights have been especially warm. The frequency of nights in which extreme heat combines with high humidity appears to have increased substantially since the 1940's, according to a 1998 study by Dian J. Gaffen and Rebecca J. Ross of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Air Resources Laboratory in Silver Spring, Md.</p>
        <p>This combination of extreme nighttime heat and humidity is a heat wave's most serious threat to health and life, many experts say, and the Gaffen-Ross study found that in some places, the frequency with which this combination exceeded a lethal threshold had doubled.</p>
        <p>What caused the increasing trend toward extreme heat? Some of it may be accounted for by increasing urbanization, said Dr. Gaffen; concrete absorbs more heat than foliage. But global warming may also be part of the explanation, she said.</p>
        <p>The National Weather Service has forecast a return to normal temperatures this week in New York City and the Northeast, as the gridlock in the skies eases enough to allow the jet stream and a trailing cold front to dip well down into the country.</p>
        <p>One red flag for the future: dryness associated with La Nina, expected to persist through the winter.</p>
        <p>What would kill the drought is one of two eventualities: the inevitable re-advance southward of the moisture-bearing jet stream as fall approaches, or tropical storms.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
