<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Campaign, Trailing Among Women, Sharpens Its Pitch to Them</title>
    <meta content="Y06GOR$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1121408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Henneberger, Melinda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E2DE1E3DF935A35754C0A96F958260" item-length="1648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Campaign, Trailing Among Women, Sharpens Its Pitch to Them</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA HENNEBERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Henneberger, Melinda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore's 2000 Presidential campaign is reaching out to women as polls suggest American women, who have heavily favored Democrats in recent elections, prefer Gov George W Bush Jr, Republican frontrunner; political consultants from both parties say disenchantment may be evidence of displaced anger over Pres Clinton's relationship with Monica S Lewinsky; Gore expresses surprise that anyone could think he might somehow end up taking fall for Lewinsky scandal; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first thing Al Gore mentioned in every speech last week was that his oldest daughter was past her due date and about to make him and his wife of 29 years grandparents. (Wyatt Gore Schiff, 6 pounds 3 ounces, finally arrived on the Fourth of July, timing that the Vice President will surely mention in future speeches.)</p>
        <p>The second thing he told crowds was that he had been reared by a mother who grew up poor, got on a bus to Nashville with her blind sister in tow, waited tables for quarter tips and, in 1936, became one of the first women to graduate from Vanderbilt Law School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first thing Al Gore mentioned in every speech last week was that his oldest daughter was past her due date and about to make him and his wife of 29 years grandparents. (Wyatt Gore Schiff, 6 pounds 3 ounces, finally arrived on the Fourth of July, timing that the Vice President will surely mention in future speeches.)</p>
        <p>The second thing he told crowds was that he had been reared by a mother who grew up poor, got on a bus to Nashville with her blind sister in tow, waited tables for quarter tips and, in 1936, became one of the first women to graduate from Vanderbilt Law School.</p>
        <p>When he listened as a child to the daily back and forth between his parents, ''it was clear to me that men and women were equal -- if not more so,'' Mr. Gore said, drawing whoops from his listeners at every stop.</p>
        <p>In his run for the White House, the Vice President is aggressively pursuing female voters, the increasingly important bloc that so far seems to favor George W. Bush slightly. And the pitch is not terribly subtle.</p>
        <p>Whenever possible, Mr. Gore is introduced to his audiences by a woman. (Christine Meyer, the mother of a 3-year-old cancer survivor, did the honors before his Philadelphia speech last week supporting cancer research. ''I said my husband is really the speaker,'' Ms. Meyer said in an interview, ''but they said no, we want you to do it. They wanted a mom's perspective.'')</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore steps onstage to the tune of ''Rock This Country,'' a country song by a female vocalist, Shania Twain. A campaign video focuses primarily on him as husband and father, with his daughter Karenna Schiff repeatedly assuring viewers that her dad is so funny.</p>
        <p>Then comes his standard stump speech, chock full of talk about day care, early-childhood education and gender equality. ''This pledge,'' he says, ''is in honor of my mother: an equal day's pay for an equal day's work.''</p>
        <p>He promises also to ''fight for the ability to balance work and family''  and ''to shield our children from gun violence.'' And his biggest applause line is usually his vow to ''make sure we have high-quality preschool available for every child.''</p>
        <p>This wildly woman-friendly agenda is not a poll-tested new focus for the Vice President. Mr. Gore has worked on these issues throughout his public life, co-sponsoring early versions of the Family and Medical Leave Act in the Senate and a series of bills on women's health in the House as far back as the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>He opposed Federal financing of  abortion early in his House career, but has been a supporter of abortion rights for many years and was a Senate co-sponsor of a bill that would have made a Federal statute of Roe v. Wade. He has surrounded himself with accomplished women who have become some of his closest aides, and he is considered by his staff to be an unusually family-friendly employer.</p>
        <p>Still, his campaign is without question reacting to polls suggesting that at least at this early date, American women, who have heavily favored Democrats in recent elections, seem to prefer Mr. Bush, an opponent of abortion.</p>
        <p>David Beckwith, a Bush spokesman, said the Governor's ''compassionate conservatism'' appealed to everybody. Even when Mr. Bush ran for governor in 1994 against a female incumbent, Ann Richards, there was virtually no gender gap, Mr. Beckwith noted: 49 percent of Texas women who went to the polls, like 53 percent of the men, supported Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Though women favored Bill Clinton over Bob Dole by 16 percentage points in 1996, one recent CNN poll had them backing Mr. Bush over Mr. Gore by 11 points. (The Vice President was farther behind among men, by 21 points.)</p>
        <p>Political consultants from both parties see the Gore numbers at least in part as evidence of displaced anger over the President's relationship with Monica Lewinsky. Even Mr. Gore's new pollster, Celinda Lake, agrees that the Lewinsky scandal appears to be suppressing his ratings with women.</p>
        <p>''There's been a delayed reaction to the Clinton factor that's unfair to Gore,'' said Ms. Lake, who specializes in tracking female voters and was brought on last week to help the campaign figure them out. ''But to women, the personal is political. As they get to know him, they'll see he's quite un-Clintonesque in that regard.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, the Vice President expressed surprise that anyone could think he might somehow wind up taking the fall for the Lewinsky scandal. ''I don't buy it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Certainly his campaign is working hard to make sure that does not  happen, recruiting women to fill the seats at his events, to come and hear his direct appeals. ''Working to close that gap,'' Ms. Lake said, ''is one of the most important tasks of the campaign.''</p>
        <p>After receiving from the headquarters of Mr. Gore's Pennsylvania campaign ''three begging phone calls indicating they need women,''  Maureen Kelly, a Pittsburgh lawyer, agreed to attend a fund-raising luncheon last week, at a discounted rate. Patricia McGrail, another lawyer, attended with her and also got a discount, paying $300, she said, for the $1,000 ticket.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kelly responded positively to Mr. Gore's remarks, and said: ''I feel bad for him. People are going to associate him with Clinton, when in fact he embodies the values most women want to see.''</p>
        <p>In private, Mr. Gore talks about the important women in his life with a respect that does suggest, as several women who heard him speak last week said, that ''he gets it.''</p>
        <p>As he chatted on Air Force Two, in a conversation that was initially off the record, the Vice President's mind was on his pregnant daughter. Would he cancel his schedule when she went into labor?</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' he said. ''You want to run to the hospital and be right there with her, but then again. . . .</p>
        <p>''Got to give her her space,'' he said, laughing at himself. ''Her mother has perfect pitch on this stuff, so I guess I'll just follow her lead.''</p>
        <p>(Mr. Gore also disclosed that while environmentalists are split over Pampers vis-a-vis cloth diapers, he favors the easy way out. ''That's not a hard call,'' he joked. ''Global warming is hard. Pampers are easy.'')</p>
        <p>Most of the women attending Gore campaign events at this point are active Democrats, of course. But during three days of almost nonstop campaign events last week, a number of women said, essentially, that they felt he was pandering, yes, and maybe even desperate -- yet also totally sincere.</p>
        <p>While commentators have primarily looked at the ways in which Mr. Gore is not enough like Mr. Clinton as a campaigner, his audiences seemed to be focusing more on what the Vice President said than on how he said it. They liked the story about his mother, and they loved the line ''I'm running to make America not just better off, but better.''</p>
        <p>At a reception in Philadelphia, one supporter, Lynne Gold-Bikin, said she had been appalled by the poll numbers showing women favoring Mr. Bush -- ''that Texan,'' as she called him.</p>
        <p>''How any woman,'' she said, ''could prefer the Governor of the state that pushes Tom DeLay and Dick Armey, who are so anti-woman I can't even think about it, over this man who is pro-choice and has this wonderful, exciting wife? I don't understand.''</p>
        <p>In Miami, at yet another fund-raising luncheon, Mayor Alex Penelas announced to Mr. Gore: ''The real person who should be introducing you is my wife. If you say you're not voting for Al Gore, she'll punch you in the nose. And she's the Republican in the family.''</p>
        <p>When she did come to the microphone, Mrs. Penelas was as believable as she was enthusiastic: ''Most people I tell them my father was Basque, they say, 'What is that?' '' When she told Mr. Gore, however, ''he told me all about their customs, he gave me an education on the Basque people -- now I say, that's knowledge.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore took it from there, and started in with how excited he was  about becoming an abuelo (a grandfather), racing through this one Spanish word as if someone had told him that the key to fluency was talking fast.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Elsa Lopez, a single mother among his listeners, said she felt he had been talking to her. ''We need quality day care,'' she said, ''not some ranch to farm these kids out on.''</p>
        <p>''Education, and choice -- my daughter just turned 4, but I decided to have her -- these things are all key,'' said Ms. Lopez, a former Republican who now works for the teachers' union and said she was thrilled to have received a free ticket to the $1,000 event.</p>
        <p>Not all women were wowed, of course, by the candidate or his focus on them.</p>
        <p>''He kept bringing up women's issues,'' said Ms. McGrail, the Pittsburgh lawyer, who is a Democrat and the mother of three.</p>
        <p>''I felt like he was dealing with soft issues,'' she said. ''I'm 44 years old; I'm too old for that. I wanted to hear about something more relevant to my life, like economic development.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the presentation she heard seems to have convinced Ms. McGrail that Mr. Gore is probably too sensitive to lead the country, and at this point she is thinking of supporting Elizabeth Dole.</p>
        <p>''Not because she's a woman,'' Ms. McGrail said, ''but because I think she'd be a strong leader. She's tough.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
