<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Heavy Smog Adds Insult To Misery</title>
    <meta content="01SMOG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1127690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDE1031F932A3575BC0A96F958260" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Heavy Smog Adds Insult To Misery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, July 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State records highest ozone levels, or smog, since late 1980's, and worst of it blankets New York City and its suburbs; main culprit is the oppressive heat, since ozone is created when other chemicals cook in sunlight on hot days (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As New Yorkers endure one of the hottest summers on record, they are also suffering a curse that compounds their lethargy and sense of ill-being: the worst smog in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>Levels of ozone, a toxic chemical that burns the lungs, stings the eyes and can dim vistas with a brown haze, are the highest since the late 1980's, records kept by the State Department of Environmental Conservation show, and as usual, the worst of it has blanketed New York City and its suburbs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As New Yorkers endure one of the hottest summers on record, they are also suffering a curse that compounds their lethargy and sense of ill-being: the worst smog in more than a decade.</p>
        <p>Levels of ozone, a toxic chemical that burns the lungs, stings the eyes and can dim vistas with a brown haze, are the highest since the late 1980's, records kept by the State Department of Environmental Conservation show, and as usual, the worst of it has blanketed New York City and its suburbs.</p>
        <p>The state has already exceeded the Federal standard for ozone pollution more times this year than it did in each of the last seven years, and there are still two months to go in the May-to-September smog season. Even upstate areas that are used to relatively clean air have had a few days this year that were smoggy enough to violate the Federal clean-air standard.</p>
        <p>Ozone levels in New York State have generally declined over the last two decades -- this year's figures would not have been unusual in the 1970's. The main culprit for this year's upward spike is the oppressive heat. Ozone is created when other chemicals cook in sunlight on hot days.</p>
        <p>''We're looking at a combination of things, starting with the heat, but including power plants working harder to keep up with record demand, and people doing more driving,'' said Peter M. Iwanowicz, director of environmental health at the American Lung Association of New York State.</p>
        <p>Put simply, ozone makes it hard to breathe, particularly for the elderly, small children, people who are exerting themselves and those with lung diseases. It burns the lungs much the way sun burns the skin.</p>
        <p>''Years of exposure can do serious damage,'' Mr. Iwanowicz said. ''It impairs the ability to fight off infection, in kids especially, and it can aggravate the trouble that heart and lung patients already have breathing, which can be fatal.''</p>
        <p>Ozone can set off asthma attacks, and experts say it contributes to New York City's highest-in-the-nation levels of asthma. A study released a few days ago showed that hospitalizations for asthma attacks in the city's low-income neighborhoods were far more frequent than was previously known.</p>
        <p>The New York metropolitan area is one of several around the country classified by the Federal Government as being in ''severe nonattainment'' of ozone standards, the second-worst category. Only Los Angeles and its near suburbs are in the worst category, ''extreme nonattainment.'' Those grouped with New York include the Chicago, Houston, Milwaukee, Baltimore and Sacramento metropolitan areas, and two areas on the outskirts of Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Ozone is not the only form of air pollution -- the Environmental Protection Agency monitors and sets standards for six lung irritants -- but in many urban areas it is the most severe, and it is the one commonly referred to as smog.</p>
        <p>About one-third of atmospheric nitrogen oxides, the main chemicals that contribute to ozone, come from electric power plants. Environmentalists say this summer's ozone problem provides more evidence that New York State and the Federal Government should make old power plants meet the same emissions standards as new ones.</p>
        <p>Coal-burning plants built in the 1940's and 50's emit 15 to 20 times as many nitrogen oxides as new gas-burning plants, while generating the same amount of power.</p>
        <p>The Pataki administration plans to achieve much of what environmental groups are asking for on nitrogen oxides, requiring that power producers reduce emissions of the chemicals by 10 percent this year from last year. By 2003, they must have cut the emissions by 70 percent from 1990 levels.</p>
        <p>''No state is doing more,'' said John Cahill, the state's Environmental Conservation Commissioner. ''We require more stringent controls on those facilities than are used in any other state.''</p>
        <p>He also pointed to a law the state enacted last year requiring heavy trucks to go through the same periodic inspections that cars are subject to, including meeting the standards for tailpipe emissions.</p>
        <p>But as state officials are quick to note, many of New York's air pollutants, including those that contribute to ozone and acid rain, blow in from states to the west. No one knows quite how many arrive that way, but Mr. Cahill said, ''New York State could shut down every facility and still have a problem.''</p>
        <p>Vehicles, another major source of nitrogen oxides, have also contributed to rising ozone levels, as people drive more each year and more of them drive sport utility vehicles and trucks that are not subject to the same emissions standards as cars.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. plans to close that loophole, which Mr. Cahill called ''a very, very important, a critical component'' of cutting smog.</p>
        <p>The state measures ozone levels continuously at 31 sites around the state. By last Sunday, those sites had recorded 25 violations of the Federal ozone standard, the most in any year since 1991, when there were 26 for the entire year. Department of Environmental Conservation officials said there might have been a few more readings that exceeded the limit in the last week, but the data were still being collected.</p>
        <p>Under a more stringent standard the E.P.A. adopted last year -- a standard that is being challenged in court -- there were 169 violations by last Sunday, compared with 162 for all of last year.</p>
        <p>Department officials said that if the new standard had been in place, there would have been 156 violations in 1997, and just 84 in 1996.</p>
        <p>This year, the monitoring station at Susan E. Wagner High School on Staten Island has recorded violations of the new standard on 15 days, the worst of any station in the state, followed by the World Trade Center site with 14 and the Riverhead site on Long Island with 13.</p>
        <p>Ozone molecules are composed of three oxygen atoms, rather than the two atoms that oxygen molecules usually contain. Ozone is created near ground level when the sun acts on nitrogen oxides emitted by smokestacks and tailpipes, combined with various hydrocarbons.</p>
        <p>Usually, the more severe the heat wave, the worse the ozone. But it is an unstable chemical that breaks down easily, so it dissipates quickly when the weather turns cool or when the chemicals needed to create it are not present.</p>
        <p>Ground-level ozone is not to be confused with the ozone layer in the upper atmosphere, which protects earth from the sun's ultraviolet radiation.</p>
        <p>Ground-level ozone confers no such benefit, and does not reach the upper atmosphere before breaking down, while upper-level ozone is too distant to harm people.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
