<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Master Planner's Big Picture</title>
    <meta content="30KOPP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1111232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppelman, Lee E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04EFD91131F933A05756C0A96F958260" item-length="3019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Master Planner's Big Picture</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>STONY BROOK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of longtime Long Island Regional Planning Board director Lee E Koppelman, who has supported mass transit, more apartments and subsidized housing despite opposition from some officials and residents and has been instrumental in shaping look of Long Island; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE voters never elected Lee E. Koppelman to anything. If he had run for office, he probably would have been roundly defeated. Yet for nearly four decades he has endured as Long Island's master planner, spanning Republican and Democratic regimes and surviving demands for his ouster from both sides of the aisle.</p>
        <p>''He's outlasted his enemies and everybody else,'' said Patrick Halpin, a former Suffolk County Executive who resisted calls for the planner's removal. ''He has provided continuity from administration to administration and continues to serve as the institutional memory for modern Suffolk County.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE voters never elected Lee E. Koppelman to anything. If he had run for office, he probably would have been roundly defeated. Yet for nearly four decades he has endured as Long Island's master planner, spanning Republican and Democratic regimes and surviving demands for his ouster from both sides of the aisle.</p>
        <p>''He's outlasted his enemies and everybody else,'' said Patrick Halpin, a former Suffolk County Executive who resisted calls for the planner's removal. ''He has provided continuity from administration to administration and continues to serve as the institutional memory for modern Suffolk County.''</p>
        <p>To his many critics, Dr. Koppelman seemed out of synch. Politically, he was perceived as a not-very-closeted big-government liberal Democrat, at odds with the electorate's conservative Republican tilt. In this bastion of balkanized home rule, he touted regional approaches, but nevertheless after his long efforts there his agency remains the only form of bicounty government on the Island, and it has powers only to recommend, not to enforce.</p>
        <p>Yet in a culture founded on the automobile and single-family homes, he preached mass transit and more apartments. He even advocated subsidized housing, which suburban Berlitz translates into racial minorities -- and political suicide.</p>
        <p>Despite it all, Dr. Koppelman not only persevered but -- perhaps more than any other living person -- has also left a lasting imprint on Long Island.</p>
        <p>Many of his utopian dreams remain on the drawing boards. But numerous pet projects that seemed so revolutionary when he first proposed them decades ago -- like protecting coastal wetlands and the underground water supply, creating Suffolk County's park system and preserving the Pine Barrens, the Peconic River Valley, farmland and other open space -- are now codified into law.</p>
        <p>''All those things were well ahead of contemporary thinking at the time; now they are taken for granted,'' said John V. N. Klein, another former Suffolk County Executive and a Republican. Mr. Halpin, a Democrat, said: ''Long Island would be a much different place -- for the worse -- without Lee Koppelman.''</p>
        <p>Although preserving open space is popular today, Dr. Koppelman remembers when politicians called it crazy. ''They would say, 'Why do we have to spend money to buy open space? That's all we have out here. We have to get rid of it.' ''</p>
        <p>Some critics remain. ''Fortunately Lee Koppelman wasn't able to accomplish too much of what he wanted,'' said the longtime chairman of the Nassau Conservative Party, John J. O'Leary. ''The key to our disagreements with him is he's been the great proponent of regional government, and we've always been for local control.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Klein, Mr. Halpin and a string of eight other county executives in Nassau and Suffolk have dealt with Dr. Koppelman in his appointed post of executive director of the Long Island Regional Planning Board, an unpaid job he has held since its creation in 1965.</p>
        <p>Before that, he was Suffolk's first planning director, starting in 1960, and kept that title while taking on the regional planning job. In 1988, he left the  county post to become director of the Center for Regional Policy Studies at the State University at Stony Brook, where he commands a seventh-floor view over the campus treetops.</p>
        <p>These days Dr. Koppelman, who turned 72 this month, is recovering from hip surgery and walks stiffly with a cane. But his mind and his vision for Long Island remain as sharp as ever. His self-deprecating wit is also undimmed. Referring to the Lee E. Koppelman Nature Preserve near Montauk Point, dedicated 10 years ago, he said, ''I presume the politicians wanted to make it posthumous.''</p>
        <p>His early career followed the footsteps of his father, a landscape architect and florist who had an elite clientele in Manhattan and in the early movie studios of Astoria. As a teen-ager, Dr. Koppelman says he was influenced by the writings of the  critic and historian Lewis Mumford.</p>
        <p>Asked about the roots of his concern for the needy, he reached further back.</p>
        <p>''It probably started when I was in the third grade,'' he said. ''I can remember the teacher, a red-headed woman. She assigned us to write about what would you do if you had a million dollars. Now this was at the height of the Depression -- you couldn't even imagine such a thing. Some wrote about 'these are all the toys I want' or 'I would get a house for my parents.' ''</p>
        <p>For a moment, Dr. Koppelman's eyes seemed to get misty. ''I wrote a paper on the ideal city,'' he said. ''There would be housing for everybody, industry and jobs for all the fathers. So I must have been a socialist utopian at the age of 9.''</p>
        <p>Still, his career as a planner began by accident. A young landscape architect with a successful practice, he moved from Queens and became active in Hauppauge civic affairs in the 1950's. ''My first encounter with him was when he was a civic gadfly and I was a town attorney,'' Mr. Klein recalled. ''He was a royal pain.''</p>
        <p>Before long, Dr. Koppelman said, ''I did a comprehensive plan for my own community. It was a freebie.'' He unveiled it in 1959 at a local meeting whose audience -- unknown to him -- included H. Lee Dennison. After the presentation, Mr. Dennison, a maverick Republican who had just been elected County Executive as a Democrat, jumped up and outlined his own plans for all of Suffolk, from highways to marinas.</p>
        <p>A few days later Dr. Koppelman was summoned to Mr. Dennison's office in Port Jefferson. They talked at cross purposes, with Dr. Koppelman focusing on saving a particular land parcel. ''Finally Dennison banged the table and said, 'Are you going to work for me or not?' It hit me like a bolt of lightning.'' Dr. Koppelman accepted the planning post as a part-time job paying $6,340. ''I had no intention of staying 40 years.''</p>
        <p>At first, the two Lees shared not only the same office but even the same desk, with the large-framed county executive towering over the planner. ''It was like Mutt and Jeff,'' Dr. Koppelman said. He served as a top lieutenant as Mr. Dennison transformed Suffolk government, creating countywide agencies for police, parks, public works, civil service, sewers and other services.</p>
        <p>Dr. Koppelman's first priority was to save environmentally vital sites that ''stood in the path of suburbanization,'' he said. ''City planners would first address land use zoning, then transportation and institutions, and whatever was left over was for parks. I reversed the process.''</p>
        <p>But he suffered an early setback at the hands of another Island titan, the master builder Robert Moses. When Suffolk officials resisted spending money to buy open space to match state funds controlled by Moses, Dr. Koppelman found Federal money the county could use for the match. But then, he said, Moses got the state Legislature to bar such local substitutions -- and stole the concept by getting the Federal money added directly to his state program.</p>
        <p>''I learned my first lesson from Moses,'' Dr. Koppelman said of the episode. ''My relationship with Moses was sometimes stormy. The word 'planner' was anathema to him. We would raise questions like, for example, why the Long Island Expressway didn't have a mass transit rail running down the median. He was totally opposed. So I was another of those pointy-headed, long-haired pains.''</p>
        <p>Although Dr. Koppelman describes himself as politically independent and above party machinations, he has often run circles around the pols. Desmond M. Ryan, director of the Association for a Better Long Island, a developers' group, said: ''He is a political entity unto himself.''</p>
        <p>The secret? Dr. Koppelman said: ''The politicians could never figure out what the source of strength was. My secret was somewhat like Robert Moses. He had Gov. Al Smith, and for the first 12 years, I had Lee Dennison. I was untouchable.'' At least until Mr. Dennison retired.</p>
        <p>Another key to Dr. Koppelman's early success was the coverage he curried in the news media, especially Newsday, and the editorial support he drew. Newsday -- which saw its own mission as a unifying force for Long Island -- was a natural vehicle for Dr. Koppelman and his regional approach. His reports, statistics and ready quotations supplied an endless stream of articles.</p>
        <p>It was Newsday that in the early 60's pushed the formation of a regional planning agency to promote cooperation between Suffolk and Nassau Counties.</p>
        <p>When the agency was established in 1965, Leonard Hall, the former Republican national chairman and a key figure in Dwight D. Eisenhower's election as president, was named chairman Dr. Koppelman got the job as the its executive director.</p>
        <p>''I probably sent the shortest resume in history,'' Dr. Koppelman said. ''It had my name and phone number and one sentence: 'I can do the job'. ''</p>
        <p>Although Dr. Koppelman had never met Mr. Hall before, the two strong personalities hit it off. ''He said: 'Dennison thinks you're a genius,' '' Dr. Koppelman recalled. ''I thought, 'What a crock, just like a politician.' But then he leaned close and said, 'You know and I know you can't be as good as they say.' '' I thought, 'Boy, this is somebody I can learn from.' ''</p>
        <p>Eventually, though, Mr. Hall came to share Mr. Dennison's appraisal.  Owen Smith, who was the board's counsel and is researching Mr. Hall's biography, said: ''Leonard Hall described Lee as one of the most brilliant men he ever knew.''</p>
        <p>But Nassau officials gave Dr. Koppelman a chilly reception. Not only was he a suspected liberal Democrat, but he was an outsider from rival Suffolk at a time when its growth began outstripping Nassau's. ''It didn't take the political forces in Nassau too long to consider me a pariah,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With civil rights groups threatening to take some of Nassau's towns to court for exclusionary zoning, Dr. Koppelman's talk of apartments and subsidized projects violated the political taboo on housing. ''Politicians in Nassau didn't even want to hear that word in those days,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He may have outsmarted himself with his impolitic views. ''The politicians were so worried, they were in a hurry to get rid of the land at Mitchel Field for other uses,'' he said. ''We were locked out of Mitchel Field. Nassau did not do a planning job there, so now you have warehouses sitting on some of the most valuable land in the county, worth $1 million an acre.''</p>
        <p>Those opportunities missed in the 60's and 70's have come full circle, with Dr. Koppelman trying to help Nassau's belated efforts to mold the random development there into a Nassau hub. He is intrigued by the possibility of a light rail or monorail link to the Long Island Rail Road, to give access to Roosevelt Field and Mitchel Field for Suffolk and New York City residents -- without drawing more traffic. But once again, there is local resistance, this time from Westbury. ''From a planning point of view, it's logical,'' he said, ''but from a political point of view, we got our heads handed to us.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Dennison announced his retirement in 1971, he asked Dr. Koppelman if he wanted to be county executive, ''but I had no interest in politics,'' Dr. Koppelman said. The voters elected Mr. Klein, a Republican. ''A lot of people thought that when John came in,'' said Dr. Koppelman, ''I would get the heave-ho.''</p>
        <p>Critics were indeed after the planner's scalp, Mr. Klein said. ''Certain party elders said, 'When you get elected, the first person to go is Koppelman,' to which I said, 'Don't count on it. When I actually was elected, the pressure got rather intense, because he was viewed as a Democrat and a tool of Dennison. It was that simple and that primitive. I said, 'Nothing doing,' and Lee and I had a great relationship, not only professionally but personally.''</p>
        <p>His repeated survivals reflected more than political agility. ''His knowledge is so encyclopedic that anybody coming into office would have to be a stone idiot not to rely on him,'' said Matthew T. Crosson, president of the Long Island Association, the business group.</p>
        <p>Dr. Koppelman's style is certainly more professorial than political. His  interview for this article -- a tutorial, really -- lasted four hours. An engineering graduate of City College, he holds a master's in planning from Pratt Institute and a doctorate in public administration from New York University and has squeezed in teaching throughout his career.</p>
        <p>Mr. Halpin said: ''He had first-rate talent on his staff, and they did excellent work. He's always been a can-do person who never shirked. He took on special assignments, like being the main driver on the new Cohalan court complex in Central Islip.'' Sometimes he served as a lightning rod, Mr. Halpin said. ''Legislators would call up and say, 'Get rid of Koppelman,' when he was doing exactly what we wanted him to do.''</p>
        <p>The former Republican majority leader of the State Senate, Ralph J. Marino of Oyster Bay, said: ''He was perceived as more liberal, so he was suspect. But he established himself as an authority and became an institution. Everybody respected him.''</p>
        <p>The scope of Dr. Koppelman's studies over the years includes such wide-ranging topics as groundwater recharge, school issues, hurricane damage, the proposed Oyster Bay-Rye bridge, dredging, the labor force, oil spills, the decline of the defense industry, irrigation, Calverton airport, solid waste disposal, clamming, local taxes, pollutants in rain runoff, telecommuting and rising sea levels.</p>
        <p>The policy man and academician also enjoys working with his hands. He has built two homes for his wife and four children ''from the footings to the ridge beam,'' first in Smithtown then here in Stony Brook. He also created Japanese gardens, inspired by a 15th-century garden in Tokyo and zen gardens in Nara and Kyoto.</p>
        <p>''Visionary'' is the word most often applied to Dr. Koppelman. Decades ago he and Mr. Dennison were proposing more rail transit and the reviving of village downtowns, recalled Mr. Ryan of the Association for a Better Long Island. ''They were ahead of their times, and in hindsight, right on,'' he said. ''One Koppelman legacy is the Hauppauge industrial park, which at the time was the largest in the nation. His utilization of the Route 110 corridor, with links to the railroad, the expressway, two parkways and Republic airport -- that was another Koppelman stroke.''</p>
        <p>Although Long Island has a sordid history of officials caught in land scandals and other corruption, its master planner was never tarnished.</p>
        <p>''Once a fellow came in, a Meyer Lansky type, proposing legalized gambling,'' Dr. Koppelman said. ''He had all these numbers of how much revenue Suffolk would get. I sat and listened until he said, 'and we'll certainly take care of you and Mr. Dennison.' Well, I was so angry that I shoved him, and he fell down the stairs. I was afraid I'd killed him, but he got up, dusted himself off and went to complain to Dennison. Dennison called and asked: 'Did you do that?' I said: ' Yes, I did.' He said: 'Good!' ''</p>
        <p>Dr. Koppelman also has a reputation as demanding taskmaster. ''He does not suffer fools,'' said Mr. Halpin. Nor does he hesitate to argue his views. A chair-throwing incident around 30 years ago climaxed one dispute between Dr. Koppelman and his chief planner, Michael A. LoGrande. ''He had a pretty wicked temper himself, but I was the thrower and he was the throwee, and fortunately I missed,'' said Mr. LoGrande, who later became county executive and is now chairman of the Suffolk County Water Authority.</p>
        <p>A few times Dr. Koppelman even threatened to resign. He recalled one critic urging him not to quit: ''He said, 'If you didn't exist, we'd have to invent you.' I got to thinking that every time I talked about subsidized housing, and they talked against it, at the next election they'd get an even bigger vote.''</p>
        <p>Owen Smith, who served as Nassau's planning chairman, and often disagreed with Dr. Koppelman, said,  ''Long Island has had two great planners, Bob Moses and Lee Koppelman, and Lee has probably had more of an impact than anybody else, short of Bob Moses, on how Long Island has developed.''</p>
        <p>His greatest achievements, Dr. Koppelman said, are the various land preservation programs. ''It's something that will last as long as the county lasts,'' he said.</p>
        <p>High on his list of disappointments is the island's neglect of rail transit. ''A proven principle of transportation was discarded, and we suffer from it today,'' he said. ''If we had concentrated on that, we wouldn't have the congestion, the traffic accidents and so forth of being dependent on the automobile. Unfortunately, it's the identifying characteristic of Long Island.</p>
        <p>''But the biggest failure has been in housing,'' he said, referring to the meager progress in getting more apartments for singles, the elderly and the poor. ''The people who fought us tooth and nail 20, 30 years ago all of a sudden discover they're senior citizens'' with few options, he said. ''One area where we've had total failure is housing for people at the bottom of the economic ladder. If I had to pick one area of greatest frustration, it would be that. Not because we didn't fight for it, but the people were not with us.''</p>
        <p>Time has proven Dr. Koppelman right, said Mr. Crosson. ''Housing is an excellent example of the vision and practicality that he has brought to his planning,'' he said. ''If Long Island had listened more attentively to that, this would be a far different place, and people's children would be living here and not in other parts of the country. I'm hard pressed to think of any instance where Long Island would not be better off, if it had not simply done what Lee Koppelman had said we should do.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
