<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mixed Day for Coca-Cola in European Illness Scare</title>
    <meta content="Y23COK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1117803"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">European Union</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitney, Craig R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7D61E3BF930A15755C0A96F958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mixed Day for Coca-Cola in European Illness Scare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Whitney, Craig R</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, June 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>European crisis for Coca-Cola Co begins to ease in France, but 15-nation European Union announces plans to carry out health inspections of its own plants in Belgium and France that had produced soft drinks blamed for outbreaks of illness early this month (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The European crisis for Coca-Cola began to ease in France today, but the 15-nation European Union announced plans to carry out health inspections of its own in plants in Belgium and France that had produced soft drinks blamed for outbreaks of illness early this month.</p>
        <p>While the French ban on Coca-Cola, Coca-Cola Light, Fanta and Sprite canned by a Coca-Cola factory in Dunkirk, France, could be lifted as early as Wednesday, Pietro Petrucci, a European Union spokesman, said European inspectors would visit that plant and one in Antwerp, Belgium, and might not finish their report until next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The European crisis for Coca-Cola began to ease in France today, but the 15-nation European Union announced plans to carry out health inspections of its own in plants in Belgium and France that had produced soft drinks blamed for outbreaks of illness early this month.</p>
        <p>While the French ban on Coca-Cola, Coca-Cola Light, Fanta and Sprite canned by a Coca-Cola factory in Dunkirk, France, could be lifted as early as Wednesday, Pietro Petrucci, a European Union spokesman, said European inspectors would visit that plant and one in Antwerp, Belgium, and might not finish their report until next week.</p>
        <p>In Belgium, where the Government was brought down June 13 in a scandal over contamination of animal-feed grains by cancer-causing dioxin, the authorities maintained a nine-day-old ban on Coca-Cola, Fanta and Sprite. The ban continued even after the company's chairman, M. Douglas Ivester, met with the caretaker health minister Monday night and apologized to Belgian consumers in newspaper advertisements today.</p>
        <p>The problems began in Belgium after 30 schoolchildren apparently became sick after drinking Coke from cans on June 7, and fears quickly spread to France, the Netherlands, Luxembourg, Italy and Spain. Today the anxiety spread to Portugal, where several thousand cans of Coca-Cola were recalled after consumers there complained of finding a black residue that the company later said was harmless carbon particles.</p>
        <p>In all, about 200 cases of stomach pains, nausea and hyperventilation have been reported. France and the Netherlands have loosened an earlier ban, limiting it to sales of cans of Coca-Cola, Fanta and Sprite shipped through Belgium, but Luxembourg is barring all Coca-Cola products.</p>
        <p>French tests of the beverages canned in Dunkirk produced no evidence of contamination, the French Government said today.</p>
        <p>Bernard Kouchner, the Health Minister of France, said that examiners had looked into 10 causes of people who became sick after drinking Coca-Cola, but concluded that there were no links between the illnesses and the beverage. Mr. Kouchner suggested that psychosomatic causes were a possibility.</p>
        <p>He also said that health inspectors had found ''no relation in particular'' between the death of a 7-month-old baby in the mother's womb and any Coca-Cola that she might have drunk. But, he said, a few empty cans in her possession had been put under seal as part of the usual judicial inquiry into the death.</p>
        <p>Marylise Lebranchu, the Consumer Minister of France, said that the Government food safety agency could give the all-clear to Coca-Cola in France on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola officials in Brussels with Mr. Ivester and Henry Schimberg, chairman of Coca-Cola Enterprises, the bottler, did not return telephone calls today.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister of Belgium, Jean-Luc Dehaene, resigned a week ago after his coalition Government lost the national elections, acknowledging that he had not handled the crisis over contaminated animal feed properly. European Union authorities have accused the Belgians of delaying action for weeks before withdrawing chicken, eggs and later meat from the market until they could certify which producers had not used the tainted feed.</p>
        <p>Belgian authorities arrested the head of an animal fat processing company in southern Belgium Monday night, and Nicole de Rouck, a spokeswoman for the public prosecutor's office in Ghent, said today that it was possible that the company had mixed motor oil with frying fat that had been used to enrich animal feed grains. The company, Fogra, is the second to be investigated in the scandal.</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola has blamed a bad batch of carbon dioxide, used to carbonate its soft drinks, for the problems in Antwerp. Aga Gas, the Swedish company that said it had supplied the gas, has denied that there was anything wrong with the gas.</p>
        <p>Cans from Dunkirk that were shipped to Belgium and Luxembourg may have picked up phenol and other chemicals used to protect shipping pallets, Coca-Cola said, but French authorities who tested both cans and pallets from Dunkirk said they had found no trace of such impurities.</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola has taken out full-page advertisements in European newspapers this week to try to counter the bad publicity but the effects of that and the scare itself on sales in Europe or elsewhere were among the many questions that the company's officials could not answer today. Analysts in New York said it was difficult to estimate how much money Coca-Cola was losing.</p>
        <p>''The $64 million question is, how effective their effort to restore confidence in their brand is,'' said Marc Cohen, an analyst for Goldman, Sachs. An analyst for Credit Suisse First Boston has said the ban is costing Coca-Cola Enterprises some $3.4 million in revenues a day.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
