<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hoping to Lure a Livelier Crowd; Historic Graveyard in Brooklyn Wants Tourists to Stroll Its Lawns</title>
    <meta content="29CEME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1134137"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Green-Wood Cemetery (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E4DA133BF93AA1575BC0A96F958260" item-length="2101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hoping to Lure a Livelier Crowd; Historic Graveyard in Brooklyn Wants Tourists to Stroll Its Lawns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Green-Wood Cemetery, huge and historic burial ground in Brooklyn, is taking its first steps toward new identity: tourist attraction; visitors could be swept away by magnificent landscape at Green-Wood; another attraction is colorful stories of politicians and gangsters, Civil War generals and industrial magnates, victims of disasters and stars of scandals whose tombs cover most of 478 acres; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The graveyard business is just not what it used to be. So Green-Wood Cemetery, the huge and historic burial ground in Brooklyn, is taking its first slow steps toward a new identity: tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>This is not as goofy -- or as ghoulish -- as it might sound. A century ago, Green-Wood was a tourist attraction, ranking right up there with Niagara Falls on the 19th-century must-see list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The graveyard business is just not what it used to be. So Green-Wood Cemetery, the huge and historic burial ground in Brooklyn, is taking its first slow steps toward a new identity: tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>This is not as goofy -- or as ghoulish -- as it might sound. A century ago, Green-Wood was a tourist attraction, ranking right up there with Niagara Falls on the 19th-century must-see list.</p>
        <p>Modern visitors who do not share the Victorians' obsession with death -- or their admiration for mawkish statues of angels and urns -- could be swept away by the magnificent landscape at Green-Wood. Another lure is the colorful stories of the politicians and gangsters, Civil War generals and industrial magnates, victims of disasters and stars of scandals whose tombs cover most of the 478 acres.</p>
        <p>So the cemetery's management has begun trying to entice the public to enter its faux-Gothic gates. ''I'd like to see us become one of the highlights of the Brooklyn tour circuit,'' said Richard J. Moylan, president of Green-Wood, which opened in 1840.</p>
        <p>Last year, Green-Wood published a lively history chronicling the deeds (and misdeeds) of its denizens. This summer, it held its first concert, featuring the music of composers buried on site. Next month, it will start selling a guide that visitors can use to find the graves of everyone from Boss Tweed to the original Brooks Brothers, and will sponsor a booth at the annual New York Is Book Country fair in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Green-Wood is hardly the only historic American cemetery trying to lure visitors and raise its public profile. In Cleveland, there are trolley tours of cemeteries. In Rochester, Mount Hope Cemetery has an ''adopt-a-grave'' program. Woodlawn, in the Bronx, has a concert series -- next month it will hold its first performance of Latino music -- and is considering an Easter egg hunt for the spring. Mount Auburn, in Cambridge, Mass., bills itself as an arboretum as well as a burial ground, and has developed a number of programs for the public.</p>
        <p>There are many reasons -- historical, sociological and financial -- for these efforts. With fewer people choosing burial, cemeteries find themselves needing to advertise the benefits of having a memorial. Cremation, which is less lucrative for cemeteries than burial, has increased in popularity, as have the scattering of ashes and burial at sea.</p>
        <p>Then there is the belief that graveyards full of visitors may discourage thieves intent on stealing their Tiffany glass windows or bronze statues.  And cemeteries are searching for money to restore some of their moldering monuments.</p>
        <p>''You can't expect current sales dollars to cover 100 years of history,'' said Thomas G. Roberts, president of the Allegheny Cemetery in Pittsburgh and chairman of the historic cemeteries committee of the International Cemetery and Funeral Association. Almost 20 years ago, Allegheny set up a foundation and began raising money for historic preservation, he said. ''Foundations have been very understanding, once we get past what I call the laugh factor.''</p>
        <p>But in New York, in death as in life, the clincher is real estate. Green-Wood, like other burial grounds around the city, is running out of space.</p>
        <p>''We are in our twilight years as an active cemetery,'' Mr. Moylan said.  The space problem is not yet acute, he added; the cemetery, which buries the remains of about 2,000 people a year, probably has enough room for another decade's worth.</p>
        <p>But that is only because the cemetery has taken to removing some of its miles of roads and pathways, and using that space to bury the dead. Only a few more scenic paths can be replaced with graves before the overall appearance of the cemetery is affected, he said.</p>
        <p>Even after the last $5,000 plot is sold, Green-Wood will continue to make money from the services that provide much of its income. Each grave can hold as many as three coffins, stacked, so family members can be buried together. Some tombs have a lot of empty slots; the piano-building Steinway family built a huge tomb in the 1870's, with space for more than 150 bodies, according to Jeffrey I. Richman, the author of the book the cemetery published, ''Brooklyn's Green-Wood Cemetery: New York's Buried Treasure.''</p>
        <p>Ultimately, however, the cemetery will have to live off the income from its investments, already its largest source of revenue. Green-Wood had almost $200 million in its various funds at the end of 1998, according to its filings with the State Division of Cemeteries. It is one of the best endowed of the state's 1,900 nonprofit cemeteries, said Richard D. Fishman, director of the division.</p>
        <p>But Green-Wood is also one of the most expensive cemeteries to maintain. It takes 135 people to manicure its steep slopes, trim its trees and shrubs and rake its leaves. The cemetery spent more than $4 million on maintenance last year, according to its filings.</p>
        <p>Although the cemetery, which is just south of Park Slope, looks pristine -- the grass neatly cut, the monuments well kept -- some of the historic markers and statues are in sore need of conservation and restoration. At the Soldiers' Monument, the four life-size statues of Civil War soldiers are missing pieces -- a hand here, an ax there, a rifle over there -- and the bronze is split in places.</p>
        <p>Most of the severe damage has occurred to monuments made of marble, which has not held up well in the face of acid rain and salt breezes. (Green-Wood has a view of New York Harbor and the Statue of Liberty.)</p>
        <p>At the monument to the composer and pianist Louis Moreau Gottschalk, for example, ''you can't make his name out and, if you touch the marble, it comes off on your hand like salt,'' said John J. Cashman, a retired police sergeant who, with Frank Mescall, leads tours at the cemetery.</p>
        <p>At one time, Mr. Cashman's tours were pretty much the only way to see the cemetery, which for much of the 20th century has maintained a low-key stance, welcoming only lot owners and their families. In this century, visitors who were not discouraged by the cemetery's miles of spiky iron fencing, topped here and there with razor wire, had to get a special pass to walk the grounds, and were strictly forbidden to take photographs. ''I've been turned away at the gate,'' said Kenneth T. Jackson, a professor of history at Columbia University.</p>
        <p>Until early in this century, Professor Jackson noted, the sort of people who built the elaborate, expensive monuments at Green-Wood and Woodlawn expected sightseers. ''You would only be spending that kind of money if you thought someone would come to see it,'' he said. He added that in the 19th century, having a fancy cemetery was a point of civic pride, much as having a major-league baseball team is today.</p>
        <p>Technically, the lots are private property and the monuments are not the responsibility of the cemetery, but of the families of the dead. But for historic cemeteries, even those family members who are still nearby may not have the means to repair the marble bust of Great-Great-Uncle Horace or to fill the cast-iron urns with begonias.</p>
        <p>That is why Mount Hope in Rochester created the adopt-a-grave program, in which volunteers care for the plantings and flower beds, said Nancy M. Hilliard, director of cemeteries for the city. Churches, garden groups and individuals maintain about 75 graves at the 196-acre cemetery, which is 160 years old and has the graves of Susan B. Anthony and Frederick Douglass.</p>
        <p>At Green-Wood, the management has established a fund to be used for restoration; Mr. Cashman donates $1 of the $6 he charges for his tours, which he leads on Sunday afternoons in the spring and fall.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moylan is learning about fund-raising and grants, and is investigating that 90's concept, corporate sponsorship, to restore monuments with strong ties to New York companies. Among the well-known corporate names represented at Green-Wood are Tiffany, Brooks (as in Brothers), F. A. O. Schwarz, Eberhard Faber of pencil fame, and the Browns of the investment firm Brown Brothers Harriman.</p>
        <p>Visitors lucky enough to tour with Mr. Richman, a lawyer who became an author and passionate Green-Wood fan, can hear about all these and more. Leonard Bernstein is buried at Green-Wood, and so is the actor Frank Morgan, who played the Wizard of Oz.</p>
        <p>There are artists -- both Currier and Ives -- and newspapermen, including Horace Greeley. Inventors abound, and are credited by Mr. Richman with creating everything from the telegraph and typewriter to safety pins and hotel room service.</p>
        <p>Most entertaining, perhaps, are Mr. Richman's stories of the outrageous, extravagant and eccentric celebrities of 19th-century New York. Mr. Richman describes the miser who left his fortune to the A.S.P.C.A., the mining magnate with a heated tomb, and the woman who vowed to give the most lavish party ever, which she did -- and then fled the country a step ahead of the tax man.</p>
        <p>What kind of people go on his tours? History hounds, Brooklyn buffs, Civil War enthusiasts, bird-watchers and genealogy mavens, Mr. Richman said. And then there are the increasing number of Americans who just love cemeteries.</p>
        <p>Katie Karrick said that when she started a newsletter called ''Tomb With a View'' in 1995, ''I got 60 subscribers, and I was flabbergasted.'' Today, she has 500 paying customers.</p>
        <p>''The Victorians really glorified death; we try to ignore it,'' Ms. Karrick said. But that may be changing as the baby boomers think about dying and want to make sure they are noticed even after death, she said. The new fashion in headstones is to include a lot of information about the deceased, like their occupations and hobbies, as well as photographs. ''I call them resume stones,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Karrick leads a tour in Cleveland called ''Stones and Bones,'' which is one of the graveyard trips run by Trolley Tours of Cleveland. ''If you do it in a reverential, pleasant way, and with a sense of humor, people are very receptive,'' said Sherrill Paul, president of the tour company, which takes more than 500 people a year on cemetery trips.</p>
        <p>Mount Auburn in Cambridge has produced a cassette tape, titled ''Reflections,'' that guides drivers around its 12 miles of roads. It also has maps showing the locations of unusual trees. As many as 125,000 people a year visit the cemetery, said Janet Heywood, director of interpretive programs for Mount Auburn, though some of those are mourners, not tourists.</p>
        <p>So Mr. Moylan may be right when he predicts that people will start visiting Green-Wood again, the way they did a century ago. ''I don't know if we can get back to the picnic baskets around the lake,'' he said, ''but we can hope.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
