<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Craft to Track Climate-Affecting Link of Sea and Wind</title>
    <meta content="15SATE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1115489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Quikscat Satellite</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">North Atlantic Treaty Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07EEDE1038F936A25755C0A96F958260" item-length="1321" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Craft to Track Climate-Affecting Link of Sea and Wind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA will launch its Quick Scatterometer, or Quikscat, on Titan 2 rocket from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California on June 18; Quikscat is new ocean-observing satellite that will continually sweep ocean tops that cover two-thirds of world and measure speed and direction of winds that stir them; gathering more information about sea-wind interface will be critical tool in improved weather forecasting, early storm detection and identifying subtle changes in global climate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The continuous interplay between wind and ocean, whether as gentle as a kiss or as harsh as a slap, eventually affects almost everything else on earth through its influence on weather and climate. Yet, except for occasional sampling, this crucial interface between sea and sky goes mostly unmonitored.</p>
        <p>This should change later this week when a new ocean-observing satellite goes into orbit to begin at least two years of daily measurements of this critical wind-sea boundary area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The continuous interplay between wind and ocean, whether as gentle as a kiss or as harsh as a slap, eventually affects almost everything else on earth through its influence on weather and climate. Yet, except for occasional sampling, this crucial interface between sea and sky goes mostly unmonitored.</p>
        <p>This should change later this week when a new ocean-observing satellite goes into orbit to begin at least two years of daily measurements of this critical wind-sea boundary area.</p>
        <p>The National Aeronautics and Space Administration's Quick Scatterometer, or Quikscat, satellite is to be launched on Friday on a Titan 2 rocket from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California.</p>
        <p>The satellite's sole instrument is a radar device called a scatterometer, which will continually sweep the ocean tops that cover two-thirds of the world and measure the speed and direction of the winds that stir them. The dividends from these measurements, picking up where similar readings from earlier satellites left off, will be both immediate and long-term, scientists say.</p>
        <p>Without satellite measurements, only limited and often inaccurate wind-sea data are available from ships, aircraft and a few ocean buoys, scientists said, and even these readings are not available for huge areas of the world's oceans.</p>
        <p>Dr. Ghassem Asrar, head of NASA's Office of Earth Science, said, ''Knowledge about which way the wind blows and how hard is it blowing may seem simple, but this kind of information is actually a critical tool in improved weather forecasting, early storm detection and identifying subtle changes in global climate.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Daniel Cayan, director of climate research at the Scripps Institution of Oceanography in San Diego, said satellites provided information about conditions in Southern Hemisphere and other less-well-traveled oceans that was not available elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''Winds over the oceans are the key to how oceans evolve and produce big changes, such as El Ninos and other widespread effects,'' said Dr. Cayan, who is not involved in the Quikscat project. ''Winds are important in understanding how heat and moisture are exchanged between the air and water, and the effect this has on large-scale climate change.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Asrar said Quikscat was unusual in that the satellite was built in record time because scientists felt there was an urgent need for the wind-sea measurements after the failure of an earlier satellite providing them. Using many readily available satellite components, the spacecraft went from conception to completion in about a year, he said.</p>
        <p>NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory, which is part of the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena, had designed an advanced scatterometer called Sea Winds for a future mission. Engineers there were able to build a Sea Winds instrument early and the Ball Aerospace and Technologies Corporation of Boulder, Colo., moved quickly to integrate it into the 1,910-pound Quikscat satellite.</p>
        <p>The satellite was to have been launched last November, but the flight was delayed because of a recent series of rocket failures that grounded the Titan launcher fleet. After a giant Titan 4 exploded during launching last August, and two other Titan 4 launchings went awry in April, failure reviews delayed further flights of this type of booster. Quikscat, atop a smaller Titan 2, could not be launched from Vandenberg until a Titan 4 on a nearby launching pad flew first, which it finally did last month.</p>
        <p>James E. Graf, the Quikscat project manager based at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, said the launching delay added $5 million to the $93 million cost of the Quikscat mission, a price that includes the satellite, its rocket and mission science support, and would prevent the spacecraft from being fully operational during the current hurricane season, as was planned.</p>
        <p>Scatterometers are instruments that transmit high-frequency microwave pulses to the ocean surface and measure the ''backscattered,'' or echoed, pulses that bounce back to the originating satellite. These signals give an indirect measurement of the speed of wind near the water in clear or cloudy weather.</p>
        <p>By taking readings from pulses fired at slightly different angles, scientists can also use the backscattered signals to calculate the direction of the winds.</p>
        <p>Scatterometers of increasing sophistication have flown in space since the early 1970's. The first, demonstrating the feasibility of the instrument, flew aboard NASA's Skylab space station in 1973 and 1974. The European Remote Sensing Satellite, still operating since its launching in 1991, carries a radar instrument that works part time as a scatterometer and has provided limited but continuous sea-wind data for eight years.</p>
        <p>The most advanced instrument until now was the NASA Scatterometer, or Nscat, launched aboard the Japanese Midori satellite in August 1996. Nscat made more than 190,000 wind measurements daily as it mapped more than 90 percent of the world's oceans every two days. But the satellite suffered a solar power failure in June 1997, and scientists lost this critical stream of data.</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Freilich of Oregon State University, the principal investigator of the Sea Winds instrument, said the Midori failure spurred the rapid development of Quikscat.</p>
        <p>''We will pick up basically where Midori left off,'' Dr. Freilich said. ''We have a more advanced instrument that will make more refined measurements than before, seeing more small-scale wind variabilities than was previously possible.''</p>
        <p>Quikscat will cover 90 percent of the earth's ice-free oceans each day, a job that took Nscat two days, and will cover a 1,120-mile swath during each orbit, one-third wider than its predecessor, Dr. Freilich said. To cover such a wide area, signals will be sent from the satellite using a dish antenna that rotates 18 times a minute to continuously sweep across the broad track.</p>
        <p>For winds moving at 7 to 45 miles per hour, the wind speed measurements are expected to be accurate within 4.5 m.p.h., and for winds of 45 to 70 m.p.h., the measurements are expected to be accurate within 10 percent. Ninety-nine percent of all ocean winds fall below these speeds, Dr. Freilich added. Scientists cannot accurately predict weather without good wind data, and lacking such information for the 70 percent of the world covered by water hampers everyday forecasting, Dr. Freilich said. ''The difficulty in predicting future weather is that we don't really know what the weather is today,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Combining Quikscat's wind data with information on ocean height from another satellite, the American-French Topex/Poseidon spacecraft, will give scientists a more complete look at wind patterns and their effects on sea waves and currents, experts say.</p>
        <p>The Sea Winds instrument will be turned on about 18 days after the launching, and scientists will spend another four months calibrating the instrument and verifying the mathematical formulas used to interpret the data. After that, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, a major partner in the project, will distribute the wind information to weather forecasters and climate researchers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graf, the Quikscat project manager, said the spacecraft would travel in a 500-mile-high orbit that crosses close to Earth's North and South Poles. Although the satellite's mission is scheduled for a minimum of two years, Mr. Graf said the spacecraft was designed to operate for four to five years.</p>
        <p>A second Sea Winds instrument is being built and is to fly on a Japanese satellite that will replace the lost Midori spacecraft in November 2000. The two scatterometers are to fly in slightly different orbits that allow them to make complementary measurements, Mr. Graf said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
