<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pact Between New Jersey and Netherlands May Mean Cleaner Air for State</title>
    <meta content="24EMIS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1163403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strunsky, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E5D61239F937A15751C1A96F958260" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pact Between New Jersey and Netherlands May Mean Cleaner Air for State</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE STRUNSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strunsky, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey and Netherlands agree to pilot project they hope will show world how to help reduce carbon dioxide emissions; agreement, which reflects goals of international treaty to fight global warming, will most likely involve Netherlands' paying--and taking credit--for measures that will help decrease pollution in New Jersey (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey and the Netherlands have agreed to a pilot project they hope will show the world how to help reduce carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>The agreement, which reflects the goals of an international treaty to fight global warming, will most likely involve the Netherlands' paying -- and taking credit -- for measures that will decrease pollution in New Jersey. This could help the Dutch comply with the goals set in an international agreement to combat global warming, and, in the process, help New Jersey clean its air, officials say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey and the Netherlands have agreed to a pilot project they hope will show the world how to help reduce carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>The agreement, which reflects the goals of an international treaty to fight global warming, will most likely involve the Netherlands' paying -- and taking credit -- for measures that will decrease pollution in New Jersey. This could help the Dutch comply with the goals set in an international agreement to combat global warming, and, in the process, help New Jersey clean its air, officials say.</p>
        <p>Several states have been investigating similar deals, but New Jersey is the first to make one.</p>
        <p>The agreement calls on the two governments to identify by the end of next year specific projects that will reduce emissions in New Jersey, and help attain goals specified by a treaty drafted in 1997 in Kyoto, Japan.</p>
        <p>A provision of the Kyoto treaty allows nations to meet their emission reduction goals essentially by paying other countries to reduce their emissions. The concept is similar to a system under the Clean Air Act that allows companies within the United States to buy and sell emission credits.</p>
        <p>''We know New Jersey has a very progressive policy, and in the Netherlands, we can learn from them,'' said Pieter Verkerk, the environmental consul at the Netherlands Embassy in Washington. ''The agreement is to find out how the credit mechanisms will work in the future.''</p>
        <p>The agreement with New Jersey, signed on Dec. 7, is permitted by a memorandum of understanding between the Dutch and United States governments that provides for cooperation between the countries on a wide range of environmental issues, Mr. Verkerk said.</p>
        <p>Robert C. Shinn, the New Jersey commissioner of environmental protection, said the agreement is the first that specifically calls for the exchange of such credits to achieve goals set by the Kyoto treaty.</p>
        <p>The treaty, known as the Kyoto Protocol, was drafted after worldwide attention was focused on global warming by the Earth Summit of 1992 in Rio de Janeiro. Reduction goals are based on a percentage of a country's 1990 emission levels, and begin taking effect in 2008.</p>
        <p>The treaty has been signed by more than 150 nations, but the United States Senate has not ratified the agreement, largely because of doubts about relinquishing control over the nation's emissions standards and the costs involved.</p>
        <p>Under one project envisioned as part of the New Jersey-Netherlands agreement, the Dutch government would pay the additional fuel cost for a power plant in Jersey City to switch from coal to natural gas. The switch would cut carbon dioxide emissions by one-third, said Eric Svensen, director of environmental policy for Public Service Electric and Gas, the utility that owns the plant.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the switch away from coal would also reduce emissions of sulfur and nitrous oxide, which contribute to smog. So New Jersey residents would get cleaner air, without having to pay extra for it. ''We wouldn't go over to natural gas currently, because natural gas is a more expensive fuel,'' Mr. Svensen said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Verkerk, the former Dutch solicitor general for environmental enforcement, said his government would buy credits to achieve up to half of its emissions reduction goal. The Dutch people will achieve the rest themselves, he said, by using cleaner fuel, curbing automobile emissions and other measures.</p>
        <p>He and Mr. Shinn, the state's commissioner of environmental protection, said that once other countries begin buying pollution credits, an international emissions credit bank could be established, allowing for more international agreements to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>One goal of the pilot agreement, the officials said, was to help work out details of the emission credit process. ''This is very much in its infancy,'' Mr. Shinn said.</p>
        <p>New Jersey and other states have their own emission reduction goals that are components of national goals.</p>
        <p>The United States is the world's largest producer of greenhouse gases, so there is some irony, Mr. Svensen said, that its states may be the first to sell emission reduction credits.</p>
        <p>''What had always been contemplated,'' Mr. Svensen said, ''was that the U.S. would be the purchasers.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
