<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Growth and Government Collude in Creating a Hazard</title>
    <meta content="Y16BEAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1138159"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="HURRICANE FLOYD: LOOKING AHEAD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricane Floyd</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dean, Cornelia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED7173CF935A2575AC0A96F958260" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Growth and Government Collude in Creating a Hazard</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CORNELIA DEAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dean, Cornelia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coastal scientists and policy makers say evacuations, disaster declarations and emergency proclamations accompanying Hurricane Floyd are a small taste of worse to come as sea levels continue to rise, storms intensify and more and more people live in vulnerable coastal areas; many warn that people will continue to build on the beach even if Federal agenices halted disaster assistance, insurance programs, infrastructure support and other spending that encourages it; say getting people off the coast safely in event of a storm is turning into a logistical nightmare (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The evacuations, disaster declarations and emergency proclamations that are accompanying Hurricane Floyd along the Atlantic coast are a small taste of worse to come, say coastal scientists and policy makers worried about rising sea levels, more intense storms and a ballooning coastal population.</p>
        <p>Weather forecasters at the National Hurricane Center and elsewhere have gotten better and better at predicting when and where storms will strike, helping officials to move residents and tourists out of harm's way in time. But population growth along the coast -- fueled in part, some experts say, by government policies encouraging development -- is more than outpacing them. Within a few years, some demographers predict,  most Americans will live in coastal counties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The evacuations, disaster declarations and emergency proclamations that are accompanying Hurricane Floyd along the Atlantic coast are a small taste of worse to come, say coastal scientists and policy makers worried about rising sea levels, more intense storms and a ballooning coastal population.</p>
        <p>Weather forecasters at the National Hurricane Center and elsewhere have gotten better and better at predicting when and where storms will strike, helping officials to move residents and tourists out of harm's way in time. But population growth along the coast -- fueled in part, some experts say, by government policies encouraging development -- is more than outpacing them. Within a few years, some demographers predict,  most Americans will live in coastal counties.</p>
        <p>As a result, timely evacuations in some areas are already becoming impossible.</p>
        <p>And if the earth is warming -- and mainstream scientists believe it is -- the rise of sea levels will accelerate, leaving low-lying areas ever more vulnerable to flooding. Plus, because hurricanes draw their energy from ocean warmth, warmer seas may mean stronger storms.</p>
        <p>The biggest burst of development on the coast has occurred since the 1960's, a time of relatively few hurricanes. Some climatologists, notably William M. Gray of Colorado State University, say this quiet weather  cannot last. They believe that hurricane frequency varies in cycles, and that another period of high hurricane frequency is beginning. If the nation returned to the prevailing patterns of the 1930's, 40's and 50's, they say, hurricanes costing tens of billions of dollars would become routine.</p>
        <p>But policy makers are finding it difficult to limit building on some of the nation's most desirable, but most hazardous, landscape. In fact, some experts say, they are doing the opposite.</p>
        <p>''The expectations and demand that the Federal Government be extremely generous and supportive of disaster victims, and the property rights movement nationally, have in a broad sense intimidated Federal, state and local officials from limiting development and redevelopment,'' said Rutherford H. Platt, a professor of geography at the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. His new book, ''Disasters and Democracy,'' deals with disaster assistance and its effects on development.</p>
        <p>''Despite all the rhetoric about mitigation,'' Professor Platt said in an interview yesterday, ''the broad thrust of Federal policy is to provide disaster grants, loans and tax deductions that encourage investment in hazardous areas.''</p>
        <p>In the case of Hurricane Floyd, President Clinton issued pre-emptive disaster declarations from New Zealand and the Governors of Florida, Georgia, South Carolina, North Carolina, Virginia, New Jersey, Delaware and Maryland all declared states of emergency, hours before the storm made landfall.</p>
        <p>Like others who have studied coastal development, Mr. Platt says  programs like disaster assistance and the Federal Flood Insurance Program, which provides low-cost coverage in flood hazard areas, can encourage unwise development. Some coastal scientists blame the insurance program, in fact, for much of the unwise development that has taken place on the coast since it went into effect in 1968.</p>
        <p>But many involved in coastal development issues maintain that even if Federal agencies halted their grants, infrastructure support and other spending, people might still flock to build on the beach.</p>
        <p>''People are going to be on the beach because they like to be on the beach,'' said Gerry Stoddard, president of the Fire Island Association, which represents homeowners on the island.</p>
        <p>But as more and more people settle at the coast, getting them out safely in the event of a storm is turning into a logistical nightmare.</p>
        <p>Ideally, evacuations should be carried out well before a storm hits, at low tide so low-lying coastal roads are not flooded, and in daylight. Even then, coastal highways are not designed to carry such a load. In fact, the prospect of throngs of residents trapped in miles-long traffic jams is what most frightens many disaster planners.</p>
        <p>There are few places more dangerous to be in a hurricane than in an automobile. But that was exactly where many people were up and down the coast as Hurricane Floyd approached. Evacuation traffic clogged almost to a halt in Florida, and Interstate 40 in North Carolina was choked with cars.</p>
        <p>As the hurricane neared Georgia, state workers were able to turn Interstate 16 into a one-way avenue out of Savannah, with traffic on both sides of the divided highway headed west, inland. But, as in this case, most coastal highways were built before engineers realized they might ever have to run only one way. So highway officials in coastal jurisdictions must scramble to retrofit, stationing portable signs, traffic cones and the like in strategic locations.</p>
        <p>In some areas, though, disaster officials are reconciling themselves to the reality that it will not be possible to get everyone out in time. That is particularly true in places like Florida, with its low-lying barrier islands and its high proportion of elderly residents, many in frail health.</p>
        <p>Officials in places like the Florida Keys and Sanibel Island, on Florida's Gulf Coast, are designating so-called ''refuges of last resort,'' places where people can shelter if they cannot escape a storm in time.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, Americans' love for beach living serves to thwart the coast's natural defense against extreme storms. Geologists know that the more building there is on the coastal barrier islands that line the East and the Gulf coasts, the more difficulty the islands themselves seem to have in recovering from hurricanes and other coastal storms.</p>
        <p>The geologists began studying the issue in detail more than 35 years ago, after the notorious Ash Wednesday northeaster of 1962. That storm, which lasted for days, devastated much of the East Coast. Undeveloped barrier islands recovered quickly; developed stretches of coast were much slower to bounce back.</p>
        <p>In part, this is because sand on these islands naturally shifts from inland dunes to offshore sandbars, which form in storms and then act as a kind of defense system, breaking waves before they can crash more destructively on the beach. When calm weather returns, gentle swells carry the sandbar sands back on shore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Platt and other experts on coastal planning say they wish coastal officials knew more about this beach geology, and the importance of keeping buildings off the beach. If they had acted on that knowledge, these experts say, barrier islands might be better able to survive storms, and there would be fewer people trying to escape them.</p>
        <p>But as long as government assistance is available, it seems likely that building in hazard areas will continue and disaster declarations will follow.</p>
        <p>HURRICANE FLOYD: LOOKING AHEAD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
