<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. Finds Broken Rules At Coal Plants, Officials Say</title>
    <meta content="Y16COA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1123732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EEDA143FF935A25754C0A96F958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. Finds Broken Rules At Coal Plants, Officials Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency finds that several electric companies have violated terms under which their coal plants were 'grandfathered' under the Clean Air Act by making major changes to produce more power without installing required pollution controls; no action has yet been taken against plants, as investigators continue reviewing data (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has found that several electric companies have violated the terms under which their coal plants were ''grandfathered'' under the Clean Air Act by making major changes to produce more power without installing the required pollution controls, Federal officials said.</p>
        <p>Inspectors have completed field audits of 6 plants and were preparing to complete work on 22 others, the officials said. No action has yet been taken against the plants, as investigators continue reviewing the data. The E.P.A. could fine the companies and require them to install equipment to control emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency has found that several electric companies have violated the terms under which their coal plants were ''grandfathered'' under the Clean Air Act by making major changes to produce more power without installing the required pollution controls, Federal officials said.</p>
        <p>Inspectors have completed field audits of 6 plants and were preparing to complete work on 22 others, the officials said. No action has yet been taken against the plants, as investigators continue reviewing the data. The E.P.A. could fine the companies and require them to install equipment to control emissions.</p>
        <p>''They have been making what we believe are major capital improvements, not routine maintenance,'' said one Federal official, who would not let himself be further identified because the investigation was still under way.</p>
        <p>The improvements included new boilers, burners and blowers for moving coal, all of higher capacity than the old ones. In some cases, the official said, the ability of the plants to produce power had been increased ''dramatically.''</p>
        <p>The Clean Air Act set strict pollution standards for new sources but much looser ones for existing power plants and factories. Under the grandfather clause, the old sources could continue to operate with minor improvements as long as their owners did not undertake major renovations.</p>
        <p>Demand for power from coal-fired plants has risen in the last few years, as de-regulation of the utility industry has allowed electric companies  with old, paid-for plants consuming cheap fuel to sell their electricity profitably across state lines, into higher-priced Eastern markets.</p>
        <p>But the nitrogen oxides they produce add to smog in the East, according to the E.P.A. and air pollution officials in the Eastern states. Smog, or ground-level ozone, is produced by the action of sunlight on nitrogen oxides, which come from vehicles and power plants, with hydrocarbons, which come from cars, oil refineries and other sources.</p>
        <p>The accusations against the power companies, most of them in the Ohio Valley, are only the latest dispute about the plants; officials in Northeastern states have long complained that their pollution travels hundreds of miles to create smog from Washington to Boston.</p>
        <p>But people in the industry said that they were under a legal obligation to keep their plants in top condition and had done nothing that would require  stricter pollution controls.</p>
        <p>About 100 E.P.A. investigators are looking at records and hardware in the plants, said Federal officials, who say the E.P.A. first made its discovery by comparing computerized databases assembled for other purposes. One database, created for the control of the sulfur dioxide emissions that cause acid rain, shows power generation and coal consumption. Another shows investments in new equipment. Matching the two, investigators said they found evidence of major improvements, the kind that should have required stricter pollution controls.</p>
        <p>But Henry V. Nickel, a lawyer who represents the Utility Air Regulatory Group, an industry coalition, said,  ''They're looking at things that everyone in industry has had to do, to keep their plants running.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nickel said that in some cases the E.P.A. had looked at production in the year that work was done on a plant, and production in the year after, and found an increase. But that, he said, was ''a perfectly fulfilling prophecy'' because ''when you shut down a facility to do a repair project, it's going to operate less in that year than in next year, when you don't have to shut down for repairs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nickel said improvements that allowed a plant to produce more kilowatt-hours from a fixed amount of fuel would not require better pollution controls, because by definition, such improvements meant a decline in pollution per unit of electricity produced.</p>
        <p>At American Electric Power, a coal-based utility that generates and distributes power in seven states,  Pat Hemlepp, a spokesman, said, ''We've known for a long time that E.P.A. has wanted to pursue an emissions reduction strategy through enforcement initiatives.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hemlepp said his company's investments in its plants had been obvious over the years.</p>
        <p>''There's not much that electric utilities do that's private,'' he said, because of regulatory requirements.</p>
        <p>In a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission this spring,  American Electric Power said the E.P.A. had requested documents from the company related to its coal plant investments and power output.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
