<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A View of/Changing Seasons; Autumn as a Mirror of Nature's Cycles</title>
    <meta content="26VIEW$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1140582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Seasons and Months</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDD153FF935A1575AC0A96F958260" item-length="1227" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A View of/Changing Seasons; Autumn as a Mirror of Nature's Cycles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene in Westchester County, NY, described as seasons change from summer to autumn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE smell of burning leaves may no longer be in the air: environmental regulations have all but eradicated that once ubiquitous sign of fall. But as surely as the autumnal equinox occurred at 7:31 A.M. on Thursday, the season is upon us, as Westchester undergoes its annual transition from green to gold and russet.</p>
        <p>Staff members of the county's Department of Parks, Recreation and Conservation probably know more about and are more affected by the changes than the average person.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE smell of burning leaves may no longer be in the air: environmental regulations have all but eradicated that once ubiquitous sign of fall. But as surely as the autumnal equinox occurred at 7:31 A.M. on Thursday, the season is upon us, as Westchester undergoes its annual transition from green to gold and russet.</p>
        <p>Staff members of the county's Department of Parks, Recreation and Conservation probably know more about and are more affected by the changes than the average person.</p>
        <p>The parks and nature preserves, while busy all summer, are in some cases even busier in the fall, especially now that Halloween seems to begin right after Labor Day and October has become a sort of monthlong harvest festival. Not only are stores full of fall decorations -- artificial red leaves, Indian corn, scarecrows -- but the Parks Department also has a full schedule of seasonal celebrations and explorations.</p>
        <p>''Fall is the best time for passive recreation,'' Jack Robbins, the department's deputy commissioner, said. ''It's an interesting time, a wonderful time to watch and observe. There are bird migrations, changing leaves, animals getting ready to hibernate.'' There are, he added, ''many layers of activities,'' some obvious, some subtle, as the natural world prepares for winter.</p>
        <p>The most obvious autumn phenomenon, of course, is the turning of the leaves. Recent weather extremes -- drought in July, floods in September -- have made it hard to predict whether it will be a brilliant or relatively subdued season as to colors, Mary Davis, the county's naturalist, said. Whatever the outcome, though, the process remains the same.</p>
        <p>What happens is this: during the spring and summer, chlorophyll is abundant in the leaves, giving them a green color. In photosynthesis, the process every school child learns about, chlorophyll combines with sunlight, water, minerals and carbon dioxide to create carbohydrates that nourish the tree.</p>
        <p>Come fall, Ms. Davis explained, the shortening of the days prompts hormonal changes in the leaves that lead to the growth of a corky layer at the base of each leaf. This layer cuts off the supply of water and nutrients, and the chlorophyll -- the green pigment -- disappears. Carotenoids, yellow and orange colors that were in the leaf all along, become apparent. In Westchester, ash, hickory, sassafras and birch should all be all golden yellow soon.</p>
        <p>But what about the brilliant reds of the maples, oaks, Virginia creepers and sumacs? For these red hues one needs sunny days and frosty nights, for it is during the warm days that the production of sugars takes place, and it is these sugars that combine with minerals to make scarlet and crimson tones. This year, Ms. Davis said, residents will just have to wait and see how the season turns out. Anyone who wants to view foliage in an organized walk can do it today at 2 P.M. at Trailside Nature Museum at Ward Pound Ridge Reservation in Cross River. (Participants should meet at the end of Michigan Road, and the number to call  for information is 763-3993). Other times are Oct. 3 from noon until 3 P.M. at Muscoot Farm in Somers (232-7118) and Oct. 16 at 2 P.M. at Cranberry Lake Preserve in North White Plains (428-1005).</p>
        <p>For those more interested in animal than plant life, there are the migrating birds. Hawks are in particular abundance in Westchester this time of year, as they make their way from north to south. Since the diminution in sunlight and the cooling temperatures are catalysts for the leaves to change color, they also lead to birds' migrations. Ken Soltesz, curator at Cranberry Lake Preserve, said that thousands of broadwing hawks that spend spring and summer in the Adirondacks fly over the county on their way to points south, some as far as South America. ''I've seen as many as 30,000 in a day,'' he said. ''When you get one of those typical fall days, with brisk northwest winds, you see a lot of hawks. That weather stimulates migration.'' The hawks fly in circular formations known as kettles, he added, sometimes riding upward more than  1,000 feet on rising air currents known as thermals. To see them, go to hawk watches at Lenoir Preserve in Yonkers at 10 A.M. on Oct. 9, Oct. 10, Oct. 23 and Oct. 30. (For information, call 968-5851.)</p>
        <p>On land, too, creatures' lives are changing. Mammals that hibernate actually conserve energy in winter by becoming dormant. During dormancy, body temperature drops, heartbeat and respiration slows and general metabolism has been altered. Some animals wake up occasionally to eat from caches of food; others neither eat nor urinate nor defecate during hibernation, living in so slow a state that body chemistry is radically altered.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, Mr. Soltesz said, the groundhog, or woodchuck, and the jumping mouse are hibernators. Woodchucks go two to six feet under the soil into hibernation chambers. They spend two to three months of the winter in a torpid state, living off of body fat accumulated on the back of their necks during the rest of the year.</p>
        <p>The jumping mouse goes into an even deeper state of torpidity. ''They hibernate singly or in pairs,'' Alfred J. Godin writes in ''Wild Mammals of New England.'' (John Hopkins University Press) ''They roll themselves tightly into a ball, with the nose buried in the belly, ears flattened against the head, eyes closed tightly and the long tail curled around or partially under the body.''</p>
        <p>As for squirrels and chipmunks, they spend time in nests and burrows during winter but do not hibernate; rather, they emerge on relatively warm days. As everyone knows, both squirrels and chipmunks gather nuts and acorns during the fall and store them for the sparse spells of winter when they dig them up. Intriguing question: how do they remember where the cache is? Is it memory or instinct, and, Ms. Davis pondered, What are instinct and intelligence anyway? There are as many questions as there are answers when dealing with nature, she said.</p>
        <p>One thing she does know: the old wives' tales that extra bushy squirrels' tails predict an extra strong winter has no truth to it. ''It just means that they have had a good spring and summer -- that they've grown a good, healthy coat of fur,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But the most fascinating aspect of all these changes, she said, is how they reflect the cyclic nature of things. Mammals hibernate, birds and even insects migrate -- now is the time to see gold and black monarch butterflies on their way to Mexico. These actions are the result of a delicate balance between the organisms' interior biochemical clocks and environmental factors, like temperature and sunlight. Leaves change color every year, sometimes brilliantly vivid, sometimes less so. And, autumn is when all of this is most apparent.</p>
        <p>''In fall, you really start seeing things,'' Ms. Davis said. ''Beyond the beautiful leaves, the dramatic colors, fall lets you see nature going through its cycles.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
