<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Interstate Deal For Clean Air Falls Through</title>
    <meta content="02ENVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1134908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED8173AF931A3575AC0A96F958260" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Interstate Deal For Clean Air Falls Through</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Sept. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Officials on both sides of regional battle over air pollution that blows from Midwest to Northeast reject proposed compromise, all but guaranteeing that long-running dispute will be settled in court; Northeast states, led by New York, made proposal, marking first time they had shown willingness to retreat from their long-held demands that states in Midwest and South reduce emissions of nitrogen oxides, group of chemicals that contribute to ozone and acid rain (M) plants</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the regional battle over air pollution that blows from the Midwest to the Northeast, states on both sides have rejected a proposed compromise, all but guaranteeing that the long-running dispute will be settled in court, not at a bargaining table.</p>
        <p>The Northeast states, led by New York, made the proposal last week, marking the first time they had shown any willingness to retreat from their long-held demands that states in the Midwest and South sharply reduce emissions by industry, particularly power plants. But today, officials on both sides of the dispute said there was no way that plan, or any other compromise, would win approval.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the regional battle over air pollution that blows from the Midwest to the Northeast, states on both sides have rejected a proposed compromise, all but guaranteeing that the long-running dispute will be settled in court, not at a bargaining table.</p>
        <p>The Northeast states, led by New York, made the proposal last week, marking the first time they had shown any willingness to retreat from their long-held demands that states in the Midwest and South sharply reduce emissions by industry, particularly power plants. But today, officials on both sides of the dispute said there was no way that plan, or any other compromise, would win approval.</p>
        <p>''We all agreed to take that proposal back and talk about it, but I can tell you now we're not going to do it, and neither are most of the other states in our group,'' Russell Harding, director of Michigan's Department of Environmental Quality, said today. ''There won't be any settlement because there isn't any middle ground.''</p>
        <p>On the other side, Robert Durand, Massachusetts' secretary of environmental affairs, said, ''We are not going to compromise our goals, and I know some other states in our group feel the same way.'' As for the prospects of a deal, he said, ''I'm content at this point to see them in court because I don't think this negotiation is going anywhere.''</p>
        <p>The compromise plan would still have required plants in the Midwest and South to reduce their emissions of a major class of pollutants, but by far less than the Northeast states and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency had been demanding.</p>
        <p>New York, the lead negotiator for the Northeast states, had been one of the most aggressive in calling for action by the other regions and by the Federal Government. As a result, other officials in the Northeastern camp said they were perplexed when the Pataki administration took the lead in drafting the proposed compromise, particularly because some of its allies had serious reservations about the plan.</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki argued today that he still believed a compromise was possible. ''I think it would be better if we could reach a settlement that provides a real and significant reduction than to risk the uncertainties of continuing the legal process,'' he said. But, he added, ''we're prepared to pursue legal action further if that is required.''</p>
        <p>Negotiators have said that there cannot be a settlement unless all 25 states reach agreement, because no state wants to cede a competitive advantage to its neighbors, and any state that held out could go to court to try to void the overall agreement.</p>
        <p>The Northeast states have some of the toughest environmental regulations, but their cities also have some of the worst air pollution. Officials have long complained that much of the pollution comes from elsewhere, particularly Midwestern power plants, a position that is supported by the Environmental Protection Agency. The Southern and Midwestern states argue that their role in Northeastern pollution is overstated.</p>
        <p>The 11 Northeast states from Maryland to Maine have gone to court, seeking to compel 14 states in the Midwest and South to cut down on emissions of nitrogen oxides, a group of chemicals that contribute to ozone, commonly known as smog, and to acid rain. Without drastic action in other regions, Northeastern officials argue, New York and other cities will be unable to comply with the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>The Northeast states have sought a standard of 0.15 pound of nitrogen oxides per million British thermal units of energy consumed. At that level, the amount of nitrogen oxides in the New York metropolitan area would decline by more than 75 percent, state officials predict. The Northeast states already plan to go to the 0.15 limit by 2003, but the Midwestern states have said they would go no lower than 0.25, and some Southern states have said that even that would be too strict.</p>
        <p>''The difference between 0.25 and anything lower is that you get into very expensive technology, and we don't want to force that on our power plants to fix a problem we think has been exaggerated,'' Mr. Harding said.</p>
        <p>Last year, the E.P.A. announced that it planned to impose the 0.15 standard. But in May, a Federal appeals court issued a temporary order blocking the E.P.A. from going ahead with that plan, and scheduled a full argument on the issue for November.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Federal agency have grown worried about their chances in court, and pressed hard for all 25 states to reach a negotiated settlement.</p>
        <p>Last week, five-state negotiating teams from each side met in Washington, and the Northeast states, led by New York, made their first compromise proposal. It would mandate that the other regions attain the 0.25 standard by 2003, and 0.20 a few years later. Within days, environmental groups were criticizing the plan, and environmental officials in some Northeast states said they doubted their states would go along with the proposal.</p>
        <p>''We are still committed to the 0.15 standard,'' Mr. Durand of Massachusetts said today. ''It's very apparent to us that the Midwestern states want to continue to allow the industrial equivalent of second-hand smoke to poison our air.''</p>
        <p>Asked if New York, too, remained committed to 0.15, Mr. Pataki said, ''I don't want to comment on any particular standard.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
