<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Best-Selling Author's Gloomy Future for Los Angeles Meets Resistance</title>
    <meta content="Y27DAV$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1080550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Davis, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ecology of Fear (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">City of Quartz (Book)1</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DB1339F934A15752C0A96F958260" item-length="1554" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Best-Selling Author's Gloomy Future for Los Angeles Meets Resistance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Jan. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Mike Davis, author of two best-selling books--City of Quartz and Ecology of Fear--that portray Los Angeles as false paradise ruled by malign elites who have stifled poor, built downtown fortress surrounded by growing ring of dying suburbs and courted environmental disaster by heedlessly encroaching on canyons and cliffsides never intended for mass habitation; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a winter Sunday morning of the sort that only Southern California seems to produce, under a brilliant blue sky scoured clean of clouds and smog, a crowd of upper-middle-class Angelenos filed into the Skirball Cultural Center and plunked down $10 each to hear a conversation with their city's reigning prophet of doom.</p>
        <p>In two best-selling books, ''City of Quartz,'' published in 1990, and ''Ecology of Fear,'' issued last fall, that man, Mike Davis, has portrayed Los Angeles as a false paradise ruled by malign elites who have stifled the poor, built a fortress downtown surrounded by a growing ring of dying suburbs, and courted environmental disaster by heedlessly encroaching on canyons and cliffsides never meant for mass habitation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a winter Sunday morning of the sort that only Southern California seems to produce, under a brilliant blue sky scoured clean of clouds and smog, a crowd of upper-middle-class Angelenos filed into the Skirball Cultural Center and plunked down $10 each to hear a conversation with their city's reigning prophet of doom.</p>
        <p>In two best-selling books, ''City of Quartz,'' published in 1990, and ''Ecology of Fear,'' issued last fall, that man, Mike Davis, has portrayed Los Angeles as a false paradise ruled by malign elites who have stifled the poor, built a fortress downtown surrounded by a growing ring of dying suburbs, and courted environmental disaster by heedlessly encroaching on canyons and cliffsides never meant for mass habitation.</p>
        <p>For this Mr. Davis, a one-time meat-cutter and now full-time Marxist urbanologist, has been hailed as something like a hero, not only by the coast-to-coast school of critics who have long looked askance at Los Angeles, but by his fellow Southern Californians whose unrelenting misery he presumes to celebrate. The winner of a $315,000 MacArthur Foundation ''genius'' grant, he has also won an unquestioned place on the short list of serious thinkers about a city whose prevailing culture has long been a blend of oligarchical boosterism and noir self-loathing.</p>
        <p>When a questioner at the Skirball Center gestured to the sunny splendor of the Sepulveda Pass outside and asked if Los Angeles was really so bad, Mr. Davis, 52, acknowledged with a rueful laugh, ''I wake up in the morning and look at the San Gabriel Mountains in incredible January -- even if it may be a symptom of global warming -- and I ask myself, 'Are you crazy?' ''</p>
        <p>For the first time, a growing chorus of Californians is effectively answering, ''Yes!''</p>
        <p>''Ecology of Fear'' (Metropolitan Books), with its thesis that the modern megalopolis of Los Angeles has no business existing in the earthquake-ridden Southern California desert, has unleashed a pent-up firestorm of criticism over Mr. Davis's methods after 16 weeks on the local best-seller list (''City of Quartz'' is No. 5 on the paperback list).</p>
        <p>Critics have cast grave doubt on many of the obscure and startling factoids that are Mr. Davis's stock in trade, calling into question his broader argument that Los Angeles is a hopelessly damned creature of unchecked real estate speculation and the mercenary folly of its ruling class.</p>
        <p>The debate has pitted rival camps of the city's interpreters against each other in a fight more typical of New York or Paris than of laid-back Los Angeles. Academics, alternative weeklies, business journals and The Los Angeles Times have all weighed in, with everything from Mr. Davis's birthplace (the desert suburb of Fontana, not Los Angeles, as the book jacket of ''Ecology'' says) to his marriages (he is on his fifth) grist for the mill. As a topic of collective conversation, he is not quite on a par with the Dodgers or the latest grosses, but he is gaining.</p>
        <p>''In my opinion, it is a significant development in the intellectual history of Los Angeles -- and don't gasp, there is such a thing,'' said Kevin Starr, the state librarian of California whose own histories of the Golden State, like ''Inventing the Dream'' (Oxford University Press, 1985) have been hailed as authoritative. ''The decade of the 90's began with 'City of Quartz' and its elegantly presented noir vision of Los Angeles as a repressive conspiracy, and sure enough, all these noir aspects came out, beginning with the riots in '92.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the decade,'' Mr. Starr continued, ''there's a different situation. Immigrant groups have revitalized the Los Angeles economy, the mood is better, and here comes a book that really makes us think about earthquakes and the epicycle of climatological reality.</p>
        <p>''Davis's offering of an unmitigatedly apocalyptic point of view is now meeting with resistance. There's going to be some bad manners, some fighting back and forth. But you've got people caring about L.A. and the theory of L.A., and I think that's very important.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis, whose unruly shock of white hair and soft, half-swallowed speaking voice convey an aura about as threatening as Linus in ''Peanuts,'' has been caught in some embarrassing mistakes. For starters, he has acknowledged fabricating an entire conversation with a local environmentalist, Lewis McAdams, for a cover story he wrote for L.A. Weekly a decade ago; he defends it as an early attempt at journalistic scene-setting.</p>
        <p>In ''City of Quartz'' (Verso, 1990), discussing the power divisions between the city's old and new elites, he misidentified the late Howard Ahmanson, the founder of the giant Home Savings empire and a conservative Christian, as Jewish, and he also described Hancock Park, one of the city's oldest WASP enclaves, as a Jewish neighborhood.</p>
        <p>He also acknowledges that he cannot find the source for his assertion in ''Ecology of Fear'' that as many as 30 bodies a year have been found in drug-plagued MacArthur Park near downtown, a claim the police dismiss as wildly off-base.</p>
        <p>''The book is a, you know, polemic, with a lot of irony and humor in it,'' Mr. Davis said in a two-hour interview at a pub near his home in Pasadena. ''It has sailed over the heads of some people.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Davis's critics say he has so twisted the facts as to make honest debate impossible. The latest critique of Mr. Davis, for example, in the weekly New Times L.A., leaves little doubt that his new book's portrait of suburban Pomona as a deserted husk is at best outdated, ignoring a decade of revival.</p>
        <p>Joel Kotkin, a fellow at the Pepperdine Institute for Public Policy in Malibu and one of Mr. Davis's most vociferous critics, said, ''What bothers me even as a person who was trained as a Marxist is that somebody would so bastardize Marxist theory to the point of making things up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis's particular calling card has been his unearthing of obscure, even fantastic, facts about Los Angeles's experience with natural and scientific phenomena, from monsoon-intensity rain to little-noticed tornados to mountain lions that prowl the city's suburban fringe. One chapter in ''Ecology of Fear,'' on wildfires, is titled, ''The Case for Letting Malibu Burn.''</p>
        <p>But Brady Westwater, a Malibu real-estate agent and amateur local historian who has appointed himself Mr. Davis's one-man truth squad, has produced reams of material, circulated on the Internet and among publications here and in New York, questioning almost every claim he makes.</p>
        <p>''There's something pathological about it,'' said Mr. Westwater, who cites, as just one example among dozens, Mr. Davis's assertion that local news organizations have long played down Southern California's experience with tornado-like storms.</p>
        <p>''I checked the L.A. Times article he actually cites as evidence of this reluctance, and it uses the words 'tornado' or 'twister' 13 times,'' Mr. Westwater said. ''You don't even have to check other sources to prove he's lying. He does it himself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis calmly contends that any book of such length and ambition (it is 461 pages, including footnotes) is bound to contain errors. ''The thing you have to understand about these books is I'm a socialist,'' he said. ''This book has an utterly radical political agenda, no holds barred.''</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Davis, who has taught at the Southern California Institute of Architecture and is now on the verge of accepting a three-year appointment to teach history ''deep in the faux-Colonial architecture of Suffolk County,'' at the State University of New York at Stony Brook, seems to slide reflexively into hyperbole.</p>
        <p>He referred to a friend, William Deverell, a respected professor in his late 30's at the California Institute of Technology, as ''the dean of L.A. historians.'' He mused of his recent visit to a Times Square seemingly devoid of homeless people: ''What's Giuliani done? Built gas chambers in Queens or something?''</p>
        <p>Doug Dutton, who owns the respected independent bookstore in Brentwood that bears his name, had a long list of orders for ''Ecology'' before it was even published. He said Mr. Davis has ''an enormous following'' among his upscale customers.</p>
        <p>''I can't help but think to a certain extent that if you agree with his theories, you'll like the book, and if you don't, you won't,'' Mr. Dutton said. ''It's a kind of analysis that's very personal, almost a grand unified theory for Los Angeles.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis insists he loves the city, which is why he is so hard on it, and says he is trying to inspire a new generation of labor activists, environmentalists and academics to carry on the battles for social justice that he himself fought as a civil rights protester and member of Students for a Democratic Society in the 60's.</p>
        <p>But he acknowledged: ''Some people like the book because they like the glamor of decay and apocalypse. Those people aren't the people I write for, although they probably help sell the book.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
