<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coke Scare Was Preceded By a May Case</title>
    <meta content="Y29COK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1119495"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donaldson, Randy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baskin, Rob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4D6113AF93AA15755C0A96F958260" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coke Scare Was Preceded By a May Case</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>BRUSSELS, June 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Belgian health ministry official says four people become sick at bar near Antwerp and blamed drinking Coca-Cola for their illnesses on May 12, almost four weeks before Coca-Cola Co publicly acknowledged contamination in Belgium that led to biggest recall in its 113-year history; first the public in general knew of scare was on June 8; Coca-Cola spokesman Randy Donaldson says company checked out May 12 incident and had no reason to be concerned; Coke spokesman Rob Baskin says it is first time he is hearing of May incident (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Almost four weeks before the Coca-Cola Company publicly acknowledged the contamination in Belgium that led to the biggest recall in its 113-year history, four people had become sick at a bar near Antwerp and blamed drinking Coke for their illnesses, a senior Belgian health ministry official said today.</p>
        <p>The first the public in general knew of the scare, which eventually led to a total 10-day ban on Coca-Cola products in Belgium and spread alarms across Europe, was on June 8 after more than 30 teen-age school-children in the town of Bornem were taken to the hospital complaining of stomachaches, dizziness and nausea.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Almost four weeks before the Coca-Cola Company publicly acknowledged the contamination in Belgium that led to the biggest recall in its 113-year history, four people had become sick at a bar near Antwerp and blamed drinking Coke for their illnesses, a senior Belgian health ministry official said today.</p>
        <p>The first the public in general knew of the scare, which eventually led to a total 10-day ban on Coca-Cola products in Belgium and spread alarms across Europe, was on June 8 after more than 30 teen-age school-children in the town of Bornem were taken to the hospital complaining of stomachaches, dizziness and nausea.</p>
        <p>But, the health ministry official said, that incident had been preceded by one on May 12 when the owner of a bar at Noorderwijk, a tiny village 20 miles east of Antwerp, called both the Ministry of Public Health and the Coca-Cola Company's staff in Belgium to say four adults had become ill after drinking Coke; the symptoms were similar to those reported by the schoolchildren this month. As in other cases, the four people complained that the Coke they drank smelled strange. Neither the company nor the Belgian authorities had alluded to the earlier incident in their accounts of the recall.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Coca-Cola at the company's Atlanta headquarters said the company had checked out the May 12 incident and had found no reason to be concerned.</p>
        <p>''Nothing was found in the plant, so it was thought to be an anomaly,'' said the spokesman, Randy Donaldson. As for why the company had not mentioned it as more recent reports of problems with Coca-Cola products emerged, he said it was not clear that the incidents were connected, even though the same plant in Antwerp was involved.</p>
        <p>Another Coke spokesman in Atlanta, Rob Baskin, said he had not heard about the May incident until today.</p>
        <p>The Noorderwijk case provides a fuller picture of the events surrounding the Coca-Cola Company's handling of an affair that by the company's own admission, has hurt its reputation and has drawn public apologies from the company's chief executive, M. Douglas Ivester. Coinciding with a food scandal in Belgium over the contamination of meat and poultry with cancer-causing dioxin, it illustrated anew why many Belgians have become nervous about the safety of the food they buy in stores.</p>
        <p>In early May, the Belgian official said, the episode at Noorderwijk seemed like an isolated incident. The Coke drunk by the adults had been packaged in small bottles by a Coke plant in Antwerp -- like those sold to the schoolchildren in Bornem -- and, afterwards, the four people complained of stomachache, dizziness and a burning sensation in the throat.</p>
        <p>Three of them were examined in a hospital, ''but the doctor could not find anything,'' the official said. Samples of Coke from the same batch were sent for analysis at a Government-licensed laboratory, and Coca-Cola was also believed to have ordered tests on the same batch, the official said. But ''because it was one case, because nothing was found in the laboratory, no action was taken,'' this official said.</p>
        <p>''We could not find any poison; there was no proof that it was linked to Coca-Cola,'' the official said.</p>
        <p>With hindsight, however, the official's account seemed to suggest that the scare may have been building slowly in Belgium for weeks before it blew up into a major embarrassment and marketing disaster for the company. But, at a time when Government officials were preoccupied with the dioxin scandal -- and only weeks before elections June 13 that brought down the Government -- it appears that the incident at Noorderwijk was simply filed away.</p>
        <p>At a news conference last week, Mr. Ivester said laboratory tests had found traces of sulfur in the carbon dioxide used to make bubbles in sodas and had discovered that cans of Coke imported from Dunkirk, France, had been contaminated by a chemical used on transportation pallets. He blamed these factors for the 249 cases of Coke-related sickness reported to the Belgian authorities. But the Belgian minister in charge of the case, Luc Van den Bossche, said the Government did not accept this explanation, arguing that the concentrations of the chemicals identified by Mr. Ivester were too low to cause illness.</p>
        <p>The sicknesses among teen-age students in Bornem, also near Antwerp, were the first reported of a series in other parts of Belgium, including Bruges, Harelbeke and Lochristi. On June 14, the Government issued a highly unusual ministerial decree banning a range of Coca-Cola products from sodas to mineral water. The ban was eased June 17 and totally lifted June 23.</p>
        <p>The Belgian health official said that once Coca-Cola had begun to recall its products in Belgium, several people called an emergency center to say that for ''one or two months'' they had detected strange smells from some new vending machines installed by Coke. Thousands of Coke vending machines in Belgium remained off limits when the overall ban was lifted last Thursday and there has been no word on when they will reopen. The smell has been described by some of those who became sick as being like gasoline or sulfur.</p>
        <p>The Belgian official said that two Coca-Cola plants closed during the ban -- at Ghent and Antwerp -- were close to reopening or already had reopened after inspections by Government officials.</p>
        <p>Belgian officials said the bulk of the illnesses appeared to have been linked to sodas produced in early June. But, despite the easing of the restrictions, the Health Ministry official insisted that the cause of the sicknesses remained unclear.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
