<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>1999 Continues Warming Trend Around Globe</title>
    <meta content="19WEAT$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1162296"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Nina (Pacific Ocean Current)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Snow and Snowstorms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E7DD1130F93AA25751C1A96F958260" item-length="1714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>1999 Continues Warming Trend Around Globe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Global warming trend continue in 1999, which is certain to join 1998 as one of the two warmest years on record; 1999 may be slightly less warm that record year of 1998 because of general cooling influence of La Nina phenomenon in eastern tropical Pacific; La Nina is expected to produce same variable weather pattern as it did last winter, and experts say that if atmospheric conditions in North Atlantic develop in a certain way, mid-Atlantic coast, including New York region, could see some heavy snow; photos; maps (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx, fragrant white blooms with a pink blush are breaking out on specimens of a popular landscaping shrub called the Koreanspice viburnum -- four to five months early. Snowdrops, among the earliest bulbs to send up shoots when winter ends, have already poked up their noses. In some New York suburbs, yellow forsythia blossoms have brought a premature touch of spring to December.</p>
        <p>''There's a little confusion out there,'' said Wayne Cahilly, an arborist at the botanical garden, and he expressed no doubt as to the reason: abnormal warmth. Or is it so unusual? ''I think this warm weather is becoming normal,'' Mr. Cahilly said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the New York Botanical Garden in the Bronx, fragrant white blooms with a pink blush are breaking out on specimens of a popular landscaping shrub called the Koreanspice viburnum -- four to five months early. Snowdrops, among the earliest bulbs to send up shoots when winter ends, have already poked up their noses. In some New York suburbs, yellow forsythia blossoms have brought a premature touch of spring to December.</p>
        <p>''There's a little confusion out there,'' said Wayne Cahilly, an arborist at the botanical garden, and he expressed no doubt as to the reason: abnormal warmth. Or is it so unusual? ''I think this warm weather is becoming normal,'' Mr. Cahilly said.</p>
        <p>Certainly it seems that way of late. Last month was the warmest November in 105 years of record-keeping in the contiguous 48 states, and the fourth-warmest in the Northeast. The trend continued into December in most of the country; as of Friday, the average temperature for the month in New York, for instance, was 5.7 degrees Fahrenheit above normal.</p>
        <p>But that is almost the least of it. Federal scientists reported last week that in the contiguous 48 states and on other global land masses, including Europe and Asia, 1999 is certain to join 1998 as one of the two warmest years on record, continuing a long-term trend toward a warmer climate.</p>
        <p>The trend has been especially sharp in the last quarter of the 20th century. Since the mid-1970's, the scientists reported, the average global surface temperature has increased at a rate of about 3.5 degrees per century -- about the same rate estimated for the 21st century if emissions of waste industrial gases that trap heat in the atmosphere are not reduced.</p>
        <p>By comparison, the world has warmed by 5 to 9 degrees since the depths of the last ice age, 18,000 to 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>Globally, this year is turning out to be slightly less warm than the record year of 1998, the scientists said, because of the general cooling influence of the phenomenon known as La Nina, a great pool of cool water that develops naturally from time to time in the eastern tropical Pacific. Because of a cooler ocean surface than last year's, the average global surface temperature in 1999 is not expected to reach the 1998 record of about 58 degrees; it will probably rank as the fifth-highest reading since 1880. Nevertheless, a planetary heating trend that made the 1990's the warmest decade on record is continuing.</p>
        <p>La Nina's counterpart, the pool of extra-warm Pacific water called El Nino, imparted an extra shot of warmth in 1998, and the global temperature had been expected to drop off this year. But despite La Nina's coolness, the temperature of the Northern Hemisphere's land masses is turning out to be the second-highest ever recorded.</p>
        <p>At 55.7 degrees, for instance, this year's average temperature in the 48 states is projected to fall just shy of a record 56.4 degrees set in 1998. The projected 1999 average global land temperature is 56.9 degrees, 1.42 degrees above the average for the years 1880-1998. The warming was especially pronounced in Europe, Asia and North America. In June and July, for example, Russia experienced one of its longest heat waves of the century.</p>
        <p>Thomas R. Karl, the director of the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C., which reported the latest figures, said he was surprised at the persistent warmth on land in a La Nina year. ''We haven't seen anything like this in the observed temperature record,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Apart from their broad effect on global temperatures, La Nina and El Nino also change patterns of atmospheric circulation, with strong short-term effects on weather around the world. Last winter, largely because of La Nina, the Eastern United States had highly variable weather, with stretches of warmer-than-normal temperatures punctuated by sharp bouts of cold. Over all, warmth dominated. But it was snowier and colder than normal in the Pacific Northwest and the Great Lakes.</p>
        <p>A similar pattern is forecast for this winter, but there is a wild card: Although it is too early to tell, federal experts say that if atmospheric conditions in the North Atlantic develop in a certain way, the mid-Atlantic coast, including the New York region, could see some heavy snow.</p>
        <p>The experts say that later next year, other natural fluctuations in circulation could bring a repeat of last summer's drought in some parts of the country, including the Middle Atlantic region and the Northeast,  as well as a more active hurricane season.</p>
        <p>Underlying these natural machinations of atmospheric behavior -- and possibly modifying them in ways not yet clear to scientists -- is a centurylong global warming trend. The average global surface temperature has risen by more than 1 degree Fahrenheit in the last century, according to the federal experts. The dominant scientific view is that emissions of heat-trapping atmospheric gases like carbon dioxide, produced by the burning of coal, oil and natural gas, are at least partly responsible.</p>
        <p>But in the last quarter-century, the rate of warming has been more than double that of the 20th-century average. Mr. Karl's group reported last week that since the mid-1970's, the global temperature has risen at a rate of about 0.35 degrees per decade, or 3.5 degrees per century. Scientists predict that the planet will warm by 2 to 6 degrees over the next 100 years (the best estimate is 3.5 degrees) if emissions of the heat-trapping gases are not cut.</p>
        <p>A warming of 3.5 degrees, according to experts, would cause widespread climatic and environmental dislocations, producing more extreme weather, raising the global sea level, causing precipitation patterns to change and shifting climatic and agricultural zones.</p>
        <p>The United States experienced record-breaking warmth in both of the two most recent winters, said scientists at the government's Climate Prediction Center in Camp Springs, Md. The center predicted last week that on average, most of the country would be warmer than normal over the January-through-March period just ahead.</p>
        <p>In the winter of 1997-98, circulation patterns influenced by El Nino played a crucial role in the warmth. Last winter, different circulation patterns associated with La Nina had a similar effect. Both La Nina and El Nino modify North America's climate by changing the position of the jet stream, the high-altitude river of air that generally runs from west to east and marks the boundary between cold northern air and warm southern air.</p>
        <p>In a La Nina winter, the jet stream typically plunges down through Montana and the northern Plains and then into the central part of the country before curving northeastward. This curve would normally take place in the East, but in a La Nina year it tends to take place farther west, leaving the Eastern Seaboard on the warm side of the warm-cold division marked by the jet stream.</p>
        <p>Eventually this whole pattern drifts eastward, bringing cold weather to the East. An influx of cold northern air is in fact expected for the latter part of this month in the Northeast, said Fred Gadomski, a meteorologist at Pennsylvania State University. This progression happens repeatedly. Sometimes in a La Nina regime, the course of the jet stream temporarily flattens out and whisks warm Pacific air all the way across the continent. Mr. Gadomski said he would not be surprised if such a nationwide warm spell developed after the upcoming cold snap passes.</p>
        <p>Other factors, too, are shaping the winter, scientists at the prediction center say. In addition to the general warming of the atmosphere, for instance, year-to-year flip-flops in circulation patterns over the North Atlantic can have a major effect on weather in the Eastern part of the country.</p>
        <p>If this so-called North Atlantic oscillation is in one mode, typified by low atmospheric pressure over the ocean, the East tends to be warm. If high pressure dominates, said Vernon Kousky, a research meteorologist at the prediction center, the jet stream tends to follow a southerly course into the ocean in the vicinity of Virginia and North Carolina.</p>
        <p>North of that line, big snowstorms can develop, Mr. Kousky said, as happened in 1995-96, a La Nina winter in which a January blizzard dropped record snows from Washington to New York, essentially shutting down the nation's capital for days.</p>
        <p>The North Atlantic oscillation's effect ''never makes itself felt till the end of December or early January,'' Mr. Kousky said, adding that forecasters at this point cannot predict its behavior this winter.</p>
        <p>A similar oscillation in the North Pacific may influence next summer's American weather, he said. The sea-surface temperature there flips back and forth between warm and cool states similar to those of El Nino and La Nina, but stays in one phase for several years. Researchers believe that it may recently have flipped into its warmer state. If it has, Mr. Kousky said, it could set off atmospheric chain reactions next summer that will bring a repeat of last summer's drought in much of the country's Northeastern quadrant, as well as a more active Atlantic hurricane season.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to alert people to that possibility,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Last summer's drought established records for dryness in the Northeast, the Middle Atlantic and the Ohio Valley, Mr. Karl's group reported last week. The April-to-July period was the driest or second-driest in all states from West Virginia to Maine. The drought was followed by record rainfall as hurricanes Dennis and Floyd struck the East Coast. Intensified drought and heavier rain are both expected to result from global warming, although no particular weather event of any kind can be attributed to it.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
