<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word/Representative James A. Traficant Jr.; Burping Cows and Space Toilets. Beam Me Up, Mr. Speaker!</title>
    <meta content="17WORD$21" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1077936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Traficant, Jim (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuntz, Tom</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904EED71E31F934A25752C0A96F958260" item-length="1474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word/Representative James A. Traficant Jr.; Burping Cows and Space Toilets. Beam Me Up, Mr. Speaker!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM KUNTZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuntz, Tom</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Word for Word column quotes some of Repr James A Traficant Jr's special one-minute addresses before House, in which he takes aim at government inanities, and often concludes with 'beam me up'; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PEOPLE just tuning in to Washington over the past year of sex, pizza and judicial racing stripes could be forgiven for wondering: Is Government usually this diverting?</p>
        <p>Of course, it's all in the eye of the beholder. But don't decide for yourself until after you've sampled the one-minute House floor speeches of Representative James A. Traficant Jr., Democrat of Ohio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PEOPLE just tuning in to Washington over the past year of sex, pizza and judicial racing stripes could be forgiven for wondering: Is Government usually this diverting?</p>
        <p>Of course, it's all in the eye of the beholder. But don't decide for yourself until after you've sampled the one-minute House floor speeches of Representative James A. Traficant Jr., Democrat of Ohio.</p>
        <p>One-minute addresses are a House tradition, affording members the opportunity at the beginning of the day to hold forth briefly on any topic they wish -- yielding a sound bite and added verbiage for the Congressional Record regardless of whether anybody present is paying much attention. The speeches will resume shortly when the new Congress takes up normal business.</p>
        <p>When they do, rest assured that Mr. Traficant will rise to be recognized. Over his more than 11 years in the House, the pro-labor, pro-school-prayer ex-county sheriff has turned the short address into his trademark, a verbal blunderbuss loaded with inanities to blast what he sees as Washington's absurdities.</p>
        <p>Usually he punctuates his remarks with a request to be ''beamed up,'' a la ''Star Trek,'' to someplace where there's more intelligent life. Here are excerpts.</p>
        <p>TOM KUNTZ</p>
        <p>On the Economy</p>
        <p>Let us tell it like it is: When you hold this economy to your nosey, this economy does not smell so rosy. If there is any consolation to the American workers, I never heard of anyone in America committing suicide by jumping out of a basement window. I yield back all of the propaganda on this great economy.  --June 10, 1997</p>
        <p>On Nike's Asian Factories</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, I say it is time for the American consumers to tell Nike to take a hikey and buy some American shoes before, so help me God, we are all working in some sweatshop.  --Aug. 2, 1996</p>
        <p>On Nafta</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, the White House says Nafta [the North American Free Trade Agreement] is creating new and exciting jobs. I did some research on those jobs: zipper trimmer, brassiere tender, jelly roller, bosom presser, chicken sexer, sanitary napkin specialist and a pantyhose crotch closer machine operator. That is what I call exciting jobs, Mr. Speaker.  --May 13, 1997</p>
        <p>On Regulation</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, the Lord's prayer is 66 words, the Gettysburg Address is 286 words, the Declaration of Independence is 1,322 words. U.S. regulations on the sale of cabbage -- that is right, cabbage -- is 27,000 words. Now, if that is not enough to give Hulk Hogan's dictionary a hernia, check this out. Regulatory red tape in America costs taxpayers $400 billion every year, over $4,000 each year, every year, year in, year out, for every family. Beam me up.  --July 29, 1998</p>
        <p>On Foreign Policy</p>
        <p>Let us check this out: China gets $60 billion in M.F.N. [most-favored-nation status] from Uncle Sam. Russia gets $15 billion in foreign aid from Uncle Sam. In exchange, Uncle Sam gets nuclear missiles pointed at our cities, two tape decks and three cases of vodka. Beam me up. I say our national security brain trust needs a proctologist on staff.  --April 1, 1998</p>
        <p>On China</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, I think it is time to tell it like it is. When it comes to China, we have gone from ''Speak softly and carry a big stick'' to ''Take the fifth and carry a toothpick.'' Beam me up.  --June 22, 1998</p>
        <p>On Reinventing Government</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, the Vice President said America needs to reinvent Government. To find out why, the G.A.O. called the R.T.C., the I.T.C. and the P.M.S. They did not know.</p>
        <p>The G.A.O. then called the D.O.D., the D.O.T. and the D.D.T. They did not know. The G.A.O. then called the C.I.A., the D.I.A., the E.P.A. and the I.U.D. They did not know. Then they asked the O.M.B. to find out. The O.M.B. created a whole new program called the Government Analysis Service, known as GAS.  --Sept. 3, 1993</p>
        <p>On God</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, a new report says only 7 percent of scientists believe in God. That is right. And the reason they gave was that the scientists were ''super smart.'' Unbelievable. Most of these absent-minded professors cannot find the toilet. Mr. Speaker, I have one question for these wise guys to constipate over: How can some thing come from no thing?</p>
        <p>And while they digest that, Mr. Speaker, let us tell it like it is. Put these super-cerebral master debaters in some foxhole with bombs bursting all around them, and I guarantee they will not be praying to Frankenstein. Beam me up here.  --Aug. 3, 1998</p>
        <p>On Space Toilets</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, space. The final frontier. The search for new life, new civilizations and now new toilets. That is right: NASA has a $30 million space toilet. You strap yourself in and 12 high-pressure air jets aid your relief. . . . Mr. Speaker, I say is time to call out the Roto-Rooter man. . . . Beam me up, Scottie, nature is calling.  --Jan. 23, 1993</p>
        <p>On Russia's President</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, in 1993, Boris Yeltsin fell off a stage in Germany. In 1994, Boris could not get off his plane in Ireland. In 1996 Boris came up missing for seven consecutive days, unexplained, before an election. In 1997, he forgot about a meeting with Vice President Al Gore. Yesterday, he fired his entire Cabinet. The White House says they are monitoring it. . . .</p>
        <p>I say monitor this. Boris Yeltsin does not need monitors. Boris Yeltsin needs Alcoholics Anonymous. I say let us save our foreign aid and let us sent some counselors over to take care of this guy.  --March 24, 1998</p>
        <p>On Flag Desecration</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, in many cities and towns across America it is illegal to kiss in public. It is illegal in some places to ride a skateboard. It is illegal to burn trash or leaves. It is illegal to yodel or sing in public and it is illegal, Mr. Speaker, to tamper with a mailbox. However, in America, it is completely legal to burn the flag, completely legal to desecrate the flag. It is even legal, Mr. Speaker, to urinate on Old Glory. In the words of a Russian comedian, ''America -- What a country.''  --June 7, 1995</p>
        <p>On Belching Cows</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, talking about garbage, the E.P.A. is spending $210,000 to study cow belching and its effects on global warming. Here is how it works.</p>
        <p>Cows will wear backpacks and have hoses connected to their mouths.</p>
        <p>Tell me, Mr. Speaker, what happens if the backpack is so tight and instead of an oral emission, Elsie goes 7.0 on the Richter scale? Will the President declare a garbage emergency . . .? Or how about maybe appoint a Congressional Bovine Burp Task Force. Or maybe the E.P.A. will require -- think about it -- scrubbers on udders, bag hoses on nostrils. I think we ought to take a cattle prod to the E.P.A.  --Sept. 26, 1991</p>
        <p>On Radioactive Beagles</p>
        <p>Madam Speaker [Barbara B. Kennelly, the Connecticut Democrat filling in as Speaker], the remains of 800 beagles and 1,700 tons of their radioactive urine and feces will be buried at a nuclear site in the State of Washington.</p>
        <p>The dead dogs have been in freezers since 1950. They were part of a study to assess the damage of radioactive fallout. The study is now conclusive: Radioactive fallout is fatal, and canines subject thereto died. But the point is, Madam Speaker, the funeral is going to cost $22 million.</p>
        <p>Tell me, are they going to ship the bodies by limo? Are they going to have gold tombstones for every hound?</p>
        <p>With 37 million people in America without health insurance, 9 million people unemployed, I would like to say that our Government is spending $22 million to erect a giant fire hydrant as a mausoleum to dead beagles.</p>
        <p>I think that says it all, Madam Speaker: America's domestic priorities have gone to the dogs.  --Oct. 9, 1991</p>
        <p>On the Government Shutdown</p>
        <p>Mr. Speaker, something does not add up. . . . Experts say, ''Don't worry, America. If the Federal Government shuts down, only nonessential workers will be furloughed.'' . . .</p>
        <p>Now the dictionary says nonessential means not necessary. Now, if that is the case, did anyone around here ever stop to think that if Congress did not borrow money to hire nonessential workers, Congress would not have to borrow more money to pay nonessential workers and Congress would not have to shut down?</p>
        <p>Beam me up, Mr. Speaker. Maybe, just maybe, the Congress of the United States is a little nonessential.  --Nov. 13, 1995</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
