<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fiddling While Antarctica Burns</title>
    <meta content="07HELV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1090609"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctica</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Helvarg, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oceans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E7D8153FF934A35750C0A96F958260" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fiddling While Antarctica Burns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Helvarg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Helvarg, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Documentary producer David Helvarg Op-Ed article on frighteningly rapid impact of global warming on Antarctic Peninsula; cites concern that sudden meltdown of Western Antarctic Ice Sheet could raise global sea levels by over 15 feet over next century; notes threat to continent's abundant wildlife; warns environmental change resulting from warming will define much of 21st century politics; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I am glad to count myself among the handful of Washington reporters who missed the impeachment trial of the President. I was off covering a far more important story in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>My trip convinced me that a hundred years from now Americans will look back at late-20th-century scientific research done in places like Antarctica and wonder how society could have been distracted by the sexual misadventures of a politician.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I am glad to count myself among the handful of Washington reporters who missed the impeachment trial of the President. I was off covering a far more important story in Antarctica.</p>
        <p>My trip convinced me that a hundred years from now Americans will look back at late-20th-century scientific research done in places like Antarctica and wonder how society could have been distracted by the sexual misadventures of a politician.</p>
        <p>For the past 30 years climatologists have predicted that global warming would occur most rapidly at the poles, a fact now confirmed by scientists in Alaska, Canada and Greenland, at the North Pole and on the Antarctic Peninsula. The peninsula is a 700-mile-long rocky kite tail curving out from the coldest, driest, highest continent on earth. The peninsula is also, as I discovered, a wildlife-rich habitat undergoing a frighteningly rapid change.</p>
        <p>At Palmer Station, one of three Antarctic bases administered by the National Science Foundation, I spoke with the chief scientist, Bill Frasier, who has been studying the Antarctic climate since 1974.</p>
        <p>''When I was a graduate student, we were told that climate change occurs but we'd never see the effects in our lifetime,'' Dr. Frasier told me. ''But in the last 20 years I've seen tremendous changes. I've seen islands pop out from under glaciers; I've seen species changing places and landscape ecology altered.''</p>
        <p>While global temperatures have, on average, warmed by 1 degree Fahrenheit over the last century -- paralleling increased industrial output of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases -- the Antarctic Peninsula has seen a jump of more than 5 degrees in just 50 years, including an incredible 10-degree average warming during its winter months. As a result, huge pieces of the ice shelf -- some sections are as large as the state of Delaware -- have begun calving off its eastern shore.</p>
        <p>And scientists are now discussing the possibility that the adjacent Western Antarctic Ice Sheet could experience a sudden meltdown, raising global sea levels by more than 15 feet over the next century (instead of one to three feet, as currently predicted).</p>
        <p>That event could, among other things, turn the Trump Tower mezzanine into waterfront property. While most experts believe this melting will occur sometime after the 21st century, by the time they know for sure it will probably be too late to do anything about it.</p>
        <p>Today's warming poses a more immediate threat to Antarctica's abundant wildlife. And here, too, there are implications that extend to the rest of the world, researchers told me.</p>
        <p>Tiny shrimplike creatures called krill -- the most abundant animal on earth in terms of their total biomass -- are the broad base of Antarctica's food chain, consumed in vast quantities by penguins, seals and whales. (A single blue whale eats four tons a day.) Without access to sea ice, krill shrink, lose weight and are vulnerable to early death.</p>
        <p>A decline of krill due to melting of the ice shelf could wreck much of the Antarctic ecosystem that depends on them.</p>
        <p>Rising temperatures also increase precipitation -- which, in Antarctica, takes the form of snow. Excessive spring snow has disrupted the nesting and breeding of Adelie penguins, leading to the extinction of many of their colonies. At the same time, more adaptable species like chinstrap penguins, elephant seals and fur seals are increasing their numbers, threatening to displace sea ice- dependent animals like Weddell seals, crabeater seals and leopard seals.</p>
        <p>What these changes in the Antarctic Peninsula suggest is that rapid warming could speed up a global chain reaction of extinctions that -- thanks to the impact of humans -- is  already under way.</p>
        <p>''Weedlike'' species that are highly adaptable to disrupted habitat (pigeons, rats, deer and elephant seals) will displace more specialized creatures (tigers, monarch butterflies, river dolphins and Adelie penguins) that depend on unique ecosystems like tropical rain forests, coral reefs and the Antarctic ice shelf.</p>
        <p>Rising temperatures may kill off certain plant species as well. At Palmer Station, I met Tad Day, a plant biologist who studies Antarctica's only two flowering plants: hairgrass and pearlwort. He has found that warming improves growth of pearlwort but appears to have a negative impact on hairgrass. Hairgrass, which was the dominant species in Antarctica, is now being displaced by pearlwort, a mosslike plant.</p>
        <p>''Global warming,'' Dr. Day told me, ''has the capacity to shift the competitive balance of species in ways that, until we get out there and do the research, we don't understand yet, and that could have important consequences on our ability to produce food and fiber.''</p>
        <p>Increasingly reliable climate models now predict a 2-to-6-degree planetary warming in the next century, with regional shifts in agriculture that will favor the industrial north at the expense of the poorer nations of Africa and Latin America. There will also be increases in extreme weather events, coastal storms and the spread of tropical diseases.</p>
        <p>In that light, the work of Antarctic scientists like the ones I met suggests that -- for better or worse -- environmental change will define much of the politics of the 21st century, whether in Washington or at the South Pole.</p>
        <p>David Helvarg is a television documentary producer and the author of ''The War Against the Greens.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Helvarg is a television documentary producer and the author of ''The War Against the Greens.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
