<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trees to Harvest, at Work in the Woods</title>
    <meta content="07LOG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1083207"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nichols Forestry and Logging</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Carolyn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Joan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Logging Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E3D71038F934A35751C0A96F958260" item-length="1290" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trees to Harvest, at Work in the Woods</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLYN BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Carolyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Joan Nichols, forester who works with her husband, Scott, a logger, in their Lebanon, Connecticut-based business; they began Nichols Forestry and Logging in Lebanon in 1990; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOAN NICHOLS had marked some 50 trees in a Lebanon woodlot. Now her husband, Scott, was cutting them down, one by one. ''This operation -- one fellow with a chain saw dropping trees, a skidder pulling them out -- is fairly typical of Connecticut,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her husband neatly dropped a 90-foot oak; his helper, Rick Connolly, readied the skidder. Watching it all was Bill Jahoda, whose family has long owned the woodlot. ''This is being done for a family sugarbush,'' explained Mr. Jahoda, a retired science professor. He'd helped select the oaks and other trees being removed to make more room for sugar maples.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Nichols is a forester; her husband is a ''supervising forest products harvester,'' a logger. They began Nichols Forestry and Logging in Lebanon in 1990, the year they got married. They said they didn't know of any other couple in Connecticut working as such a team.</p>
        <p>She said she grew up on Long Island, and had not expected to take up logging. She did love her family's vacation trips to Maine and to the Adirondacks, however. ''I always liked the woods,'' she said. ''I didn't like being in the city.'' She said she considered a career in environmental education until her studies at SUNY's College of Environmental Science and Forestry at Syracuse set her to thinking along other lines. ''We require wood products,'' she said. ''The more I learned about cutting trees, I thought, 'If we're going to do it, we should do it right.' ''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOAN NICHOLS had marked some 50 trees in a Lebanon woodlot. Now her husband, Scott, was cutting them down, one by one. ''This operation -- one fellow with a chain saw dropping trees, a skidder pulling them out -- is fairly typical of Connecticut,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Her husband neatly dropped a 90-foot oak; his helper, Rick Connolly, readied the skidder. Watching it all was Bill Jahoda, whose family has long owned the woodlot. ''This is being done for a family sugarbush,'' explained Mr. Jahoda, a retired science professor. He'd helped select the oaks and other trees being removed to make more room for sugar maples.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Nichols is a forester; her husband is a ''supervising forest products harvester,'' a logger. They began Nichols Forestry and Logging in Lebanon in 1990, the year they got married. They said they didn't know of any other couple in Connecticut working as such a team.</p>
        <p>She said she grew up on Long Island, and had not expected to take up logging. She did love her family's vacation trips to Maine and to the Adirondacks, however. ''I always liked the woods,'' she said. ''I didn't like being in the city.'' She said she considered a career in environmental education until her studies at SUNY's College of Environmental Science and Forestry at Syracuse set her to thinking along other lines. ''We require wood products,'' she said. ''The more I learned about cutting trees, I thought, 'If we're going to do it, we should do it right.' ''</p>
        <p>After graduation, she worked for the United States Forest Service in Montana for two years before settling in Connecticut, where she worked for a sawmill -- and eventually met Scott, a contract logger who had briefly attended the University of Maine before deciding he'd rather go to work. ''We met in the woods,'' she said. The Nichols, both 39, have two daughters, 2 and 4. And while they may be unusual as a working couple, their activities are not at all unusual in the business of logging -- a dangerous, demanding business worth some $414 million annually to the state's economy.</p>
        <p>Douglas Emmerthal, of the Connecticut D.E.P.'s Division of Forestry, said that logging has high rates of injury, and fatality rates higher than those of firefighting or police work. ''It's a high-overhead business,'' he added. ''Insurance -- liability and workman's compensation -- is a huge expense.'' Equipment is costly, with $800 chain saws just the beginning. A few years ago, the Nichols paid $83,000 for a new skidder and $90,000 for a used tri-axle logging truck. Each would cost more today, and Mr. Emmerthal noted that the latest, most sophisticated models are expensive indeed. ''It's not hard to spend $250,000,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Logging has become increasingly professional in recent years. To remain certified as a ''wood products harvester'' or a ''supervising wood products harvester,'' a logger must attend programs on topics like safety and environmentally sound practices. ''It's not just a bunch of guys with chain saws,'' said Mrs. Nichols. ''Loggers need to do a good job -- leave the woods in good shape, but also supply specific products.'' That means thorough planning and careful work. ''When I meet with landowners,'' she said, ''I try to get an idea of their objectives. I do an inventory, and I try to give them as much information as possible.''</p>
        <p>A logger also needs information. Where and how will this timber be used? Generally, said Mr. Nichols, ''You need to know before you lay it on the ground.'' Every mill has specific requirements, for specific products, and those often change, Mr. Emmerthal pointed out. ''You have to do a lot of homework, make a lot of phone calls,'' he said. ''Say you cut a tree into 9-foot, 6-inch lengths. Maybe you'll find a market tomorrow that would have paid a third more for 9-foot, 8-inch lengths.''</p>
        <p>Timber from Connecticut is marketed widely and winds up in all kinds of products.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Nichols eyed the Jahodas' logs. ''Better logs are going to a mill in Quebec. Lower grade material is going to local mills for railroad ties and pallet material,'' she said. The Jahodas' best logs would go to a veneer mill in northern Vermont. On a recent day Mrs. Nichols met in the Jahodas' driveway with Pierre Lambert, a mill owner from Quebec who had come to Connecticut to buy timber.</p>
        <p>Loggers and landowners are always looking for good markets, affordable trucking has made longer hauls feasible, and new projects keep coming along. Mr. Connelly, the skidder operator, recently bought a sawmill and has been working with Mr. Nichols to learn more about wood and woodcutting. He hopes to sell manufactured post-and-beam house packages.</p>
        <p>Almost 60 percent of Connecticut is forested, with about 90 percent of the forested land privately owned. ''I don't worry about running out of timber,'' said Mrs. Nichols. ''More is coming of age.''</p>
        <p>But there are concerns like the increasing fragmentation of woodlands. ''Woodlots are getting smaller,'' she said, as owners divide their land among younger family members. Some people haven't the means or interest to keep a wooded parcel. Many owners just want to get their land cleared; they tell her they need the money.</p>
        <p>Said Mrs. Nichols: ''I tell them, 'I can do that. I can pay for your timber -- but you can't cut timber like that again for 40 years. It's not going to look pretty, and it's definitely not in the best interest of the resource'.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes, of course, land is simply cleared for new development. With rising land values, she noted, ''The development pressure on woodlots are severe.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nichols added that he has to make a living. If a landowner decides to clear everything, that's what he does. ''I'd rather do lots like this,'' he said, looking over the Jahodas' carefully managed land. ''Scott is a highly skilled logger; he handles his chain saw fast, but carefully,'' said Mr. Jahoda. ''Joan has deep environmental concerns. She'll say, 'I don't think you should cut this,' even though it could be money in her pocket.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jahoda has found that landowners are becoming more interested in management plans that not only produce timber but also provide other benefits, like improved wildlife habitat. ''We've had a forestry plan here since 1980,'' he said. The family land -- which includes trails and a pond -- was named a model tree farm, or managed woodlot, in 1985.</p>
        <p>Trees kept falling. ''I hate to see them come down,'' he said. ''They're old friends -- but they're crowding the sugar maples. My son has about 350 taps here in the spring.'' He set off to show Mrs. Nichols the sugar house, where his son boils sap to make syrup. Meanwhile they talked. Oak growth is down, they noted, because so many deer and turkeys are devouring acorns.</p>
        <p>Recent research suggests that acid rain is leeching calcium from the soil. ''That's frightening,'' said Mr. Jahoda. But mostly they talked about their fondness for the woods. ''This isn't just a paycheck,'' said Mrs. Nichols. ''It gets under your skin.'' She belongs to logging and forestry organizations and is Lebanon's tree warden.</p>
        <p>Still, she chuckled when asked what she and her husband plan for their own woodlot -- 74 acres they just purchased in Lebanon. ''Nothing right now,'' she said. ''I'd like to walk the woods and not worry about working it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
