<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ketchum's challenge is how to remake the Zippo as something other than a cigarette lighter.</title>
    <meta content="Y18ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1093277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lighters</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ketchum Advertising</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D91631F93BA25750C0A96F958260" item-length="801" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ketchum's challenge is how to remake the Zippo as something other than a cigarette lighter.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Ross Sorkin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sorkin, Andrew Ross</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ketchum Advertising takes assignment to create campaign that recasts famous Zippo lighter as something more than cigarette lighter, and, most importantly, aim the campaign at young people, but not too young (the 21- to-26-year-olds) (Advertising column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE assignment was not exactly straightforward: create an advertising campaign that recasts the famous Zippo lighter as something -- anything -- other than a cigarette lighter. And, most importantly, aim the campaign at young people, but not too young.</p>
        <p>Ketchum Advertising Pittsburgh accepted the challenge. Employing the theme ''Use it to start something,'' an ambitious new campaign shows Zippos lighting birthday candles, romantic fires on the beach and even conversations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE assignment was not exactly straightforward: create an advertising campaign that recasts the famous Zippo lighter as something -- anything -- other than a cigarette lighter. And, most importantly, aim the campaign at young people, but not too young.</p>
        <p>Ketchum Advertising Pittsburgh accepted the challenge. Employing the theme ''Use it to start something,'' an ambitious new campaign shows Zippos lighting birthday candles, romantic fires on the beach and even conversations.</p>
        <p>''These are not cigarette lighters; they are ignition devices,'' Lee St. James, creative director at Ketchum Advertising Pittsburgh, part of Omnicom Group, said, laughing.</p>
        <p>While the lighters could be used to ignite cigarettes, he acknowledged, ''I like to think of it as portable fire.''</p>
        <p>Trying to attract significantly younger buyers -- Zippo's current customers average 45 years old -- Zippo has introduced a decidedly irreverent print and television campaign toeing a very fine line between promoting its lighters and promoting smoking.</p>
        <p>''It's a really weird position for me because I don't want to be advocating cigarette smoking, but people are still going to light cigarettes with them,'' Mr. St. James said. ''The hope was to find alternative uses for the product and not link it to cigarette smoking.''</p>
        <p>To that end, the campaign is aimed squarely at 21-  to 26-year-olds, a generation perhaps unfamiliar with Zippo's place in American culture. The Zippo Manufacturing Company, based in Bradford, Pa., was founded in 1932 and gained notice in World War II when the lighters became popular among American soldiers. Since then, Zippos have become a staple of a community of collectors. In fact, 21 percent of owners are lighter collectors, according to the company.</p>
        <p>The campaign is estimated to cost $10 million, which is by far the largest advertising budget ever for the family-owned company. It began running in the fall and returns next week with a new series of print, television and outdoor ads.</p>
        <p>The push to use humor and sophisticated imagery for Zippo is meant to convey a new sense of nicotine-free cool. For example, the print ads include images of a surfer meditating on an exotic beach encircled by candles and a young couple lying on a couch at a trendy lounge bar, staring into the flame of the Zippo lighter seemingly transfixed.</p>
        <p>The print ads have appeared or will appear in Details, Detour, Elle, Entertainment Weekly, Maxim, P.O.V., Premiere, Spin, Rolling Stone and Vibe magazines.</p>
        <p>The television commercials, blending humor with bizarre plot twists, are aimed directly at the MTV generation. In all four spots, a fictitious character referred to as ''Zippo Guy'' gets in trouble using his Zippo in outlandish situations. In one commercial, he is caught by two farmhands trying to light the excreted gas from a cow.</p>
        <p>''According to recent studies the ozone layer is rapidly depleting,'' Zippo Guy is heard saying. ''The main cause for this phenomenon is the mass release of bovine gases. Igniting these gases early on will keep them form rising into the ozone.'' He adds, ''I will save the planet for the ages.'</p>
        <p>The commercials have run or are running on the Comedy Central, ESPN, ESPN2 and MTV cable networks.</p>
        <p>Speaking of Zippo's traditionally older customers, Patrick Grandy, marketing communications manager for Zippo, said, ''If they don't get it, that's O.K., because it's not a message that was directed and designed for them in the first place.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, ''I don't think we're turning them off.''</p>
        <p>Other media vehicles for the campaign include radio commercials that ran in the fall during the Howard Stern syndicated morning radio show, a Web site (www.zippomfg.com) and postcards aimed at college students. Outdoor advertising is being added to the mix with posters to appear on telephone kiosks throughout Manhattan; Zippo hopes to expand the posters to include Los Angeles by next fall.</p>
        <p>Despite the campaign's mandate not to promote cigarette smoking, one publication, The Source, a hip-hop magazine for young people, declined to run the ads after briefly entering into talks with Zippo.</p>
        <p>''We have a policy not to accept any liquor or tobacco advertisements in the magazine,'' said Peter Ferraro, associate publisher for advertising at The Source.</p>
        <p>''When push came to shove I sat down with the publisher and we decided not to take it,'' he added, ''because in the end you know anyone is going to associate a lighter with lighting cigarettes. And whether they had a surfer lighting candles on the beach or somebody lighting birthday candles, it was still just a little too close to comfort for us.''</p>
        <p>''Our 16-  and 18-year-old kids are at an age when they are making decisions about whether or not to smoke,'' Mr. Ferraro said. ''What do you do with a lighter? You know?''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
