<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Double Vision: The Return Of Powers, Austin Powers</title>
    <meta content="18TAKI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1116260"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="TAKING THE CHILDREN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Peter M</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Austin Powers: the Spy Who Shagged Me (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Extreme (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Limbo (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Taking the Children</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EFD7163BF93BA25755C0A96F958260" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Double Vision: The Return Of Powers, Austin Powers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nichols, Peter M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter M Nichols reviews films Austin Powers: The Spy Who Shagged Me, Extreme and Limbo, focusing on their suitability for children; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Austin Powers: The Spy Who Shagged Me</p>
        <p>Mike Myers, Heather Graham, Seth Green, Verne J. Troyer, Michael York, Robert Wagner, Mindy Sterling, Will Ferrell, Elizabeth Hurley, Rob Lowe  Directed by Jay Roach  PG-13  95 minutes</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Austin Powers: The Spy Who Shagged Me</p>
        <p>Mike Myers, Heather Graham, Seth Green, Verne J. Troyer, Michael York, Robert Wagner, Mindy Sterling, Will Ferrell, Elizabeth Hurley, Rob Lowe  Directed by Jay Roach  PG-13  95 minutes</p>
        <p>Glued to the Jerry Springer show on their surveillance screens, NATO early-warning team members notice something truly alarming. That bullet-headed nut case in the fistfight with the Ku Klux Klan Grand Dragon looks suspiciously like Dr. Evil (Mr. Myers). Come to think of it, bullet head's son, Scott Evil (Mr. Green), said it all when he introduced the Springer segment: ''My Father Is Evil, and He Wants to Take Over the World.''</p>
        <p>Unaware of Evil's escape from outer space (don't ask), Austin Powers (Mr. Myers), the manic yellow-toothed international man of mystery from the original Powers adventure (1997), parties on with his bride,  Vanessa (Ms. Hurley). Suddenly she reveals herself to be Evil's robot, sprays him with bullets from her breasts, which turn into machine guns, and detonates.</p>
        <p>That frees Austin to resume womanizing, which he celebrates with a romp through a hotel wearing nothing but the simian hairdo blanketing his chest. Charged with reapprehending Evil, he then goes time traveling to 1969, where the Carnaby Street scene is enlivened by the agent Felicity Shagwell (Ms. Graham).</p>
        <p>All the while, Evil schemes to destroy Washington with a laser beam. ''Great plan, Einstein,'' says Scott Evil, a sarcastic Generation X-er who accuses his father of a ''Star Wars'' rip-off. The doctor also robs Austin of his ''mojo'' (this movie's version of the Force), which fuels sexual appetite. Now there's a crisis.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Pure slapstick and always clearly so.  SEX -- Continual references are part of the spoof. For example, a rocket shaped like a penis inspires a long string of double-entendres involving cameo appearances by guest stars. And Austin prances nude, though not frontally so. It's silly stuff, but where children are concerned it adds up to considerable sexual content.  PROFANITY -- A stream of scatological references and related obscenities.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?</p>
        <p>AGES 3-10 -- Most parents will consider the film unsuitable.  AGES 11-13 -- This is a borderline age. Individual parental guidelines apply, but most children this age will be eager.  AGES 14 AND UP -- There shouldn't be a problem.</p>
        <p>Extreme</p>
        <p>A two-dimensional (no glasses required) Imax film at the Sony Imax Theater in Manhattan  Directed by Jon Long  No rating -- 44 minutes</p>
        <p>In a spectacle as huge as the eight-story Imax screen, surfers and wind surfers, skiers and snow boarders and ice and rock climbers perform under challenging circumstances.</p>
        <p>Surfers on Oahu in Hawaii are towed by jet ski into seas too heavy to paddle through. Left on their own, they rocket shoreward, pursued by breaking walls of water 30 to 40 feet high. Skiers and boarders plummet down near-vertical mountains, flying off cliffs and artfully avoiding the mini-avalanches racing along with and sometimes ahead of them. On vertical (and occasionally beyond vertical) cliffs and ice sheets, one man and several women claw their way to dizzying perches hundreds of feet above. Who's got the sunscreen?</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- None.  SEX -- None.  PROFANITY -- None.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?</p>
        <p>AGES 3-10 -- They'll be enthralled.  AGES 11 AND UP -- They will, too, though some older children may grow annoyed with wooden attempts to verbalize these exploits with banalities like ''getting into who you are'' and going to ''a place where time doesn't exist.''</p>
        <p>Limbo</p>
        <p>Mary Elizabeth Mastrantonio, David Strathairn, Vanessa Martinez, Kris Kristofferson, Casey Siemaszko  Directed by John Sayles  R -- 126 minutes</p>
        <p>In Alaska, Donna (Ms. Mastrantonio), a talented, hard-pressed club singer, is attracted to Joe (Mr. Strathairn), a quiet former fisherman who now works as a handyman. That displeases Noelle (Ms. Martinez), Donna's deeply troubled teen-age daughter, who is tired of her mother's seemingly never-ending parade of disastrous boyfriends.</p>
        <p>Joe is a bookish, soft-spoken man with a mysteriously tragic air about him who, it turns out, left the sea after a fatal accident 25 years earlier. It also happens that he and Noelle work for the same employers and  she even has a crush on him, which doesn't exactly improve relations with her mother.</p>
        <p>All around them Alaska is being carved up by developers who would allow the interior to be turned into a parking lot as long as the spectacular coastal vistas are maintained to draw the floating hotels for the elderly cruising north for a look at the proverbial last frontier.</p>
        <p>Into the harder world of everyday Alaskans comes Joe's half-brother Bobby (Mr. Siemaszko), a former resident who has gone south for better pickings but has run into problems with some associates over a boatload of drugs. To avoid these people Bobby makes a run for it on his yacht through beautiful ice-flecked waters.</p>
        <p>Unaware of Bobby's situation, Joe has taken Donna and Noelle along for what they think will be a pleasurable sail. While anchored one evening the three of them are below when they hear shots on deck. Escaping through a forward hatch, they swim to shore on a deserted island and hide, shivering in the forest while those who dispatched Bobby search for them but finally leave.</p>
        <p>For the next 10 days they survive off the land and local waters, huddle in the ruins of a fox farmer's shack and stoke a signal fire that they hope will attract rescuers and not Bobby's attackers. Noelle, a fine writer herself, discovers a diary written years ago by the fox farmer's daughter and reads excerpts by firelight.</p>
        <p>A depressing tale it is, too. But they persevere, confront and comfort one another, giving rise to hope that they might make a compatible unit once this is over. Then an aircraft engine is heard in the distance.</p>
        <p>VIOLENCE -- Shots are heard but no violence is seen, nor is there any in the rest of the film. Noelle, however, experiments with self-mutilation, cutting herself slightly.  SEX -- Donna and Joe are shown in bed after love-making, and embracing in the woods.  PROFANITY -- A moderate amount, sparingly and tellingly employed.</p>
        <p>For Which Children?</p>
        <p>AGES 14 AND UP -- Mr. Sayles (''The Secret of Roan Innish'') has made another strong, thoughtful film about credible people under pressure. Many older teen-agers will respond, and parents could well decide that in this case the benefits outweigh the R rating.</p>
        <p>TAKING THE CHILDREN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
