<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Muscle, Muscle Everywhere</title>
    <meta content="19WALD$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1108610"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="CARS AND THE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Sections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DA1F3CF93AA25756C0A96F958260" item-length="1463" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Muscle, Muscle Everywhere</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Muscular horsepower of modern cars and light trucks noted (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TAIL FINS went, round headlights gave way to square ones, and then chrome all but disappeared. But the biggest change in cars over the last few years is not cosmetic. It is under the hood: the engine is on steroids.</p>
        <p>Year by year, cars and light trucks have undergone a remarkable transformation, through a host of changes in engines and transmissions. The typical family vehicle of the late 1990's has turned into something that in the 1970's would have qualified as a mean street machine. And more changes are waiting in the wings that will make cars more muscular yet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TAIL FINS went, round headlights gave way to square ones, and then chrome all but disappeared. But the biggest change in cars over the last few years is not cosmetic. It is under the hood: the engine is on steroids.</p>
        <p>Year by year, cars and light trucks have undergone a remarkable transformation, through a host of changes in engines and transmissions. The typical family vehicle of the late 1990's has turned into something that in the 1970's would have qualified as a mean street machine. And more changes are waiting in the wings that will make cars more muscular yet.</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency, which has kept track since 1975, says in a draft report that for the 1998 model year, the average car had 160 horsepower, up 60 percent from 1981. Light trucks, including sport utility vehicles, which now make up almost half the market, were at 190 horsepower, also up 60 percent. A family that bought three cars in 1981 and replaced them with two new ones in 1998 would have more horsepower in the driveway now.</p>
        <p>These days, it is not uncommon for performance cars like the Lexus GS 400 to contain more power than some heavy trucks -- 300 horsepower for the sedan to 275 for a number of Mack Truck's 18-wheelers -- and more than the engine of the typical four-seat passenger plane.</p>
        <p>''The horsepower race is on -- it's never been off,'' said Thomas W. Asmus, the senior research executive for DaimlerChrysler in Auburn Hills, Mich. ''With the strong economy, people are willing to spend money on all kinds of automobile features that in less good times they're not willing to spend money on. Vehicle performance has great market appeal.''</p>
        <p>But not everyone is so happy. ''The traditional horsepower war certainly shows no sign of abating,'' said John DeCicco, the transportation program director at the American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy. He, too, agreed that consumers are getting what they ask for, but, he added, ''We are seeing automotive technology running amok.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. DeCicco and other environmentalists, the growth of engine efficiency is a case of the road not taken. Manufacturers have three choices when it comes to engine innovations that get more work from a gallon. They can give cars smaller, lighter engines that will maintain performance while cutting fuel consumption. Or they can increase weight while keeping performance constant. But almost without exception, they have used the gains to make cars faster -- and sometimes heavier as well.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. estimates that if auto makers had kept constant the car's weight and number of seconds it takes to accelerate to 60 miles per hour, but continued to add the same improvements to engines and transmissions, then 1998 cars would have averaged 33.5 miles per gallon, and trucks 25.7 miles per gallon. In both cases, this would have been about 5 miles per gallon better than the average for vehicles actually sold.</p>
        <p>INSTEAD, the application of advanced technology to engines is driving performance ever higher, even though the other big determinant of acceleration, vehicle weight, has been rising. According to the E.P.A.'s draft report, the Light-Duty Automotive Technology and Fuel Economy Trends study, since 1981 the average vehicle has gained more than 550 pounds, reaching 3,760 pounds in 1998, from 3,201. Even with that extra heft, the time it takes a car to accelerate to 60 miles per hour from a stop, the most widely used measure of performance, has gone from 14.4 seconds in 1981 to 10.8 seconds in 1998.</p>
        <p>Cars are only half the story, almost literally, since they accounted for about 55 percent of sales in 1998, down from 81 percent in 1975. Light trucks have shown a similar increase in performance, despite their larger size.</p>
        <p>Acar with 100 horsepower was once a common, respectable model, but of 200 models in Consumer Reports' 1999 auto issue, only four had less than 100 horsepower.</p>
        <p>Behind the trend in engine innovations  are several refinements, most of which began in high-end cars and are working their way down to the ''econobox'' end of the market. A number of the new developments have made engines work better by making it easier for them to breathe.</p>
        <p>One is the switch to four valves per cylinder from the traditional two. Valves control the flow of gases into and out of the cylinder,  a space about the size of a small can of peanuts. The valves, which control openings varying in size from a quarter to a half dollar, let the fuel-air mixture in as the piston goes down, and let the exhaust gases out as the piston rises. Every bit of friction that these gases encounter, on the way in or the way out, is power that does not go to the wheels. As engine speed increases, and more gas has to be moved through the valves, adding valves lets air in and out more easily, increasing the range of speeds at which the engine can operate efficiently.</p>
        <p>And that, in turn, has allowed engines to get slightly smaller, because a small engine operating at 6,000 r.p.m. can produce as much power as a slightly larger one operating at 5,000 r.p.m. Engines not only move weight, but they're also heavy themselves. And for every pound that engine weight is reduced, designers can cut at least another  pound from the car's suspension and frame. With each pound lost, the number of horses per 100 pounds of weight rises, and the car can accelerate faster. All of this weight loss -- and more -- has been eaten up by fatter bodies.</p>
        <p>Other engine refinements are still in their infancy, including variable valve timing, in which intake valves stay open longer and exhaust valves open sooner, depending on engine speed, and electronic controls or multiport fuel injectors, which smooth out the flow of fuel to the cylinders, to reduce friction.</p>
        <p>Of course, there remains the question of when exactly extra horsepower is truly needed. Lexus introduced its powerful sport sedan, the GS 400, with the advertising theme ''Something Wicked This Way Comes.'' To environmentalists, the whole trend adds up to Something Wasteful. ''They advertise these things with people driving up Pike's Peak, or whatever, but 95 percent of the people who buy these things don't do that,'' said Ann R. Mesnikoff, an global warming specialist at the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>Cars ran fine 15 years ago when the average engine was 60 horsepower smaller, she said, adding, ''How much performance do people need?''</p>
        <p>In Valves, Timing Is Everything</p>
        <p>SOME of the most promising engine improvements are still in the development stage -- variable valve timing, for example. Honda does this now with a mechanical system, but more flexible, capable mechanisms are on the way.</p>
        <p>Today, almost all engine valves open and close in lock step with the turning of the crankshaft, like a cuckoo in a clock that pops out precisely when the minute hand reaches the 12. With variable timing, valves would stay open longer, or shut later, depending on engine speed.</p>
        <p>When the engine is running fast, the fuel-air mixture flowing into the cylinders has a lot of momentum. Keep the intake valves open an extra fraction of a second, and that momentum will fill the cylinders extra-full, giving the engine more power. And if the exhaust valves open slightly early in high-speed operation, that prevents the cylinder from repressurizing in the exhaust stroke, which would cut power.</p>
        <p>A number of companies are working on systems using valves operated hydraulically or by electric impulses through solenoids.</p>
        <p>A related improvement would be to use the intake valves, rather than the throttle, to control the amount of fuel and air going to the cylinders. Closing the throttle increases air friction, reducing efficiency; closing a valve early to limit fuel doesn't.</p>
        <p>Engineers have found other ways to cut friction, including electronic controls that make the car run smoothly at low engine speeds and multiport fuel injectors that  even fuel flow to the cylinders.</p>
        <p>One step on the drawing boards is an engine with a variable compression ratio that would produce a burst of extra power by briefly allowing extra fuel and extra air into the cylinder.</p>
        <p>If a car needed a 160-horsepower engine but could perform adequately most of the time with 150, then a manufacturer could substitute the lighter, more fuel-efficient engine. When the car needed an extra 10 horsepower -- say, for merging onto a busy expressway -- an engine with a variable compression ratio could provide it on demand.</p>
        <p>MATTHEW L. WALD</p>
        <p>CARS AND THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
