<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Aims to Have 5% of Electricity From Wind by 2020</title>
    <meta content="20WIND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1117099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D7123BF933A15755C0A96F958260" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Aims to Have 5% of Electricity From Wind by 2020</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Sec Bill Richardson says he will announce plan to produce 5 percent of nation's electricity from wind by 2020, up from 0.1 percent now, phone interview; holds wind technology has most potential of any renewable energy technology at present; photo (M)g</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Energy Secretary Bill Richardson says he will announce on Monday a plan to produce 5 percent of the nation's electricity from wind by 2020, up from one-tenth of 1 percent now. Under the plan, the Federal Government, the nation's largest electricity customer, would rely on wind for 5 percent of its use by 2010.</p>
        <p>''We think that wind technology has the most potential of any renewable energy technology right now,'' Mr. Richardson said in a telephone interview. The other leading renewable contenders are electricity from the sun or from biomass, including crop wastes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Energy Secretary Bill Richardson says he will announce on Monday a plan to produce 5 percent of the nation's electricity from wind by 2020, up from one-tenth of 1 percent now. Under the plan, the Federal Government, the nation's largest electricity customer, would rely on wind for 5 percent of its use by 2010.</p>
        <p>''We think that wind technology has the most potential of any renewable energy technology right now,'' Mr. Richardson said in a telephone interview. The other leading renewable contenders are electricity from the sun or from biomass, including crop wastes.</p>
        <p>Outside experts agree that wind is the closest to being competitive in price. Charles R. McGowin, the team leader for renewable energy at the Electric Power Research Institute, of Palo Alto, Calif., a utility consortium, said, ''There's a lot of untapped wind potential in the United States, particularly in the upper great Plains, North Dakota, Wyoming, South Dakota and Minnesota and Iowa.'' One problem, though, is that transmission lines will have to be built if wind machines become widespread enough.</p>
        <p>Department officials say wind turbines, the industry's preferred term for windmills, are good cash producers for farmers, who can graze cattle or grow crops in their shadow.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richardson, who will make the plan public in a speech to the American Wind Energy Association's annual meeting, in Burlington, Vt., said the department would seek to ''merge technology with good commercialization.''</p>
        <p>The department will take steps like encouraging ''wind-friendly codes and covenants,'' investing money in research and development, and encouraging vocational schools to help train ''wind smiths.''</p>
        <p>Around the country, about 2,500 megawatts of capacity are expected to be in service by the end of this month, up from about 1,600 megawatts a year ago. The difference, 900 megawatts, is about the capacity of one medium-size nuclear plant.</p>
        <p>The Enron Corporation began construction last month of a 16.5-megawatt plant in California to meet demand for ''green power'' there. The company expects that, as the power market there is deregulated, customers will choose clean power.</p>
        <p>Several projects are scheduled for completion by June 30, when a Federal tax credit of 1.7 cents per kilowatt-hour expires. The Clinton Administration is seeking a renewal for projects completed over the next five years.</p>
        <p>The price of a kilowatt-hour from wind has declined to about 5 cents, said Dan W. Reicher, Assistant Secretary for Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy. It was as high as 40 cents when the Federal Government first pushed wind turbines for electricity production during the oil crises of the 1970's. Combined with the production tax credit, the price is low enough to find buyers.</p>
        <p>The department believes that the cost of production must fall to between 2 cents and 2.5 cents per kilowatt-hour to succeed in the first decades of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>The average American residential consumer pays about 7 cents per kilowatt-hour, which is enough energy to light a 75-watt bulb for 13 hours.</p>
        <p>The industry has made large strides on cost, though, partly by increasing the size of its machines. The first turbines were a few kilowatts, good for a house or two; now they are 1,000 times larger. The biggest being installed now are 1.65 megawatts, with blades the length of the wings on a Boeing 727, but engineers are drawing plans for turbines of up to 4 megawatts in capacity.</p>
        <p>Another source of price cuts is improvements in electronics. Blades used to have to turn at a fixed rate to make alternating current at the strict 60 cycles per second required; now they can turn at whatever rate the wind pushes them, and the energy is electronically converted to 60 cycles. Wind machines now cost $900 to $1,200 per kilowatt to install; the Energy Department expects the price to decline to $625 a kilowatt by 2020.</p>
        <p>Direct comparisons of construction costs with coal or natural gas plants are difficult, because those plants can operate 24 hours a day, but wind turbines operate only when the wind is blowing. Wind turbines typically produce only a little more than one-third of the amount of electricity that would result from operation 24 hours a day at 100 percent operation. But ''once you're up and running, there is no fuel cost and the maintenance cost is negligible as well,'' said Kent Robertson, a spokesman for the wind association.</p>
        <p>Another big change since the 1970's, one helpful to wind, is that states are deregulating their electricity systems, and the manufacturing of power by independent producers, as opposed to utilities, will soon be the norm, many industry executives say. The utilities were never very enthusiastic about building wind capacity themselves, but soon they will not be building any capacity of any sort, and when the utilities are buying all their electricity from independent plants running on coal or natural gas, then buying power from a wind farm will not be much different, experts say.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
