<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Life, the Universe and Everything</title>
    <meta content="17EVERDET" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1077639"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Everdell, William R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fromkin, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Way of the World, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D8113EF934A25752C0A96F958260" item-length="1540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Life, the Universe and Everything</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William R. Everdell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Everdell, William R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William R Everdell reviews book The Way of the World: From the Dawn of Civilzations to the Eve of the Twenty-First Century by David Fromkin; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE WAY OF THE WORLD  From the Dawn of Civilizations to the Eve of the Twenty-first Century.  By David Fromkin.  253 pp. New York:  Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE WAY OF THE WORLD  From the Dawn of Civilizations to the Eve of the Twenty-first Century.  By David Fromkin.  253 pp. New York:  Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>MANY historians nowadays write with more concern for a nonprofessional audience than they did 40 years ago, but even so relatively few of their books unabashedly invite nonhistorians to enjoy and profit from them. One such is a tour de force called ''A Peace to End All Peace'' (1989), about the diplomatic origins of the modern Middle East. The author, David Fromkin, is a professor of international relations, a branch of political science, and like many in political science -- including Machiavelli himself among its long-ago founders -- he is an unapologetic practitioner of his field's parent discipline, history.</p>
        <p>''The Way of the World,'' however, is quite a different project. It began, Fromkin writes, when he was asked by a Wall Street hedge fund manager over lunch, ''Can you tell the story of humanity in the universe and make it whole?'' He answered that yes, he thought he could, and began to produce this universal history in 222 pages of text. Two hundred and twenty-two pages for everything? A ''History of the World in 300 Pages'' was written by Rene Sedillot 50 years ago, but the extra 78 pages have not made it any easier to find today. Sir Walter Raleigh wrote ''an universall Historie'' to while away prison time, but it went to more than one volume; Puritans took it as an indispensable supplement to the sacred history of the Bible, but few people consult it now. In a sense the whole philosophy of Hegel is a universal history, as is a 50-page reply to it, Marx and Engels's ''Communist Manifesto,'' but both have lost their appeal. Toynbee's 10-volume ''Study of History'' has aged faster. William H. McNeill's still more recent ''Rise of the West'' was only one volume but it was more than 1,000 pages. Fromkin himself acknowledges only one model, the 1920 ''Outline of History'' by H. G. Wells (and makes no mention of the book Wells was replying to, Spengler's 1918 ''Decline of the West'').</p>
        <p>Fromkin distinguishes eight stages in universal history, most of them hinging on events historians of many stripes can agree on as the most significant in the history of humankind: the emergence of the hominid line, apes with brains, in prehistoric Africa (''Becoming Human''); the discovery of agriculture and the creation of the first cities -- settlements whose residents were not all farmers (''Inventing Civilization''); the sudden rise of universalizing religious and moral systems all over civilized Eurasia in the sixth century B.C. (''Developing a Conscience''); the birth of the idea of world civilization with the empires of ancient Eurasia (''Seeking a Lasting Peace''); the rise of rationalism and empirical science (''Achieving Rationality''); the irreversible encounter, after the 15th century, between human societies in Eurasia and Africa and those in the Americas (''Uniting the Planet''); the industrial modernization that began in the 18th century (''Releasing Nature's Energies''); and finally the steady movement toward democratic government centered in the 19th century and the unsteady movement toward decolonization and world law in the 20th (''Ruling Ourselves'').</p>
        <p>This is of course a Western view, and it is a progressive one. Fromkin is convinced, as against many post-moderns, that things have got better for us humans since the Upper Paleolithic. Though he easily imagines disasters that can interrupt or reverse the long-term trends he describes, he sees no compelling argument for turning back. In four concluding chapters, he attempts to extrapolate a future, which he admits is not easy -- a little like trying to predict global warming from one very warm November. He expects further difficulties with population and environment; he looks forward to the colonization of other planets, and he sees the greatest immediate challenge as the tension between the rising need for world law and the rising drive toward cultural self-determination.</p>
        <p>Small wonder that such a book, a universal history in short compass, is one of the great literary challenges. Think of all those human lives lived since Australopithecus walked in Laetoli three and a half million years ago, or even in the five and a half thousand since prehistory ended in ancient Sumer (or was it Egypt?) with the invention of writing. Those billions of lives, multiplied by their experience, are the raw stuff of history, and yet the history of a single family could easily fill a university library. The art is in deciding how to cut, whom to leave out and why, all the while facing the overwhelming odds that truth will be left on the cutting room floor. ''Telling one story necessarily means not telling another,'' Fromkin writes, and he has a pretty good idea of what he has bitten off. Not only are you biased to begin with toward your own culture, its past and its valuations of other cultures; you are biased toward your own career as a historian, which will necessarily have been concerned with a much narrower slice. ''Life is a story that each of us tells to his or her self; and it therefore is a tale told by an unreliable narrator,'' Fromkin admits. And finally, since no one can know enough to write universal history alone, you will inevitably be indebted to other writers and researchers. How will you find the space you need to credit them?</p>
        <p>Then there is the problem of presentation. It is rarely new discoveries that demand to be recounted in a universal history, and as Pope observed, nothing needs to be so well expressed as that which oft was thought. With enough left out of even ordinary histories to make history elliptical by nature, universal history has so much ellipsis that the only way to deal with it is to use a style as elevated and a language as allusive and referential as the ones we use for poetry. Fromkin can be allusive, as when he disposes of World War II in a single daring sentence: ''The war resumed in 1939-1945 and Germany lost again.'' He can often be lapidary, too, as in ''Today's world is the world that America wanted, but it is not a world that America made.'' This makes it all the more clear when he falls short, as in ''Looking back, what happened in modern history was that a millennium ago, Europe began to develop a distinctive mentality.''</p>
        <p>Fromkin deserves considerable credit for skirting or resisting his guild interests. He spends only a few paragraphs rehearsing the fruits of his own research on the modern Middle East. His use of other historians' work is wise and acknowledged with unobtrusive generosity, and only once or twice (for example on our knowledge of Harappan and Mesoamerican writing) does he accept a tendentious or obsolete source. If he is perhaps too insistently politically incorrect, giving the Greeks too much credit for empirical rationality, Europeans too much credit for democracy and Americans too much for individualism, if he forgives dominant cultures more than he should for imperialism, slavery, proletarian misery and environmental destruction, he credits no culture for acting against self-interest. This book might easily serve as a supplementary textbook in secondary schools, especially with the addition of a few pictures and time lines. Schoolchildren love to contemplate the big picture, from both the moral and the long-term historical points of view. There are hardly any textbooks in the prehistory and ancient history of our planet for young people, probably because of that silent struggle for power in local school districts. A surprisingly large faction would be outraged if children were taught that dinosaurs vanished from the earth some 60 million years before the first hominids walked upright on it. A similarly large faction would be steamed if the approximate date that cities first arose in Mesopotamia (4000 B.C.) were pre-empted as the date of God's creation of the cosmos. The result is a tremendous confusion about the definitions of terms and the importance of events in what Fromkin rightly calls the unique and therefore epic story of how we got here, and what it all means, if anything.</p>
        <p>''The Way of the World'' is a title famously used by the risque Restoration playwright William Congreve. Perhaps Fromkin's idea was to avoid freighting his book with the unmediated moral seriousness universal history has traditionally demanded. More likely it was to prefigure his central narrative, which is that the meaning of human history is not divine but natural, and his central moral, which is that humans must take responsibility even for the natural and make their own history. The responsibility becomes heavier and heavier as our numbers become greater and greater, our cultures less and less various and our choices fewer and fewer. History is now universal whether we like it or not. As Fromkin writes, in one of his most lapidary pronouncements: ''Now we're all in the same boat. It may be a seaworthy boat; but it would be less worrisome if there were more than one.''</p>
        <p>William R. Everdell is the author of ''The First Moderns.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">William R. Everdell is the author of ''The First Moderns.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
