<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Challenging That Cheeseburger</title>
    <meta content="07CONT$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1151447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="ON THE CONTRARY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akst, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Contrary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smoking and Tobacco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDB163AF934A35752C1A96F958260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Challenging That Cheeseburger</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANIEL AKST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Akst, Daniel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel Akst On the Contrary column compares litigation against tobacco industry with imaginary suit filed against fast-food industry for harming people by selling cheeseburgers that have potential of causing heart disease and deaths; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IMAGINE that you're a trial lawyer. You've noticed that Americans are getting fatter, and that the government blames obesity and inactivity for more than 300,000 premature deaths every year.  You've also noticed that scientists believe fatty foods kill people, and that fast-food outlets are selling cheeseburgers with both hands.</p>
        <p>You pilot your late-model Mercedes into the drive-through lane, risking grease stains on the leather upholstery. You make a purchase and discover that fast-food packaging is mute as to a more important risk. Nowhere does it say that eating a bucket of hot wings could result in serious injury or death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IMAGINE that you're a trial lawyer. You've noticed that Americans are getting fatter, and that the government blames obesity and inactivity for more than 300,000 premature deaths every year.  You've also noticed that scientists believe fatty foods kill people, and that fast-food outlets are selling cheeseburgers with both hands.</p>
        <p>You pilot your late-model Mercedes into the drive-through lane, risking grease stains on the leather upholstery. You make a purchase and discover that fast-food packaging is mute as to a more important risk. Nowhere does it say that eating a bucket of hot wings could result in serious injury or death.</p>
        <p>So you sue, hoping to win millions on behalf of heart patients -- as well as potential heart patients, who claim compensation for the worry that all those cheeseburgers may someday give them heart disease. Better yet, perhaps the states, unwilling to regulate cheeseburgers, will retain you to sue on behalf of the taxpayers, who have had to foot the public health bill for all the cheeseburgers they can't stop eating.</p>
        <p>Far-fetched? Why? The same line of reasoning underlies the litigation that has succeeded so spectacularly against the tobacco companies; similar suits are pending against manufacturers of guns.</p>
        <p>''The connection between cigarettes and guns,'' says Richard Daynard, a law professor at Northeastern University who founded the Tobacco Products Liability Project to spur lawsuits against the industry, ''is that both used political influence to escape safety regulation, and eventually people got tired of that and turned to the courts.''</p>
        <p>He is right, and at first it is easy to applaud the plaintiffs' lawyers who brought the suits. But are guns and cigarettes really the same? For better or worse, Americans have the right to bear arms, the government already regulates guns, and it's at least debatable whether guns, unlike cigarettes, really do more harm than good. Besides, our experiences with outright prohibition of dangerous products like alcohol and drugs have been terrible.</p>
        <p>The point is not the merits of gun control (which I advocate) or smoking (which I abhor). The point is, who decides? Despite the role of money in politics, government can regulate harmful products whenever there is the political will to do so. So it is puzzling to find governments as plaintiffs in product liability lawsuits. ''It's bizarre to go to court and ask for relief from the fact that you have the wrong laws,'' said Daniel Polsby, a law professor at George Mason University.</p>
        <p>Consider global warming. When coastal cities find themselves building dikes to keep the waves at bay, why not sue Exxon and General Motors over their role in changing the world's climate? And why wait until the waters start rising? The science on global warming is already substantial, but having good science on your side is no prerequisite for suing, as the makers of silicone breast implants (and their unfortunate shareholders) well know.</p>
        <p>By the lights of modern jurisprudence, it would make perfect sense for ''victims'' of fast food and climate change to sue, and the sooner the better: they might even succeed at deterring substantial harm. One claim against gun makers is that they failed to take the steps they should have to make sure that weapons aren't used improperly. But last year, 15,935 Americans died in alcohol-related car accidents, and the auto industry for years has known how to install devices that could make it more difficult for someone impaired by alcohol to start a car. Why isn't the plaintiff's bar assaulting Detroit on that point?</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is just that they haven't gotten to it yet. At the moment, another target is in their sights: H.M.O.'s. The lawyers see themselves as protectors of innocent patients against profit-hungry corporations bent on rationing care. If the lawyers succeed (their first case is against Aetna), H.M.O.'s may indeed change the way they do business. But premiums will inevitably rise, forcing more Americans to join the 44 million who already lack health insurance.</p>
        <p>THAT'S the trouble with letting lawyers and juries tackle social problems that elected officials can't seem to solve: when the buck is passed to the courts, the outcome may never suit anyone but the lawyers. Consider the Supreme Court's record. It upheld slavery until the Civil War made its decisions moot. It tried to paper over racial segregation with the ''separate but equal'' fiction, and when that failed, ordered public schools integrated, yet de facto school segregation persists. Roe v. Wade has hardly laid the abortion debate to rest.</p>
        <p>It's hard to believe that lawyers, judges and juries can do any better with guns or global warming (or gluttony). But if the political system remains paralyzed by money and cynicism, it shouldn't be surprising if the courts try.</p>
        <p>ON THE CONTRARY Daniel Akst is a novelist and financial journalist. His column tilting at conventional business wisdom appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Daniel Akst is a novelist and financial journalist. His column tilting at conventional business wisdom appears the first Sunday of each month. E-mail: culmoney@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
