<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Altered Itineraries As the World Heats Up</title>
    <meta content="07REP.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1151164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E4D6143BF934A35752C1A96F958260" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Altered Itineraries As the World Heats Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William K Stevens Correspondent's Report column explores possibility that global warming, if it develops as forecast, may result in shifting of seasonal vacation travel plans (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT probably isn't necessary to cancel or change vacation plans just yet, but global warming -- if it develops as forecast -- promises in time to revise travelers' lists of preferred destinations.</p>
        <p>A warmer, more pleasant England, for instance, might replace an extremely hot Greece as a summer vacation spot of choice. Beachgoers, skiers, scuba divers, autumn leaf-peepers, anglers and just plain sightseers all may have to find new places to go, and some of today's prized destinations may wither as new ones blossom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT probably isn't necessary to cancel or change vacation plans just yet, but global warming -- if it develops as forecast -- promises in time to revise travelers' lists of preferred destinations.</p>
        <p>A warmer, more pleasant England, for instance, might replace an extremely hot Greece as a summer vacation spot of choice. Beachgoers, skiers, scuba divers, autumn leaf-peepers, anglers and just plain sightseers all may have to find new places to go, and some of today's prized destinations may wither as new ones blossom.</p>
        <p>Or so says a recent study conducted for the World Wildlife Fund by the Climatic Research Unit of the University of East Anglia in England.</p>
        <p>The average annual surface temperature of the globe has already risen by about 1 degree or a little more over the last century; in many parts of the Northern Hemisphere, the warming has been much greater.</p>
        <p>Computer models of the atmosphere forecast a further rise of 2 to 6 degrees over the next century, with a best estimate of about 3.5 degrees, if industry and motor vehicles continue to spew heat-trapping carbon dioxide into the air at today's rates. By comparison, the world is 5 to 9 degrees warmer now than in the depths of the last ice age 18,000 to 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>Some regions would warm more, some less, and some may actually cool. But in any region where the average annual temperature rises, climate experts say, high summer temperatures are expected to become even higher. In general, climatic zones would shift northward in the Northern Hemisphere, southward in the Southern, and from lower to higher altitudes globally. And everywhere, the sea level would rise -- by about 20 inches globally over the century,  according to best estimates -- with potentially grave consequences for beach resorts.</p>
        <p>Projections of this sort are inherently chancy, but they are all that scientists have to go on. So the climate experts at East Anglia used computer models to look at the  possible effect of global warming on 10 of the world's favorite tourist destinations over the next century. And while the study was geared toward Britons, it has relevance for Americans, as well.</p>
        <p>Some of the findings:</p>
        <p>* Rising seas and a subsequent increase in beach erosion could eliminate many beaches and even submerge large parts of some popular islands, like the Maldives.  Florida could be particularly vulnerable to beach erosion, the study said. Some Caribbean islands could be similarly affected, said David Viner, a co-author of the study.</p>
        <p>* Higher temperatures could kill coral ecosystems, eliminating scuba-diving meccas from the Caribbean to the Maldives.</p>
        <p>* Ski resorts at lower elevations, like those at Garmisch in Germany and Kitz buhel in Austria, might suffer from less snow, causing skiers to crowd higher-elevation resorts. Similar shifts could take place in North America.</p>
        <p>* Rising temperatures could encourage the spread of malaria from North Africa to southern Spain.</p>
        <p>* Hotter summers in the eastern Mediterranean, where the number of days with temperatures higher than 100 degrees would increase, may discourage summer visits to Greece and Turkey. But summer weather in England should become warmer and more reliable, encouraging many Britons to stay home and attracting more foreign visitors.</p>
        <p>In many tourist areas, the study said, warmer temperatures might stimulate disease outbreaks, more forest fires and more air pollution.</p>
        <p>A warming climate, Mr. Viner said, could shift the range of some sport fish; in the United States, anglers pursuing these fish make major contributions to local economies. Trout and salmon, for instance, are cold-water fish, and previous studies have shown that their habitat and range could be substantially reduced as streams warm up.  On the other hand, the range of warm-water species like bass could expand.</p>
        <p>Studies have also suggested that in New England, trees with relatively dull fall colors, like oaks and hickories, could eventually move up from the Middle Atlantic and replace the brilliant maples that draw crowds of foliage admirers every autumn.</p>
        <p>How soon might these consequences be felt? Assuming the forecasts are reasonably accurate, it depends largely on whether climate change proceeds smoothly or in abrupt temperature jumps.</p>
        <p>One example of how global warming might be a mixed blessing: In Alaska, where substantial warming has already taken place, the tourist season has been lengthened. But if it gets warm enough, the thawing of Alaska could eliminate many of the subarctic charms that make it so attractive.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
