<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coke Products Are Ordered Off the Shelves in Four Countries</title>
    <meta content="Y16COKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1115757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dioxin (Chemical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">France</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Luxembourg</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Belgium</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Enterprises</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dehaene, Jean-Luc (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Luxembourg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Belgium</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Luxembourg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990616T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E2DF1E38F935A25755C0A96F958260" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coke Products Are Ordered Off the Shelves in Four Countries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Governments of France, Belgium, Luxembourg and Netherlands have ordered products from Coca-Cola Co off their shelves after dozens of people who drank soft drinks became ill; move comes on heels of health worries over food contaminated with dioxin that began in Belgium and spread across Europe; on June 13, reverberations from dioxin scare led to resignation of Belgian Prime Min Jean-Luc Dehaene; recall, which affects less than 1 percent of Coke's global sales, is another public blow for Coca-Cola, which has been struggling with declining sales in many regions; Coca-Cola executives say that problems along two points in its vast-bottling system, which is controlled in Belgium by Coca-Cola Enterprises, Coke's largest bottler, led to defects in its products; company insists products are safe to drink; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the biggest recall in Coke history, the Governments of France, Belgium, Luxembourg and the Netherlands have ordered products from the Coca-Cola Company off their shelves after dozens of people who drank the soft drinks became ill.</p>
        <p>The move comes on the heels of a health scare over food contaminated with dioxin that began in Belgium and spread across Europe. On Sunday, the reverberations from the dioxin scare led to the resignation of the Belgian Prime Minister, Jean-Luc Dehaene.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the biggest recall in Coke history, the Governments of France, Belgium, Luxembourg and the Netherlands have ordered products from the Coca-Cola Company off their shelves after dozens of people who drank the soft drinks became ill.</p>
        <p>The move comes on the heels of a health scare over food contaminated with dioxin that began in Belgium and spread across Europe. On Sunday, the reverberations from the dioxin scare led to the resignation of the Belgian Prime Minister, Jean-Luc Dehaene.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Belgium ordered Coke to remove all its soft drinks in bottles and cans from stores. Luxembourg followed suit yesterday. France told Coca-Cola to stop shipping cans and bottles from a plant in Dunkirk, near the Belgian border, where some of the contaminated Cokes originated, and the Netherlands banned all Coke products coming from Belgium. France has also informed Coke that it will ask for a recall today of all canned Coke products already shipped from the Dunkirk plant.</p>
        <p>The recall, which affects less than 1 percent of Coke's global sales, is another public blow for Coca-Cola, which last year sold $18.8 billion worth of soft drinks around the world but has been struggling with declining volume in many regions. In Europe, Coke's efforts to buy competing brands like Schweppes and Orangina have hit hurdles repeatedly over the last nine months amid regulatory concerns about market domination.</p>
        <p>''It's like there's a curse over the Continent when it comes to Coke right now,'' said Jennifer Solomon, a beverage stock analyst for Salomon Smith Barney. ''It's puzzling, and it's unfortunate.''</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, Coca-Cola executives said that problems along two points in its vast bottling system, which is controlled in Belgium by Coca-Cola Enterprises, Coke's largest bottler, had led to defects in its products.</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday, 31 middle-school students complained of a bad taste and later became sick with nausea and vomiting after drinking Coke from glass bottles that had been filled at a plant in Antwerp. The students, who attended a school in Bornem, were drinking Coke in part because of a contest in which points were printed underneath bottle caps. The points can be redeemed for prizes. As many as eight students remained hospitalized yesterday, The Associated Press reported, although a Coke spokesman said he was not aware that anyone was still hospitalized.</p>
        <p>Those soft drinks, the statement said, had been bottled using carbon dioxide that was defective and that caused ''an off-taste in the bottled product.'' The company said all bottles produced with the defective carbon dioxide, which creates the bubbles in a carbonated soft drink, had been recalled.</p>
        <p>But the company insisted that the products were safe to drink. ''This issue affects the taste of the soft drinks only,'' it said in the statement.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported that one person showed symptoms of hemolysis, in which red blood cells are destroyed.</p>
        <p>A second problem arose on Thursday, when people complained of nausea after drinking cans of Coke products bought from vending machines. The cans smelled bad on the outside, and people who opened them and drank the contents became ill. ''Everything inside the can was O.K., but there was a package-integrity issue,'' said a Coca-Cola spokesman, Rob Baskin. That problem, with reports continuing as recently as Monday, was traced yesterday to wooden pallets used to ship the cans.</p>
        <p>The cans came from a plant in Dunkirk, France, but the problem pallets are used only in Belgium, Mr. Baskin said. The wood had been treated with a substance that transmitted what the company called ''an offensive odor on the outside bottom of the can.'' The complaints came from several places around Belgium, including Korttrijk, a city in the southwest, Mr. Baskin said. Again, the Coca-Cola statement said, ''The product is safe.''</p>
        <p>Asked to explain why people became sick if the soft drinks were safe, he said, ''It may make you feel sick, but it is not harmful.''</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola executives are scheduled to meet with the Belgian health ministry today to discuss their findings and to ask for approval to resume selling Coke products in Belgium. Belgian television news last night carried footage of store owners clearing Coke products from their shelves.</p>
        <p>''It's the first time in recent memory that we have been asked to withdraw products from an entire marketplace,'' Mr. Baskin said. The recall in Belgium and Luxembourg affects all products sold by Coke, including Coca-Cola, Coca-Cola Light, Sprite, Fanta, Nestea, Aquarius sports drinks and Bon Aqua water. Some of those products are affected by the recall in France and the Netherlands, although Mr. Baskin said he did not know which were produced at the Dunkirk plant or handled for other markets through Belgium.</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola's share price fell $1.063 yesterday to finish the day at $63.75. Coca-Cola Enterprises lost $1.063, closing at $34.188.</p>
        <p>Belgium has long been an important market for Coke and Coca-Cola Enterprises. The most recent Coca-Cola Enterprises annual report, which devotes an entire page to the company's operations in Belgium, says that Belgians are among the most enthusiastic Coke drinkers in Europe. ''Today, per capita consumption is 260, among the highest in Europe,'' it said. That measure, the number of eight-ounce servings consumed per person per year, is nearly three times that of France, at 96, and well ahead of Germany, at 200.</p>
        <p>Michael Bellas, chief executive officer of Beverage Marketing, a trade group in Manhattan, said, ''They have a wonderful track record, but this has got to hurt a little bit.'' Coca-Cola's market share in Belgium, he added, is 68 percent, well ahead of the No. 2, Cadbury Schweppes P.L.C., which has a 4 percent share.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Coca-Cola has had its plans to acquire the Orangina brand from Pernod Ricard S.A. rejected by the French Government and an appeals court, although Coke is trying to structure the deal in a way to win approval. And after encountering stiff resistance from the European Union as well as individual countries, Coke scaled back plans announced in December to buy the Cadbury Schweppes brands outside the United States, with the exception of France and South Africa. What had been a $1.85 billion deal was trimmed to $1.1 billion, and now excludes most of the European Union countries.</p>
        <p>Beverage industry stock analysts said Coke would have to move quickly to control any public-relations damage stemming from the recall. ''The key issue is quickly resolving this and aggressively communicating to the consumer that safe products are going back on the shelf,'' said Bill Pecoriello, a beverage analyst for Sanford C. Bernstein, adding that he thought there would be little impact on earnings at Coke unless the problem dragged on through the summer.</p>
        <p>Belgian authorities have been dealing with the dioxin scare, in which the cancer-causing chemical was found in animal feed in recent months. The discovery led to a ban on poultry, pork, beef, eggs and meat products, both within Belgium and abroad.</p>
        <p>While different substances are involved, the Coke recall lengthens the list of groceries that have lost some of their luster.</p>
        <p>''If I had kids at the Coca-Cola drinking stage, I would be telling them not to drink it out of the can anymore,'' said Steve Ketele, a retired journalist who lives outside Brussels. ''But thank God, they are in the wine-drinking stage.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
