<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Sues New York City Over Disposal of Freon Appliances</title>
    <meta content="25FRID$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1095073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Douglas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Appliances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5DC1730F936A15750C0A96F958260" item-length="613" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Sues New York City Over Disposal of Freon Appliances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS MARTIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Martin, Douglas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawsuit filed by Federal Government seeks to impose heavy fines on New York City for disposing refrigerators and other appliances in ways that cause ozone-depleting refrigerants to be released into atmosphere; US Environmental Protection Agency says that city has intentionally ignored Federal rules on proper disposal of appliances and asks for fine of more than $50 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A lawsuit filed yesterday by the Federal Government seeks to impose heavy fines on New York City for disposing refrigerators and other appliances in ways that cause ozone-depleting refrigerants to be released into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In documents filed in Federal District Court in Manhattan, the United States Environmental Protection Agency said the city had intentionally ignored Federal rules on proper disposal of the appliances and asked for a fine of more than $50 million, or $27,500 for each day since March 25, 1994, when the order took effect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A lawsuit filed yesterday by the Federal Government seeks to impose heavy fines on New York City for disposing refrigerators and other appliances in ways that cause ozone-depleting refrigerants to be released into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>In documents filed in Federal District Court in Manhattan, the United States Environmental Protection Agency said the city had intentionally ignored Federal rules on proper disposal of the appliances and asked for a fine of more than $50 million, or $27,500 for each day since March 25, 1994, when the order took effect.</p>
        <p>''Given the city's failure to properly address this important issue in the past,'' said Jeanne M. Fox, the regional administrator of the E.P.A., ''the Federal Government felt it necessary to pursue this legal action, and expects that it will result in increased environmental awareness on the part of city administrators.''</p>
        <p>Leslie Allan, a Sanitation Department deputy commissioner and the agency's chief lawyer, said she had not seen the legal papers and had no comment on the lawsuit. But she said the agency believed that a new policy enacted on March 15 puts it in compliance with the Federal order.</p>
        <p>Under that policy, the Sanitation Department has posted new guidelines in various buildings for the removal of the refrigerant Freon or Freon substitutes from appliances. The guidelines suggest that people wishing to dispose of appliances that contain Freon should call the Sanitation Department's Action Center at (212) 219-8090 before placing the item on the curb. Sanitation workers will then remove the refrigerant and tag the appliances before taking them away.</p>
        <p>But Mary Mears, an E.P.A. spokeswoman, said that ''just putting out notices is not enough'' and that the Sanitation Department needed to provide greater documentation.</p>
        <p>The city, despite the new policy, remains liable for the complete fine for the five years that it did not comply with the administrative order, she said.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, the sooner they come into compliance, the less the penalties they will face,'' Ms. Mears said.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. charged that the Sanitation Department had failed since the order was implemented to remove Freon or its substitutes from compacting trucks in which refrigerators, air-conditioners and other appliances containing Freon are crushed. Freon had thus escaped into the atmosphere, it said. The gas also might have escaped at the city's landfill at Fresh Kills on Staten Island, where the appliances were further crushed.</p>
        <p>Freon belongs to a class of chemicals called chlorofluorocarbons, or CFC's, that can damage the ozone layer, which shields the earth from ultraviolet radiation that can cause skin cancers, cataracts and other health problems. The gas has been banned in the United States since 1995 because of its effects on the environment, but is still found in many older appliances and automobiles.</p>
        <p>Freon substitutes in use since then contain another class of ozone-damaging gases, called hydrofluorocarbons.</p>
        <p>Daniel Lashof, a senior scientist at the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental group, said that emissions from discarded appliances were one of the largest causes of the release of chlorfluorocarbons into the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>He said the rarity of the gases -- they have sometimes been smuggled in from other countries, particularly Russia -- made their recycling especially important. He called the city's disposal practices ''worse than careless.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Mears said it was unusual for a municipality to be charged with violations in appliance disposal. Most violations occur at establishments that handle scrap metal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
