<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE SPEECH -- Gore's Open Meetings; Gore Is Using New Medium To Convey Message: Himself</title>
    <meta content="02GORE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1157747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFDD163EF931A35751C1A96F958260" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE SPEECH -- Gore's Open Meetings; Gore Is Using New Medium To Convey Message: Himself</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>CONCORD, N.H., Nov. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Al Gore, campaigning in New Hampshire, has revamped his approach, abandoning scripted speeches in favor of chats and what he calls open meetings and portraying self as real person; is talking more about own life; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore used to be a stick-to-the-script kind of guy. Lots of mind-numbing facts about the gross domestic product. But since he revamped his campaign two months ago after a slide in the polls, Mr. Gore has also revamped himself and thrown out the script of his standard stump speech.</p>
        <p>Now, the vice president is trying to  appeal to real people by portraying himself as a real person, too. He does not make full-blown speeches; he chats. He wanders into living rooms to talk with 30 people or into school gymnasiums to talk with 300 and conducts Oprah-style discussions, which he calls open meetings. He sometimes relies on stock answers to convey his positions on the issues: He wants to resubmit the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty that the Senate recently rejected. He wants to bring ''revolutionary change'' to public schools. He wants to give health insurance to all children. [Excerpts, Page A28.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore used to be a stick-to-the-script kind of guy. Lots of mind-numbing facts about the gross domestic product. But since he revamped his campaign two months ago after a slide in the polls, Mr. Gore has also revamped himself and thrown out the script of his standard stump speech.</p>
        <p>Now, the vice president is trying to  appeal to real people by portraying himself as a real person, too. He does not make full-blown speeches; he chats. He wanders into living rooms to talk with 30 people or into school gymnasiums to talk with 300 and conducts Oprah-style discussions, which he calls open meetings. He sometimes relies on stock answers to convey his positions on the issues: He wants to resubmit the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty that the Senate recently rejected. He wants to bring ''revolutionary change'' to public schools. He wants to give health insurance to all children. [Excerpts, Page A28.]</p>
        <p>But more often than not, the message is about him. He talks about being a grandfather, about having lived in a trailer park, about how much he likes the pop singer Ricky Martin. And the medium of open meetings is an important part of the message -- that Mr. Gore is open, not the android of his reputation but a confident, freewheeling guy, able to handle any topic thrown at him, able to relate to all kinds of people.</p>
        <p>The result is a scene like one on Tuesday at a high school here, where he was asked about violence. on television. Mr. Gore said he liked to watch ''The Simpsons,'' prompting a round of applause from the teenage audience. Then he talked about watching the Simpsons watch ''The Itchy and Scratchy Show,'' the cartoon within the cartoon, with its parody of violence. ''They'll take out a chain saw and slice the arms off, horrible, blood spurting out, and Bart and Lisa and the little baby, Maggie, they'll laugh and giggle at this mayhem,'' he says, laughing himself.</p>
        <p>''I'm sitting there watching this, saying, 'Oh my God, this is awful,' '' he laughs, but he says he also enjoys it. ''I'm really kind of conflicted, and that's what they're going for,'' he says, making the point that people become desensitized to violence when they see it all the time.</p>
        <p>Earlier that day, he told business executives that he lived in a trailer park after he joined the Army. And out popped the little-known fact that he once was a housing developer.</p>
        <p>Later at an American Legion post in Manchester, he was hailed by veterans for enlisting in the Army, but he insisted that he was not as brave as that implies. He became an enlisted man, as opposed to trying to become an officer, he said, because it meant only two years in the service, not three. Still, he conveyed an empathy with his fellow veterans and quoted a poem from a Vietnam buddy: ''Each face may lose its name and time will not defer, but there will always be the bond between who we are and where we were.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said recently that campaigns are ''transformational,'' and in the past two months, as he has sought to regain an edge on his challenger, former Senator Bill Bradley, Mr. Gore has undergone a very public transformation as he searches for who he is and who he wants to be.</p>
        <p>As he and his aides see it, Mr. Gore's challenge is not to show his smarts; he knows the issues inside out. His challenge is to show that a lifetime in politics has not stifled his growth, that he is not all tactics and caution, that he can think on his feet and engage the nation on his own terms, not as a spear-carrier in the Clinton administration.</p>
        <p>The open format lends Mr. Gore an air of effortlessness, of someone open to the vicissitudes of real people, someone willing, as Michael Whouley, a strategist for Mr. Gore, says, to ''put himself out there.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore will say, ''Have at it,''  taking questions for an hour or so. He stays until the last person drifts away, fulfilled, his campaign hopes, by having had the chance to mull their concerns -- from global warming to the human genome project --  one on one with the vice president.</p>
        <p>Questions from his audiences often go over the same ground, and Mr. Gore relies on them to make his policy points. For example, his answers to questions about health care now usually involve a deconstruction of the health care proposal offered by Mr. Bradley, his only rival for the Democratic nomination.</p>
        <p>''My plan says let's insure all children,'' he says. ''We'll get to 88 percent of the American people and we'll put provisions in place that will help others get access to health insurance.'' He says Mr. Bradley ''gets just about the same amount -- 89 percent instead of 88 percent -- but he spends three times as much money and uses the entire surplus.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes he is asked about subjects that he never brings up on his own. Recently in Claremont, N.H., he was asked for his position on the death penalty. ''I've always supported it,'' he replied, ''because I think society has a right to make careful judgments about when that ultimate penalty ought to be applied.''</p>
        <p>He inevitably gets a question about leadership, which he often uses to distance himself from President Clinton. In Concord, he was asked to identify his ''one weakness.'' He said that for a long time, he held his own views in check because his role was to support President Clinton. ''I think it's a weakness as a presidential candidate and certainly would be as president, if I didn't shed myself of that, which I have,'' he said. ''What you want to know is, what is my own spontaneous reaction to what comes up? What is my judgment?''</p>
        <p>But his advisers keep telling him that the most important thing he can do is tell people ''who he is.'' And so in his standard introduction, he talks about his family, mainly his mother and father and their triumphs over hardscrabble beginnings in the Tennessee hollows.</p>
        <p>His mother was among the first women to graduate from Vanderbilt Law School. His father was at the forefront of the civil rights movement. Mr. Gore artfully presents his parents' backgrounds to explain his fundamental goals.</p>
        <p>''In honor of my mother, I pledge that the progress we've made in women's rights in this century is only the beginning of what we will do in the next century,'' he declares. ''In honor of my father, I pledge that the progress we've made in civil rights in this century will be only the beginning of the progress we make in the next century.''</p>
        <p>But this could be treacherous ground for Mr. Gore. The sheer drama of his parents' lives highlights the lack of overt struggle in his own, as the son of a Senator growing up in a hotel in Washington. He almost never mentions his elite education at St. Albans and Harvard. Instead he recalls the chaotic touchstones of his generation -- the assassinations, Vietnam, Watergate.</p>
        <p>But he is rarely expansive about about what these events meant to him. ''I went to Vietnam,'' he said at a recent living room appearance in Keene. ''And I came back and I felt the pressures that were tearing our country apart. I saw Watergate unfold. I just wanted nothing to do with politics,'' which he says left him ''disillusioned,'' especially after his father lost his Senate seat in 1970.</p>
        <p>For all of his personal references, his discussions often give only the illusion of intimacy. This was most striking here at the high school when a young woman asked him if he would ban cigarettes and marijuana.</p>
        <p>He said he would ban marijuana but that it would not be ''practical'' to ban cigarettes because so many people were addicted to them. He denounced tobacco companies, but never mentioned that his older sister, Nancy, a smoker since age 13,  died of lung cancer in 1984.</p>
        <p>In his acceptance speech at the 1996 Democratic National Convention, Mr. Gore had talked extensively about his sister's death, describing their last moments together. His speech was widely panned for seeming to exploit his sister's death. Now he never mentions her at all.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
