<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Robotic Adventurer Aims for Mars' South Pole</title>
    <meta content="30MARS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1157210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Polar Lander (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mars (Planet)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E4DF103FF933A05752C1A96F958260" item-length="1232" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Robotic Adventurer Aims for Mars' South Pole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American spacecraft is racing toward Mars and first landing in polar region of another planet; robotic Mars Polar Lander is being aimed for landing on Dec 3 on vast terraces of ice and dust a few hundred miles from planet's south pole; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Less than a century after explorers made their first heroic assault on the poles of Earth, an American spacecraft is racing toward Mars and the first landing in the polar region of another planet.</p>
        <p>The robotic Mars Polar Lander is being aimed for a landing on Friday on the vast terraces of ice and dust a few hundred miles from the planet's south pole. Spring is turning to summer there, the season of constant sunlight, which the craft will draw on for energy to power its computer and transmitter and array of cameras, sensors, digging arm and ovens for heating and analyzing soil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Less than a century after explorers made their first heroic assault on the poles of Earth, an American spacecraft is racing toward Mars and the first landing in the polar region of another planet.</p>
        <p>The robotic Mars Polar Lander is being aimed for a landing on Friday on the vast terraces of ice and dust a few hundred miles from the planet's south pole. Spring is turning to summer there, the season of constant sunlight, which the craft will draw on for energy to power its computer and transmitter and array of cameras, sensors, digging arm and ovens for heating and analyzing soil.</p>
        <p>Over the next three months, if all goes well, the craft will prospect the frigid landscape for water and investigate the thin air above, the surface and the underground for clues to the planet's climate history. Photographs taken by previous craft reveal the polar terrain to be layered with the residue of dust and ice, each layer of varying thicknesses reflecting past weather patterns.</p>
        <p>The $165 million mission will thus be seeking answers to the two most important scientific questions about Mars: where is the water and was the planet significantly warmer and wetter in its early history, as suggested by abundant evidence of surface erosion? These questions strike at the heart of the larger question of whether life in some form could ever have arisen on Mars.</p>
        <p>''This is really the first in a series of missions that will explore on the surface different parts of the planet, particularly looking for water,'' said Dr. David Paige, a scientist at the University of California at Los Angeles. ''We know there's water in the atmosphere. We don't know where else there's water on Mars.'' Mission scientists liken their strategy for exploring the layered polar terrain to the reading of tree rings or ice cores in learning about Earth.</p>
        <p>Within a week of settling on the surface, about 500 miles from the pole, the lander is to flex its 6.5-foot mechanical arm and begin digging a trench about 20 inches deep. In winter, carbon dioxide frost would probably be covering the site. Now the surface will probably be fine dust, left by wind storms that frequently blow over the planet. A tiny camera mounted on the arm will take color pictures of the soil and trench walls.</p>
        <p>Since there is water vapor in the atmosphere, scientists expect to find some water ice in the soil. The mechanical arm is to scoop up soil samples and place them in ovens for analysis by instruments designed by the University of Arizona. The electric ovens will heat the samples to see what gases are released. By measuring the amount of water vapor and carbon dioxide gas, scientists will be able to determine the amount of ice beneath the surface, as well as minerals that may have formed when Mars had a warmer climate. Eight samples are expected to be examined during the mission.</p>
        <p>''Everything we know about life says that water is an essential part of it,'' said Dr. William V. Boynton, a University of Arizona planetary scientist who developed the instruments for testing the soil. ''If Mars was always as dry as it appears now to be, then it's not very likely life could have ever gotten started. But if there really were oceans on Mars at one time, that's exciting.''</p>
        <p>The craft is also carrying two probes, each the size of a basketball, for penetrating even deeper, perhaps more than three feet. It is supposed to release the probes just before entering the Mars atmosphere. The probes are to slam into Mars at 400 miles an hour, hitting 30 to 35 miles away about a minute ahead of the spacecraft. Each impact should drive a five-inch-long penetrator into the ground, where instruments are to heat soil to look for water vapor from any buried ice.</p>
        <p>In honor of the first explorers to reach Earth's South Pole, the two probes have been named Amundsen and Scott. The Norwegian Roald Amundsen led the first successful expedition to the South Pole, reaching it on Dec. 14, 1911. Robert Falcon Scott, an Englishman, arrived with his team a month later, beaten in their quest and the entire team destined to die on their return trip.</p>
        <p>The lander's other scientific instruments include a multispectral, stereoscopic camera for observing the landscape; a meteorology package for measuring air temperature, winds, pressure and humidity, and a light detection and radar system, called lidar, that emits laser light to detect clouds and hazes.</p>
        <p>Attached to the Russian-designed lidar is a small microphone supplied by the Planetary Society, a group advocating space exploration. The microphone will be used to try to make the first recordings of sounds on the surface of Mars.</p>
        <p>''It's an effort to bring all human senses to bear on the Red Planet,'' Dr. Paige of U.C.L.A. said. ''We have already brought sight and touch to Mars, almost taste if you consider our analytical experiments with soil samples.''</p>
        <p>If successful,the lander will be the fourth spacecraft to operate on the planet's surface. Two Viking spacecraft landed there in 1976, and Mars Pathfinder, with its tiny roving vehicle Sojourner, explored midlatitude geology in 1997.</p>
        <p>Norman Haynes, director of systems management at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory in Pasadena, Calif., said the spacecraft was in ''excellent condition and behaving exactly the way we designed it to do.''</p>
        <p>Engineers at the laboratory, which directs the mission for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, have spent weeks reviewing all navigation instructions that have been transmitted to the lander to avoid a repetition of the embarrassing mistake that doomed its traveling companion, the Mars Climate Orbiter. A mixup between English and metric units in navigation data sent the spacecraft off course, and probably to its destruction, as it was attempting to orbit Mars in September. All radio contact with the craft was lost.</p>
        <p>As originally planned, the climate orbiter was to act as a communications relay station for the lander. The lander's own radio can transmit directly to Earth, but is too weak to handle the full data load. ''It's a loss but not a crippling one for the lander's mission,'' Dr. Paige said.</p>
        <p>Fortunately, another orbiting craft, Mars Global Surveyor, has been circling the planet on a mapping mission since 1997 and will be relied on as the lander's main link in communicating its discoveries in the southern polar region of Mars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
