<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="19OBSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1078362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Archeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Archaeology and Anthropology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3DF1430F93AA25752C0A96F958260" item-length="483" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Team of Australian and American researchers concludes that earliest humans in Australia may have inadvertently wiped out most of large animal species on continent 50,000 years ago; Colorado State University researchers studying growth of vegetation on range land since 1970 find that there appear to be ecological consquences to phenomenon of nightime temperatures increasing at twice rate of average daytime temperatures (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Extinction, Ancient Style</p>
        <p>As a protector of fellow creatures, modern humans' record is spotty at best. The steamroller of progress has put some species on the endangered list, and even flattened some to extinction. But now comes word that not-so-modern humans didn't do so well either.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Extinction, Ancient Style</p>
        <p>As a protector of fellow creatures, modern humans' record is spotty at best. The steamroller of progress has put some species on the endangered list, and even flattened some to extinction. But now comes word that not-so-modern humans didn't do so well either.</p>
        <p>A team of Australian and American researchers has concluded that the earliest humans in Australia may have inadvertently wiped out most of the large animal species on the continent 50,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>Like other parts of the world, Australia was at one time home to a diverse assortment of so-called megafauna. In Australia's case, these included a marsupial that weighed as much as a linebacker, a horned tortoise that was about the size of a compact car, and a flightless ostrich-like bird, Genyornis newtoni, that tipped the scales at 200 pounds.</p>
        <p>Many of these large animals became extinct around the same time, but exactly when has been unclear. The reason has been unclear as well, with some scientists blaming climate change and others, human activity. The researchers, who wrote about their work in a recent issue of the journal Science, used a variety of newer dating techniques on fossilized eggshells of Genyornis to calculate that the birds suddenly disappeared 50,000 years ago. This was a time of only mild climate change, the researchers note.</p>
        <p>But it was about 5,000 years after the first humans arrived on the continent. So the researchers speculate that systematic burning of vegetation by these aboriginal Australians disrupted the food chain enough that Genyornis and other shrub- and tree-loving species became extinct.</p>
        <p>Tracking Temperatures</p>
        <p>Back to modern times for a moment. Much has been made of the fact that human activity is causing global temperatures to rise. But the picture is more complex than that: In land areas, average annual minimum temperatures (that is, nighttime temperatures) are increasing at twice the rate of average annual maximum (daytime) temperatures.</p>
        <p>Three Colorado State University researchers, studying the growth of vegetation on range land since 1970, have discovered that there appear to be ecological consequences to this phenomenon. The researchers, writing in Science, found that higher minimum temperatures have cut the production of buffalo grass, a prime food source for grazing cattle, and increased the abundance of invasive, nongrassy plants.</p>
        <p>The researchers speculate on several reasons for this. For one thing, they say, the warmer nights extend the growing season, which would primarily benefit cool-season plants (like the nongrasses) that grow most rapidly. These plants would rob the hot-season (and slower growing) grasses of nutrients and water. Warmer nights also increase plant respiration, which will speed up loss of carbon by the plant (thus slowing growth) if there is not a corresponding increase in photosynthesis during the day.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
