<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>JERSEY DIARY</title>
    <meta content="27DIAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1118904"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E2DD143AF934A15755C0A96F958260" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>JERSEY DIARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>While visiting Las Vegas last week, we went to see the new Venetian Hotel. Walking in its reproduction of St. Mark's Square in front of the Doge's Palace, I said to my wife, ''The only things missing are the pigeons.''</p>
        <p>With that, the man next to us -- who did not know us or where we lived -- turned to me and said: ''I just saw a couple of pigeons. They looked like they came from New Jersey.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>While visiting Las Vegas last week, we went to see the new Venetian Hotel. Walking in its reproduction of St. Mark's Square in front of the Doge's Palace, I said to my wife, ''The only things missing are the pigeons.''</p>
        <p>With that, the man next to us -- who did not know us or where we lived -- turned to me and said: ''I just saw a couple of pigeons. They looked like they came from New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>JERRY STEIN</p>
        <p>While a ''Florio Free'' bumper sticker delivers a distinct political opinion in New Jersey, its meaning gets muddled once the attached car crosses state borders.</p>
        <p>A Delaware resident, reading the message, asked, ''Is Florio one of those chemicals that's depleting the ozone layer?''</p>
        <p>DOROTHY FISCHER</p>
        <p>While waiting for my husband to select shrubs at a nursery in Hillsdale, I saw a little girl about 4 or 5  standing alone. I asked her what her name was but she refused to tell me. I said that if she told me her name, I would tell her mine.</p>
        <p>''I know your name,'' she said. ''It's Grandma.''</p>
        <p>BELLE G. KESSELMAN</p>
        <p>We were at one of our favorite restaurants in West Orange with some friends recently when one of them said, ''Remember when you didn't have a waitperson,''</p>
        <p>''Or,'' another said, ''even know what a waitperson was. How about when they keep asking if you guys are doing O.K.''</p>
        <p>I said, ''The best one we had was in Hawaii. A young guy in a flowered shirt handed us each a chilled fork and said, 'I'm Wayne, your salad person.' ''</p>
        <p>Was that posh service or what?</p>
        <p>DORIS L. MEYER</p>
        <p>Scene: The kitchen table:</p>
        <p>Child No. 1: ''You know that book that starts, 'Call me E-mail?' ''</p>
        <p>Husband and I (laughing): 'You mean, ''Call me Ishmael.' ''</p>
        <p>Child No 1: ''Yeah.''</p>
        <p>Husband: ''Do you know what book that is?''</p>
        <p>Child No 1: ''I know. The book about whales.''</p>
        <p>Child No 2: ''Free Willy?''</p>
        <p>DEBRA GALANT</p>
        <p>I guess anybody going to see ''Austin Powers'' shouldn't really be looking for a genteel crowd.</p>
        <p>At a theater in Nutley the other night, an altercation broke out between a row of teen-agers and a mom. Finally, the usher came to the mother's aid, after which a middle-aged woman turned around to admonish the teen-agers.</p>
        <p>''Is this how your mothers taught you to act?'' the woman asked.</p>
        <p>''No,'' was the response. ''But our mothers aren't here.''</p>
        <p>The old saying goes, ''When three different people tell you or suggest to you a different way to do something, it is time to listen.''</p>
        <p>Or, ''Things happen in threes.''</p>
        <p>For me, it was driving the roads of New Jersey recently and having to  fill my car with gas. I stopped at three different Shell stations and had bad experiences at all three.</p>
        <p>When I mentioned this to a friend from Long Island, she commented, ''It seems the only good shells to be found in New Jersey may be at the shore.''</p>
        <p>LAURA COBRINIK</p>
        <p>Infringing on our liberties, the State</p>
        <p>Would ban nude bathing at Higbee Beach. But wait!</p>
        <p>Where will they go, those poor unfortunates</p>
        <p>Who cannot find a bathing suit that fits?</p>
        <p>BOB McKENTY</p>
        <p>Overheard on the steps leading to the beach at the Spring Lake boardwalk on Memorial Day weekend:</p>
        <p>Mother to young son (about 3 or 4 years old): ''No, Joey, tie-dyed is not the same thing as high tide.''</p>
        <p>PAT DURKIN-WIGNALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
