<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>19-Year-Old's Weather Research Has the Experts Taking Note</title>
    <meta content="11CLIM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1091537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">State University of New York at Stony Brook</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Croke, Meredith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7DA163EF932A25750C0A96F958260" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>19-Year-Old's Weather Research Has the Experts Taking Note</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <dateline>STONY BROOK, N.Y., March 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles Meredith Croke, freshman at State University of New York at Stony Brook, who is studying global weather patterns; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two years ago, Dr. Robert D. Cess, a climatologist at the State University of New York here, grumbled when another professor urged him to supervise a local high school student in a summer program for bright teen-agers.</p>
        <p>The problem, Dr. Cess said, was that in nearly four decades as a professor, he had never found any use for an undergraduate research assistant, let alone a junior from Miller Place High School, even one with a passion for weather.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two years ago, Dr. Robert D. Cess, a climatologist at the State University of New York here, grumbled when another professor urged him to supervise a local high school student in a summer program for bright teen-agers.</p>
        <p>The problem, Dr. Cess said, was that in nearly four decades as a professor, he had never found any use for an undergraduate research assistant, let alone a junior from Miller Place High School, even one with a passion for weather.</p>
        <p>He grudgingly agreed, and sent the student, Meredith Croke, then 17, down the hall to a computer in an empty office. He told her to familiarize herself with its sophisticated package of number-crunching software. ''I figured that would take at least half the summer,'' Dr. Cess said.</p>
        <p>He went to lunch. ''When I got back,'' he said, ''she asked me, 'Professor Cess, what shall I do next?' ''</p>
        <p>Dr. Cess began to think that Ms. Croke might have some potential after all, he said, and now he is sure of it.</p>
        <p>Ms. Croke's research at Stony Brook on links between clouds and temperature has been accepted for publication in The Journal of Climate, a prominent research periodical that is usually the province of gray-haired Ph.D.'s, not peach-faced 19-year-olds.</p>
        <p>The same work was rejected by judges last year for the finals of the Westinghouse Science Talent Search, a high school competition that is now sponsored by the Intel Corporation. That was a blow, Ms. Croke said, ''But I'll take this any day.''</p>
        <p>Dr. James J. Hack, a climate scientist at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., said, it was extremely unusual for someone so young to be doing research in an important area.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hack reviewed an early version of the paper. ''It's original and provocative and raises interesting questions about one of the central mysteries of the climate system,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Croke's research led to a full scholarship to Stony Brook, where she is a freshman with plans for graduate work in applied physics and meteorology. ''There is just something about weather,'' she said, ''how it's always changing, with so many things involved in it.''</p>
        <p>Her parents, Robert, a Suffolk County police inspector, and Susan, a secretary, said that they had no idea where their daughter's fascination with weather came from, but that it was there at a young age.</p>
        <p>When she was 5, during trips in the car she would chat idly in the back seat -- until the forecast came on the radio, Mr. Croke said. ''She'd stop dead and listen to the weather,'' he said.</p>
        <p>When she was 10, for Christmas she wanted a weather station with an anemometer to check wind speed. ''We thought that was a somewhat unusual request,'' Mr. Croke said. Instead of becoming addicted to Nickelodeon or MTV, she sat mesmerized by satellite images on the Weather Channel.</p>
        <p>She applied for the summer program at Stony Brook in 1997, writing in her application about her love of weather.</p>
        <p>Her aim was to find relationships between long-term patterns of cloudiness, precipitation and temperature across Long Island, she said. Dr. Cess gave her a weighty tome with 87 years of global weather data, and she began sifting for clues using the computer.</p>
        <p>The study expanded to the East Coast, then the West Coast near San Diego and the southern Great Plains. Slowly, a pattern emerged. In years that were cloudier than normal in these places, she also found fluctuations in high pressure systems in the North Pacific and the North Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Ms. Croke's work significantly advances the understanding of the relationship between changes in cloudiness and things like high pressure systems, which are in turn related to global temperature changes, Dr. Cess said.</p>
        <p>Warmer weather tends to spawn more clouds, but the details remain -- well -- cloudy, Dr. Cess said. Clouds can cool and warm the planet, reflecting some of the sun's heat back into space but also acting like an insulating blanket, trapping some heat near the surface.</p>
        <p>''It's like trying to unscramble an egg,'' he said to illustrate how difficult it is to find patterns in the turbulence of global weather.</p>
        <p>Ms. Croke's research appears to reveal at least one small link, he said. It may help scientists refine computer models of the atmosphere that are being used to assess the potential impact of global warming but are hampered by a lack of understanding of the physics of clouds.</p>
        <p>The paper is dense with technical terms and statistical formulas. But there is at least one hint of adolescence in the acknowledgments: ''One of us (MC) would like to thank her dad for letting her use the car to get to Stony Brook during this time.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Croke said that for now, her climate research will take a back seat to introductory calculus and literature courses and track meets. She runs 60 or 70 miles a week to stay in shape for cross-country races, she said.</p>
        <p>But this summer, she will be back at her research. Her locked office awaits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
