<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Real Nightmare Remains</title>
    <meta content="14HART$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1085145"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1D9143AF937A25751C0A96F958260" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Real Nightmare Remains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gary Hart</byline>
      <dateline>KITTREDGE, Colo.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Since the same forces that produced our national nightmare are all still at work -- an independent inquisitor as a fourth branch of government, a 1960's-inspired battle over the bounds of private morality, the co-optation of the political parties by cultural forces, the expansion of press ''scrutiny'' into public officials' private lives and, it must be said, the frailty, error and some would say sinfulness of human beings -- it is premature to hope the nightmare is over.</p>
        <p>So long as these conditions exist, our society will continue to devour its leadership. Many Americans are angry right now because they believe that neither the President nor his prosecutors and defenders have placed the national interest above personal and partisan interests. Though some insist on judging the President on how he manages his personal life, history will judge him on how he has -- or has not -- helped manage Russia's transition to democracy, reformed the military or prepared the nation for the next, inevitable energy crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Since the same forces that produced our national nightmare are all still at work -- an independent inquisitor as a fourth branch of government, a 1960's-inspired battle over the bounds of private morality, the co-optation of the political parties by cultural forces, the expansion of press ''scrutiny'' into public officials' private lives and, it must be said, the frailty, error and some would say sinfulness of human beings -- it is premature to hope the nightmare is over.</p>
        <p>So long as these conditions exist, our society will continue to devour its leadership. Many Americans are angry right now because they believe that neither the President nor his prosecutors and defenders have placed the national interest above personal and partisan interests. Though some insist on judging the President on how he manages his personal life, history will judge him on how he has -- or has not -- helped manage Russia's transition to democracy, reformed the military or prepared the nation for the next, inevitable energy crisis.</p>
        <p>The intense focus on private morality comes at the expense of focusing on public morality. Sex is more intriguing, more tractable, more commercially rewarding than an issue like hungry children or homeless youths or inadequate health care for the elderly or global warming -- or any other symptoms of our warped social priorities.</p>
        <p>It is also distressing that talented Americans reject public service because it means running the gantlet of hazing now required of candidates and of nominees for appointive office. Added to the corrupting influence of campaign fund-raising and the absence of civility in the public forum, the evisceration of private lives is too much to ask people of stature and dignity to accept. We may be on our way to having a corps of public officials whose sexual report cards are spotless but who accept millions in special interest campaign money and callously neglect the needs of the poorest among us.</p>
        <p>In an effort to combat excessive intrusiveness, some prospective candidates for national office, including  Senator John McCain and Gov. George Bush, have recently let it be known that they will refuse to answer certain personal questions. As some of us know, however, this is no assurance against surreptitious surveillance or media feeding frenzies.</p>
        <p>The First Amendment gives no one the license to use the ''character issue'' to destroy character. Character is demonstrated over a lifetime, and nowhere more tellingly than in a public official's willingness to put principle above career, even if that principle is to say, ''It's none of your business.''</p>
        <p>It will be decades, if ever, before we fully understand the public's response to the impeachment drama, especially the disparity between the President's favorable job rating and the substantially lower level of public trust in him.</p>
        <p>Some say it is simply a reflection of a booming economy. But I think the American people may be saying, We know the difference between what is interesting and entertaining -- public officials' personal lives -- and what is important -- our children's future.</p>
        <p>Our society has been forced to confront paradox: the paradox of public leadership and private fallibility, the paradox of cultural conservatism and personal individualism. We are a people who historically have found our paradoxes -- slavery among them -- difficult to resolve.</p>
        <p>There is no amount of ''scrutiny'' that can penetrate the complexities of relationships, the layers of personality, the tangle of public duty and personal flaw, the awful, complex, fragile thing called the human heart.</p>
        <p>We can only hope now for a society mature enough to understand that genuine morality is about more than sex, that fidelity is not simply a sexual term, that a leader can be sexually pure but lack public morality, that qualities of duty, honor and courage can be demonstrated by fallible human beings.</p>
        <p>Once we know these things, we can dismiss the ''independent'' inquisitors, we can demand that news organizations report more prominently and more faithfully on the public's business, and we can, once more, welcome our most talented citizens into public service.</p>
        <p>Gary Hart, the former Democratic Senator from Colorado, is the author, most recently, of ''The Minuteman.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gary Hart, the former Democratic Senator from Colorado, is the author, most recently, of ''The Minuteman.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
