<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Damaging Delay on a Test Ban</title>
    <meta content="05SUN2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1135674"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Tests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Tests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DB133AF936A3575AC0A96F958260" item-length="532" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Damaging Delay on a Test Ban</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial scores Senate Republicans for delaying ratification of nuclear test ban treaty</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Negotiating the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty in 1996 was a triumph for American diplomacy. Its provisions, which prohibit all atmospheric and underground nuclear tests, would lock in the United States' current technological lead, prevent China from testing advanced new weapons designs and block non-nuclear countries that have signed the treaty from conducting future nuclear tests. It would also put increased pressure on countries that have not yet signed, like India and Pakistan, to avoid further testing and to accept the treaty.</p>
        <p>The 152 countries that have signed the treaty are all abiding by its terms. But the agreement becomes legally binding only when ratified by a list of 44 countries, including all current nuclear powers. Only 21 of these countries have ratified so far. Perversely, the United States, which has the most to gain from the treaty achieving legal force, is among the holdouts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Negotiating the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty in 1996 was a triumph for American diplomacy. Its provisions, which prohibit all atmospheric and underground nuclear tests, would lock in the United States' current technological lead, prevent China from testing advanced new weapons designs and block non-nuclear countries that have signed the treaty from conducting future nuclear tests. It would also put increased pressure on countries that have not yet signed, like India and Pakistan, to avoid further testing and to accept the treaty.</p>
        <p>The 152 countries that have signed the treaty are all abiding by its terms. But the agreement becomes legally binding only when ratified by a list of 44 countries, including all current nuclear powers. Only 21 of these countries have ratified so far. Perversely, the United States, which has the most to gain from the treaty achieving legal force, is among the holdouts.</p>
        <p>That is because Senate Republicans have held ratification hostage to their own competing agenda of missile defense. No defensive system yet exists that can reliably protect the United States against incoming missile attack. The Clinton Administration has agreed to spend $4 billion over the next six years on research and testing for a limited missile defense system and has set aside a further $6.6 billion for possible construction. It is also negotiating with Russia on changes in the 1972 Antiballistic Missile Treaty to permit expanded missile defenses.</p>
        <p>But that has not been enough for the Republicans, especially the chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, Jesse Helms. He wants his committee to delay taking up the test ban treaty until the Administration submits two other agreements that the Administration does not yet have the votes to pass -- an earlier set of amendments to the 1972 ABM treaty and the completely unrelated Kyoto treaty on global warming. That timetable would further needlessly delay the test ban treaty and could even risk unraveling it as other countries lose patience with the Senate's stalling.</p>
        <p>The test ban treaty, endorsed by America's top military commander and the directors of the nation's nuclear weapons laboratories, should be ratified promptly on its own merits. The Republican leadership needs to show greater responsibility on this issue. Senator Trent Lott, the majority leader, should insist that Mr. Helms put ratification on the Foreign Relations Committee's calendar early this month.</p>
        <p>That would give the full Senate a chance to act in time for the United States to take part in an important review conference scheduled for October. A successful conference would encourage India and Pakistan to join the treaty. Russia and China, the other nuclear powers that have not yet ratified, are more likely to do so once Washington does. Ratifying the test ban treaty would reduce nuclear dangers around the world. Senator Helms and his fellow Republicans should stop holding it up.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
