<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>E.P.A. to Give States Edict On Clean Air for U.S. Parks</title>
    <meta content="18ENVI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1101230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Janofsky, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DC113BF93BA25757C0A96F958260" item-length="914" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>E.P.A. to Give States Edict On Clean Air for U.S. Parks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Janofsky, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmental Protection Agency is preparing to give states new deadline to clean up air pollution in national parks and wilderness areas; states will be asked to assess their haze problems over next few years and submit plans for cleanup strategies to agency between 2003 and 2008; deadline for cleanup is 2064; goal is to return air quality in scores of parks and wild areas to what amounts to pre-industrial conditions: pure air; ambitious goal has evoked criticism on both sides of issue (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On some days in Acadia National Park in Maine, the air pollution is so bad, visibility is half what it might be on a clear day.</p>
        <p>The same is true in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park in Tennessee, the Shenandoah National Park in Virginia and so many other national parks and wilderness areas -- where the pollution frequently matches the levels in major cities -- that the Environmental Protection Agency is preparing to give states a new deadline to clean them up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On some days in Acadia National Park in Maine, the air pollution is so bad, visibility is half what it might be on a clear day.</p>
        <p>The same is true in the Great Smoky Mountains National Park in Tennessee, the Shenandoah National Park in Virginia and so many other national parks and wilderness areas -- where the pollution frequently matches the levels in major cities -- that the Environmental Protection Agency is preparing to give states a new deadline to clean them up.</p>
        <p>The deadline: 2064.</p>
        <p>As part of regulations that could be announced by President Clinton as early as Thursday, which is Earth Day, states will be asked to assess their haze problems over the next few years and submit plans for cleanup strategies to the agency between 2003 and 2008.</p>
        <p>Over the following six decades, they would set out to return air quality in scores of parks and wild areas, especially in the East, to what amounts to pre-industrial conditions. That is, pure.</p>
        <p>It is an ambitious goal that, like many other environmental policies, has evoked criticism on both sides of the issue. This week, lobbyists for environmental and industry groups continued to meet with Administration officials. The officials emphasized that details were still being worked out, including the possibility that deadlines might vary in different parts of the country.</p>
        <p>Some environmental groups say that 60 years is too long to wait to clean up areas that are used and revered by millions of Americans each year. They say technology now exists to clean up the leading sources of the pollution, power plants that burn coal and other fossil fuels, at a much faster pace.</p>
        <p>''This is far too weak to accomplish where we need to go,'' said Armond Cohen, director of the Clean Air Task Force, a consortium of 80 environmental groups, based in Boston. ''It is the first step, and it does set a marker, which is helpful and better than nothing. But it's not sufficient. The time frame is too slow.''</p>
        <p>L. Bruce Hill, senior staff scientist for the Appalachian Mountain Club in Gorham, N.H., a conservation group with 80,000 members, applauded the E.P.A. for shortening its original schedule, which would have required 200 years to meet the goals of the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>He called the goal of restoring pure air to the wilds within a generation ''a huge accomplishment.''</p>
        <p>But he said 60 years was too long to wait, calling the regulations ''softer than they could be.''</p>
        <p>Power industry executives, as well as elected officials in the South and Midwest, who constantly argue with Northeastern states over the pollution that drifts across their borders, argue that the new regulations are too rigid, and in some cases, redundant. They say that cleanups could cost billions of dollars, a price that could be reflected in electricity bills.</p>
        <p>''Most folks on the industry side of the issue say the regulations are too inflexible,'' said Dave Flannery, legal counsel for the Midwest Ozone Group, which represents 25 power companies in nine states. ''We feel their approach is taking on too much too fast. We need a much more flexible, more cautious program.''</p>
        <p>Paul Bailey, vice president for environment of the Edison Electric Institute, a trade association that represents most of the country's power plants, said states also needed wider latitude in eliminating haze because problems are more concentrated in some areas. Also, Mr. Bailey said, some states may need to work with neighboring states to develop a regional strategy, which could take longer to implement. The draft encourages states to work together, and some already are, like the Grand Canyon Visibility Transport Commission, which is studying air quality problems in nine Western states.</p>
        <p>Murray Johnson, policy analyst for the Southern Governors Association, said that other programs aimed at improving air quality for health reasons already addressed the objectives of the E.P.A.'s new proposal. He said some of the governors were concerned that resources being used to make the air healthier would be ''misallocated'' to improve visibility.</p>
        <p>''We believe there are a lot of visibility benefits to what we're doing now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One apparent reason for regulators' allowing so many years for improvement is that the visibility problem is partly one of esthetics, not public health.</p>
        <p>In a recent draft of the new regulations, E.P.A. officials determined that ''visibility impairment caused by air pollution occurs virtually all the time'' at most national parks.</p>
        <p>Like many air quality regulations, the proposed haze protocols bring a new focus to an old problem -- the older fossil-fuel power plants, which have been excluded from the strictest controls of the 1977 Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Concentrated in the East, they produce as much as 75 percent of the sulphur dioxide emissions that are polluting parks and wilderness areas, some environmentalists say.  Forcing them to meet modern emission standards or shutting them down, they say, would go a long way toward cleaning up the parks.</p>
        <p>The proposed regulations are expected to require states to identify the main sources of pollution and either force companies to modernize their plants to reduce emissions or, in an approach that has been used to help control smog and acid rain, to buy and sell pollution credits in a trading arrangement that would reduce a region's overall pollution.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
