<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Word for Word/Protest Studies; Skywriting, Collective Disappearance And Other Ways to Up the Revolution</title>
    <meta content="05WORD$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1158585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E1D8153EF936A35751C1A96F958260" item-length="1120" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Word for Word/Protest Studies; Skywriting, Collective Disappearance And Other Ways to Up the Revolution</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HEY-HEY! Ho-ho! L.B.J. has got to go!'' The classic syncopated chant from the antiwar movement of the late 1960's was borrowed by protesters who took to the streets of Seattle last week during the meeting of the World Trade Organization. But the words were tweaked to fit the multisyllabic objects of a broad new range of outrages, including corporate globalization, automatic teller machine fees, environmental imperialism, coffee-bar gentrification, genetically modified food, endangered turtles, logging, shrimp farming, aggressive landlords and unemployment among Hollywood studio workers.</p>
        <p>''Hey-hey! Ho-Ho! W.T.O. has got to go!'' was the closest the Seattle demonstrators got to a foot-stomping beat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HEY-HEY! Ho-ho! L.B.J. has got to go!'' The classic syncopated chant from the antiwar movement of the late 1960's was borrowed by protesters who took to the streets of Seattle last week during the meeting of the World Trade Organization. But the words were tweaked to fit the multisyllabic objects of a broad new range of outrages, including corporate globalization, automatic teller machine fees, environmental imperialism, coffee-bar gentrification, genetically modified food, endangered turtles, logging, shrimp farming, aggressive landlords and unemployment among Hollywood studio workers.</p>
        <p>''Hey-hey! Ho-Ho! W.T.O. has got to go!'' was the closest the Seattle demonstrators got to a foot-stomping beat.</p>
        <p>It's been a long time since Abbie Hoffman was able to speak volumes against the establishment by publishing a manifesto with the perversely simple title, ''Steal this Book.'' A generation later, courses in ''protest studies'' are taught by colleges and even high schools. Demonstrations are now firmly supported by academic theory and even boot-camp training.</p>
        <p>Perhaps inevitably, political action has moved from the dorm room to the Internet. Here are excerpts from two Web sites that had links to organizers of the Seattle protests.</p>
        <p>JOE SHARKEY</p>
        <p>The Ruckus Society, founded in 1995 in Berkeley, Calif., sponsors camps and seminars to train protesters for environmental and human rights groups. Neatness counts when it comes to dealing with the news media, the Society says on its Web site (www.ruckus.org):</p>
        <p>This chapter includes a checklist of what you should do, and when you should do it, to have the best shot at getting your action's message out. But these steps can be for naught if not done with thorough professionalism. Journalists are professional cynics, and if you're sloppy, they will notice it, and it will color their coverage. So go the extra mile; proofread the press release again; make the extra phone call. Never cut corners.</p>
        <p>Ruckus says it has trained hundreds of activists in nonviolent civil disobedience, many at rugged camps at more than a dozen rural locations in North America.</p>
        <p>Our showcase venue is Action Camp. Through these trainings, we help people learn the skills they need to practice civil disobedience safely and effectively. These trainings contain cerebral elements as well as physical, like classroom-style instruction for action planning, communicating with the media and nonviolent philosophy and practice. Safety and nonviolence are integral themes of each subject taught.</p>
        <p>Among the courses taught at the camps:</p>
        <p>Basic ropework, belaying, rappelling, knots, harness and hardware. Anchors, hammocks and platforms, jumaring, equipment care and repair. Protest situations such as tree sits, bridge blockades, building climbs, stack climbs, etc. will be illustrated, discussed and practiced.</p>
        <p>Blockades:These are, in some regard, the brown bread basics of direct action. Among the subjects we will demonstrate, discuss and practice are: tree sits, tripods, lockboxes, railboxes, barrel blockades, vehicle blockades, water blockades, bridge actions, cattle guard blockades, putting cup blockades, etc. Learn how to lock your head to something. . . .</p>
        <p>How to Hang Yourself from an Urban Structure: Disclaimer -- This is a basic guideline for how to create the image of a hanged man from a company sign (generally oil companies). Only an EXPERIENCED climber can comprehend and practice this form of direct action, and even then only with extensive training.</p>
        <p>Rock-climbers, mountaineers, and activists with the desire but not the experience DO NOT QUALIFY to try this activity. Only people who have years of urban, direct action . . . should even consider training for this. You WILL get hurt attempting this without proper training, setting the movement for social justice, environmental security and human rights back in the eyes of the world. A good activist is a living activist.</p>
        <p>Nonviolence Works expounds on the theory of modern social activism and provides links to human rights groups. One expert cited on its Web site (www.nonviolenceworks.org) is Gene Sharp, a director of the Albert Einstein Institution in Cambridge, Mass, and author of ''The Methods of Nonviolent Action'' (1973). In it, he lists 198 techniques for fighting the good fight, including:</p>
        <p>5. Declarations of indictment and intention</p>
        <p>12. Skywriting and earthwriting</p>
        <p>14. Mock awards</p>
        <p>22. Protest disrobings</p>
        <p>23. Destruction of own property</p>
        <p>28. Symbolic sounds</p>
        <p>30. Rude gestures</p>
        <p>31. ''Haunting'' officials</p>
        <p>35. Humorous skits and pranks</p>
        <p>52. Silence</p>
        <p>53. Refusing honors</p>
        <p>54. Turning One's Back</p>
        <p>65. Stay at home</p>
        <p>69. Collective disappearance</p>
        <p>102. Prisoners strike</p>
        <p>144. Stalling and obstruction</p>
        <p>148. Mutiny</p>
        <p>158. Self-exposure to the elements</p>
        <p>162. Sit-in</p>
        <p>165. Wade-in</p>
        <p>169. Nonviolent air raids</p>
        <p>177. Speak-in</p>
        <p>In the 60's, protest philosophy was short and sweet. Professor Sharp makes a more expansive argument in ''The Importance of Strategic Training in Nonviolent Struggle.''</p>
        <p>If one wishes to accomplish something, the chances of achieving that goal will be greatest if one uses one's available resources and leverage to maximum effectiveness. That means having a strategic plan which is designed to move from the present (in which the goal is not achieved) to the  future (in which it is achieved). Strategy pertains to charting the course of  action which makes it most likely to get from the present to a desired situation in the future. This type of thinking and planning, which some individuals undertake for ordinary purposes in daily life, should be undertaken by leaders of social and political movements.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, however, strategic planning is rarely given the attention it deserves with such movements. . . .</p>
        <p>It's a long way from spring break in Fort Lauderdale, but those immersed in today's no-nonsense protest studies need a holiday trip from time to time, like this one offered by the Ruckus Society:</p>
        <p>Alternative Spring Break Action Camp 2000</p>
        <p>When: March 2000, exact dates to be announced later.</p>
        <p>Where: Florida, exact location to be announced later.</p>
        <p>Who: Student activists from all over the United States.</p>
        <p>The Ruckus Society, Ozone Action, and Free the Planet have teamed up to co-sponsor the first Alternative Spring Break/Climate Change Action Camp. This ground-breaking training will bring a vanguard of student activists . . . to Florida for a spring break celebration markedly different from the standard fare.</p>
        <p>The training is designed to increase the overall effectiveness of student advocacy by providing participants with a new set of technical campaign tactics and strategies, while building stronger ties of cooperation. We will emphasize campaign work that challenges the corporate culture that has laid claim to colleges and universities alike. While our primary focus will be on global warming, the Action Camp will also offer . . . skills to tackle a wide array of environmental, human rights, fair-trade, and social justice abuses that are inextricably tied to the ''corporatization'' of our academic institutions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
