<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Handful of Dust</title>
    <meta content="08SUN1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1129268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E5DC1330F93BA3575BC0A96F958260" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Handful of Dust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial says drought oppressing Eastern Seaboard should prompt individual and collective conservation both now and when rains return (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Drought is a slow emergency. It does not swoop down out of the skies like a tornado or pull the earth apart at its seams like an earthquake. A drought of the kind the Eastern seaboard is suffering now, the worst of this century in at least four states, is the product not of one summer's failed rains but of chronic dryness over several seasons -- compounded by routine profligacy in our use of water. It is the result of what we have all been taught to call good weather -- hot, it is true, but blue skies day after day, mild winters, little snow. It is also the result of what we have come to call normal water use.</p>
        <p>The drought of 1999 has become severe enough to bring about a flurry of administrative actions intended to mitigate its effects on farms, businesses and communities. On Friday, President Clinton ordered the appropriate Federal agencies to form a task force to organize timely drought relief. New Jersey's Governor, Christine Todd Whitman, and the Governors of Maryland, Delaware and West Virginia have all imposed mandatory restrictions on water use. Secretary of Agriculture Dan Glickman has declared West Virginia and 33 counties in 5 surrounding states a disaster area. Meanwhile, the Senate approved $7.4 billion in aid to farmers, to which a drought and disaster relief package will need to be added in the House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Drought is a slow emergency. It does not swoop down out of the skies like a tornado or pull the earth apart at its seams like an earthquake. A drought of the kind the Eastern seaboard is suffering now, the worst of this century in at least four states, is the product not of one summer's failed rains but of chronic dryness over several seasons -- compounded by routine profligacy in our use of water. It is the result of what we have all been taught to call good weather -- hot, it is true, but blue skies day after day, mild winters, little snow. It is also the result of what we have come to call normal water use.</p>
        <p>The drought of 1999 has become severe enough to bring about a flurry of administrative actions intended to mitigate its effects on farms, businesses and communities. On Friday, President Clinton ordered the appropriate Federal agencies to form a task force to organize timely drought relief. New Jersey's Governor, Christine Todd Whitman, and the Governors of Maryland, Delaware and West Virginia have all imposed mandatory restrictions on water use. Secretary of Agriculture Dan Glickman has declared West Virginia and 33 counties in 5 surrounding states a disaster area. Meanwhile, the Senate approved $7.4 billion in aid to farmers, to which a drought and disaster relief package will need to be added in the House.</p>
        <p>This is all to the good, and it may also re-concentrate, for a moment, our attention on this nation's patterns of water usage. Drought is nothing new, and dealing with it does not require radically new ideas. Any number of entities, including  the Western Drought Coordination Council and the National Drought Policy Commission, have been spawned in recent years in order to monitor drought conditions and respond to them as the long-term events they are. According to the National Drought Mitigation Center, no state had a drought plan during the 1976-77 dry spell. This year 30 states do, and nearly every encounter with water scarcity leads to a set of recommendations -- essentially the ones invoked in a drought emergency -- meant to discourage consumption and encourage recycling.</p>
        <p>But once the rains begin again and controls are lifted, water use tends to rebound to previous levels. Drought dramatizes an epistemological problem that has real, practical effects. There is something almost intangible about the causes of drought, something as abstract and as forceful as fate. A high-pressure dome has kept rain from the mid-Atlantic states this summer, a weather pattern related to the occurrence of La Nina, a drop in sea-surface temperature in the eastern equatorial Pacific last winter. It is hard to tie any single drought unequivocally to the solid evidence of global warming, but that too lurks in many people's minds as the ultimate cause of this summer's parching.</p>
        <p>Against such a grand array of forces, it can be hard to imagine how taking a shorter shower or watering the lawn less frequently makes a difference. But individual action -- conserving water -- is the basis for collective action, and collectively, the residents of drought-stricken states can make an enormous difference in their own welfare, both now, when stream levels are at record lows, and in the future, when rain returns.</p>
        <p>Farmers, of course, are forced to take the weather as it comes, and they understand just how illusory any sense of expectation based on what passes for normal really is. Consumers can scale back water use to the bone with little more than inconvenience. But farms, like many other forms of industry, require water for economic survival, which is exactly what is at risk again this year. The reserves of water in reservoirs and aquifers have been steadily diminishing. So have the economic reserves of American farmers, who find themselves bringing their products to market, if they survive this dry season at all, at depressed prices. Neither of these problems, drought or farm income, can be solved with a sudden flurry of attention.</p>
        <p>They require long-term commitment and the changing of habits that are so persistent we have come to call them normal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
