<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Academic and Career Skills Merge</title>
    <meta content="18VOCS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1101008"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenberg, Merri</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vocational Training</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E2DD153BF93BA25757C0A96F958260" item-length="2174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Academic and Career Skills Merge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MERRI ROSENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenberg, Merri</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes some of courses taught at award-winning Saunders Trades and Technical High School in Yonkers, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was not a pretty sight. An array of computer boards lay splayed open, their wires dangling, as young workers juggled instruction manuals and precision tools trying to figure out how to turn them into usable computers again.</p>
        <p>The scene was an electronics and computer circuitry classroom at the 1,300-student Saunders Trades and Technical High School here, which has won two national awards in the last year while overturning stereotypes of vocational schools as a dumping ground for students who cannot meet the demands of college preparatory classes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was not a pretty sight. An array of computer boards lay splayed open, their wires dangling, as young workers juggled instruction manuals and precision tools trying to figure out how to turn them into usable computers again.</p>
        <p>The scene was an electronics and computer circuitry classroom at the 1,300-student Saunders Trades and Technical High School here, which has won two national awards in the last year while overturning stereotypes of vocational schools as a dumping ground for students who cannot meet the demands of college preparatory classes.</p>
        <p>In fact, students clamor for the right to attend Saunders and tackle a nine-period day, which encompasses both academic courses and technical training. ''We are the school of choice in Yonkers,'' said Carolyn Koppe, the dean of students. ''We get 500 to 600 applications for 300 places. There is a waiting list, sometimes in the hundreds, to come here.''</p>
        <p>Saunders, which was founded in 1909 as the first public vocational school in the state, was the only vocational school recognized last year as a Blue Ribbon National School of Excellence by the United States Department of Education. It was also one of 17 schools in the country honored by the department as a New American High School, a designation that recognizes distinguished career training as well as strong academic training. As a result, the school received a one-year $6,000 grant for programs, as well as a $9,000 grant to do a long-term study of its graduates.</p>
        <p>''What's unique about Saunders is that they have high academic standards and strong vocational preparation within the same campus,'' said Ivonne Jaime, an education program specialist for the New American High School Initiative at the Education Department in Washington, who had visited Saunders as part of the evaluation process. ''You won't find that model as widely as area vocational schools. Some of Saunders's programs are exceptional, especially some of their career academies. In fashion technology for example, the work the students do is exceptional with the integration of academics and the ability of students to integrate their work. It helps students learn.''</p>
        <p>Administrators at Saunders decided to pursue the Blue Ribbon award after receiving their Middle States Association accreditation in October 1994. ''We knew we were a good school,'' Mrs. Koppe said, ''and they told us that we were the best-kept secret around, so we decided to apply.''</p>
        <p>For Saunders students, however, there's no mystery about the attraction of the school's combination of academics and hands-on experiences. ''Here, you use your hands and your brain,'' said Felderi Santiago, a senior who was an adept trouble-shooter in the computer class and who has a paid internship with ADL Data Systems in Dobbs Ferry.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, in the most recent English test administered by the state, Saunders students did not do well. The reason was that the majority of them do not have English as their first language, the principal, Bernard P. Pierorazio, said.</p>
        <p>Students in Yonkers apply to three magnet programs (two programs may be at the same school) as part of a ballot system. The school district's central office tries to accommodate requests in placement, taking into account academic requirements for programs like chemistry and environmental science.</p>
        <p>As freshmen, students spend half a year in an exploratory program, rotating among classes in either the technical, vocational or occupational areas. As sophomores, students select a major like computerized industrial design, carpentry, auto mechanics, construction and facilities management, architectural technology, bio-environmental technology, food service and restaurant management and chemical technology. By the time they are seniors, many students work as paid or unpaid interns in their chosen field for half the school day. Senior technical students are also expected to pursue independent research projects.</p>
        <p>Besides intensive technical training, Saunders offers the basic Regents program of math, science, English, foreign languages and social studies, as well as advanced-placement courses in English, calculus, physics, chemistry, environmental science and United States history.</p>
        <p>Like their counterparts at other schools, Saunders students are involved in after-school sports, student government and extracurricular activities.</p>
        <p>''I knew I had a lot of options by doing this,'' said Deepak Thomas, a senior who is a chemical technology major. ''I want to do engineering, and this gives me a good foundation. I got interested in chemistry through the freshman exploratory program. Right now, I'm working on a project to discover whether chocolate has good stuff in it for nutrition by analyzing the amino acids.''</p>
        <p>Deepak, who is a member of the school's tennis team, the Key Club service organization and the environmental club, has also worked summers for Consumers' Union testing strollers and educational toys, like chemistry sets.</p>
        <p>A classmate of his, Chris Larca, who is the senior class president, yearbook editor and an active member of various other clubs, explained the attraction of Saunders this way: ''I wanted to be a genetic engineer since I was 12. Now I'm looking toward computers and electrical engineering. I like watching my hands at work, and creating something with my knowledge. Science is the way of the world. There will always be a job.''</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in the county students  who want a vocational education are usually assigned by their home districts to spend two hours a day at the campuses of the Southern Westchester or Putnam/Northern Westchester Boards of Cooperative Educational Services; they spend the rest of the day at their home schools for academic instruction.</p>
        <p>All the schools offering vocational training strive to give students the technical skills to compete in the current work market and the intellectual skills to adapt to future changes in their fields.</p>
        <p>At Saunders, for example, each vocational and occupational area, has a crafts committee of working professionals who meet with the teachers to keep them up to date on industry requirements as well as employer needs.</p>
        <p>''When I was a student here, we did strictly oil heating,'' said Eddie Frazier, a 1979 Saunders graduate from  the era before the school went co-educational and now a teacher of heating and air conditioning. ''In the last 10 years, we've included air conditioning, gas heat and more technology. They use torches in 10th grade, and we used them as seniors. Today's students also use computers to make schematics of their boiler design, as well as how to price out a job. Now they have to understand building construction, electrical work, and plumbing, as well as how to deal with issues like freon removal from refrigerators. Times are changing and they have to have more skills.''</p>
        <p>His colleague, Tom Sabia, a 1970 Saunders graduate, said: ''Students have to deal with issues like global warming, refrigerator recycling, environmental regulations and all sorts of issues that we didn't. Now students need to understand why they need math and science and are expected to do more thinking on their own.'' (In the old days at Saunders,  math and science were taught by shop teachers; now they are part of the academic curriculum).</p>
        <p>Likewise, Donald McKenzie, superintendent of the Putnam/Northern Westchester Board of Cooperative Educational Services in Yorktown Heights, explained, ''Our auto mechanics class, for example, goes on line with car manufacturers to be up to date on industry standards and specifications.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the Southern Westchester board in Rye Brook has started a program aimed at placing  100 juniors and seniors studying automotive technology with dealers in paid internships.</p>
        <p>The technology needed to keep the students up to date does not come cheaply. Although Yonkers school officials say they do not calculate costs per student at Saunders versus costs at other high schools, a spokesman for the district did say that the school has higher per pupil costs for supplies and equipment, offset in part by grants and outside financing from the Federal Government and businesses, as well as alumni.</p>
        <p>There is some concern that the new Regents standards, which require high school students to pass rigorous tests in five academic subjects in the next three years, could discourage some students from taking part in vocational programs.</p>
        <p>Dr. Stacey Holmes, Superintendent of the Southern Westchester Board of Cooperative Educational Services, said, ''There's a tremendous challenge for students to do two things, which is to be professionally certified and earn a Regents diploma.''</p>
        <p>At Saunders, Mr. Pierorazio, said: ''We grabbed the bull by the horns two years ago and required all students to take Regents courses. We're not waiting for the state to impose mandates.''</p>
        <p>Saunders also has agreements to permit students to take some college courses. For example, students in the advanced placement environmental science course can take organic chemistry at either Manhattan College in Riverdale or at Purchase College. Similarly, students in the chemical technology program can take an analytic chemistry class at Westchester Community College in Valhalla.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frazier, the teacher and graduate of Saunders, noted that while he and most of his classmates went directly into industry, today's students are just as likely to pursue higher education.</p>
        <p>Eighty-two percent of the 1997 Saunders graduating class -- the latest year from which figures are available -- are now in college. Over the years, Saunders graduates have gone on to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Harvard, Yale, Columbia, Cornell, Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, the United States Air Force Academy, the Naval Academy and the United State Military Academy as well as other nationally recognized universities and colleges.</p>
        <p>''We're telling them that college is out there if they want it,'' said Mrs. Koppe, the dean of students. ''We're encouraging students to go on to college. They're prepared for it. Just because you're a carpenter here, it doesn't mean you have to be a carpenter the rest of your life. Maybe you just want to have the skills to fix up your own house.''</p>
        <p>The Kitchen Is the Classroom</p>
        <p>YORKTOWN HEIGHTS -- WEARING a toque and white jacket, Tom Shea spooned cooked apricots onto a layer of sponge cake. Others cut away excess cake and transferred sponge circles to stainless steel baking pans. Elsewhere in the clean but noisy kitchen, a pastry instructor, Ron Lunge, reached across a counter and whipped Bavarian cream into an airy confection.</p>
        <p>''It's called tempering,'' Mr. Lunge said. ''What is tempering? It's when you introduce cold, or thinning stuff, so it blends easier. You want the air to stay in the whipped cream.'' As he demonstrated how to  layer fruit, cake and whipped cream for an English trifle or an Italian zuppa inglese, Mr. Lunge explained how to spread out fruit without breaking the sponge layer and how to keep the whipped cream from settling.</p>
        <p>The nine young men and one young woman were high school students in the culinary arts program of the Putnam/Northern Westchester Board of Cooperative Educational Services at the board's campus here. About 100 juniors and seniors sign up each year, most of them juniors planning to study for two years, although a one-year course is offered. The course duplicates the hectic pace and drama of a restaurant. It also requires the students to read about food and its preparation, including the use of kitchen equipment, preparation of sauces, deep frying, making stock and cooking fish, among other things.</p>
        <p>''The students do a two-week rotation in each curriculum area, which includes menu planning, cost, pricing and customer relations,'' Chef Stanley Rupinski, who runs the food part of the program, said. ''We also have an on-premises catering operation, where they might be responsible for making pasta for 350 people. I believe in creating a comfortable atmosphere where learning becomes fun and interesting. The kids don't seem to mind the hard work because they see they'll be using it. The idea is not only to teach them industrial cooking but to give them the people skills they'll need. We have a 95 percent placement record with our students, either in industry, self-employment or for further education.''</p>
        <p>The students run an on-site restaurant, the Educated Palate, open on Thursdays for a fixed price of $15 for lunch. For Tom Shea of Mahopac, a junior at Mahopac High School, enrolling in the culinary arts program was an improvement over his previous experience with auto mechanics. ''I'll probably apply to Johnson and Wales,'' he said, referring to the university in Providence. R.I., that is known for its hotel and restaurant management programs. ''I like baking, and it looks good when it's finished. Eventually, I would want to work on a cruise ship.''</p>
        <p>Yasmin Barnes, a Peekskill High School senior who wants to attend college in the fall, chose the culinary arts program because: ''I'm going to try to be an actress. This is a good trade to learn.''</p>
        <p>MERRI ROSENBERG</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
