<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coca-Cola Earnings Fall 21%, Reflecting Troubles in Europe</title>
    <meta content="Y16COKE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1123716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coca-Cola Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hays, Constance L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soft Drinks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recalls and Bans of Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7DB143FF935A25754C0A96F958260" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coca-Cola Earnings Fall 21%, Reflecting Troubles in Europe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE L. HAYS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hays, Constance L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coca-Cola Co says second-quarter profit fell 21 percent, in part because it had to pull millions of soft drinks off the market in Europe; net income dropped to $941 million compared with $1.19 billion a year earlier; worldwide sales volume fell 2 percent compared with 10 percent a year ago; revenue rose 4 percent, to $5.38 billion from $5.15 billion (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In part because it had to pull millions of soft drinks off the market in Europe last month, the Coca-Cola Company's second-quarter profit fell 21 percent, the company said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In the quarter ended June 30, net income dropped to $942 million, or 38 cents a diluted share, compared with $1.19 billion, or 48 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In part because it had to pull millions of soft drinks off the market in Europe last month, the Coca-Cola Company's second-quarter profit fell 21 percent, the company said yesterday.</p>
        <p>In the quarter ended June 30, net income dropped to $942 million, or 38 cents a diluted share, compared with $1.19 billion, or 48 cents a share, in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Worldwide sales volume, measured in cases of finished drinks, fell 2 percent, compared with a 10 percent increase in the period a year earlier. The company appears to be spending heavily on marketing even as volume declines. It reported that revenue rose 4 percent, to $5.38 billion from $5.15 billion, but that sales, administrative and general expenses increased 10 percent.</p>
        <p>The volume and earnings were about what Wall Street had expected, and Coke shares rose $2.125, closing at $64.</p>
        <p>It was the fourth consecutive quarter in which Coke reported a decline in earnings, but analysts seemed to take the results in stride.</p>
        <p>''The good news is, there's no incremental bad news,'' said Jennifer Solomon, a beverage analyst with Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Coca-Cola's top management, including its chairman and chief executive, M. Douglas Ivester, has scheduled an unusual meeting with analysts and investors in New York on Thursday. Topics on the agenda include the recall in Europe, global business conditions and Coke's growth outlook.</p>
        <p>In a statement yesterday, the company said the recall, which began in Belgium on June 14 with hundreds of people saying they became ill after drinking Coke products and spread to France, Luxembourg and the Netherlands, was a factor in its performance. About 17 million cases of Coke products had to be recalled and destroyed.</p>
        <p>In addition, two plants in Belgium and a third in France were shut down while Coca-Cola sought to determine what had made people ill. The company concluded that a flawed batch of carbon dioxide, used to carbonate its soft drinks, from a Belgian plant may have caused a bad smell in one set of products and that a phenol compound used to protect shipping crates in the French plant may have done the same thing. But in both cases, Coca-Cola maintained that the substances it detected were present in amounts too tiny to have made anyone ill.</p>
        <p>The recall's effect on Coca-Cola's earnings was 2 to 3 cents a share, the company said.</p>
        <p>While volume fell 6 percent in European markets, it declined in many other places, as well. In China, volume dropped 9 percent, a decline the company attributed to severe flooding in the eastern part of the country last month and to the fallout from the bombing by the United States of the Chinese Embassy in Belgrade, Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>In India, volume rose 2 percent, far less than in the second quarter of 1998, when it grew 33 percent. Again, the weather was at fault, Coca-Cola said, noting that the early monsoons decreased sales near the end of the quarter. Over all, volume fell 2 percent in the Middle East and East Asian division.</p>
        <p>Volume was flat in Latin America, compared with a 12 percent increase in the second quarter last year, and sales in countries like Venezuela and Colombia continued to slide. In Africa, volume fell 1 percent, mostly in the southern part of the continent, where the company said unrest in Zimbabwe and economic weakness in South Africa drove down demand.</p>
        <p>In the United States, volume fell 1 percent, compared with an 8 percent increase in the period a year earlier.</p>
        <p>In Japan, one of Coke's largest markets, volume grew 6 percent, a turnaround from a 3 percent decline in the second quarter last year.</p>
        <p>Equity income, from bottlers in which Coca-Cola holds a stake, has fallen 83 percent so far this year, the company said. That pace is ahead of last year's, when equity income decreased 79 percent, a reflection of the sales slowdowns that bottlers are encountering.</p>
        <p>''The equity-income line was supposed to be a nice contributor to earnings growth,'' said Emanuel Goldman, a global consumer products analyst for Merrill Lynch. ''It's backward now.'' Of the quarter as a whole, he added: ''It's like Zeus was hurling thunderbolts at them, and Zeus worked for Pepsi.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
