<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="14FSUM$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1092463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7DB133EF937A25750C0A96F958260" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-17</p>
        <p>NATO Attempts to Ease Past Tensions With Russia  NATO is seeking to reassure Russia about its enlargement, in time for the celebration of its 50th anniversary. Russia still hopes to blunt any military advantage the alliance derives from admitting Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary and to discourage the inclusion of other former Soviet bloc nations in the future.</p>
        <p>1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-17</p>
        <p>NATO Attempts to Ease Past Tensions With Russia  NATO is seeking to reassure Russia about its enlargement, in time for the celebration of its 50th anniversary. Russia still hopes to blunt any military advantage the alliance derives from admitting Poland, the Czech Republic and Hungary and to discourage the inclusion of other former Soviet bloc nations in the future.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Bomb Assault in Istanbul  Three assailants threw gasoline bombs into a crowded Istanbul department store, killing at least 12 people and injuring many more, a fire service official said. It was not immediately clear who carried out the attack.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Clemency Sought for Gunman  The Vatican told the Italian government that it would favor clemency for Mehmet Ali Agca, the Turkish gunman who tried to assassinate the Pope in 1981. Mr. Agca is serving a life sentence in an Italian prison.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Bombs Explode in Kosovo  Three powerful bombs exploded in northern Kosovo tearing into people and killing at least six, including two children, and wounding dozens just as the leaders of the province's ethnic Albanian majority departed for a new round of peace talks with the Serbs in Paris.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>U.S. Seeks Dissident's Release  Nguyen Thanh Giang, a Vietnamese dissident, was reportedly arrested outside his home on March 4. In statements that appeared to tacitly confirm the arrest, Vietnam rejected calls by the United States for his immediate release, criticizing them as ''brazen interference.'' The new tensions come ahead of a new round of talks on a trade agreement between the United States and Vietnam.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>20-35</p>
        <p>Reshaped Appeals System Is Being Challenged  A heavy caseload is forcing a reshaping of the Federal appeals courts, creating a two-level system in which tens of thousands of appeals receive limited reviews, judges and legal scholars say. The question of whether the new shortcuts are fair has been put squarely before one of the appeals courts that has championed the changes.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Bomber's Sabotage Described  Starting in 1975, long before his arrest as the Unabomber, Theodore J. Kaczynski began a 20-year effort in Montana against what he called the octopus of technology, engaging in environmental sabotage that included burning logging equipment and damaging snowmobiles.</p>
        <p>20</p>
        <p>Possible Pesticide Substitute  Government scientists have found that the natural oil that gives peaches their perfume also kills fungus in the soil. It could replace methyl bromide, a widely used pesticide that is toxic to people and damages the ozone layer.</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Mexican Mafia Under Attack  Federal authorities have turned their attention once again to la Eme, known as the Mexican Mafia, one of California's most powerful prison gangs, charging its members with waging a brutal campaign for control of Southern California's gangs and drug trade.</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>Police Initiatives Offered  President Clinton said in his radio address that recent reports of police misconduct had shaken the public's faith in the police, and he proposed several measures that he said would help restore that trust.</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>37-46</p>
        <p>Teen-Age Immigrants Are Far From Home and Alone  Over the last several years, a small but growing number of teen-age immigrants -- virtually all boys, some as young as 14 or 15 -- have arrived in New York without their parents, much like the child immigrants of a century ago. Most are in this country illegally and are trapped in an underground ruled in large measure by fear -- of the immigration authorities, child welfare agencies, smugglers, thugs and bosses, past and potential.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Town Takes a Stand on Fences  The town board in Haverstraw, N.Y., has adopted a law that bars homeowners from installing wooden stockade fences so that the unfinished side faces out toward neighbors.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Hotel Project Poses Challenge  The redevelopment of the Times Square area is producing some unconventional structures, none more so than the Doubletree Hotel being built on top of 13 levels that will include stores and a 25-screen movie theater. A theater cannot have conventional support columns blocking its sight lines, which posed substantial challenges.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>47-49</p>
        <p>Garson Kanin  A prolific playwright, author and director, who created numerous Broadway and Hollywood classics, including ''Born Yesterday'' and ''Adam's Rib,'' was 86.</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>Muriel Bentley  An early member of Ballet Theater who was praised for her comic gifts and witty dancing, was 82.</p>
        <p>48</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>46  Weather</p>
        <p>26  Cong.Vote</p>
        <p>46</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
