<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Climate Experts' New Worry: Altered Air Patterns</title>
    <meta content="18WARM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19990607T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1108408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Phenomenon)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevens, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4DA153EF93BA25756C0A96F958260" item-length="1565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Climate Experts' New Worry: Altered Air Patterns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. STEVENS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stevens, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Climate experts begin studying patterns of large-scale atmospheric circulation--big, swirling global air currents that dictate where it is warm and cold, wet and dry, and where storms go; some of them say that global warming, instead of producing new patterns, may instead by changing frequency of existing circulation regimes; one study suggests that warming may provoke more frequent appearances of El Nino; another suggests that warming has a connection to more frequent appearances of a circulation regime whose prevailing winds deliver more warmth and precipitation to northern Eurasia and northwestern North America, while generally cooling the US east of the Rockies and drying out southern Europe and the Middle East; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists have long been convinced that global warming, whether natural or caused by human action, would amount to more than a simple, uniform rise in temperature. One response of the climate system to warming, for instance, might be the creation of new patterns of large-scale atmospheric circulation -- the big, swirling global air currents that dictate where it is warm and cold, wet and dry, and where storms go.</p>
        <p>It has been thought that these new circulation patterns would be distinctly different from the kind that now exist. But lately, in an effort to understand better how broad changes in climate might affect day-to-day weather, experts have begun to scrutinize the patterns more closely. Now a number of researchers say that instead of producing new patterns, global warming may instead be changing the frequency of existing circulation regimes, as they are called. And that would have enormous implications for weather around the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Scientists have long been convinced that global warming, whether natural or caused by human action, would amount to more than a simple, uniform rise in temperature. One response of the climate system to warming, for instance, might be the creation of new patterns of large-scale atmospheric circulation -- the big, swirling global air currents that dictate where it is warm and cold, wet and dry, and where storms go.</p>
        <p>It has been thought that these new circulation patterns would be distinctly different from the kind that now exist. But lately, in an effort to understand better how broad changes in climate might affect day-to-day weather, experts have begun to scrutinize the patterns more closely. Now a number of researchers say that instead of producing new patterns, global warming may instead be changing the frequency of existing circulation regimes, as they are called. And that would have enormous implications for weather around the world.</p>
        <p>One recent study suggests that warming may provoke more frequent appearances of El Nino, the vast pool of warm water in the tropical Pacific Ocean that touches off widespread meteorological havoc.</p>
        <p>Another suggests that warming has a connection to more frequent appearances of a circulation regime whose prevailing winds deliver more warmth and precipitation to northern Eurasia and northwestern North America, while generally cooling the United States east of the Rockies and drying out southern Europe and the Middle East.</p>
        <p>These regimes, including the circulation pattern associated with El Nino, have indeed become prevalent in recent decades, when a centurylong rise in average global surface temperature has been the steepest. The temperature has risen in the last 100 years by about 1 degree Fahrenheit, to nearly 60 degrees, with the 1990's ranking as the warmest decade of the century.</p>
        <p>The dominant view among experts is that rising emissions of heat-trapping waste industrial gases like carbon dioxide are responsible for some of the warming. If emissions are not reduced, according to this view, the average global surface temperature will rise by about 3.5 degrees in the 21st century. By comparison, the world is 5 to 9 degrees warmer now than in the depths of the last ice age 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>Experts have long said that one effect of global warming will be to alter precipitation patterns -- increasing rainfall in some places, decreasing it in others. A warmer atmosphere, according to this view, causes more water to evaporate from the surface. Also, a warmer atmosphere holds more moisture, so that when a storm system comes through a given locality to make it rain, the rain is heavier. Data collected and analyzed by Federal scientists suggest a trend in that direction in the United States. Conversely, where it does not rain, a warmer atmosphere might make droughts worse.</p>
        <p>But however much rain may fall in a given spot, it is the atmospheric circulation patterns that determine where those spots are and where it is colder or warmer on a given day. Now scientists are concentrating on those patterns, and they are finding that in many parts of the world they flip back and forth between two alternating, semistable regimes, on time scales of years and decades.  The most familiar of these oscillations is that of El Nino and its cold-water counterpart, La Nina. In it, sea-surface temperatures in the tropical Pacific perpetually alternate between warmer and colder states. The two regimes bring about different patterns of storm tracks and air mass movements.</p>
        <p>Similar oscillations in the North Atlantic and North Pacific produce alternating regimes whose wind patterns determine how storms, heat and cold affect land in Northern Hemisphere, , particularly in winter and spring. Some scientists believe these two oscillations are linked by a third, this one bridging the Arctic.</p>
        <p>At this stage of research, scientists cannot firmly link global warming to changes in circulation patterns. But one study by British and Italian scientists, reported recently in the journal Nature, examined data on atmospheric circulation over the last 50 years in the Northern Hemisphere.  The researchers looked to see whether there had been any change in frequency of large-scale circulation regimes. The data revealed that there had: in recent decades, patterns had shifted to favor a warmer climate for most land areas in the Northern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>In a general warming of the globe, the air above those land areas would be expected to warm more than that above the oceans, because of differing abilities to absorb heat. But the authors of the new study postulate that the change in circulation patterns is the main reason the land has lately warmed so much.</p>
        <p>That is, they say, the climate of the hemisphere shifts naturally back and forth between two dominant regimes. Both the North Atlantic and North Pacific oscillations are believed to be affected by this shift. But if some external influence imparts a warming or cooling impulse, the scientists say, the oscillation could be tipped in favor of one regime or the other. The external influence could be either natural, like a change in solar radiation, or artificial, like carbon dioxide emissions.</p>
        <p>''What we're saying is that you can understand much of the observed climate change in terms of that picture,'' said Dr. Tim Palmer, a climatologist at the European Center for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts in England and one of the study's authors. While the study does not prove that human-induced global warming caused the change in frequency of circulation patterns, he said, the change is consistent with it.</p>
        <p>Such global warming would not produce new types of weather patterns, but it would change the probability of occurrence of existing ones, Dr. Palmer said. And differing regional patterns of warming are a direct consequence of that, he said.</p>
        <p>Another oscillation, in the Arctic, involves the strength of high-altitude winds that circle the North Pole near the Arctic Circle. The winds oscillate between stronger and weaker states, with consequences for weather and climate farther south. Some experts believe that the Arctic oscillation is being altered by global warming.</p>
        <p>The theory is that at certain critical altitudes, roughly from 6 to 12 miles, increasing carbon dioxide has the effect of warming the tropics but cooling the polar regions. This would increase the temperature contrast between the two regions and strengthen the pole-girdling vortex of winds. In turn, westerly winds off the Atlantic would be strengthened, making northern Eurasia warmer and wetter.</p>
        <p>Some scientists, like Dr. John Michael Wallace, an atmospheric scientist at the University of Washington, think that the Arctic and North Atlantic oscillations are so closely tied together as to be the same thing. The effects of the Arctic oscillation over the North Pacific, he said, are more subtle. ''It's hard to see them clearly,'' he said, ''because another big thing is going on there; that's the variability related to El Nino.''</p>
        <p>The El Nino-La Nina cycle is the strongest year-to-year natural climatic oscillation. The two alternating states have markedly different effects on weather. In a strong El Nino, for instance, prevailing jet-stream winds slam into the southern tier of the United States, producing floods, mudslides and tornadoes. In La Nina, the central United States typically gets very cold weather as well as tornadoes, while much of the East is warm and tranquil.</p>
        <p>Historically, El Nino has appeared every two to seven years; La Nina shows up less often. But over the last two decades, El Nino has appeared more frequently, and in much of the 1990's it seemed to go on more or less continuously. Could this be related to global warming?</p>
        <p>Some scientists have raised the possibility. Dr. Kevin Trenberth, a researcher at the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, Colo., has postulated that the time interval between El Ninos depends on how long it takes to recharge the tropical system by reaccumulating heat at the sea surface. Global warming, he suggests, may enable the system to recharge faster, making El Nino appear more often.</p>
        <p>Another study reported recently in Nature appeared to lend credence to this view. Researchers at the Max Planck Institute for Meteorology in Hamburg, Germany, used a computerized model of the climate system's general circulation to study the effects of global warming on El Nino's frequency. In the past, these climate models have been unable to simulate the behavior of the tropical Pacific finely enough to address the issue.  The Planck researchers said they had overcome that problem, and their simulation produced more frequent El Nino conditions and more powerful La Nina events.</p>
        <p>None of this constitutes anything remotely approaching a last word on the response of the climate system's natural churnings to global warming. But as Dr. Wallace says, experts have begun focusing on responses ''that look like distortions of natural patterns.'' All those patterns are part of a single, integrated climate system, and scientists are just beginning to zero in on how they relate to one another in the context of a warming atmosphere.</p>
        <p>That task only makes the problem of climate change more complicated than ever.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 7, 1999, Monday  A chart in Science Times on May 18 about global air patterns reversed the strength and direction of the Arctic winds that affect storm tracks in the North Atlantic region. The stronger Arctic winds from the west result in more intense storm tracks across the region; the weaker Arctic winds from the east result in weaker storm patterns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 7, 1999, Monday</p>
        <p>A chart in Science Times on May 18 about global air patterns reversed the strength and direction of the Arctic winds that affect storm tracks in the North Atlantic region. The stronger Arctic winds from the west result in more intense storm tracks across the region; the weaker Arctic winds from the east result in weaker storm patterns.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
