<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="08OBSE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1113551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lizards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricane Mitch</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Rainier National Park</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Arizona</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reptiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990608T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DB1339F93BA35755C0A96F958260" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists discover that monitor lizard is equipped with 'turbocharger,' a throat pump that provides extra air for lungs when they walk or run; new study by British and American researchers finds that rains released by Hurricane Mitch, which struck Central America in October, were torrential, but not exceptional; study by scientist with United States Geological Survey finds that Mount Rainier National Park, 60 miles from Seattle, has one of highest average weekly levels of ozone of any location in state; University of Arizona researchers say they may have found remnants of failed planet circling a double star system 150 light-years from Earth (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Turbocharged Lizards</p>
        <p>An easy way to improve the performance of a race car is by adding a turbocharger, a compressor that pumps extra air into the engine, allowing the fuel to burn more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Scientists have discovered that a monitor lizard is similarly souped up. It comes equipped with a turbocharger of its own, a ''throat pump'' that provides extra air for the lungs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Turbocharged Lizards</p>
        <p>An easy way to improve the performance of a race car is by adding a turbocharger, a compressor that pumps extra air into the engine, allowing the fuel to burn more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Scientists have discovered that a monitor lizard is similarly souped up. It comes equipped with a turbocharger of its own, a ''throat pump'' that provides extra air for the lungs.</p>
        <p>When lizards walk and run, they amble from side to side, flexing their bodies laterally. The muscles that are responsible for this flexing work in a different direction to expand the chest for breathing. So, according to one hypothesis, at higher speeds flexing predominates and breathing suffers, meaning that most lizards cannot get enough air.</p>
        <p>Studies of monitor lizards have tended to contradict this hypothesis, however, because they have not shown any constraint on oxygen consumption. The new work, by scientists from Harvard, the University of Massachusetts and the University of California at Irvine, demonstrates that the difference is the monitor lizard's throat pump.</p>
        <p>The researchers, who reported on their work in the journal Science, used videoradiography -- moving X-rays, in essence -- to view what went on inside a lizard as it trundled along on a treadmill.</p>
        <p>As the lizard breathes, air is drawn both into the lungs and into an expanding cavity in the throat area. The cavity contracts, pumping the air into the lungs. When the researchers disabled the throat pump by propping the mouth open, monitor lizards showed the same impairment of lung activity as other lizards.</p>
        <p>The Making of a Disaster</p>
        <p>Hurricane Mitch, which struck Central America in October, was the deadliest storm in the Western Hemisphere this century. About 11,000 people were killed, mostly in Honduras and Nicaragua, in the flooding and mudslides that accompanied days of torrential rain.</p>
        <p>But while it was torrential, that rain was not exceptional, according to a new study by British and American researchers. Rainfall amounts in the storm, they say in a letter to the journal Nature, were comparable to other severe storms in the Atlantic region.</p>
        <p>The scientists had a bit of good luck: one rain gauge survived the deluge (they are often destroyed in hurricanes), and recorded 35 inches of rain over four days ended Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>The researchers suggested that other factors were largely responsible for the widespread damage and loss of life. Among these, they say, were the timing of the storm (it came at the end of the rainy season, when the ground was already saturated and could not soak up any more rain), the deforestation of hillsides for use in agriculture, and forecasts that had predicted the storm would move to the north and stay at sea, when it turned south and inland.</p>
        <p>Wind-Borne Pollution</p>
        <p>National parks and wilderness areas are innocent bystanders amid the violence that is air pollution, soiled by contaminants carried on the wind from urban areas. Things have gotten so bad that in April, the Clinton Administration asked states to develop long-range plans for cleaning up the outdoors.</p>
        <p>Further evidence of the extent of the problem comes from a study of the air at Mount Rainier National Park in Washington, which shows that it has higher concentrations of ozone than nearby urban areas. Elevated ozone levels can harm vegetation and animals, including humans.</p>
        <p>The study, by a scientist with the United States Geological Survey, showed that the park, which is only 60 miles from Seattle, has the highest average weekly levels of ozone of any location in the state.</p>
        <p>Most of this is from ozone-creating compounds produced by the burning of fossil fuels in cars and industry in the Seattle area. But the problem is exacerbated because of Mount Rainier's elevation. Ozone concentrations tend to increase at higher altitudes as some ozone from the stratosphere disperses downward.</p>
        <p>A Failed Planet</p>
        <p>Astronomy has been awash in recent discoveries of planets orbiting other stars. Now, researchers from the University of Arizona say they may have found the remnants of a failed planet circling a double star system 150 light-years from Earth.</p>
        <p>The astronomers analyzed infrared emissions from material around the star system and determined that it was coming from dust similar to that in the bands of dust in the asteroid belt between Mars and Jupiter. That belt resulted from a would-be planet that could not form because of Jupiter's huge gravitational forces. The scientists concluded that similar forces must be at work in the double star system to account for the debris.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
