<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Budget Fight Pits Business Against Environmentalists</title>
    <meta content="Y13SPE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1152902"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiner, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE4DC143DF930A25752C1A96F958260" item-length="1226" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Budget Fight Pits Business Against Environmentalists</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM WEINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiner, Tim</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White House and Congress press efforts to strike final budget deal, even as new pro-business, anti-environmental amendments are appearing; both sides have dug in so deeply on fights over environmental issues that some members of Congress fear defeat of spending bills to which measures are attached--step that could cripple efforts to compromise on budget and prevent government shutdown (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The most explosive issues remaining in the budget battle are legislative land mines pitting business interests against environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Even as the White House and Congress try to strike a final deal, new pro-business, anti-environmental measures are appearing, including  one that seeks to block the government from collecting millions of dollars in fines from power companies it says are defying clean-air laws.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The most explosive issues remaining in the budget battle are legislative land mines pitting business interests against environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Even as the White House and Congress try to strike a final deal, new pro-business, anti-environmental measures are appearing, including  one that seeks to block the government from collecting millions of dollars in fines from power companies it says are defying clean-air laws.</p>
        <p>Both sides have dug in so deeply on these fights over land, air, water and money that some members of Congress fear the defeat of the spending bills to which the measures have been attached, a step that could cripple efforts to compromise on the budget and prevent a government shutdown.</p>
        <p>The last days of any Congressional session are a kind of witching hour, when amendments like the power companies' proposed measure can appear suddenly, sometimes seemingly out of nowhere. Political deals cut in private materialize as fine print in a thousand-page bill.</p>
        <p>''You never know what phoenix will come up out of the ashes over the weekend,'' Speaker J. Dennis Hastert of Illinois said on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The spending bills must eventually be passed to keep the government going, but Congress could still continue to extend its deadline, as it already has three times. As the last legislation this year, they can carry politically sensitive material that would not normally pass the normal  checks.</p>
        <p>These include the measures known as riders, so called because they are about unrelated, limited issues attached to the spending bills.</p>
        <p>The Senate has already put two dozen environmental riders on the $15 billion Interior Department spending bill. President Clinton, threatening a veto, called the riders ''a stealth attack on the environment'' and said he would send the bill ''straight back to the recycling bin'' unless they were removed.</p>
        <p>One of the new measures, which has not yet found a sponsor, would stymie the Justice Department's efforts to fine power companies for modernizing plants without modernizing pollution controls, as required by clean-air laws.</p>
        <p>The power companies want to block the Environmental Protection Agency from collecting millions of dollars in fines it wants to impose on 32 coal-fired plants in the Midwest and the South. The plants' emissions are blamed for acid rain in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>The Edison Electric Institute, the trade association of investor-owned utilities that generate three-fourths of the nation's electricity, is leading the charge to persuade Congress to add a last-minute amendment written by the power companies.</p>
        <p>It appealed for ''legislative relief'' in a letter sent on Wednesday to the most powerful members of Congress. A senior official of the institute said today that he thought a senator would sponsor the amendment in the next few days.</p>
        <p>Four Republicans -- Representatives Sherwood Boehlert of upstate New York, Rick A. Lazio of Suffolk, Michael N. Castle of Delaware and Wayne T. Gilchrest of Maryland -- said in a letter sent on Thursday to Mr. Hastert that the power companies' bid was ''a blatant effort'' to protect plants that ''spew out pollutants that create ozone, haze and acid rain'' in the towns and cities they represent.</p>
        <p>Dan Weiss, the political director of the Sierra Club, called the power companies' move ''an unbelievable assault on efforts to control smog and acid rain.''</p>
        <p>The Environmental Protection Agency sued the utilities on Nov. 3, accusing them of failing to make 17 plants abide by tough new standards. The proposed amendment would block $27,500-per-day penalties from piling up against the plants while the power companies seek to settle the suit. At the same time, the agency took administrative action against 15 other plants.</p>
        <p>Paul Bailey, the Edison Electric Institute's vice president of environmental issues, said in an interview: ''Utilities are stuck between a rock and a hard place. State law requires them to provide reliable service. They're getting this message from the E.P.A. saying they're being fined for operating in violation of the clean-air laws. If the government would give us the absolute assurance they can continue operating, that would solve it.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Congress understands the problem we're facing, and they're trying to help us find a solution to it right now. There are efforts right now to craft the right legislative language. There are some potential sponsors'' in the Senate.</p>
        <p>In the earlier riders attached to spending bills, Republican senators took steps to allow more logging in national forests and to let mining companies dump thousands of tons of waste on Federal land. Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, wants to allow coal miners to keep dumping slag into streams.</p>
        <p>Senator Kay Bailey Hutchison, Republican of Texas, wants to delay new rules requiring oil companies to pay royalties the government says they owe. Another new measure cropped up on Thursday. It would delay until the next administration takes power a new rule that Mr. Clinton has proposed to block new roads in 40 million acres of national forest.</p>
        <p>The White House and Congress continued to negotiate today over the environmental riders by telephone and fax. Both sides have proposed compromises, but neither side has agreed. A White House official said today that he did not know if compromise was possible.</p>
        <p>Any one of these riders could derail the five remaining spending bills when they come to the floor in the House and the Senate next week, both Republicans and Democrats in Congress said.</p>
        <p>''The environmental riders are still hanging out there,'' said Representative David R. Obey of Wisconsin, the ranking Democrat on the House Appropriations Committee. ''Some members will die over those. Others will die if they're attached.''</p>
        <p>Republicans say they plan to lash all five bills into a single $390 billion juggernaut. That means that every objection that every member has to every issue within the bill will be concentrated into one vote to support that omnibus measure or let it fall.</p>
        <p>Other problems also loom. There is a $6.5 billion gap between what Congress has agreed to spend and the bottom line beyond which the spending will dip into the Social Security surplus -- even with the creative accounting that Republicans have used to disguise more than $20 billion in the spending bills.</p>
        <p>Then both sides have to agree on whether the final accounting for the spending by the Congressional Budget Office lets them argue plausibly that the bills will not tap into the retirement funds.</p>
        <p>Other potential blockades remain as well. No deal has been struck to allow the United States to pay the $926 million in back dues it owes the United Nations. The White House wants a quarter-billion dollars more for debt relief for the world's poorest nations. Senator Herb Kohl, Democrat of Wisconsin, threatens to stop the Senate cold next week in the name of protecting his state's 23,000 dairy farmers.</p>
        <p>Any one of these issues -- the riders, the U.N. dues, the debt relief, the debate over the Social Security surplus -- could bring the omnibus spending bill down to defeat, said the House minority leader, Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri.</p>
        <p>''I'm very concerned that it can't pass,'' Mr. Gephardt said today.</p>
        <p>Mr. Obey, the Democrat who has the most authority over the spending bills in the House, said, ''You run the risk of it blowing up, because of the critical mass of people opposed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
