<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian Woes May Aid U.S. Emissions Goals</title>
    <meta content="Y01CLI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1096817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Information Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cushman, John H Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990401T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0DE1439F932A35757C0A96F958260" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian Woes May Aid U.S. Emissions Goals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cushman, John H Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Information Administration, Federal Govt's energy-forecasting agency, says US and other industrial countries may find it easier and cheaper than expected to comply with proposed treaty to fight global warming, largely because of reduced fuel consumption in Russia; since agreement on global warming allows international trading of pollution credits as way to control emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases emitted mainly by burning of fossil fuels, more of cuts that treaty seeks may come from former Soviet Union; US, world's leading source of greenhouse gases could meet treaty's targets without completely reversing its recent increases in emissions, which have grown with energy use as domestic economy has blossomed (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States and other industrial countries may find it easier and cheaper than expected to comply with a proposed treaty to fight global warming, thanks largely to reduced fuel consumption in Russia, the Government's energy-forecasting agency said today.</p>
        <p>Because the agreement on global warming allows international trading of pollution credits as a way to control emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases like those that come from burning fossil fuels, more of the cuts that the treaty seeks may come from the former Soviet Union and less from the United States, the Energy Information Administration said in its annual long-range forecast.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States and other industrial countries may find it easier and cheaper than expected to comply with a proposed treaty to fight global warming, thanks largely to reduced fuel consumption in Russia, the Government's energy-forecasting agency said today.</p>
        <p>Because the agreement on global warming allows international trading of pollution credits as a way to control emissions of heat-trapping greenhouse gases like those that come from burning fossil fuels, more of the cuts that the treaty seeks may come from the former Soviet Union and less from the United States, the Energy Information Administration said in its annual long-range forecast.</p>
        <p>That would mean that the United States, the world's leading source of greenhouse gases, could meet the treaty's targets without completely reversing its recent increases in emissions, which have grown with energy use as the domestic economy blossomed. But substantial reductions in emissions would still be needed.</p>
        <p>The agreement, negotiated in Kyoto, Japan, in 1997 and signed last year by the Clinton Administration, has not been ratified by the Senate, where it faces significant opposition from lawmakers who say it would be too costly and would cause disruptive cuts in energy use.</p>
        <p>The Kyoto Protocol calls for the United States to cut its emissions of greenhouse gases within 10 to 15 years to a level 7 percent below its emissions in 1990. Emissions in 1997 were 10 percent above the 1990 level and the energy agency has forecast that by 2010 they will be 33 percent above the 1990 level unless measures are imposed to reduce them.</p>
        <p>But even as the United States and some other countries continue to burn more fossil fuels and to emit more carbon dioxide, the main greenhouse gas, Russia and its neighbors are burning and emitting less than previously forecast, the agency said today.</p>
        <p>Under the treaty, countries that give off more greenhouse gases than the treaty allows may buy surplus reductions from countries that give off less than their targets.</p>
        <p>The energy agency said the continuing depression in Russia and other former Soviet states was holding down energy use and would probably produce a huge bubble of emissions credits by the time the treaty is supposed to come into force, between 2008 and 2012. The expected emissions of carbon dioxide in Eastern Europe and the former Soviet Union in the year 2010 are likely to be 13 percent lower than predicted last year, the new forecast said.</p>
        <p>These countries will have at least 374 million metric tons worth of carbon credits available to sell to other countries, it said. Last year, the agency forecast that these countries would have only 196 million metric tons of carbon credits. (Under the treaty, emissions of all greenhouse gases are tallied in units of carbon, one of the elements released when fossil fuels are burned.)</p>
        <p>For countries like the United States whose emissions are growing far beyond the limits set by the treaty, the change is significant.</p>
        <p>To meet the targets of the Kyoto Protocol, industrialized countries would need to eliminate about 822 million metric tons of carbon from their anticipated emissions.</p>
        <p>''If the industrialized nations that have agreed to carbon emissions caps can purchase these credits, this level of trading alone would allow their carbon emission levels to rise by an average of 7 percent over 1990 levels, and still meet the Protocol's average emissions target of 7 percent below 1990 levels,'' the energy agency said.</p>
        <p>Worldwide, the agency said, carbon emissions are expected to be 39 percent greater in 2010 than they were in 1990. While that is 4 percent less than the agency predicted last year, it suggests that the world as a whole is doing far less than needed to head off the risks of global warming.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
