<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spitzer and Pataki Dueling Over Environmental Mantle</title>
    <meta content="19SPIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1146513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot L (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E6D91439F93AA25753C1A96F958260" item-length="1637" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spitzer and Pataki Dueling Over Environmental Mantle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Atty Gen Eliot L Spitzer has lived up to his environmental campaign pledges in his first nine months in office, but in so doing, has invaded territory that for five years has largely been domain of Gov George E Pataki; turf battle surfaced recently, when Pataki released details of plan to cut power plant pollution; Spitzer simultaneously disclosed that he was making headway in investigation of possible violations of pollution rules at state's coal-fired plants; aides to two officials say that, over all, they are working well together; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One Monday last April, hundreds of representatives of New York's private environmental groups gathered in Albany for Earth Day Lobby Day, an annual meet-and-greet session with elected officials.</p>
        <p>In a packed auditorium, Eliot L. Spitzer, New York's new Attorney General, described his plans to use unconventional legal tactics to pursue polluters and to invigorate his office's environmental bureau, which had shrunk under his predecessor, Dennis C. Vacco. The crowd cheered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One Monday last April, hundreds of representatives of New York's private environmental groups gathered in Albany for Earth Day Lobby Day, an annual meet-and-greet session with elected officials.</p>
        <p>In a packed auditorium, Eliot L. Spitzer, New York's new Attorney General, described his plans to use unconventional legal tactics to pursue polluters and to invigorate his office's environmental bureau, which had shrunk under his predecessor, Dennis C. Vacco. The crowd cheered.</p>
        <p>When he added that he planned to work closely with Gov. George E. Pataki on some issues, there was a smattering of boos. ''Now, now,'' Mr. Spitzer said, smiling, ''he's my client.''</p>
        <p>The complicated dynamics in that auditorium foreshadowed what has since turned out to be a prickly but productive interplay on environmental issues between the state's Republican chief executive and its Democratic top lawyer.</p>
        <p>In his first nine months in office, according to a variety of environmental groups, Mr. Spitzer has lived up to environmental campaign pledges that he outlined in commercials showing him walking the shores of the Hudson River deploring its stain of pollution from General Electric factories.</p>
        <p>But in so doing, he has invaded territory that for five years has largely been the domain of Mr. Pataki, who, despite a few detractors in the environmental movement, has built an impressive reputation as a conservationist.</p>
        <p>The turf battle surfaced most recently last Wednesday, when Mr. Pataki released details of an ambitious plan to cut power plant pollution. Simultaneously, Mr. Spitzer disclosed that he was making headway in an investigation of possible violations of pollution rules at the state's coal-fired plants. Neither camp was quick to fill the other in on its plans.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Pataki's own announcement, according to a variety of state environmental officials, was partly meant to parry a move made by Mr. Spitzer last month, in which he revealed that he was preparing to sue 17 out-of-state power plants that sully New York's air with wind-blown plumes of pollution.</p>
        <p>Aides to the two officials say that, over all, they are working well together, adding that a little dynamic tension was not a bad thing.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Spitzer said in an interview that his pollution-fighting efforts and those of Mr. Pataki ''fit together wonderfully.''</p>
        <p>''If there is some element of competition -- and I don't see it that way,'' Mr. Spitzer said, ''well, look, it's generating great policy.''</p>
        <p>Michael McKeon, a spokesman for the Governor, declined to comment other than to say that Mr. Pataki and Mr. Spitzer were working ''pretty well'' together.</p>
        <p>From his first days in office last January, Mr. Spitzer seemed intent on pursuing environmental cases. In contrast, Mr. Vacco had been criticized by environmental groups for mainly taking on an environmental case only after it had been referred for prosecution by lawyers at the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>A few days after he took office, Mr. Spitzer met with the environmental staff, encouraging its members to think creatively and try to bring new kinds of cases against polluters. ''At the Environmental Protection Bureau, there was a palpable sense of relief, a feeling that limitations were being taken off,'' Mr. Spitzer said. ''I said we are here to bring the cases you can conjure, cases that will perhaps push the law, that will test new theories of our ability to be interventionist.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's approach was reflected in the people he hired.</p>
        <p>To run his environmental bureau, which has 35 lawyers and 7 staff scientists, he recruited Peter H. Lehner, 40, a seasoned environmental lawyer at the Natural Resources Defense Council, a large private conservation group.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer, who is 40, had no experience with environmental cases in his previous work as a lawyer and assistant district attorney in Manhattan, he said, and so felt compelled to find an environmental adviser to help shape policy.</p>
        <p>In a move that irritated many people in Governor Pataki's office, Mr. Spitzer chose Judith Enck, 39, a longtime environmental lobbyist in Albany who had been a persistent and outspoken critic of Mr. Pataki's policies. Several people in the Pataki administration, one of whom described Ms. Enck as ''a bomb thrower,'' said the Governor's staff was incredulous that she had been picked to shape Mr. Spitzer's environmental agenda.</p>
        <p>Ms. Enck said that it was difficult for her to consider joining government after so many years of criticizing it, but that she found that she could work for Mr. Spitzer, who came to public office without the baggage that weighs down most elected officials.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Spitzer used family wealth to finance most of his campaign, she said, ''he's the first statewide elected official I know who is beholden to no one.''</p>
        <p>Since the spring, the list of environmental cases has steadily grown. Many were referred by the Department of Environmental Conservation -- the traditional means by which environmental violations are prosecuted by the state -- but Mr. Spitzer has also been pursuing leads and building cases on his own as well.</p>
        <p>They range from small-scale attacks on companies that are believed to have polluted neighborhoods to wide-ranging forays against the giant energy companies whose coal-fired plants are thought to contribute to the sterilization of Adirondack lakes and the smog that cloaks much of the state each summer.</p>
        <p>The environmental bureau also dusted off a rarely used legal weapon -- public nuisance laws -- to go after some companies that were creating chronic pollution problems. This was a tactic last employed by two other Democratic attorneys general, G. Oliver Koppell and Robert Abrams, who both served during the terms of a Democratic Governor, Mario M. Cuomo.</p>
        <p>In such cases, the attorney general does not have to move in lock step with actions by the state environmental conservation agency.</p>
        <p>''If D.E.C. says there's no violation, it's not like we're going to pack our bags and go away,'' Mr. Lehner said.</p>
        <p>This philosophy has alarmed some representatives of the business world, who say the parallel legal actions can confront a business owner with an unfair kind of environmental double jeopardy.</p>
        <p>''This raises uncertainty about when you know you're really in compliance with statutes and regulations,'' said Kenneth J. Pokalsky, the director of environmental programs for the Business Council of New York State, an Albany lobbying organization representing industry. Even if a company passes muster with the state environmental agency, he said, ''it could still be subject to state-initiated cases.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer has not restricted environmental litigation to private companies.</p>
        <p>In May, when Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani prepared to auction off city-owned lots that had sprouted popular community gardens, Mr. Spitzer joined in a suit against New York City, contending that it had failed to assess the environmental impact of the land sale under the State Environmental Quality Review Act, known by the acronym Seqra.</p>
        <p>A State Supreme Court justice in Brooklyn delayed the sale, and the city swiftly shifted to negotiations with environmental groups, finally selling the disputed lots to groups that would preserve the gardens. ''That was the first time the state had ever sued the city for a violation of Seqra, and it worked,'' Ms. Enck said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's awareness of the garden issue came from that lobbying day in Albany in April, when a woman from a city environmental group, dressed as a flower, asked him about his stance on the controversy, Ms. Enck recalled. ''That led to us getting involved,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Friction between Mr. Spitzer and the Pataki administration has been greatest over the issue of pollution from power plants. Early this year, Mr. Lehner broached the idea of pursuing lawsuits directly against individual owners of coal-burning power plants in up-wind states, and hired independent energy experts to pore over company and government records to find evidence of violations.</p>
        <p>By September, the accumulated evidence was sufficiently compelling that Mr. Spitzer announced plans to sue the owners of 17 plants to force cleanups.</p>
        <p>Recently, attorneys general of several New England states, as well as officials from Toronto -- all of which are affected by pollution from some of the power plants -- discussed with Mr. Spitzer the possibility of joining in the lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who had essentially owned the acid rain and smog issues in New York, has been forced to make room for a newcomer. But Mr. Spitzer insists that their work is complementary, not competitive.</p>
        <p>''Whatever the Governor does through regulations, action still needs to be taken against law breakers, and that's what we're doing,'' Mr. Spitzer said.</p>
        <p>Next on Mr. Spitzer's agenda is General Electric, which is locked in a battle with the Federal Environmental Protection Agency over how to deal with the PCB's, polychlorinated biphenyls, left in the Hudson River by two of the company's factories.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer said his lawyers were preparing to open a new legal front this fall against the company, perhaps using tactics similar to those used successfully in recent years against big tobacco companies.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, Mr. Spitzer met with top executives and lawyers for General Electric, in a meeting that was the equivalent of the weighing-in sessions held by boxers before they enter the ring for a prizefight.</p>
        <p>The top lawyer for the company, Stephen D. Ramsey, a former Justice Department official, presented a firm, spirited defense of the company's actions, Mr. Spitzer said. But Mr. Spitzer said he was unfazed.</p>
        <p>''I like lawyers like Steve,'' Mr. Spitzer said. ''They're aggressive and firm and fun to joust with.''</p>
        <p>That bout is expected to begin early next month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
