<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Summary of the Major Actions of the Legislature's 222d Session</title>
    <meta content="22LEGI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19990824T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1132483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Clifford J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E7D91338F931A1575BC0A96F958260" item-length="3021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Summary of the Major Actions of the Legislature's 222d Session</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY and RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard; Levy, Clifford J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Summary of major actions by New York State Legislature during 222d session that ended August 6; photos; details of bills approved or rejected on matters of budget, crime and justice, education, taxes, health care, consumer affairs, environment and energy, transportation, welfare and families, government and ethics and business and labor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Legislature has weathered some tumultuous years, but the 222d session left even Albany veterans shaking their heads at the partisan fisticuffs and sullen standoffs, the tendency to hunker down on routine matters. When the session finally concluded nearly two months late with the Assembly recessing around 3 A.M. on Aug. 6, members leaving the chambers seemed relieved that it was over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York Legislature has weathered some tumultuous years, but the 222d session left even Albany veterans shaking their heads at the partisan fisticuffs and sullen standoffs, the tendency to hunker down on routine matters. When the session finally concluded nearly two months late with the Assembly recessing around 3 A.M. on Aug. 6, members leaving the chambers seemed relieved that it was over.</p>
        <p>In truth, it wasn't. The last hours were marked by the same disarray that was apparent all year: the traditional down-to-the-wire agreements between the Governor and the Legislature could not be immediately translated into laws because leaders of the Republican-controlled State Senate had ended the session in frustration several hours earlier, while the Assembly continued meeting. The Senate is now scheduled to approve those bills in a short special session in the fall.</p>
        <p>To many lawmakers, it was an exasperating coda to an unsatisfying and unproductive session, one that began with big hopes but yielded a budget that was tied for the latest in state history. Relations between Gov. George E. Pataki, a Republican, and the Democrats in control of the Assembly were more prickly than ever, and in the spring, the budget stalemate essentially thwarted progress on everything else for weeks.</p>
        <p>There was one major issue that drew consensus during that time. Legislative leaders of both parties, eager to win the favor of voters in a suburban special election, swiftly and unexpectedly repealed the decades-old tax on commuters who work in New York City.</p>
        <p>As the session wound down, lawmakers agreed to stiffen penalties for stalking and for blocking abortion clinics, expand the state's database of DNA specimens from criminals, and allow the construction of new power plants. But talks on many important matters, from revamping the state's drug laws to writing new rules for polluted industrial sites, were abandoned.</p>
        <p>Of the 8,807 bills introduced in the Assembly, 1,606 passed, officials said. In the Senate, 6,117 bills were introduced, and 1,432 passed. A total of 715 bills passed both houses, a relatively low figure compared with recent years. Of those, the Governor has signed 409 and vetoed 13. The remaining ones are awaiting his decision on whether to sign.</p>
        <p>The following were the major actions of the session:</p>
        <p>The Budget</p>
        <p>The Legislature completed passage of the 1999-2000 budget in the early morning hours of Aug. 4, tying the record for tardiness set in 1997 by going 126 days into the fiscal year.</p>
        <p>But the delay was misleading. Once the Governor agreed to negotiate actively with legislative leaders, it took just a month to settle the outlines of the budget, and another month to hammer out the details, draft it and pass it. And while a record for lateness would suggest a difficult budget filled with sacrifice, the final $73.3 billion package gave everyone enough to claim victory.</p>
        <p>Overall, the budget raises spending 3.8 percent, though the part generated from state taxes will rise more slowly. The increase is larger than the Governor had wanted, though still modest for such flush times, and considerably smaller than what the Democrats had sought.</p>
        <p>At Mr. Pataki's insistence, the budget spends none of the $1.8 billion surplus that accumulated during the last fiscal year. Instead, it will be salted away to ease the way for tax cuts that are to take effect next year and the year after.</p>
        <p>The Governor also succeeded in nearly doubling spending on child-care subsidies for the poor, to more than $800 million, an effort that is seen as crucial to helping parents move from welfare to work.</p>
        <p>The Legislature beat back the Governor's proposed cuts to Medicaid and education, and the budget even raises aid to local school districts by more than $900 million, a record sum, to a total of more than $12 billion. The Assembly Democrats made sure that it also expanded a program to provide prekindergarten classes and reduce class sizes in the early grades.</p>
        <p>The basic outlines of the budget are about what the Senate Republicans had proposed all along, and they also secured more than $400 million a year in new tax cuts that they had sought. The budget also reflects more than $1 billion in tax cuts that were passed in previous years, and are now going into effect.</p>
        <p>Crime and Justice</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Makes it a felony, rather than a misdemeanor, to cause extreme pain or death to a domestic animal, raising the maximum penalty to two years in prison and a $5,000 fine, rather than one year and $1,000.</p>
        <p>Requires the Parole Board to keep the identity of crime victims confidential in certain instances.</p>
        <p>Makes it a crime to make a false bomb report, punishable by having to pay restitution up to $10,000.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would ban ''bar crawls,'' organized bar-hopping events.</p>
        <p>EXPECTED TO PASS BOTH HOUSES</p>
        <p>Would mandate the collection of DNA samples from about 50 percent of all people convicted of felonies, up from 8 percent now, and from about 100,000 people now in prison, on probation or on parole, for entry into a computer database and use in solving future crimes. (The Assembly has passed this bill and the Senate has committed to passing it at a special session later this year.)</p>
        <p>Would make it a crime to stalk a person, defining stalking as following or harassing with intent to cause harm, with penalties up to seven years in prison. (The Assembly has passed this bill and the Senate has committed to passing it at a special session later this year.)</p>
        <p>Would make it a crime to block access to an abortion clinic and increase penalties for injuring clinic workers. (The Assembly has passed this bill and the Senate has committed to passing it at a special session later this year.)</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have softened some of the severest drug possession penalties under the state's Rockefeller-era drug laws, while providing for more treatment of people arrested on drug charges.</p>
        <p>Would have strengthened several of the state's sex crime laws, including: imposing a mandatory sentence of 25 years to life in prison for anyone convicted for the second time of a sex crime against a person under the age of 15; making it a separate crime to use ''date rape'' drugs to commit rape or sodomy, and prohibiting the granting of bail to any person arrested who has a history of sex crimes against children.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed prosecutors, like defendants, to appeal sentences and decisions on bail.</p>
        <p>Would have imposed a wide range of restrictions on gun possession and sale, including requiring that lost or stolen guns be reported to the police and that a person complete a gun safety course before obtaining a firearms license.</p>
        <p>Would have increased penalties for a range of violent crimes committed by juveniles.</p>
        <p>Would have simplified the state's multilayered court system.</p>
        <p>Would have eliminated discretionary parole by ending the practice of sentencing felons to a range of time in prison, replacing such sentences with specific terms.</p>
        <p>Would have authorized construction of a new maximum-security prison.</p>
        <p>Would have created a category of ''bias crimes,'' raising the penalties for various crimes when the victim has been chosen on the basis of race, ethnicity, sex or sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed the state to commit sex offenders to mental hospitals for an indefinite period after their prison terms are completed.</p>
        <p>Would have raised fees paid by local governments for court-appointed lawyers who represent indigent criminal defendants  to $100 an hour from $40.</p>
        <p>Would have toughened the standard for drunken driving to a blood alcohol level of 0.08 percent from the current 0.10 percent.</p>
        <p>Would have provided automatic revocation of a driver's license for five years for a person convicted the third time in 10 years of driving while intoxicated or impaired by drugs.</p>
        <p>Would have created the crime of ''identity theft'' for people who use other people's names and credit information, and would have required financial-services companies to notify customers that they are selling or transferring information about customers to someone else.</p>
        <p>Would have required that prison inmates make a $7 co-payment for medical treatment.</p>
        <p>Would have limited the ability of inmates to file lawsuits.</p>
        <p>Would have required New York City police officers to reside in the city, with the same requirement imposed in certain other localities.</p>
        <p>Would have created new county and family court judges.</p>
        <p>Education  LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Allows certain communities to break away from existing school districts and form their own districts, specifically aimed at Kiryas Joel, a Hasidic enclave in Orange County.</p>
        <p>Continues to exempt the New York City School Construction Authority from rules that require government agencies to split most construction jobs among many contractors.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would overhaul special-education programs to reduce incentives to local districts to classify students as learning-disabled.</p>
        <p>Would raise to 17 from 16 the age at which a person can legally drop out of school.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have relaxed new requirement of the Board of Regents that students pass Regents examinations to earn high school diplomas.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed teachers to expel persistently troublesome students from their classrooms.</p>
        <p>Taxes</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Eliminates New York City's income tax on commuters who work in the city but live elsewhere. Applied only to commuters living in New York State, but a court subsequently ruled that it must apply to out-of-state-commuters as well. Estimated savings to taxpayers: $360 million a year.</p>
        <p>Allows Nassau County to impose a 1 percent tax on all property sales, until Jan. 31, 2001. Estimated cost to taxpayers: $70 million.</p>
        <p>Reduces the corporate-profits tax on banks and insurance companies to a top rate of 7.5 percent from 9 percent. Estimated savings to businesses: $100 million a year.</p>
        <p>Raises by 25 percent the state's earned income tax credit for the working poor, particularly those with children, to a maximum of $939 a year. Estimated savings to taxpayers: $125 million a year.</p>
        <p>Extends a property tax break for the owners of 280,000 co-operative apartments and condominiums in New York City that averages almost $600 per unit. Estimated savings to taxpayers: $166 million a year.</p>
        <p>Postpones from Dec. 1, 1999, to March 1, 2000, the elimination of the sales tax on clothes, up to $110 per item. Estimated cost to taxpayers: $100 million.</p>
        <p>Suspends the sales tax on clothes, up to $500 per item, for a week in September 1999, and another week in February 2000. Estimated savings to taxpayers: $50 million.</p>
        <p>Health Care  AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would allow a judge to compel a mentally ill person with a history of violence to receive treatment, including involuntary confinement, if such action is requested by a family member, doctor or roommate.</p>
        <p>Would require that all residents and employees of nursing homes receive influenza vaccinations.</p>
        <p>Would require that children receive the hepatitis B vaccine by seventh grade.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have continued the state's system of imposing charges on hospital bills to finance hospital care for the indigent, and to help pay for the education of doctors at teaching hospitals. (The system, which expires at the end of the year, will be taken up in a special legislative session later this year.)</p>
        <p>Would have greatly expanded the state's anti-tobacco advertising and education program.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed patients to sue health-maintenance organizations for denying coverage of treatments.</p>
        <p>Would have created a state registry to provide consumers information about any doctor, including educational background, malpractice history and any disciplinary actions.</p>
        <p>Consumer Affairs  LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Requires that used mattresses be labeled as such with prominent tags.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would require that all automated teller machines display on screen any charges that will be assessed for use of the machine.</p>
        <p>Would create an office within the State Department of Health to advise people who are having problems with managed-care companies.</p>
        <p>Would allow anyone aged 62 or older to terminate a housing lease without penalty when a medical condition leaves the tenant unable to live independently, and the tenant is moving in with a family member.</p>
        <p>Would renew for one year the law against ticket-scalping.</p>
        <p>Would renew for two years the law allowing thousands of lofts, mostly in Manhattan, to be used as dwellings.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have required health insurance companies to pay for fertility treatments.</p>
        <p>Would have required health insurance companies, under policies that cover prescription drugs, to cover prescribed contraceptives as well.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed car rental companies to sell customers collision damage waivers, insurance policies covering damage to the rental cars, and would have eliminated the cap on the renter's liability for damage to the car.</p>
        <p>Would have required credit-reporting agencies to provide a free credit report to any resident, as often as once a year, upon request.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed for-profit credit counseling, a practice now outlawed.</p>
        <p>Would have imposed several limitations on consumer lawsuits and damage awards.</p>
        <p>Environment and Energy  LEGISLATION VETOED</p>
        <p>Would have allowed cities to ban the use of the pesticide Avitrol, which is used to poison pigeons.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Directs the creation of a statewide cancer map, the first in the nation, matching types and frequency of cancers with known sources of air and water pollution.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would allow the Public Service Commission, appointed by the Governor, to issue environmental permits for new power plants; no state agency is now authorized to do so.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have refinanced the state's Superfund program for cleaning toxic contamination sites, which is nearly out of money, by imposing new fees on industry.</p>
        <p>Would have prohibited New York industries from selling or trading ''pollution credits,'' earned by reducing airborne emissions, in such a way that they would end up being acquired by industries in the Midwest that contribute to the state's acid rain.</p>
        <p>Would have required that neighbors be notified 48 hours in advance of the application of pesticides to any property by a commercial firm.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed the construction of cellular phone towers without environmental review.</p>
        <p>Transportation  LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Requires school buses to be operated with headlights and taillights on, day or night.</p>
        <p>Allows the Department of Motor Vehicles to deny registration to a prospective school bus operating company when it appears that the same operator had a registration revoked while doing business under a different name.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would allow New York City to reduce speed limits to as low as 15 miles per hour, from the current minimum of 25 miles per hour, on streets where speed bumps and other traffic-slowing devices are used.</p>
        <p>Would allow mentally disabled people to ride New York City subways and buses at half-fare, as physically disabled people now do.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have allowed a speed limit of 65 miles per hour, rather than 55, on some Long Island highways.</p>
        <p>Would have required bus drivers and motorists involved in accidents with buses to submit to a breath test.</p>
        <p>Would have required the mandatory revocation of the driver's license of a bus driver who tested positive in a random drug or alcohol test.</p>
        <p>Welfare and Families  LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Brings New York into compliance with Federal law on adoptions; includes requirements that ''permanency planning'' hearings be held for foster children every year and that the state establish a system for checking to see if prospective adoptive or foster parents have criminal records.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have increased penalties for failure to pay child support.</p>
        <p>Would have raised the amount that parents receiving welfare can collect in child support payments without losing their welfare benefits.</p>
        <p>Would have created the crime of unlawfully providing a child with a large quantity of alcoholic beverages.</p>
        <p>Would have made it a crime to do body piercing on people under 18, with the exception of ear piercing.</p>
        <p>Would have prohibited the sale of laser pointers to people under 18.</p>
        <p>Government and Ethics  LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Makes it easier for Presidential candidates to get on New York's primary ballots by reducing the number of voter signatures candidates must collect on petitions.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would speed disbursement of state aid to municipalities.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have extended four years the state's law governing lobbyists. (A more stringent proposal is expected to be taken up at a special session later this year.)</p>
        <p>Would have imposed significant new campaign-finance limitations, including a ban on ''soft money'' contributions to party committees and lower ceilings on individual contributions to campaigns.</p>
        <p>Would have provided for government financing of political campaigns, linked to campaign spending limits.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed legislative committee chairmen to call a joint Senate-Assembly conference committee when both houses pass substantially similar bills, rather than limiting the power to call conference committees to the leaders of the two houses.</p>
        <p>Would have provided for television coverage of Senate and Assembly sessions.</p>
        <p>Business and Labor  LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Authorizes the creation of trademarks for use in marketing agricultural products as being from New York State, and as being from particular regions of the state.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would allow the New York City corrections officers' union to take millions of dollars a year out of the city's pension fund for distribution to its members.</p>
        <p>Would allow state prison guards with heart conditions to retire with full, tax-free pensions.</p>
        <p>Would extend authorization for the Quick Draw lottery game until March 31, 2001.</p>
        <p>Would make electronic signatures legally binding.</p>
        <p>Would require that boxing judges disclose their scoring after each round.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have created a voluntary system to allow merchants to use devices that scan driver's licenses to verify the age of people buying tobacco and alcohol.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed New York to join Powerball, the multistate lottery game.</p>
        <p>Would have attempted to limit the ability of plaintiffs to file lawsuits for damages and reduced the potential for punitive damages.</p>
        <p>Would have prohibited banks from charging more than a $15 penalty for returned checks.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 24, 1999, Tuesday  A report on Sunday summarizing the New York State Legislature's 222d session misstated the fate of two bills. One allows merchants to use devices that scan driver's licenses to verify the ages of people buying tobacco and alcohol; it passed and awaits the Governor's signature. The other limits the ability of inmates to file lawsuits; it passed and is now law.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 24, 1999, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A report on Sunday summarizing the New York State Legislature's 222d session misstated the fate of two bills. One allows merchants to use devices that scan driver's licenses to verify the ages of people buying tobacco and alcohol; it passed and awaits the Governor's signature. The other limits the ability of inmates to file lawsuits; it passed and is now law.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
