<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Some See Rusting Factories, Government Sees a Source of Solar Energy</title>
    <meta content="Y04SOLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1128252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Energy Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richardson, Bill (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Solar Energy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E7DE1630F937A3575BC0A96F958260" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Some See Rusting Factories, Government Sees a Source of Solar Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Energy Sec Bill Richardson will be in Chicago on Aug 4 to unveil first step in project to use solar panels at polluted sites to make much-needed electricity without disturbing buried contaminants (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Energy Department has a new idea for what to do with derelict, polluted urban industrial properties that no one wants to pay to clean up: cover them with solar panels.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Bill Richardson will unveil the first step in a project to use solar panels at polluted sites to make much-needed electricity without disturbing buried contaminants on Wednesday in Chicago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Energy Department has a new idea for what to do with derelict, polluted urban industrial properties that no one wants to pay to clean up: cover them with solar panels.</p>
        <p>Energy Secretary Bill Richardson will unveil the first step in a project to use solar panels at polluted sites to make much-needed electricity without disturbing buried contaminants on Wednesday in Chicago.</p>
        <p>The department, the city and the local electric utility, Commonwealth Edison, will announce that they have induced a solar panel manufacturer to set up shop on a 17-acre former dump site. The city and utility have promised to buy $8 million worth of solar panels, some of which, department officials say, will cover derelict sites and feed energy into the local electric grid.</p>
        <p>''It's going from the worst old stuff to the best clean stuff,'' Mr. Richardson said in a telephone interview. ''It's a win-win for everyone, because it addresses job creation, air quality and contaminated sites.''</p>
        <p>The panels produce electricity with no pollution, officials say. Chicago plans to use some of its cells to light parks, municipal buildings and transit stations.</p>
        <p>Panels installed on contaminated sites can be trucked away and set up elsewhere if a better use is found for the land, officials involved in the project said.</p>
        <p>The Energy Department is discussing similar projects in Los Angeles, Stamford, Conn., Washington and other cities. It is also working with the Regional Plan Association in New York to look for suitable sites in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut. And it is involved in a study of whether a closed landfill in a treeless area of Babylon, N.Y., would be a good place for windmills.</p>
        <p>The Chicago site is on North Sacramento Avenue, on the West Side, and was used for years for demolition material and other debris. The city closed down the operator, Sacramento Crushing, in 1996 because of environmental violations, and later seized the property and spent $9 million in the last 18 months on cleanup. The city has cleaned up a building on the site and is giving the solar manufacturer, the Spire Corporation, of Bedford, Mass., a low lease rate on 5,000 square feet.</p>
        <p>''There are all sorts of benefits for operating there, from tax advantages to rent advantages to labor cost advantages,'' said Roger D. Little, president and chief executive of Spire.</p>
        <p>Mr. Little said of the site, ''it's not like a toxic waste site, but it's probably something you don't want to build a nursery school on.''</p>
        <p>Environmental laws generally require a cleanup before the land can be re-used, which sometimes dooms such sites to abandonment, but Energy Department officials say they are confident that environmental regulators will allow re-use for solar energy production if the use does not disturb the contaminants.</p>
        <p>Dan W. Reicher, the assistant secretary for renewable energy, said that in places where the soil was contaminated with toxic chemicals -- which is true in hundreds of thousands of acres of ''brownfields'' in cities around the country -- installing racks of solar panels did not require digging in the dirt. Once erected, the panels require minimal human intervention, he said.</p>
        <p>Solar panels would be a good use for sites in the Superfund waste cleanup program, he said. In addition, department officials say, putting solar cells in urban settings bypasses bottlenecks in the power distribution system by generating supplemental electricity where it is needed.</p>
        <p>The Chicago plant, which Spire will own, can produce one megawatt a year of panels if operated one shift a day, but can make three megawatts if operated around the clock, Mr. Little said. If it does, it will employ 100 people. It builds 2-foot by 4-foot panels, each of which produces 50 watts in full sunlight, enough to run a single 50-watt light bulb. A typical installation would be 60 panels, or 3 kilowatts, enough to run an average house, he said, and would cost about $30,000, including the equipment to convert the electricity to standard household voltage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
