<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baby's Death Leads To a Foundation To Aid Other Infants</title>
    <meta content="11SIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1099210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sudden Infant Death Syndrome</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Considering Alexander Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williamson-Noble, Hugh</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williamson-Noble, Esmeralda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spear, Linda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sudden Infant Death Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D81738F932A25757C0A96F958260" item-length="1555" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baby's Death Leads To a Foundation To Aid Other Infants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA SPEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Spear, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>IRVINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Considering Alexander Foundation in Irvington, NY, founded by Esmeralda and Hugh Williamson-Noble, whose 7-month-old son died of Sudden Infant Death Syndrome in September 1995 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOMETIME in the early morning hours of Sept. 17, 1995, a 7-month-old boy, Alexander Williamson-Noble, died of SIDS. He was survived by his parents, his twin brother, Robert, an older sister, Florentina, and another brother, Andrew. What makes Alexander more than a statistic is that in his death, he became the driving force for the Considering Alexander Foundation, started by his parents, Esmeralda and Hugh Williamson-Noble.</p>
        <p>''No one asked if we were willing to give up our child,'' Mrs. Williamson-Noble said recently. ''Alexander was just stolen from us. Since crib death wrenched our son from us, we've vowed to go after this killer, day after day, until it is stamped off the face of the earth.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOMETIME in the early morning hours of Sept. 17, 1995, a 7-month-old boy, Alexander Williamson-Noble, died of SIDS. He was survived by his parents, his twin brother, Robert, an older sister, Florentina, and another brother, Andrew. What makes Alexander more than a statistic is that in his death, he became the driving force for the Considering Alexander Foundation, started by his parents, Esmeralda and Hugh Williamson-Noble.</p>
        <p>''No one asked if we were willing to give up our child,'' Mrs. Williamson-Noble said recently. ''Alexander was just stolen from us. Since crib death wrenched our son from us, we've vowed to go after this killer, day after day, until it is stamped off the face of the earth.''</p>
        <p>The couple met in London when Mr. Williamson-Noble was an executive for Trafalgar House and Mrs. Williamson-Noble worked in hotel administration.</p>
        <p>All four children were born in England, and the family relocated to New York when the twins were 11 weeks old. ''It took us all a while to adapt to everything new,'' Mrs. Williamson-Noble said. ''But we finally adjusted. The older children began to thrive in their new school, and the twins brought us all a great deal of joy.''</p>
        <p>On the morning of Alexander's death, everyone had slept later than usual. ''When we realized the time, Hugh went downstairs to warm the babies' bottles and I went straight to the nursery,'' Mrs. Williamson-Noble said. ''Much to my surprise, Robert was the only one crying. Alexander appeared to be still asleep, and I remember thinking, how strange.''</p>
        <p>In the dim early morning light, Mrs. Williamson-Noble saw that Alexander was completely covered by his blanket; only his legs were partly visible. ''A wave of panic overtook me, and I grabbed the blanket and pulled it from him,'' she said. ''Hugh had just come in with the bottles of formula, and he saw the look of fear on my face. He reached for Alexander, and I asked him if something was wrong. He said he wasn't sure. That's when I knew. All I can recall at that point was that I screamed like a wounded animal. Holding Robert, I ran as fast as I could to the phone in our bedroom and dialed 911.''</p>
        <p>The parents also called friends living nearby who came right over to be with the older children. As the paramedics from the Irvington Volunteer Ambulance Corps arrived, Mrs. Williamson-Noble became aware of a lot of people in uniform. Later she realized that they were police officers who were there to assess the problem and accompany the paramedics and the baby to the Community Hospital at Dobbs Ferry. By the time the parents arrived at the hospital, the paramedics and the emergency room staff held out little hope for Alexander.</p>
        <p>''I begged everyone not to give up,'' Mrs. Williamson-Noble said.  ''Parents are supposed to die before their children, not the other way around, but when the doctor who was doing his best to save our baby returned to tell me that Alexander had died of SIDS, probably hours before we found him, I hadn't even heard the word before. He told me that it was Sudden Infant Death Syndrome -- known in England as Cot Death -- an infant fatality with no apparent cause and no relationship to his care. The twins were born perfect -- six pounds each -- and thrived every day. I had cared for them, kept them safe, and now one of them was dead.''</p>
        <p>An autopsy followed, which confirmed the cause of death, and the family celebrated a Mass of Angels, instead of planning a conventional funeral. Within days, the family began planning the foundation. As chairwoman of the Considering Alexander SIDS Foundation, Mrs. Williamson-Noble has shored up support for a Windflower Ball -- so named because the windflower, or anemone, is evanescent -- only in bloom for a short time.</p>
        <p>At the event, Sotheby's will direct  live and silent auctions featuring items, including a Land Rover, donated by businesses and individuals.  Mrs. Williamson-Noble has received items from Prince Charles, Robert F. Kennedy Jr. and Robert Redford. She has also got help from two SIDS researchers involved in studies financed in part by the foundation, and she is active in other marketing activities. In recent months, she devised a thermometer, which is given to parents of newborns at hospitals. It displays room temperature and offers guidelines for reducing the risk of SIDS.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mrs. Williamson-Noble and the foundation board set up a SIDS hot line at the Children's Hospital at Westchester Medical Center, supported by members of the pediatric pulmonology department at New York Medical College Center. Volunteers answer the phone around the clock, steering callers to grief counselors and support groups.</p>
        <p>Dr. Allen J. Dozor, chief of pediatric pulmonology at New York Medical College, said members of his department have spoken to as many as 20 families a year who have lost a child to SIDS or have children with apnea (interrupted breathing) who have been resuscitated. ''In my belief, SIDS is the most horrendous thing that happens to young families,'' he said. ''The suddenness and lack of explanation for the death leaves mothers, fathers and siblings with unadulterated pain, unnecessary guilt and frustration. Family members never get over it.''</p>
        <p>What further complicates the matter is the sometimes accusatory manner in which family members are treated by police officers, medical examiners, neighbors, friends and the press. ''Although we didn't deal with any outside pressure or suspicion from the coroner, police or the press,'' Mrs. Williamson-Noble said, ''we were all just a mass of pain, anger, sadness, fear and guilt -- the guilt was the hardest, since there was nothing we had done to attach to it.''</p>
        <p>Dr. William P. Fifer, who is on the staff of the New York State Psychiatric Institute and a professor of pediatric psychology at Columbia University, said: ''We surmise that some babies are made vulnerable by some form of prenatal injury of which the mother is almost never aware. This problem may immediately affect the neurological or cardiovascular system of the fetus or have long-term effects. It is these children, we believe, that are at increased risk for SIDS.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fifer's interest in finding new ways to assess infants' risk of neurological deficits led to his seeking funds from the National Institutes of Health for a grant to study this issue.  ''Our work delves into how a baby's heart and respiration rate change in response to sounds, temperature and movement,'' he said. ''We look at chemo receptors to the environment and whether a baby processes carbon dioxide and oxygen effectively. With our findings, we hope to better assess which children are most at risk for SIDS and prevent what was once inevitable.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fifer's study extends to American Indians who live in Aberdeen, S.D. Members of several tribes in that region report five to six times the average rate of SIDS and have helped investigators identify reasons for the deaths. ''Our study has been in place for five years, and our statistics confirm some existing suppositions regarding the cause of crib death,'' Dr. Fifer said. ''With an extension of the grant and further investigation, we expect to get more answers.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fifer's research indicates that children who are put to sleep on their abdomen are at higher risk than those children put to bed face up. Another characteristic is that children who are layered by too many clothes or blankets have temperature fluctuations that can lead to SIDS. Smoking during the pregnancy by either or both parents and second-hand smoke in the household after a child is born further increases risk.</p>
        <p>Because these factors have been identified and the public has been told about them, Dr. Fifer says the incidence of SIDS has been reduced by half. ''Personally, and perhaps selfishly, I'm so glad my own children made it through the vulnerable period in the first year of life, but just as important is that I want our work to insure that others don't have to endure what the Williamson-Noble family has suffered.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Williamson-Noble reported that there are 12 SIDS deaths a day in the United States. Dr. Dozor said: ''Our role as medical professionals has been to treat and stamp out illness, but just as important is our role in research and education that leads to prevention. We're very pleased that the Westchester Medical Center has been heavily involved in creating new services like the SIDS hot line that will not only treat the illnesses of children but help the families who struggle to nurture and protect their children in every way.''</p>
        <p>The Windflower Ball will be held Friday at the Union League Club in Manhattan. The talk show host Meredith Vieira is co-chairwoman and the television meteorologist Storm Field is co-chairman. Further information is available by getting in touch with the Considering Alexander SIDS Foundation at 591-4177 or at Post Office Box 3, Ardsley-on-Hudson, N.Y. 10503. Those wanting to reach the SIDS hot line should call the hot line nurse, Madeline Heydendael, at 654-3922.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
