<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Memo; Gore Shows Strengths in California</title>
    <meta content="Y20GOR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1139275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Altos (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Willie L Jr (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Tipper</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE0DE1E3CF933A1575AC0A96F958260" item-length="1074" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Memo; Gore Shows Strengths in California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Sept. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore receives enthusiastic reception in two-day campaign swing through California; photo of Gore with Mayor Willie L Brown Jr in San Francisco; photo of Tipper Gore at Los Altos fund-raiser (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is sometimes overlooked in the Bill Bradley buzz from Washington, but Vice President Al Gore is a formidable candidate for President.</p>
        <p>He showed it on a trip Thursday and Friday, exciting audiences of Hispanic business executives in San Diego, environmental enthusiasts in Los Angeles, Hollywood donors, high school students in Santa Monica and Fresno, gay and lesbian leaders and then bricklayers here, and finally Silicon Valley contributors in Los Altos, although the highlight of that last event might have been Tipper Gore sitting in on drums with a band descended from the Grateful Dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is sometimes overlooked in the Bill Bradley buzz from Washington, but Vice President Al Gore is a formidable candidate for President.</p>
        <p>He showed it on a trip Thursday and Friday, exciting audiences of Hispanic business executives in San Diego, environmental enthusiasts in Los Angeles, Hollywood donors, high school students in Santa Monica and Fresno, gay and lesbian leaders and then bricklayers here, and finally Silicon Valley contributors in Los Altos, although the highlight of that last event might have been Tipper Gore sitting in on drums with a band descended from the Grateful Dead.</p>
        <p>Using a wireless lapel microphone that enabled him to stray from a lectern, Mr. Gore seemed relaxed when he discarded a text or told modest jokes with smooth timing. And he repeatedly attacked Republicans over what he called their lack of support for public education and excessive ''allegiance'' to the National Rifle Association.</p>
        <p>No two-day swing is a campaign, especially in a fickle state where a new set of television advertisements can cause polls to swing 10 points in a week. A Bradley victory in New Hampshire could spur a wave of enthusiasm in California, which elects 434 Democratic delegates, one fifth of the 2168.5 needed to win the 2000 nomination.</p>
        <p>But as the erstwhile radical State Senator Tom Hayden, who is comfortable endorsing both Mr. Gore and Warren Beatty, the actor, observed in Santa Monica on Thursday: ''I don't feel a Bradley swell except among entertainment people who are basketball freaks. Of course, that's a base.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, almost the entire Democratic establishment has endorsed Mr. Gore. Gov. Gray Davis made his support official on Thursday, calling the Vice President more qualified than ''anyone else on the planet'' for the Presidency. Mr. Gore thanked him by saying he had named the colorless Governor ''national charisma adviser to my Presidential campaign,'' but that was the only joke the Vice President told about his famously wooden image -- which was not on display this week.</p>
        <p>But endorsements are more embarrassing, especially to a Vice President, when you do not have them than effective when you do. As Antonio Villaraigosa, Speaker of the State Assembly and one of Mr. Gore's supporters, acknowledged in a San Diego interview, endorsements are ''kind of like the relish on a hot dog.''</p>
        <p>''It makes it taste better,'' Mr. Villaraigosa said, ''but without the hot dog, it's not much.''</p>
        <p>For now, though, California is a Gore fire wall against Mr. Bradley's potential in New Hampshire and in New York, where the March 7 primary falls the same day as California's.</p>
        <p>Support from Hispanic voters is a crucial element of that defense, and Mr. Gore's most telling points in a speech to the United States Hispanic Chamber of Commerce convention in San Diego were on education. He won strong applause for urging ''high-quality preschool'' for all and ''zero tolerance toward guns in our schools,'' and received cheers for saying the nation should ''start treating teachers like professionals.''</p>
        <p>To the convention, and later to a San Francisco meeting to announce plans for a gay, lesbian, bisexual and transgendered community center, Mr. Gore argued, ''Our success as a nation comes not, as some would have it, in spite of our diversity, but because of our diversity.''</p>
        <p>He also made direct political appeals to the bricklayers, denouncing Republicans for ''union busting'' and discussing in detail pension legislation before concluding with a slogan he said he had learned in Tennessee: ''Early to bed, early to rise, work like hell and organize.''</p>
        <p>But the more intriguing -- and seemingly as effective -- elements in his speeches were the personal stories he used to make political points.</p>
        <p>His metaphor for the need to work steadily over the long haul and not expect easy successes -- which he used in speaking to the environmentalists about global warming and to contributors about the campaign -- was an account of how he had recently run his first marathon with his two daughters.</p>
        <p>His family was part of all the hopeful lessons he drew, especially at the fund-raisers at Lew and Edie Wasserman's Hollywood home and George and Judy Marcus's Los Altos estate.</p>
        <p>At each event, where his campaign said about $200,000 was raised, Mr. Gore praised his 87-year-old mother's ambition, early in this century ''when poor girls were not supposed to dream,'' in working her way through college and becoming one of the first women to graduate from Vanderbilt Law School. He said he had been shocked to learn as a boy that women once had been barred from voting (until a surprise switched vote in Tennessee's Legislature ratified the 19th Amendment in 1920).</p>
        <p>''Shock had turned into optimism,'' he said on Friday in Los Altos, ''because if we had come so far in less than one lifetime, then we were on a pretty impressive trajectory with momentum in the right direction.''</p>
        <p>''I want to make you this pledge that the progress we have made for women's rights in this century represents only the beginning of the progress we are going to make in the 21st century. I am for a woman's right to choose, I'm for equal pay for equal work, for breaking down the barriers and creating true equality.''</p>
        <p>He told of a similar shock and epiphany when his father showed him slave rings, to which blacks once were shackled, in a Carthage, Tenn., mansion. They reflected cruelty to be measured against progress to be made fighting discrimination, he said.</p>
        <p>Tipper Gore was cited for observing after a meeting with Dr. Stephen W. Hawking -- the physicist crippled by Lou Gehrig's disease, who speaks through a computer voice and has  the use of only a thumb and one finger -- that a century ago Dr. Hawking would have been ignored because of his handicap, but that technology and wisdom now offered society the chance to profit from his genius.</p>
        <p>Before the overnight flight back to Washington on Saturday, Mrs. Gore played with the Flying Other Brothers Band. The band had an extra set of drums for her and their first number together was ''Women Are Smarter.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
