<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Too Hot? Blame Ohio</title>
    <meta content="08COLM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19990829T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1129214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="COPING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heat</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strum, Charles</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990808T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DE1230F93BA3575BC0A96F958260" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Too Hot? Blame Ohio</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES STRUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Strum, Charles</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Strum Coping column, noting that our ancestors lived through plague, famine and persecution, holds New Yorkers, despite being bombarded by Doppler radar and 3-D weather graphics, should just accept fact that city is hot in summer; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S summer in New York. Get over it.</p>
        <p>You already know the air isn't bracing, which is why New York is not called San Francisco.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S summer in New York. Get over it.</p>
        <p>You already know the air isn't bracing, which is why New York is not called San Francisco.</p>
        <p>Some wise guy with a science degree will poke a fat finger in your chest and invoke Mount Pinatubo, El Nino and the Greenhouse Effect. That is pretty heady stuff, very trendy. But is it helpful context when you're standing on a subway platform with your shirt stuck to your back? Does Mr. Science want you to take up a collection to mend the ozone layer? Don't bother. As Lewis Black, the fulminating comedian, said recently: ''We've got men, we've got rockets, we've got Saran Wrap. Fix it!''</p>
        <p>Or live with it, the way our parents and grandparents did. Some of them came from the old country, places that lacked not only air-conditioning but also oscillating fans, antiperspirant and iced Snapple. It was infernally hot in the old country, but at least the dehydrated peasantry wasn't subject to the 11 P.M. news alarms, whipping slack-jawed viewers into frenzies of dread with the Heat Index, the specter of chronic lung disease or suffocation.</p>
        <p>Remember, our ancestors lived through plague, famine and persecution even before they got to New York. For them, by comparison, the city's weather was congenial. A real unifying force. A way to make conversation in English.</p>
        <p>In New York before Freon, people learned to cope by undressing, drinking and not moving. Still a good idea. Darwinism at its finest.</p>
        <p>Women went stockingless in cotton house dresses. Men in sleeveless undershirts sat on stoops drinking Rheingold in bottles, fanning themselves with The Journal-American, watching droplets of chin sweat make dark spots on sandstone steps. Old people sat like sculptures in front of fans that moved heavy air without cooling it. Shouting children, slick and grimy, ran in and out of buildings until dusk.</p>
        <p>The point is this: It was hotter than hell in New York in the summer, long before Doppler radar and swirling 3-D graphics; nature as chaos produced by George Lucas.</p>
        <p>Weather sells. Fear of weather sells more. And the hottest July on record has only guaranteed more Armageddon TV: stories about negligent drivers who leave grandma in the family mini-van, windows rolled up; a puny tomato crop; morgue overcrowding, and some Chicken Little, Ph.D., to explain how hydrofluorocarbons will raise the air temperature enough to put Flatbush under water by 2015.</p>
        <p>So let's look at reality.</p>
        <p>Didn't your shirt stick to your back last summer, too? The summer before? How about 1957?</p>
        <p>Of course it's hot. What do you expect, being closer to the sun for three months?</p>
        <p>What's more, New York has more concrete and asphalt in less acreage than any place on earth. After just one morning of 88-degree heat, road tar and discarded chewing gum morph into byways of urban magma. Sunlight, trapped by the city's concrete canyons, radiates even more heat when exposed to plate glass, restaurant exhaust fans and seven million people, many of whom have just emerged from subway platforms where temperature extremes are beyond calculation.</p>
        <p>Take this simple test: Try to remember New York without air-conditioning. You can't. You can't remember what it was like to step off a hot bus, onto a hot sidewalk, into a sweltering coffee shop, back to the sidewalk and then into your un-air-conditioned office or factory building. At the end of the day, of course, you couldn't wait to get home to the fetid air of your un-air-conditioned apartment to sit around in your underwear.</p>
        <p>You call that hell? Real New Yorkers called it summer.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to my friend Dennis, who spent six years as a weekend meteorologist in the Air National Guard. One summer, during my own two-week tour with the Army guard, we bumped into each other at Camp Drum, N.Y., near Lake Ontario. It was then that he confided to me the real secret of New York's weather: It comes from someplace else.</p>
        <p>I watched in the tower as he finished some charts for the day's training flights for helicopter pilots. How, I asked. could he tell what the weather would be later in the day? He described wind patterns, cloud formations cold fronts, highs and lows. He sounded like Everyweatherman.</p>
        <p>''So you plot all this stuff and come up with a forecast?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>''You can do that,'' he said. ''Or you can do what I do. Look at Cleveland. ''Forty-eight hours later, we'll probably have the same weather.''</p>
        <p>COPING  Correction:  August 29, 1999, Sunday  The Coping column on Aug. 8, about enduring this summer's heat wave, misstated the position of Earth this time of year. In the Northern Hemisphere, Earth is farther from the Sun in summer than in winter; the heat of summer results from the tilt toward the Sun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 29, 1999, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Coping column on Aug. 8, about enduring this summer's heat wave, misstated the position of Earth this time of year. In the Northern Hemisphere, Earth is farther from the Sun in summer than in winter; the heat of summer results from the tilt toward the Sun.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
