<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In America; Dark Clouds</title>
    <meta content="23HERB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1139836"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herbert, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epstein, Paul (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Bob Herbert</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DB143FF930A1575AC0A96F958260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In America; Dark Clouds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BOB HERBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herbert, Bob</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bob Herbert Op-Ed column discusses warming of earth's oceans and atmosphere and extreme weather events that scientists believe are associated with it; cites contention of Dr Paul Epstein, associate director of Center for Health and Global Environment at Harvard Medical School, that while it cannot be said that global warming 'caused' outbreak of St Louis encephalitis or any other event, New York metropolitan area experienced precise weather conditions favorable to such an outbreak (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I remember my mother coming in from a storm one night many years ago and telling us, ''You don't want to know what's going on out there.''</p>
        <p>I think there's a tendency to take a similar approach to the undeniable warming of the earth's oceans and atmosphere, and the extreme weather events that scientists believe are associated with it. If you watch television or read the newspapers or step outside you might begin to think a plague of biblical proportions is under way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I remember my mother coming in from a storm one night many years ago and telling us, ''You don't want to know what's going on out there.''</p>
        <p>I think there's a tendency to take a similar approach to the undeniable warming of the earth's oceans and atmosphere, and the extreme weather events that scientists believe are associated with it. If you watch television or read the newspapers or step outside you might begin to think a plague of biblical proportions is under way.</p>
        <p>New Jersey is trying to recover from some of the worst flooding in its history. And just a month ago New York City was brought to a virtual standstill when, as reported in The Times, ''clouds like those that had merely puckered overhead all summer suddenly discharged up to four inches of rain in less than three hours.''</p>
        <p>Hurricanes, heat waves, droughts, torrential downpours and flooding, raging forest fires, deadly disease outbreaks -- all descending on us in frighteningly rapid succession. You can be forgiven for not wanting to know what's going on out there.</p>
        <p>But pull yourself together. This is serious.</p>
        <p>The outbreak of St. Louis encephalitis, the potentially deadly viral disease that is spread by mosquitoes, was so unexpected in New York that doctors at first were unsure of what they were seeing. But a paper published in March 1998 in the Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society noted that climate warming and outbreaks of extreme weather could be expected to have serious implications for the spread of such diseases.</p>
        <p>The paper was titled, ''Biological and Physical Signs of Climate Change: Focus on Mosquito-Borne Diseases.'' It said, ''Throughout this century public health researchers have understood that climate circumscribes the distribution of mosquito-borne diseases, while weather affects the timing and intensity of outbreaks.'' Among the diseases mentioned in the paper was St. Louis encephalitis, which has been detected in recent weeks not only in New York City but in Westchester County and suburban Connecticut as well.</p>
        <p>The lead author of the paper was Dr. Paul Epstein, associate director of the Center for Health and the Global Environment at Harvard Medical School. He stressed in an interview this week that you cannot say that global warming ''caused'' the outbreak of St. Louis encephalitis or any other event. But it is known that the metropolitan area experienced the precise weather conditions favorable to such an outbreak -- a mild winter (during which some of the mosquitoes hibernate in the subways, believe it or not) followed by a very hot and very dry summer (July was the hottest on record), which encourages breeding, reduces the prevalence of the mosquitoes' natural predators and speeds up the maturation of the virus.</p>
        <p>And those conditions are the ones associated with the climate change that is believed to be taking place.</p>
        <p>Much more serious public health consequences from extreme weather events have been occurring in developing countries. The incredible rains and flooding that accompanied Hurricane Mitch, which killed more than 11,000 people in Central America last year, led to outbreaks of cholera, malaria, dengue fever and other diseases.</p>
        <p>Dr. Epstein said it is important to recognize the serious threats to public health that are among the consequences of climate change and extreme weather events. That awareness can lead to better surveillance and earlier and more effective public health responses.</p>
        <p>The threat to public health combined with the enormous economic costs of these extreme weather events would, if people were sensible, prompt us to develop environmental and energy policies designed to alleviate such problems. We'll see.</p>
        <p>We are learning that ''climate change is not a gradual process,'' said Dr. Epstein. He said he hopes the brutal consequences of the weather extremes that we are experiencing will ''motivate us to move toward a transition to clean energy and energy efficiency in a much more rapid fashion.''</p>
        <p>Note: In one of the references to Celeste Goring-Johnson in Monday's column I inadvertently referred to her as Mrs. Hawkins. Hawkins is the last name of an official in the district attorney's office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
