<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Let's Not Get Too Wired</title>
    <meta content="22TENN$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1125188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tenner, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDC173EF931A15754C0A96F958260" item-length="1006" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Let's Not Get Too Wired</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Tenner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tenner, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researcher Edward Tenner Op-Ed article questions view that all Americans should be on Internet; holds nonusers and occasional users have rational grounds for skepticism; cites ways in which Internet users benefit from reluctance of others to get wired; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Commerce Department has just reported that 67 percent of Americans still do not use the Internet. Even 38 percent of households with personal computers don't have an Internet connection.</p>
        <p>Is this bad news? It certainly can look that way. African-American and Hispanic households are much less likely to have access to the World Wide Web than white or Asian-American households. The big cities in the Northeast are significantly less connected than those in the West. The report concludes that the gap between the already-wired haves and the less-connected have-nots is turning a ''digital divide'' into a ''racial ravine.''</p>
        <p>Few will argue with the report's concern about this gap, and with the call for expanded access to the Web in schools, libraries and other public places. (It may be time to throw in some new books, too.) But the document implies more. It suggests -- though it never quite says directly -- that everybody should be on the Web, just as nearly everybody is on the telephone network.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Commerce Department has just reported that 67 percent of Americans still do not use the Internet. Even 38 percent of households with personal computers don't have an Internet connection.</p>
        <p>Is this bad news? It certainly can look that way. African-American and Hispanic households are much less likely to have access to the World Wide Web than white or Asian-American households. The big cities in the Northeast are significantly less connected than those in the West. The report concludes that the gap between the already-wired haves and the less-connected have-nots is turning a ''digital divide'' into a ''racial ravine.''</p>
        <p>Few will argue with the report's concern about this gap, and with the call for expanded access to the Web in schools, libraries and other public places. (It may be time to throw in some new books, too.) But the document implies more. It suggests -- though it never quite says directly -- that everybody should be on the Web, just as nearly everybody is on the telephone network.</p>
        <p>But does everybody want to be? Nonusers and occasional users have rational grounds for skepticism. A survey included in the report found that 40 percent of all respondents were ''very concerned'' about confidentiality on the Internet. People regularly give up Internet connections because of expense or disappointment -- ''temporary'' files accumulate on hard drives if not removed, innocuous search queries land the user at a pornographic link, malicious programs are outpacing anti-virus software, and so on.</p>
        <p>In fact, there are hints that users of public terminals may actually enjoy computing most. Douglas Rushkoff, the cyberculture journalist, has reported that a survey by some of his students at New York University found that only half of the children at private elementary schools (students who were required to have their own laptop computers) were happy about computing, while their public school counterparts (who mostly used school equipment) were uniformly enthusiastic about it. For these public school students, computer sessions are treats, not encumbrances. Somebody else maintains the hardware and software.</p>
        <p>Regular users of the Web should heed this and learn to appreciate the nonwired and occasional user, for several reasons. For example, these holdouts prod the computer industry into cutting profit margins and lowering prices for connections. If a personal Internet link really became as ubiquitous and as necessary as the telephone, the drive for new business would stop, and providers might seek growth in higher charges or more intrusive on-line advertising instead.</p>
        <p>Also, if everyone were on the Web, the rest of cultural life, although it would not evaporate, could certainly be impaired. Book sales have already slumped even though the economy has surged and on-line bookselling has exploded. Independent and small-chain bookstores are folding. Compressed on-line music formats may displace some higher-quality CD's. Internet holdouts help protect intellectual variety and choice in such areas.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, the unconnected also benefit on-line shoppers. They help maintain the retail outlets and catalogues that are valued as alternatives (and as printed and physical showrooms) even by many of those who would rather fill electronic shopping carts. You might order your new car on line, but you'd probably swing by the local showroom to get a look first. And the sales taxes paid by patrons of local retailers are helping to buy more time for the exemption still enjoyed by on-line buyers. Universal service would almost surely mean farewell to the free ride.</p>
        <p>But the biggest benefit from the Internet holdouts is not what they consume but what they save: energy. In ''Earth in the Balance,'' Al Gore celebrated the potential of a future national computer network to help spare the environment through telecommuting. Now we have wide access to the Internet, yet consumption of electricity continues to rise as electronic devices multiply. Some scientists, unconvinced that reserves are growing as reported, predict new petroleum shortages within a decade. If so, the Web's contribution to the energy load will compound them.</p>
        <p>Today's personal computers are thermally as well as metaphorically hot. My now-antique 1993 P.C. is rated at 150 watts; its 1999 Pentium III successor has a power supply for 200 watts.</p>
        <p>And that's without the monitor. Add another 120 to 140 watts for a 17-inch screen. (By the way, Windows 98 supports two active monitors with one computer.) A deluxe speaker system may have its own power supply, plus a powered subwoofer. A laser printer is increasingly a must. High-speed connections, riveting action games and fixed-rate service also encourage users to keep their computers fired up longer than in pre-Internet days. As in a casino, time can lose meaning on the Web.</p>
        <p>Thanks to all that cruising, the servers and routers that harbor Web sites and distribute data -- and the factories that make the chips -- use energy prodigiously. Writing recently in Forbes, Peter Huber has estimated that it takes ''about 1 pound of coal to create, package, store and move 2 megabytes of data'' and that computer-related demand already consumes 13 percent of America's electricity.</p>
        <p>Internet enthusiasts should consider what would happen to their utility bills if most nonusers jumped onto the Internet just as new generations of chips arrive, running hotter than ever. During the summer, the extra heat would be pumped into city streets by air-conditioners, supercharging the local microclimate as well as contributing to global greenhouse gases; we would demand still more cooling, until cities and even regions faced the likelihood of blackouts.</p>
        <p>So Web users ought to count their blessings, think of the money they're saving with their on-line purchases, support a balanced program of information access for all Americans -- and take a Luddite to lunch.</p>
        <p>Edward Tenner is a visiting researcher in the geosciences department at Princeton and the author of ''Why Things Bite Back.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Edward Tenner is a visiting researcher in the geosciences department at Princeton and the author of ''Why Things Bite Back.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
