<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Quest to Tie Strings: Particles and Quartets</title>
    <meta content="11ESSA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1106737"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Browne, Malcolm W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Essay</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Physics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EFD8143FF932A25756C0A96F958260" item-length="1160" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Quest to Tie Strings: Particles and Quartets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM W. BROWNE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Browne, Malcolm W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Malcolm W Browne Essay on the subtle and uncertain connections between music and physics and mathematics; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The discovery of animal bones with holes drilled at regular intervals has encouraged paleoanthropologists to believe that Neanderthals were playing music on crude flutes 43,000 years ago. True or not, musical instruments have an ancient lineage firmly based on physics and mathematics.</p>
        <p>In the 5th century B.C., both Pythagoras of Samos (the one who discovered the theorem about right triangles) and Chinese bronzesmiths who cast musical bells hit upon systematic scales of notes defined by mathematical relationships. Music seems almost as old as human history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The discovery of animal bones with holes drilled at regular intervals has encouraged paleoanthropologists to believe that Neanderthals were playing music on crude flutes 43,000 years ago. True or not, musical instruments have an ancient lineage firmly based on physics and mathematics.</p>
        <p>In the 5th century B.C., both Pythagoras of Samos (the one who discovered the theorem about right triangles) and Chinese bronzesmiths who cast musical bells hit upon systematic scales of notes defined by mathematical relationships. Music seems almost as old as human history.</p>
        <p>But connections between music and science are subtle and uncertain, and all too often we are asked to accept on faith the supposed links between the concert hall and the laboratory.</p>
        <p>A seemingly endless debate persists between those who regard music as a branch of physics and those who see it as the artistic product of inspired but inexplicable minds. The latest attempt to bridge the chasm between these divergent perspectives was offered in New York last week at the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum by the Emerson String Quartet and a Columbia University physics professor, Dr. Brian Greene, whose words-and-music performance was not exactly a recital and not exactly a lecture; it was something like what people in the 1960's called a ''happening.''</p>
        <p>The five black-clad performers sought to demonstrate an underlying kinship between some seminal ideas of physics and music; Dr. Greene's depiction of Newton's clockwork universe, for instance, was followed by two elegantly structured Bach fugues. A simplified introduction to the modern theory of superstrings preceded some hard-to-get-to 12-tone works by Anton Webern and Alban Berg.</p>
        <p>Superstring theory is an attempt to bring into consonance two bodies of thought central to modern physics: relativity, which helps to explain cosmic-scale interactions, and quantum mechanics, which describes the domain of the ultra-small. Both theories are wonderfully successful within their own domains, but have yet to be united as a single coherent description of the universe -- unless, perhaps, the superstrings theory turns out to be correct.</p>
        <p>That theory (or rather, the five versions of it grouped together as components of a larger theory) depend on mathematical correspondences between 10 different dimensions of reality -- as mind-boggling an idea as any in science. It is easy enough to envision a three-dimensional cube, but when even one more spatial dimension is added, as in a four-dimensional tesseract or ''hypercube,'' visualization becomes impossible.</p>
        <p>Thus, the acceptance of a 10-dimensional description of reality requires an act of faith in the mathematics involved. Many physicists would like to become believers, if only because superstrings would solve many problems, including the mystery of how gravity is related to the other forces of nature.</p>
        <p>Perhaps an analogous act of faith is required to fully accept the atonal and 12-tone music of Arnold Schoenberg and his followers, some of which was played at the Guggenheim event.</p>
        <p>But acts of faith in both music and mathematics are hard for ordinary people to swallow. A much more accessible connection between music and science lies in the fact that music and science often seem to cohabit creative minds. Among the thinkers who noticed this was Gottfried Wilhelm von Leibniz, who invented calculus independently of Newton. He wrote:</p>
        <p>''Music is the hidden mathematical endeavor of a soul unconscious it is calculating.''</p>
        <p>A conspicuous example of the admixture of science and music was Aleksandr Borodin, a distinguished Russian chemist and physician, who in his spare time wrote the opera ''Prince Igor,'' three symphonies and some other immortal orchestral and chamber works. He is less well known for having pioneered a field of carbon-fluorine chemistry that ultimately led to nonstick cookware and freon refrigerants; unknowingly, the composer helped to found a branch of chemistry that has unfortunately led to depletion of the global ozone layer.</p>
        <p>If there is a connection between Borodin's wild sonorities and his sober chemistry, it is obscure.</p>
        <p>Dr. John F. Putz, a mathematician at Alma College in Michigan, thought he perceived mathematical influences in the music of Mozart. Some of his evidence came from a search of Mozart piano music for a mathematical proportion called the ''golden ratio'' -- a number known to mathematicians, architects and others since ancient times.</p>
        <p>The golden ratio, which defines many patterns in nature (including the spiral patterns at the centers of daisies) can be calculated by dividing up a straight line into two unequal segments. If this is done in such a way that the ratio of the whole line to its larger segment is the same as the ratio of the larger segment to the smaller segment, the resulting ratio works out to about 1.61803 to 1: a value known as the ''golden ratio.''</p>
        <p>In an article in Mathematics Magazine, Dr. Putz wrote that the golden ratio defines proportions in architecture that many people find pleasing, so he looked for this ratio in paired sections of a Mozart sonata. Each of the three movements of Mozart's Sonata No. 1 in C major was divided by the composer into two parts, with a short ''exposition'' at the beginning followed by a longer ''recapitulation and development.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Putz found a very close agreement with the golden ratio in the lengths of the two sections of each of the first two movements of the sonata, but not in the third movement. ''We must remember that these sonatas are the work of a genius,'' Dr. Putz wrote, ''and one who loved to play with numbers. Mozart may have known of the golden ratio and used it.''</p>
        <p>But he added an acknowledgment that it was probably Mozart's inspired mind and not any mathematical calculation that produced the music.</p>
        <p>Many have applied mathematical relationships to musical composition. Among the most influential of the mathematical composers was Joseph Schillinger, whose system of composition found its way into movie sound tracks, synthesizer music and many other musical forms. Schillinger's most famous student was George Gershwin, and even the physicist Albert Einstein thought highly of Schillinger's system.</p>
        <p>Some physicists, like Dr. Richard F. Voss of I.B.M., have asserted that music has a strong ''fractal'' element; that is, it contains rhythmic and melodic structures that sound the same at all size scales. (Fractal geometry, which supposedly describes the ''self-similarity'' of mountain ranges or shore lines as viewed from any distance, is a part of chaos theory.)</p>
        <p>But the question of whether music and physics can be illuminated in terms of each other remains open. It is entertaining to hear the views of physicists about the ultimate realities of existence. It is also entertaining to listen to great music. But it remains to be proved that these two fields of creative endeavor are causally linked.</p>
        <p>In his essay ''The Joy of Music,'' the composer Leonard Bernstein wrote: ''We bumble. We imitate scientific method in our attempts to explain magic phenomena by fact, forces, mass, energy . . .</p>
        <p>''The only way one can really say anything about music is to write music.''</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
