<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; Where Will Hillary Clinton Love New York?</title>
    <meta content="30SUN3$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1111435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randolph, Eleanor</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DD1430F933A05756C0A96F958260" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; Where Will Hillary Clinton Love New York?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR RANDOLPH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Randolph, Eleanor</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eleanor Randolph Editorial Observer column on where Bill and Hillary Clinton should vacation in New York as she prepares for possible Senate race; discusses access to voters and donors and scenic backdrops offered by various sites (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill and Hillary Clinton are said to be planning a vacation in New York this summer. The First Lady needs to learn more about the state she might like to represent in the Senate, but their problem is where exactly to go.</p>
        <p>Most Americans put a high priority on beaches or battlefields, canyons, mountains or theme parks. Mrs. Clinton would presumably prefer to spend her time with voters and donors. She will also need enough scenery for photo opportunities -- the kind of exquisite backdrop for a commercial that brings out the healthiest fresh-air look in even the wonkiest of indoor politicians. Unfortunately, many of the state's most scenic spots have already been used by Gov. George Pataki.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill and Hillary Clinton are said to be planning a vacation in New York this summer. The First Lady needs to learn more about the state she might like to represent in the Senate, but their problem is where exactly to go.</p>
        <p>Most Americans put a high priority on beaches or battlefields, canyons, mountains or theme parks. Mrs. Clinton would presumably prefer to spend her time with voters and donors. She will also need enough scenery for photo opportunities -- the kind of exquisite backdrop for a commercial that brings out the healthiest fresh-air look in even the wonkiest of indoor politicians. Unfortunately, many of the state's most scenic spots have already been used by Gov. George Pataki.</p>
        <p>The Clintons' analyzers are said to be looking at the electoral possibilities of Shelter Island, the Finger Lakes and the Adirondacks. Shelter Island has a few advantages. It is close to Steven Spielberg's place in East Hampton, and some of the nation's biggest campaign contributors are a short ferry ride away. Also, Shelter Island would not be considered too fancy because, technically, it is not a Hampton. In fact, some people on Shelter Island have been hunkering down for years, hoping that nobody from the Hamptons looks north and discovers them. Since it would be hard for the locals to remain invisible with the Clintons there and since Shelter Island has a particularly hazardous colony of journalists, the couple might prefer more remote territory.</p>
        <p>The Finger Lakes between Syracuse and Rochester would be an easy choice, with the universities and the home of Susan B. Anthony. But Adirondack State Park offers a challenge -- six million acres worth of everything from wilderness to water parks. The real problem is that the region is so heavily Republican that a local Democrat usually tries to keep such tendencies hidden from the neighbors.</p>
        <p>Republican roots go deep in this wild territory. Teddy Roosevelt started coming to the Adirondacks as a boy. Calvin Coolidge summered near Saranac Lake. One Democratic President, Grover Cleveland, apparently visited sometime in the previous century. A fisherman who weighed in at 300 pounds, Cleveland was undoubtedly a challenge to the watercraft of the day.</p>
        <p>As for donors, most of the old rich -- like the Rockefellers, Vanderbilts and Morgans, who owned ''camps'' the size of Blenheim -- are gone. The next moneyed generation has arrived, discovering anew the incredible beauty and discomfort of an Adirondack twig chair. So far, however, there seems to be some reluctance about hosting an outgoing President and his up-and-coming wife.</p>
        <p>Gary Heurich, a Washington, D.C., brewer who owns one of the park's splendid private properties, has sent word that the Clintons are welcome to visit. Mr. Heurich, however, warns that he is not a Democrat but an independent, which, he says, ''may be as close as they'll get.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Heurich's camp, whittled down to a few hundred acres after the family gave a few thousand acres to the state as forest preserve, has three houses, including a renovated lighthouse. There is also a helipad and a mile of shoreline on Lake Champlain.</p>
        <p>Among the attractions of the area are golf courses and such scenic spots as the place where Samuel de Champlain shot two Iroquois chiefs with his harquebus (gun) and started the French and Indian War. Birders bring their binoculars for over 100 species of birds. Nearby are also the beaches where young Canadian humans come south each August to swim in the nude.</p>
        <p>If such amusements do not appeal to the First Lady, the park is full of serious issues as well. Adirondack lifers can talk for days about acid rain, motor-boat hazards, seasonal economics, prisons or wildlife, particularly the common loon. Whether they will vote for her, even if they find her surprisingly charming, is another matter.</p>
        <p>Finally, the Adirondacks include a number of places that are great but not so grand, like the western hills where my family celebrates summer. For us, a star-studded evening means a chair on the nearest dock. Gatherings feature bring-your-own casseroles and beer, and everybody smells like a bath oil known for offending not merely humans but also bugs. It's a lovely place to August, but socially, at least, we are a long way from the Hamptons and a lot closer to rural Arkansas.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
