<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jeweler-Artists Making Much Of Measure</title>
    <meta content="15OPOP$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1130595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liebenson, Bess</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jewels and Jewelry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4DF1739F936A2575BC0A96F958260" item-length="686" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jeweler-Artists Making Much Of Measure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BESS LIEBENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liebenson, Bess</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bess Liebenson reviews show of millennium jewelry on view at Brookfield Craft Center, Brookfield, Conn; photos</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RINGS, bracelets and necklaces with a link to the millennium can be seen in ''Measure by Measure: Jewelers Explore the Four Dimensions,'' on view through Aug. 29 at the Brookfield Craft Center.</p>
        <p>''We looked to the field and noted some important trends in metal-smithing,'' said John I. Russell, the Craft Center's executive director, who invited Robert Dancik, an artist and jeweler, to create a show addressing the subject. Mr. Dancik came up with a concept on measurement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RINGS, bracelets and necklaces with a link to the millennium can be seen in ''Measure by Measure: Jewelers Explore the Four Dimensions,'' on view through Aug. 29 at the Brookfield Craft Center.</p>
        <p>''We looked to the field and noted some important trends in metal-smithing,'' said John I. Russell, the Craft Center's executive director, who invited Robert Dancik, an artist and jeweler, to create a show addressing the subject. Mr. Dancik came up with a concept on measurement.</p>
        <p>''As the millennium approaches, people are engaged in measuring various parts of their lives, the lives of others, and the world around them,'' Mr. Dancik said. ''Issues of measuring global warming, how much money we make, how long until retirement or the square footage of our house are on our minds.'' So, he said, for the exhibition, ''we asked artists to create works which explore measurements in its many manifestations include height, width, length and time.''</p>
        <p>Twenty-five artist-jewelers were offered the challenge of creating a piece totally different from that traditionally made by professional jewelers.</p>
        <p>''This was an opportunity to play, to fantasize, to beyond their usual type of work,'' Mr. Russell said. ''They did so big time.''</p>
        <p>''Although we were familiar with the artists' work,'' added Judith T. Russell, the gallery's manager, ''when we opened the boxes we were shocked. Suddenly, unencumbered by the confines of making pieces to be sold and worn, artists moved unrestrained into the process of making a piece for the show. They wanted as well to be provocative to their fellow jewelers -- that was an issue.'' The show contains unexpected works. Despite most of the artists being jewelers, there's not a lot of jewelry, and the materials in their hands are other than precious metals and stones; polymer, glass, clay, wood and paper, have been invested with chic. The display of oddments, most purely sculptural and highly narrative, is set against the unifying humble foil of brown paper.</p>
        <p>''In between the world of traditional jewelry and pure sculpture lies a vast region for experimentation,'' Mr. Russell said. The tone of the exhibition is established by Mr. Dancik's installation-collage of watches and other devices: a digital timer, carpenter's level, measuring spoon and slide rule set against a map. Robert Ebendorf, whose work can be seen in museums in 14 countries including the Victoria and Albert in London, offers ''Inch Your Way Through Life,'' a sculpture carved from a river stone with tape-measure streamers. ''Although it has the imagery of a necklace, it's too big, too heavy and too long to wear,'' said Ms. Russell.</p>
        <p>Bobby Hansson, author of ''The Fine Art of the Tin Can'' (Lark Books, Ashville, N.C. 1996) presents ''Baby Sitar'': a sculpture, its neck an old ruler attached to a can showing a woman playing a mandolin to which a measuring spoon is added. Christopher Darway submits ''Analog Computer,'' a stainless steel digital clock in the shape of a pyramid. A green light ignites numbers, turned by the mesmerizing rolling action of a motor.</p>
        <p>Linda Kaye-Moses's ''Temporayne,'' a neck piece of metal, 14-karat gold, beetle wings, boulder opal and Favrile glass, hangs above an antique wood case covered with hosta leaves, mica schist, paper and sterling, in turn elevating a poem capturing moments in time.</p>
        <p>Jewelers are also looking at personal ornamentation in other cultures and at other times. ''This is but one small thread in the whole American craft movement,'' Mr. Russell said. ''There is so much overlap and crossing of lines with old traditional rules thrown by the board. People are not going to see that except through the lens or porthole of a place like Brookfield.''</p>
        <p>The Lynn Tendler Big Nell Gallery at Brookfield Craft Center (Route 25, 286 Whisconier Road, Brookfield) is open Monday through Saturday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sundays from noon to 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
