<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends; Blaming the Victim In the Drought War</title>
    <meta content="15SHAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1130795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sharkey, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drought</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conservation of Resources</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DA1239F936A2575BC0A96F958260" item-length="954" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends; Blaming the Victim In the Drought War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sharkey, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Average water user is taking the blame for this summer's drought and bearing the brunt of emergency measures taken in response to it; some experts say state and local governments and new media have failed to recognize drought as a complex set of phenomena that demand long-range regional planning and hard decisions after the inevitable rains come and the emergency decrees fade away; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS this summer's drought hangs on like an unwanted guest at the cottage, the cherished American pastime of lawn watering has been criminalized by states desperate to change people's behavior and save water.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman declared a state of emergency on Aug. 5, invoking extraordinary powers that threaten people with fines up to $5,000 for disobeying water-use rules. The state's commissioner of environmental protection, Robert C. Shinn Jr., even called on citizens to snitch on one another. ''We depend on neighbors to monitor their neighbors because there aren't enough police to do what we have to do,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS this summer's drought hangs on like an unwanted guest at the cottage, the cherished American pastime of lawn watering has been criminalized by states desperate to change people's behavior and save water.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, Gov. Christine Todd Whitman declared a state of emergency on Aug. 5, invoking extraordinary powers that threaten people with fines up to $5,000 for disobeying water-use rules. The state's commissioner of environmental protection, Robert C. Shinn Jr., even called on citizens to snitch on one another. ''We depend on neighbors to monitor their neighbors because there aren't enough police to do what we have to do,'' he said.</p>
        <p>New Jersey officials also said more severe measures could be imposed, including the monitoring of home water use.</p>
        <p>The restrictions may be helping. New Jersey's water supply has improved slightly since the emergency decree and with the help of recent scattered thunderstorms. But a basic question remains: How did this rap get pinned on the average citizen?</p>
        <p>After all, when a power blackout hit a big chunk of Manhattan during last month's heat wave, no one blamed apartment-dwellers for running air conditioners. Instead, politicians denounced Consolidated Edison for not planning better and investing more to anticipate surges in demand.</p>
        <p>But during the current drought, virtually the only official response has been to point a finger at homeowners and issue emergency measures. While cutting back sharply on nonessential water use makes obvious sense, some experts say state and local governments and the news media have failed to recognize drought as a complex set of phenomena that demand long-range regional planning and hard decisions after the inevitable rains come and the emergency decrees fade away.</p>
        <p>''Government should have a greater role in planning for water resources rather than just blaming people,'' said Wenonah Hauter, the director of the Public Citizen's Critical Mass Energy Project, a Washington organization founded by Ralph Nader that lobbies for better technological and political approaches to the use of energy and natural resources.</p>
        <p>''A lot of what we're hearing is haphazard responses about lawns,'' Mr. Hauter said, ''but there are longer-term issues such as the effect of urban sprawl on water resources that government should be paying attention to.''</p>
        <p>Americans are willing to make sacrifices in crises. There is widespread support, for example, for providing emergency relief to the farm industry, which is exempt from most emergency water restrictions. But there is often little public discussion about emergency powers exercised by governors  on matters like home water use and lawn watering.</p>
        <p>''In general, there should be a more robust public debate about how about government functions in a liberal democracy in times of emergency -- especially about the amount of power that moves to the central authority, whether in Trenton, Albany or Washington,'' said Andrew Grossman, a political science professor at Albion College in Albion, Mich., citing the potential for civil rights abuses.</p>
        <p>The Federal Government has set up a commission to study the drought. But so far the Government's chief response has been to declare disaster emergencies in New Jersey, Connecticut, West Virginia and parts of New York, Pennsylvania, Maryland, Virginia, Kentucky, Ohio and New Mexico. These decrees provide Federal emergency subsidies to the farming industry, which has lost billions of dollars in withered summer crops.</p>
        <p>AND it's not just food crops at stake. In New Jersey, for example, the leading cash crop category is nursery, greenhouse and lawn-sod products -- mainly decorative plants, shrubs and bushes sold at garden centers for home use -- which accounted for $255 million in sales last year. So while homeowners are restricted in watering their shrubs and plants, farmers are able to continue producing such plants for sale.</p>
        <p>Even with their beloved lawns, Americans have shown a willingness to voluntarily reduce water use without the threat of criminal prosecution, said Gordon T. Geballe, an associate dean of the Yale University School of Forestry and Environmental Studies. ''In the New Haven area, there are a large number of lawns that are brown, and we don't have a water shortage yet,'' he said,  noting that lawns account for about 30 percent of water use in metropolitan regions.</p>
        <p>Professor Geballe said some people are reappraising the real costs of their emerald-green expanses of grass -- and are adjusting their behavior to ''escape the lawn-must-always-be-green addiction'' in favor of  an ''ecological approach'' that takes into account both a lawn's use of water and the contribution that lawn mowers make to carbon dioxide emissions, which may contribute to climatic phenomena like drought.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, plant experts say there is a practical way to mitigate future droughts without the threat of criminal prosecution. Karen Snetselaar, a professor of biology at St. Joseph's University in Philadelphia, said the overwatering of grass and plants encourages them to keep their roots close to the soil surface, where they are most vulnerable during droughts.</p>
        <p>''People tend to water every day,'' she said, ''and most of the time that's the wrong thing to do, unless you are trying to get seeds to germinate or when you have very young plants.''</p>
        <p>Instead, by watering grass, shrubs and plants no more than once a week the plants will modify their behavior and ''send their roots farther down in the soil,'' she said. ''That way, when it doesn't rain for a while, the plants have extensive root systems and they're O.K. for a longer period the next time there's a drought.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
