<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>. . . And Lungs May Be Key In the Anatomy of a Horse</title>
    <meta content="11SIDE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1122530"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liebenson, Bess</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E6D7173CF932A25754C0A96F958260" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>. . . And Lungs May Be Key In the Anatomy of a Horse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BESS LIEBENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liebenson, Bess</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bess Liebenson reviews interactive science exhibition on anatomy of horses at Bruce Museum, Greenwich, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE interactive science exhibition called ''Horse Play'' represents a first for the Bruce Museum -- which sometimes seems to have covered every conceivable stretchable topic. (''We've done boats and planes,'' said the museum's science curator Marianne Smith, ''but not horses.'')</p>
        <p>The family-oriented exhibition, which will remain on view through Oct. 31 in the museum's science and ethnology gallery, ponders the natural history of the horse and the Thoroughbred in particular. It explores the physical characteristics that make a racehorse swift, a polo pony agile and a jumper courageous. The exhibition, a companion to the art show, ''The Thoroughbred: Born to Run and Jump,'' also considers the partnership between horse and rider.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE interactive science exhibition called ''Horse Play'' represents a first for the Bruce Museum -- which sometimes seems to have covered every conceivable stretchable topic. (''We've done boats and planes,'' said the museum's science curator Marianne Smith, ''but not horses.'')</p>
        <p>The family-oriented exhibition, which will remain on view through Oct. 31 in the museum's science and ethnology gallery, ponders the natural history of the horse and the Thoroughbred in particular. It explores the physical characteristics that make a racehorse swift, a polo pony agile and a jumper courageous. The exhibition, a companion to the art show, ''The Thoroughbred: Born to Run and Jump,'' also considers the partnership between horse and rider.</p>
        <p>It was the museum's curator of education, Robin Garr, whose passion for the animals inspired the exhibition. The museum deemed it quite appropriate to have an exhibition on horses in a region where equestrian skills are certainly highly appreciated. The interactive exhibition opens with the story of the beginning of equine evolution: a small browsing animal the size of a fox running on padded feet through marshy ground feeding on berries and leaves. When berries became available inconsistently,  only the swifter, with longer legs and stronger teeth, adapted.</p>
        <p>''As one of the oldest mammals, the horse learned to survive on the purest of diets -- grass,'' said Ms. Smith, adding that ''on the open grasslands they were vulnerable to other predators like mountain lions and wolves, so they developed acceleration. They can accelerate faster than a Ferrari, going from 0 to 40 miles an hour in six strides.''</p>
        <p>It took 55 million years to develop into the large fast-footed athlete of today. The Thoroughbred, which traces its male lineage to three stallions of the 18th century, has not only been selectively bred to run and jump, but also to do so carrying a human being on its back. Two life-sized lucite horses dramatically illustrate the horse's skeleton, outlining its muscle, circulatory and reproductive systems. Arteries, shown in red, illustrate oxygen carried from the lungs via the heart to the cells. Carbon dioxide, formed when nutrients in the cells combine with oxygen to release energy, is removed by the veins, shown in blue.</p>
        <p>An impressive display of skulls, leg bones, lungs and larynx help demonstrate the anatomy of the horse and the qualities that mold a Thoroughbred into a supreme athlete.</p>
        <p>The horse's huge lungs (2 feet by 3 feet) reflect its high energy needs -- at full gallop taking in five gallons of air a second. Its large rib cage protects the heart and lungs, its long skull reveals 40 teeth including 12 incisors to tear into the hay and grasses. Outsized eyes on the sides of the head provide a nearly 360 degree view. And the Thoroughbred's legs, evolved to be inordinately long and light, also developed for speed and endurance.</p>
        <p>While the first section lays the groundwork with the evolution, anatomy and physiology of the horse, the story on two levels, for adults and children, moves on to the horse and rider. A large-screen, eye-witness video adds color and action, showing a horse and rider racing, playing polo and show jumping.</p>
        <p>In a dressing area children can try on racing silks, weigh in as a jockey would, saddle up and mount one of two model training horses (created by a jockey recovering from an injury) to practice their riding skills. Farther along in the exhibition, children can shoe a horse, braid real horsehair and learn how to bridle a horse.</p>
        <p>''As a museum of art and science, we like to represent the art of a subject,'' Ms. Smith said, ''but also to prod beneath, to discover the natural science of a subject -- in this case what makes a Thoroughbred such a powerful animal.''</p>
        <p>The Bruce Museum , 1 Museum Drive in Greenwich, is open Tuesday through Saturday, 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. and Sundays 1 to 5.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
