<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="05FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1097943"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990405T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD91139F936A35757C0A96F958260" item-length="1339" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>NATO Says It Will Airlift Kosovo Refugees to Safety  NATO moved to assume responsibility for the hundreds of thousands of Kosovo refugees, announcing that it would begin the first massive airlift of its 50-year history to bring in supplies and take out about 100,000 people to temporary shelter in the United States and Europe. And in a series of raids before dawn Monday, NATO missiles and bombers struck Serbia hard, hitting the Yugoslav Air Force headquarters in Zemun, a suburb of Belgrade, and other targets around the country, Serbian television said. Pentagon and NATO officials confirmed that air raids were going on, but declined to give any details.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Conditions have deteriorated alarmingly as the tide of refugees has swelled to 30,000 along the Macedonia border, and death and disease are becoming commonplace.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-11</p>
        <p>NATO Says It Will Airlift Kosovo Refugees to Safety  NATO moved to assume responsibility for the hundreds of thousands of Kosovo refugees, announcing that it would begin the first massive airlift of its 50-year history to bring in supplies and take out about 100,000 people to temporary shelter in the United States and Europe. And in a series of raids before dawn Monday, NATO missiles and bombers struck Serbia hard, hitting the Yugoslav Air Force headquarters in Zemun, a suburb of Belgrade, and other targets around the country, Serbian television said. Pentagon and NATO officials confirmed that air raids were going on, but declined to give any details.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Conditions have deteriorated alarmingly as the tide of refugees has swelled to 30,000 along the Macedonia border, and death and disease are becoming commonplace.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The official Yugoslav news media said that at least 4 civilians had been killed and 17 wounded in strikes all over Serbia, as NATO widened its attacks on Yugoslavia's civilian as well as military infrastructure.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Pope John Paul II appealed for a ''humanitarian corridor'' to bring urgent relief to hundreds of thousands of refugees and denounced the burning of towns and villages as well as the destruction wrought by aerial attacks. Religious leaders around the United States used their Easter sermons to condemn the hostilities in Yugoslavia and lead prayers for the ethnic Albanians driven from their homes in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Even as NATO forces press the war against Yugoslavia, there are Serbs across the United States fighting deportation on the ground that they do not want to be returned home to face conscription into a military engaged in an ethnic purge.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Military experts say the lack of detailed, after-action reports have made it impossible to assess the allies' claim that they are steadily dismantling Belgrade's war-making powers.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Report of Germ War Programs  A book by the senior defector from the Soviet germ warfare program says that Soviet officials concluded that two major epidemics in China were caused by a serious accident at one of China's secret plants for developing biological weapons.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Political Test for Hindus  India's governing Hindu nationalist party is facing a political showdown with its largest coalition partner, a very public test of wills that has much of the nation speculating about whether the year-old Government is about to fall.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A12-18</p>
        <p>When Market Research Becomes Schools' Work  Product research companies and advertising agencies have enlisted dozens of schools in special partnerships that use children as captive, if willing, subjects of market research during the school day. For the most part, the partners to these deals -- companies, school officials, teachers, parents and children -- are happy with them, and some see them as ways to supplement school budgets. But some critics think that the focus groups, which for years have been conducted after school, are out of place during the school day.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>An Effort to Curb Free Music  Downloading music from the Internet is moving beyond college campuses and into offices and homes, and its rapid acceptance has caught the recording companies unprepared. A method of digital compression known as MP3 allows music to be sent quickly and freely over the Internet, with a quality near that of CD's. To limit unauthorized music sites, the recording industry has begun a counteroffensive against fans, profiteers, Internet search engines, manufacturers of MP3 players and even some of its own artists who have put their music on-line.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>College Comparison Shopping  An increasing number of college and university applicants are shopping for the best deal among the schools that want them. Although schools have always competed for the best high school students with offers of grants, loans and other inducements that are sometimes based on need and sometimes on merit, bargaining has become a new element of the courtship, prompting some admissions experts to compare it to shopping for a used car.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>F.B.I. Ends Search for Atheist  F.B.I. agents completed a three-day search at a Texas ranch for clues to the disappearance of Madalyn Murray O'Hair, the atheist leader who vanished in 1995, but they declined to say whether they found anything.</p>
        <p>A15</p>
        <p>Federal Funds to Fight Violence  Three Federal agencies, seeking to stop youth violence in its earliest stages, are giving schools the chance to compete for money for anti-violence programs, mental health services and police officers. Up to $180 million from the Departments of Education, Justice and Health and Human Services will be shared by 50 winning districts nationwide, agency officials said.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>A Tornado's Aftermath  Emergency crews searched through the rubble left behind by a tornado that devastated Benton, La., on Saturday, and survivors at Easter services remembered the six who died and the more than 100 who were injured. Eight twisters reported in northwestern Louisiana forced 200 people from their homes.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Other Regions Are Sharing The Threat of Acid Rain  Scientists for years have viewed the Adirondack Mountains, where hundreds of lakes and streams can no longer sustain life because of chronically high acidity, as the region that suffers the most from acid precipitation. But a new Federal report concludes that despite important strides in reducing air pollution, acid precipitation remains a serious problem in the Adirondacks and is a growing threat in the Appalachians, Colorado's Front Range and elsewhere.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Florio's Long Road Back  Former New Jersey Gov. Jim Florio is trying to make a political comeback, running for the Democratic nomination for the United States Senate seat to be vacated next year by Senator Frank R. Lautenberg. But Mr. Florio is having difficulty building support in parts of the state, and his biggest threat comes from leaders within his own party.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Advocate's Death a Mystery  A prominent East Village neighborhood advocate and community board member was found cut and bleeding outside a Queens apartment building early Saturday morning and died that evening at Elmhurst Hospital Center, the police said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Apartments Destroyed by Fire  Residents returned to the remains of their apartments in a Lower East Side building to see what could be salvaged from the fire-ravaged structure.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-8</p>
        <p>SPORTSMONDAY</p>
        <p>D1-10</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Rafael C. Benitez  A rear admiral who directed an extraordinary rescue operation when his submarine caught fire during the cold war, he was 81.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-10</p>
        <p>Virus Fails to Boost Stock  Most computer antivirus companies failed to reap new revenue when the Melissa virus struck E-mail programs last week. In the last few years, digital vaccinations have become so widely used in the United States and Europe that even all the media attention devoted to Melissa failed to nudge the market.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Book Chain Merger Under Fire  The proposed merger of Barnes &amp; Noble and the nation's largest wholesaler, Ingram Book Group, is undergoing intense Federal scrutiny and is being investigated by the California Attorney General's office.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Proposal to Guide Site Names  A United Nations agency, faced with mounting disputes about Internet addresses and complaints from trademark holders, is completing a proposal for bringing order to the chaos of addresses in cyberspace.</p>
        <p>C4</p>
        <p>Stocks Higher in Tokyo  Stocks were trading higher in Tokyo today. At midday, the benchmark Nikkei index of 225 issues was up 232.20 points, or 1.43 percent, at 16,522.39.</p>
        <p>(Bloomberg News)</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: A visit by China's Prime Minister; a new defense against an old killer; Floyd Norris on Russia.</p>
        <p>Columns: William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E6</p>
        <p>TV Listings</p>
        <p>E7</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>A18</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
