<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Science Fiction</title>
    <meta content="03SCIFIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1074045"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jonas, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butler, Octavia E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zettel, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">McAuley, Paul J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gresh, Lois H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinberg, Robert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Parable of the Talents (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Playing God (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Invisible Country, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Termination Node, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Science Fiction</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E3DC1F3CF930A35752C0A96F958260" item-length="1144" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Science Fiction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gerald Jonas</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jonas, Gerald</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gerald Jonas reviews following books: Parable of the Talents by Octavia E Butler; Playing God by Sarah Zettel; The Invisible Country by Paul J McAuley; and The Termination Node by Lois H Gresh and Robert Weinberg (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Religion has always been a problem for science fiction writers. While they are occupationally biased toward rationality, their stock in trade is imagining plausible futures -- and no speculation about future societies can be complete without considering the evolution of current belief systems or the advent of entirely new religions. Yet few writers have taken this challenge seriously. When religion has not served merely as a symbol of irrational reaction, it has usually figured as window dressing -- a few hints of altered rituals or creeds to remind the reader that this is indeed ''the future.'' Among the memorable exceptions: Walter M. Miller Jr.'s ''Canticle for Leibowitz,'' James Blish's ''Case of Conscience,'' Frank Herbert's ''Dune'' series, Gene Wolfe's multivolume ''Book of the New Sun.'' Add to these Octavia E. Butler's PARABLE OF THE TALENTS (Seven Stories, $24.95), which continues and deepens the story she began five years ago in ''Parable of the Sower.''</p>
        <p>Once again, the protagonist is Lauren Oya Olamina, a 21st-century prophet, born, she believes, to bring a new kind of truth to troubled times. Reeling from environmental, political, financial and military blows, American society is just barely surviving in the opening years of the next millennium. The revelation that Olamina feels called upon to share can be summed up in two sentences: ''God is Change'' and ''The Destiny of Earthseed is to take root among the stars.'' ''Earthseed'' refers both to her new faith and to the small circle of believers she assembles through the force of her personality and her writings, which consist of aphoristic verses that couch revolutionary thoughts in deceptively simple words.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Religion has always been a problem for science fiction writers. While they are occupationally biased toward rationality, their stock in trade is imagining plausible futures -- and no speculation about future societies can be complete without considering the evolution of current belief systems or the advent of entirely new religions. Yet few writers have taken this challenge seriously. When religion has not served merely as a symbol of irrational reaction, it has usually figured as window dressing -- a few hints of altered rituals or creeds to remind the reader that this is indeed ''the future.'' Among the memorable exceptions: Walter M. Miller Jr.'s ''Canticle for Leibowitz,'' James Blish's ''Case of Conscience,'' Frank Herbert's ''Dune'' series, Gene Wolfe's multivolume ''Book of the New Sun.'' Add to these Octavia E. Butler's PARABLE OF THE TALENTS (Seven Stories, $24.95), which continues and deepens the story she began five years ago in ''Parable of the Sower.''</p>
        <p>Once again, the protagonist is Lauren Oya Olamina, a 21st-century prophet, born, she believes, to bring a new kind of truth to troubled times. Reeling from environmental, political, financial and military blows, American society is just barely surviving in the opening years of the next millennium. The revelation that Olamina feels called upon to share can be summed up in two sentences: ''God is Change'' and ''The Destiny of Earthseed is to take root among the stars.'' ''Earthseed'' refers both to her new faith and to the small circle of believers she assembles through the force of her personality and her writings, which consist of aphoristic verses that couch revolutionary thoughts in deceptively simple words.</p>
        <p>Butler's narrative skills are impressive. We follow the rise and fall of Earthseed's first communal home through a chorus of voices that jump around in time, giving us contrasting perspectives on the heartbreaking events that test the faith and will of the founding mother, her family and her adherents. Most remarkably, the ideas they espouse -- at the risk of their freedom and even their lives -- are presented with the respect they deserve. The tenets of Earthseed arise from a thought-provoking collaboration between the scientific and religious imaginations. As the founder's husband notes, ''Olamina believes in a god that does not in the least love her.'' Conceding that Earthseed ''isn't a very comforting belief system,'' Olamina achieves prophetic stature by insisting that in the long run the true test of a religion is whether the solace it offers conforms with the nature of the universe we live in.</p>
        <p>Despite its provocative title, PLAYING GOD (Aspect/Warner, $22), by Sarah Zettel, disappoints, because the author fails to take her stated theme seriously enough. In two previous novels, ''Reclamation'' and ''Fool's War,'' Zettel ranged across time and space with the bracing confidence of a latter-day Asimov or Heinlein. In ''Playing God,'' she focuses on the fate of a single planet and, paradoxically, loses her way.</p>
        <p>In a not-so-distant future, human beings have averted the destruction of the earth by splintering into competitive but mutually respectful political and economic entities called enclaves. A species of warlike aliens on a distant world has not been so lucky: after nearly destroying their ecosystem with biological and nuclear weapons, they find that their only hope for survival is a worldwide makeover proposed by Bioverse Incorporated Enclave. The project involves temporarily evacuating 1.3 billion aliens to giant orbiting spaceships, followed by ''full-scale bioremediation efforts to clean the planet up after two centuries of extremely dirty warfare.'' As if that were not difficult enough, the aliens suffer ''massive anaphylactic reactions'' from close contact with humans, so attempts to keep the mutually murderous clans from killing each other on the spaceships must be supervised from afar.</p>
        <p>The humans who devote themselves to this project must respect the alien culture while containing the aggressive tendencies inherent in it. I wish I could report that Zettel successfully dramatizes this problem. Unfortunately, she allows the situation to deteriorate into open conflict, which she then describes in prose that lacks the snap and conviction of her earlier books. Despite page after page of dutifully detailed description, I never got a clear picture of the aliens or their society. Even worse, I did not much care what happened to the humans whose efforts to ''play god'' give way, in the end, to all-too-predictable melodrama.</p>
        <p>If you are unfamiliar with the work of Paul J. McAuley, his new collection of stories, THE INVISIBLE COUNTRY (Eos/Avon, paper, $13.50), provides a useful introduction to this engaging writer. The title story, set in a grim near-future London, is told in a noirish style that might be characterized as ''bio-punk.'' A former professional biologist, McAuley conjures a world ravaged by global warming and a breakdown in social order exacerbated by the easy availability of intrusive biotechnology. In a convincing demonstration of his stylistic sleight of hand, he transmutes this nightmarish vision into a dream of utopia right under the reader's nose, so to speak.</p>
        <p>Four of the nine stories in this collection evoke a future (also encountered in McAuley's novel ''Fairyland'') in which ''dolls,'' gene-engineered humanoid creatures, serve as all-purpose slaves. By coming at this painful subject from the point of view of society's human outcasts, McAuley avoids the twin traps of facile moralizing and maudlin sentiment. Another story, ''Recording Angel,'' shares setting and theme with McAuley's recent novel ''Child of the River'' and casts some light on the confusing background of that work, the first in a promised trilogy.</p>
        <p>When I was 10 years old, I read a book entitled ''Tom Swift and His Electric Elephant Gun.'' I can still remember the thrill generated by the technological wonder of a superweapon that allowed Tom to subdue a ponderous pachyderm without actually killing it. A similar sense of wonder animates the recent crop of computer-driven techno-thrillers, of which THE TERMINATION NODE (Del Rey/Ballantine, $24), by Lois H. Gresh and Robert Weinberg, is a suitably breathless example.</p>
        <p>An evil mastermind is killing off computer hackers faster than you can say ''delete.'' Only the skills of a superhacker, Judy Carmody, known to her on-line friends as ''TerMight,'' can save the day -- not to mention the billions of dollars of electronic bank deposits about to vanish forever at the click of a mouse.</p>
        <p>I would not venture a guess about whether this Internet-savvy collaboration will stir feelings of wonder in today's young readers. I can only report that the book's series of brutal murders raised not so much as a hair on the back of my neck, since the authors failed to breathe life into these victims before they were dispatched.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
