<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Britain, Mosquitoes Look Like Scourge of Death</title>
    <meta content="15BUGS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1138042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macfarquhar, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DF173CF936A2575AC0A96F958260" item-length="712" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Britain, Mosquitoes Look Like Scourge of Death</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macfarquhar, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses coverage of New York City's encephalitis problems in British press; examples; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you happened to be tracking New York City's encephalitis problems from Britain for the last week, you might be forgiven for recoiling in horror at the Black Death devastating Gotham.</p>
        <p>''A Plague on New York: Panic as City Is Sprayed to Control Killer Mosquitoes'' screamed The Daily Mail, a tabloid. ''Helicopters Attack Killer Biting the Big Apple,'' bellowed The Express, another tabloid, and The Evening Standard, a third tabloid, warned darkly, ''New York in Fight Against Deadly Brain Bug.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you happened to be tracking New York City's encephalitis problems from Britain for the last week, you might be forgiven for recoiling in horror at the Black Death devastating Gotham.</p>
        <p>''A Plague on New York: Panic as City Is Sprayed to Control Killer Mosquitoes'' screamed The Daily Mail, a tabloid. ''Helicopters Attack Killer Biting the Big Apple,'' bellowed The Express, another tabloid, and The Evening Standard, a third tabloid, warned darkly, ''New York in Fight Against Deadly Brain Bug.''</p>
        <p>If the headlines were not frightening enough, the articles surely were. ''Panic swept New York last night as a plague of mosquitoes killed three people and left 57 more fighting for their lives,'' The Daily Mail wrote breathlessly. ''Helicopters were weaving in and out of skyscrapers, dousing the city's streets with powerful insecticide.''</p>
        <p>City residents were described as rushing to railroad stations to get away, or cowering indoors so as not to be infected. Those unlucky enough to get sick were depicted as keeling over from seizures, paralysis, fever and brain swelling.</p>
        <p>Some papers seemed slightly pleased that Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, apparently famous abroad for his quality-of-life crackdowns, had met a pest he might not be able to lick.</p>
        <p>''The tough New York Mayor has beaten crime, squeegee merchants and, bizarrely, ferret owners who want him to overturn his ban on keeping them as pets,'' wrote a reporter for The Express. ''Now he may finally have met his match.'' The mosquitoes, the report went on to say, have proved ''immune to the zero tolerance he successfully displays to most other irritants.''</p>
        <p>One paper, the sometimes sober, sometimes sensational Times, even talked as if it were a contest between insects and politics. ''The giant political ambitions of Rudolph Giuliani, the Mayor of New York, are under attack from a swarm of mosquitoes spreading fear and disease throughout the city,'' its report said.</p>
        <p>The articles indicated that no matter where the suffering seven million went, they could not escape. ''Subway trains are filled with the smell of insect repellent as New Yorkers generally heed requests to spray themselves,'' The Express said.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, some wrote admiringly that New Yorkers were steely enough to disregard the whole thing. ''Normally neurotic New Yorkers, who dash to the dermatologists at the slightest sign of a pimple, largely ignored the goings-on,'' wrote a correspondent for The Scotsman.</p>
        <p>Just as interesting were the explanations of why New York had been visited by this plague, perhaps even deserved it. One writer in The Daily Telegraph said it was because smoking was so commonly banned in the city. Mosquitoes would stay away, he said, if only there was more cigarette smoke in the air.</p>
        <p>A reporter in The Guardian explained that it all stemmed from global warming. New York was well on its way to becoming Kuala Lumpur, the story surmised, because unstable weather in the northern half of the globe was allowing pests and diseases to migrate north.</p>
        <p>And then there was the odd pun or joke about past menaces, real or imagined. ''The city that thrives on buzz has found a version it wants to go away fast,'' The Express said. ''At least you could see Godzilla.''</p>
        <p>Still, all the hoopla did not seem to be deterring travel plans. Both British Airways and Virgin Atlantic Airways said there had been no perceptible drop in reservations. If the airlines did get questions about a menace, it was one farther south.</p>
        <p>''We haven't gotten any calls on the mosquitoes,'' Christine Pilson of Virgin Atlantic said. ''The issue of the moment seems to be Hurricane Floyd.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
