<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parasites, Not Pollution, May Produce Frog Deformities</title>
    <meta content="Y30FRO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1103972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parasites</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Parasites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parasites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0D8103DF933A05757C0A96F958260" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parasites, Not Pollution, May Produce Frog Deformities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists report that they have found evidence that frog deformities that have been found in rising number of frogs around country are being caused not by toxic substances but by parasitic worms; findings discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trailing tangles of a dozen limbs or missing legs altogether, the deformed frogs found in rising numbers around the country have become a powerful symbol of what many fear is an ever more poisoned environment. But at least in some areas, scientists report today, evidence shows that the frog deformities are being caused not by toxic substances but by parasitic worms.</p>
        <p>In two new studies focusing on  Pacific tree frogs in California, separate teams of researchers report in the journal Science that when parasitic worms known as trematodes burrow into a frog's developing limb, the infestation can cause exactly the kinds of deformities seen in frogs in the wild. Scientists say the studies provide the first solid evidence pointing to a culprit behind the long mysterious deformities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trailing tangles of a dozen limbs or missing legs altogether, the deformed frogs found in rising numbers around the country have become a powerful symbol of what many fear is an ever more poisoned environment. But at least in some areas, scientists report today, evidence shows that the frog deformities are being caused not by toxic substances but by parasitic worms.</p>
        <p>In two new studies focusing on  Pacific tree frogs in California, separate teams of researchers report in the journal Science that when parasitic worms known as trematodes burrow into a frog's developing limb, the infestation can cause exactly the kinds of deformities seen in frogs in the wild. Scientists say the studies provide the first solid evidence pointing to a culprit behind the long mysterious deformities.</p>
        <p>''We've finally solved one piece of the puzzle,'' said Dr. Stanley K. Sessions, the lead author of one of the new papers and a herpetologist at Hartwick College in Oneonta, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Dr. Andrew Blaustein, an ecologist at Oregon State University who was not involved with the new studies, said: ''This is the best experimental evidence so far showing a particular agent causing the limb deformities we see in nature. I think parasites will explain a lot of the deformities.''</p>
        <p>Researchers interviewed, including Dr. Sessions and Pieter T. J. Johnson, lead author of the other new paper, all emphasized that the new findings did not rule out the possibility that chemical pollutants or increasing ultraviolet light caused by a thinning ozone layer could be causes of deformities elsewhere.</p>
        <p>''Maybe the people next to the ponds they studied can breathe a sigh of relief,'' said Dr. Judy Helgen, a research scientist at the Minnesota Pollution Control Agency in St. Paul, ''but everywhere else we have to be vigilant. It would be irresponsible to sit back now and say, 'Oh, no, it's not a chemical cause.' ''</p>
        <p>Researchers said most of the scientific community had ignored or even ridiculed the idea that parasites could create deformities. The big laboratories and big money were focused on chemicals and, to some degree, ultraviolet radiation. So far, though, researchers say, while there is much evidence that chemicals can cause some kinds of limb deformities in the laboratory, there has been little to show that chemicals are actually deforming frogs in the wild.</p>
        <p>''This will cause a lot of soul-searching,'' Dr. David Wake, a herpetologist at University of California at Berkeley, said of the new studies. ''A lot of people will have to re-evaluate what they're doing.''</p>
        <p>Working without high-powered competition, two teams of mostly undergraduates were able to uncover the importance of parasites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson was an undergraduate at Stanford University when he carried out his experiments on Pacific tree frogs, or Hyla regilla, with two undergraduates and one post-doctoral colleague. His team showed that frogs exposed to higher concentrations of the trematode Ribeiroia had greater numbers of deformities and died at a higher rate.</p>
        <p>In the other paper, Dr. Sessions and two undergraduates provided corroborating evidence from five species of frogs from 12 sites in Arizona, California, New York and Oregon. All their deformed frogs were infected with the trematodes around the bases of their limbs.</p>
        <p>In Minnesota, where there have been the greatest concerns about frog deformities and water quality, Dr. Helgen said there remained no clear-cut cause.</p>
        <p>In spite of the new study, she said, ''for us, chemicals are the leading hypothesis.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Helgen said her collaborators had found no sign of Ribeiroia in the Minnesota frogs, nor any sign of a connection at their study sites between parasites and deformities.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sessions' study has also revived a longstanding controversy  over the role of a hotly debated class of chemicals, retinoids, which can be dangerous to humans. Dr. Sessions' group argued that the types of multiple-limb deformities it saw in wild frogs, because of their structural details, could not have been produced by retinoids.</p>
        <p>But Dr. David Gardiner, a developmental biologist at the University of California at Irvine, said Dr. Sessions' paper had employed ''absolutely too narrow a description of what retinoic acid can do.''</p>
        <p>''These studies don't resolve anything,'' Dr. Gardiner said.</p>
        <p>Researchers said that while the deformed amphibians, which typically die before reaching sexual maturity, added pressure on amphibian populations, there did not seem to be any direct connection between deformities and worldwide declines in amphibians. Hot spots for die-offs, researchers agreed, do not correlate well with hot spots for deformities.</p>
        <p>In spite of the discovery of the role of parasites, biologists, including those behind the new studies, say both deformities and population declines should still be viewed as signals that something may be amiss. Researchers said human-induced changes, including pollution, could well have led to increases in parasite-induced deformities, causing parasites to increase in number or frogs to become more susceptible.</p>
        <p>''Our study does not eliminate water quality from being an issue on the national level,'' Mr. Johnson said. ''We're not signaling the all-clear.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
