<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coal's Hot Competition Forges a Breed of Giants</title>
    <meta content="21COAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1086822"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Long, William R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D6173DF932A15751C0A96F958260" item-length="1172" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coal's Hot Competition Forges a Breed of Giants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM R. LONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Long, William R</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US coal industry is increasingly controlled by well-financed, sharply focused companies, with top 10 companies now controlling 61 percent of nation's output, up from 35 percent in 1988; causes include changes in mining technology that require economies of scale, practices of electric utilities, which have tripled their coal consumption since 1970, and the fact that smaller operators are at disadvantage bargainging with railroads; profit margins are squeezed as lucrative long-term contracts written in 1970's and 80's expire and utilities demand progressively lower rates in new contracts; photo; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COAL mining is no longer a huge industry but its role in the economy is still crucial. That is because coal is burned to generate more than half the electricity produced by American power companies.</p>
        <p>But it has been difficult to make money in coal, partly because there is simply so much of it and partly because of environmental regulations. So with overproduction and competition helping to hold prices down, many mines are going on the block, while a few giants are seizing the opportunity to gain even bigger market share.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COAL mining is no longer a huge industry but its role in the economy is still crucial. That is because coal is burned to generate more than half the electricity produced by American power companies.</p>
        <p>But it has been difficult to make money in coal, partly because there is simply so much of it and partly because of environmental regulations. So with overproduction and competition helping to hold prices down, many mines are going on the block, while a few giants are seizing the opportunity to gain even bigger market share.</p>
        <p>''It has been a very brutally competitive business,'' said Steven F. Leer, chief executive of Arch Coal Inc. and chairman of the National Mining Association. ''People have become very efficient in their mining techniques, and now you're seeing those efficiency drives spill over to the consolidation and trying to reduce overhead.''</p>
        <p>The top 10 companies control 61 percent of the nation's coal output, up from 35 percent in 1988, according to a study by Arch, now the country's No. 2 coal producer behind the Peabody Holding Company. And experts predict that the consolidation trend will continue. Among the latest companies to offer their coal interests for sale are Chevron, the oil industry giant, and Cyprus Amax Minerals, a copper mining company.</p>
        <p>The reshuffling has multiple causes, including changes in mining technology and in the practices of electric utilities. Like some other industries, coal is increasingly dominated by well-financed, sharply focused large companies.</p>
        <p>Acquisitions by Peabody, which is based in St. Louis, have helped strengthen its lead. It had 13.8 percent of total production in 1998, up from 7.5 percent a decade ago.  Peabody itself was bought last year by Lehman Merchant Banking Partners II for $2.3 billion.</p>
        <p>Arch, also based in St. Louis, has jumped from No. 16 in 1996 to No. 2, with 9.7 percent of production, by merging with Ashland Coal and acquiring the ARCO coal unit of  Atlantic Richfield for $1.7 billion. Kennecott Energy of Gillette, Wyo., a subsidiary of Rio Tinto P.L.C., a mining giant based in London, became No. 3 by buying several large mines in Wyoming.</p>
        <p>Now up for sale are the rest of Cyprus Amax Coal and Chevron's Pittsburg &amp; Midway Coal Mining, both based in Englewood, Colo., a suburb of Denver.</p>
        <p>The coal tonnage used by utilities has nearly tripled since 1970, but no one worries about running out of supply. The United States still has more than 1,000 recoverable tons of coal for every resident, enough to last more than 250 years at current rates of consumption.</p>
        <p>Consolidation in coal mining offers economies of scale beyond the usual savings on shared overhead. Big improvements in productivity, like the use of ''longwall'' mining machines for underground work and heavy earth-moving equipment for surface mines, have pushed the amount of capital needed to open a competitive mine beyond the means of smaller producers.</p>
        <p>Smaller coal companies also have a disadvantage in negotiating freight rates, said Daniel A. Roling, a senior metals and mining analyst with Merrill Lynch in New York. ''If you only are a one-mine company shipping on one railroad, you have no leverage, and you're going to pay dearly to move your coal,'' Mr. Roling said.</p>
        <p>The same goes for negotiating coal prices with utilities. ''The customers keep consolidating and getting bigger,'' he added. ''If you're going to have any kind of negotiating strength, you have to negotiate from size.''</p>
        <p>Profit margins are being squeezed as lucrative long-term contracts written in the 1970's and 80's expire and utilities demand  progressively lower rates in new contracts.</p>
        <p>''There is a mad scramble to reduce the cost of power production,'' said Gerald E. Vaninetti of Resource Data International, an energy market research and service company in Boulder, Colo. ''The last couple of years it has really gotten intense.''</p>
        <p>HE Federal Clean Air Act, meanwhile, has pushed utilities away from coal with high sulfur content, mined in  northern Appalachia, the Middle West and other areas, in favor of low-sulfur Western coal, especially from the vast Powder River Basin of Wyoming and Montana. Compared with coal mined underground in the East, Powder River coal produces less heat per ton, but it is much cheaper to extract with surface mining and is cheaper for Midwestern utilities to burn even after shipping costs are included.</p>
        <p>As a result, production is steadily shifting west. The National Mining Association calculates that coal mines west of the Mississippi will produce 546 million tons in 1999, approaching the 575 million tons from the East. Coal production in the East has been flat since 1980, while Western production has more than doubled.</p>
        <p>''The West is going to capture all additional growth,'' said J. Chris Leshock, an energy forecaster at Resource Data International.</p>
        <p>That trend is reinforced by Phase 2 of the Clean Air Act, which will cut sharply the allowable sulfur dioxide emissions from most generating plants, starting next January.</p>
        <p>Some utilities have installed ''scrubbers,'' which reduce pollution, in coal-burning plants, to meet the new requirements while still burning high-sulfur coal. Some have bought emission credits that allow their plants to exceed the standards. But most have found it more economical to switch to low-sulfur coal, or use a blend of the two.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leshock said that demand for coal to generate electric power would continue to grow, because coal remains cheaper than natural gas, but that nearly all the growth would be at existing coal-fired plants, which tend to have ample excess capacity.</p>
        <p>Most coal analysts say there is only a remote chance the United States will impose tough curbs on carbon dioxide emissions, as outlined in the 1997 Kyoto Protocol, aimed at curtailing greenhouse gases. The National Mining Association has deplored the Clinton Administration's signing of the pact and opposes Senate ratification. Mr. Leshock said the Kyoto restrictions ''could wipe out something on the order of one-third of the U.S. coal industry'' and ''make it uneconomical overnight.''</p>
        <p>Kyoto aside, coal is a ''dog-eat-dog industry'' but one where the big dogs can be healthy, said Joel Price, an energy consultant in the Denver suburb of Lakewood. ''Those that can hang on long enough,'' Mr. Price said, ''will divide up the spoils -- not get rich, but do fine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
