<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kisii Journal; Malaria, a Swamp Dweller, Finds a Hillier Home</title>
    <meta content="Y21KEN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1124957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kisii (Kenya)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kenya</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Malaria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D91F3FF932A15754C0A96F958260" item-length="1300" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kisii Journal; Malaria, a Swamp Dweller, Finds a Hillier Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>KISII, Kenya, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kisii, Kenya, is center of serious malaria outbreak; experts are particularly concerned because city's altitude, nearly 6,000 feet, was considered too high for mosquitoes that spread malaria parasite; problem in Kisii underscores how disease is changing and spreading in Africa to new areas; resistance to various drugs is also rising steeply; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ward 6 in the hospital here could not be much more crowded: Bethsheba Bosibori, 52, lay in bed with a woman she did not know, with another sitting at her feet and a third coughing on a mat on the floor. In all, 113 women were packed into a room with 23 beds.</p>
        <p>''If they are small, there can be three'' in a bed, said Sister Elizabeth Maranga, a nurse. ''Big bodies -- only two.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ward 6 in the hospital here could not be much more crowded: Bethsheba Bosibori, 52, lay in bed with a woman she did not know, with another sitting at her feet and a third coughing on a mat on the floor. In all, 113 women were packed into a room with 23 beds.</p>
        <p>''If they are small, there can be three'' in a bed, said Sister Elizabeth Maranga, a nurse. ''Big bodies -- only two.''</p>
        <p>This small city in western Kenya is the center of a serious outbreak of malaria, one of the worst in recent years, and all the more worrisome to experts because malaria has not usually been a widespread problem here. At an altitude of nearly 6,000 feet, Kisii had been considered too high for the mosquitoes that harbor the parasites that spread the sickness to live very long.</p>
        <p>But since May, more than 300 people have died of malaria in this regional hospital alone, among some 18,000 cases the staff has seen. Several hundred more -- no one is sure how many -- have died elsewhere.</p>
        <p>One million people die in Africa each year from malaria, the second biggest killer on the continent, after AIDS, according to the United Nations. The problems here in Kisii underscore how the disease is changing and spreading on the continent.</p>
        <p>For reasons not fully understood, doctors say, the disease seems to be moving to higher altitudes and to other places where transmission has been low. Resistance to various drugs used for treating the disease, particularly chloroquine, is also rising steeply.</p>
        <p>Unusual rain patterns since last year's El Nino storms also seem to be driving the numbers upward. Here in Kisii it rarely rains this time of year, but on a recent day, it poured down, draining into pools of water that stagnate and breed the mosquitoes that carry the malaria parasite.</p>
        <p>''When you think it will disappear, then it rains again,'' said Dr. Wycliffe N. Mogoa, a pediatrician and the medical superintendent here at Kisii District Hospital. ''There will be more stagnant water, the mosquitoes will hatch and there will be problems again.''</p>
        <p>The rains have been so irregular that the outbreak has stretched out for longer than three months. Last year, the worst year in memory for malaria in Kenya because of El Nino rains, the outbreak lasted only a month and a half, Dr. Mogoa said.</p>
        <p>The outbreak has been especially hard on children and on women weakened from recent childbirth. But no one is immune. On a recent day, on a hill in a village near here, Machoge Akunga, a farmer about 50 years old, lay dead under a gray blanket on a straw mat, his wife and sister waiting next to the body inside their hut. He had 11 children.</p>
        <p>His family said he came down with a headache, fever and dizziness, and his joints became sore, all symptoms of malaria. But they did not take him to a doctor.</p>
        <p>''It didn't seem serious,'' said his niece, Kemunto, 26. Three days later, at noon, he died.</p>
        <p>Doctors say poverty and lack of information about malaria help it spread, and both problems were evident at Mr. Akunga's hut. His cousin, Samuel Kebwarwo, also has malaria but said he was turned away from a hospital because he could not afford treatment, which costs a little more than $1.50.</p>
        <p>In the crowd of perhaps two dozen people there, no one could say exactly how malaria was spread or how to prevent it.</p>
        <p>''If you have experience,'' Mr. Akunga's niece said to visitors, ''maybe you can explain it.''</p>
        <p>Cases of malaria in the highlands of western Kenya have been rising slowly over the last five years, including in Kisii, and it remains a mystery exactly why, said Col. Ronald Rosenberg, commander of the United States Army Medical Research Unit, which is studying malaria in Kenya.</p>
        <p>One possible theory that appears not to be borne out is global warming, which would theoretically create better conditions for mosquitoes, he said. An analysis of 65 years of hospital admissions in the nearby town of Kericho, at roughly the same altitude as Kisii, showed that climate was unrelated to the number of malaria cases reported.</p>
        <p>Colonel Rosenberg said he believes drug resistance and unusual rains, at least in the last two years, are major reasons. He theorized a third: that public transportation has improved, and people in the highlands are traveling more often to malaria-infected areas and returning sick.</p>
        <p>''That's kind of a sociological explanation that may have some truth to it,'' he said. ''It's probably not everything but it could be a contributing factor.''</p>
        <p>But what makes the disease worse still -- often to the point where it cannot be treated -- is that people often take only pain relievers or go to herbalists or even quacks, cheaper than most real doctors, said Dr. Bart De Porter, field coordinator in Kisii for the French branch of Doctors Without Borders.</p>
        <p>''If it works, they don't come to us,'' Dr. De Porter said.</p>
        <p>International aid groups have camped themselves in Kisii, sending in doctors like Dr. De Porter as well as drugs and mattresses.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, the outbreak has become a political issue. Local politicians have accused President Daniel arap Moi of purposely not controlling the epidemic as a way of punishing  one of his most formidable challengers, the former Finance Minister, Simeon Nyachae. He represents this district in Parliament.</p>
        <p>To show his concern, Mr. Moi toured the hospital here last week, and it was bursting with patients -- 800 people were here, when the capacity is only 250. Aid organizations say that the medical staff at a nearby Government health center was reinforced only briefly, seemingly as a show for his visit.</p>
        <p>But Dr. Mogoa said the Government has responded well.</p>
        <p>''The President had come to assess a serious epidemic in good faith,'' he said. ''And instead of local politicians joining him, they are making noise, and in the end they have never stepped foot in this hospital, which belongs to them. You can't play politics with an epidemic.''</p>
        <p>Still Kenya's health officials say they do not have enough drugs, doctors or transportation to cope with the crisis. In frustration, they are focusing their hope on better education about malaria in the future -- which drug companies and some international health agencies and researchers hope someday will also include a vaccine and aid groups hope will include greater use of preventive measures like mosquito nets.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, doctors say July is shaping up to be the worst month yet this year. On a recent evening, an 8-year-old boy, Richard Mukuya, lay in a malaria-induced coma, his hand held by his father, Anthony. Mrs. Bosibori lay in the crowded women's ward and said many people she knew were infected with malaria, including several of her grandchildren.</p>
        <p>''I have never seen so many people sick with malaria,'' she said.</p>
        <p>At nightfall, a hard and steady rain began, the drops pounding on the ward's tin roof, making it impossible to hear anything else and dripping into yet more puddles for mosquitoes to breed and spread sickness.</p>
        <p>''This is very bad news,'' Dr. De Porter said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
