<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NORTHEAST STATES SOFTENING STANCE ON AIR STANDARDS</title>
    <meta content="28ENVI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1133731"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ozone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New England States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cahill, John P (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6DE133BF93BA1575BC0A96F958260" item-length="1357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NORTHEAST STATES SOFTENING STANCE ON AIR STANDARDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, Aug. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Northeastern states, led by New York, propose to settle long-running dispute over smokestack pollution from Midwest, and accept less stringent standards on windborne pollutants; states have EPA encouragement to negotiate ways to meet criteria of Clean Air Act; less stringent standard would still mandate significant reduction in nitrogen oxides that travel east and contribute to ozone and acid rain; New York commissioner John P Cahil takes lead; environmentalists are furious at apparent retreat, charging New York Gov George Pataki is trying to enhance his stature within Republican party by taking pro-business stance; Cahill insists litigation is still possible (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After years of battling over smokestack pollution that blows from the Midwest and the South, Northeastern states, led by New York, have signaled for the first time a willingness to retreat from their demands that other states significantly reduce their emissions.</p>
        <p>A proposal by the Northeastern states for settling the dispute, drafted in the wake of legal setbacks, would accept emissions of a key class of pollutants by Midwestern and Southern industries at a rate 67 percent higher than the Northeastern states had demanded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After years of battling over smokestack pollution that blows from the Midwest and the South, Northeastern states, led by New York, have signaled for the first time a willingness to retreat from their demands that other states significantly reduce their emissions.</p>
        <p>A proposal by the Northeastern states for settling the dispute, drafted in the wake of legal setbacks, would accept emissions of a key class of pollutants by Midwestern and Southern industries at a rate 67 percent higher than the Northeastern states had demanded.</p>
        <p>The states, with the encouragement of the Environmental Protection Agency, have been negotiating methods of meeting the criteria of the Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>The less stringent standard, introduced by negotiators for the Northeastern states on Tuesday and Wednesday in Washington, would still mandate a significant reduction in the pollutants, nitrogen oxides. The nitrogen oxides travel east and northeast on the prevailing winds, and contribute to ozone and to acid rain in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>''It's just an option that all the states agreed to take back and discuss,'' said John P. Cahill, New York's Environmental Conservation Commissioner, who represented the state in the talks. He described it as ''something that was worked on by all the states of the Northeast.''</p>
        <p>But officials of other states involved in the talks, along with environmentalists who closely follow them, said the Pataki administration had taken the lead in creating the new stance.</p>
        <p>While the representatives of the 10 other Northeastern states knew the proposal was to be floated as a trial balloon, it was not clear whether their states would accept the standard in the long run.</p>
        <p>New York's position carries great weight, and Mr. Cahill has acted as the region's lead negotiator in the talks with 14 states in the Midwest and South.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are furious at the apparent retreat. ''Anyone concerned with clean air and health would have huge reason to be outraged by this,'' said Peter Iwanowicz, director of environmental health for the American Lung Association of New York State.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Cahill suggested that a deal with the other regions may be the best the Northeastern states can attain, though he insisted that the Northeast has not given up hope that its original position might prevail. The E.P.A., which has taken the side of the Northeastern states, had been moving to impose the more stringent standard on the other regions through its regulatory power, but after two recent setbacks in court, the E.P.A. has pressed the states on both sides to reach a compromise.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists and state officials saw politics behind the shift. ''A negotiated deal is a big group hug among all these Republican governors,'' said a top environmental official with one of the Northeastern states, who spoke on the condition that his name and his state not be used. He said that Gov. George E. Pataki, who would like to be considered for the Republican vice presidential nomination, ''would get a lot of the credit'' for a compromise.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that as Mr. Pataki tries to enhance his stature within the national Republican Party, it cannot help him to be involved in a dispute with other Republican governors, particularly when his pro-environment stance could be portrayed as anti-business. Among the Northeastern states, six governors are Republicans, four are Democrats and one is an independent. Among the Southern and Midwestern states, seven governors are Republicans and seven are Democrats.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists argue that New York and the Northeastern states still have an important weapon left in their arsenal: they can sue under the 1990 amendments to the Clean Air Act to force action by the E.P.A. and the other states.</p>
        <p>As a general rule, it is New York's Attorney General, Eliot L. Spitzer, a Democrat, not the Governor, who decides the state's position in litigation, and Mr. Spitzer might be able to pursue a lawsuit on the emission standards even if Mr. Pataki is unwilling. Officials in Mr. Spitzer's office said they were still studying the new proposal from the Northeastern states.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cahill said, ''No one is taking any option off the table,'' including litigation.</p>
        <p>At the same time, E.P.A. officials fear that if they try to impose a tougher standard on the Midwest and South, rather than striking a deal, the process could drag past the 2000 election, when there might be a Republican administration inclined to drop the matter entirely. Environmentalists say that those same E.P.A. officials do not want a pitched regional dispute to hinder Vice President Al Gore's Presidential bid.</p>
        <p>Northeastern states have long complained that their high levels of nitrogen oxides are largely attributable to industries, particularly electric power plants, in the Midwest and South, a claim supported by the E.P.A. and by independent studies.</p>
        <p>All the major urban areas of the Northeast, especially New York City and its suburbs, fail to meet the Clean Air Act standards for ozone pollution, which burns the eyes, stings the lungs and can, over time, contribute to serious health problems like asthma.</p>
        <p>Over the last five years, 11 Northeastern states have filed petitions with the E.P.A., asking it to force industries in states to the west and south to meet, by 2003, a standard of 0.15 pounds of nitrogen oxide emissions for every million British thermal units of fuel consumption in the summer, when ozone is at its worst.</p>
        <p>The Northeastern states have all agreed to move to the 0.15 standard, regardless of what other states do. That has raised fears in the power industry, which is moving to more freewheeling competition among power producers, that Northeastern power plants, forced to adopt expensive emission controls, could be put at a disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Negotiators for the Midwest and South have proposed a standard of 0.25 pounds, 67 percent higher. Under the proposal made this week, the Northeastern states would accept that, at least at first, with a 0.25 standard by 2003, and a later reduction to 0.2. That marked the first time the Northeastern states have signaled that they would accept anything less stringent than 0.15, and officials with some of those states said they were not sure their states could actually agree to the proposal.</p>
        <p>In the Northeast, where state rules are among the strictest in the nation, many power plants and factories already operate within the 0.15 standard. New York's Department of Environmental Conservation said that the statewide average is about 0.2.</p>
        <p>In some Midwestern states, the average is two or three times as high. Even the 0.25 standard would require many power plants and factories in the South and the Midwest to install costly pollution control devices, and the stricter the standard, the more expensive it would be.</p>
        <p>If all the regions cut emissions to 0.15, New York estimates, summertime nitrogen oxide levels in the New York metropolitan region would drop by about 80 percent. At 0.25, the decline would be more than 65 percent -- significant, but not enough to get the metropolitan area into compliance with ozone standards.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. said last year that it would impose the 0.15 standard, but several Midwestern states and utilities challenged that decision in court. In May, the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia ruled that the E.P.A. had to establish the merits of its nitrogen oxide standards before it forced states to submit plans for reducing emissions. An earlier ruling by the court said the E.P.A. had not justified its standards on ozone and soot.</p>
        <p>Given the court's decision, Mr. Cahill said, the Northeastern states might not be able to rely on the E.P.A. ''The uncertainty of the court ruling certainly is giving all parties reason to pause,'' he said.</p>
        <p>David R. Wooley, counsel to the Clean Air Task Force and a professor of environmental law at Pace University, said that Mr. Cahill's fear is understandable, but unwarranted. Like other environmentalists, he argued that a negotiated settlement could be unenforceable -- a worry that Mr. Cahill acknowledged might be well-founded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
