<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Gun in Mosquito War Gets Its Bug Without Poison</title>
    <meta content="19TRAP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1139066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pesticides and Pests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Biophysics Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Encephalitis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mosquitoes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pesticides</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E7DE113CF93AA2575AC0A96F958260" item-length="632" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Gun in Mosquito War Gets Its Bug Without Poison</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City overlooks Mosquito Magnet in battle against St Louis encephalitis; device, marketed by American Biophysics, emits a plume of carbon dioxide that attracts mosquitoes, which it then sucks into a small vacuum, where they dehydrate and die within a day; uses no poisons and eliminates risk of breeding a pesticide-resistant strain of insect; each device, about the size of a gas barbeque, can control mosquitoes in an area of one acre (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As New York City relies on pesticides to battle St. Louis encephalitis, it has overlooked new technology for controlling mosquitoes that uses no poisons and eliminates the risk of breeding a pesticide-resistant strain of insect.</p>
        <p>The device is about the size of a gas barbecue, and it emits a plume of carbon dioxide that attracts mosquitoes. The device then sucks them into a small vacuum, where they dehydrate and die within a day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As New York City relies on pesticides to battle St. Louis encephalitis, it has overlooked new technology for controlling mosquitoes that uses no poisons and eliminates the risk of breeding a pesticide-resistant strain of insect.</p>
        <p>The device is about the size of a gas barbecue, and it emits a plume of carbon dioxide that attracts mosquitoes. The device then sucks them into a small vacuum, where they dehydrate and die within a day.</p>
        <p>American Biophysics, based in East Greenwich, R.I., is marketing the device over the Internet under the name Mosquito Magnet.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard bought six of the devices and has ordered six more for use at its station on Great Inagua in the Bahamas, where the Air Force found the mosquito problem so bad that it decided the island was uninhabitable, said Lieut. Russ Hellstern, a spokesman for the Coast Guard station in Clearwater, Fla.</p>
        <p>''Since they put in those mosquito machines, you can actually walk outside without being completely attacked,'' Lieutenant Hellstern said. ''It's amazing.''</p>
        <p>The technology was developed during the last seven years by industry and government researchers at the Agricultural Research Service laboratory in Gainesville, Fla., as part of an effort to develop ways to repel insects without using poisons. It was this pest-control unit that invented DEET, the most commonly used insect repellent in America.</p>
        <p>''The advances in terms of effectiveness in the last five years are pretty amazing,'' said Donald R. Barnard, research leader of the Mosquito and Fly Research Unit at the laboratory. He said that about three million pounds of insecticides are released into the atmosphere each year in the United States, and that Americans spend roughly $67 million a year on pest control.</p>
        <p>Malathion, the pesticide being used in New York, is considered one of the safest, but Dr. Barnard said a greater risk than the chemical's effect on people was the possibility that mosquitoes might adapt to it and become resistant.</p>
        <p>The director of the city's Office of Emergency Management, Jerome M. Hauer, said through a spokesman: ''The middle of a crisis is not the time to evaluate new technologies. We are going with technologies recommended by the State Department of Health, the Federal Government, as well as experts in the field.'' He said the Mayor's office would ''be happy to take a look at'' alternatives to pesticides in the future.</p>
        <p>The model of the device now being produced uses a catalytic converter to turn propane gas into carbon dioxide. A mosquito takes carbon dioxide to be the mark of a blood-bearing mammal, and flies toward what it believes is a meal. Researchers found, however, that an even more powerful attractant was a chemical in the breath of oxen and cattle, and so it was added to the carbon dioxide emitted by the Mosquito Magnet.</p>
        <p>Company officials said each machine could control mosquitoes in an area of one acre. Dan Kline, who tests the machines for the Federal Agriculture Department, said the Magnet had been tested only in enclosed areas, where it collected ''almost all'' the mosquitoes released.</p>
        <p>The trap is not likely to solve New York's problem by itself, experts think, but sensible placement of the devices could sharply reduce the need for pesticides and repellents, they say. In a park, for example, they could be put near sewers, drains and ponds, where mosquitoes breed.</p>
        <p>A second company, Biosensory Inc., of Willimantic, Conn., is expected to begin producing traps using similar methods next year, said James Nolen, president of the company. His product will look more like an 18-inch-tall bird, and be called the Dragonfly, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
