<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GORE VOWS TO BAN NEW OIL DRILLING ALONG TWO COASTS</title>
    <meta content="22GORE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1147317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Offshore Exploration and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Property</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E6DF1E39F931A15753C1A96F958260" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GORE VOWS TO BAN NEW OIL DRILLING ALONG TWO COASTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>RYE, N.H., Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore says that as President he would ban any new offshore drilling for oil and gas along California and Florida coasts; Pres Clinton last year extended moratorium on drilling first imposed by Pres Bush; proposal by Gore, who is battling Bill Bradley for support of environmental groups, would go beyond that to apply to companies that have already bought billions of dollars of new leases but have not yet started drilling; such a ban could be implemented by executive order, but it would immediately set stage for major legal challenges to a Gore Administration; there are 36 existing leases off California, 146 off Florida (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore said today that as President he would ban any new offshore drilling for oil and gas along the California and Florida coasts.</p>
        <p>President Clinton last year extended a moratorium on drilling first imposed by President Bush. But the proposal by Mr. Gore, who is battling his Presidential rival, Bill Bradley, for the support of environmental groups, would go beyond that to apply to companies that have already bought billions of dollars worth of leases but have not yet started drilling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore said today that as President he would ban any new offshore drilling for oil and gas along the California and Florida coasts.</p>
        <p>President Clinton last year extended a moratorium on drilling first imposed by President Bush. But the proposal by Mr. Gore, who is battling his Presidential rival, Bill Bradley, for the support of environmental groups, would go beyond that to apply to companies that have already bought billions of dollars worth of leases but have not yet started drilling.</p>
        <p>Such a ban could be implemented by executive order, but it would immediately set the stage for major legal challenges to a Gore Administration. There are 36 existing leases off California, 146 off Florida.</p>
        <p>The ban would not cover drilling in Gulf Coast states other than Florida, where oil and gas exploration is central to the economy and more accepted by government officials and residents, or off the Alaskan coast.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore portrayed his proposal, for which he said he expected to be ''attacked,'' as being part of a bold environmental agenda that he promised would be the centerpiece of his Presidential campaign. The campaign was preparing to broadcast in California tonight a new 30-second  commercial on the drilling issue.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to worry about oil washing up on the shores of Santa Barbara or Monterey or on any coast, east or west, or on the coast of Florida,'' he said in a speech to environmentalists here that was also carried via satellite to a group in California.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's pledge to limit drilling is part of an urgent effort by his campaign to capture the support of the nation's major environmental groups, which so far have not endorsed anyone. This is a blow to the Vice President, a longtime environmentalist whom many perceive as a natural ally of the environmental movement.</p>
        <p>By playing hard to get, the groups have forced Mr. Gore to make promises that go beyond the Clinton Administration's policies. It is a tactic that organized labor also used before the A.F.L.-C.I.O. endorsed the Vice President at its annual meeting earlier this month.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists have been reluctant to jump behind Mr. Gore in part because of what many see as the Administration's mixed record. They complain that over the years, the White House has not done enough to fight global warming or restrict logging on public lands.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists also consider Bill Bradley, Mr. Gore's sole rival for the Democratic Presidential nomination, a staunch ally. Mr. Bradley, in fact, received higher ratings in the Senate for his work on environmental issues than Mr. Gore did when he served there.</p>
        <p>There is also concern among environmentalists, as there is more broadly among Democrats, that Mr. Gore may not be able to win a general election against Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, the Republican front-runner, and so they would be better off not making an endorsement.</p>
        <p>The Sierra Club and the League of Conservation Voters, the nation's top two mainstream politically active environmental groups, have not rallied behind the Vice President. The groups' top officials, some of whom privately back Mr. Gore, say that they have never endorsed candidates during the Democratic primary process.</p>
        <p>A third national environmental group active in politics, Friends of the Earth, has endorsed Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>''We're seeing the major party candidates fighting to capture our hearts,'' said Deb Callahan, president of the League of Conservation Voters.</p>
        <p>Carl Pope, executive director of the Sierra Club, said that neither Mr. Gore nor Mr. Bradley had articulated a comprehensive vision for the future. ''The differences in their records doesn't warrant our making a choice between them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Polls show that the environment is a central issue with many voters, especially swing voters in the suburbs and women.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley has a lifetime rating from the League of Conservation Voters of 84 percent, a reflection mainly of his work on environmental problems in New Jersey, which he represented in the Senate for 18 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore had a rating of 64 percent, which reflected several absences from votes during his career, the large number of toxic Superfund sites in Tennessee that have not been cleaned up, as well as Mr. Gore's father's position on the boards of coal companies that were involved in strip-mining.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Gore acknowledged today that Mr. Bradley had a strong record. ''I haven't challenged his commitment to the environment,'' Mr. Gore said. ''I think he has a pretty good voting record on the environment.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that the difference between them was that he was a leader on various environmental issues, citing his role in passing the law to clean up Superfund sites and his campaign against global warming.</p>
        <p>But officials from the environmental groups are skeptical.</p>
        <p>''Many environmentalists feel Clinton-Gore have been lax in leading on global-climate issues,'' Ms. Callahan told an audience in New York on Tuesday night that included Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pope said that Mr. Bradley's problem was that he had not made clear how central the environment was to his candidacy.</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Gore's problem was that ''because he has said so much on the environment in the past, it will be hard for him to say something bold and new.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's other big task, Mr. Pope said, is to re-establish his environmental credentials, because ''Bill Clinton has diminished Gore's environmental reputation over the last seven years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore seemed to be addressing some of these concerns today. He was more assertive than he has been so far about staking his candidacy on environmental issues.</p>
        <p>He noted that he was going further -- ''significantly further'' -- than the Clinton Administration in banning the use of future drilling leases.</p>
        <p>His statement brought swift reaction from the oil and gas industries, which promised to keep pushing to drill in new areas.</p>
        <p>''There is a long way between now and Al Gore's inauguration,'' said Robert Stewart, president of the National Ocean Industries Association, a trade group for offshore contractors.</p>
        <p>The industry is already embroiled in a dispute over an existing lease off  Florida owned by Chevron, which has asked Commerce Secretary William M. Daley to overturn Florida's efforts to block the company's drilling plan. Mr. Daley's decision could come early next year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore mentioned the Florida conflict but did not give his view on what Mr. Daley should do. A spokeswoman said the Vice President thought it would be ''inappropriate to interfere in the existing process.''</p>
        <p>But Senator Bob Graham, Democrat of Florida, said the Vice President's position ''sends a loud message to the Commerce Department: reject Chevron's offshore drilling application.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's proposal could have the broadest impact on drilling off California, where various companies have obtained 40 leases near the Central Coast, many off southern San Luis Obispo County.</p>
        <p>There are indications of vast deposits of oil under the sea bed, perhaps up to one billion barrels. The rights, valued at about $1.2 billion, were obtained from 1968 to 1984. They have remained undeveloped so far.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said that the benefits to all citizens of fishing, tourism and appreciation of beautiful vistas ''far outweigh'' any monetary benefits to the oil industry from ''the tiny little bit of extra oil'' that would come from drilling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
