<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Returning Gleam To Marble Church; Crumbling Piece of City History Is Getting Its Stones Restored</title>
    <meta content="12MARB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1130064"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marble Collegiate Church (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunlap, David W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock and Stone</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED61739F931A2575BC0A96F958260" item-length="1133" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Returning Gleam To Marble Church; Crumbling Piece of City History Is Getting Its Stones Restored</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dunlap, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses $1 million project to repair, restore and clean stones that consist of foundation for Marble Collegiate Church on Fifth Avenue and 29th Street in Manhattan; church's history noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If any church in New York City ought to have its stonework in good repair, it is the one called Marble.</p>
        <p>Looking like a Romanesque pile of sugar cubes, it was consecrated in 1854 as the Fifth Avenue Church. But the glistening stones imprinted themselves on the civic consciousness, and the building material at last gave its name to the congregation, which was formally designated the Marble Collegiate Church in 1906.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If any church in New York City ought to have its stonework in good repair, it is the one called Marble.</p>
        <p>Looking like a Romanesque pile of sugar cubes, it was consecrated in 1854 as the Fifth Avenue Church. But the glistening stones imprinted themselves on the civic consciousness, and the building material at last gave its name to the congregation, which was formally designated the Marble Collegiate Church in 1906.</p>
        <p>Now, the congregation is repaying the favor. It has undertaken a $1 million repair, restoration and cleaning of the stones, all of them discolored and some disturbingly eroded by time, the seasons, polluted air and acid rain.</p>
        <p>''To our knowledge, this has not been touched in 145 years,'' said Dr. Arthur Caliandro, the senior minister. ''We really needed to do it, to brighten the building up and bring it back to its lustrous original self.''</p>
        <p>While it does not rival the grandeur of St. Patrick's Cathedral farther up the avenue, the Marble Church at 29th Street has been in the public eye for a long time. Centuries, in fact. As part of the Collegiate Reformed Protestant Dutch Church, it traces its origins to 1628. And it was the pulpit for 52 years of Dr. Norman Vincent Peale, author of ''The Power of Positive Thinking.''</p>
        <p>What is now an intense job of architectural surgery -- a web of scaffolding envelops the landmark as workers go over the stone surface with diamond-edged grinders, chisels and knives -- began innocently enough two years ago as a simple cleaning project of the marble, which was quarried in Hastings-on-Hudson, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''The building has never had a bath,'' said Dwight D. Rangeler, the church master. ''Our first image was, 'Wouldn't it be nice to bring up a garden hose and spray it on the building?' ''</p>
        <p>Before they could start cleaning, however, church leaders were advised to examine the facade.</p>
        <p>They brought in Diane S. Kaese, senior architect at Wiss, Janney, Elstner Associates, a nationwide engineering and architectural firm based in Northbrook, Ill., that specializes in solving problems for existing buildings.</p>
        <p>That was when the congregation learned that sugar has an ominous meaning in the stone trade -- not white and sparkling but granular and crumbling. An inspection disclosed that the marble was ''sugaring'' in many spots under a black gypsum crust caused by decades of exposure. In some places, the mortar had turned to powder, if it remained at all. Blocks could be rocked back and forth by hand. Through stones in the bell tower, one could see blue sky.</p>
        <p>Church leaders decided to seize the opportunity provided by a strong economy to undertake a more ambitious restoration of their building. ''We want to make sure it can last for another few generations,'' Mr. Rangeler said. ''By that time, some new preservative techniques may have come to the fore.''</p>
        <p>''It's got to be done,'' he said. ''Or else.''</p>
        <p>Or else more of the conditions he saw the other day on a not-too-happy tour of the facade given by Ms. Kaese; Timothy D. Henry and Timothy J. Farrell of Henry Restoration, the contracting company from Nesconset, N.Y., and John K. Copelin of the William A. Hall Partnership, the architect for the church.</p>
        <p>They began along the rooftop balustrade. Ms. Kaese paused. ''It looks like someone poured hot water on a sugar cube and it melted,'' she said, pointing to an 18-inch-high, 4-cusp opening called a quatrefoil.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it did. The contours of the once-crisp carving had softened into a doughy lump and the surface was the color of a calico cat: white marble, black gypsum crust and orange granules.</p>
        <p>''I shouldn't have worn bifocals today,'' Mr. Rangeler said as he peered over Ms. Kaese's shoulder at the deterioration. ''I should have come up blind. I don't want to see this.''</p>
        <p>At the base of a spire at the southeast corner of the church, Ms. Kaese was able to stick her finger all the way into a masonry joint because there was so much space between stones and so little mortar.</p>
        <p>''Theoretically, that should not be,'' she said.</p>
        <p>They shimmied their way along the planks and through the narrow network of pipe supports. ''Here, Dwight, I want to show you this,'' Ms. Kaese said, pointing to the arabesque base of a pier on the south facade from which a knoblike ornament known as a boss had simply broken off.</p>
        <p>''Ay, ay, ay, ay, ay,'' was Mr. Rangeler's appreciative response.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farrell, the field superintendent for Henry Restoration, kept watch on his crew. One worker was using a chisel to extract old mortar from a buttress. ''Don't bury that shank all the way in or you'll pop the stone, O.K.?'' Mr. Farrell cautioned.</p>
        <p>At another buttress, Mr. Farrell used a low-tech device called the flat of his hand to determine the condition of the stone. Instead of a sharp report, the block sent back a hollow reverberation. ''It doesn't sound good,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Discouraging as this litany might seem, Ms. Kaese does not despair. Over all, she said, the metal anchors behind the stone blocks are in good shape and there has been minimal breakage of stone. But there is more surface and joint deterioration than she expected to find.</p>
        <p>Some stones will have to be recarved. Others must be replaced entirely. Most of them will be cleaned with a light misting of water that will eventually dissolve the gypsum crust. For those that are badly stained, a clay-based poultice can be applied -- not unlike a facial mudpack, Ms. Kaese said.</p>
        <p>Church leaders are tamping down expectations in the congregation that the building will emerge dazzling from its cocoon. ''It's going to be cleaner than this,'' Mr. Copelin said, ''but it's not going to be the Taj Mahal.''</p>
        <p>After the restoration work is finished, in about four months, the grounds around the building will be landscaped and the building will be illuminated at night.</p>
        <p>''Churches -- not only Marble -- serve as lighthouses to passers-by,'' Dr. Caliandro said. ''For many, there's a feeling of comfort, hope and security when they see churches. Also for the neighborhood. The Flatiron district is moving north and we will be helpful to the whole value of the neighborhood by being outstanding.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
