<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Next!</title>
    <meta content="10RAEBURT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1075794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raeburn, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maddox, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">What Remains to be Discovered (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DD1E3FF933A25752C0A96F958260" item-length="1183" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Next!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Paul Raeburn</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Raeburn, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paul Raeburn reviews book What Remains to Be Discovered: Mapping the Secrets of the Universe, the Origins of Life, and the Future of the Human Race by John Maddox (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT REMAINS  TO BE DISCOVERED  Mapping the Secrets of the Universe, the Origins of Life, and the Future of the Human Race.  By John Maddox.  434 pp. New York:  The Free Press. $26.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT REMAINS  TO BE DISCOVERED  Mapping the Secrets of the Universe, the Origins of Life, and the Future of the Human Race.  By John Maddox.  434 pp. New York:  The Free Press. $26.</p>
        <p>When humanity's ancestors arose out of the primordial soup, they soon realized there was little to eat except primordial salad -- with, perhaps, an occasional meal of saber-toothed tartare. It fell to an enterprising young scientist among them to discover fire, and soon they were dishing up the world's first barbecue. Science had changed their lives. But what else could science bring them? Another kind of fire? Not likely. Science was wonderful, but its work was done. With a well-kept cave, a solid club and, now, a steady fire, what else did they need?</p>
        <p>They were wrong, of course; science had yet to produce the microwave oven, among other useful things. But on the eve of the millennium the question about science's future reappears. In his widely discussed 1996 book, ''The End of Science,'' John Horgan argued that, indeed, the end is nigh: The big discoveries have all been made.</p>
        <p>Horgan, a veteran science writer, did not argue that we have answered all the big questions; he is as curious as the next guy about, say, the nature of human consciousness or life on other worlds. The problem, he wrote, is that we will probably never find the answers -- or the solution will be some dispiriting triviality. Consciousness may one day be revealed to be nothing more than an accumulation of nerve impulses. As to the question of extraterrestrials, Horgan says we will never be able to get far enough out into space to find out. The impossibility of exceeding the speed of light hangs from us like a ball and chain.</p>
        <p>Sir John Maddox doesn't buy any of this. Maddox was for almost 23 years editor in chief of the British journal Nature, one of the world's leading scientific publications. By deciding what to publish, he was more than an observer of the scientific enterprise -- he helped to shape it. In ''What Remains to Be Discovered,'' he attempts to set an agenda for the coming decades, even centuries. The title was carefully chosen: He discusses what scientists need to find out, and where they might look. He doesn't try to predict what they will find. He mischievously avoids mention of Horgan, but Maddox is clearly out to refute him. ''Science, far from being at an end, has a long agenda ahead of it,'' Maddox writes. And the discoveries to come will change our view of the world ''as radically as it has been changed since the time of Copernicus.''</p>
        <p>To show what we don't know, Maddox catalogues what we have learned. One of the most important discoveries in cosmology, for example, is Hubble's Law. It says that other galaxies are moving away from us, and the farther they get the faster they go. Along with the idea of the Big Bang, it has vastly clarified our understanding of the universe. Unfortunately, it has also given rise to contradictions about the age of the universe. A verification or modification of Hubble's Law is urgently needed and could come within a decade, Maddox says.</p>
        <p>Other problems are likely to be tougher. Two of the towering intellectual achievements of the 20th century are Einstein's theory of gravitation and the theory of quantum mechanics. Einstein's theory deals with the universe and space-time. Quantum mechanics explains the inner workings of the atom. There ought to be a theory of quantum gravity -- but nobody has been able to find one. That is the ''chief present obstacle to a better understanding of the physical world,'' Maddox says.</p>
        <p>In molecular biology research has leaped forward; within a few years, the entire human genetic code will be available on CD-ROM's. Yet all researchers will have done, Maddox points out, is name the parts. They have so far made little progress in figuring out how genes and the cellular machinery arose or how they work. Given the complexity of an individual human cell -- crammed with 100,000 genes and thousands of proteins -- researchers will need computer models to figure out what is going on, Maddox says. Curing cancer sounds simple by comparison, although that is a likely consequence of this research.</p>
        <p>Maddox also envisions a time when far more will be known about human evolution. The genomes of apes and humans differ by only a few percent, but in an unusual way. Humans have 23 pairs of chromosomes, while great apes have 24. And part of the ''missing'' ape chromosome turns up on one arm of human chromosome 2. How could natural selection have produced such a radical cut-and-paste job? Answering such questions will require ''every scrap of information from paleontology and ecology. . . . But that is how the history of the human race will be reconstructed in the next century or so.''</p>
        <p>Maddox's optimism extends to brain science and mathematics, and he is hopeful that we will devise a way to protect ourselves from any killer meteorite that might be bearing down on earth. Only when he discusses such problems as AIDS and global warming does he seem to waver. It is jarring to see him take an unkind swipe at Robert C. Gallo, the co-discoverer of the AIDS virus: Gallo ''first sought to diminish the discovery of the virus by Luc Montagnier . . . and then to give his own comparable work the ring of authenticity.'' He criticizes Gallo for predicting, in 1984, that an AIDS vaccine was only a few years away. ''This corrosive incident has reflected badly not only on those concerned, but on the research community as a whole,'' he writes. Many researchers agreed with Gallo then, and Gallo was displaying the kind of hopefulness that Maddox clearly shares. He also takes a shot at the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, the international agency charged with evaluating research on global warming. ''I.P.C.C. seems not to have appreciated that the prospect of climate change is bad news for most people,'' he writes, and its conclusions would be more persuasive ''if it were demonstrably open to the possibility that the bad news may not be true.'' This puzzling remark becomes even more mystifying when, a few pages later, he agrees with the panel that under current conditions ''there is no serious doubt that global warming will occur.''</p>
        <p>When he takes the longer view, however, Maddox makes a persuasive case that science has far to go. Does that mean Horgan was wrong? It may take a few centuries to find out. Horgan recalls the early explorers, to whom the swelling seas seemed infinite. They were wrong; but perhaps the belief sustained them.</p>
        <p>Paul Raeburn is a senior editor at Business Week and the author of ''Mars: Uncovering the Secrets of the Red Planet.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Paul Raeburn is a senior editor at Business Week and the author of ''Mars: Uncovering the Secrets of the Red Planet.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
