<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Surprise Possibility: A Dignified Democrat Race</title>
    <meta content="28ASSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1148854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dartmouth College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2D61038F93BA15753C1A96F958260" item-length="881" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Surprise Possibility: A Dignified Democrat Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Clymer analysis notes that Vice Pres Al Gore and former Sen Bill Bradley discussed important, complicated issues during forum at Dartmouth College and invited voters to judge them not for campaign jabs but by their earnest concerns about problems; maintains that since Gore and Bradley have committed themselves to series of these meetings, dignified campaign for their party's nomination has become, if not certainty, then surely distinct possibility (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Democratic Presidential candidates tonight discussed important, complicated issues in their first joint event and invited voters to judge them not for campaign jabs but by their earnest concerns about problems from health care to homosexuals' rights to campaign finance.</p>
        <p>It was almost a secret meeting, scheduled against the fourth game of the World Series, and so the ratings for the town meeting, broadcast by WMUR in Manchester, N.H., and nationally by CNN, will probably be minuscule. The scheduling seemed odd since the electorate constantly complains to reporters and pollsters that neither candidates nor news organizations pay attention to issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Democratic Presidential candidates tonight discussed important, complicated issues in their first joint event and invited voters to judge them not for campaign jabs but by their earnest concerns about problems from health care to homosexuals' rights to campaign finance.</p>
        <p>It was almost a secret meeting, scheduled against the fourth game of the World Series, and so the ratings for the town meeting, broadcast by WMUR in Manchester, N.H., and nationally by CNN, will probably be minuscule. The scheduling seemed odd since the electorate constantly complains to reporters and pollsters that neither candidates nor news organizations pay attention to issues.</p>
        <p>But since Vice President Al Gore and former Senator Bill Bradley have committed themselves to a series of these meetings, a dignified campaign for their party's nomination tonight became, if not a certainty, then surely a distinct possibility.</p>
        <p>Tonight's format did not invite detailed discussion, and of the many issues covered, health care was the subject on which they came closest to engaging each other directly. In discussing their health care proposals, Mr. Gore said Mr. Bradley's was too expensive. Mr. Bradley said that it was not as expensive as Mr. Gore thought, but that ''it's a big problem and it needs a big solution.''</p>
        <p>For the subject to be examined seriously, Mr. Gore's suggestion that future debates focus on particular topics seemed apt.</p>
        <p>Both candidates played to a larger perspective than their questioners, New Hampshire citizens chosen by lot with questions approved by the broadcasters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore took a fairly narrow question on energy conservation and gave a broader answer, saying, ''We, in our country, have a lot of work to do. Global warming is a real problem. Air pollution is a real problem. Water pollution is a real problem. We've got to clean up the toxic waste sites. And you know, a President of the United States who is committed to cleaning up the environment and fighting for all of the families that now suffer with asthma or other health problems because of the dirty environment -- a President can make a huge difference.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley declined an invitation to criticize the Clinton-Gore Administration over its campaign fund-raising, saying merely that there had been ''irregularities.'' Instead, he said that in order to change the system, the public had to be aroused, and so did civic leaders.</p>
        <p>''You need a President that is going to make campaign finance reform one of the top three or four or five issues,'' he said, ''because he recognizes how it is connected to our ability to insure more Americans, to our ability to reduce child poverty. From my perspective there is no issue that is as linked to other issues as campaign finance reform. That's why it is an imperative.''</p>
        <p>And when asked about civil rights for homosexuals, each answered the specific question and went on to talk about human dignity. Mr. Bradley said homosexuals should be allowed to serve in the armed forces.</p>
        <p>Then he said: ''It's important that we can talk about gay Americans and realize that they are our neighbors, they're our bosses. They're no different in many ways than all of us. And we have to get to a time in America where we can see beneath skin color, eye shape or sexual orientation to the individual, because that is when we are going to be able to achieve the dignity that I think America stands for.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore said he opposed same-sex marriages, adding: ''I think that the story of our country is in part an unfolding of the American dream with a deeper meaning in each generation. It's a mystery how Thomas Jefferson could write the words of our Declaration and own slaves. It's a mystery how the founders in Philadelphia could write our Constitution and not allow women to vote. But we have taken the inner meaning and power of our founding documents and the spirit of America and breathed new life into them in each new generation. And the time has come for gays and lesbians to be recognized within the circle of human dignity.''</p>
        <p>Most joint appearances get interesting when sparks fly. Tonight the most intriguing moments came at the end, when each man was asked to define Presidential leadership.</p>
        <p>Each answered in terms of past Presidents. Mr. Gore cited Abraham Lincoln, who could ''assert values and elevate those values so that people buy into them and base their decisions on those values.'' He said Franklin D. Roosevelt was the ''finest example of articulating a vision -- of how we could get through the Depression and win World War II.''</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Bradley cited Jimmy Carter for ''absolute integrity'' and Woodrow Wilson for an ''ability to see the future before it's here.''</p>
        <p>And in what may have been the most thoughtful comment of the evening, the former Senator cited the last President of the Soviet Union. He said Mikhail S. Gorbachev ''saw that the world must change and had the courage to make that change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
