<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Retreat on Clean Air</title>
    <meta content="26SUN1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1163923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EED71339F935A15751C1A96F958260" item-length="600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Retreat on Clean Air</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial hails recent Clinton Administration rulings that will require big investments by oil, auto and utility companies to cut smog-causing chemicals</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early last summer, clean-air advocates were on the run. Back-to-back rulings in May by conservative, anti-regulatory judges in the Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit had shredded much of the administration's air pollution strategy, invalidating tough new federal health standards and blocking efforts to reduce smog in the eastern half of the United States. But in some mysterious way the ruling seemed to stiffen the resolve of federal and state officials, and ever since then the big polluters have been the ones on the run. In the last week alone, the Clinton administration issued several major rulings that will require big investments by the oil, automobile and utility companies to reduce smog-causing chemicals.</p>
        <p>The most important of these rulings will require auto makers to build cleaner vehicles and oil companies to refine cleaner gasoline. Taken together, these measures should reduce pollutants in standard cars by about 75 percent from today's levels. But the most important aspect of the ruling is that it will subject so-called light trucks -- sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans -- to essentially the same requirements as ordinary cars. Until now, light trucks have been allowed to produce up to three times the pollution of standard cars because regulators have classified them as work vehicles, even though they now account for about half of all new-car purchases.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early last summer, clean-air advocates were on the run. Back-to-back rulings in May by conservative, anti-regulatory judges in the Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit had shredded much of the administration's air pollution strategy, invalidating tough new federal health standards and blocking efforts to reduce smog in the eastern half of the United States. But in some mysterious way the ruling seemed to stiffen the resolve of federal and state officials, and ever since then the big polluters have been the ones on the run. In the last week alone, the Clinton administration issued several major rulings that will require big investments by the oil, automobile and utility companies to reduce smog-causing chemicals.</p>
        <p>The most important of these rulings will require auto makers to build cleaner vehicles and oil companies to refine cleaner gasoline. Taken together, these measures should reduce pollutants in standard cars by about 75 percent from today's levels. But the most important aspect of the ruling is that it will subject so-called light trucks -- sport utility vehicles, pickup trucks and minivans -- to essentially the same requirements as ordinary cars. Until now, light trucks have been allowed to produce up to three times the pollution of standard cars because regulators have classified them as work vehicles, even though they now account for about half of all new-car purchases.</p>
        <p>Both the auto makers and the oil companies grumbled about the costs of the new rules, which will add perhaps $200 to the price of a sport utility vehicle and a few pennies to a gallon of gasoline. But there was less grumbling than usual, for two reasons. One is that all the major presidential candidates have endorsed tougher rules. The other was a decision over a year ago by Carol Browner, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, to spread the cost of the cleanup by asking the oil companies to reduce the sulfur content in gasoline. This will make it easier for the car makers to meet the new targets because sulfur clogs up a vehicle's catalytic converter, the device that cleans car exhaust of pollutants.</p>
        <p>Another ruling, announced by Ms. Browner earlier this month, would give 400 utilities and manufacturing plants in 12 states until 2003 to cut by half the pollutants that are blown eastward by prevailing winds, adding to smog in the Northeast. The ruling -- made in response to four northeastern states that are seeking relief from windblown pollution -- is only the latest of several efforts to crack down on the aging, coal-fired power plants in the Midwestern and border states that lie at the root of some of the country's biggest pollution problems.</p>
        <p>In separate actions, for example, the E.P.A. and New York's attorney general, Eliot Spitzer, have sued more than 30 such plants for allegedly failing to install anti-pollution equipment in violation of the Clean Air Act. Meanwhile, Gov. George Pataki has ordered New York's own power plants to cut the emissions that cause smog and acid rain. The governor has also promised to impose new emissions standards on cars sold in New York that he says will be even stronger than those announced by President Clinton last Monday.</p>
        <p>All of this has happened since the disheartening court decisions in May and despite dire predictions that in an election year neither the administration nor politicians with possible national aspirations, like Mr. Pataki, would risk offending pivotal Midwestern states and big industries. These fears, fortunately, appear to have been premature.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
