<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Culture of Sunbathers, Tips for Shielding the Skin</title>
    <meta content="15BROD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Health &amp; Fitness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1115462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Skin</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Columns/Personal Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sunburn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6D71738F936A25755C0A96F958260" item-length="1244" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Culture of Sunbathers, Tips for Shielding the Skin</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody Personal Health column on protecting oneself from hazards of sunburn; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As warm and wonderful as it feels to bask under the rays of the summer sun, it is not very good for the body. In my teen-age years, we had tanning contests to see who could get the darkest the fastest. In my 20's, I slathered my bikini-clad body in baby oil to attract as many tanning rays as I could in the little time I had for sunbathing. Now, decades later, when I look at the spotted skin that has begun to wrinkle on my arms and legs, I cannot help wishing I had known then what I know now.</p>
        <p>Although most Americans still precede the word ''tan'' with ''healthy,'' it is anything but. A tan, which results from the formation of the pigment melanin in skin cells called melanocytes, is the body's attempt to defend itself against sun damage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As warm and wonderful as it feels to bask under the rays of the summer sun, it is not very good for the body. In my teen-age years, we had tanning contests to see who could get the darkest the fastest. In my 20's, I slathered my bikini-clad body in baby oil to attract as many tanning rays as I could in the little time I had for sunbathing. Now, decades later, when I look at the spotted skin that has begun to wrinkle on my arms and legs, I cannot help wishing I had known then what I know now.</p>
        <p>Although most Americans still precede the word ''tan'' with ''healthy,'' it is anything but. A tan, which results from the formation of the pigment melanin in skin cells called melanocytes, is the body's attempt to defend itself against sun damage.</p>
        <p>Melanin absorbs some of the incoming rays to keep them from harming other cells. But this protection is far from complete. I only hope that by protecting my skin from further sun damage I will not end up like my my grandmother, who lived on a beach and whose skin resembled elephant hide by the time she reached 70.</p>
        <p>At this point, we all should know better, but I still see sunbathers galore, mostly teen-agers and young adults and a fair number of baby boomers minimally clad and well greased as they seek a so-called ''healthy tan.'' Because it is unlikely that sun-loving Americans will suddenly take to the shade, pharmaceutical and skin care companies have come up with a host of new products that can help to minimize -- though not eliminate -- the damage of sun exposure.</p>
        <p>Rays of Ruin</p>
        <p>By now everyone knows that it is ultraviolet, or UV, rays that both tan and damage the skin. The wavelengths of concern are UVB (290 to 320 nanometers) and shorter and longer UVA (320 to 400 nanometers). The atmosphere's ozone layer blocks another type, UVC (200 to 290 nanometers), as well as large amounts of UVB. But the closer the sun is to the earth's surface and the more degraded the ozone layer, the more UVB gets through.</p>
        <p>Although UVB has long been recognized as the cause of sunburns and superficial skin cancers called basal-cell carcinomas, recent studies have implicated it as a cause of melanoma, the most serious form of skin cancer, as well. One or two blistering sunburns early in life can greatly increase the risk of developing a potentially fatal melanoma.</p>
        <p>Also, those who are exposed to occasional bursts of sunlight, like indoor workers who spend weekends and vacations in the sun, appear to be at greater risk of melanoma than people who are continuously exposed, like farmers and fishermen.</p>
        <p>However, farmers and fishermen and others who are always in the sun get many basal-cell carcinomas on exposed parts of their bodies. The fairer the skin, the more prone people are to developing superficial skin cancers. A blond, blue-eyed friend just had 14 of these lesions removed from his face and back. Though not as deadly as melanoma, these cancers can eventually spread if not removed, a process that can leave noticeable scars, especially on the face.</p>
        <p>UVA radiation may also be implicated in cancer. It can damage the genes, especially a tumor suppressor gene called p-53, and impair the workings of the immune system. But the damage it most commonly causes is premature aging of the skin, or photoaging: wrinkled, leathery skin pockmarked with brown spots.</p>
        <p>The longer rays of UVA can penetrate the deeper layers of the skin where they degrade the elastic fibers and collagen that keep the skin smooth and firm. If you would like to know how young your skin would look had it not been repeatedly exposed to UVA, check your buttocks. Or compare the skin on the outside of your arms with the side against your body.</p>
        <p>People who frequent tanning salons are assaulting their skin with high doses of UVA radiation. UVA can also penetrate window glass, including car windows. It passes through water and it is released as well from fluorescent and halogen bulbs. Unlike UVB, which is more intense in summer, at midday and at higher altitudes, UVA radiation is much less affected by season, time of day or altitude. It is present all day year-round everywhere and it represents more than 90 percent of the UV radiation that reaches the earth's surface.</p>
        <p>How Good Are Sunscreens?</p>
        <p>Anyone shopping for skin protection products is bound to be confused. Labels state sun protection factors, or S.P.F., ranging from 4 to 60 and make claims like ''waterproof,'' ''water resistant,'' ''sweat proof,'' ''all-day protection,'' ''complete protection'' and ''total sunblock.'' New regulations, which the Skin Cancer Foundation worries  will further confuse the public, will create only three categories ''minimal'' (S.P.F. 2 to 12), ''moderate'' (12 to 30) and ''high'' sunburn protection (30 or more).</p>
        <p>The first fact worth noting is that the rating refers only to the product's ability to reduce exposure to UVB radiation. Laboratory tests using liberal amounts of the product reveal how much longer a person may be protected from sunburn than if no sunscreen were applied. Thus, if you would normally burn in 20 minutes in the sun, using a product with an S.P.F. rating of 15 would theoretically keep you from burning for five hours.</p>
        <p>However, there are three important limitations. One, to be most effective, sunscreens should be applied half an hour before exposure. Second, most people do not apply nearly enough sunscreen to achieve laboratory levels of protection. The amount an average-size adult in a bathing suit should use is one ounce per application, repeated every few hours. The way most people use sunscreen the rating would be only half or less what the label states, so you would be wise to choose a product with high sunburn protection. Third, unless you use a product that offers good protection against both UVB and UVA radiation, even if you do not burn, you will be exposing your skin to a lot of UVA damage.</p>
        <p>There are more than two dozen new products available that offer more complete UV protection. These contain either micronized zinc oxide or titanium oxide or Parsol 1789 (avobenzone). Other products containing benzophenone also reduce exposure to UVA but not as effectively, studies have indicated.</p>
        <p>Women who wear face makeup would be wise to choose a product that offers such protection, and everyone who is in the sun even sporadically during the day can benefit from the use of a face lotion that offers UVA and UVB protection; it should be applied liberally and reapplied whenever the face is washed. Also apply a lip balm with full protection repeatedly throughout the day. Note, however, that it is not yet known whether products containing vitamin E, vitamin C or other antioxidants enhance their sun protection value.</p>
        <p>Of course, the best way to avoid sun damage is to stay out of it as much as possible. When in the sun, wear a hat with a brim at least three inches wide and protect your eyes with sunglasses (UV light can cause cataracts). Relax in the shade, but since UV rays scatter, use sunscreen even if you are under an awning or beach umbrella. And, whenever possible, cover your skin with clothing.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
