<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lessons From a School Where the Worm Club Rules</title>
    <meta content="10CUTT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1144261"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="CUTTINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden/Columns/Cuttings</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0D61031F933A25753C1A96F958260" item-length="1069" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lessons From a School Where the Worm Club Rules</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE RAVER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WORMS seem unlikely ambassadors for a troubled world, but they were popular members of the after-school garden club I helped start last year at Public School 15 -- the Patrick Daly School, named for the principal who was shot to death while searching for a pupil seven years ago -- in Red Hook, Brooklyn. These worms were teaching us to be good stewards of the earth, until their ecosystem crashed -- because of their own global warming, I think -- but we're going to try again.</p>
        <p>Our club is small: about 10 kids, fourth- and fifth-graders, and four grown-ups, though sometimes the grown-ups act like kids and vice versa. We started out last fall, planting bulbs in the school's central courtyard, which had a forgotten, overgrown look.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WORMS seem unlikely ambassadors for a troubled world, but they were popular members of the after-school garden club I helped start last year at Public School 15 -- the Patrick Daly School, named for the principal who was shot to death while searching for a pupil seven years ago -- in Red Hook, Brooklyn. These worms were teaching us to be good stewards of the earth, until their ecosystem crashed -- because of their own global warming, I think -- but we're going to try again.</p>
        <p>Our club is small: about 10 kids, fourth- and fifth-graders, and four grown-ups, though sometimes the grown-ups act like kids and vice versa. We started out last fall, planting bulbs in the school's central courtyard, which had a forgotten, overgrown look.</p>
        <p>''I went to this school, and I never knew this was here,'' said Enily Mieles, a volunteer for the Americorps program, standing under the drifty branches of a weeping white birch. We gather here every Thursday after school to weed and prune and plant things. Half the time we just look at stuff.</p>
        <p>Like catkins dangling from a hazelnut tree. Or the empty shells of the nuts discarded by the squirrels that ate half our tulip bulbs last year.</p>
        <p>''Look at that!'' shouted Mercedez Delgado on one clear, chilly afternoon, opening her arms to a sugar maple ablaze with orange light. We looked up its name -- ''Acer saccharum'' -- in our tree book, and noticed how the shape of the leaf is different from that of A. rubrum, the red maple. Then somebody, who will remain nameless because he repented, smashed a worm. ''Why did you do that?'' I asked, deadpan. He shrugged, grinning. His pals giggled.</p>
        <p>So, we talked a bit about what earthworms do, like churning and aerating the soil, and how red worms, another species, could turn our garbage into gold for the garden.</p>
        <p>Desmond Hill rolled his eyes, as if I were kidding, which is his favorite activity. But the next week, I brought in two pounds of red worms from the Lower East Side Ecology Center, along the East River in Manhattan, where worms turn garbage to compost. And that afternoon, Lower East Side worms began eating Red Hook garbage -- chopped-up lettuce, carrots and the like -- and making compost for our garden.</p>
        <p>''Maybe we should call ourselves the Worm Club,'' Desmond said, as we got the worms' habitat ready: shredding newspaper and sprinkling it with water, tossing it like spaghetti into a rubber bin about the size of a laundry basket. The worms like it damp, but not too damp.</p>
        <p>We weighed their first meal: old lettuce, coffee grounds, eggshells, banana peels and cantaloupe rind.</p>
        <p>''Worms love melon rind,'' I told them. ''But they don't like cabbage. It's hard to digest, so it sits in the box and starts to smell.'' So, it's best to stay away from cabbage and onions, and meat, of course, which attracts critters other than worms.</p>
        <p>''Worms are nasty,'' Mercedez said, giggling happily.</p>
        <p>Questions tumbled out: If you cut a worm in half, will it die or grow into two worms? Do worms have bones? Eyes? Teeth? Blood? How long do they live? ''Does a worm go through an aging process,'' Jesse Horenstein asked, ''like being a baby, and then a kid, and then a teen-ager?''</p>
        <p>And how do they mate? (Or marinate, as Luiz Miranda asked, which is apt, because they lie there, two together, with this slime wrapped around them.) We watched ''Wormania,'' a video made by Mary Appelhof, a biologist and worm maniac in Kalamazoo, Mich.</p>
        <p>Nobody could remember the word ''hermaphrodite'' -- something to do with being both male and female. But if a worm has both eggs and sperm, why didn't it make its own babies? Harriet Chichester, the school's science teacher, gave a talk on genetics. Luiz turned philosophical. ''I think if you made your own babies, you'd never get to know anybody,'' he said. ''Even if you went to heaven, you wouldn't know anybody.''</p>
        <p>Now, there's a scary thought. But to get back to the nitty-gritty, if a pound of worms can eat a half-pound of garbage in one day, how much can two pounds of worms eat? A wave of math anxiety washed through the room, until Michael Pagan, staring solemnly at the ceiling, intoned, ''one pound.'' We weighed out a pound, and put it in one corner of the bin, which has plenty of air holes. Then we sprinkled handfuls of worms over the shredded paper and watched them wriggle away from the light (worms hate light) toward their first meal.</p>
        <p>By then, even Mercedez was holding a worm in her hand. Desmond named his new friends Kevin, Josh and Frank. But Ms. Chichester, who screamed when she first held a worm, asked me to keep the bin at my house, and to bring it back on Thursdays. Over the weeks, the kids fed them and looked at them under magnifying glasses -- to find their ''five hearts,'' or circulation system; the clitellum, or band through which they exchange sperm; the egg cases that look like gold beads.</p>
        <p>Then, all of a sudden, something went haywire: most of the worms died. Maybe we gave them too much food, or water, or not enough newspaper, or maybe my apartment got too hot. So, I dumped them in the composter in my backyard (where a few survivors have apparently procreated big time). And this year, we'll try again, with Christina Datz Romero, the compost queen on the East River, as our worm coach. It's a can-do club: Luiz says we're going to solve New York's garbage crisis.</p>
        <p>More information on worms and gardening in the schools is available from the Lower East Side Ecology Center, (212) 420-0621; Worm Digest, (541) 485-0456 (www.wormdigest .org); Mary Appelhopf, Flowerfield Enterprises, (616) 327-0108, or the National Gardening Association, (800) 538-7476.</p>
        <p>CUTTINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
