<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki to Order Emissions Cuts For Power Sites</title>
    <meta content="14SMOG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1145208"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cahill, John P (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DB1330F937A25753C1A96F958260" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki to Order Emissions Cuts For Power Sites</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George E Pataki plans to order power plants in New York State to sharply cut smokestack emissions of sulfur dioxide, which causes acid rain, and nitrogen oxides, which cause smog and contribute to acid rain; move will raise electricity rates by 1 or 2 percent and put NY ahead of rest of country in cleanup schedule set by Clean Air Act; will enable natural-gas power plants, which are costly to build, to compete against coal plants, which will have to install expensive filters; Environmental Conservation Comr John P Cahill says slight rise in electric rates will be more than offset by environmental benefits (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki will order power plants in New York State to make sharp cuts in the smokestack emissions that cause acid rain and smog, his aides said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The move will raise the state's electricity rates by 1 to 2 percent, they said, but it will put New York substantially ahead of the rest of the country in the cleanup schedule set by the Federal Clean Air Act.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki will order power plants in New York State to make sharp cuts in the smokestack emissions that cause acid rain and smog, his aides said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The move will raise the state's electricity rates by 1 to 2 percent, they said, but it will put New York substantially ahead of the rest of the country in the cleanup schedule set by the Federal Clean Air Act.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who is expected to outline the plan at a news conference today, will order cuts in two kinds of pollution: sulfur dioxide, the main cause of acid rain, and nitrogen oxides, which cause smog and also contribute to acid rain, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>While an impending Federal rule would require cuts in nitrogen oxides only in the summer, when smog is at its worst, the new New York State regulations would require the same reductions all year, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Word of Mr. Pataki's plans pleased both environmental groups seeking cleaner air and power companies with proposals to build new natural-gas power plants in the state. These plants are costly to build but produce much less pollution than the old coal-burning plants that dominate in western New York.</p>
        <p>Under the new rules, the gas-fired plants will be able to compete against coal plants, energy experts say, because the coal plants will have to invest in expensive systems to filter pollution.</p>
        <p>''This is a very exciting and bold move by the Governor,'' said Ned Sullivan, the executive director of Scenic Hudson, a private environmental group. ''No other state has mandated this level of reduction for acid rain control.''</p>
        <p>The slight increase in electric rates would be more than offset by the environmental benefits, said John P. Cahill, the New York Commissioner of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>''No one could dispute now that New York has done more than any other state in the country to control emissions from its sources,'' Mr. Cahill said yesterday, after describing the plan.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, the New York plan could add momentum to efforts in Congress to pass Federal legislation that would require similar reductions.</p>
        <p>Owners of some of the state's coal-fired plants, which sit mainly in  western New York and the upper Hudson Valley, said they could not comment on specifics until after the Pataki administration released details today.</p>
        <p>But some said they planned to comply with whatever new standards emerged once the new regulations were written.</p>
        <p>''Our goal is always to meet or exceed environmental standards,'' said Frank Rapley, a spokesman for NRG Energy Inc., a Minneapolis company that recently bought two of the biggest power plants in the state, Dunkirk and C. R. Huntley, near Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Starting next year, a provision of the Clean Air Act will require a 35 percent reduction in nitrogen oxide emissions from power plants, but only from May through September. The state would require the same reduction throughout the year.</p>
        <p>As a result, annual emissions would drop from levels like those seen in 1998 -- 102,000 tons -- to 62,000 tons a year, according to state environmental officials. That level is 20,000 tons less than the Federal rule would allow, they said.</p>
        <p>The planned reductions in sulfur dioxide emissions would be even sharper, dropping from more than 300,000 tons a year -- the level in 1998 -- to less than 130,000 tons a year, with the reduction being phased in from 2003 to 2007, Mr. Cahill said.  Under the Clean Air Act, New York would only be required to cut its sulfur dioxide pollution to 262,000 tons a year, according to state officials.</p>
        <p>A spate of recent studies has shown that pollution cuts called for under the Clean Air Act will not be sufficient to repair damage to forests, streams and lakes around the Northeast from acidic rain and snow.</p>
        <p>Over all, New York environmental officials calculate, only 17 to 20 percent of the acid rain problem in the Adirondacks and other areas upstate comes from pollution produced by New York's own power plants. The rest comes from coal-fired power plants in the Middle West and South, Mr. Cahill said.</p>
        <p>New York has been locked in a dispute for a decade with those states. By moving to cut its pollution, Mr. Cahill said, the state can increase the pressure on them to follow suit.</p>
        <p>Officials at the Federal Environmental Protection Agency said that some of Mr. Pataki's planned cuts in power-plant pollution would have been required anyway. Some states downwind of New York have petitioned the E.P.A. to force some of New York's old coal-fired plants to cut pollution that drifts east and contributes to problems.</p>
        <p>But they conceded that some of New York's moves, particularly the cut in nitrogen oxides throughout the year, went beyond anything done by any other states.</p>
        <p>Many private environmental groups were delighted by the Pataki plan. ''It sets a new tone and increases New York's commitment to putting more pressure on Washington to make it all happen,'' said Ashok Gupta, an economist at the  Natural Resources Defense Council. But, he said that if Congress did not quickly follow suit with stronger Federal laws, it might still be possible in several years for New York to retreat.</p>
        <p>In a separate development, Eliot L. Spitzer, the State Attorney General, who is investigating eight of New York's older power plants for possible violations of Federal and state pollution rules, sent letters on Tuesday to their owners requesting hundreds of pages of documents.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer announced last month that he planned to sue the owners of power plants in upwind states, on the ground that their pollution harmed New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>According to Larry Shapiro, a lawyer for the New York Public Interest Research Group, a lobbying and environmental organization, the moves by Mr. Pataki and Mr. Spitzer show that New York is finally getting serious about stanching the flow of air pollution, whether its source is smokestacks in upwind states or in New York itself.</p>
        <p>''We're going to have to lead by example,'' Mr. Shapiro said, ''and that's what the Governor's doing.''</p>
        <p>Many air pollution experts said that the maneuvers implied a significant amount of political competition for credit as New York moved toward cutting pollution, with the Republican Governor and Democratic Attorney General eager to be perceived as a leader on the issue.</p>
        <p>But Darren Dopp, a spokesman for Mr. Spitzer, said the final result was a good one. ''The bottom line is that a little competition between us and them is good for the air,'' he said yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
