<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Congressman Who Loved Science</title>
    <meta content="09BROW$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1091012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="A CONVERSATION WITH: GEORGE E. BROWN JR."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dreifus, Claudia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, George E Jr (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Conversations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04EEDC103FF93AA35750C0A96F958260" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Congressman Who Loved Science</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA DREIFUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dreifus, Claudia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Rep George E Brown Jr, ranking Democrat on House Committee on Science and dean of Congressional science buffs; he has degree in physics and experience as engineer; speaks of his fascination with science, and his conviction that science could be basis for better world; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative George E. Brown Jr. of California, the ranking Democrat on the House Committee on Science and the former chairman of the House Committee on Science, Space and Technology, is the dean of the Congressional science buffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, 79, has been a crucial supporter of manned and unmanned space exploration. He was an author of legislation creating the Environmental Protection Agency, a prime mover behind efforts to include ozone layer protections in the Clean Air Act and an advocate of restructuring the national weapons laboratories to meet the needs of a peacetime economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative George E. Brown Jr. of California, the ranking Democrat on the House Committee on Science and the former chairman of the House Committee on Science, Space and Technology, is the dean of the Congressional science buffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, 79, has been a crucial supporter of manned and unmanned space exploration. He was an author of legislation creating the Environmental Protection Agency, a prime mover behind efforts to include ozone layer protections in the Clean Air Act and an advocate of restructuring the national weapons laboratories to meet the needs of a peacetime economy.</p>
        <p>''From my earliest days, I was fascinated by science,'' Mr. Brown said on a recent afternoon in his offices on Capitol Hill, his wife, Marta, at his side. ''Also by my earliest days, I was fascinated by a utopian vision of what the world could be like. I've thought that science could be the basis for a better world, and that's what I've been trying to do all these years.''</p>
        <p>Q. How skilled are scientists and researchers at presenting their case to Congress?</p>
        <p>A. Very unskilled. They, generally speaking, have too great a faith in the power of common sense and reason. That's not what drives most political figures, who are concerned about emotions and the way a certain event will affect their constituency. If you're going to work in a political environment, you have to know the reasoning of the people you're dealing with. You have to talk to them realistically. It does very little good to appeal to high principle, although I would not say that's insignificant. The vast majority of politicians think they are functioning on high principle.</p>
        <p>Q. Some months ago, we interviewed Dr. Leon Lederman, the former head of the Fermi National Laboratory. It was his view that it may have been a mistake over the years for the scientists to ask for funding as a part of the cold war. Do you agree with him?</p>
        <p>A. Well, I wouldn't describe it as a complete mistake. But to build the funding of science for the next generation on the basis of the cold war was not well advised. That implied that science wasn't important enough to survive without a cold war. The truth is that science -- research and development -- is probably the most important factor in the progress of the human race over the last several thousand years. To base support of science on something that ephemeral as temporary alliances and enemies is ridiculous!</p>
        <p>Q. What's your take on the Czech President and playwright Vaclav Havel's famous statement that the fall of Communism has meant ''the end'' of science?</p>
        <p>A. Well, like many people, I've tried to understand Mr. Havel as much as I could. I think his feeling was that science was the ultimate expression of a neo-modernist philosophy and that it is inherently bad because it fails to consider human emotions and needs. It was probably his hope that once the cold war was over and the need to have overwhelming military strength had dissipated, that people would revert to a more benign and caring and nonrational way of interacting.</p>
        <p>Havel was influenced by the fact that the Communist system considered itself to be the ultimate in ''scientific rationalism.'' Communism was touted from the beginning as a ''scientific'' way of looking at the problems of society. It wasn't. It probably never could be. It represented an effort to control society with a philosophy that was antithetical to freedom and democracy.</p>
        <p>Q. You're a strong advocate of international cooperation in science and yet, you are very critical of our State Department. Why?</p>
        <p>A. Because the State Department gives lip service to the importance of international cooperation in science. And lip service is about all they give. They are reducing the number of scientific attaches at overseas missions, and scientists in policy-making positions in the State Department here in Washington.</p>
        <p>My problem with the State Department is that they spend most of their time in this area in long, drawn-out international negotiations. They negotiate a new science and technology cooperation treaty. You can almost count on their doing that periodically with each country we have good relations with. Basically, it's a photo opportunity for the presidents of the two countries. Then, believe it or not, the administration doesn't request any money to carry out the provisions of the agreement. This isn't unique to the current Administration; they all do it.</p>
        <p>Q. The microbiologist Rita Colwell, an expert on cholera, was named last year to be the nation's top scientist, to head the National Science Foundation. Does her appointment represent a sea change in the N.S.F.'s direction?</p>
        <p>A. Her appointment could portend a new direction in the support of science in the United States. Her career and her achievements reflect the direction science funding is going into in the future. In other words, jobs, industrial opportunities are going to stem more from the biological sciences than from chemistry and physics. I see biology as being the greatest area of scientific breakthroughs in the next generation. So, I'll probably be supporting her in any changes she wants to make in the direction of the N.S.F.'s funding.</p>
        <p>Q. Are you a scientist?</p>
        <p>A. I'm not. I'm a politician. I started out with a background in science. I do have a degree in physics and did a short stint as an engineer. I was interested in science before I even knew what science was. I used to read science-fiction magazines when I was a kid, stories about space travel, and that led me -- structuring my college training in math, physics, chemistry, astronomy -- a little bit.  I've been on the Science Committee in the House since 1965.</p>
        <p>Q. When you are putting together science policy, how much do you rely on staff?</p>
        <p>A. How do you quantify that? I rely very, very heavily on the staff of the House Science Committee. That's because we have some the best people with the best scientific backgrounds available anywhere in the country. These people are good enough to know how to express my views, even when they don't agree with them. That's always very helpful.</p>
        <p>Q. Former Senator John Glenn was able to parlay his support for science into a second ride in space. Have you considered doing the same?</p>
        <p>A. (Laughs) I've indicated to NASA Administrator Dan Goldin that if he thinks I'm physically qualified, I'd still like to go into space. In any event, politicians have been known to use their influence to get things that they want.</p>
        <p>Q. When you give speeches, you say that you expect to watch the progress of the space program from your perch in heaven some day. What exactly do you mean?</p>
        <p>A. That I think we're soon going to have the exploration of the heavens by humans, starting with Mars and the rest of the solar system. I think maybe Dan Goldin and a few other people have this sense that human settlement of the universe is, beginning with what's nearest to us, an inevitable progression of human beings.</p>
        <p>Q. Where do you vote on the ''is there other life out there'' question?</p>
        <p>A. I consider the probability that there is other intelligent life in the universe overwhelming. And we will ultimately find it. It may not be exactly what we think it ought to be, but it will be intelligent life. It may be far more intelligent than we are. And that will be an interesting situation. How do we deal with a situation where we are encountering someone with vastly superior intellectual powers to ourselves? Now, I'm not fearful of that. Because highly evolved life will not be looking at new life forms as enemies. They will be looking on them as their children who need to be encouraged to develop even further.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you see a beneficent kind of ''Star Trek'' scenario for our space future?</p>
        <p>A. I think it will be beneficent, and I like ''Star Trek.'' The people who write ''Star Trek'' are going through all these same scenarios as you are. They are asking, ''What is a reasonable rational future for the human race?'' And then they try to project that into a television program.</p>
        <p>Q. I don't mean this disrespectfully, but as a senior member of the House, do you ever think about retirement?</p>
        <p>A. I have no desire or ambition to enter another career just to earn more money or something like that. So my criteria for retirement will be determined by my sense whether or not I'm adequately fulfilling the responsibilities I have.</p>
        <p>Some of my colleagues, years before they retired, weren't accomplishing anything. I don't want to do that. What I've always wanted to do is help shape ideas about the emerging human culture, the kind of thing that Newt Gingrich sometimes did. I think I can make a small contribution to that, maybe not as much as Newt. But I think I'm more on the right track. We'll see. As to my decision as to whether I decide to retire or not, that may be conditioned on how you write this story.</p>
        <p>A CONVERSATION WITH: GEORGE E. BROWN JR.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
