<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Abroad at Home; The Fault, Dear Brutus</title>
    <meta content="31LEWI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1164867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Two Thousand (Year)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE5DE1238F932A05751C1A96F958260" item-length="700" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Abroad at Home; The Fault, Dear Brutus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony Lewis Op-Ed column says last 1,000 years are noteworthy for remarkable achievements in science and technology; says one transforming change over thousand years is adoption of scientific method: commitment to experiment, to test every hypothesis; says it is willingness in all aspects of life to consider possibilities other than received truth; says it is openness to reason, and there is no escape from demands of reason (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When we think of our achievements at the end of this millennium, it is not artistic expressions of the human spirit that come to mind. Today's music and literature and art can hardly claim to surpass the past's. Not many contemporary buildings can be compared to Chartres.</p>
        <p>It is science and technology at which we excel. In the year 1000 most people lived in isolated communities, unaware of other societies. Today, from the palm of our hand, we can send words around the world. We can cure disease. We can destroy cities with a single weapon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When we think of our achievements at the end of this millennium, it is not artistic expressions of the human spirit that come to mind. Today's music and literature and art can hardly claim to surpass the past's. Not many contemporary buildings can be compared to Chartres.</p>
        <p>It is science and technology at which we excel. In the year 1000 most people lived in isolated communities, unaware of other societies. Today, from the palm of our hand, we can send words around the world. We can cure disease. We can destroy cities with a single weapon.</p>
        <p>Underneath the particulars there has been one transforming change over this thousand years. It is the adoption of the scientific method: the commitment to experiment, to test every hypothesis. But it is broader than science. It is the open mind, the willingness in all aspects of life to consider possibilities other than the received truth. It is openness to reason.</p>
        <p>Reason, Freud said, is persistent. It keeps trying to get past the dark instinctive forces in our psyche: ''This is one of the few points on which one can be optimistic about the future of mankind.'' He wrote that in 1933, just as the Nazis were about to show how powerful unreason can be.</p>
        <p>There you have the conflicted character of the century just ending. It saw dazzling scientific achievements -- and the darkest human instincts working on an unprecedented scale. More than 100 million people were killed in the name of ideology, perhaps 25 million by the Nazis, the rest by Communist regimes. This terrible century, Hannah Arendt called it.</p>
        <p>And the slaughter continued till the end of the century. Millions more have died in recent years, hated for their beliefs or their ethnic identity. Nothing in earlier centuries outdid the savagery of Cambodia, Bosnia or Rwanda.</p>
        <p>The great enemy of reason in this century has been political utopianism: absolute belief in a supposedly perfect system. In the totalitarian state that utopianism produced, dissent could not be tolerated; everything and everyone were forced into a single mold. The result was catastrophe for man and nature.</p>
        <p>The romance with political utopias is ended now. But the struggle for reason, for the open mind, continues. Human beings have a tenacious ability to shut out what they do not want to know: the novel, the uncomfortable. We all have disabling certitudes. We all suffer from deafness of the mind.</p>
        <p>Deafness to reason is especially dangerous today on one question: how to maintain a livable earth. I think it is the most profound challenge of the new millennium.</p>
        <p>Evidence of global warming, for example, is all around us. The increasing number of damaging storms, the higher winter temperatures: Something is happening. And the evidence is not just personal or anecdotal. A well-based scientific study published this month said that an area of Arctic Sea ice larger than Massachusetts is melting every year. Continuation of that trend will mean a significant rise in sea levels and the swamping of coastal cities around the world.</p>
        <p>Related to the environmental challenge is population growth. There were about 310 million people in the world in the year 1000. We have just passed the six-billion mark. We can feel the pressure of the rising numbers, on other species and on nature generally, even in a spacious country like the United States. In Rwanda, poor, small and densely populated, population pressure surely contributed to sparking the genocide.</p>
        <p>It will require all of our ingenuity and commitment to meet the challenges of environmental degradation and population growth. But even modest steps are obstructed now by ideology or a self-interest that cannot see beyond the short term. Like Mr. Micawber, we hope that something will turn up.</p>
        <p>Whatever our faith, there is no escape from human responsibility -- from the demands of reason. As President Kennedy said at the end of his inaugural speech in 1961, ''Let us go forth to lead the land we love, asking His blessing and His help, but knowing that here on earth God's work must truly be our own.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
