<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unnatural Forces Preying on the Island's Future Geography</title>
    <meta content="TERRAI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1140550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geology</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geology</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E5DF143FF935A1575AC0A96F958260" item-length="2091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unnatural Forces Preying on the Island's Future Geography</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on warnings from geologists that mankind, through industrialization, has acccelerated gelogical time to such an extent that it threatens Long Island's existance; photo; maps (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT a difference 14,000 years makes! Back when the last ice age was ending, the ocean was 300 feet lower than it is now. Long Island was not even an island;  it was still attached to the mainland.</p>
        <p>Geologic time -- the time it takes nature to change the face of the Earth -- usually moves at, well, a glacial pace. On a planet that is 4.5 billion years old, a millennium is hardly an occasion for celebration. It is a mere hiccup in the grand cosmic sweep.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT a difference 14,000 years makes! Back when the last ice age was ending, the ocean was 300 feet lower than it is now. Long Island was not even an island;  it was still attached to the mainland.</p>
        <p>Geologic time -- the time it takes nature to change the face of the Earth -- usually moves at, well, a glacial pace. On a planet that is 4.5 billion years old, a millennium is hardly an occasion for celebration. It is a mere hiccup in the grand cosmic sweep.</p>
        <p>But critics now fear that mankind has accelerated geologic time into a dangerous fast-forward that threatens Long Island's very existence. They say that industrialization has created unnatural forces, heating the atmosphere and raising sea levels at speeds that could prove catastrophic in the foreseeable future, starting in several decades.</p>
        <p>Famed beaches like Fire Island and oceanfront communities like Long Beach could vanish underwater. Across Nassau and Suffolk, wide swaths of the densely populated and low-lying South Shore could be ravaged by storms and inundated. Vital bays and wetlands could be devastated, their delicate marine ecology disrupted. Some native plants and creatures could die out and other species could invade. Salt water intrusion could jeopardize fresh-water wells. A rising water table could flood places that now seem high and dry.</p>
        <p>Waterfront property, now the most desirable, could become a liability as the waterline steadily creeps inland and streets turn into canals. Society could face agonizing decisions: Is it better to abandon billions of dollars of developed areas to the encroaching tides or to undertake the immense, costly construction of protective sea walls and a system of dikes along the most vulnerable points on Long Island's hundreds of miles of coastline?</p>
        <p>Maybe none of these events will happen. Some experts dispute such doomsday prognostications as being wildly overblown. Prior predictions of rapidly rising sea levels, they say, have already failed to materialize.</p>
        <p>But a growing body of scientists contends that global warming and higher sea levels are real trends, even if the experts are uncertain of the exact extent, timing and impact. While wary of making precise predictions of pending disaster, those experts say that Long Islanders -- 2.6 million people living on a relatively narrow strip of land surrounded by water -- would be foolish to dismiss an issue that could drastically affect the next generation.</p>
        <p>''You don't have to be panicked, but that doesn't mean you should ignore it, either,'' said Jay J. Tanski, a coastal geologist in the Sea Grant program at the State University at Stony Brook. Mr. Transki has been using computers to draw maps of areas that would be affected by various sea levels and by the flooding caused by severe storms that strike once or twice a century on average, the so-called 50- and 100-year storms.</p>
        <p>One nasty season like the marathon heat wave of this past summer does not impress scientists. But the undeniable fact that the 10 warmest years on record were all in the 1980's and 1990's is hard to dismiss, say officials at the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. And last year was the hottest of all.</p>
        <p>The smart response, Mr. Tanski said, is ''neither alarm nor complacency'' but realistic concern. A colleague at Stony Brook, Dr. Marvin A. Geller, a professor of atmospheric science and director of the Marine Sciences Research Center, agrees. ''The uncertainty in the projections should not be taken as an excuse'' to avoid preventive and remedial action, he said. ''It shouldn't throw us into paralysis.''</p>
        <p>Relatively modest precautionary steps taken now may fend off the most likely flooding and storm problems for several decades, many experts say. Those measures include the building up of dunes on barrier beaches and of lawns fronting on bays and the raising of existing bulkheads.</p>
        <p>''Holland is an example of a place that's lived on under an attack on its coast line and still prospered,'' Dr. Geller said.</p>
        <p>When big storms threaten Long Island, television camera crews usually head for the docks of Freeport to report on the flooded streets and basements. ''We've been working with the Village of Freeport, and they're saying it seems to flood more,'' Mr. Tanski said. ''Some of the things in the mitigation plan might be as simple as raising their bulkheading and lawns. If the sea rises a foot in 100 years and you can raise bulkheads by six inches, you've solved that problem for at least 50 years.''</p>
        <p>Another obvious battlefront is Long Island's most heavily populated oceanfront, Long Beach Island. Wisely or not, that strip houses 50,000 people in Atlantic Beach, Long Beach, Lido Beach and Point Lookout.</p>
        <p>''Whatever God and nature have in store for the next millennium, we're not able to control, but whatever we can do, we're doing,'' said Bruce Nyman, the city manager of Long Beach. The city recently spent millions of dollars on new bulkheads on the bay, and they are several inches higher than before. The city is also preparing to build and protect dunes along its two-mile boardwalk as part of a $72 million beach restoration by the Army Corps of Engineers.</p>
        <p>At one extreme of the global warming debate, a Columbia University computer study predicts an accelerated melting of the polar ice caps that would elevate the oceans by dozens of feet, wreaking havoc not only on Long Island but on New York City and coastal cities worldwide. ''The real wild card is what happens to the Antarctic ice sheet,'' Dr. Geller said.</p>
        <p>While such a cataclysm may be theoretically possible, many experts consider the chances to be remote.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to be telling people south of Montauk Highway that they should be moving or else,'' said Lee Koppelman, the executive director of the Long Island Regional Planning Board. ''I'm skeptical of these doom and gloom types who see a tremendous rise in sea levels. What makes them think the polar ice cap is going to instantly melt?</p>
        <p>''These people don't have a sense of the difference between cosmic time and human time. Even if their hypotheses are correct, it would take place over several hundred years.''</p>
        <p>But more and more scientists believe that something new is happening that could pose dangers.</p>
        <p>''For a long time I was skeptical that we are seeing global warming, but I've become less skeptical as time goes on,'' Dr. Geller said. ''The evidence seems to be increasing rather than decreasing.''</p>
        <p>In the scientific community, he said, ''A very significant majority would support the view that global warming will take place, and a somewhat lesser fraction say we're seeing it take place now. However, some of those would take exception to exaggerated claims of a disaster.''</p>
        <p>Virtually all the experts agree that sea levels have been gradually rising for thousands of years, in the latest of the Earth's long history of alternating warming and cooling cycles. Ever since the ice ages, climbing temperatures have been raising the sea level by melting the glaciers. The oceans have also been rising simply because warmer water expands and takes up more space than cooler water.</p>
        <p>Then there are the complications of human civilization in the last two centuries of population growth, modern agriculture, urban development and industrialization. Deforestation has removed countless trees that normally absorb carbon dioxide. Billions of tons of carbon dioxide are spewed into the atmosphere every year from the burning of fossil fuel -- coal, oil, natural gas and gasoline -- to heat buildings, run factories, fuel electric generators and power motor vehicles. Methane and nitrous oxide emissions are also up significantly.</p>
        <p>The result is the so-called greenhouse effect, trapping more heat from the sun's rays and warming the planet. ''Just the basic physics of putting these greenhouse gases into the atmosphere is certainly increasing the forces that should lead to global warming -- that's incontrovertible,'' Dr. Geller said. ''The exact timing, that's more controversial.''</p>
        <p>In the next century, worldwide temperatures could increase by 2 to 6 degrees, compared to just 1 degree in the last century and only several degrees over the past several thousands of years, according to a panel of experts convened by the United Nations.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A.'s forecast on the rise in sea levels for the next hundred years ranges from 1 to 4 feet, with about 2 feet as the most probable figure. Compounding Long Island's problem is that the land here is also sinking slightly into the Earth's crust.</p>
        <p>''I expect there would be winners and losers -- for example, areas of Russia might become more useful for agriculture,'' Dr. Geller said. ''But I find it difficult to imagine any scenario where Long Island comes out the winner. Obviously the lowest parts go first, and on Long Island some of the most precious resources are also the lowest -- our wetlands and our beaches.''</p>
        <p>Lives here could also be affected in other ways, Dr. Geller said. Rising temperatures would affect human comfort and health, and the resulting demand for more air conditioning could put stress on the electrical power system, as the past summer has already demonstrated.</p>
        <p>The changing climate could affect rainfall, too. Warmer air holds more moisture, and many experts predict more and heavier rainstorms. There may even be more severe nor'easters and hurricanes, making for a dangerous combination if sea levels also rise. But many experts consider such theories to be speculative.</p>
        <p>Despite efforts to curb the emission of greenhouse gases, population growth and the drive for development have so far proven to be stronger forces.</p>
        <p>Regardless of whether or when sea levels will rise, scientists say that not enough is being done to deal with present-day storm, erosion and flooding problems. ''We're not even addressing the issue of storm surges now,'' Mr. Tanski said. ''We have storms that come through and raise the sea level by 15 feet in a matter of hours,'' not decades or centuries.</p>
        <p>Facing the storm problems of today is the best preparation for coping with a rising sea level in the future, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Koppelman said that ''the only things that worry me is storm events'' and added, that if he was asked if government is doing a good job at responding, ''my answer is no.'' He declared: ''We only respond to crisis. We don't do intelligent planning. Once you have built the city of Long Beach, put houses on Fire Island and have a state park at Jones Beach, the objective has to be to maintain the barrier beaches. We can't just let nature do its thing. And it's much easier to fill a breach when a wheelbarrow will do the job than wait till the gap is a mile wide.''</p>
        <p>Many environmentalists oppose beach restoration as an unnatural and temporary fix and a waste of money.</p>
        <p>Others disagree. Gerard Stoddard, president of the Fire Island Association, representing about half of that community's property owners, said: ''Beach nourishment is a viable engineering and environmentally benign solution to protect eroding shorelines over typical planning horizons of 30 to 50 years. The key to looking at global warming is you might as well do what is proven practical to preventing the loss of resources. There's nothing inherently wrong with dredging. The only thing not good about it is the expense.''</p>
        <p>A major handicap in dealing with erosion and global warming issues is ''there's no one entity responsible for it,'' Mr. Tanski said. ''Because of the nature of the problem, it has to be addressed by all players, academic, Federal, State, regional and local.'' Unfortunately, he said, human nature is such that ''we kind of wait till disaster happens and then say we have to go back and fix things back the way they were.''</p>
        <p>But he has seen some small victories for foresightedness. In the recent reconstruction of the Loop Parkway, which connects the eastern tip of Long Beach Island to the Meadowbrook Parkway and the Long Island mainland, the roadbed was built six inches higher.</p>
        <p>It may not sound like much. But in cases of severe storms and flooding, Mr. Tanski said, ''People may actually be able to get out of there.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
