<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Bold Tactic in the Pollution Wars</title>
    <meta content="20MON2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1139257"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nitrogen Oxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sulfur Dioxide</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot L (Atty Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DF1E3CF933A1575AC0A96F958260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Bold Tactic in the Pollution Wars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial lauds announcement by New York Attorney General Eliot Spitzer that he intends to sue 17 coal-fired power plants in five Midwestern and border states in effort to force them to reduce sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide emissions, which are carried eastward by prevailing winds and are major cause of smog and acid rain (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At just the right moment, New York's Attorney General, Eliot Spitzer, has come forward with a new weapon in the unending battle against air pollution that blows into New York and other Northeastern states from power plants upwind. Mr. Spitzer announced last Wednesday that he intended to sue 17 coal-fired power plants in five Midwestern and border states in an effort to force them to reduce emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide. These pollutants, which are carried eastward by prevailing winds, are major causes of urban smog and of the acid rain that has caused so much damage to New York's forests and waterways.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's move has lifted the spirits of clean-air advocates, whose efforts to control windblown pollution have lately suffered one setback after another. The most recent and devastating blow was a ruling by the Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit that temporarily stayed a carefully crafted Federal plan requiring 22 states east of the Mississippi to reduce the emissions that cause smog. Subsequent efforts to negotiate a voluntary agreement between the Eastern and Midwestern states have gone nowhere. Meanwhile, the Republican Congress has shown no interest whatsoever in revisiting the Clean Air Act, despite mounting evidence that its provisions, particularly those on acid rain, need tightening.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At just the right moment, New York's Attorney General, Eliot Spitzer, has come forward with a new weapon in the unending battle against air pollution that blows into New York and other Northeastern states from power plants upwind. Mr. Spitzer announced last Wednesday that he intended to sue 17 coal-fired power plants in five Midwestern and border states in an effort to force them to reduce emissions of sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide. These pollutants, which are carried eastward by prevailing winds, are major causes of urban smog and of the acid rain that has caused so much damage to New York's forests and waterways.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer's move has lifted the spirits of clean-air advocates, whose efforts to control windblown pollution have lately suffered one setback after another. The most recent and devastating blow was a ruling by the Court of Appeals for the D.C. Circuit that temporarily stayed a carefully crafted Federal plan requiring 22 states east of the Mississippi to reduce the emissions that cause smog. Subsequent efforts to negotiate a voluntary agreement between the Eastern and Midwestern states have gone nowhere. Meanwhile, the Republican Congress has shown no interest whatsoever in revisiting the Clean Air Act, despite mounting evidence that its provisions, particularly those on acid rain, need tightening.</p>
        <p>Legal experts give Mr. Spitzer's initiative a fighting chance, even though it is based on an obscure and largely untested provision of the Clean Air Act. Under the act, older power plants were granted exemptions from the law's strict pollution standards in the expectation that they would be shut down in a few years and replaced with newer, cleaner plants. But the law also specified that plants that were significantly upgraded in order to lengthen their life span had to comply with the same pollution controls as new plants.</p>
        <p>After six months of sleuthing, involving detailed examination of Federal and state records, Mr. Spitzer's staff identified 17 plants where the owners made big capital improvements in order to extend the plant's life span and increase power output while making no meaningful investment in pollution controls. Further investigation by New York, other states or the Environmental Protection Agency may well turn up more offenders. But Mr. Spitzer believes that he has nailed the biggest and most obvious polluters. One plant in Ohio emitted more nitrogen oxide in 1998 than the 21 dirtiest New York power plants combined.</p>
        <p>These older plants are truly malignant. They contribute not only to smog and acid rain, but to global warming. They are also the largest source of mercury emissions, which are lethal for fish and other wildlife. But as they have already demonstrated in the D.C. Circuit, the power companies are  determined to resist change.</p>
        <p>Mr. Spitzer clearly has standing in court -- that is, the right to sue -- because under the Clean Air Act, he need only demonstrate that New York has suffered from windblown pollution, a point on which there is irrefutable evidence. His more problematic task will be to persuade a Federal judge to require that a particular plant reduce emissions with expensive new controls. The utilities will argue that their investments were aimed solely at maintaining the reliability of existing equipment. Mr. Spitzer believes he has enough documentation to show that the owners' sole motive was to retool the plants and enlarge capacity.</p>
        <p>Because Mr. Spitzer is a Democrat, there was some grumbling in the administration of Gov. George Pataki that he was trying to steal the Governor's thunder on clean-air issues. The grumblers should be saluting Mr. Spitzer instead. Mr. Pataki's credentials on this issue are secure enough. What he and the entire Northeast need are more allies and more weapons. The Attorney General has given them both.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
