<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Motor City Come Up With A Clean Machine?</title>
    <meta content="19BRAD$15" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1108603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="CARS AND THE ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0DD1F3CF93AA25756C0A96F958260" item-length="3333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Motor City Come Up With A Clean Machine?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILLIAM C. FORD JR., the new 42-year-old chairman of the Ford Motor Company, became an environmentalist the way many baby boomers did. As a boy, he loved to hike, fish and go camping; he hated to revisit a spot only to find that someone else had made a mess of it. In high school, he volunteered to spend afternoons picking up trash along a nearby river. At Princeton University, he read books by radical environmentalists and stayed up late discussing how to save the earth.</p>
        <p>Then he joined the family business as a vehicle-planning analyst in 1979, and got a shock when he tried to raise environmental concerns. ''Coming to an old-line auto company, people looked at me like I was a Bolshevik for bringing it up, for even asking the questions,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILLIAM C. FORD JR., the new 42-year-old chairman of the Ford Motor Company, became an environmentalist the way many baby boomers did. As a boy, he loved to hike, fish and go camping; he hated to revisit a spot only to find that someone else had made a mess of it. In high school, he volunteered to spend afternoons picking up trash along a nearby river. At Princeton University, he read books by radical environmentalists and stayed up late discussing how to save the earth.</p>
        <p>Then he joined the family business as a vehicle-planning analyst in 1979, and got a shock when he tried to raise environmental concerns. ''Coming to an old-line auto company, people looked at me like I was a Bolshevik for bringing it up, for even asking the questions,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Whether the problems were air and water pollution from factories, or tailpipe emissions from the cars that came off the assembly lines, managers then had no interest in taking action, Mr. Ford said. As Ford's director of business strategy in the early 1990's, he sent out a memorandum calling a meeting on environmental policy -- only to be warned immediately by the company's lawyers that even writing the memorandum, much less holding the meeting, could be used against Ford in an environmental lawsuit.</p>
        <p>On several occasions, Mr. Ford said, he reached the point where he told his wife that he was going to leave the company to form an environmentalist group. ''My friends and my wife always convinced me that the impact I could have would be far greater if I stayed,'' said Mr. Ford, sitting in the same conference room where he had held his meeting on environmental policy over the lawyers' objections. ''And they were right, ultimately, but they were more patient than I was.''</p>
        <p>After decades of often vociferous hostility toward the environmental movement, Ford Motor and the rest of the auto industry are beginning to show some interest in improving their records on pollution. While car makers are still capable of rousing the ire of environmentalists, notably by increasing their output of gas-guzzling but high-profit sport utility vehicles, attitudes within the industry are slowly but perceptibly changing.</p>
        <p>A new generation of auto executives is taking charge, one that views environmental values as part of mainstream American life. Some, like Mr. Ford, are relatively young; some are older executives who have moved into the auto industry from other businesses, like detergent manufacturing, that came to terms with environmentalists long ago. While a few foreign auto makers, notably Honda, have touted their environmental records for years, domestic auto makers are just starting to see theirs as a marketing strength, giving them a financial incentive to compete on who can be greenest.</p>
        <p>''Market survey after market survey tells us environmental issues are increasingly important to our customers,'' said Harry J. Pearce, the vice chairman of General Motors.</p>
        <p>Until recently, virtually all of the auto industry's improvements were forced by Government regulation and were bitterly fought at every turn. To some extent, that is still the case; the industry fiercely opposes any tightening of fuel-economy regulations, for example, despite evidence that gasoline consumption contributes directly to global warming.</p>
        <p>Yet now, many auto makers are also beginning to look for ways to clean up their factories and the vehicles they sell without waiting for regulators to step in. The main example so far has been Ford's decision, beginning with the 1999 model year, to make all its sport utility vehicles roughly as clean as cars, instead of continuing to exploit a loophole in Federal regulations that allows the off-road vehicles to emit several times more pollution per mile than cars do. Ford is also buying junkyards, with a plan to reuse more auto parts instead of letting them clog landfills.</p>
        <p>Other auto makers are also taking voluntary steps. All of Honda's American-made Civics and Accords now meet California's strict emissions standard, and its Odyssey minivan and Passport sport utility vehicle have very low emissions, although the CR-V sport utility does not. DaimlerChrysler is working on a host of initiatives, like working on low-pollution synthetic diesel. And General Motors has spent hundreds of millions of dollars to develop and market an electric car, while helping the Nature Conservancy to buy and then preserve the habitats of rare species.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most surprisingly, the auto industry did fairly little lobbying against the Clinton Administration's proposal earlier this month to require much lower tailpipe emissions, particularly from sport utility vehicles and pickups. Instead, it demanded, and got, new Federal regulations requiring oil companies to sell much cleaner gasoline -- a decision that will make it easier to produce clean-burning cars, but enraged the oil industry.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists are divided on how much credit to give the auto makers. Some, like John DeCicco, the transportation program director at the Washington-based American Council for an Energy-Efficient Economy, are fairly generous. ''The management of the auto industry is part of our American society, which has internalized environmental values over the last three decades,'' he said.</p>
        <p>OTHERS are more dubious. One is Daniel Becker, a vocal critic of the auto industry for nearly a quarter-century, first as an aide to Ralph Nader, and now as the Sierra Club's director for energy policy and global warming. Mr. Becker said that Ford's decision to clean up its sport utility vehicles was the only significant, voluntary step that Detroit had taken in recent decades to improve the environment, and he questioned whether other steps would come soon.</p>
        <p>The auto industry still bankrolls various groups, like the Coalition for Vehicle Choice, that criticize Federal fuel-economy rules and international efforts to limit global warming, Mr. Becker noted. Auto advertising executives continue trying to persuade Americans that relatively unregulated, high-profit sport utility vehicles are appropriate substitutes for cars, he said. Indeed, with profits on full-size sport utility vehicles running at $12,000 or more apiece, auto makers have increased production and sales in this category more than sixfold since the early 1990's. ''In terms of policy decisions, in terms of product lines,'' Mr. Becker said, ''I don't think the change has started in a dramatic way.''</p>
        <p>Auto industry leaders say they deserve more credit. John G. Smale, a marketer of soaps and detergents who became the chairman of Procter &amp; Gamble and then of General Motors, said car makers had caught up with other businesses in understanding that environmental issues were important to consumers.</p>
        <p>''I think G. M. was slower than P. &amp; G., certainly in coming to that realization, but I think that's true of the rest of the industry too,'' said Mr. Smale, who is now chairman of the G. M. board's powerful executive committee. ''I think, by and large now, the industry sees it the same way.''</p>
        <p>Nobody disputes that the sheer size of the auto industry makes it tremendously important to the environment. G. M., Ford and DaimlerChrysler are the world's three largest companies in terms of sales; their closest rivals are trading companies and retailers, which do not actually make the products they sell, followed by big oil companies. For all the attention that Internet and software companies receive, G. M. still has 11 times the sales of Microsoft and 22 times as many employees.</p>
        <p>Without question, the most dramatic shift in environmental stance recently has been at Ford. Alexander Trotman, the company's chairman and chief executive until the end of last year, led auto industry criticisms of the efforts to limit global warming, questioning the scientific basis for environmentalists' concerns. He was also skeptical of moves to further reduce tailpipe emissions. The decision to build cleaner-burning sport utilities was led by another top Ford executive, Jacques Nasser, a 51-year-old ally of Mr. Ford's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotman retired early this year, and Mr. Nasser replaced him as the company's chief executive; Mr. Ford became chairman. A great-grandson of Henry Ford's, he won the family's confidence to run the company, even though he was one of the younger members of the Fords' fourth generation. A nephew of Henry Ford 2d's, he had not grown up as heir apparent at the family-controlled company.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford and Mr. Nasser share a strong interest in the environment, although not necessarily the same interest in nature. The differences are apparent even in their offices. Mr. Ford's looks like a greenhouse: while one wall is a floor-to-ceiling window with a 20-mile view across metropolitan Detroit, most of the vista is obscured by potted ficus trees. More plants festoon the desk, coffee table and conference table, while the long shelf behind his desk is covered with peace lilies under special growing lights. ''I need a machete,'' Mr. Ford quipped as he walked in.</p>
        <p>MR. NASSER'S office next door is, by contrast, a desert. A single, small plant sits incongruously on the floor in front of a gigantic window as big as Mr. Ford's. The plant, which has coiled leaves that resemble spikes, does not look happy.</p>
        <p>Nicknamed ''Jac the Knife'' because of his cost-cutting measures in Ford Motor's European operations during the early 90's, Mr. Nasser never mentioned camping or rivers or great books when asked how he became interested in the environment. Instead, he plunged into an 11-minute soliloquy on the importance of brands and how their images were formed in the public mind.</p>
        <p>In an increasingly global economy, Mr. Nasser said, consumers increasingly turn to a few well-known brands, like Volvo's small but famous car-making division, which Ford Motor bought earlier this year. At the same time, the rise of the Internet and other forms of communications has made it possible for information about a company's activities in any city to spread quickly all over the world. So to have a popular, global brand that consumers will seek out, a company must be a good corporate citizen everywhere, Mr. Nasser concluded.</p>
        <p>''Brands are becoming more important, and corporate image is becoming more important on a global basis,'' he said. ''And it's very difficult, I think, in today's environment to have a global image that is substantially different from your local image.''</p>
        <p>In other words, car makers can no longer put big, polluting factories in out-of-the-way communities and hope no one will notice. Nor can they make particularly dirty vehicles and hope no one will notice. Rival auto makers estimate that Ford's cleaner sport utility vehicles are costing the company at least $100 million a year, mainly for bigger catalytic converters, an expense Ford says it is not passing on to consumers. While a few other S.U.V.'s are being cleaned up, most are not, and rival executives are criticizing Ford for taking action.</p>
        <p>Bernard Robertson, DaimlerChrysler's senior vice president for engineering, said Ford had to do something in response to criticisms of its huge Ford Expedition sport utility vehicle and its even larger Ford Excursion, which will go on sale this autumn. The Excursion will be the world's largest S.U.V., taller than Michael Jordan and weighing as much as three Ford Escorts; with its 44-gallon gas tank and a fuel economy as low as 10 miles per gallon, it has been dubbed the ''Ford Valdez'' by the Sierra Club. ''With the Expedition and Excursion, Ford has gone to the extremes of consumption,'' Mr. Robertson said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford said that he understood the criticisms of the Excursion. But he maintained that some auto maker was inevitably going to build such a giant vehicle, and at least Ford was designing it to be as clean as most cars.</p>
        <p>SUCH excuses do not satisfy Mr. Becker of the Sierra Club, who said that while he believed that Mr. Ford genuinely cared about the environment, he doubted that such views had spread widely through the company. ''This is a very large ship, and he's a small rudder so far,'' Mr. Becker said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford has also shifted his company's position on global warming, but not as much as environmentalists would like. He said there was a scientific basis for concern, but that any international agreement to limit the problem would have to include developing nations. Many environmentalists believe this to be politically impossible.</p>
        <p>Some environmentalists also fault the auto industry for not having sold many alternatives to the gasoline-powered car. All of the big auto manufacturers are spending heavily to research alternative technologies, like electric cars, which use batteries or, more recently, fuel cells, which generate electricity by combining hydrogen and oxygen without combustion. Yet alternative-fuel cars have become a chimera that has receded ever further into the future for most of this century. Regulators in California and New York required a decade ago that electric cars be widely available by now. They retreated from that goal, however, as technological advances proved inadequate and as gasoline-powered cars became steadily cleaner.</p>
        <p>G. M. has actually put an electric vehicle, the EV1 coupe, on the market in California and Arizona. But its limited range and small passenger compartment have made it a marketing failure, with only 289 leased in 1997 and 264 last year, many by environmentalists and image-conscious celebrities. Mr. Smale said G .M. had learned some valuable technological lessons from the EV1, including how to develop better batteries for electric cars.</p>
        <p>Ford sells most of the alternative-fuel vehicles in the United States, but these are mainly electric and natural gas-powered pickup trucks and vans purchased by utilities and Government agencies. Honda and Toyota plan to appeal to the public soon by selling small cars powered by a combination of a gasoline engine and an electric battery.</p>
        <p>AMERICA'S small-car market is shrinking, however, and both companies plan to ship limited numbers of their vehicles here. They will also have to sell them below the high cost of manufacturing them.</p>
        <p>Despite lavish Federal subsidies and numerous promises by auto makers to put high-mileage cars on sale by 2004, there is little sign of continuing public interest in fuel economy. This is probably linked to the fact that gasoline is still cheaper than bottled water in most of the country, even though gas prices recently rebounded.</p>
        <p>The 10 most fuel-efficient cars on the market now account together for less than 1 percent of sales in the United States, while auto makers no longer even bother putting fuel-economy statistics in their advertisements. They have found that such information does not draw customers.</p>
        <p>BARRING another energy crisis, the main environmental issue in the United States is likely to remain the ever-growing fleet of gasoline-powered cars being driven ever more miles, thereby contributing to smog and global warming. Alternative-fuel vehicles are most likely to be introduced in Europe and East Asia. That's where gasoline costs $4 a gallon and up, and where people are more willing to accept small cars that are suitable for city driving but less so for the highway, said Robert C. Purcell, G. M.'s executive director of advanced technology vehicles.</p>
        <p>G.M., in particular, used to have a grim reputation for refusing to acknowledge that environmental problems even existed. David Lewis, an automotive historian at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor who worked as a speech writer for two G. M. presidents from 1959 to 1965, said company policy then was to insist it was the oil refineries and other businesses, not cars, that caused air pollution.</p>
        <p>''If we were accused of contributing to air pollution, we would simply say nothing had been proved,'' Mr. Lewis said.</p>
        <p>Not only did G. M.'s cars pollute the air, but so did its factories. Trying to show that the river next to one of its assembly plants was clean in the early 1960's, G. M. officials dumped in live fish in front of television cameras, which filmed the fish as they swam around. The next morning, after the cameras had left, Mr. Lewis said, workers returned to scoop out the fish, which were by then floating belly up.</p>
        <p>G. M. has recently begun improving its efforts regarding the environment, with John F. Smith Jr., the company's chairman and chief executive, joining the board of the Nature Conservancy, following the lead of Mr. Smale, a longtime member of the conservancy's board.</p>
        <p>Having seen customers avoid detergents that included phosphates in the early 1970's, Mr. Smale came to the chairmanship of G. M. in 1992 with a strong appreciation of the risks for companies tarred as environmentally insensitive. He began lecturing G. M. managers on the importance of the issue. The company's current executives, he said, ''realize that a lot of people in the country care about environmental responsibilities.''</p>
        <p>Until the last few months, some of the strongest criticisms of environmentalists have come from the former Chrysler Corporation. Robert J. Eaton, the company's chairman, and Robert A. Lutz, the vice chairman, were outspokenly skeptical of claims that global warming might be a problem. A brilliant car designer who resents any criticism of his industry, Mr. Lutz published a business-advice book last year in which he briefly compared ''environmental extremists'' to Communists, saying that both sought to eliminate the public's freedom to travel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lutz retired last year -- he now runs a car battery company; Mr. Eaton, now a co-chairman of DaimlerChrysler A.G., is expected to retire soon. Since Chrysler was acquired late last year by Daimler-Benz A.G., a leader in research on fuel cells and other environmentally sensitive technologies, the combined company has shown more enthusiasm for cleaner vehicles.</p>
        <p>To the constant irritation of Detroit auto executives, foreign auto makers have had relatively little trouble with American environmentalists. Most top-selling foreign cars are fairly fuel-efficient because they were designed in countries where gasoline is expensive. During the 1970's, Japanese auto makers came up with cleaner engines for their small cars at a time when American auto makers were still contending that low-emissions technology was unfeasible.</p>
        <p>But while foreign cars may be ubiquitous in coastal cities like New York and Los Angeles, they remain less common in the Midwest. G. M. still sells more cars and other family vehicles in the United States each year than every Japanese and European auto maker combined.</p>
        <p>The harmony between foreign auto makers and American environmentalists may yet fade, as the foreign companies have begun to sell larger vehicles. Toyota, in particular, has been moving aggressively into the market for S.U.V.'s, while setting a fairly slow timetable for reducing their emissions. But after decades of hostility toward Detroit, most environmentalists still focus on auto makers based in Michigan.</p>
        <p>The younger American auto industry executives want to change this pattern. They insist that as an older generation of leaders continues to retire, environmental progress will continue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ford said that during his 20-year ascent through the company ranks, he was often struck by how many other young managers were worried about the company's environmental performance. They were thwarted from doing much, Mr. Ford said, because ''there were a few people in key management positions that didn't want to hear of it.''</p>
        <p>The growing number of environmentally committed people moving into positions of responsibility in the auto industry will enable further initiatives to clean up the world's air and water, Mr. Ford said.</p>
        <p>He added, ''I'm not sure, if I were chairman 10 years ago, that the world would have been ready for my views.''</p>
        <p>CARS AND THE ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
