<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As a Mars Landing Nears, NASA Says All Seems Fine</title>
    <meta content="Y03MAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1158022"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Polar Lander (Spacecraft)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mars (Planet)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19991203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E5DF143EF930A35751C1A96F958260" item-length="981" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As a Mars Landing Nears, NASA Says All Seems Fine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <dateline>PASADENA, Calif., Dec. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA says Mars Polar Lander will set down at Martian south pole on Dec 3 after 11-month cruise across interplanetary space; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After an 11-month cruise across interplanetary space, the Mars Polar Lander was pronounced sound and on course today and ready to live up to its name by setting down on the cold, high ground near the Martian south pole.</p>
        <p>The landing, the first at the polar region of another planet, is scheduled for 3:01 p.m. (Eastern time) on Friday. NASA's reliance on new technologies and the strange polar environment that is the spacecraft's destination seemed to make mission officials and scientists increasingly apprehensive about the chances for success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After an 11-month cruise across interplanetary space, the Mars Polar Lander was pronounced sound and on course today and ready to live up to its name by setting down on the cold, high ground near the Martian south pole.</p>
        <p>The landing, the first at the polar region of another planet, is scheduled for 3:01 p.m. (Eastern time) on Friday. NASA's reliance on new technologies and the strange polar environment that is the spacecraft's destination seemed to make mission officials and scientists increasingly apprehensive about the chances for success.</p>
        <p>''There's still a very real possibility that we may not hear anything,'' Richard Cook, the project manager for the mission, said of the moments after the spacecraft is due to land. Silence could signal anything from a minor communications lapse to a serious malfunction.</p>
        <p>But if the landing is a success, the robotic spacecraft will begin pros pecting the landscape of dirt and ice for traces of water and evidence of the planet's climatic history, all part of the greater quest to learn if life in some form ever arose on Mars or could still exist in moist, sheltered niches. The explorations are expected to continue for three months, through the continuous daylight of summer in the Martian polar latitudes.</p>
        <p>Dr. David Paige, a project scientist at the University of California at Los Angeles, said the spacecraft was being aimed ''as close as we possibly can get to a place where there is likely to be ice.''</p>
        <p>The 1,200-pound spacecraft is supposed to settle down on a relatively smooth, rolling surface of broad terraces a few hundred miles from the south pole. The ''target sector,'' at about 76 degrees south latitude and 195 degrees west longitude, is far from the edge of the permanent polar ice cap, but far enough south that only a few weeks ago the surface was still covered by the carbon dioxide frost of winter.</p>
        <p>''It's a completely different terrain from any previous landing sites on Mars,'' Dr. Paige said.</p>
        <p>An analysis of recent photography by another spacecraft orbiting Mars showed the landing area to be marked by long, low parallel ridges, shallow gullies and depressions, and scattered protruding knobs, all shaped by the presence of ice on the surface and underground and the coming and going of seasonal frosts.</p>
        <p>Dr. Sam Thurman, flight operations manager for the project here at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory, said the spacecraft was being continuously tracked and its navigation instructions checked and revised in the final hours of its approach. A slight correction in its flight path could be made as late as six and a half hours before entry into the thin Martian atmosphere.</p>
        <p>If all goes according to plan, the spacecraft will turn its nose forward for the plunge into the atmosphere. It will shed a segment that supported its interplanetary flight. And then it will release two probes, each the size of a basketball. They are to smash into the Martian surface several miles away from where the spacecraft will come to rest.</p>
        <p>Speeding in at 15,400 miles an hour, the spacecraft will enter the upper fringes of Martian air for the five and a half minute descent to landing. Atmospheric friction will start the braking process, raising temperatures on the heat-shield to 3,000 degrees. About two minutes before landing, the craft's parachute will unfurl, then its three metal legs will be deployed and a camera will snap pictures of the looming polar landscape.</p>
        <p>Finally, 12 rocket thrusters will fire to slow the descent to five miles an hour when the lander is just above the surface. The exhaust is expected to kick up plumes of polar dust.</p>
        <p>It will be 4:20 a.m., local time on Mars, and 12:01 p.m. at the control room here. But because the craft must wait for the dust to settle before it deploy an antenna, and because radio signals take 14 minutes to reach Earth from Mars, flight controllers do not expect to receive confirmation of a successful landing until 12:39.</p>
        <p>If all goes well, the spacecraft's first radio transmission is supposed to last 45 minutes and include camera shots of its footpads and the surface nearby. But if the ground the lander happens to stand on is sloping, the craft may be tilted so that its small antenna cannot link up with Earth. Mr. Cook said the spacecraft's computer has instructions for correcting the problem, or flight controllers could send new instructions through the craft's smaller omni-directional antenna.</p>
        <p>Within a couple of days of obtaining a communications link, the polar lander craft should be sending a regular flow of pictures and reports on temperatures, air pressure and humidity in the frigid region. On late Tuesday or Wednesday, the craft's six-and-a half-foot-long mechanical arm is to begin scratching and digging in the soil, collecting samples to examine for the presence of water ice. Unless the ground is frozen solid, the digger should be able to reach down 20 inches for samples.</p>
        <p>''We have good reason to believe there is water in the polar soil,'' Dr. Paige said. ''The question is how deep, in what form and how abundant is the water.''</p>
        <p>The two microprobes, Deep Space 2, were designed to penetrate even deeper, perhaps three feet or more, in the search for evidence of water.</p>
        <p>Coverage of the landing is available on the Web from NASA at:</p>
        <p>marslander.jpl.nasa.gov/</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
