<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OBSERVATORY</title>
    <meta content="24OBSE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1132804"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soil</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Erosion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Space Telescope Science Institute</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carnegie Institution of Washington</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fountain, Henry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Columns/Observatory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E4DE1238F937A1575BC0A96F958260" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OBSERVATORY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY FOUNTAIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fountain, Henry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Astronomers from Space Telescope Science Institute, studying late-stage stars known as red giants, discover that some of them apparently gobble up large planets whole; long-term study of watershed in Wisconsin farmland suggests that topsoil erosion problem is not as dire as has been generally believed; study by scientists from Carnegie Institution of Washington and other institutions shows that elevated levels of carbon dioxide in air--of kind that accompanies industrialization--can change structure of soil, making it clumpier; soil that sticks together better resists rain and wind (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Planet-Eating Stars</p>
        <p>Over the last several years, a score of giant planets have been discovered far beyond the solar system. Now, new research suggests that at one time, other so-called extrasolar planets must have existed as well. These planets, however, disappeared long ago, becoming food for the stars they were orbiting around.</p>
        <p>Astronomers from the Space Telescope Science Institute, studying the late-stage stars known as red giants, have discovered that some of them apparently gobbled up large planets whole.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Planet-Eating Stars</p>
        <p>Over the last several years, a score of giant planets have been discovered far beyond the solar system. Now, new research suggests that at one time, other so-called extrasolar planets must have existed as well. These planets, however, disappeared long ago, becoming food for the stars they were orbiting around.</p>
        <p>Astronomers from the Space Telescope Science Institute, studying the late-stage stars known as red giants, have discovered that some of them apparently gobbled up large planets whole.</p>
        <p>How can they tell? Well, like the cat that swallowed the canary, while there may not be even a feather left behind, it is evident what has gone on. A red giant that has been on a binge, the astronomers note, emits more infrared light (as it heats up from absorbing the planet's gravitational energy), spins faster (as it digests all that excess angular momentum), and shows lithium in its spectrum (getting a fresh supply of the element from the planet).</p>
        <p>Most of the large planets that have been discovered are in orbits that are close enough to their stars that in another couple of billion years or so, when the stars reach red-gianthood, the planets will become just so much fodder.</p>
        <p>Reassessing Erosion</p>
        <p>Modern agriculture has often been viewed as a villain, blamed for, among other things, the lack of flavor in fruits and vegetables, the demise of the family farm and the alarming rate of topsoil erosion in the United States.</p>
        <p>But at least in the case of soil erosion, agriculture may not be such a big bad wolf after all. A long-term study of a watershed in Wisconsin farmland suggests that the erosion problem is not as dire as has been generally believed. The rate of erosion in the study area has been decreasing since the Dust Bowl of the 1930's and is now 6 percent of what it was then.</p>
        <p>The research was conducted by a scientist at the University of California at Los Angeles, who in 1973 resumed a study begun 35 years before. The result is a long record of precise measurements of sediment buildup and erosion in Coon Creek Basin in western Wisconsin. A report on the work appears in the current issue of the journal Nature.</p>
        <p>In many previous studies of erosion, soil movement was examined in one area and then calculated, through modeling, for an entire watershed. The Coon Creek study is much more extensive. Among other findings, it determined that the amount of soil leaving for good, headed down the Mississippi River, has remained basically unchanged for years.</p>
        <p>The results suggest that soil conservation efforts, which have been greatly expanded over the last two decades with practices like minimal tilling of cropland, have had the intended effect.</p>
        <p>Good News in the Air</p>
        <p>If indeed there is less soil erosion these days, then perhaps society as a whole deserves some of the credit.</p>
        <p>A study by scientists from the Carnegie Institution of Washington and other institutions has shown that elevated levels of carbon dioxide in the air -- of the kind that accompanies industrialization -- can change the structure of soil, making it clumpier. And soil that sticks together better resists rain and wind.</p>
        <p>The researchers, who discussed their work in a recent issue of Nature, exposed soils from three types of ecosystems to different levels of carbon dioxide over three to six years. In most of the experiments, small aggregates of soil -- clumps about one-tenth of an inch in diameter -- increased.</p>
        <p>The researchers are not sure why the soil structure changes, but suspect that it is the work of a fungus that has a symbiotic relationship with plant roots.</p>
        <p>Plants exposed to more carbon dioxide usually produce more carbohydrate, some of which is used by the fungi to produce a sugar-protein compound called glomalin. Glomalin is thought to function as a kind of lubricant to help the fungi's filament structure extend through the soil. But it also may act almost like a glue, holding soil particles together.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
