<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Ever-Present Plague: Dust</title>
    <meta content="LICLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1086771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE6DB173DF932A15751C0A96F958260" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Ever-Present Plague: Dust</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERY housekeeper fights a never-ending battle against dust. At times it seems that the dust begins to collect on surfaces immediately after they are wiped clean. Actually this is not an exaggeration, because the dust is circulating in the air around us and it starts to settle when the air currents subside.</p>
        <p>What is dust and where does it come from? Dust is simply fine bits of matter that are capable of floating in the air. It can range in size from invisible microscopic  particles to grains of sand.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERY housekeeper fights a never-ending battle against dust. At times it seems that the dust begins to collect on surfaces immediately after they are wiped clean. Actually this is not an exaggeration, because the dust is circulating in the air around us and it starts to settle when the air currents subside.</p>
        <p>What is dust and where does it come from? Dust is simply fine bits of matter that are capable of floating in the air. It can range in size from invisible microscopic  particles to grains of sand.</p>
        <p>Dust particles are formed when a substance is broken down either physically, through abrasion, or chemically, through combustion. Every time someone enters your home they bring a little dust with them from the outside. The best way to minimize this incoming dust is by installing area rugs at all entrances. Encourage people to wipe their feet before treading inside. Vacuum and shake out these rugs weekly.</p>
        <p>This, however, is only a small part of the dust battle, because most dust in a home is created inside. It comes from two major sources: the fabrics around the house and our own bodies. Clothes, drapes, carpets, upholstery, towels and other fabrics are constantly being worn away every time we move or brush against them. Eventually the fabric erodes into tiny lint and filament particles that eventually settle as dust.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the human body continually  produces considerable quantities of dust as it sheds dried out layers of skin. As new layers are created, old ones dry and disintegrate into dust particles.</p>
        <p>Since neither of these dust sources can be eliminated, the best the housekeeper can do is to pick up the dust as soon as it settles. In spite of all the advances in technology, the best dust-collecting tools are ones that have been around for decades: the dust cloth, the dust mop and the vacuum. The techniques for using these tools are basic and obvious.</p>
        <p>The only trick to using the dust cloth is in selecting one made of natural cotton fibers. Cloths with synthetic fibers are less absorbent and can produce a static charge that repels dust away from the cloth. Dusting sprays are also useful because they give the dust cloth or mop an electrostatic charge that attracts dust particles. Sprays are effective, but can be expensive.</p>
        <p>The only way to pull dust from fabrics is by washing, shaking or vacuuming them. Carpets should be vacuumed every week because they are major dust collectors. Every time someone walks across a carpet, the fibers throw some dust into the air. In addition, the dirt and dust particles embedded in the carpet abrade the surrounding fibers to produce even more dust.</p>
        <p>Upholstered chairs and sofas readily collect dust, and they spew it into the air whenever someone sits down. You can vacuum more dust from a chair cushion if you place it in a large plastic bag. Close the mouth of the bag around the vacuum nozzle and allow the machine to suck the air and dust out of the pillow.</p>
        <p>Most housekeepers ignore clothes closets during the weekly cleanup, yet the closets are significant dust producers. Garments shed fibers whenever they are removed or replaced from the rack. This abrasion can be reduced considerably by keeping clothes in individual plastic bags. It is not necessary to buy special bags for this; simply use the ones that come from the cleaners. Remember to vacuum the closet floor periodically or the dust that settles there will be thrown into air each time someone opens the closet door.</p>
        <p>With a vacuum cleaner, the amount of dust collected depends on the suction power of the machine and the filter inside. In most vacuum cleaners the collecting bag acts as a dirt filter. Paper bags have a better filtration action than cloth bags; some can capture particles as small as 10 microns. Special vacuum bags that can capture particles as small as one micron are also available (they cost more than ordinary bags), but they cannot be used in all vacuums because require extra suction. They must be used in vacuums with powerful motors.</p>
        <p>Dust is a byproduct of combustion. Whenever fossil fuels, heating oil, natural gas or wood are burned, they are converted into heat energy and combustion gases (wood also has an ash residue that disintegrates into dust). The combustion gases carry minute particles that settle as dust. Well-tuned burners consume more fuel with less waste. Have the burner in your heating system tuned annually by a heating specialist and make sure the venting system is well maintained. In a forced-air system the filter traps airborne dust. It should be replaced whenever it gets dirty.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
