<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amid Apollo 11 Nostalgia, Questions on NASA's Fate</title>
    <meta content="18MOON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1999" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1124422"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1999"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Moon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apollo Project</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Aeronautics and Space Administration</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19990718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E4DE103FF93BA25754C0A96F958260" item-length="1427" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amid Apollo 11 Nostalgia, Questions on NASA's Fate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NASA officials, scientists and others involved in space projects prepare to celebrate 30th anniversary of Apollo 11 lunar landing even as they wonderabout space agency's fate; many worry that United States has lost can-do spirit and will to carry out ambitious, expensive space endeavors; some have mixed feelings about celebrations that dwell on the past; concern is that Apollo should not be held up as model for planning space exploration for long haul; project resulted from cold war confrontation between United States and Soviet Union; it was crash program and too expensive to be sustained once immediate goal was achieved; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over dinner a few weeks ago, a former astronaut who walked on the Moon and one of the Apollo flight directors got to skylarking about the good old days, something people do when they think of their past receding and a big anniversary approaching, in this case the 30th anniversary of the Apollo 11 lunar landing on July 20, 1969.</p>
        <p>They laughed almost to tears telling cherished stories, one trying to top the other, about the time men flew to the Moon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over dinner a few weeks ago, a former astronaut who walked on the Moon and one of the Apollo flight directors got to skylarking about the good old days, something people do when they think of their past receding and a big anniversary approaching, in this case the 30th anniversary of the Apollo 11 lunar landing on July 20, 1969.</p>
        <p>They laughed almost to tears telling cherished stories, one trying to top the other, about the time men flew to the Moon.</p>
        <p>Then a cloud seemed to pass over their faces. Without prompting, they wondered in sadness and perplexity what had happened to the good old days.</p>
        <p>Where were the astronauts on Mars? The permanent lunar bases or the giant space stations wheeling through orbit? This was the future that should have arrived by now, as prophesied in the heady atmosphere of the Apollo 11 triumph. Both men -- the astronaut Charles (Pete) Conrad Jr., who was soon to die after a motorcycle accident on July 8, and the flight director Gerald Griffin -- worried that the United States had lost the old can-do spirit and the will to carry out ambitious, expensive space endeavors.</p>
        <p>Such were the bittersweet thoughts among some of those of the Apollo generation as they began celebrating the time when human beings first (and last) set foot on another world. On Friday, the anniversary of the day they rocketed off to the Moon, the first moonwalkers, Neil A. Armstrong, now 68, and Buzz Aldrin, 69, visited the Kennedy Space Center in Florida for a reunion with many who worked on their mission. Michael Collins, 69, who piloted the Apollo command module in lunar orbit while the other two astronauts landed on the Moon, was invited but did not attend.</p>
        <p>Yes, they had some post-Apollo regrets. ''I guess all of us would like to see more things going on in terms of space exploration,'' Mr. Armstrong told reporters.</p>
        <p>He grinned. ''The regret on our side is, they used to say years ago, we are reading about you in science class,'' Mr. Armstrong said. ''Now they say, we are reading about you in history class.''</p>
        <p>NASA officials, scientists and others involved in current space projects have mixed feelings about such celebrations that dwell on the past.</p>
        <p>''If we spend so much time celebrating history, trying to replicate history, we may never get a chance to make new history,'' Daniel S. Goldin, the head of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, said last week.</p>
        <p>The concern is that Apollo, though worthy of tribute, should not be held up as a model for planning space exploration for the long haul. The project was not really about science or space exploration, but the cold war confrontation between the United States and the Soviet Union. It was a crash program and too expensive to be sustained once the immediate goal was achieved.</p>
        <p>''The Apollo program is not replicable,'' Dr. John M. Logsdon, director of the Space Policy Institute at George Washington University, wrote in the current issue of Space News. ''It was a product of a specific time in history, as the Soviet Union and the United States were using space firsts as a surrogate battlefield for their global geopolitical competition. It was definitely not part of a societal commitment to space exploration and development.''</p>
        <p>As Dr. Logsdon recalled, in April 1961 President John F. Kennedy asked his advisers to identify a ''space program which promises dramatic results in which we could win.'' The answer was a race to send men to the Moon before the 1960's ended.</p>
        <p>''It is hard to conceive a similar question, 30 years later, for which the answer is to send people to Mars -- or any other Apollo-like space undertaking,'' Dr. Logsdon concluded.</p>
        <p>Many other things have changed since the time of Apollo 11. Americans seem to have lost their taste for grand adventures if they require long-term commitments of money and expanded Government power.</p>
        <p>With the end of the cold war, the Russians have gone from being adversaries, whose early space triumphs provoked the Moon race, to allies. They are partners in a $100 billion project to assemble and operate an Earth-orbiting space station, though the financially strapped Russians often have troubles paying bills and meeting schedules. Other partners are the Europeans, Japan and Canada. Major programs of human space flight are becoming unaffordable, except through multinational collaborations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldin conceded that Russian participation has added what he called a ''Perils of Pauline'' element to the space station project, now scheduled to be completely assembled in orbit in 2004. The NASA Administrator said he would meet with Russian space officials this week to assess the implications of a recent Proton rocket failure on Russia's ability to launch the Russian service module for the space station on Nov. 12. Under current plans, no further American space shuttle missions can be launched to the station until the service module is in place. Even when the much-delayed station is operating with international crews, human flight will still be confined to circling Earth. No one has flown to the Moon since December 1972, or is likely to for years to come. On the 20th anniversary of Apollo 11, in 1989, President George Bush called for a national commitment to return astronauts to the Moon and send them to Mars by 2019, the 50th anniversary. His Space Exploration Initiative came to nothing fast.</p>
        <p>Since then, the Clinton Administration issued a space policy declaration giving highest priority to the space station and restricting NASA from beginning preliminary work on human flights to the Moon or Mars until after the station is in full operation.</p>
        <p>Dr. Alex Roland, a historian of technology at Duke University, said that human space flight was still in its ''barnstorming period,'' comparable to aviation before the 1930's. The development of larger, sturdier airframes ushered in commercial passenger flight. And military strategists began to conceive of the airplane as an effective weapon of war. Human space flight, he said, has yet to find an indispensable place for itself.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Roland suggested three changes that could bring that about, none of which is likely to occur in the immediate future. One would be a large-scale commercial exploitation of space, like huge solar-power arrays, that required people to maintain it, something like workers on offshore oil rigs. Fossil fuels would have to be running low before that becomes likely, he said. Other possibilities would be finding some military use, far-fetched at the moment, or developing much less expensive launching systems, which could open up opportunities for commercial, scientific or even tourist flights.</p>
        <p>Most of the brightest stars in the post-Apollo space program have been robotic spacecraft. They have scouted out all the planets except Pluto, rendezvoused with comets and asteroids and probed the far horizons of the cosmos. They have landed and looked for life on Mars, and will again over the next decade. One is orbiting Jupiter and its large moons right now, and another is on its way to orbit distant Saturn.</p>
        <p>The Moon has been revisited twice in this decade by modest spacecraft, which may have found evidence of water ice at the lunar poles. At the end of this month, after 18 months of circling the moon, Lunar Prospector is to be crashed into the lunar surface to look for more definitive evidence. Early Tuesday morning, the anniversary of the Apollo 11 Moon walk, a space shuttle is scheduled to lift off on a mission to deliver the Chandra X-ray Observatory to orbit, opening one more window on the universe that had been closed before telescopes could be placed above Earth's atmosphere. One more important difference from the Apollo days: the shuttle Columbia will be commanded by Col. Eileen Collins of the Air Force, the first woman to lead a shuttle mission.</p>
        <p>As the celebrations began, Neil Armstrong was asked what he thought the lasting legacy of Apollo would be. It was, he said, ''a demonstration that man was not chained to this planet.''</p>
        <p>At the time of Apollo, the historian Arthur Schlesinger Jr. predicted that in 500 years, the 20th century would probably be remembered in history mainly for its pioneering space flights, humanity's first venture beyond its native planet. He repeated this assessment recently at a retrospective symposium on the vibrant, tempestuous 1960's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
