<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food; Rules of The Game</title>
    <meta content="30FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="78" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1195793"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rules (London Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reynolds, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E2DD1530F933A05757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food; Rules of The Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jonathan Reynolds</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reynolds, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Reynolds Food article on British foods, as served at Rules, 202-year-old London institution; photos; recipes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first question one must always ask about British food is, What is it? Roast beef? The famously inedible Bovril and Marmite? Oh, I know: that comfort food with preschool names like bubble and squeak, toad-in-the-hole and spotted dick. Well, every country has roast beef, and the other caricatures sound like cheap Jay Leno rim shots.</p>
        <p>But certainly British food has the worst P. R. of any cuisine in the world -- its most rigid detractors (not just the French) claim it's causing the hole in the ozone layer. Although friends of mine say foreign food in Britain -- French, Italian and Indian, in particular -- is often better than in its native land, the popular belief is that the Brits still haven't figured out how to cook their own very well. And it's not embraced by many outside the U.K.: there are probably more Chinese, Thai and Zimbabwean restaurants on any one block of New York than there are British restaurants in the entire city. But developers take note: the one British restaurant I'm aware of, Tea and Sympathy on Greenwich Avenue, frequently has lengthy lines outside.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first question one must always ask about British food is, What is it? Roast beef? The famously inedible Bovril and Marmite? Oh, I know: that comfort food with preschool names like bubble and squeak, toad-in-the-hole and spotted dick. Well, every country has roast beef, and the other caricatures sound like cheap Jay Leno rim shots.</p>
        <p>But certainly British food has the worst P. R. of any cuisine in the world -- its most rigid detractors (not just the French) claim it's causing the hole in the ozone layer. Although friends of mine say foreign food in Britain -- French, Italian and Indian, in particular -- is often better than in its native land, the popular belief is that the Brits still haven't figured out how to cook their own very well. And it's not embraced by many outside the U.K.: there are probably more Chinese, Thai and Zimbabwean restaurants on any one block of New York than there are British restaurants in the entire city. But developers take note: the one British restaurant I'm aware of, Tea and Sympathy on Greenwich Avenue, frequently has lengthy lines outside.</p>
        <p>My first experience with British eats occurred when I was a fairly wretched (and mercifully quite unsuccessful) drama student in the London of the mid-1960's, when, thanks to the Beatles, runaway film production and Mary Quant, England was more or less considered the center of the universe. I shivered through the fall in a studio flat near (then) very down-market Notting Hill Gate and had to put pennies into a hallway meter several times in the course of a bath to keep the hot water four inches high in the tub. (Don't conjure the image.) I remember that our favorite riff at school was imitating Peter O'Toole's T. E. Lawrence after he'd trekked across the desert for days with an Arab lad and demanded of an astonished officers-only club, ''We want . . . two . . . glahsses . . . of . . . le . . . mon . . . ade,'' and threatening to implode (as usual).</p>
        <p>On a student's budget, meals consisted of sausages filled with highly questionable grains, soggy-crusted pub grub served at room temperature, runny custards poured over all sweet ''puddings'' and something called a Wimpy, which was, if you can believe it, a really bad rival of a McDonald's burger. After three months of this, for a reason I now forget, I ventured solo into Simpson's in the Strand, a clubby British beef parlor with paneled walls, waiters in tails and a serious air of condescension. I'm fairly sure I had the thinly sliced, red-juiced beef from the silver-domed carving trolley, brussels sprouts in cream and something at the finish that was sticky with either golden syrup or treacle. Not bad, but not exactly haute.</p>
        <p>What I remember most was watching a jolly fellow with a thickly veined nose and cheeks, ruddied from years of alcohol, dig two silver spoons into a ceramic tub of Stilton, which he then chased with a glass of port. He seemed sent for my delight from the casting department over at Ealing Studios, a Falstaffian Churchillian deliriously happy in his own mostly unintelligible fog. After he left even jollier than when he arrived, I ordered the tub of cheese and a chaser of port -- and found my own version of O'Toole's lemonade in the culinary desert: Stilton and port remains one of the great marriages in all gastronomy. For years I thought that was about all there was to recommend English food.</p>
        <p>So when I recently visited London, it was serendipitous to rediscover Rules, the 202-year-old institution in Covent Garden that, because of a recent change in chefs, has far exceeded the Stilton-and-port boundary. (Though it has excellent versions of that as well.) Here it becomes clear what British food is when it is done well: bold flavors of meat, game and wild salmon; the richness of butter, cream and poultry fat; fresh, crunchy (when called for) vegetables; and puddings that surprise and delight. I realized the problem with British food is that, like Hemingway and Beckett, it's so easy to imitate badly. Just try the steak-and-kidney pie at Tea and Sympathy. Or read a little Mamet.</p>
        <p>''Our country lost its way after World War II with rationing and scarce money,'' says the restaurant's chef of three years, David Chambers, who has already won Rules the title of Best Game Restaurant in Great Britain. ''If you wanted to be a chef, you had to be French or Swiss,'' he says. ''We've finally caught up and recreated what we had 50 to 60 years ago. People are fed up with marble and glitz and all this East-West Mediterranean fusion stuff.''</p>
        <p>Well, you won't find any marble, glitz or sun-dried tomatoes here, no layered food or surrealist plate presentations. In fact, I'm not sure Tony Blair approves of the place at all, since the current prime minister is obsessed with making Britain seem new, and Rules is decidedly old. It was a favorite stamping ground of Dickens, Edward VII and Graham Greene (much of whose ''End of the Affair'' takes place here); one of Rules's private rooms was the setting for a celebrated dinner for Margaret Thatcher and her cabinet -- at which she, upon being asked by a waiter, ''And Madame Prime Minister, what about the veg?'' reportedly said, ''They'll have what I'm having.''</p>
        <p>In a country that actually applauds eccentricity rather than simply paying it lip service (John Rocker, call British Airways), Rules is probably the most eccentric -- and therefore most British -- restaurant in London. At first glance, its interior appears sedately Victorian; on closer examination it's downright bizarre -- as though the owners of ''21'' and Palm told Warner LeRoy to go for it. There, on a wall of one of its chandeliered rooms, cheek by jowl with a huge gilt-framed oil painting of Hamlet holding Yorick's skull, hang black-and-white cartoons and Vanity Fair watercolor portraits of the once famous, a couple of mounted ibex heads and a pair of crossed swords; over there, a quartet of women's busts in marble and some awards the restaurant has won; above is a stained-glass faux skylight so modern it could have been assembled by Picasso; and right there, painted on a curved section of wall, is a full-color mural of Lady Thatcher -- Lady Thatcher's hair, mostly -- revealing garters on one thigh and all armored up as Saint George, with the Falklands in the background. In her hand she proudly brandishes a staff whose pennant is emblazoned ''Rules.'' In cleverer hands this all would either be kitschy or claustrophobic; here, it has a sort of anarchistic honesty earned over the centuries. It looks like a place where you could have a good time. And you can!</p>
        <p>If, as Russell Baker once suggested, the white race is not really white but pink, surely the Brits are the pinkest of all, and the clientele at Rules the pinkest of the pink. This has nothing to do with class or race but, rather, with Britishness. Although there are tourists aplenty in the restaurant, right next to them blue-suited businessmen in striped, high-collared shirts puff cigars; next to them, burly natives in T-shirts and sweats happily dig into a plate of raw Irish oysters; and over yonder a group of Sloane Rangers enjoys a sherry lunch. They allow smoking here, but for some reason it's not noticeable. And the service is distinctly unintrusive: no interrupted conversations announcing the specials, for instance. In fact, the service is excellent: a puree of root vegetables was returned because it was cold, and not only did the waiter apologize profusely, whisking the offending plate away, but the matre d'htel arrived in a dither and asked -- asked -- Would you allow us to remove the cost of that course from your bill to make up for our error? Would that satisfy you?'' Would I allow it?</p>
        <p>And the food? Rules claims it specializes in game -- it even has its own game estate nearby in Teesdale where it kills and hangs (for seven days) most of it. Chef Chambers recently took eight members of his kitchen staff to a shoot because ''there's a synergy between cooking and shooting. Shooting teaches them respect for the food they're killing.'' He then made them blind-taste squirrel and rabbit to see if they could tell the difference -- sort of like a wine tasting, only in this case an attempt to distinguish between varmints.</p>
        <p>If you like game, you'll like it here; it's done extremely well, and the variety is staggering. Aside from the more common (and milder) pheasant, venison and grouse, at various times of year you can also get what might be called Extreme Game -- animals I was sure existed only in ''Alice in Wonderland'': blackgame, pouchard, snipe, teal, ptarmigan and wigeon. But be warned -- Extreme Game is an acquired taste, often very livery. (The menu brags that snipe has a ''woody flavor similar to sweetly rotting mushrooms.'') If you're not used to it, it can be a shock. (And if you're squeamish, best not ask exactly what jugged hare is. For the stouthearted, there's a definition below.) The smell of wigeon we had on one visit practically blew us out the window.</p>
        <p>But what I find most enjoyable about Rules is its singularly British fare -- the most sensual terrine of foie gras laced with slivettes of wild duck, amazingly creamy and light at the same time; the lush and salty Stilton-and-broccoli soup with roasted almonds (or the Stilton-and-walnut tart with a spiky pear chutney); the many fresh vegetables; or the steak-and-kidney pudding made with a suet crust and served with an oyster on top. (If you don't like the bitter taste of kidney, don't eat it; it's delicious without, though better with.) The desserts, particularly the sticky toffee pudding and the Sauternes cr me caramel with Armagnac prunes, will transport you back to the nursery -- though the addition of what tastes like strawberry jam to the bottom of a burnt English custard (cr me brlee) is an improvement only a colonizer could love. And I would give you the recipe for the grilled 10-ounce sirloin steak, but you can't get meat that good here without importing an Aberdeen Angus steer. (After that, the recipe's pretty simple.) If all this sounds heavy (and much of it is), be reminded that in addition to the delicate grilled Dover sole and the poached finnan haddock, game is practically fat free.</p>
        <p>To my mind, a perfect evening in London is spent eating the following menu at Rules, then walking a few blocks east, past Simpson's in the Strand, crossing the night-black Thames on Waterloo Bridge -- St. Paul's glowing on your left, Parliament alight on your right -- and catching a play at the National; and then crossing Waterloo Bridge back -- St. Paul's on your right, Parliament on your left -- and if you've got room, stopping back at Rules (or Simpson's) for a little Stilton, port and highly civilized condescension.</p>
        <p>Oh, and as promised, here is the definition of jugged hare (though in deference to the faint of heart, it can be read only in a mirror): Jugged hare is a rabbit whose throat has been slit and is then cooked in its own blood.</p>
        <p>Stilton-and-Broccoli Soup</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>2 1/2 cups leeks, tough outer green leaves removed and thinly sliced</p>
        <p>1 cup onions, chopped</p>
        <p>1/2 cup celery, finely chopped</p>
        <p>2 3/4 pounds broccoli, stalks peeled and diced, florets separated</p>
        <p>7 cups chicken stock</p>
        <p>1 cup heavy cream</p>
        <p>3/4 pound Stilton, coarsely grated</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste</p>
        <p>1 cup almonds, thinly sliced.</p>
        <p>1. Heat the oil over medium-low heat in a heavy-bottomed pot. Sweat but don't brown the leeks, onions and celery, about 20 minutes. Add the broccoli and sweat for 10 minutes more. Add stock.</p>
        <p>2. Bring to a rolling boil over medium-high heat, then lower the heat and simmer till the vegetables are tender, about 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. In a food processor, puree the vegetables in their broth and return them to the pot.</p>
        <p>4. Ten minutes before serving, stir in cream, then the grated Stilton. Once the cheese has melted, taste. Add pepper and, if necessary, salt.</p>
        <p>5. Serve immediately. Pass the almonds in a separate bowl, and garnish the soup generously.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Steak-and-Kidney Pudding</p>
        <p>2 1/2 pounds beef chuck, cut into 1-inch cubes</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons salt</p>
        <p>3/4 teaspoon freshly ground black pepper</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons lard (much preferred) or (ho-hum) mildly flavored olive oil</p>
        <p>1/3 cup onions, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1/3 cup carrots, finely chopped</p>
        <p>3/4 pound veal kidney, cut into 1-inch pieces</p>
        <p>2/3 cup all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>8 cups beef stock</p>
        <p>3 cups mushrooms, quartered</p>
        <p>5 tablespoons Worcestershire sauce</p>
        <p>Suet pastry (see recipe)</p>
        <p>6 oysters (or as many as you want), shucked.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 375 degrees. Sprinkle beef with salt and pepper; then in a large deep ovenproof saute pan over high heat, heat lard or oil until hot. Saute beef cubes until browned; add onions and carrots and saute 10 minutes more. Add kidney and continue sauteing another 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Stir in flour and bake for 10 minutes, uncovered. Remove from oven and place over medium-low heat. Scraping up whatever sticks to the bottom, add stock, mushrooms and Worcestershire. Simmer and stir occasionally for 45 minutes. Season to taste, cool, transfer to a container and refrigerate overnight.</p>
        <p>3. Cut off 1/5 of each suet pastry disk and roll the remaining pastry into circles about 10 1/2 inches in diameter and 1/16 inch thick.</p>
        <p>4. Line 6 18- to 20-ounce pudding basins or 5-inch ramekins with the pastry, pressing dough evenly around the sides. Fill with steak and kidney mixture. Roll out the reserved pastry and cover each pudding, crimping the edges closed.</p>
        <p>5. Here's the weird part: wrap each basin entirely in plastic wrap. (This makes it a steamed pudding rather than a browned pie.) Tie string around the outside (to keep plastic wrap snug) and put puddings on racks in pans of simmering water, covered, for 2 hours, making sure the water stays 2/3 the way up the sides of the basins.</p>
        <p>6. Remove the puddings from the water and remove the plastic wrap. Just before serving, cut a small hole in top of each and insert as many oysters as you like. (At Rules they put one oyster inside the pudding and another on the side in its shell.)</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 puddings.</p>
        <p>Note: The puddings can be kept for 3 days, cooked or uncooked, in the refrigerator. Reheat in a 375-degree oven, about 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>Savory Suet Pastry</p>
        <p>3 cups all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons chives, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 cup (8 ounces) beef suet, coarsely chopped (much preferred), or (ho-hum) unsalted margarine (2 sticks), placed in the freezer overnight, and cut into small chunks</p>
        <p>About 2/3 cup hot water ( 1/2 cup cold water if using margarine).</p>
        <p>1. In a food processor, pulse flour, chives and suet (or margarine) until fat is incorporated, about 9 times. Continue pulsing and add water slowly, till dough forms clumps and pulls away from side of bowl.</p>
        <p>2. Knead the dough on a floured board till soft. Make a thick disk about 6 inches in diameter.</p>
        <p>3. Cut the disk into 6 equal portions, form smaller disks, wrap in plastic and chill for at least 2 hours before using.</p>
        <p>Yield: Pastry for 6 puddings, 18 to 20 ounces each.</p>
        <p>Sticky Toffee Pudding</p>
        <p>4 tablespoons unsalted butter</p>
        <p>2/3 cup firmly packed brown sugar</p>
        <p>2 large eggs</p>
        <p>1 cup self-rising flour</p>
        <p>1 1/3 cups pitted dates, coarsely chopped</p>
        <p>1 cup water</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons golden syrup (see note)</p>
        <p>Butterscotch sauce (see recipe).</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 300 degrees. In a mixing bowl, cream the butter with the brown sugar, then mix in the eggs and fold in the flour.</p>
        <p>2. Puree the dates with 1 cup warm water and mix into batter.</p>
        <p>3. Film 6 7-ounce custard cups with golden syrup, then fill with batter and bake for 40 to 45 minutes or until a knife inserted at the edge comes out clean.</p>
        <p>4. Run a knife around the sides of puddings and invert onto serving plates. Pour warm butterscotch sauce over each and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 puddings.</p>
        <p>Note: Lyle's golden syrup is available at most supermarkets.</p>
        <p>Butterscotch Sauce</p>
        <p>1 cup heavy cream</p>
        <p>1/2 cup brown sugar</p>
        <p>1/2 cup white sugar.</p>
        <p>In a small heavy-bottomed saucepan mix all the ingredients and bring to a boil over medium heat. Cook, stirring almost constantly, until reduced and thickened, about 20 minutes. This is delicious not only on this pudding but also on just about everything except steak.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Reynolds is a playwright and screenwriter.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Reynolds is a playwright and screenwriter.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
