<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28FSUM$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E4D7173DF93BA15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1298" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Chretien's Liberals Retain Hold on Canada Parliament  Jean Chretien won a bold gamble, becoming the first Canadian Prime Minister to win a third consecutive majority government since World War II. Defying forecasters, Mr. Chretien's Liberals swept Ontario and picked up several seats in Quebec, reducing the parliamentary delegation of the separatist Bloc Quebecois.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-14</p>
        <p>Chretien's Liberals Retain Hold on Canada Parliament  Jean Chretien won a bold gamble, becoming the first Canadian Prime Minister to win a third consecutive majority government since World War II. Defying forecasters, Mr. Chretien's Liberals swept Ontario and picked up several seats in Quebec, reducing the parliamentary delegation of the separatist Bloc Quebecois.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Gaza Boy's Death Re-examined  The Israeli Army said Palestinian bullets, rather than Israeli gunfire, might have killed the 12-year-old Palestinian boy whose death on Sept. 30 was videotaped and widely televised. Palestinians, including the cameraman, assailed the report.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Call for Middle East Monitors  Mary Robinson, the top United Nations human rights official, said international monitors should be considered for the West Bank and Gaza, where she called the conditions of Palestinian civilian life ''bleak.''</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>No Victory Claim in Haiti Yet  Former President Jean-Bertrand Aristide acted very much the chief of state as he emphasized the need to unite Haitians to work for his program of national peace and development, but he did not declare himself the winner of the election on Sunday, pending official results.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Mexican Cabinet Complete  President-elect Vicente Fox Quesada chose his security and justice ministers, completing his cabinet four days before his inauguration.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Spy Trial in Moscow  A lawyer for Edward Pope, an American businessman charged with espionage, said the judge had allowed an important piece of evidence that could help exonerate him.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Sri Lanka Rebel Talks of Peace  Velupillai Prabhakaran, leader of the separatist Tamil Tiger rebels and known as a ruthless guerrilla strategist, said his group was ready for unconditional talks with the government on ending the 17-year conflict.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Yugoslav Criticizes U.N.  President Vojislav Kostunica said the United Nations and Western powers had ''failed to do their part of the job'' and stop Albanian attacks on Serbian police and citizens. But Mr. Kostunica and his government lifted threats that Serbian forces might move into a three-mile security zone to deal with armed Albanians.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Ex-Leader Adjusts to New Life  Former President Alberto K. Fujimori of Peru seems weary but defiant as he adjusts to a new life as a private citizen in Japan, after a decade in which he governed Peru as an authoritarian ruler. In an interview, he expressed no regrets about his most fateful decisions in a life of politics that apparently ended last week when he resigned from office.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A16-26</p>
        <p>Gore Asks for Patience As Bush Pushes Ahead  Vice President Al Gore, in a brief televised prime-time address, urged patience while he contests Florida's decision to award its decisive 25 electoral votes to Gov. George W. Bush. Mr. Gore asserted that he was not engaged in a struggle for power but in an effort to preserve the ''integrity of democracy.'' Mr. Bush pressed forward with transition planning, meeting in Austin with his designated White House chief of staff, former Transportation Secretary Andrew Card. Mr. Bush, despite his claim to victory, told aides to continue calling him governor, rather than president-elect. Dick Cheney, his vice presidential nominee and transition director, said he was opening a full-scale transition operation in rented space in Washington, using donations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>In Tallahassee, lawyers for Mr. Gore asked a state judge to declare him the winner and award him the state's 25 electoral votes.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>The Florida Senate's president, a Republican, said Gov. Jeb Bush had indicated he was willing to sign special legislation intended to award Florida's electoral votes to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>A25</p>
        <p>The Clinton administration said it would not release $5.3 million in transition funds or turn over an office ''until a final winner'' emerged.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>The Democrats' two Congressional leaders, Representative Richard A. Gephardt and Senator Tom Daschle, went to Florida to participate in a televised conference call with Mr. Gore and Senator Joseph I. Lieberman to demonstrate Congressional support for Mr. Gore's efforts.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Texas Death Case Review  The Supreme Court agreed to review the case of a Texas death row inmate, Johnny Paul Penry, whom state authorities have classified as mentally retarded. Mr. Penry, 44, was convicted in 1979 of the rape and murder of a 22-year-old woman.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>The court met for the fourth time since 1993 to consider whether a skinny Congressional district in North Carolina is the product of an unconstitutional racial gerrymander.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>The justices agreed to decide whether ''medical necessity'' can justify distributing marijuana, in violation of federal law, to people who use it to relieve pain or medical symptoms that cannot be effectively treated by conventional means.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>State Data Shows Extent Of Profiling in New Jersey  At least 8 of every 10 state trooper searches of automobiles on the New Jersey Turnpike in the last decade involved minority drivers, according to state documents. The state attorney general said the figures showed that a systematic process of racial profiling had become a routine part of state police operations.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Judge Faults Officer's Firing  A federal judge ruled that the New York Police Department had violated the First Amendment rights of Officer Yvette Walton, who was dismissed after she criticized the tactics of the Street Crime Unit.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>An F.D.R. Home for Sale  An 18-room mansion in Hyde Park, N.Y., that once belonged to Franklin Delano Roosevelt is priced at $599,500, and the National Park Service and some preservationist groups are none too pleased.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>City Backing Museum Project  Officials said City Hall would provide land and a subsidy for the Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum's $678 million plan to build a 40-story curvilinear outpost on the East River.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-12</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F7</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Dismissal Is Rescinded  The New York State education commissioner overturned the dismissal of Robert E. Riccobono, one of the five superintendents removed for poor performance by former city Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew. Mr. Riccobono was ordered reinstated as a Board of Education employee.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>Louis S. Goodman  The pharmacologist, a discoverer of an effective anticancer chemotherapy and a creator of a textbook used by generations of doctors, was 94.</p>
        <p>A27</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-22</p>
        <p>Microsoft Antitrust Appeal  Microsoft told a federal appeals court that Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson had committed a host of procedural and substantive errors and that his antitrust finding and remedies should be overruled.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>G.E. Designates Welch Heir  G.E. said Jeffrey R. Immelt, the 44-year-old head of GE Medical Systems, would succeed John F. Welch Jr. as chairman and chief executive at the end of next year.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Raider Sues Over Rival Merger  Kirk Kerkorian, who tried to buy Chrysler in 1995, sued DaimlerChrysler and three officials, saying they gained control of the automaker under false pretenses in 1998.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>New Seed Standards Sought  The American Seed Trade Association said a small amount of genetically engineered material should be allowed in seeds considered free of modification because it is becoming impossible to ensure that a bag of seeds will not have some mixed in.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>FASHION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A28-29</p>
        <p>Editorials: A plea for patience; falling short on global warming; Haiti's disappearing democracy.  Columns: Thomas L. Friedman.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E7  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
