<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Gets Environmental Boost in New York</title>
    <meta content="Y25GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1179151"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endorsements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">League of Conservation Voters</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DA1E30F936A15751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Gets Environmental Boost in New York</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>DOBBS FERRY, N.Y., Feb. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore is endorsed by New York League of Conservation Voters, racking up one more special-interest group in his seemngly lopsided race against Bill Bradley (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Against the backdrop of a placid Hudson River on an unusually balmy winter afternoon, Vice President Al Gore today received the endorsement of the New York League of Conservation Voters, racking up one more special-interest group in his seemingly lopsided race against former Senator Bill Bradley.</p>
        <p>''Bradley has a good record, but Gore's is better,'' Paul J. Elston, chairman of the league's board, told about 100 people assembled here, citing Mr. Gore's work on fighting global warming, air pollution, toxic waste and oil drilling in the Arctic National Refuge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Against the backdrop of a placid Hudson River on an unusually balmy winter afternoon, Vice President Al Gore today received the endorsement of the New York League of Conservation Voters, racking up one more special-interest group in his seemingly lopsided race against former Senator Bill Bradley.</p>
        <p>''Bradley has a good record, but Gore's is better,'' Paul J. Elston, chairman of the league's board, told about 100 people assembled here, citing Mr. Gore's work on fighting global warming, air pollution, toxic waste and oil drilling in the Arctic National Refuge.</p>
        <p>''No other candidate in this race can hold a candle to Al Gore on this issue,'' Mr. Elston said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore has locked up the endorsements of several groups that represent core Democratic values and that might otherwise have remained neutral or even supported Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>The former New Jersey senator's record on the environment, as well as on organized labor, teachers, abortion rights and gay rights, is equal to if not better than Mr. Gore's, according to ratings by those interests. And yet major groups representing those interests have signed on with Mr. Gore. For example, the national League of Conservation Voters, based in Washington, gave Mr. Bradley an 84 percent approval rating for his environmental record in the Senate; Mr. Gore got 64 percent .</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore needed today's endorsement because many environmentalists have been deeply divided between the two candidates; one group, Friends of the Earth, has already endorsed Mr. Bradley.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Kennedy Jr., a New York environmental lawyer and member of the league's board, along with another board member, Lawrence Rockefeller, had already endorsed Mr. Gore and were instrumental in urging the state league to endorse him.</p>
        <p>''We all like Bill Bradley,'' Mr. Elston said in an interview. ''He's a good environmentalist, but he has not treated the environment as a central piece of his political persona, and Al Gore has.''</p>
        <p>Not all environmental groups have rushed to Mr. Gore's side. The state league's national organization, the League of Conservation Voters, for example, is remaining neutral, as is the Sierra Club. And several people active in the movement, like John Cronin in the Hudson River Valley, are withholding their support.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cronin said Mr. Gore did not deserve his support because the Clinton administration had failed on two issues important to him by not forcing General Electric to clean up the PCB's that are contaminating the Hudson and by not restricting power plants that pollute the river.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cronin said he was not backing Mr. Bradley, either. ''Bradley hasn't made a satisfactory case to New York,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was careful today to try not to alienate any possible Bradley voters, and he spoke well of his opponent's environmental record.</p>
        <p>''Bill Bradley does have a good environmental record,'' he said,  ''and I acknowledge that. But I deeply appreciate your willingness to look at not only the two very similar records on votes, but also to go beyond that and look at leadership, because I've worked hard.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
