<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mr. Clinton's Land Legacy</title>
    <meta content="10MON1$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1167605"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDC1E3BF933A25752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="687" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mr. Clinton's Land Legacy</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Having lost to Ronald Reagan in the 1980 elections, Jimmy Carter was more or less on his way out the door when, on Dec. 2 of that year, he signed the Alaska Lands Act, protecting 100 million acres of Alaskan wilderness from commercial development. The act remains one of Mr. Carter's proudest achievements. Like Mr. Carter, President Clinton now finds himself headed for the exit, with one more year as a lame-duck president burdened by a hostile Congress. Yet he may find the legacy he seeks and needs just where Mr. Carter found it -- in the preservation of the American landscape.</p>
        <p>This would be an unexpected outcome for a man who ranked environmental concerns near the bottom of his agenda when he came to office seven years ago. But the truth is that Mr. Clinton has a fighting chance to create more new protected open space than anyone since Mr. Carter and, before that, Theodore Roosevelt. Between 1901 and 1909,  Roosevelt, one of Mr. Clinton's heroes, created 5 national parks, 50 wildlife reserves and 99 million acres of national forests. Bruce Babbitt, the secretary of the interior, believes that the beginning of the 21st century presents a similarly promising moment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Having lost to Ronald Reagan in the 1980 elections, Jimmy Carter was more or less on his way out the door when, on Dec. 2 of that year, he signed the Alaska Lands Act, protecting 100 million acres of Alaskan wilderness from commercial development. The act remains one of Mr. Carter's proudest achievements. Like Mr. Carter, President Clinton now finds himself headed for the exit, with one more year as a lame-duck president burdened by a hostile Congress. Yet he may find the legacy he seeks and needs just where Mr. Carter found it -- in the preservation of the American landscape.</p>
        <p>This would be an unexpected outcome for a man who ranked environmental concerns near the bottom of his agenda when he came to office seven years ago. But the truth is that Mr. Clinton has a fighting chance to create more new protected open space than anyone since Mr. Carter and, before that, Theodore Roosevelt. Between 1901 and 1909,  Roosevelt, one of Mr. Clinton's heroes, created 5 national parks, 50 wildlife reserves and 99 million acres of national forests. Bruce Babbitt, the secretary of the interior, believes that the beginning of the 21st century presents a similarly promising moment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's opportunities lie in three areas. The first is his plan to prohibit the building of new roads in at least 40 million acres of national forests, in effect putting them off limits to logging and other commercial activities. The president can do this administratively and without Congressional approval. But the rule-making process, which includes extensive public hearings, will require nearly a year to complete, giving the plan's Congressional enemies plenty of time for mischief. Mr. Clinton must therefore be ready to fight legislative amendments and other devices aimed at extending the process into the next administration, when a president less hospitable to conservation could occupy the White House.</p>
        <p>The second opportunity lies in the Antiquities Act of 1906, a little-known statute that allows presidents, by executive order, to protect public lands by designating them as national monuments. Mr. Clinton, who has already set aside nearly two million acres in Utah, is now considering four new monument designations, and is expected to act on at least one of these -- a million-acre monument near the Grand Canyon -- tomorrow. Every president except Richard Nixon, Mr. Reagan and George Bush has used this device in the last 94 years, and not once have the designations been revoked by Congress.</p>
        <p>The third opportunity lies, oddly enough, in Congress itself. This Congress has been largely unsympathetic to adding to the federal estate since the conservatives swept to power in 1994. But last year, two House members who rarely agree on anything co-wrote a bill that could dramatically strengthen the protection of America's natural resources. In one of the oddest Congressional couplings in years, George Miller, a liberal conservationist from California, and Don Young, a conservative property rights advocate from Alaska, cobbled together a measure that would provide a guaranteed financing stream of $2.8 billion annually for the federal Land and Water Conservation Fund and other undernourished conservation programs. The bill has flaws, and Senate support is far from certain. But it is something on which the administration, which also wants a permanent financing stream for conservation, can build.</p>
        <p>The administration has other environmental obligations this year besides land acquisition. The Environmental Protection Agency, for example, needs to strengthen its regulations governing water pollution originating on factory farms. It would be heartening -- astounding, actually -- if Mr. Clinton and Vice President Al Gore could persuade Congress to pass one meaningful piece of legislation on global warming. But a land legacy is clearly Mr. Clinton's best shot at environmental posterity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
