<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russian and U.S. Crew Ready To Blast Off to Space Station</title>
    <meta content="Y30SPA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/30/science/30SPAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1243204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soyuz Project</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leary, Warren E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shepherd, William M (Capt)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gidzenko, Yuri P (Lt Col)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krikalev, Sergei K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Space Cooperation and Ventures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DE1430F933A05753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russian and U.S. Crew Ready To Blast Off to Space Station</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leary, Warren E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian and American astronauts prepare to blast off from Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakhstan to dock with new orbiting International Space Station on four-month shakedown mission to make it habitable; US astronaut Capt William M Shepherd will enter craft as first commander; Russian cosmonaut Yuri P Gidzenko will command Soyuz spacecraft on two-day trip to station; will control rendezvous and docking; Sergei K Krikalev will serve as flight engineer; $60 billion space station being constructed by 16 nations led by US and Russia is currently 143-foot-long structure of linked modules weighing 162,000 pounds; will be expanded to mass of 1 million pounds over next five years, covering area larger than football field and will include at least four major scientific modules (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A patient crew of astronauts is ready to blast off to the International Space Station to begin what could be more than 15 years when humans will continually occupy the orbiting outpost.</p>
        <p>The three-man crew of astronauts from Russia and the United States is scheduled to lift off aboard a Russian Soyuz rocket from the Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakhstan at 2:53 a.m., Eastern time, on Tuesday. If all goes well, this Expedition One crew will dock with the new space station early Thursday to begin a four-month shakedown mission to make the spacecraft habitable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A patient crew of astronauts is ready to blast off to the International Space Station to begin what could be more than 15 years when humans will continually occupy the orbiting outpost.</p>
        <p>The three-man crew of astronauts from Russia and the United States is scheduled to lift off aboard a Russian Soyuz rocket from the Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakhstan at 2:53 a.m., Eastern time, on Tuesday. If all goes well, this Expedition One crew will dock with the new space station early Thursday to begin a four-month shakedown mission to make the spacecraft habitable.</p>
        <p>One astronaut, Capt. William M. Shepherd, 47, of the United States Navy, is to open the space station's hatches at around 6 a.m. Thursday and enter the craft as its first commander. The other crewmen are Yuri P. Gidzenko, 35, a lieutenant colonel in the Russian Air Force, and Sergei K. Krikalev, 38, a veteran Russian astronaut who has flown on Russian and American spacecraft.</p>
        <p>Colonel Gidzenko is to command the Soyuz craft on its two-day trip to the space station and to control the rendezvous and docking of the two vehicles, while Mr. Krikalev serves as flight engineer. Aboard the station, the three men will begin tasks to turn the pressurized aluminum structure into a home.</p>
        <p>The International Space Station, a $60 billion project being constructed by 16 nations led by the United States and Russia, currently is a 143-foot-long structure of linked modules weighing 162,000 pounds. Over five years, it is to grow to a mass of one million pounds, cover an area larger than a football field and include at least four major scientific modules.</p>
        <p>The crew has trained for this moment for almost five years. The flight was delayed for years because of spacecraft and rocket problems, most notably a more than two-year wait for the Russians, who did not have the money they needed to complete the command and living module, Zvezda, which was finally launched in July. ''I'm really glad that we've gotten to the day where our training is behind us,'' Captain Shepherd said earlier this month at a news conference. ''It's been a very long road.''</p>
        <p>One advantage of working so closely together for so long, the crewmen said, is that they know one another and their jobs so well that they can react to situations without communicating. Even though Captain Shepherd speaks fluent Russian and his partners are well-versed in English, the men said they communicate in a combination of the languages.</p>
        <p>''We say jokingly that we communicate in 'Runglish,' '' Mr. Krikalev said, ''so that when we are short of words in one language we can use the other.''</p>
        <p>The first resident crew of the station is not only highly trained, it also has a great deal of experience in space. Captain Shepherd, who was deputy manager for the space station program from 1993 to 1996, has spent 440 hours in space on three shuttle flights. Colonel Gidzenko spent 180 days in space as commander of a mission to the Russian Mir space station. Mr. Krikalev has spent 15 months in space on two extended missions to Mir and two space shuttle flights and is a veteran of seven spacewalks.</p>
        <p>Jeff Hanley, the lead flight director for the mission at the Johnson Space Center, said the main job of the Expedition One crew was to establish precedents for living on the station and dealing with two control centers, one in Houston and the other outside Moscow.</p>
        <p>Crew workdays are set up generally to begin around 1 a.m., Eastern time, when a buzzer will awaken the astronauts, he said. After two hours for personal activities, eating breakfast and reading e-mails and other communication from Earth, the crew will begin daily tasks and prescribed exercise routines to counteract the effects of weightlessness.</p>
        <p>After a midday lunch break, they  work until midafternoon, when they have a daily planning meeting with ground controllers about the next day's activities. After dinner and some free time, they will go to sleep at around 4:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>On its first day aboard the station, the crew is to set up food heaters, activate a water processor, turn on the special suction toilet, charge power tools and test communications links. Later, they will install computers and set up networks, start the oxygen generator and carbon dioxide removal system and turn on equipment throughout the station.</p>
        <p>This crew will perform only limited scientific research, since most of its time will be spent in setting up the station and stowing gear and supplies left on previous visits by Russian Progress cargo craft and American space shuttles. During its tour, the crew will also play host to three shuttle missions bringing up new station components and at least one unmanned Progress flight.</p>
        <p>Currently, the station consists of the Russian-made Zarya cargo module, the first section of the space station, which was launched in November 1998; the United States' Unity connecting node, attached the following month; the Zvezda control and living unit, attached in July; and a truss structure, gyroscope assembly and docking port, added this month by the shuttle Discovery.</p>
        <p>The space station is to grow substantially during the first crew's stay, and part of its job will be helping with the construction. In December, the shuttle Endeavour will deliver a giant United States solar power array and in January, the Atlantis will bring up the main American scientific module, Destiny. At the end of February, Discovery is to return with racks of scientific equipment for the American laboratory and the Expedition Two replacement crew, which will be commanded by a Russian.</p>
        <p>The Expedition One crew will return to Earth aboard Discovery, leaving behind the Soyuz craft that brought it to the station as a ''lifeboat'' for future crews in case an emergency forces an evacuation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
