<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Quick, Call the Astrophysicist: The Heavens Need Updating!</title>
    <meta content="19GLAN$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Museums" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Planetariums</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hayden Planetarium</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Museum of Natural History (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glanz, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E0DE1731F93AA25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1373" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Quick, Call the Astrophysicist: The Heavens Need Updating!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES GLANZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glanz, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Research-grade astrophysicists are now working at planetariums like the new Hayden Planetarium in New York; shift acknowledges that only scientists in forefront of reserch can keep a planetarium from descending into simple-mindedness or musty irrelevancy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU may be forgiven for mistaking the space show at the rebuilt Hayden Planetarium in New York City for a 10-billion-light-year roller-coaster ride. The curving, plunging trip through a simulated three-dimensional universe has much in common with that most elemental and mindless of entertainments -- and the final drop into the blaze of the Big Bang is a doozy.</p>
        <p>Behind the fun, though, the 20-minute show reflects a sharp departure at planetariums nationally -- a shift from canned and dated presentations to ones with a thorough knowledge of current research.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU may be forgiven for mistaking the space show at the rebuilt Hayden Planetarium in New York City for a 10-billion-light-year roller-coaster ride. The curving, plunging trip through a simulated three-dimensional universe has much in common with that most elemental and mindless of entertainments -- and the final drop into the blaze of the Big Bang is a doozy.</p>
        <p>Behind the fun, though, the 20-minute show reflects a sharp departure at planetariums nationally -- a shift from canned and dated presentations to ones with a thorough knowledge of current research.</p>
        <p>The space show follows the same journey each time, like a movie, and is narrated by Tom Hanks. But it incorporates recent data and calculations on local stars, galactic structure, the Orion nebula in the Milky Way's outer regions, the distribution of galaxies around the Milky Way and the structure of the universe. Pulling those data together for the show would have been unthinkable without the help of the new astrophysics department at the American Museum of Natural History, which includes the glass-enclosed Rose Center for Earth and Space, where the spherical planetarium sits.</p>
        <p>Just as they would at any major university, the department's 10 or so Ph.D. astronomers and astrophysicists spend most of their time researching the real universe using telescopes, satellites, computers or pencil and paper. But while that arrangement is standard in academia, it veers from what happens at most planetariums.</p>
        <p>As programs like the Hayden's incorporate real astronomical data and struggle to keep up with the accelerating pace of scientific discovery, the presence of astrophysicists at these institutions is quickly becoming more common. With a population of exactly zero in American planetariums before 1992, research-grade astrophysicists are being hired not just in New York but also in Chicago, Denver and Salt Lake City, with others on the way.</p>
        <p>The shift acknowledges that only scientists in the forefront of research can keep a planetarium from descending into simple-mindedness or musty irrelevancy.</p>
        <p>''It would be suicide to build a place and not have the capacity to inform its contents -- daily, daily,'' said Neil deGrasse Tyson, the director of the Hayden Planetarium, who is an astronomer in the new department and a visiting professor at Princeton University. (He received his Ph.D. at Columbia.) ''Without that, all you've made is a World's Fair pavilion. And you're flashy when you open and a year later it's dusty and tired.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Michael Shara, a curator of astronomy at the American Museum of Natural History, said that the in-house expertise ''lets us journey off the surface of the Earth,'' combining data from the Hubble Space Telescope and other satellites, ground-based telescopes and current computer simulations to create accurate models of the Milky Way and the universe at large for the romp in the space show.</p>
        <p>Having practicing scientists on the scene also helps ensure that science will be presented as a voyage of discovery rather than a recitation of prepackaged results, said Dr. Laura Danly, a curator of space science at the Denver Museum of Natural History, whose planetarium is undergoing a major renovation.</p>
        <p>''There are a lot of misconceptions, or perhaps oversimplifications, about what science is and what it does,'' said Dr. Danly, who is also an assistant professor of physics and astronomy at the University of Denver. ''Science is a process of discovery that has very specific rules. But it's still a foray into the unknown. It's every bit as adventurous as going into the jungle and looking for the tiger.''</p>
        <p>Unlike planetariums, natural-history museums, with their emphasis on living and once-living things like tigers and dinosaurs, have made a practice of keeping research scientists on staff. Perhaps not coincidentally, these museums have seldom failed to connect with the public.</p>
        <p>''It tends to move exhibitions in a more creative way toward the edge of discovery,'' said Dr. Michael J. Novacek, a curator of paleontology, senior vice president and provost of science at the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>Dr. Novacek, who estimates that the museum as a whole supports about 80 resident researchers in various fields (now including astrophysics), said they also help identify places where museumgoers must be warned that the scientific results are still provisional -- an exhibit on global warming, for example.</p>
        <p>The results, said David Harvey, a vice president for exhibition at the museum, are a ''movable feast of solid information and vision.'' Mr. Harvey hastened to add that scientists do not always carry the day in honing the content of an exhibition. The independent research of the exhibit preparators, as they are called, sometimes helps bring the scientists up to date on the latest results in a specific field, Mr. Harvey said.</p>
        <p>But having the scientists on hand also helps museums, and planetariums, go beyond exhibitions and allow visitors to use real scientific instruments or even do research themselves. At the Adler Planetarium and Astronomy Museum in Chicago, with four staff members who conduct astronomy or astrophysics research and other collaborators from the city's universities, visitors on Friday nights are offered help operating a telescope in New Mexico remotely, using the Internet.</p>
        <p>''The public gets to see what astronomers really do,'' said Dr. Lucy Fortson, a research astronomer at the Adler who also has a research appointment at the University of Chicago.</p>
        <p>In Denver, where the museum employs two astronomers, including Dr. Danly, a program is afoot to teach nonscientists to mine NASA data for results that might actually be publishable, just as the museum coaches amateurs in digging up fossils in the American Southwest.</p>
        <p>The urge to have astronomers around is spreading. The Hansen Planetarium in Salt Lake City will soon hire one, said Dr. Sarah George, who is the director of the planetarium and the Utah Museum of Natural History. ''It's kind of like having a catalyst on your staff to ensure that your content is up to date,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The new movement is a relief to astronomers with public education in their blood, Dr. Fortson said. ''Why should I have to give up my research to do public education and outreach?'' she asked. ''That had been the status up to four or five years ago.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Fortson concedes that there are lingering challenges, among them persuading granting agencies, notably the National Science Foundation, that planetarium staff members can do serious astronomy and that ''I haven't tossed in the towel.''</p>
        <p>DR. DOUGLAS DUNCAN, a research scientist in the department of astronomy and astrophysics at the University of Chicago who inaugurated the new movement when he was hired as astronomy director at the Adler in 1992, said  there are other obstacles to incorporating the hyperactive world of research science into the down-to-earth administration of planetariums. ''The cultures clash enormously,'' he said. ''Within the department I'm considered the mild-mannered, probably-not-cutthroat-enough faculty member. I would get to the planetarium and I was the hard-driving, ruthless professional astronomer.''</p>
        <p>The Adler's astronomy department is now directed by Dr. Evalyn Gates, a cosmologist at the University of Chicago, and has steadily supported the infusion of scientists in planetariums.</p>
        <p>All of those sociological subtleties are likely to be lost on people who are merely absorbing the science, and enjoying the goose bumps, of displays like the Hayden's show.</p>
        <p>Carter Emmart, the planetarium's manager for science visualization and virtual reality, said that a ''tour director'' in the dome will eventually guide the journey with the equivalent of a joystick on a different trajectory each time. And astronomers like Dr. Shara will be able to use the dome in this mode in off hours to better understand the latest computer calculations and images from space.</p>
        <p>''It's beyond the special-effects arena: we are interpreters translating the science,'' Mr. Emmart said. ''This has been a symphony of very talented people all pulling together.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
