<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When It Comes to Finding Energy, Now There Is a Choice</title>
    <meta content="19ENER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1248502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Connecticut Energy Cooperative</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tuhus, Melinda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE1DE143BF93AA25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1274" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When It Comes to Finding Energy, Now There Is a Choice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MELINDA TUHUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tuhus, Melinda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First residents of Connecticut got to choose their energy supplier on Nov 1; under state's 1998 electricity deregulation law, 18 companies have won approval from state's Dept of Public Utility Control to provide electricity; so far, Connecticut Energy Co-operative is only one that has actually submitted customers' names to department to make the switch; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NOV. 1 may not go down in history as a day of seismic import, but it was important for Bob Maddox.</p>
        <p>''That day was historic for Connecticut,'' he said, ''because the first residents in the history of the state got to choose their energy supplier.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NOV. 1 may not go down in history as a day of seismic import, but it was important for Bob Maddox.</p>
        <p>''That day was historic for Connecticut,'' he said, ''because the first residents in the history of the state got to choose their energy supplier.''</p>
        <p>Four hundred state residents chose the Connecticut Energy Cooperative, and Mr. Maddox is the co-op's marketing director.</p>
        <p>Under the state's 1998 electricity deregulation law, 18 companies so far have won approval from the Connecticut Department of Public Utility Control to provide electricity. The co-op is the only one that has actually submitted customers' names to the department to make the switch.</p>
        <p>The law separated the generation and distribution functions of energy supply, requiring that Connecticut Light &amp; Power and United Illuminating Company sell off their generating plants while continuing to run the transmission and distribution lines that deliver energy to the state's 1.3 million residential customers, as well as businesses.</p>
        <p>As distribution companies, they are still wholly regulated by the state utility control department. If consumers don't choose a new supplier, they will by default buy energy through the ''standard offer'' of the companies that United Illuminating and Connecticut Light &amp; Power have contracted with to provide electricity, at 5 cents and 5.5 cents per kilowatt hour, respectively, to the state's residential customers who don't use electric heat. The fuel provided is a mix of nuclear, fossil and large hydro-power.</p>
        <p>The co-op was founded in 1999 by consumer advocates and environmentalists who were concerned that the new law would favor big users of electricity over small consumers.</p>
        <p>''The co-op can help level the playing field, by bringing individuals together to increase their buying power,'' Mr. Maddox said. He is an outgoing state representative who helped defeat a previous deregulation bill and fought for changes to  benefit small users in what became the 1998 law.</p>
        <p>The co-op offers consumers an option called EcoWatt that provides energy from 100 percent renewable sources, including small hydro-power, wind, and methane gas from landfills. The cost is 6.5 cents per kilowatt hour.</p>
        <p>''For the average family it's the equivalent each month of a single fast food meal,'' Mr. Maddox said. EcoWatt is the only energy source in New England certified as coming from totally renewable sources by the Center for Resource Solutions, an independent nonprofit organization based in California.</p>
        <p>So far, the co-op has recruited 1,000 members to its energy program, two-thirds of whom have chosen EcoWatt. About half the members were switched Nov. 1, and Mr. Maddox said he expected the rest to be switched by the end of the month.</p>
        <p>The co-op is trying to appeal to a range of energy consumers, not just environmentalists. It also offers ValueWatt, energy that comes from the same mix as the standard offer and costs 5.25 cents per kilowatt hour, making it slightly cheaper than Connecticut Light &amp; Power's standard offer and slightly more expensive than that of United Illuminating. By pooling consumers' resources, the co-op also offers competitive prices on fuel oil, natural gas, propane, solar energy and telecommunications. It also promotes efficiency and energy conservation through, for example, replacing incandescent light bulbs with compact fluorescents, installing insulation, and changing behavior.</p>
        <p>''By putting frozen food in the refrigerator to defrost it, your refrigerator doesn't have to work so hard,'' said Mr. Maddox. ''Or by using a flashlight from your car when you come home at night, or putting a motion detector on your porch light, you don't have to leave an outside light on for hours while you're away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maddox said the average home in Connecticut uses 600 kilowatt hours per month, but that number could be brought down to 200 without sacrificing comfort. For example, he said, he lives in a 2,200-square-foot, three-bedroom home in Bethlehem and uses 150 kilowatt  hours a month. He uses solar heat, a wood stove, and a back-up oil burner.  ''Some of my friends still believe I sit here with a candle with four sweaters on and freeze to death,'' he said. In fact, he said the temperature in his home is a comfortable 68 degrees in winter.</p>
        <p>The co-op has been recruiting members through television advertising, direct mail, and a partnership program that offers a discount in membership -- from $30 to $20 -- for individuals who join through one of 23 partners. Some of the partners are not surprising: the Connecticut chapter of the Sierra Club, the Connecticut Green Party, and various progressive energy and environmental groups. But other partners include faith-based groups, the Town of Chester, and a community group in inner-city New Haven.</p>
        <p>Joining the energy co-op was a natural for the Town of Chester, which considers itself ''environmentally aware,'' said First Selectman Martin Heft. The town has worked to clean up Chester Creek and to preserve open space. The co-op is a way to further environmental goals and also save money for the town's 2,800 households, he said.</p>
        <p>Bill Battle of New Haven sits on the co-op's board of directors. He also is president of the board and interim director of the Newhallville Restoration Corporation, which provides housing for low-income families. He said he was living in Europe during the Chernobyl nuclear disaster, an experience that made him a foe of nuclear energy. He supports the co-op's emphasis on energy efficiency and renewable energy options, and said he appreciates how knowledgeable board members and staff are on energy issues.</p>
        <p>''It's not like they're tree huggers,'' he said. ''We have people who've been working on energy issues for a long time.''</p>
        <p>Beryl Lyons, a spokeswoman for the Department of Public Utility Control, said the licensing process ensured that companies offering electricity had the technical know-how, managerial skills and financial resources to do the job.</p>
        <p>The department has set the standard offer rates according to the 1998 law's requirement that consumers get a 10 percent reduction in their utility bills during the transition period, which will expire on Dec. 31, 2003.</p>
        <p>After the cap expires, prices will depend on the vagaries of weather and climate, availability of energy resources and other factors, said Joel Gordes, a consultant working on renewable energy and conservation issues and specializing in climate change. He is a member of the energy co-op.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lyons said that the companies approved and the five whose applications are pending provided ''a good start'' in offering consumers choice. But, she cautioned, ''You are not going to unravel 100 years of monopoly in six months or a year.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gordes said one recent piece of bad news could turn into good news for the co-op. The Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change released a new report in late October, confirming the human impact on global warming and reporting that global temperatures could rise over the next century even more than earlier predicted. Since fossil fuels are a big contributor to global warming, Mr. Gordes said, ''It would be hard to find a better argument for joining the co-op.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
