<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summary of Major Actions of the Legislature's 223rd Session</title>
    <meta content="25BILA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210328"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perez-Pena, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEED91430F936A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="3068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summary of Major Actions of the Legislature's 223rd Session</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Perez-Pena, Richard</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, June 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Summary of major actions taken by New York State Legislature in its 223rd session; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 223rd session of the New York State Legislature roared to a close Friday, with a head-spinning succession of deals on major issues that made this the most productive session in recent memory.</p>
        <p>The Senate, the Assembly and Gov. George E. Pataki agreed on a far-reaching package of gun controls, a major overhaul of the state's sexual assault laws and a law providing heavier penalties for hate crimes. On the final day of the session, they reached agreement on a law allowing patients to look up doctors' malpractice histories, a few days after striking a deal on a law requiring parental notification when pesticides are used in schools, and possible neighborhood notification when they are used on lawns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The 223rd session of the New York State Legislature roared to a close Friday, with a head-spinning succession of deals on major issues that made this the most productive session in recent memory.</p>
        <p>The Senate, the Assembly and Gov. George E. Pataki agreed on a far-reaching package of gun controls, a major overhaul of the state's sexual assault laws and a law providing heavier penalties for hate crimes. On the final day of the session, they reached agreement on a law allowing patients to look up doctors' malpractice histories, a few days after striking a deal on a law requiring parental notification when pesticides are used in schools, and possible neighborhood notification when they are used on lawns.</p>
        <p>It was a session marked early by feuding between Mr. Pataki and a fellow Republican, the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, that had some Republicans saying the governor was trying to overthrow the Senate leader. Later, it was the Democrats' turn to fight among themselves. The Assembly majority leader, Michael J. Bragman, attempted a coup against the speaker, Sheldon Silver, that failed and left the Democrats splintered and wary of each other.</p>
        <p>But relations between the two parties -- particularly between Mr. Silver and Mr. Pataki -- were remarkably calm throughout, with little of the partisan carping, personal attacks and legislative paralysis that have marked the last several years.</p>
        <p>The state budget was completed on May 5, just 35 days overdue, in the least contentious process since 1993, after years of budgets that ran two, three, even four months late. That averted the gridlock of previous years, when the focus on the overdue budget prevented work on other issues.</p>
        <p>A persistent theme of the session was the Senate Republicans' moving further than ever to the left, fearful of their prospects in November. They only grudgingly accepted bills on gun control, hate crimes, pesticide notification and other subjects long embraced by the Assembly Democrats.</p>
        <p>The Democrats gave ground on the sexual assault laws, but over all, won more big legislative victories than in any other year since Mr. Pataki became governor.</p>
        <p>Lawmakers were unable to reach agreement on a few notable issues, including a bill that would have required legislative approval and a local referendum for a proposed Indian casino in the Catskills, and proposed rule changes for Republican presidential primaries.</p>
        <p>In the Assembly, 9,938 bills were introduced and 1,036 were passed. In the Senate, 7,038 bills were introduced and 1,261 were passed. Some 681 bills passed both houses. Mr. Pataki has signed 94 of those.</p>
        <p>Budget</p>
        <p>The state, continuing to enjoy the bounty of the economic boom, is awash in tax revenues that allowed a significant increase in spending and sizable tax cuts at the same time. Lawmakers approved a $77.5 billion budget, up 5.7 percent from the year before, with tax cuts that will eventually be worth $1.2 billion a year.</p>
        <p>They increased spending on education by 8.7 percent, to more than $13 billion, including continued expansion of the two-year-old program to provide prekindergarten classes for 4-year-olds and smaller class sizes in the early grades.</p>
        <p>The largess extended to college students, who saw state tuition assistance increase significantly, and to the elderly, who saw a doubling of the state program to help the low-income elderly pay for prescription drugs.</p>
        <p>Medicaid, the largest part of the budget at $29 billion and the spending area that had generated the most pitched battles since Mr. Pataki became governor, was never an issue. As part of a deal reached in December on health coverage for the uninsured, the governor agreed that for the first time he would not try to cut Medicaid, the health care program for the poor.</p>
        <p>At the governor's insistence, the budget included the first limits ever placed on New York's state debt, the highest in the nation. The ceilings will go into effect gradually over more than a decade, but they were welcomed by Wall Street rating agencies. The budget also greatly increased the size of the state's various reserve funds, to more than $3 billion.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Pataki and the Legislature agreed to put a $3.8 billion bond act before voters in November to help pay for the Metropolitan Transportation Authority's capital program and improvements to the state's roads and bridges.</p>
        <p>Crime and Justice</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Decriminalizes the possession and sale of hypodermic needles without a doctor's prescription.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would ban assault weapons, mirroring the federal ban, and allow local prosecutors to enforce the law.</p>
        <p>Would require the inclusion of trigger locks with all new handguns sold.</p>
        <p>Would require that new handguns be test-fired before sale so they could be entered into a ''ballistic fingerprint'' database for all guns used in crimes, for comparison later with bullets and shell casings found at crime scenes.</p>
        <p>Would require background checks of gun buyers at gun shows, even when the seller was a private citizen, not a gun dealer.</p>
        <p>Would raise the minimum age for obtaining a handgun permit and buying a handgun to 21 from 18.</p>
        <p>Would explicitly apply the crimes of rape and sodomy to cases of date rape and acquaintance rape.</p>
        <p>Would increase penalties for sale or use of date rape drugs.</p>
        <p>Would create a sex crime of forcible touching, with more severe penalties than have been possible.</p>
        <p>Would raise the maximum age of victims for cases of statutory rape to 15 from 14, and would raise the maximum age of victims for cases carrying the most severe penalties to 13 from 11.</p>
        <p>Would increase penalties for repeat sex offenders and for people who committed sex crimes against mentally disabled people.</p>
        <p>Would abolish laws that prevented prosecution of sex crimes when the victim was the attacker's spouse.</p>
        <p>Would prohibit the granting of bail for people accused of serious sex crimes against minors.</p>
        <p>Would eliminate the requirement that sex crime victims report the crimes to the police immediately to qualify for services provided by the State Crime Victims Board. The victims would become eligible for coverage of hospital treatment, counseling, lost wages and damaged or stolen property.</p>
        <p>Would require state financing of rape crisis centers.</p>
        <p>Would provide longer prison sentences for certain crimes when the victim was singled out because of bias based on race, religion, sex, sexual orientation, national origin or disability.</p>
        <p>Would make the shipping of ''bootleg'' cigarettes into the state without paying state taxes, now a misdemeanor, a felony for repeat violators, and would impose fines for such violations up to $100 per carton.</p>
        <p>Would prohibit the shipment of cigarettes by mail-order companies, including those selling through the Internet, directly to customers. Would require instead that the cigarettes be shipped to a licensed retailer, where the customer could pick them up, but would have to show proof of age and pay state taxes.</p>
        <p>Would increase fines for sales of cigarettes to minors.</p>
        <p>Would make people imprisoned for killing a spouse or partner eligible for work release if they could show they were victims of severe domestic violence.</p>
        <p>Would make an assault by a teacher on a student, or an assault by a student on a teacher, a felony.</p>
        <p>Would provide a mechanism for people to remove their names from the state registry of suspected child abusers if they could provide proof that they were innocent.</p>
        <p>Would exempt mothers from criminal penalties for abandoning newborn babies if they left their babies in safe places like hospitals or police stations.</p>
        <p>Would strengthen state laws against money laundering, including broadening them to cover wire transfers.</p>
        <p>Would require bounty hunters to complete a training course and to notify local law enforcement when working in a particular area, and would make them liable for injuries and property damage they caused.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have allowed prosecutors to appeal bail settings and sentences in sex crime cases.</p>
        <p>Would have banned ''canned hunting,'' the practice of shooting captive animals on private reserves.</p>
        <p>Would have streamlined the state's multilayered court system.</p>
        <p>Would have created 36 Criminal Court and Family Court judgeships in New York City to ease overcrowding.</p>
        <p>Would have lowered the blood-alcohol threshold for drunken driving charges to 0.08 from 0.10.</p>
        <p>Business and Labor</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Sets the minimum wage for hotel and restaurant workers who earn tips at $3.30 an hour. The minimum wage had been slated, under a law passed last year, to rise to $3.52 from $2.90.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would require legislative approval for any casino established by an Indian tribe outside its reservation.</p>
        <p>Would require that by July 1, 2003, all cigarettes sold in New York meet fire-safety standards.</p>
        <p>Would subject herbal cigarettes to the same regulation as tobacco cigarettes, including banning sales to minors.</p>
        <p>Would restrict to tobacco shops the sale of bidis, cigarettes from India that are considered more unhealthy than ordinary cigarettes.</p>
        <p>Would ban tobacco ads visible outdoors near schools, day care centers, playgrounds and other places where children congregate.</p>
        <p>Would provide automatic annual cost-of-living increases for retired public employees.</p>
        <p>Would free public employees from having to make contributions to their pensions after 10 years of employment.</p>
        <p>Would allow the expansion of the New York Stock Exchange to proceed by authorizing New York City's Industrial Development Authority to sell $255 million in bonds for the project, and by authorizing the state's Empire State Development Corporation to condemn and acquire property across the street from the current exchange.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have raised the state minimum wage for most categories of workers to $6.75 an hour from $5.15.</p>
        <p>Would have banned self-service display cases of cigarettes, requiring that a buyer ask a sales clerk for them.</p>
        <p>Would have given farm workers the same protections given to most classes of workers, including a higher minimum wage and rules on working conditions.</p>
        <p>Would have required nonsmoking areas in most restaurants.</p>
        <p>Environment and Energy</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Prohibits companies that have earned pollution credits by reducing their air emissions from trading or selling those credits to companies in Midwestern states that are contributors to acid rain in New York.</p>
        <p>Phases out use of MTBE's, a group of gasoline additives that reduce air pollution but have been found to contribute to ground-water contamination.</p>
        <p>Provides $250 million to subsidize purchases of electric power by companies that locate or expand in New York, or that pledge not to leave the state.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would allow counties and New York City to require that neighbors be given 48 hours' notice before commercial application of pesticide on a property, and would require that schools give notice of pesticide application to parents who have requested such notice.</p>
        <p>Would require that the seller of a property give to the buyer written notice of any known toxic contamination of the property.</p>
        <p>Would allow towns and villages to regulate the use of motorized water scooters, including banning them entirely.</p>
        <p>Would impose air emission standards on motorized water scooters.</p>
        <p>Would prohibit the Long Island Power Authority from charging large disconnection fees to customers who switch to fuel cells or to other alternative sources of electricity.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have spent more than $300 million a year to promote electric power conservation and use of cleaner fuels.</p>
        <p>Would have refinanced the state's bankrupt Superfund program for cleaning up toxic waste sites, by imposing fees on industry and taking money out of the state treasury.</p>
        <p>Would have created a clean-up program for brownfields, sites that are not polluted enough to qualify for the Superfund program, in which the state would do the work when property owners are unwilling or unable.</p>
        <p>Education</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Provides incentives for people to become teachers, particularly in low-income communities, including grants of up to $3,400 a year to cover education costs for people who agree to teach in communities with teacher shortages; grants up to $2,000 per year to help teachers with temporary licenses cover the costs of achieving permanent certification; a teaching internship program for college students; and grants of up to $10,000 a year for up to three years for highly rated teachers who agree to switch to communities with teacher shortages.</p>
        <p>Expands the state's tuition assistance program for college students by $141 million a year, by raising the maximum grant to $5,000 from $4,125 per year; raising the family income eligibility ceiling to $80,000 from $50,500; and eliminating a rule that a student's grant may not cover more than 90 percent of tuition.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would provide a wider range of investment options for the state's tax-sheltered college savings account program.</p>
        <p>Would make it easier for teachers to remove disruptive students from their classrooms.</p>
        <p>Would require school districts to fingerprint prospective employees and conduct background checks on them.</p>
        <p>Would establish whistle-blower protections for school employees who report acts of violence in schools to the police.</p>
        <p>Would prohibit the practice of ''silent resignations,'' in which school employees accused of wrongdoing can resign and not have their actions reflected in the records forwarded to prospective new employers.</p>
        <p>Taxes</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Eliminates the tax on utility bills for businesses and reduces it for residences to 2 percent from 3.25 percent, for a savings to businesses and taxpayers, when fully put in effect in five years, of $330 million a year.</p>
        <p>Makes college tuition fully deductible from state personal income taxes, for a savings to taxpayers of $200 million a year.</p>
        <p>Eliminates the ''marriage penalty'' in state income tax, in which married couples paid more than they would if they were single and filed separately, for a savings to taxpayers of $200 million a year.</p>
        <p>Expands the earned income tax credit, a tax break for the working poor, for a savings to taxpayers of $125 million a year.</p>
        <p>Eliminates some taxes for businesses that move to economically distressed areas, for a savings to businesses of $40 million a year.</p>
        <p>Expands the tax credit for child care expenses, for a savings to taxpayers of $25 million a year.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have eliminated the state's 4 percent tax on gasoline and given counties the option of doing away with their 3 to 4 percent tax on gasoline.</p>
        <p>Health Care</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Expands a program to subsidize prescription drug costs for people 65 or older, raising the income eligibility for a single person to $35,000 from $18,500, more than doubling the number of people eligible, to 220,000, at a cost to the state of $180 million a year.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would provide protection against retaliation for health care workers who reported suspected wrongdoing by their employers, including requiring investigation by the Department of Labor and providing fines for employers who punished whistle-blowers.</p>
        <p>Would allow people to look up the malpractice records of doctors, including on the Internet.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have allowed disabled people to remain on Medicaid after obtaining jobs, while requiring that they pay a monthly premium.</p>
        <p>Would have required health insurance companies to cover the cost of infertility treatments.</p>
        <p>Consumer Affairs</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Extends the state's ban on ticket scalping for one year.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would prohibit Consolidated Edison from passing on to customers costs related to a leak and subsequent shutdown at its Indian Point nuclear reactor.</p>
        <p>Would prohibit telemarketers from gaining access to bank accounts and account information without written consent of consumers, and would require all telemarketers to be bonded and registered with the state.</p>
        <p>Would allow people to put themselves on a list of people whom telemarketers would be prohibited from calling unsolicited.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have prohibited discrimination based on sexual orientation in employment, housing and several other areas.</p>
        <p>Would have allowed tenants in rent-stabilized apartments to deduct from their state taxes the rent increases charged when landlords undertake major capital improvements.</p>
        <p>Transportation</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Places on the November ballot a $3.8 billion bond act for transportation projects.</p>
        <p>Gives the Metropolitan Transportation Authority the authorization to sell $22 billion in bonds for its new capital program, including refinancing $12 billion in outstanding bonds from previous programs.</p>
        <p>Creates the Southern Tier Rail Authority, to help provide rail service on an unused line across Steuben, Allegany, Cattaraugus and Chautauqua Counties.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would require that children under 16 wear seat belts when riding in the rear seats of cars, rather than children under age 10, as required now.</p>
        <p>Welfare and Families</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would allow student internships and work-study jobs held by college students on welfare to count toward work requirements under the welfare law.</p>
        <p>Would raise to 18 from 16 the maximum age for a ''person in need of supervision,'' a designation made by a judge that allows the court to order the youth to return home, attend school, undergo drug treatment or receive counseling.</p>
        <p>Would require criminal background checks and fingerprinting for workers in licensed child care facilities.</p>
        <p>Government and Ethics</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION ENACTED</p>
        <p>Imposes limits on state debt, eventually restricting it to 4 percent of the annual personal income of state residents, down from more than 6 percent now.</p>
        <p>Provides $180 million to help local governments cover the costs of Family Health Plus, a new program to assist low-income people in acquiring health insurance.</p>
        <p>Provides $105 million in aid to Nassau County, in return for the county's making $260 million in budget cuts over the next four years, and provides that if those cuts are not made, the state can impose a financial control board on the county.</p>
        <p>Creates the Nassau Interim Financing Authority to sell bonds on behalf of the county.</p>
        <p>Raises the limit on New York City's debt by $4 billion.</p>
        <p>Provides $45 million in emergency aid to the Buffalo schools.</p>
        <p>Provides $10 million in emergency aid to the Yonkers schools.</p>
        <p>AWAITING SIGNATURE</p>
        <p>Would revise the State Constitution to make the language gender-neutral.</p>
        <p>LEGISLATION FAILED</p>
        <p>Would have changed the rules for Republican presidential primaries in New York to make it virtually automatic for well-known candidates to get on the ballot, and to simplify the ballot itself.</p>
        <p>Would have banned largely unregulated ''soft money'' campaign contributions and imposed new, lower limits on contributions made directly to candidates and parties.</p>
        <p>Would have provided for public financing of campaigns.</p>
        <p>Would have required that the Assembly and the Senate convene a conference committee to work out their differences when both houses pass bills that are substantially similar.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
