<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Appeals Court Upholds E.P.A. Rules to Reduce Smog in the Northeast</title>
    <meta content="Y04EPA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1181187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northeastern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Missouri</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wisconsin</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0D91738F937A35750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Appeals Court Upholds E.P.A. Rules to Reduce Smog in the Northeast</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TINA KELLEY</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal appeals court upholds EPA rules limiting pollution from Midwestern states that causes unacceptable levels of smog in Northeast; says further review is necessary to determine how regulations apply to Georgia, Missouri and Wisconsin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In what clean-air advocates called a watershed ruling, a federal appeals court yesterday upheld rules limiting pollution from Midwestern states that causes unacceptable levels of smog in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>In a 2-to-1 ruling, a panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit upheld an Environmental Protection Agency rule requiring the control of smog-causing chemicals that move from 19 states, among them Indiana, Ohio and West Virginia, to states like New York and parts of New England. Coal-burning power plants are the primary source of the main chemical, nitrogen oxide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In what clean-air advocates called a watershed ruling, a federal appeals court yesterday upheld rules limiting pollution from Midwestern states that causes unacceptable levels of smog in the Northeast.</p>
        <p>In a 2-to-1 ruling, a panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit upheld an Environmental Protection Agency rule requiring the control of smog-causing chemicals that move from 19 states, among them Indiana, Ohio and West Virginia, to states like New York and parts of New England. Coal-burning power plants are the primary source of the main chemical, nitrogen oxide.</p>
        <p>The ruling limits the amount of nitrogen oxide that states can emit into the atmosphere. In some cases, the new limit may require power plants to reduce their emissions to one-fourth or one-sixth of what had previously been allowed, said Peter Lehner, chief of the environmental protection bureau of the New York attorney general's office. States can choose to limit emissions as they wish but are expected to focus on power plants.</p>
        <p>''This decision means that we again can move forward to bring cleaner, healthier air to more than 138 million people living in the eastern half of the United States,'' Carol M. Browner, the agency's administrator, said in a statement.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. had issued regulations regarding emissions in 1998, but litigation delayed their being put into effect.</p>
        <p>The regulations are now expected to take effect by 2003 for some plants and by 2005 for others. The rules originally applied to 22 states; yesterday's ruling said further review was necessary to determine how the regulations applied to Georgia, Missouri and Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>More than half of the reductions in emissions would come in six states: Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Ohio, Pennsylvania and West Virginia.</p>
        <p>In addition to New York, the other states affected are Alabama, Connecticut, Delaware, Kentucky, Maryland, Massachusetts, New Jersey, North Carolina, Rhode Island, South Carolina, Tennessee and Virginia.</p>
        <p>''The total amount of air pollution, especially in the summer, will be dramatically less,'' Mr. Lehner said, predicting that people would be able to notice reductions in smog and would see some relief from asthma and other respiratory diseases that are exacerbated by air pollution.</p>
        <p>While the current regulations focused on summer smog, he said, the controls might also be necessary in winter, and that should reduce acid rain and particulate pollution.</p>
        <p>''This is an extraordinarily big step toward getting year-round controls,'' Mr. Lehner said.</p>
        <p>David Hawkins, senior attorney at the Natural Resources Defense Council, an environmental advocacy group involved in the suit, said the Environmental Protection Agency would now be able to cut pollution from coal-burning plants by more than a million tons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins said Ohio, one of the worst polluters, had more hospital admissions during smoggy periods than New York State.</p>
        <p>''Some of the states that are the biggest polluters of other states are also the biggest polluters of their own citizens,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Calls to the lawyer representing the Midwest Ozone Group, a coalition of utility and coal companies that fought the regulations, were not returned last night.</p>
        <p>Judges Stephen F. Williams and Judith W. Rogers sided with the E.P.A. Judge David B. Sentelle dissented.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
