<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1247739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EFD6143BF935A25752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-18</p>
        <p>Israeli Air Attacks Retaliate for 4 Deaths  Israeli helicopters rocketed Palestinian targets in the West Bank after a day of surging violence in which Israeli soldiers shot and killed eight Palestinians and wounded dozens more in raging street battles. The helicopter strikes came after a meeting of the security cabinet of Prime Minister Ehud Barak, who had been pressed to order a tough military response to Palestinian shootings that killed four Israelis on Monday.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton met with the prime minister and president in Jerusalem and delivered an emotional eulogy for Leah Rabin, who died of cancer on Saturday.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-18</p>
        <p>Israeli Air Attacks Retaliate for 4 Deaths  Israeli helicopters rocketed Palestinian targets in the West Bank after a day of surging violence in which Israeli soldiers shot and killed eight Palestinians and wounded dozens more in raging street battles. The helicopter strikes came after a meeting of the security cabinet of Prime Minister Ehud Barak, who had been pressed to order a tough military response to Palestinian shootings that killed four Israelis on Monday.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Hillary Rodham Clinton met with the prime minister and president in Jerusalem and delivered an emotional eulogy for Leah Rabin, who died of cancer on Saturday.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Clinton to Open Vietnam Tour  President Clinton is to arrive in Hanoi today to open a new chapter in postwar relations with Vietnam.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>In Brunei, President Clinton held what will very likely be his last meetings with the leaders of South Korea and Russia. He appeared to reach no firm conclusion with President Kim Dae Jung of South Korea over whether Mr. Clinton should visit North Korea before he leaves office in January, and he made little progress on arms control with President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Indian Film Star Freed  The elderly movie idol Rajkumar, left, who had been held captive for 109 days in an ever-shifting series of jungle encampments, was freed by the notorious bandit Veerappan.</p>
        <p>A16</p>
        <p>Gandhi Is New Party Leader  Sonia Gandhi, standard bearer of the Nehru-Gandhi political dynasty, was elected president of the Congress Party, India's second largest, by an overwhelming margin.</p>
        <p>A17</p>
        <p>Honors for a Rights Advocate  Martin Macwan, who founded the National Campaign on Dalit Human Rights to protect India's ''untouchable'' underclass, will be honored by two major American human rights organizations.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A20-32</p>
        <p>Florida Bars Recounts; Bush Rejects Gore Appeal  The Florida secretary of state refused requests by two big Democratic counties to accept results of further manual recounts. The announcement came after officials of Gov. George W. Bush's campaign rejected a proposal personally made by Vice President Al Gore that both sides accept recount results.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush later responded publicly that a manual recount would be neither fair nor accurate.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Earlier, the Florida Supreme Court declined to block further hand recounts, and heavily Democratic Broward County began a manual recount of more than half a million votes. A federal appeals court in Atlanta agreed to hear Governor Bush's request for an injunction to block further recounts, paving the way for possible review by the United States Supreme Court. Palm Beach County again delayed its recount after the Florida Supreme Court put off acting on the county's request for clarification of a dispute between the secretary of state, a Republican, and the attorney general, a Democrat, on the recount's legality. Miami-Dade County officials meet tomorrow to review their decision not to proceed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Courts across the country have recently been far more liberal in interpreting what is a proper ballot.</p>
        <p>A32</p>
        <p>Most of the absentee ballots from abroad waiting to be tallied have been received by counties that favored Mr. Bush on Election Day.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>A Republican House leader, Tom DeLay, sent a memo to Republicans noting that Congress can reject electoral votes deemed tainted.</p>
        <p>A29</p>
        <p>Los Angeles Police Convictions  Three of four officers charged with framing gang members and planting evidence were convicted. It was the first case to go to trial in a major police corruption scandal.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Bishops on Crime and Victims  The nation's Roman Catholic bishops adopted a broad but detailed statement on America's criminal justice system, calling both for a new commitment to rehabilitate criminals and for greater attention to the rights and well-being of victims.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-12</p>
        <p>Deal to Cut Emissions Feeding Northeast Smog  Virginia Electric Power, prompted by legal action by New York State and the E.P.A., agreed to cut emissions by 70 percent at eight coal-burning plants accused of contributing to acid rain and smog in the Northeast. Officials hope the agreement will set a precedent for power companies in the Midwest and the South.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>PATH Fare and Tolls May Rise  The Port Authority of New York and New Jersey is weighing a plan that could double the basic fare on PATH trains to $2 and increase tolls at several bridges and tunnels to $7 from $4 in rush hours, officials said.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Accusations of Improprieties  Republicans accused Democrats of inappropriately gathering dozens of votes from hospitalized psychiatric patients in the close race in New Jersey's 12th Congressional District won by Representative Rush Holt, who denied the accusations.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Admission in Socialite Murder  A lawyer for Kenneth Kimes said his client had told detectives that he and his mother dumped the body of Irene Silverman at a New Jersey construction site. But it was not clear if Mr. Kimes's confession was genuine.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Monitoring Prescriptions  Pharmaceutical marketers spend millions buying information from pharmacies, the federal government and the A.M.A on the prescribing patterns of health care professionals.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>CIRCUITS</p>
        <p>G1-16</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B13-14</p>
        <p>Alexander M. Schindler  The rabbi who led the Reform movement of American Judaism through 23 years of growth was 75.</p>
        <p>B13</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-20</p>
        <p>Interest Rates Hold  The Fed held interest rates steady, but with unemployment low and energy prices high it said it was not yet ready to proclaim inflation no longer a threat. The Fed's statement did not allude to the uncertainty over the presidential election or recent uncertainty in the markets.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T to Spin Off a Cable Unit  AT&amp;T, under pressure to reduce its holdings in the cable industry, will spin off Liberty Media, which owns stakes in programming companies.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-14</p>
        <p>National Book Awards  Susan Sontag received the fiction award for ''In America''; in nonfiction, Nathaniel Philbrick was honored for ''In the Heart of the Sea: The Tragedy of the Whaleship Essex.''</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>HOUSE &amp; HOME</p>
        <p>F1-20</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A34-35</p>
        <p>Editorials: Decisions and delays in Florida; a presidential journey to Vietnam; executing Johnny Paul Penry.</p>
        <p>Columns: Bob Herbert, William Safire.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>E10  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E13  Crossword</p>
        <p>E6  Weather</p>
        <p>D8  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
