<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="26FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1250520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Correction Stories</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D61E3AF935A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Correction of letter to editor in Nov 26 Arts and Leisure regarding veteran television comedians</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-30</p>
        <p>Links to bin Laden Gnaw At F.B.I. in Cole Inquiry  F.B.I. officials investigating the bombing of the destroyer Cole have kept open the possibility that the attack may have involved powerful figures in Yemen who have close ties to Osama bin Laden, the F.B.I.'s most-wanted terrorist.</p>
        <p>6</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>3-30</p>
        <p>Links to bin Laden Gnaw At F.B.I. in Cole Inquiry  F.B.I. officials investigating the bombing of the destroyer Cole have kept open the possibility that the attack may have involved powerful figures in Yemen who have close ties to Osama bin Laden, the F.B.I.'s most-wanted terrorist.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Milosevic Named Party Leader  A characteristically defiant Slobodan Milosevic staged his political comeback, winning re-election as leader of his Socialist Party of Serbia and denouncing as a coup the popular uprising that swept him from power last month.</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Elections in Canada  Prime Minister Jean Chretien is fighting for political survival, as his advantage over the conservative opposition narrows. If the Liberals fare poorly in Monday's elections, they will probably depose him, ending a decade of party leadership and seven years as prime minister.</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Climate Treaty Talks Fail  Negotiations aimed at finishing a treaty to curb global warming broke down after two weeks of intense negotiations at The Hague, on disputes between American and European negotiators.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>33-46</p>
        <p>Broward County Election Officials Complete Recount  Weary election officials in Broward County finished their manual recount of ballots, cutting Gov. George W. Bush's lead over Vice President Al Gore in half.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Lawyers for Mr. Bush withdrew one lawsuit before filing new suits asking a judge to direct four Florida counties to reinstate the absentee ballots of overseas military voters.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The voting figures in Florida are expected to show a thin victory for Mr. Bush, but Mr. Gore's campaign has made it clear that he expects to fight on, whatever the result.</p>
        <p>33</p>
        <p>State lawmakers and elections officials around the country are proposing changes in voting procedures to reduce the potential for legal challenges in close elections.</p>
        <p>35</p>
        <p>The message from conservatives these days is simple and unified -- that the Democrats are trying to steal the election.</p>
        <p>37</p>
        <p>Care Centers Under Scrutiny  The nation's largest chain of assisted living facilities has come under scrutiny over the quality of care and safety conditions at some of its centers.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Gifts for Those With Plenty  Many Americans have amassed all the goods they need, so they are asking for gifts they can use up.</p>
        <p>39</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>49-56</p>
        <p>Harlem Realty Renaissance Not Quite So Big After All  Just as Harlem seems to be undergoing a renaissance, with property values rising and new stores and restaurants springing up, downtown real estate agencies, after taking a closer look, have quietly scrapped plans to open satellite offices in Harlem.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Yes, It Really Is More Crowded  If New York feels more crowded these days, it's because it is. There are more people living in the city, more people working in it and more people coming to visit. And it's not just a matter of numbers; affluence intensifies the impression.</p>
        <p>49</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>49</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>57-58</p>
        <p>Keith Mant  A pathologist who provided evidence from exhumed corpses that was used to send a number of Nazi doctors to the gallows after World War II, he was 81.</p>
        <p>58</p>
        <p>Chess</p>
        <p>57  Weather</p>
        <p>59</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
