<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Guts on Sticks</title>
    <meta content="03NORMANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="98" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1251954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norman, Geoffrey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckibben, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Long Distance: A Year of Living Strenuously (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E2DE153AF930A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Guts on Sticks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Geoffrey Norman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Norman, Geoffrey</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Geoffrey Norman reviews book Long Distance: A Year of Living Strenuously by Bill McKibben (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG DISTANCE</p>
        <p>A Year of Living Strenuously.</p>
        <p>By Bill McKibben.</p>
        <p>191 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG DISTANCE</p>
        <p>A Year of Living Strenuously.</p>
        <p>By Bill McKibben.</p>
        <p>191 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
        <p>AT 37, Bill McKibben decided to test himself. In a time of aging marathoners and mountain climbers, and a culture drenched in images of fitness and sport, this is a routine impulse, easily pigeonholed. And because he's a journalist, McKibben knew from the beginning that he will write about training and competing after a lifetime of avoiding sports. This is no more surprising than the next political memoir.</p>
        <p>McKibben sets no records as a cross-country skier. But as a writer, he leaves the conventions and the formulas far behind, and his book succeeds -- indeed, triumphs -- as so many racers do, on heart as much as talent. McKibben is a former staff writer for The New Yorker and brings a journalist's diligence to the business of learning to be an athlete. The choice of a sport is easy enough. He lives in the Adirondacks in upstate New York, where the winter snows are deep, and he already enjoys cross-country skiing for recreation. The Olympic Training Center is in nearby Lake Placid, so McKibben will be able to work out there. Finally, cross-country racing is a sport that depends on endurance. Speed, agility and balance are gifts that come to true athletes through grace. Endurance can be acquired through training and will.</p>
        <p>McKibben puts himself in the hands of a trainer named Rob Sleamaker, and begins a program: ''Six hundred hours of training in the next 12 months, right around the bottom of the scale for Olympic athletes.'' In his first race, he skis into a fellow competitor and is later knocked down himself, then flails futilely on skis that are not properly waxed. ''Now there was nothing to do but herringbone, spreading my skis like wings on the snow to keep myself from sliding backwards. As I started to pant, my glasses began to fog, and soon it was like skiing through a San Francisco summer.''</p>
        <p>Inevitably, McKibben gets better. He learns more about his sport, and so do we: there are sections on the seductions of expensive gear, the mysteries of diet, something called the ''VO2 Max'' (a measure of how efficiently the body uses oxygen), the lore of cross-country skiing and its frustrations in a time of global warming -- global warming being a subject about which McKibben has written and lectured, and which now seems like a personal nemesis. He becomes something of a self-absorbed fitness addict and experiences the stoic sense of joy that to many endurance athletes is the real point. In a 45-kilometer race, he finds himself in a personal competition with another racer and wins. ''I felt,'' he writes, ''like, well, an athlete.'' McKibben tells these things well, in a spare and refreshingly self-deprecating style.</p>
        <p>All this alone would have made a solid book. Then, as he is stacking firewood on a fall afternoon before the winter when he would ski his final race in Norway, the news comes: ''The M.R.I. showed that Dad had a brain tumor, 'an aggressive nonbenign tumor.' They were operating on Tuesday. Just like that.''</p>
        <p>There is endurance, and then there is endurance. Or, as McKibben remarks after a physical that charts eight months of (remarkable) progress as an athlete, ''My heart might have become more efficient, but my heart seemed no stronger.'' The ordeal of the next months dwarfs anything McKibben has endured in any race or training session. It would be unfair to synopsize McKibben's account of how he and his family coped with this ordeal. It is enough to say that this part of his tale is told with exquisite sensitivity and insight.</p>
        <p>He had begun his experiment, he writes, ''in an effort to try on a new identity, the way a high school boy might try on meanness, or a college boy might grow a goatee. . . . But now, watching Dad, I realized that I'd mainly discovered what a solid thing an identity is. He, at least, was unchanged even by this catastrophe.''</p>
        <p>McKibben makes it, eventually, to Norway, ''a place defined in some ways by endurance.'' It is a quality that, by now, both he and his readers might equate with wisdom.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Norman's most recent book is ''Two for the Summit: My Daughter, the Mountains, and Me.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Geoffrey Norman's most recent book is ''Two for the Summit: My Daughter, the Mountains, and Me.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
