<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Happy, Scary New Day for Design</title>
    <meta content="15MUSC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/arts/15MUSC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20001022T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238828"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E0D61E3CF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="3812" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Happy, Scary New Day for Design</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp assesses changes in design field, fueled by new economy, that have sparked public imagination like no other since late 1960's and early 1970's; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is scary to be living at a time when a particular creative field grips the public imagination as powerfully as design has in recent years. I can't recall anything like it since the late 60's and early 70's, when movies and pop music exercised a magnetic hold on the minds of baby boomers. Today, the vigor pulses through fashion, furniture, art direction, graphics and product and image design with a similarly captivating verve. Design has taken on its own life, and this raises a problem often encountered in consumer culture. The energy is pure delight. But can we turn it off?</p>
        <p>The new economy has been the major stimulus for the design phenomenon. Its most conspicuous expressions are appliances for data exchange -- computers, cell phones, personal organizers, digital cameras -- and the software programs and communications systems to which they are linked. Another stimulus emanates from the world of medicine: designer drugs, genetic engineering, cyber-prosthetics and advanced techniques in cosmetic surgery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is scary to be living at a time when a particular creative field grips the public imagination as powerfully as design has in recent years. I can't recall anything like it since the late 60's and early 70's, when movies and pop music exercised a magnetic hold on the minds of baby boomers. Today, the vigor pulses through fashion, furniture, art direction, graphics and product and image design with a similarly captivating verve. Design has taken on its own life, and this raises a problem often encountered in consumer culture. The energy is pure delight. But can we turn it off?</p>
        <p>The new economy has been the major stimulus for the design phenomenon. Its most conspicuous expressions are appliances for data exchange -- computers, cell phones, personal organizers, digital cameras -- and the software programs and communications systems to which they are linked. Another stimulus emanates from the world of medicine: designer drugs, genetic engineering, cyber-prosthetics and advanced techniques in cosmetic surgery.</p>
        <p>As expressions of The New, these products have inherited the myth of progress, modernity's defining legend. This is not the first time design has embodied that myth. In the early 20th century, the old economy (machine age) myth revolved around cars, ships, planes and other mechanized forms of transportation. But the myth also reshaped the face of buildings, fashion, decoration, paintings and other conventional forms. The new economic myth is having a similar impact. In addition to generating snazzy new shapes for laptops and hand-helds, this myth is transforming the look of buildings, interiors, books, landscapes, advertisements and other traditional forms of design.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists use the term ecotone to describe the area where two adjacent ecosystems -- a wetland and a forest, say -- overlap. The ecotone has an ecology of its own. It can support forms of life not found in either of the adjacent systems. Today there exists the cultural equivalent of an ecotone between the old and new economies, between the culture of industrial production and that of informational exchange. Design today is flourishing in this region. Its symbol is the veil, a graphic device that conveys the conflicting desire to conceal and reveal.</p>
        <p>Shadow, translucency, reflection, refraction, dappling, stippling, blurring, shimmering, vibration, moire, netting, layering, superimposition: these are some of the visual devices used to render the veil in contemporary design. Recent examples include the Apple G4 Power Cube; shadow niches in the walls of the British architect John Pawson; the spring 2001 collection by the fashion designer Helmut Lang; curtains by the Dutch designer Petra Blaisse; a new book, ''Life Style,'' by the Canadian graphics designer Bruce Mau. His book, which is to be published next month, is an ideal opportunity to examine the significance of the veil as a contemporary design motif.</p>
        <p>''Life Style'' (Phaidon, $69.95) is one long Salome's dance. A 627-page strip tease performed with an endless variety of veils, the book tantalizes readers with glimpses into the thinking of one of the most creative minds at work in design today. Book covers, posters, videos, exhibitions, collaborations with architects, editors, filmmakers, performance artists and writers: Mau's projects in these and other media are graphically documented in a book that presents itself as a manifesto as well as a monograph.</p>
        <p>You should not skip over the written portions, for these make clear that Mau does far more than bombard people with alluring, decontextualized images. ''Life Style'' is a designer's celebration of the book. Mau champions books at a historical moment when print culture is thought to be vanishing into the new economy's trash compactor. In this sense, Mau is picking up the threads of his fellow Canadian, Marshall McLuhan, and weaving them into a counterargument against McLuhan's prophecies of the book's doom. While perceived by some as trendy, Mau has a staunchly traditional attachment to the printed page.</p>
        <p>Recently, Mau mentioned to me that graphic design is a young man's game. Now at 40, perhaps he sees ''Life Style'' as a summary of his work in a field he is preparing to quit. More likely, his comment simply reflected his commitment to working in the present. Contemporaneity -- the atmosphere of the present -- is Mau's product. It is easy to see him selling it in the many media he has yet to tackle.</p>
        <p>Mau, who is based in Toronto, is best known to date as Rem Koolhaas's co-author of ''S,M,L,XL,'' the acclaimed 1998 monograph on Koolhaas's buildings and ideas. Though the architect's work provides most of the book's content, Mau gets equal billing for the project: on the book's cover, the two names appear in type of equal size. The collaboration sent a message. Form and content are not fully divisible. A book's design, particularly when its content is visual art, should match the intelligence of its subject and even interact with it throughout the course of production. An enriched sensibility may emerge along the way. This is the message Mau has been sending from the outset of his career.</p>
        <p>His professional present began in 1985 with the publication of Zone 1/2, a soft-cover anthology of writings on the contemporary city. He designed a cover of blue and dark blue squares arranged in a tight mosaic pattern that evoked satellite surveillance photography. The letters of the title were made from perforated dots that revealed the flamingo pink of the page beneath.</p>
        <p>Zone 1/2 s reprinted in ''Life Style'' in its entirety, a book-within-the-book laid out on five double-page spreads. The print is too small to read. It registers as a series of thumbnail scrims, periodically punctuated with photographs, maps and other graphic devices. These create the effect of small explosions in the text, the visual equivalent of urban events.</p>
        <p>Mau's sensibility is resolutely urbane: the artistic quality of his work is more essential to him than its commercial success. By the standards of academic publishing, however, Zone 1/2 was quite successful, and this led to the launching of Zone Books, a publishing co-venture with MIT Press. Edited by Jonathan Crary, Michel Fehrer and Sanford Kwinter, the imprint has specialized in visual art and urban culture, new titles as well as classic studies in these fields by authors like Panovsky and Batailles.</p>
        <p>Since 1990, Mau has designed books in a similar vein for the Getty Research Institutes Publications Program, under the direction of Julia Bloomfield. In 1992, he was hired by Chee Perlman to redesign I.D. magazine, a trade publication that under Perlman's editorial direction became the leading chronicler of contemporary design.</p>
        <p>Mau is now the imprint's imprint. There is a characteristic Bruce Mau look. It didn't come out of nowhere. Rauschenberg's silkscreens; color field paintings by Lewis, Frankenthaler and Olitsky; the pointillism of Seurat: these are some obvious visual precedents for the superimposed veils of image and text that one encounters throughout Mau's print work. Too, his approach echoes the visual/textual collage aesthetic of ''The Medium Is the Massage,'' the 1966 paperback by McLuhan and the graphic designer Quentin Fiore. This book has become a classic for the wired generation.</p>
        <p>WHAT emerges in the pages of ''Life Style,'' however, is not just a distinctive aesthetic -- a Mau brand -- but the consistently high level of cultural sophistication represented by his clients. His roster consists almost exclusively of high-end publishers and cultural institutions. This focus, as well as the intelligence of his own work, is responsible for Mau's own lifestyle, the professional image Mau currently projects.</p>
        <p>To put it another way, Mau's reputation rests on the ingenuity with which he blurs the boundaries between picture and text. He operates in an ecotone between print and visual culture. From that position, Mau perceives the distortions that images and words can separately impose on our view of the world. Mau is powerless to correct these distortions. But he can call attention to their presence. And he can provoke us toward skepticism about their claims to truth. That is the function of Mau's veils.</p>
        <p>The veil evokes a universe of metaphors. Religious: maya, the veils of illusion; the veil of the temple; the glass we now see darkly through; glory be to God for dappled things.</p>
        <p>Political: the deceptions practiced on a grand scale by public officials, particularly at election time.</p>
        <p>Economic: the use of advertising and public relations to screen consumers from consumerism's unsavory effects.</p>
        <p>Philosophical: the shadows in Plato's cave; the borders between our private worlds and the public realm we share.</p>
        <p>Psychological: mental structures -- denial, desire, dissociation -- that enable us to filter, focus or ignore feelings, knowledge and perceptions.</p>
        <p>The veil design motif brings all these connotations into play.</p>
        <p>With the Apple Power Cube, we see through a glass, darkly, but on the Internet we shall see each other virtually face to face. In advertisements, the Cube is presented as the embodiment of omnipotence and omniscience, an entity whose name we almost dare not utter. The inner and outer enclosures create an ecotone of color, a silver shade generated by the laying of clear plastic over white.</p>
        <p>From the exterior, the Cube is a pure product of what used to be called industrial design. Even its abstract, geometrical shape harks back to the Bauhaus-influenced products displayed in the Good Design shows organized in the 50's by the Museum of Modern Art. The innards, easily removed by means of a handle, represent the increasing miniaturization of information-age technology. The Cube's inner and outer enclosures symbolize an interface between the old and new economies.</p>
        <p>''Silver makes everything disappear,'' Andy Warhol remarked apropos the decor of his 47th Street studio. The tone of the G4 nudges this technology-packed device toward immateriality. So does the silence of its fan-less operation. Perhaps this is not, after all, a machine, but a box of emptiness, a chunk of force-field that has been captured from the event-horizon of a black hole and returned to earth, where its power to warp time, space and gravity has been harnessed to serve consumer needs.</p>
        <p>The Cube plays off against the infinite variety of forms in which other computers come packaged, and the ceaseless abundance of images that materialize on its dematerialized flat screen. The Cube is a rounded-off Platonic solid. Its speakers play the music of the spheres. On the screen -- a veil of pixels -- everything is changing, morphing, mutating, pointillistic. The Cube transcends change.</p>
        <p>Helmut Lang's clothes display the rigor, consistency and playfulness of a philosophical system. But what is the philosophy? Some garments in his new collection have been compared to bondage attire. Featuring strips of cloth, tightly woven around the torso, they could also be seen as resortwear for mummies. Lang himself said his inspiration came from pictures of insects. Both interpretations are true. Fashion is a convention for simultaneously loosening and defining the boundaries between an individual and the social and natural environments in which she moves. It is a form of bondage, but one that the wearer is free to change or discard at any moment. Indeed, part of the bondage of fashion is that the cut and color of the boundaries must be changed as often as possible. They have, at most, an insect's life span.</p>
        <p>Norbert Elias, author of ''The Civilizing Process,'' used the term homo clausus, the conventional sociological image of the individual as a self-contained entity. Just because human organs are contained within the skin, it does not follow that a self is likewise circumscribed. On the contrary, a self is in large part an accumulation of relationships with the world outside the skin, a set of complex interactions with a rich variety of environments that began before birth. In the fashion world, society is an ecotone between a self and the stars. Self-image becomes tantamount to a world view.</p>
        <p>Consider the fashion show. The young woman on the runway is a walking ecotone. We may identify her personality with her appearance, but even her appearance embodies cultural expectations ranging from body type to facial characteristics to the changing image of fashion projected on her by designers of clothes, hair, make-up.</p>
        <p>Then of course there are the conventions of the fashion show itself: lighting, sound, movement, photography, editorial rank and spectatorship. Where does she stop and we start? Perhaps, if it weren't for the straps, the model's self would be very nearly uncontainable. She would dissolve in the glare of flashbulbs, her corporeal presence dissipating ever outward in reproductions transmitted by newspapers, magazines and TV.</p>
        <p>Petra Blaisse makes Christo look like a hobo. Blaisse wraps walls, windows and entire buildings with fabrics and landscapes of great subtlety and strength. Her work, now the subject of a fine show at Storefront for Art and Architecture on Manhattan's Lower East Side, includes projects for private houses, theaters, a convention hall and a men's prison.</p>
        <p>Many of Blaisse's projects were designed in collaboration with Rem Koolhaas. Her curtain for the Nederlands Dans Theater, a composition of metallic discs on black fabric that repeats the grid of stage lights behind, has become the logo for the Koolhaas building in the Hague. For the Rotterdam Kunsthal, Blaisse designed a diagonal terrace of trees that veils the windows. Inside, she conceived a spiral curtain track that transforms a two-dimension wall of fabric into a fluted cloth column.</p>
        <p>The Villa Floirac, designed by Koolhaas for a family in Bordeaux, has become the most celebrated private house of recent times. For it, Blaisse designed a curtain system that allows fabrics to envelop the exterior and interior of the building. An inner curtain of aqua-colored netting covers a plate-glass wall extending the length of the second-floor living room. On the exterior, the owners can deploy a metallic thermal sheet. A screen of thin birch trees extends the effect of veiling into the landscape.</p>
        <p>Koolhaas's architecture, designed for a wheelchair-bound man and his family, is an essay in the interweaving of prospect and refuge. Blaisse's curtains are the warp to the architect's woof. The combination of thermal sheeting, plate glass, aqua netting and birch trees is a vision out of a dream. It reminds us that architecture arises from the ecotone between material and metaphor.</p>
        <p>Apple claims that the Power Cube's minimalist design makes it suitable for any decor. Not true. The little gizmo wants to be enveloped within an environment as basic and translucent as the Cube itself. Specifically, it wants an interior by John Pawson, our leading maestro of light, shadow and void. The British architect, designer of the Calvin Klein store on Madison Avenue, is the subject of ''John Pawson,'' another monograph published by Phaidon this month.  With an illuminating text by Deyan Sudjic,  the book describes the spiritual underpinnings of Pawson's aesthetic.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, Pawson traveled to Japan, lived for a time in a Buddhist monastery and briefly considered becoming a monk.  According to Sudjic, Pawson's design work is still informed by Buddhist beliefs. A central tenet of Japanese Buddhism is the concept of esho funi. Roughly translated as ''the oneness of life and its environment,'' esho funi means that living beings and their surroundings, while different, are two sides of one entity. Buckminster Fuller exhorted his followers to ''Reform the environment, not man.'' Fuller's idea would be unacceptable in Buddhist philosophy.</p>
        <p>Yet architects do design environments. Clients hire them to make agreeable places, not to reform their spiritual lives. The most architects can hope for is a client whose values are sympathetic to their own. Even then, the places created by architects are spatially circumscribed. Even a Buddhist temple may be situated in an unsympathetic milieu, or why would a religion be needed at all? (This is the perpetual Utopian problem.)</p>
        <p>From a Buddhist perspective, the spiritual and the material are also aspects of a single entity. This is why there is no contradiction in the alliance between Pawson and Calvin Klein. The work of both men is aspirational. Klein makes more explicit links between aspiration and desire (for sex, money, fame), but neither is Pawson running a monastery. What links the two, to each other and to the culture at large, is an appreciation for beauty, and a talent for creating real and virtual spaces where beauty shines.</p>
        <p>Some artists and critics like to think of beauty as an incentive to reach toward the good and the true. I agree that art can be part of a philosophical system. But in the consumer society, beauty can also be a smokescreen -- a tool for distracting our attention from the bad and the false, the less savory side of consumerism itself. What a car! What a body! What a cool computer!  Who wants to think about the sweatshop labor, acid rain, social disruption and disease that may be caused by the manufacture or use of these products? In this sense, beauty can be a veil, an invitation to overlook the ugly that we implicitly accept by buying into the system.</p>
        <p>This is the case not only with individual objects. The desire to overlook the ugly is a major factor behind the present infatuation with the design medium as a whole. With that infatuation, consumers -- what used to be called the public -- are giving design enormous authority. Call it a myth, a virus or a mass psychosis. Like any authority, the design phenomenon derives its power from denial. It persuades people to leave unpleasant things out of the picture. A fancy story like this one is an example of denial at work.</p>
        <p>Buildings account for 63 percent of energy consumption and 50 percent of so-called greenhouse gases. Yet I make a living writing about architecture as if it could be separated from this reality. (Smog as veil?) There are many ways to rationalize this practice: if buildings are going to be built, they ought to be good. Science falls outside my sphere of competence. Since my column runs in an arts section, readers would get bored with continuous commentary on solar collectors, the violence of urban development, sick building syndrome and the politics of French social housing.</p>
        <p>SOMETIMES I take the unsavory aspects of architecture into account, the social and cultural as well as the environmental degradation.  But I'm no good as Jeremiah. I write about buildings because I find the flux of urban life aesthetically appealing. I'll go on using the Truth is Beauty trick as long as I can get away with it.</p>
        <p>Buildings, being large and expensive, are typically seen, at a distance, as totems of external authority. In the context of the new economy, they become emblems of the global operating system, allied more closely to similar totems in other cities than to their own towns. The Power Cube, being small and cheap, occupies personal space. For consumers, the stakes here are higher. One can choose to buy another computer. One cannot choose to opt out of the global operating system.</p>
        <p>Your oil company is working hard to protect the environment! It's relatively easy, even accurate, to blame big business for consumerism's sinister effects. The hard task is to reckon with the psychological mechanisms that enable consumers to look the other way. This is the subject tackled by Israel Rosenfield in his dazzling and uncanny new novel ''Freud's Megalomania.'' In the book's fictional last testament by the father of psychoanalysis, Freud argues that the need for self-deception (denial) is far more powerful than the sex or death drives as a motive for human behavior.</p>
        <p>At once a satire and a probing philosophical essay, the book combines a bogus manuscript with footnotes that cite true events from Freud's life along with references to his writings and other psychoanalytic texts.  These are then framed by other fictional devices: an introduction by a fictive editor (Prof. Albert J. Stewart) and a (fictional) postscript by (the real) Anna Freud. The result is an ecotone between two kinds of reality: (subjective) fiction and (objective) fact. The book's intellectual texture resembles a moire: truths about human nature shimmer in the layering of reporting atop invention. Reading it, the mind swivels among similarities and differences, between objective and subjective realities. It occupies a region that cannot be sustained either by reporting and invention alone.</p>
        <p>This is one of the major ideas uncovered by the structure of Rosenfield's book. The mind is dense with veils that float between what we see, what we know, what we believe and how, or whether, we choose to act. What is the value of this? To produce skepticism. To induce doubt. To propose that seeing is not believing.</p>
        <p>Design can perform a similar service. Mau does this. Like Rosenfield, he rubs together different kinds of information. The opaque and and the semitransparent. Picture and text. Focused and blurred. That the mind is given no place to rest. The eye can momentarily alight here or there, only to be quickly drawn away, to a different place on the same plane, or toward an implied zone of great or lesser depth. The effect is equivalent to critical thinking: a constant oscillation between conviction and doubt.</p>
        <p>Pawson, Blaisse and Lang beckon the beholder into a similar frame of mind. Their work simultaneously expresses a given condition and a problem. The condition is that the information age operates as much inside the brain as outside it. The problem is how to clear up mental confusion so as to reach a place of historical and moral awareness. Veils are at once facts to be contemplated and fictions to be pulled aside.</p>
        <p>Even the Power Cube computer, which visually abases itself before the new economy, enlarges the user's capacity to resist as well as to conspire with economic globalization. Computers have made it possible for opponents of the World Bank to contest its trade policies, for example, as organizers of the Seattle protest did earlier this year. The image of power projected by the Cube is ambiguous. Where does the power lie? The Cube's beauty is in the eye of the beholder. Doubt, too, is an individual matter.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE  Correction:  October 22, 2000, Sunday  A picture caption last Sunday with the continuation of a front-page article about the role of design in contemporary culture misstated the location of a Calvin Klein store designed by John Pawson. It is in Seoul, South Korea, not Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 29, 2000, Sunday  An article on Oct. 15 about trends in design and the work of the graphics designer Bruce Mau with Zone Books misspelled the surname of one of the imprint's editors. He is Michel Feher, nor Fehrer. The article omitted the names of two other prominent editors at Zone who have worked with Mr. Mau; they are Hal Foster and Ramona Naddaff. The article also misspelled the surnames of two authors published by Zone. They are the art historian Erwin Panofsky, not Panovsky, and the philosopher Georges Bataille, not Batailles. And the article misspelled the surname of a former editor of I.D., a leading magazine in the field. She is Chee Pearlman, not Perlman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 22, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>A picture caption last Sunday with the continuation of a front-page article about the role of design in contemporary culture misstated the location of a Calvin Klein store designed by John Pawson. It is in Seoul, South Korea, not Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Correction: October 29, 2000, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article on Oct. 15 about trends in design and the work of the graphics designer Bruce Mau with Zone Books misspelled the surname of one of the imprint's editors. He is Michel Feher, nor Fehrer. The article omitted the names of two other prominent editors at Zone who have worked with Mr. Mau; they are Hal Foster and Ramona Naddaff. The article also misspelled the surnames of two authors published by Zone. They are the art historian Erwin Panofsky, not Panovsky, and the philosopher Georges Bataille, not Batailles. And the article misspelled the surname of a former editor of I.D., a leading magazine in the field. She is Chee Pearlman, not Perlman.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
