<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE TREASURY DEPARTMENT -- Man in the News; Industrialist With a Twist -- Paul Henry O'Neill</title>
    <meta content="21ONEI$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/21/politics/21ONEI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kahn, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Paul H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DE1F39F932A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE 43rd PRESIDENT: THE TREASURY DEPARTMENT -- Man in the News; Industrialist With a Twist -- Paul Henry O'Neill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH KAHN with FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kahn, Joseph; Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Man in the News profile of Pres-elect George W Bush's appointee as Commerce Secretary, Paul Henry O'Neill; he was born Dec 4, 1935, and has been chairman of Alcoa since 1987; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Early in his tenure at Alcoa, Paul H. O'Neill faced the sort of public relations crisis that keeps corporate chief executives awake nights.</p>
        <p>The National Wildlife Federation was holding a news conference in Washington to denounce the Pittsburgh aluminum manufacturer as the nation's single worst polluter.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Early in his tenure at Alcoa, Paul H. O'Neill faced the sort of public relations crisis that keeps corporate chief executives awake nights.</p>
        <p>The National Wildlife Federation was holding a news conference in Washington to denounce the Pittsburgh aluminum manufacturer as the nation's single worst polluter.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill slipped into the news conference and, after the complaint was read, stormed the dais to respond to what he called a ''scurrilous attack on our integrity.'' Alcoa adheres to all government environmental codes, he argued, and the group had facts wrong. The stunt captured as many headlines as the environmental group's accusations.</p>
        <p>When President-elect George W. Bush named Mr. O'Neill today as his treasury secretary, he selected a man who is a prototypical Republican, a punctilious budget expert who has served Presidents Richard M. Nixon, Gerald R. Ford, Ronald Reagan and Mr. Bush's father, and a captain of old-line industry who dines in Pittsburgh's Duquesne Club and inspects Alcoa's far-flung properties on the company's corporate jet.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. O'Neill is also a bit of a maverick. He has taken positions on global warming, energy taxes, education, Social Security and health care that are decidedly nonpartisan and, in a few cases, seemingly un-Republican.</p>
        <p>He also remade Alcoa, a struggling rust-belt company when he assumed control 13 years ago, into the best performing stock in the Dow Jones industrial average last year with an energetic and occasionally quirky focus on international expansion, workplace safety and open-plan architecture.</p>
        <p>No lavish corner office for him. In the new headquarters he helped design in Pittsburgh, he works in a cubicle and holds meetings in Alcoa's kitchen.</p>
        <p>''This is a man who simply delights in challenging conventional wisdom,'' said Tim Wirth, the former Colorado senator, a Democrat who has known Mr. O'Neill for 30 years.</p>
        <p>As treasury secretary, Mr. O'Neill, who is 65 and bears a passing resemblance to Harry S. Truman, will be the new administration's senior economic policymaker at a time when the stock market is tumbling and the economy is slowing abruptly, threatening the decade-long expansion.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill will play a sizable role in designing and implementing the president-elect's economic strategy, including the sweeping tax cuts Mr. Bush proposed on the campaign trail and the introduction of private investment accounts for Social Security. He will also serve as the administration's ambassador to Wall Street and its diplomatic liaison with foreign financial leaders.</p>
        <p>Though he is not an investment banker like Robert E. Rubin or an academic whiz like Lawrence H. Summers, Mr. Clinton's former and current treasury secretaries, his supporters are confident that Mr. O'Neill accomplishes at least one prerequisite for the post. He sends a relatively reassuring message that American economic policy is in experienced, if little-known, hands.</p>
        <p>''In Paul O'Neill, the president-elect has attracted an exceptional and talented person,'' said Alan Greenspan, the Federal Reserve chairman, who met Mr. O'Neill when both worked in the Ford administration.</p>
        <p>But Mr. O'Neill also seems to relish a good fight over policy, and that makes him a wild card in a Bush cabinet.</p>
        <p>The two men met for the first time five years ago at an education conference in New Jersey, where Mr. Bush was attending as Texas' new governor and Mr. O'Neill attended with Tom Ridge, the Pennsylvania governor who named the executive to lead an education task force in his state. On education, Mr. O'Neill's drive to institute unified testing standards for Pennsylvania meshed well with Mr. Bush's own education initiatives in Texas.</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill also reflected Bush priorities when he staked out an aggressive position against President Clinton's health care initiative in 1993 and 1994. During Alcoa's annual meeting in 1994, he called Mr. Clinton's proposal for universal health care an ''empty box'' that would do ''irreparable harm'' to the nation.</p>
        <p>But just as often, he has displayed an independent streak. He reached out to labor, for example, ending Alcoa's sometimes adversarial relationship with its union, the United Steelworkers of America. Together with George Becker, the Steelworkers president with whom he became friends, Mr. O'Neill devised a new model of collective bargaining, helping produce a research paper on the subject that the Steelworkers union circulated to other corporate executives.</p>
        <p>''This man would make a great treasury secretary in any administration, Democratic or Republican,''  Mr. Becker said.</p>
        <p>Despite his earlier spat with Mr. Clinton, Mr. O'Neill later attended White House sessions with the president to discuss how best to fight global warming, signaling greater concern about the issue than Mr. Bush has shown to date.</p>
        <p>In 1990, breaking decisively with fellow corporate executives, Mr. O'Neill made a public push to persuade Mr. Bush's father to slap a $10 per barrel tax on the price of oil as a way of reducing energy use, protecting the environment, and helping close the budget deficit. The tax would have added about 40 cents a gallon to the price of gasoline.</p>
        <p>That stance is precisely opposite the position held by the president-elect, who wants to cut taxes and concentrate on finding new supplies of oil, not reducing its use.</p>
        <p>But aides to Mr. Bush said Mr. O'Neill was well aware that in his new role his job will be to support Mr. Bush's agenda.</p>
        <p>After being introduced today by Mr. Bush, Mr. O'Neill acknowledged his reputation for outspokenness and pledged to check the impulse to hold forth on his personal views.</p>
        <p>The days of being ''a free-ranging, self-admitted maverick'' are over, Mr. O'Neill said. ''That was yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Paul Henry O'Neill was born on Dec. 4, 1935, in St. Louis. He has a bachelor's degree in economics from Fresno State College in California and a master's degree in public administration from Indiana University. He began working as a computer systems analyst at the Department of Veterans Affairs in 1961. He later moved to the Office of Management and Budget in the White House, where he worked until 1977, serving Presidents Nixon and Ford.</p>
        <p>It was there that Mr. O'Neill became a budget wizard, people who worked with him said. But his expertise went beyond the green-eyeshade kind; he also fashioned himself as a student of federalism, the balance between conservative visions of slashing the government and the liberal drive to increase Washington's role in social initiatives.</p>
        <p>Suzanne Woolsey, who worked with him at the budget office and who now works at the National Academy of Sciences, said Mr. O'Neill ''virtually invented'' block grants, federal matching funds for state programs. Block grants allow the central government to play a role in local policy without smothering it.</p>
        <p>At that time Mr. O'Neill also met Dick Cheney, then Mr. Ford's chief of staff. The two stayed in touch over the years, and Bush supporters said that Mr. Cheney was Mr. O'Neill's most concerted advocate in the Bush camp. Though he has not been a major donor to the Republican Party, Mr. O'Neill gave $5,000 to Mr. Cheney's political action committee in 1994, records show.</p>
        <p>As a corporate executive, Mr. O'Neill proved a skillful player in Washington. In 1993, he helped broker a compromise under which Russia agreed to stop dumping aluminum onto world markets in return for loans to modernize its industry. The agreement obviated the need for punitive trade sanctions on Russia's new government.</p>
        <p>''It's typical that the industry people come in foaming at the mouth about the need for sanctions,'' said W. Bowman Cutter, a Clinton administration economic official at the time. ''Paul was totally balanced. He saw both sides and worked for a principled solution that made sense for everybody.''</p>
        <p>In the competitive world of metals, Mr. O'Neill is recognized for revamping Alcoa's inventory control, accounting systems and manufacturing processes, so that the company's profits and cash flow soared. Before he took over, it took Alcoa 40 days to get aluminum plates for airplane wings through an inspection process; Mr. O'Neill whittled that to four days. The company is typically among the first to release its earnings each quarter, in good part because the financial systems Mr. O'Neill installed enabled its finance people to close their books quickly.</p>
        <p>By well-timed acquisitions he turned Alcoa into a huge global player. In 1998, for example, Alcoa purchased Inespal, Spain's nationalized aluminum industry, for $410 million.</p>
        <p>''He bought assets worth $4 billion for essentially 10 cents on the dollar,'' said R. Wayne Atwell, an analyst with Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, which advised the Spanish government. ''Spain wanted a higher price, so he waited until they came down. And he made the best acquisition I've seen in the aluminum business in 20 years.''</p>
        <p>Mr. O'Neill has grown extremely wealthy at Alcoa. In 1999, the year he stepped down as chief executive but stayed on as chairman of the board, he was paid $2.95 million in salary and bonus.</p>
        <p>As of this spring, Alcoa reported that Mr. O'Neill owned 1.6 million shares of Alcoa, worth $50 million at today's Alcoa closing price of $31.44 per share, and had options to buy another 4.6 million shares at varying prices well below the current level.  The most recent options grant, allowing the purchase of 1.4 million shares at $21.05 per share, would be worth $14.5 million at Alcoa's current price.</p>
        <p>Alcoa's options plan, unlike many in corporate America, allows recipients to exercise all of the options after one year. Since his last options grant came in January 1999, Mr. O'Neill is free to exercise all his options before he takes office if he is confirmed as treasury secretary.</p>
        <p>That is in contrast to the situation faced by Mr. Cheney, who owns options in Halliburton, the energy company he formerly served as chief executive, that cannot be exercised before he takes office. He has indicated that he would forfeit the benefits from those options.</p>
        <p>Profile  Paul Henry O'Neill</p>
        <p>Born: Dec. 4, 1935, St. Louis</p>
        <p>Hometown: Pittsburgh</p>
        <p>Education: B.A., Fresno State College; M.P.A., Indiana University.</p>
        <p>Career Highlights: Site engineer, Morrison-Knudsen, 1955-57; systems analyst, Veterans Administration, 1961-66; assistant director, associate director and deputy director, Office of Management and Budget, 1967-77; vice president, senior vice president, president, International Paper Company, 1977-87; chairman, Alcoa, 1987-present; chairman and chief executive, Alcoa, 1987-98.</p>
        <p>Family: Married to Nancy Jo Wolfe; three daughters, one son.</p>
        <p>Hobbies: Painting  (Source: Associated Press)(pg. A35)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
