<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Excerpts From the Vice President's Speech on Energy Policy</title>
    <meta content="Y28GTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210938"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E5D81030F93BA15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Excerpts From the Vice President's Speech on Energy Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, June 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Vice Pres Gore's campaign speech on energy policy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Vice President Al Gore's speech today on energy policy, as released by his campaign:</p>
        <p>All of you who drove to work today know that the cost of gasoline is simply too high for America's working families. In the first part of this year, oil company profits increased nearly 500 percent. That's why I've called for a federal investigation of concentration, noncompetitiveness and pricing practices in the oil industry. Now that the investigation has started, I would like to call for public hearings so the voices of American consumers can be heard.</p>
        <p>But now is also the time to recognize that the challenge we face is even broader than soaring gasoline prices. We see the same underlying problem in our aging power systems that are becoming less reliable. And we see it in the old engines and power plants that waste so much energy and in doing so create way too much pollution that makes our air unhealthy, and our world warmer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from Vice President Al Gore's speech today on energy policy, as released by his campaign:</p>
        <p>All of you who drove to work today know that the cost of gasoline is simply too high for America's working families. In the first part of this year, oil company profits increased nearly 500 percent. That's why I've called for a federal investigation of concentration, noncompetitiveness and pricing practices in the oil industry. Now that the investigation has started, I would like to call for public hearings so the voices of American consumers can be heard.</p>
        <p>But now is also the time to recognize that the challenge we face is even broader than soaring gasoline prices. We see the same underlying problem in our aging power systems that are becoming less reliable. And we see it in the old engines and power plants that waste so much energy and in doing so create way too much pollution that makes our air unhealthy, and our world warmer.</p>
        <p>But we don't have to accept a future of more pollution. We don't have to accept a future where kids and grandparents have to stay indoors on a muggy day, and where the days themselves get muggier still.</p>
        <p>Here's the good news: we have the means and the technology to meet all these challenges. . . .</p>
        <p>Today, I'm proposing a new Energy Security and Environment Trust, a bold and unprecedented commitment to achieve an even more prosperous economy, powered by cleaner, more reliable energy, in a healthy, truly livable environment.</p>
        <p>First, we will modernize and improve our nation's power systems, to prevent future power outages before they affect you and your family. We will ensure reliable and affordable electricity by providing new incentives to industry to improve our power lines. And we will give special incentives to companies that want to use their own, more efficient power systems on-site, or use renewable energy, such as wind or solar power.</p>
        <p>Second, we will do more to protect our kids and our parents from the smog and soot that cause asthma.</p>
        <p>One of the best ways we can do this is by giving new incentives to industry to transform dirty old power plants into modern, clean sources of energy. For that, we will need enforceable, market-based standards that are comprehensive instead of piecemeal. And we need to end monopolies, and instead let competition bring us clean energy and smaller energy bills.</p>
        <p>We are blessed with abundant supplies of coal, petroleum and natural gas; we have to use these resources wisely.</p>
        <p>With new technology, we can make all our energy sources cleaner, safer and healthier for our families. We will bring together the best minds from the private sector and create an open competition to design the best incentives for old power plants and industries to change, to improve, to modernize and move ahead.</p>
        <p>Through the power of free markets, we will take a dramatic step forward for our children's health, which will also be a dramatic new step toward a stable climate.</p>
        <p>Third, while we modernize our power systems and reduce pollution here at home, we must aggressively pursue the global market for new energy technology that is expected to reach $10 trillion in the next two decades, as other countries also take steps to overcome pollution and the threat of global warming.</p>
        <p>As the world implements the Kyoto treaty, we must ensure that all developed and developing nations do their part.</p>
        <p>Fourth, as we reduce America's dependence on big oil and imported oil for the long term by finding new and better ways to produce clean, affordable, and reliable energy here in America we will work even more closely with industry and labor to bring cleaner cars, trucks and buses to showrooms and streets around the world.</p>
        <p>This is a multi-hundred-billion-dollar industry; we've got to seize the lead, before Japan or any nation beats us to it.</p>
        <p>Fifth, we will cut taxes so families can start buying those 100-mile-per-gallon cars as they hit the showrooms. Even the best innovations are of little use if they are stuck in a lab, unaffordable and unattainable to you, your family or your business. But tax credits can make them competitive, and then mass production will bring the prices down even further.</p>
        <p>We will also give tax credits so that it is not far-reaching fantasy to put a solar roof on your home, or to renovate your home to make it more energy efficient, but an affordable and money-saving practicality.</p>
        <p>We will also make major new investments in light rail and mass transit, to make your neighborhoods more livable and to liberate families from having to buy gas at any price, if they'd really prefer not to.</p>
        <p>Finally, we will do more than use the technologies of the future; we as a nation will aggressively invest in the skill and creativity of the people who discover them, and the factory workers who produce them.</p>
        <p>There will be no new bureaucracies; no new agencies or organizations, because the era of old government is over. We'll measure performance carefully and ensure that we reach our goals with common-sense standards.</p>
        <p>But it is America's innovators and entrepreneurs, investors and working men and women who will forge the real solutions, not the federal government.</p>
        <p>I know these challenges are not easy. And for me, they have never been without controversy. But my commitment to the environment has always run deeper than politics. We have to do what's right for our earth because it is the moral thing to do.</p>
        <p>It involves all of our lives, from the simple security of having safe, reliable, affordable electricity for your home; to America's ability to keep building and selling the best new cars, trucks, and technology to the world; to guarding our children from the summer smog that is made worse by global warming, and securing for our grandchildren the expectation of a joyful array of seasons that we took for granted when we grew up ourselves.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
