<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Swiss Voters Reject Limit On Number of Foreigners</title>
    <meta content="Y25SWI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/25/world/25SWIS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1233647"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Switzerland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olson, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Switzerland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DE143AF936A1575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Swiss Voters Reject Limit On Number of Foreigners</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH OLSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olson, Elizabeth</byline>
      <dateline>GENEVA, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Swiss voters reject proposal to impose constitutional limit on percentage of foreigners in country, apparently heeding government warnings that it risked harming economy and ties with rest of Europe (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Swiss voters rejected a proposal today to impose a constitutional limit on the percentage of foreigners in their country, apparently heeding government warnings that it risked harming the economy and ties with the rest of Europe.</p>
        <p>The proposal would have set a ceiling of 18 percent on the number of foreigners in this country of 7.2 million people.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Swiss voters rejected a proposal today to impose a constitutional limit on the percentage of foreigners in their country, apparently heeding government warnings that it risked harming the economy and ties with the rest of Europe.</p>
        <p>The proposal would have set a ceiling of 18 percent on the number of foreigners in this country of 7.2 million people.</p>
        <p>Over all, more than 63 percent voted against the measure, which had been proposed by center-right groups seeking to close Switzerland's borders to ''unqualified'' workers and to many refugees. Despite the relief in official Switzerland, which had fretted that a yes vote would have harmed the country's tourist-dependent image, there was concern over the relatively large vote in favor of the measure.</p>
        <p>The vote had been closely watched because of rising xenophobic sentiments in Europe, which have increased under the flood of refugees seeking to flee wartorn regions, especially the countries that were once part of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Resentment here against refugees from Kosovo and, earlier, Bosnia helped secure surprising electoral gains a year ago for the right-wing Swiss People's Party, which campaigned against reported abuses by asylum seekers.</p>
        <p>The success, and inclusion in the government, of the anti-immigrant Freedom Party in Austria revealed the fears of an aging European population that national identities were being eroded. The Swiss measure's opponents worried that this sentiment might be strong enough to win a majority of Swiss voters, even though they have rejected similar  restrictions a half dozen times in past decades.</p>
        <p>Not counting diplomats and workers for international agencies and some other excepted categories,  Switzerland's population is now 19.3 percent foreign.</p>
        <p>The percentage of foreigners is much higher in the French-speaking part of the country; they make up one-third of Geneva's population, for instance. As expected, though, that area rebuffed the measure.</p>
        <p>But the mostly German-speaking cantons in the eastern part of the country that have the biggest influx of people from the former Yugoslavia had larger proportions favorable to the ceiling. The narrowest defeat came in the central state of Schwyz, where 51.6 percent voted against the measure. No canton approved it.</p>
        <p>To be passed, the proposal would have required a majority both of voters and of the 26 cantons.</p>
        <p>The measure's supporters began collecting signatures to put it on the ballot shortly after Bosnian refugees began to arrive in the early 1990's, coinciding with the beginning a decade of economic doldrums in Switzerland. Supporters insisted that barriers needed to be erected against  the loss of Swiss jobs to cheap labor.</p>
        <p>One organizer, Philipp Muller, denied accusations that the measure was racist and said he hoped that the vote would force an overhaul of immigration policies. The government already has proposed new laws that would limit the numbers of workers from countries outside the European Union and better integrate foreigners into Swiss life.</p>
        <p>But there was some concern that the nearly 40 percent support for the measure represented a deeply disgruntled segment of Swiss. ''The vote shows that the government must take these people's views into consideration,'' argued another organizer for the measure, Luzi Stamm. He said much of the support for the measure had come from blue-collar workers who feared losing  their jobs.</p>
        <p>But Swiss companies argued that closing borders would prevent recruiting for people with specialized skills. With unemployment at 1.8 percent last month, the lowest since 1992, companies are looking outside the country for workers.</p>
        <p>The proposed cap would have counted European Union citizens as foreigners, which also would have jeopardized agreements the Swiss just approved with the 15-nation union.</p>
        <p>In the voting today, a series of proposals to encourage renewable energy were also defeated, even though Switzerland, like other European countries, has seen increases in gasoline and heating oil prices.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
