<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Modern Design Remains Faithful to Its Context</title>
    <meta content="06MUSC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1220306"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lever House (Manhattan)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Office Buildings and Other Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leatherbarrow, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Childs, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Muschamp, Herbert</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Uncommon Ground (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000806T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE4DD113DF935A3575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1549" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Modern Design Remains Faithful to Its Context</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MUSCHAMP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Muschamp, Herbert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbert Muschamp reviews book Uncommon Ground by Thomas Leatherbarrow, on modern architectural form; offers examples, including David Childs's restoration of New York City's Lever House, of how modern architects take landscape into account; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN the absence of alternatives, there may be no more important project under way in New York right now than David Childs's restoration of Lever House, the International Style skyscraper on Park Avenue at 54th Street. Designed by Gordon Bunshaft and completed in 1952, Lever House was the first glass curtain wall tower to rise in New York. It remains among the 20th century's major landmarks.</p>
        <p>Lever House established Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill as the most progressive firm in the postwar United States. Along with the Seagram Building, the Guggenheim Museum, the CBS Building and the United Nations headquarters, it helped make New York the leading city for architectural innovation in those years. Mr. Childs became chairman of S.O.M. in 1990. His homage to Bunshaft is no mere sentimental journey. The restoration, due for completion this fall, is uncovering qualities that are becoming valued in architecture once again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN the absence of alternatives, there may be no more important project under way in New York right now than David Childs's restoration of Lever House, the International Style skyscraper on Park Avenue at 54th Street. Designed by Gordon Bunshaft and completed in 1952, Lever House was the first glass curtain wall tower to rise in New York. It remains among the 20th century's major landmarks.</p>
        <p>Lever House established Skidmore, Owings &amp; Merrill as the most progressive firm in the postwar United States. Along with the Seagram Building, the Guggenheim Museum, the CBS Building and the United Nations headquarters, it helped make New York the leading city for architectural innovation in those years. Mr. Childs became chairman of S.O.M. in 1990. His homage to Bunshaft is no mere sentimental journey. The restoration, due for completion this fall, is uncovering qualities that are becoming valued in architecture once again.</p>
        <p>''Uncommon Ground,'' a book by Thomas Leatherbarrow, should help admirers of modern architecture to form a more precisely analytic appreciation of those qualities. Mr. Leatherbarrow, a professor of architecture at the University of Pennsylvania, also provides a key for interpreting contemporary work, including recent projects by Mr. Childs, Rafael Vinoly and Peter Eisenman.</p>
        <p>The book, due in October from M.I.T. Press, is a revisionist work. It corrects the distorted view that modern architects were insensitive to the physical context of their buildings. Focusing on projects by Richard Neutra and two less well-known figures, Antonin Raymond and Aris Konstantinidis, Mr. Leatherbarrow shows that modernists did not regard building sites simply as blank slates for inscribing their fantasies of a uniform, technological society.</p>
        <p>Further, he contests the notion that modern architects were latter-day Vandals, intent on shattering the cultural continuity of regional and urban life. Rather, the best of them adapted industrial building techniques to the lay of the land. Modern design mediated between prefabricated construction and local topography. It reconciled the homogenizing nature of modernity with regional differences. Its aim was to prevent the shattering of continuity in the industrialized world, not to accelerate it.</p>
        <p>In other words, Frank Lloyd Wright and Luis Barragan were not the only architects who took landscape into account. Architects like Neutra regarded the city as an evolving topography in which landscape and successive layers of built form intersected over time.</p>
        <p>But why use past tense? The International Research Institute for Climate Prediction at Columbia University's Lamont-Doherty Earth Observatory, completed earlier this year, perfectly illustrates Mr. Leatherbarrow's ideas. Designed by Vinoly, the institute is the most sensitively sited building I've visited since Tod Williams and Billie Tsien's Neurosciences Institute in La Jolla, Calif. Both are science buildings. Both command impressive natural, partially urbanized sites. Both embody a conception of science as the culture of nature.</p>
        <p>Vinoly's project is in Palisades, N.Y., on a cliff-top site on the west side of the Hudson. The institute's design is as serenely elegant as its name is clunky. Almost Wrightian in its relationship to the landscape, the institute is composed of two arc-shaped wings that overlap at the center, forming a double-width lobby area at the building's entrance. The roof is also designed as two pairs of overlapping arcs. A clerestory between the arcs illuminates the corridor that bisects the full length of the building's interior.</p>
        <p>Mr. Leatherbarrow writes that the modern relationship between construction and topography is best seen in section (a cutaway drawing), rather than in plan (from above) or elevation (from outside). The institute's central corridor offers a walk through this idea. The ground on which the building sits slopes gradually down toward the north. The land has not been leveled off. This is translated into the interior by flights of steps that break the corridor into segments.</p>
        <p>Materials and exposed structure further integrate construction and site. The corridor runs beneath an arcade of wood bow trusses that support the roof and create an outside-in impression of trees. Internal office windows, facing into the corridor, pull light and views into the core. Bearing walls are made from the same local stone that erupts in boulders from the ground outside. The arcs of the wings and the metal roof echo contours of land and water.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Leatherbarrow, the conflict between technological progress and cultural continuity exists only in theory, not in the real world of architecture. Vinoly's building proves the point. The Palisades were formed 200 million years ago. One of the functions of the climate research institute is to monitor the global warming that could result in their submersion. Try that on for continuity.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, in a review of Peter Eisenman's design for the Staten Island Institute of Arts and Sciences, I wrote that Eisenman's buildings should be seen as links between the history of places and the history of ideas. At the site of a recent design for a hotel on the Friedrichstrasse in Berlin, these two histories already run closely parallel. The Hotel am Spree Dreieck is a homage to two unbuilt Berlin projects designed by Mies van der Rohe in 1921 and 1922. The two projects were Mies's first explorations of the glass tower, a type that culminated in the completion of the Seagram Building 37 years later. Eisenman's plan, situated on the exact spot of Mies's 1921 project (no site was designated for the 1922 project), takes the International Style tower back to its Expressionist roots.</p>
        <p>In 1921, Mies had yet to rationally integrate steel construction into his skyscraper aesthetic. His Berlin towers were as much Expressionist as they were modern. Eisenman has essentially reversed the course of Mies's later development. His design uses a scientific technique to arrive at an Expressionist result. The design was generated by computer. Mies's two Berlin designs were loaded into the software and morphed into a single, composite structure.</p>
        <p>The hotel combines the three-pointed star configuration of Mies's 1921 ground plan with the biomorphic contours of his 1922 scheme. The result is indescribably sexy. As with Mies's projects, the hotel's most prominent feature is the floor planes, stacked one above the other like a theatrical multiplex of urban stages. It's peek-a-boo time, not only for the hotel guests, but also for Berlin and for Mies, its greatest 20th-century architect. The irrational within the rationalist stands exposed. Eisenman's site is the history of modern architecture and of the role Berlin played in it before Hitler came to power.</p>
        <p>THE most conspicuous feature of the Lever House restoration is the repair of the glass curtain wall. The spandrel glass, originally a uniform green, had become a random two-tone mix. But the restoration should also open our eyes to the fact that Bunshaft's design involved more than wrapping a pretty skin around some steel and concrete. The building's importance lies with the integral relationship between skin, structure and site. At Lever House, skin and section are one.</p>
        <p>The stretch of International Style towers along Park Avenue south of 59th Street has been criticized for destroying Park Avenue's sense of place. Precisely the opposite is true. The towers revealed a deeper sense of place than the masonry buildings that preceded them. Park Avenue is a feat of engineering: a viaduct for cars suspended over the train tracks that run beneath. The machine aesthetic of the towers raises this infrastructural dimension above the ground.</p>
        <p>The exposed columns of Lever House punch through the thin crust of sidewalk and convey the impression of stilts straddling the subterranean tracks. The window mullions extend that vertical thrust to the skyline. The tower's floating base and stacked floor planes reveal that New York is a horizontal as well as a vertical city. Each floor replicates the slice of ground beneath it.</p>
        <p>Apart from the advantage it takes of sunlight, Lever House does not reflect the natural topography of Manhattan. Rather, the design adapts construction to the artificial topography of a city that has evolved over time. Lever House itself is part of the city's accretive nature. So is its restoration. Half a century after its completion, we see the building with fresh eyes.</p>
        <p>When new, Lever House was received as a sign of progress, socially and aesthetically. Office workers benefited from the natural light and the clear, open spaces. The city gained from being among the first to realize the utopian ideal visualized by Mies and other modernists. These qualities are still evident. But they are enriched by our awareness of a psychological dimension underlying the modern forms. Park Avenue is a CAT scan of New York's collective brain: our ambition, our exhibitionism, our compulsion to build platforms for our ideas. The city is more upfront about these urges than it was 50 years ago. In that sense, Lever House can stand for progress still.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
