<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Antarctic Test Raises Hope On a Global-Warming Gas</title>
    <meta content="Y12IRO$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/12/science/12IRON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Iron (Nutrient)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Antarctic Regions</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pacific Ocean</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Polar Regions/Antarctic Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carbon Dioxide</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diet and Nutrition</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001012T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D9173FF931A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Antarctic Test Raises Hope On a Global-Warming Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Researchers find that dispersing small amounts of iron in biologically barren seas near Antarctica produces large blooms of tiny plants that pull carbon dioxide, important greenhouse gas, out of air; say process, earlier demonstrated in relatively barren tropical Pacific, is far more significant for issues related to climate in cold southern seas; describe work in journal Nature; say it is too soon to start large-scale iron-seending efforts, citing oceans' complex ecology and chemistry; say effort, at best, could absorb only small part of carbon dioxide in atmosphere (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bolstering the theory that iron is a vital -- and often missing -- link binding the atmosphere, oceans and climate, scientists have found that dispersing small amounts of the metal in biologically barren seas near Antarctica produces large blooms of tiny plants that pull an important greenhouse gas, carbon dioxide, out of the air.</p>
        <p>The process, which some researchers call the Geritol effect, had already been demonstrated in the tropical Pacific, which is also relatively barren, but the findings in the cold southern seas are potentially far more significant for issues related to climate, scientists say. That is because the chilled surface waters of the southern ocean sink to great depths, where they can remain for centuries. Thus plants that take up the carbon dioxide would theoretically sink to the ocean bottom, purging the atmosphere of some of the heat-trapping carbon dioxide that has accumulated from human activities like burning fossil fuels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bolstering the theory that iron is a vital -- and often missing -- link binding the atmosphere, oceans and climate, scientists have found that dispersing small amounts of the metal in biologically barren seas near Antarctica produces large blooms of tiny plants that pull an important greenhouse gas, carbon dioxide, out of the air.</p>
        <p>The process, which some researchers call the Geritol effect, had already been demonstrated in the tropical Pacific, which is also relatively barren, but the findings in the cold southern seas are potentially far more significant for issues related to climate, scientists say. That is because the chilled surface waters of the southern ocean sink to great depths, where they can remain for centuries. Thus plants that take up the carbon dioxide would theoretically sink to the ocean bottom, purging the atmosphere of some of the heat-trapping carbon dioxide that has accumulated from human activities like burning fossil fuels.</p>
        <p>In an experiment, conducted last year between Tasmania and Antarctica, researchers confirmed that vast, desertlike stretches of the world's southern oceans are primed to explode with photosynthesis but lack only iron, one of the most abundant substances elsewhere on earth.</p>
        <p>But the researchers, who described their work in today's issue of the journal Nature, said it was too soon to start large-scale iron-seeding efforts because the new experiment raised as many questions as it answered about the complex ecology and chemistry of the oceans. Moreover, at best, they said, it would only absorb a small amount of the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.</p>
        <p>Also, they noted, the experimental  bloom of plankton was not tracked long enough to assess whether the carbon harvested from the air sank into the deep sea or was released once again in carbon dioxide gas.</p>
        <p>''There are still fundamental scientific questions that need to be addressed before anyone can responsibly promote iron fertilization as a climate control tactic,'' said Dr. Kenneth H. Coale, an oceanographer who helped design the earlier studies of iron's effects in the tropical Pacific.</p>
        <p>But in research using computer models incorporating the results from the fertilization effort, Dr. Andrew J. Watson, a geochemist at the University of East Anglia in Norwich, England, found that the effect was consistent with changes seen in past periods of geological history when large amounts of iron dust blown from the continents enriched the southern seas, causing plankton blooms that appear to have reduced carbon dioxide levels in the air.</p>
        <p>The response of ocean waters to the infusion of iron far exceeded predictions, several of the authors said.</p>
        <p>The team estimated that releasing three and a half tons of dissolved iron over about 30 square miles of sea caused a tenfold rise in the amount of phytoplankton. Monitored by satellite, the patch eventually stretched out into a J-shaped filament that covered 660 square miles, pulling perhaps several thousand tons of carbon dioxide from the air in the process, said Dr. Rob Murdoch, the research director for New Zealand's National Institute of Water and Atmospheric Research, which was one of the groups involved in the project.</p>
        <p>The bloom persisted for more than six weeks, while the previous blooms created in the tropics dissipated in half that time, Dr. Murdoch said.</p>
        <p>He said this finding suggested the need for caution in using the technique. ''We don't know a heck of a lot about this pristine environment down there,'' Dr. Murdoch said.</p>
        <p>Over all, the scientists involved in the experiment said they calculated that iron-feeding, even if the entire southern ocean was used, would probably remove no more than several hundred million tons of carbon dioxide from the air each year, a far cry from the five billion tons or so entering the air each year from industries, vehicles and other sources.</p>
        <p>But several companies are already making plans to fertilize the sea with iron, both to attack global warming and to stimulate fisheries.</p>
        <p>And the United States Department of Energy is considering partially underwriting a proposal from the University of Hawaii and an American company, Greensea Ventures, to conduct a larger test of the iron-fertilizing process in the ocean west of the Galapagos Islands.</p>
        <p>In an independent commentary accompanying the Nature reports, Dr. Sallie W. Chisolm, a plankton expert at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, said the researchers had not answered the most important questions -- including, for example, identifying the final fate of the carbon dioxide absorbed by the plankton. Dr. Chisolm concluded that industrial-scale use of the technique was likely to backfire.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
