<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Cost of Keeping Gore's Promises</title>
    <meta content="22BART$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3DA1E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Cost of Keeping Gore's Promises</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bruce Bartlett</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is no doubt that the Clinton-Gore administration's proudest economic accomplishment was balancing the federal budget. Al Gore would like voters to trust him as the guardian of that legacy and of the surplus that has replaced the deficits of the 1980's and early 1990's. Hence, in his campaign, he makes much of his plans to use more of projected surpluses for paying down the national debt than would George W. Bush. Mr. Gore also talks a great deal about the ''cost'' of Mr. Bush's proposed tax cut.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore's spending proposals also carry costs. One estimate, by the National Taxpayers Union, puts the dollar size of Mr. Gore's new spending  at more than $2 trillion over 10 years -- enough to take up the entire non-Social Security surplus without anything left over for tax cuts. (Both candidates rule out spending the portion of the surplus attributable to Social Security.) Even the lowest estimates in the press put the figure at well over $1 trillion, with Mr. Gore's tax cuts reducing the surplus by an additional $500 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is no doubt that the Clinton-Gore administration's proudest economic accomplishment was balancing the federal budget. Al Gore would like voters to trust him as the guardian of that legacy and of the surplus that has replaced the deficits of the 1980's and early 1990's. Hence, in his campaign, he makes much of his plans to use more of projected surpluses for paying down the national debt than would George W. Bush. Mr. Gore also talks a great deal about the ''cost'' of Mr. Bush's proposed tax cut.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore's spending proposals also carry costs. One estimate, by the National Taxpayers Union, puts the dollar size of Mr. Gore's new spending  at more than $2 trillion over 10 years -- enough to take up the entire non-Social Security surplus without anything left over for tax cuts. (Both candidates rule out spending the portion of the surplus attributable to Social Security.) Even the lowest estimates in the press put the figure at well over $1 trillion, with Mr. Gore's tax cuts reducing the surplus by an additional $500 billion.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Gore's initiatives are of a kind that could all too easily lead to a return of deficits if the budget surpluses don't materialize as planned. He makes more proposals than Mr. Bush for entitlements -- programs that continue without annual appropriations. True, Mr. Bush's $1.6 trillion tax cut would also be written into law as continuing indefinitely. But history shows that presidents and Congresses are far more willing to raise taxes in the event of a revenue shortfall than they are to cut entitlements.</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Gore's and Mr. Bush's plans would reduce the surplus by an equivalent amount, assuming that they both got their way with Congress and kept all of their promises -- something that is of course unlikely. Because presidents cannot enact programs on their own, voters know they must look at the candidates' proposals not only at face value, but also as an indication of their differing philosophies of government. In this respect, there is a clear division between Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore believes that government should direct and control the use of the surplus that is not allocated to debt reduction, whether on the tax side or the spending side. He would increase government spending substantially more than Mr. Bush, would cut taxes less, and would aim more of his tax cuts to specific taxpayer behavior -- giving parents a credit to pay for their children's after-school programs, for example. It is fair to characterize most of Mr. Gore's proposed tax cuts as little different substantively from direct spending, except that they go through the tax code rather than the appropriations process.</p>
        <p>By contrast, Mr. Bush would ''spend'' more of the surplus on across-the-board tax cuts. Moreover, most of his reductions, in contrast to Mr. Gore's, would not depend on taxpayers' behavior, but would be given to all of them in the form of rate decreases. Cutting taxes allows people to keep more of their money, so that they decide, rather than the government, how to apportion it. Some may invest their savings, and some may spend it, but either way it will be the taxpayer's decision, not the government's.</p>
        <p>And since the economic stimulus from tax rate reductions is greater than that from new spending or targeted tax cuts, the net budgetary cost of Mr. Bush's proposals would likely be considerably less than the gross figure Mr. Gore alludes to.</p>
        <p>Finally, the cost of a presidential candidate's program cannot be measured solely in terms of its impact on the budget. Many initiatives could impose large costs on the private sector in the form of regulations. In this area, too, Mr. Gore's ideas would seem the costlier. His plans regarding global warming and health maintenance organizations, for example, would have substantial costs for business.</p>
        <p>The question of whose program costs more is important, but the ''costs'' of federal policies go beyond direct revenue lost or money spent. The effect on the economy as a whole (and with it, future tax collections) can be profound, and that is where the deep philosophical differences of Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush come seriously into play.</p>
        <p>Bruce Bartlett, a senior fellow with the National Center for Policy Analysis, was a deputy assistant treasury secretary in the Reagan and Bush administrations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bruce Bartlett, a senior fellow with the National Center for Policy Analysis, was a deputy assistant treasury secretary in the Reagan and Bush administrations.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
