<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="Y10CAM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000613T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DF1F3FF933A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS  GORE CONSIDERS HIS LEGACY  Vice President Al Gore has clearly given extensive thought to his legacy. Emphasis on extensive. Here was his answer Thursday at a fund-raiser in Los Angeles when a guest asked him how history would view him after two terms as president: ''I would hope that at the end of my tenure it would be said that during those years the American people reached their highest potential and had obstacles and impediments removed from their way, that the progress and prosperity of our nation continued and accelerated, that we gave every child health care and moved quickly toward universal health care for all, that we revolutionized the educational system and brought the productivity revolution of the private sector into the schools and respected teachers and made our schools the very best in the world. I would want it said that we were a more harmonious nation where race and ethnicity were understood and recognized but didn't make a difference because we respected one another's differences and embraced what we had in common. I would want it said that violence declined sharply. I would want it said that the environment became a central principle of what we did and how we did it and that we led the world toward a successful confrontation with the problem of global warming. I would want it said that we reformed our politics and campaign financing and that we made democracy more real in the lives of our people, and finally, I would want it said that at the end of those years we as Americans had a stronger belief in our own ability to govern ourselves and to make our dreams real.'' Katharine Q. Seelye (NYT)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS  GORE CONSIDERS HIS LEGACY  Vice President Al Gore has clearly given extensive thought to his legacy. Emphasis on extensive. Here was his answer Thursday at a fund-raiser in Los Angeles when a guest asked him how history would view him after two terms as president: ''I would hope that at the end of my tenure it would be said that during those years the American people reached their highest potential and had obstacles and impediments removed from their way, that the progress and prosperity of our nation continued and accelerated, that we gave every child health care and moved quickly toward universal health care for all, that we revolutionized the educational system and brought the productivity revolution of the private sector into the schools and respected teachers and made our schools the very best in the world. I would want it said that we were a more harmonious nation where race and ethnicity were understood and recognized but didn't make a difference because we respected one another's differences and embraced what we had in common. I would want it said that violence declined sharply. I would want it said that the environment became a central principle of what we did and how we did it and that we led the world toward a successful confrontation with the problem of global warming. I would want it said that we reformed our politics and campaign financing and that we made democracy more real in the lives of our people, and finally, I would want it said that at the end of those years we as Americans had a stronger belief in our own ability to govern ourselves and to make our dreams real.'' Katharine Q. Seelye (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE POLLS</p>
        <p>BUSH AND GORE STILL EVEN  Two new national polls have Gov. George W. Bush and Vice President Al Gore still locked in a race that is too close to call. One new survey gives Mr. Bush a slight edge, 41 percent to 38 percent. The poll, conducted by Princeton Survey Research for Bloomberg News, surveyed 1,208 adults between May 25 and June 4 and has a margin of sampling error of 3 percentage points. A CNN-USA Today Gallup poll taken last week put Mr. Bush at 44 percent and Mr. Gore at 44 percent, with a margin of error of 5 percentage points.(NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REFORM PARTY</p>
        <p>BUCHANAN'S SPOKESMAN FIRED  Neil Bernstein, campaign spokesman for Patrick J. Buchanan, was dismissed yesterday by Bay Buchanan, the candidate's sister and his chief strategist. In a press release announcing his own departure, Mr. Bernstein said: ''I have attempted to inject creativity and vision into the press operation and to the campaign at large. However, the desire to add even a modicum of creativity and vision into this campaign is not shared by Bay Buchanan or the majority of the senior staff.'' True, Ms. Buchanan said, adding that Brian Dougherty, a former producer at Fox Television News, has succeeded Mr. Bernstein. Of Mr. Bernstein, who joined the campaign in October, she said, ''We wish him well.''Michael Janofsky (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE INTERNET</p>
        <p>PARTIES UNVEIL WEB SITES  In the growing world of online campaigning, both Democrats and Republicans unveiled party-sponsored Web sites this week -- both designed to look a lot like news pages. The new sites, in fact, contain many news articles, but also have a heavy dose of promotional materials. The Republican site, www.GOP.gov, has an exclusively political focus and is designed to give Congressional Republicans a chance to post their press releases. The Democratic site, www.FreeDem.com, is also heavy on politics, but also lists things like movie reviews and top news stories. It also offers free Internet access, a feature the party says is intended to ''help span the digital divide.'' Leslie Wayne (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN  Correction:  June 13, 2000, Tuesday  A report in the Campaign Briefing column on Saturday misstated support for Gov. George W. Bush in a CNN-USA Today Gallup poll on the presidential race. He was favored by 48 percent of likely voters, not 44.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 13, 2000, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A report in the Campaign Briefing column on Saturday misstated support for Gov. George W. Bush in a CNN-USA Today Gallup poll on the presidential race. He was favored by 48 percent of likely voters, not 44.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
