<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Refusing To 'Live With AIDS'</title>
    <meta content="01GORD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/01/opinion/01GORD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1251592"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordimer, Nadine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E6D9103DF932A35751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="747" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Refusing To 'Live With AIDS'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Nadine Gordimer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordimer, Nadine</byline>
      <dateline>JOHANNESBURG</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Nadine Gordimer says there is no time left beyond present to tackle HIV and AIDS; notes latest figure for cases worldwide is 36 million, with 1 million children orphaned by the disease last year; says AIDS is first modern disease to strike developed and developing world simultaneously and to give both large stake in finding cure; says she is surprised that AIDS was not public health issue in presidential electioneering in United States; says every segment of society should promote open discussions about AIDS; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Living with AIDS: This is the bravely defiant description of life adopted by those who know that their span will be decided by whether life-prolonging drugs are available to them or a cure is discovered in time to defeat death.</p>
        <p>But those of us who are neither H.I.V.-positive nor AIDS-infected also ''live with AIDS.'' Mark Malloch Brown, who administers the United Nations Development Program, has defined the disease as ''the world's most dangerous insurgent.'' The latest figure for cases worldwide is 36 million, according to the United Nations. Some 11 million children were orphaned by AIDS last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Living with AIDS: This is the bravely defiant description of life adopted by those who know that their span will be decided by whether life-prolonging drugs are available to them or a cure is discovered in time to defeat death.</p>
        <p>But those of us who are neither H.I.V.-positive nor AIDS-infected also ''live with AIDS.'' Mark Malloch Brown, who administers the United Nations Development Program, has defined the disease as ''the world's most dangerous insurgent.'' The latest figure for cases worldwide is 36 million, according to the United Nations. Some 11 million children were orphaned by AIDS last year.</p>
        <p>Even at a time when other insurgents threaten -- global warming, the pollution of seas, the destruction of wetlands and forests -- these figures stun. Whatever the pace at which these other very real dangers are approaching us, AIDS is not ''threatening'': it is here. And no country can take comfort from figures that show it is less infected, less affected, than a country where one individual in 10 or one in four is a sufferer, where babies are born doomed, where governance itself is threatened by AIDS decimation among the qualified, economically active population.</p>
        <p>The ideal of globalized development to overcome the poverty in which 1.3 billion of the world's people live is being undercut and could be nullified by the pestilence among us. In sub-Saharan Africa, according to a business report in The Star, a Johannesburg newspaper, AIDS could reduce economic growth by 25 percent over 20 years. If there is still time for the human race to deal with advancing ecological problems, there is no time left beyond the present to tackle H.I.V. and AIDS.</p>
        <p>David J. Rothman, a professor of Social Medicine at the Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons, has written that AIDS ''is the first modern disease to strike the developed and developing world simultaneously and to give both a large stake in finding a cure.'' The hydra head of AIDS rises with multi-consequences that know no frontiers.</p>
        <p>There have been signs this year that governments, international financial agencies and multinational companies are increasing financing for research and preventive programs and to address the vast range of problems -- parentless homes, incapacitated breadwinners -- that accompany the disease. In July, the World Bank announced the provision of $500 million for these purposes in Africa.</p>
        <p>Still, the future of the world's children is no future if they are born HIV-positive or contract the virus while they are schoolboys and girls. We have to break irrevocably the silence that stigmatizes victims and inhibits frankness in education for prevention. The broad front, in anti-AIDS campaigns everywhere, is now focusing on the need for far more everyday public discussion of the complex issues involved.</p>
        <p>Surprising, to an outsider, is that AIDS was evidently not a public health issue in the presidential electioneering in the United States. Politicians, community leaders, economists, academics, business people, writers and artists, social and sporting clubs, priests, pastors, rabbis, imams -- all must join government and anti-AIDS agencies to promote openness. Radio, television and the Internet need to be utilized fully in their power of reaching the widest audiences in the history of communication.</p>
        <p>In South Africa, where the United Nations has just revealed that the country is considered to have the world's fastest-growing AIDS epidemic and the highest number of people living with H.I.V. and AIDS, AIDS education is given in schools, just as it is in America. Anti-AIDS messages appear on giant billboards and are the subject of admonitory pop songs. But the discussion also needs to come home, as part of family talk. Mothers, fathers, grandparents, uncles and aunts -- there has to be free discussion with children and youth about their natural sexual desires in the context of this epidemic.</p>
        <p>This week, for World AIDS Day, the South African Broadcasting Company published a banner headline above a two-page newspaper spread. Its call, on behalf of children and young people: ''Love them enough to talk about sex.''</p>
        <p>It's a rubric for every country, all mores, every class, religion and color. Collectively, we can't ''live with AIDS,'' watching members of our human family sicken and die.</p>
        <p>Nadine Gordimer, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1991, is a member of the working group on AIDS of the United Nations Development Program.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Nadine Gordimer, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1991, is a member of the working group on AIDS of the United Nations Development Program.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
