<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gardening</title>
    <meta content="04GARDENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Gardens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gardens and Gardening</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6D6153DF937A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2147" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gardening</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Verlyn Klinkenborg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of books on gardening; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few gardens, in literature or in life, were ever more disconsolate than the Bast garden, a derelict Long Island estate in William Gaddiss great novel ''JR. JR himself, an 11-year-old entrepreneur and denizen of Americas commercial deep, describes the Bast property: ''This here old house with these little pointy windows and this like big barn in back by the woods? With this big high scraggly hedge out front like? The narrator uses a different language to describe the place. He calls it an ''arboreal veterans ward full of ''trees which appeared to stagger without even provocation of a breeze, rearing their splintered amputations in all directions, an enclave invaded by a horticultural ''Laocoon of honeysuckle, grape and roses.</p>
        <p>Every gardener knows how that feels. Winter is a way of forgetting natures profligacy, which summer compounds annually. By now, Northeastern woods and road edges, lawns and borders are writhing with botanical JRs -- plants that are determined and opportunistic even when immature. But there is no dereliction in America quite like the dereliction found in European gardens. There simply hasnt been time for it. At Aberglasney, an ancient garden in Wales, a yew tunnel exists that may be between 700 and 1,000 years old. It is called a tunnel, but in photographs it resembles a yew esophagus. Aberglasney was home in the early 1300s to Llywelyn the Luxurious and, four centuries later, to the poet John Dyer, author of ''Grongar Hill, a well-esteemed landscape poem published in 1726. ''Thick round the ragged Walls pale Ivy creeps, Dyer wrote about Aberglasney, and it has been the task of the Aberglasney Restoration Trust to remove that ivy and repair those walls. An excellent book has been written about the project by Penny David, A GARDEN LOST IN TIME: The Mystery of the Ancient Gardens of Aberglasney (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, $34.95). This is a garden book with real villains -- time, vandals, thieves and Japanese knotweed, which overran the place in the last century. The late-Victorian taste for Japanese knotweed, a highly invasive species, proves that fashion doesnt merely come and go; sometimes it must be actively repulsed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few gardens, in literature or in life, were ever more disconsolate than the Bast garden, a derelict Long Island estate in William Gaddiss great novel ''JR. JR himself, an 11-year-old entrepreneur and denizen of Americas commercial deep, describes the Bast property: ''This here old house with these little pointy windows and this like big barn in back by the woods? With this big high scraggly hedge out front like? The narrator uses a different language to describe the place. He calls it an ''arboreal veterans ward full of ''trees which appeared to stagger without even provocation of a breeze, rearing their splintered amputations in all directions, an enclave invaded by a horticultural ''Laocoon of honeysuckle, grape and roses.</p>
        <p>Every gardener knows how that feels. Winter is a way of forgetting natures profligacy, which summer compounds annually. By now, Northeastern woods and road edges, lawns and borders are writhing with botanical JRs -- plants that are determined and opportunistic even when immature. But there is no dereliction in America quite like the dereliction found in European gardens. There simply hasnt been time for it. At Aberglasney, an ancient garden in Wales, a yew tunnel exists that may be between 700 and 1,000 years old. It is called a tunnel, but in photographs it resembles a yew esophagus. Aberglasney was home in the early 1300s to Llywelyn the Luxurious and, four centuries later, to the poet John Dyer, author of ''Grongar Hill, a well-esteemed landscape poem published in 1726. ''Thick round the ragged Walls pale Ivy creeps, Dyer wrote about Aberglasney, and it has been the task of the Aberglasney Restoration Trust to remove that ivy and repair those walls. An excellent book has been written about the project by Penny David, A GARDEN LOST IN TIME: The Mystery of the Ancient Gardens of Aberglasney (Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson, $34.95). This is a garden book with real villains -- time, vandals, thieves and Japanese knotweed, which overran the place in the last century. The late-Victorian taste for Japanese knotweed, a highly invasive species, proves that fashion doesnt merely come and go; sometimes it must be actively repulsed.</p>
        <p>In a similar vein comes Gertrude Jekylls LOST GARDEN: The Restoration of an Edwardian Masterpiece (Garden Art Press, $49.50), by Rosamund Wallinger. This is the chronicle of Upton Grey in Hampshire, a garden designed by Gertrude Jekyll in 1908. In the early 1980s, Wallinger and her husband decided to move to the country for the things that only the country can provide, like ceaseless physical labor and strife with rampant plants. (Wallinger had a hard time finding the Japanese knotweed she needed to complete Jekylls original designs. No nursery would sell it to her.) If not as Rabelaisian as the story of Aberglasney, ''Lost Garden has the charm of honesty. Wallinger was a rank amateur when she began restoring this remarkable garden to Jekylls specifications, and her candor will be appreciated by fellow amateurs and gardeners perhaps less rank wherever they may toil.</p>
        <p>Always irresistible are garden books that feature, as a kind of stately epilogue, group photographs of the gardening staff. There are two such books this spring: GARDENING AT SISSINGHURST (Frances Lincoln, $45), by Tony Lord, and THE GARDEN AT CHATSWORTH (Viking Studio, $40), by one of Chatsworths current occupants, the Duchess of Devonshire. The Sissinghurst volume is published in association with the National Trust, and like most books with that affiliation, it is both inspiring -- Sissinghurst, after all, is what many Americans imagine when they think of English gardens -- and unashamedly practical, full of sentences like ''suckering is always a problem with filberts, though suckering is nothing compared to the problems caused by 180,000 visitors annually.</p>
        <p>The 19th-century equivalent of Sissinghurst, though on a much grander scale, was Chatsworth, which saw 80,000 visitors in the summer of 1849. At the time, Chatsworth was the horticultural domain of Sir Joseph Paxton, the brilliant head gardener who erected its Great Conservatory (and later designed the Crystal Palace) and founded Pastons Magazine of Botany. Alluding to Volume XI of Paxtons magazine, in which the creation of Chatsworths Emperor Fountain is described, the Duchess of Devonshire writes, blithely, ''As I am sure this book is by your bed I wont weary you with all that is written therein, a sentence worth pondering for the range and quality of its implications. There are 21 gardeners in the Chatsworth group photo. Two more were on holiday when it was taken.</p>
        <p>As for you and me, we garden alone, or at best in pairs, and in America to boot. The book by my bed is one of the most American gardening tomes ever published, Edward C. Smiths VEGETABLE GARDENERS BIBLE: Discover Eds High-Yield W-O-R-D System for All North American Gardening Regions (Storey, paper, $24.95). With the exception of William Woys Weavers well-respected ''Heirloom Vegetable Gardening, I distrust any vegetable-gardening book that doesnt feature a person with a cheesy grin and a basketful of tomatoes and peppers on its cover. Smith, who gardens in Vermonts Northeast Kingdom, more than fills the bill. ''W-O-R-D stands for ''Wide Rows, Organic Methods, Raised Beds and Deep Soil, and as mnemonics go, ''W-O-R-D is pretty feeble. But the principles Smith advocates are completely sound, as is his practical advice. In every small town, there is a vegetable garden that people go out of the way to walk past. Smith is the guy who grew that garden.</p>
        <p>Smiths neighbor, spiritually speaking, is Andy Wasowski who, with his wife, Sally Wasowski, has written a book called THE LANDSCAPING REVOLUTION: Garden With Mother Nature, Not Against Her (Contemporary, $27.95). This is one of the few books Ive ever seen that offers advice on how to liberate topiary -- to return a hornbeam cube to its natural shape, for instance -- not that most of us have topiary waiting to be set free. But many of us do have lawns. ''The Landscaping Revolution is an enjoyable, instructive polemic against the American greensward, unless its moss or buffalo grass, a polemic, in fact, against nonnative planting in general and the laws -- written and implicit -- that force it down our throats. Iconoclasm in the gardening world is usually as understated as the Duchess of Devonshires prose. Not here. This is the only gardening book I know with an R. Crumb cartoon in it. Even if you dont wholly accept the Wasowskis nativist position, ''The Landscaping Revolution has a wealth of good ideas and trenchant observations about landscape design. The antidote -- topiary like, as JR might say -- is David Joyces TOPIARY AND THE ART OF TRAINING PLANTS (Firefly, cloth, $40; paper, $24.95), an inviting, practical guide to botanical bondage.</p>
        <p>What most gardeners always need more of is ideas. These may come on a grand scale, as they will to readers of THE HISTORY OF GARDEN DESIGN: The Western Tradition From the Renaissance to the Present Day (Thames and Hudson, paper, $44.95), edited by Monique Mosser and Georges Teyssot, first published a decade ago as ''The Architecture of Western Gardens and now available in paperback. This is a dense, overcrowded, academic book, but it is also filled with historic illustrations, including beautifully stippled plans of historic gardens as seen from the clouds. No less grand or academic is GREATER PERFECTIONS: The Practice of Garden Theory (University of Pennsylvania, $35), by John Dixon Hunt. The metaphorical nature of the garden means that it intersects with nearly every cultural domain, and Hunts subject is the representation of gardens as much as gardens themselves. Again, this book is well illustrated, and its argument will substantially enlarge many gardeners frame of reference. Penelope Hobhouses new book is also festooned with grand ideas. It is called PLANTS IN GARDEN HISTORY (Pavilion/Trafalgar Square, paper, $29.95). Hobhouse addresses design theory and the succession of styles, but her real concern is at ground level, among the foliage and inflorescences of the plants themselves. As a result, ''Plants in Garden History is an unusually informative history for practicing gardeners and more accessible than either ''Greater Perfections or ''The History of Garden Design.</p>
        <p>But most of us need ideas on a more intimate scale. Our problem isnt really whether to plant a mile of lime walk or build a Great Conservatory or fire the undergardeners junior assistant. Its hosta or euphorbia? Gazebo or pergola? Brickwork or stone? For questions like those, this season offers a cornucopia of books. The distinctive PLANTFINDERS GUIDE series (Timber, $34.95 each) has been augmented by Garden Ferns, by Martin Rickard, Early Bulbs, by Rod Leeds, and Cacti and Other Succulents, by Keith Grantham and Paul Klaassen; additional volumes in the GARDENERS GUIDE series (Timber) include Growing Temperate Bamboos ($29.95), by Michael Bell, and Agaves, Yuccas, and Related Plants ($34.95), by Mary and Gary Irish, and then there is LAVENDER: The Growers Guide (Timber, $29.95), by Virginia McNaughton. From Jane Taylor, there is SPECIAL PLANTS: Over 500 Outstanding Plants for the Enthusiastic Gardener (Quadrille, $35), an elegant survey. R. Roy Forster and Alex M. Downie have written a truly thoughtful introduction to THE WOODLAND GARDEN: Planting in Harmony With Nature (Firefly, paper, $19.95). There are two comprehensive new works on landscaping: the SUNSET NORTHEASTERN LANDSCAPING BOOK (Sunset, paper, $29.95), edited by Ken Druse, and TAYLORS MASTER GUIDE TO LANDSCAPING (Houghton Mifflin, $40), by Rita Buchanan, an especially rich and invigorating volume. And there is ARMITAGES GARDEN PERENNIALS: A Color Encyclopedia (Timber, $49.95) by Allan M. Armitage, an illustrated guide -- full of opinion -- to garden-worthy perennials from all over the world. I plan to shelve this volume right beside the Wasowskis book.</p>
        <p>Most gardeners are also shoppers, or will be after reading Armitage, and for them Ruah Donnelly has written THE ADVENTUROUS GARDENER: Where to Buy the Best Plants in New England (Horticultural Press, $24.95). Since many of these nurseries offer mail-order service, the value of this book isnt regionally restricted. Urban residents whose gardening consists mostly of gawking at street trees will want to consider Arthur Plotniks indispensable URBAN TREE BOOK: An Uncommon Field Guide for City and Town (Three Rivers Press, $18.95). Its scope is national, but for Westerners I would add Michael Kuhnss TREES OF UTAH AND THE INTERMOUNTAIN WEST: A Guide to Identification and Use (Utah State University, paper, $14.95), a perfect companion to Plotniks book.</p>
        <p>For most of us, books are all the gardening staff we will ever have, which is a relief because they are so much easier to get along with. You could hardly ask for wiser or more personable counsel in the garden than you get from Allen Lacy, whose writings in Homeground, his gardening newsletter, have been gathered in IN A GREEN SHADE: Writings from Homeground (Houghton Mifflin, $24). Nor could you ask for a more coherent and comprehensive array of information than that in William Cullinas NEW ENGLAND WILD FLOWER SOCIETY GUIDE TO GROWING AND PROPAGATING WILDFLOWERS OF THE UNITED STATES AND CANADA (Houghton Mifflin, $40). Dont let the title deceive you. This wonderful book may originate in New England, but its range is nearly continental. And though wildflowers are its nominal subject, their garden kin are legion. Cullina has written a keenly intelligent, beautifully arrayed work of botanical and horticultural research.</p>
        <p>Gardeners are a practical people, all told. They like the gritty details, and they understand the force of time, which is why most of us find stories of individual gardens so moving, whether theyre being restored from ancient oblivion or created anew. Gardening adheres to its ideal preoccupations, and from time to time it also yields to necessity. Beth Chatto has become a practitioner of the necessary ideal, a gardener who began with an inhospitable site -- dry, gravelly soil in a former parking lot -- and created a garden that actually acknowledges the implications of global warming. The results are visible in BETH CHATTOS GRAVEL GARDEN: Drought-Resistant Planting Through the Year (Viking Studio, $35). What Chatto offers, as many gardeners already know, is crisp enthusiasm and a vivid sense of what is possible. Her gravel garden is not a universal solution to difficult sites or dry ground, but it exemplifies the kind of accommodation to local conditions that should inspire every gardener. This is a gentle manifesto for a green future.</p>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg writes editorials for The Times. He is the author of ''Making Hay and ''The Last Fine Time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Verlyn Klinkenborg writes editorials for The Times. He is the author of ''Making Hay and ''The Last Fine Time.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
