<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Interests; Ask Me No Questions</title>
    <meta content="22COLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1224444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Survivor (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Gail Collins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EEDF1E3EF931A1575BC0A9669C8B63" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Interests; Ask Me No Questions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Collins Op-Ed column on issues facing presidential nominees Gov George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore draws comparison with television program Survivor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Well, it took a year, but we've finally got those presidential candidates nominated. And thanks to the conventions, we now understand that George W. Bush likes nothing better than to hang around with members of minority groups, that Al Gore likes nothing better than to hang around with Tipper, and that everybody in the Reform Party is crazy.</p>
        <p>Some of us have been privileged to attend all these interesting events, and I'm sure you're brimming with questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Well, it took a year, but we've finally got those presidential candidates nominated. And thanks to the conventions, we now understand that George W. Bush likes nothing better than to hang around with members of minority groups, that Al Gore likes nothing better than to hang around with Tipper, and that everybody in the Reform Party is crazy.</p>
        <p>Some of us have been privileged to attend all these interesting events, and I'm sure you're brimming with questions.</p>
        <p>Why do you think the four least likable people on ''Survivor'' made it to the finals? I can't find anybody to root for.</p>
        <p>In life as in politics, when people have significant self-interest in the outcome of a contest, they very seldom worry about who's the most adorable competitor. But I'm a little disturbed that whenever I bring up the presidential election, you start talking about reality-based TV.</p>
        <p>I definitely think voters would get more involved in the presidential race if they knew that whoever loses would get his torch snuffed out on election night.</p>
        <p>Do you know why the Democrats say the average family would only save 62 cents a day under the Bush tax cut, and the Republicans say it's thousands of dollars?</p>
        <p>I have a feeling you're going to tell me.</p>
        <p>It's because there are tons of families toward the bottom who don't have any income taxes to cut. The Gore people always average them in.</p>
        <p>How much would a typical family save under the Al Gore tax cut?</p>
        <p>Lots and lots. We are of course presuming the typical family is a married couple whose children are ready to go to college and whose parents are about to die and leave them a farm.</p>
        <p>How much would a really, really rich family save under the George Bush tax cut?</p>
        <p>Republicans do not recognize the term ''really, really rich.'' However, successful entrepreneurs would get a pile.</p>
        <p>I used to think the way Gore keeps talking about health care was pandering, but then I noticed that the most dimwitted person on the ''Survivor'' island was Sean the doctor. Don't the medical schools screen their students anymore?</p>
        <p>Next month, you'll probably try to get me to talk about the Olympics. Let me warn you now, I have trouble regarding synchronized swimming as a sport.</p>
        <p>I already know who I'm going to vote for. Call me when the leaves fall.</p>
        <p>Wait a minute. What about the national dialogue? This is a community process by which we, the people, direct the course of the country, not some poll about which roommate you want to see banished from the on-camera commune.</p>
        <p>O.K., the issue I'm really worried about is the polar ice cap. Did you read the story about how it's melted?</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, this campaign reflects the fact that young people don't vote and old people know that global warming isn't going to really start hitting home until they're out of the picture. They're way more worried about being stuck in an H.M.O. where the only physician on call is Sean from ''Survivor.''</p>
        <p>I'm serious. My issue is that I want the North Pole frozen again.</p>
        <p>I think it's safe to assume that deep in his heart, Al Gore is even more worried about the ice cap than you are.</p>
        <p>What about George W. Bush?</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush thinks the jury is still out on global warming. Not to mention evolution.</p>
        <p>I think the Bush campaign should talk more about the polar ice cap and less about bringing morality back to the White House. Everybody knows Al Gore would never do anything to hurt Tipper.</p>
        <p>Look, the Republicans believe the immorality started in 1992, when Bill Clinton stole the election from George Bush with the help of Ross Perot and big donors with murky Asian connections, then turned around and stole their issues, and the credit for the economy. They also blame the Clintons for everything that happened in the 60's, including Nehru jackets. Obviously, you are not going to wipe all that out by electing a monogamous Democrat.</p>
        <p>So they think Clinton is like Richard the devious corporate consultant on ''Survivor''?</p>
        <p>I think they would be more likely to mention the Antichrist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
