<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mercury Levels Found Unsafe in Fish From 6 New Sites Upstate</title>
    <meta content="15MERC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1207528"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservoirs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mercury (Cruise Ship)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hu, Winnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hazardous and Toxic Substances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waterways and Other Bodies of Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E3D6103EF936A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mercury Levels Found Unsafe in Fish From 6 New Sites Upstate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WINNIE HU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hu, Winnie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State health report shows that rising levels of mercury have contaminated fish in at least six more upstate water bodies, including two major reservoirs in Catskills that supply drinking water to New York City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state health report issued yesterday shows that rising levels of mercury have contaminated the fish in at least six more upstate water bodies, including two major reservoirs in the Catskills that supply drinking water to New York City.</p>
        <p>Fish and wildlife in the Pepacton  and Cannonsville Reservoirs, as well as in three rivers and a lake, have been found with accumulated mercury deposits that, if eaten by people, could pose long-term health risks. The report brings the total number of affected water bodies that have been identified upstate to 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A state health report issued yesterday shows that rising levels of mercury have contaminated the fish in at least six more upstate water bodies, including two major reservoirs in the Catskills that supply drinking water to New York City.</p>
        <p>Fish and wildlife in the Pepacton  and Cannonsville Reservoirs, as well as in three rivers and a lake, have been found with accumulated mercury deposits that, if eaten by people, could pose long-term health risks. The report brings the total number of affected water bodies that have been identified upstate to 25.</p>
        <p>The mercury does not pose such a  threat to the drinking water in the Catskills reservoirs, which provide 90 percent of the city's water supply. ''There has been extensive sampling and there has not been any detectable levels,'' said Mary Mears, a spokeswoman for the Environmental Protection Agency, which monitors the drinking water quality along with city officials.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Post, a spokeswoman for the State Department of Environmental Conservation, which worked with the health department on the report, said the classification of the reservoirs, as well as Beaver Lake and the Susquehanna, Chenango and Unadilla Rivers, was a result of improved monitoring efforts -- not necessarily more mercury contamination in the waters. ''It's highly unlikely that this is the result of any significant environmental change or increase in mercury contamination,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Several environmentalists warned yesterday, however, that the escalating mercury levels would inevitably contaminate the city's drinking water if state and federal officials did not take further steps to curtail the acid rain and pollution from coal plants that is causing most of the mercury buildup in the water bodies.</p>
        <p>''There's absolutely no excuse for this occurrence now,'' said John F. Sheehan, a spokesman for the Adirondack Council, an advocacy and protection group. ''We know how to control these pollutants, but we have not taken the steps necessary to stop the pollution.''</p>
        <p>The health report's findings come at a time when state officials and environmentalists are increasingly recognizing the damage from acid rain and power plant smoke and undertaking more stringent measures to curb that pollution.</p>
        <p>Last month, Gov. George E. Pataki signed a bill passed by the Legislature that was intended to limit the amount of pollutants drifting into New York from coal-burning plants in Midwestern and Southern states. State Attorney General Eliot L. Spitzer has also sued the owners of 12 coal-fired plants in the Midwest, asserting that they had not installed federally required pollution controls.</p>
        <p>While the annual report does not address those issues, it advises people to limit the amount of fish and wildlife that they eat, because of the pollution risks. The health department warns that mercury-contaminated fish can contribute to neurological diseases and birth defects.</p>
        <p>''The advisory is for recreational anglers,'' said Claire Pospisil, a spokeswoman for the State Department of Health. ''It's basically to help people minimize their exposure to contaminants in sport fish and to reduce the health risk.''</p>
        <p>But several environmentalists said the report should serve as a warning to government officials that the mercury buildup was more widespread than they had thought and that it would take decades to reduce the concentration of mercury in fish to a safe level.</p>
        <p>William Cooke, director of governmental relations for the National Audubon Society in New York, said he no longer allowed his family to eat fish caught from any of the state's rivers and lakes.</p>
        <p>''At the end of the day,'' he said, ''it's in all the waters of New York. I tell people, 'Don't eat the fish.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
