<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Earth Day Goes Global as It Turns 30</title>
    <meta content="09EART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1190645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Verhovek, Sam Howe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hayes, Denis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E2D71E3FF93AA35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1018" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Earth Day Goes Global as It Turns 30</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Verhovek, Sam Howe</byline>
      <dateline>SEATTLE, April 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Dennis Hayes, leader of first Earth Day 30 years ago, who is leading one planned for Apr 22; talks about what has changed and what remains same ecologically around world; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With 4,500 organizations planning events in more than 180 countries, the 30th Earth Day is living up to its name in a way that was not true for the first Earth Day, which was largely a domestic affair and a major spark for two landmark pieces of federal environmental legislation, the Clean Air Act and the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>But if much has changed over the years about Earth Day, one thing about this year's event on April 22 is strikingly similar to the original: Denis Hayes is leading the effort.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With 4,500 organizations planning events in more than 180 countries, the 30th Earth Day is living up to its name in a way that was not true for the first Earth Day, which was largely a domestic affair and a major spark for two landmark pieces of federal environmental legislation, the Clean Air Act and the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>But if much has changed over the years about Earth Day, one thing about this year's event on April 22 is strikingly similar to the original: Denis Hayes is leading the effort.</p>
        <p>In 1970, just a few years out of Stanford University, where he was student body president, Mr. Hayes dropped out of the Kennedy School at Harvard to serve as national coordinator for the first Earth Day, which was the brainchild of Senator Gaylord Nelson of Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>There was more than a bit of the angry young man in Mr. Hayes's approach to galvanizing public ire over air and water pollution. This time around, as the chairman of the international Earth Day Network, Mr. Hayes, 55, says ecological crises, especially global warming, are no less severe. But the lawyer and environmental advocate says the ''clean energy agenda'' at the heart of this year's rallies is ''almost Reaganesque in its robust optimism.''</p>
        <p>The earth ''is confronting some extremely difficult problems,'' said Mr. Hayes, who resigned in the Reagan administration when budget cuts were imposed at the federal Solar Energy Research Institute, which he directed. ''How do you deal with racism, how do you deal with ethnic tensions that have existed for thousands of years? We don't have any clever ideas. Global warming is an enormous threat to the well-being of the planet, but it's one where we honest to God do know what to do, and it's a matter of summoning the necessary political will.''</p>
        <p>Summoning the will to confront global warming is thus the chief goal of the Seattle-based Earth Day Network, which says the biggest rally in this country on April 22 will be on the Mall in Washington.</p>
        <p>Much as earlier Earth Days led to a push on causes like recycling, organizers hope this year's energy agenda will lead consumers, government agencies and businesses to expand conservation efforts and the use of cleaner forms of energy, including solar and wind power. The agenda includes tougher pollution standards for cars, appliances and factories.</p>
        <p>All of these are achievable and even affordable goals, Mr. Hayes insisted this week at Earth Day offices in downtown Seattle, where a giant world map flags the locations of Earth Day events across the planet.</p>
        <p>To cite a smattering of events, there are workshops for youth in Burkina Faso on solar cooking; a children's clean-air bicycle rally in New Delhi; rallies to curb global warming in five cities in Bangladesh; a car-free event in Seoul, South Korea; and an ''eco-festival'' in London. A clean-air rally in Mexico City may draw more people than the one in Washington, Earth Day organizers say.</p>
        <p>But in all cases, Mr. Hayes said, these groups are focusing on a ''single, unifying global problem that has a local dimension to it: groups that are fighting tanker traffic through  Puget Sound, groups trying to protect the rain forests of Nigeria or the Arctic Wildlife Refuge, Bangladeshis scared to death of an ocean rise that will take out their country, all of them are really mobilized to get engaged in a clean-energy agenda.''</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Hayes said he had been struck in international travels by how many political leaders, not just ordinary citizens, cited pollution as a dominant problem.</p>
        <p>The 25th anniversary of Earth Day in 1995 was not without controversy, as some environmentalists complained that the event had taken on a nebulous feel-good air and a degree of corporate sponsorship that led some to say Earth Day had been ''greenwashed'' out of significance.</p>
        <p>And this time, even as organizers have emphasized more teach-ins and grass-roots events, Earth Day organizers had to stand by with some pain as a recent dispute unfolded over a decision by ABC News to have one of the event's celebrity leaders, Leonardo DiCaprio, interview President Clinton about global warming. (Mr. Hayes said the movie star had helped galvanize youth interest in the environment.)</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if environmental advocates have sometimes been accused of lacking a sense of humor, that does not seem to be an issue at Earth Day headquarters or on the Web site, www.earthday.net. One of the network's projects is a daily online compendium of environmental news called the Daily Grist, billed as ''gloom and doom with a sense of humor'' and marked by puns and tongue-in-cheek headlines.</p>
        <p>The Daily Grist even offered an April Fool's edition reporting, among other things, that a coalition of New Mexico environmental groups was backing a massive shopping complex  ''in the sprawling suburbs of Albuquerque,'' which grateful developers were thinking of naming Muir Valley. ''It's just a bunch of scrub brush,'' one environmentalist was quoted as saying. Another said, ''All the species on this land can be found in at least two or three other places, so I don't see a real problem.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes said a little such humor was a good thing, but he hoped this year's event would spur a serious commitment to energy efficiency. His ire has clearly been raised by sport utility vehicles and large cars.</p>
        <p>''Detroit took the most environmentally irresponsible vehicle that is made in the world, found a loophole for it in the standards, and then sold it to the greenest cohort of American consumers,'' he said. ''Most of the S.U.V. decision-makers among consumers are young urban females, who are the strongest environmentalists in the country. They sold it on the basis of urban safety, and all these photographs of them in the Serengeti, as though you're going to drive your S.U.V. through the hills of East Africa.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
