<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ideas &amp; Trends: Kaleidoscope; Trying Hard to Bring The Future Into Focus</title>
    <meta content="05BERK$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/05/weekinreview/05BERK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244594"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E0DC1439F936A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2068" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ideas &amp; Trends: Kaleidoscope; Trying Hard to Bring The Future Into Focus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore and Gov George W Bush have both sent so many conflicting policy signals during campaign that it is unclear which direction either would take as president or how they would lead their parties, which are themselves riven between left and right; possible moderate and conservative Bush presidencies and moderate and liberal Gore presidencies described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BY Tuesday night, America will know if it's President George W. Bush or President Al Gore. But just which President Gore or President Bush will it be?</p>
        <p>Will it be the President Bush who invites Representative Barney Frank, the liberal firebrand, to brunch? Or the Bush who lends out an Oval Office anteroom to Charlton Heston, the head of the National Rifle Association?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BY Tuesday night, America will know if it's President George W. Bush or President Al Gore. But just which President Gore or President Bush will it be?</p>
        <p>Will it be the President Bush who invites Representative Barney Frank, the liberal firebrand, to brunch? Or the Bush who lends out an Oval Office anteroom to Charlton Heston, the head of the National Rifle Association?</p>
        <p>Will it be the President Gore who banishes, once and for all, the internal combustion engine? Or the Gore who reaches across the partisan divide and eliminates, once and for all, the national debt?</p>
        <p>These possibilities may sound fanciful, but they reflect the assorted Gores and Bushes who held forth on the campaign trail this year: the populist, protect-the-little-people Gore and the centrist foe of big government; the Bush who railed against abortion to religious conservatives and the compassionate conservative who is as apt to invoke Franklin Roosevelt as Ronald Reagan.</p>
        <p>Because they've sent so many conflicting signals, no one knows for sure which direction either new president would take or how they would lead their parties -- which are themselves riven between left and right. And these intraparty divisions mean the winning party could well face internecine warfare usually seen only on the losing side. The bloodletting could be fierce.</p>
        <p>Whatever policies the new president does put forward will be complicated by the fact that even if he captures a wider margin than the polls now suggest, he will not enjoy a popular mandate. He will have to negotiate with a Congress where control of the House might turn on narrow margins, forcing across-the-aisle charm offensives.</p>
        <p>In addition, either Mr. Gore or Mr. Bush will be besieged by people and constituencies who feel they are owed much for delivering the election. And once the president appeases one group, he will offend another. The winner, in fact, may have more trouble in his own party because of promises made -- and expectations met.</p>
        <p>''This election will raise more questions than it will settle about the political future of the country,'' said Rachel Gorlin, a Democratic strategist. ''What you're dealing with is two guys who have never in the past been ideologically motivated but have ideological bases. The real question is, how much do Bush and Gore have to play to their base in order to govern? It's very scary to be contemplating this on the eve of the election.''</p>
        <p>Much depends on which Al Gore or which George Bush emerges.</p>
        <p>BUSH THE MODERATE</p>
        <p>New best friend: Richard A. Gephardt, the House Democratic leader.  New worst enemy: Tom DeLay, the House whip.  Pet issue: Prescription drugs.  Slogan: ''Leave no child behind.''  Missing their payback: Dick Cheney, N.R.A., National Right to Life Committee.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Bush makes good on his mantra of bipartisanship, and his moderate side prevails, he would probably be willing to significantly dilute his proposals, like his huge tax cut plan, and instead go for more modest trims, making teachers and schools more accountable, retooling Social Security in a way that Democrats could accept and settling on a prescription drug plan.</p>
        <p>For this to work, Mr. Bush would have to aggressively court Democrats in the House and Senate, and reassure Republicans he was no sellout. ''He's going to need to find 25 Democrats and say, 'Look, I can't get this done alone,' '' said Representative John R. Kasich of Ohio, chairman of the Budget Committee. ''There will always be pressure on Bush to be more conservative than he's being. But he's going to have to do what he knows he can get done -- and just take the heat sometimes.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Bush would have to fend off interest groups, like the health care industry, that would demand he look out for them.</p>
        <p>Even if Republicans retain the House, Mr. Bush may want to try this moderate approach because the margins will be so thin. He may not feel as if he owes anything to conservatives in Congress because he did not turn to them to help him get elected. But many conservatives who held their tongues in the name of Mr. Bush's election may insist he does indeed owe them and will not stay quiet. Gary L. Bauer, for one, a prominent abortion foe who ran in the presidential primaries, said the right would be furious if Mr. Bush did not appoint an anti-abortion Supreme Court justice. If Mr. Bush wins, Mr. Bauer argued, he will owe voters in states where those with ''the pro-life view'' helped him win. If he doesn't repay those voters, Mr. Bauer warned. ''he could find himself facing real battles within his own party.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Kasich put it, ''There's going to be a lot of yelling and screaming.''</p>
        <p>BUSH THE CONSERVATIVE</p>
        <p>New best friend: Joseph I. Lieberman.  New worst enemy: Hillary Rodham Clinton.  Pet issue: Ending partial birth abortion.  Slogan: ''Returning honor and dignity to the White House.''  Missing their payback: Senator John McCain, Representative Jennifer B. Dunn, Log Cabin Republicans.</p>
        <p>It could be that Mr. Bush's talk of ''compassionate conservatism'' was merely a way to repackage his genuine conservative beliefs in a more palatable way. As president, he might seize the moment to embrace a hard-right agenda, especially if Republicans retain control of Congress.</p>
        <p>Far from backing down from his tax cut, this George Bush will press for it with gusto. He would stock the courts with judges who champion states' rights. He might try to undo gun control laws and increase the military budget.</p>
        <p>But Democrats, and Republican moderates, would not sit still. The margins will be so tight in the Senate it would not take much for one Bush foe to filibuster -- and block the new president's initiatives.</p>
        <p>''If they came out with tax cuts that disproportionately help the top one percent,'' warned Senator Paul Wellstone, Democrat of Minnesota, ''or if they have a bill that guts a lot of workplace safety rules, I'll certainly try as a senator to use my leverage to fight what I think is wrong.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush could face even more trouble from inside his own tent, from someone like Senator McCain, who could bedevil Mr. Bush in the same way that Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan bedeviled Mr. Clinton. Mr. McCain enjoys such a high profile that he could be a big impediment if he raised questions about the Bush tax cut. The twist is that Mr. Gore might well become closer to Mr. McCain than would Mr. Bush. After all, Mr. Gore has pledged that the McCain campaign finance bill would be his first legislative initiative. A conservative Mr. Bush would have little interest in campaign finance reform.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats are unnerved by the prospect of entreaties from Mr. Bush. Acknowledging that Mr. Bush was more of a schmoozer than Mr. Gore, Representative Charles Rangel, the outspoken Democrat from New York, said, ''Some people would rather have a beer and go fishing with Bush.''</p>
        <p>Could the veteran liberal, who will be Ways and Means Committee chairman if Democrats take the House, cut deals at the fishing hole with the conservative from Midland? ''I don't fish,'' Mr. Rangel said.</p>
        <p>GORE THE MODERATE</p>
        <p>New best friend: Senator John McCain  New worst enemy: Hillary Rodham Clinton or Marian Wright Edelman, founder of the Children's Defense Fund.  Pet issue: Cracking down on ''cultural pollution.''  Slogan: ''Shut down failing schools.''  Missing their payback: Black and Hispanic caucuses, Hollywood, National Abortion Rights Action League.</p>
        <p>This version of Al Gore shares similarities with the moderate George Bush. He would press for Social Security reform, more money for education and teacher accountability. He would try to eliminate the marriage penalty.</p>
        <p>To do all this, Mr. Gore would work elbow-to-elbow with Congressional Republicans. In an interview aboard his campaign bus last week, Mr. Gore sounded like a go-along-get-along politician as he made the case that he could work with Speaker Dennis Hastert if Republicans hang on to the House.</p>
        <p>''Denny Hastert is certainly not a Newt Gingrich,'' he said. ''In the event that my fondest hopes don't work out for the House, I will spare no effort to try to drain away the poison and partisanship that has become way too prominent in the last decade.''</p>
        <p>Seeking to burnish his bona fides on the right, he added, ''I was roundly criticized by my own party for initiatives that I took part in to work with former President Reagan on strategic weaponry.''</p>
        <p>The moderate Al Gore would probably back down from his campaign promises to tackle issues like global warming that could infuriate industry. And he may be more inclined to stroke a key constituency -- the high-tech industry -- rather than labor.</p>
        <p>But unions would not sit still for that. By rallying behind Mr. Gore during the primaries, they rescued him from being toppled by Senator Bill Bradley and expect some payback. Labor officials have put Mr. Gore on notice that he had better not cave to high-tech industry officials pushing for an increase in visas so unskilled workers can travel to the United States -- and compete for jobs with union members.</p>
        <p>''Gore would feel enormous pressure from the high-tech community because they just throw their weight around here like it's nobody's business,'' said Jerry Shea, the governmental affairs director of the A.F.L.-C.I.O. ''We expect a very big fight.''</p>
        <p>Republicans will eagerly stoke the flames. If Republicans keep the House, many Democrats fear that Mr. DeLay will find some way to trap President Gore into siding with labor or industry, like forcing a vote on a trade bill.</p>
        <p>Beyond traditional liberal constituencies, many of the left-leaning members of his party, including environmentalists and abortion rights advocates, would not sit idle if Al Gore behaves like a Republican. ''He wouldn't turn his back on us, because we've been with him all the way through the process,'' said Daniel J. Weiss, political director of the Sierra Club.</p>
        <p>But in the case of environmentalists, Mr. Gore might decide to turn on a small segment -- those who backed Ralph Nader.</p>
        <p>GORE THE LIBERAL</p>
        <p>New best friend: John J. Sweeney of the A.F.L.-C.I.O.  New worst enemy: Senator Trent Lott, the Republican leader.  Pet issue: Prescription drugs.  Slogan: ''Fight for the people, not the powerful.''  Missing their payback: Joseph I. Lieberman, Gov. Gray Davis, Democratic Leadership Council.</p>
        <p>If the Democrats win back the House and make gains in the Senate, the pressure from his core supporters as well as the new speaker, Richard Gephardt, will be intense for Mr. Gore to press an ambitious populist agenda. But that may not be such a good thing. Because even with a House barely under Democratic control, the vice president will never be able to satisfy his constituencies.</p>
        <p>The liberal Mr. Gore -- if he is to win a second term -- may have learned the lesson from Mr. Clinton that it is not always safe to champion issues that may win over a partisan audience but could alienate the larger public. Consider Mr. Clinton's failed plan early in his first term to overturn the ban against gays in the military. He could, but it is not likely that Mr. Gore would trumpet his remarks during the primaries that he would back civil unions between gays.</p>
        <p>But in moving to the left, Mr. Gore risks imperiling the progress Mr. Clinton made in making the Democratic Party more electable by appropriating Republican issues. The new Democrats whom this liberal Mr. Gore could alienate do not want to return to the old way of doing business.</p>
        <p>One way or another, Mr. Gore has to be ready to infuriate not only Republicans, but other Democrats.</p>
        <p>''The real question for him,'' said Senator Bob Kerrey, the Nebraska Democrat, ''is whether he is willing to antagonize members of his own party.''</p>
        <p>Each of these scenarios is different, but every one predicts gloves-off brawling between the parties and within them -- among winners and losers alike. Certainly, players in this town are no strangers to enemies lists, vicious backstabbers and brutal fights, but all that could have been just the dress rehearsal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
