<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Suggests Gore Supports Higher Gas Prices</title>
    <meta content="Y24BUS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1209762"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Graham, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruni, Frank</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Earth in the Balance (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DA1730F937A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Suggests Gore Supports Higher Gas Prices</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK BRUNI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruni, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>TUSCALOOSA, Ala., June 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George W Bush challenges Vice Pres Al Gore's record and positions on several fronts and suggests thayt he is partly responsible for--and a proponent of--high gasoline prices; cites Gore's 1992 book on the environment, Earth in the Balance; seeks to deflect attention from highly publicized, bitterly controversial execution of Gary Graham at Texas state prison in Huntsville; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the morning after a highly publicized, bitterly controversial execution in Texas, Gov. George W. Bush quickly tried to change the subject today, challenging Vice President Al Gore's record and positions on several fronts, from Social Security to the longstanding investigations into the fund-raising practices of Democrats in 1996.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush was most eager today to cast Mr. Gore as someone who was partly responsible for -- and a proponent of -- high gasoline prices.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the morning after a highly publicized, bitterly controversial execution in Texas, Gov. George W. Bush quickly tried to change the subject today, challenging Vice President Al Gore's record and positions on several fronts, from Social Security to the longstanding investigations into the fund-raising practices of Democrats in 1996.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush was most eager today to cast Mr. Gore as someone who was partly responsible for -- and a proponent of -- high gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>Carrying with him a copy of ''Earth in the Balance,'' Mr. Gore's  1992 book on the environment, Mr. Bush twice read aloud a passage describing ''higher taxes on fossil fuels'' as ''one of the logical first steps in changing our policies in a manner consistent with a more responsible approach to the environment.''</p>
        <p>''Want to talk about energy?'' Mr. Bush said this morning to the reporters on his campaign plane, who had spent the last several days grilling Mr. Bush about capital punishment. Then, opening the book, he said, ''Page 173.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was on his way to Alabama from Texas, and his attention to the book suggested that he wanted to move on from the subject that had dominated news coverage of his campaign, the execution Thursday night of a convicted killer named Gary Graham.</p>
        <p>Mr. Graham was put to death by lethal injection at the state prison in Huntsville at 8:49 p.m. central time after many legal experts said he had received a deeply flawed trial and 5 of 17 members of a state parole board voted Thursday afternoon to commute his sentence to life in prison. A half-hour before that, Mr. Bush read a statement to reporters in which he expressed his confidence that ''justice is being done.''</p>
        <p>Over 19 years, dozens of courts and dozens of judges had heard and rejected appeals by Mr. Graham's lawyers. But he steadfastly proclaimed his innocence of the 1981 murder for which he was given a death sentence and in a statement just before his execution said, ''The truth will come out.'' It took a full minute for prison officials to strap a struggling Mr. Graham to the gurney.</p>
        <p>In response to questions from reporters on his campaign plane, Mr. Bush said he was not aware of the details of Mr. Graham's final minutes. When the governor was asked if he understood how other people, looking at the facts in Mr. Graham's case, could come to a different conclusion than he had, Mr. Bush said: ''Yes, I do. Good people can disagree.''</p>
        <p>Referring to all the prominent people, like the actor Danny Glover and the Rev. Jesse Jackson, who rallied to Mr. Graham's cause, Mr. Bush said: ''I don't resent it in the least. I think it's part of the American process.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's assertion today that Mr. Gore supported higher gasoline prices came as he and Mr. Gore jockeyed for position on a campaign issue that is suddenly looming large.</p>
        <p>And it deflected attention from reports of the enormous sums of campaign money that Mr. Bush had received over the years from the gas and oil industry. Mr. Gore has suggested that Mr. Bush's coziness with the energy industry would make him reluctant to intervene on behalf of consumers.</p>
        <p>''There seems to be an effort out of Washington to blame me for rising energy prices,'' Mr. Bush said at a news conference here around midday. ''The American people aren't going to buy that. The Clinton-Gore administration has been there for seven years and we're more dependent now than ever before on foreign oil sources. And I'm amazed that they're trying to shift the blame.''</p>
        <p>Douglas Hattaway, a spokesman for the Gore campaign, said that the Clinton administration had consistently explored ways to reduce dependency on foreign oil. He also questioned Mr. Bush's ties to the oil industry, noting that Mr. Bush wanted to give companies access to oil reserves in pristine patches of Alaskan wilderness that Mr. Gore wants to protect.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Hattaway said that what Mr. Gore was proposing in ''Earth in the Balance'' was not higher prices at the gasoline pump, but special taxes -- to go into an environmental trust fund -- on companies that harvested and produced fuels that cause pollution. Mr. Hattaway said that Mr. Gore's plan included details that would protect consumers from higher gasoline prices.</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Bush was clearly feeling ''the heat over gas prices and his failure to take on his friends in the oil and gas industry.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE TEXAS GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
