<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flawless, But Never Quite Loved</title>
    <meta content="02SHEE$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1204132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheehy, Gail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02EFD7133CF931A35755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flawless, But Never Quite Loved</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gail Sheehy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sheehy, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gail Sheehy Op-Ed article holds that Vice Pres Al Gore is swaying voters on policy issues, but alienating them by coming across as a man without messy personal flaws or strong convictions; drawing</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The more meticulously Al Gore articulates his message, the better he scores with voters on issues high on their agenda -- health care, education and Social Security -- but the less they like him. Why do so many voters wish they could take the Al Gore out of Al Gore's positions?</p>
        <p>He tries too hard to be perfect.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The more meticulously Al Gore articulates his message, the better he scores with voters on issues high on their agenda -- health care, education and Social Security -- but the less they like him. Why do so many voters wish they could take the Al Gore out of Al Gore's positions?</p>
        <p>He tries too hard to be perfect.</p>
        <p>Perfection is a serious flaw for a modern politician. Mr. Gore has suffered from it all his life. In his senior yearbook, his prep school classmates at St. Albans called him ''frighteningly good at many things,'' but his habitual perfectionism didn't make people like him; rather, it provoked the meanspiritedness of envy. Behind his back some classmates called him ''Ozymandias,'' after the king in the Shelley poem who cries, ''Look on my works, ye mighty, and despair!''</p>
        <p>The ur-attribute of a successful politician is charm. People look first for a candidate they like, and it is easier to like a candidate who needs to be loved -- who can't wait to get to the next fund-raiser and who sticks around, like President Clinton, until chairs are being upturned on the banquet tables, until every pair of eyes has been looked into as if at a new best friend.</p>
        <p>But Al Gore doesn't need to be loved. He needs to be right.</p>
        <p>Not only is he a polymath who makes the rest of us feel like slackers; he lacks glaring flaws: no dark past, no drunken parent or dubious paternity, no private demons, no cheating at Harvard, no bad-boy brother or left-wing wife; alas, not even a Gennifer. How is the poor man to compete in the Politics of Personal Biography!</p>
        <p>Al Gore's goody-goodiness deprives him of the messy imperfections that allow voters to get past their envy of the famous and powerful. Unlike Bill Clinton, who stole the show at a recent fund-raiser by mocking his own aging in office -- ''I was always the youngest person who did everything. Now . . . I'm just kind of an old, gray-haired redneck'' -- the vice president has scarcely aged in his seven White House years. No love handles or shoe-polish hair color. He is fanatic about preserving a near-perfect physique.  On the day in 1976 when he learned a congressional seat was coming vacant, he immediately dropped to the floor and started doing push-ups. Today he does crunches on Air Force Two. His perfect abs are a silent rebuke to all those boomer men who have graduated beyond size 36 belts.</p>
        <p>Al Gore is ridiculed for his slow, deliberate speaking style. Why does he plait each sentence as if he were teaching macrame to kindergartners? Does he have to enunciate every consonant? Must he use Tidewater Gentleman grammar at truck stops?</p>
        <p>Probably, yes. There is a plausible reason that Al Gore speaks the way he does. Unlike George W. Bush, he does not have patrician roots. His father was born in a place called Possum Hollow, in a home without running water or electricity, surrounded by folks who spoke Tennessee hillbilly.  Albert Gore Sr. had to commute to Nashville to take night classes in law. He disciplined himself to speak with formal precision, and he raised his boy to be a more perfect version of himself, sending him to St. Albans for polish.</p>
        <p>When his son last ran for president, in 1988, Senator Gore Sr. boasted to me: ''Al's grammar is as near perfect in extemporaneous speeches as you can come by. You can just see the commas falling in.''</p>
        <p>Overt intellectualism is another flaw the American public does not easily forgive. And while he wasn't a spectacular student, Al Gore likes nothing better than immersing himself in a complex subject like arms control or global warming. You can just see his neurons branching.</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton gets away with being brainy by sounding folksy and never making voters feel stupid. George W. doesn't worry about improving on his father's malapropisms. He doesn't read books and is proud of being nonintellectual. But he gets his ideas across as fast as Instant Messaging, and in a caffeine-high, dumbed-down America, that's what counts.</p>
        <p>Another intangible trait of Al Gore's that troubles voters was expressed in a recent New York Times/CNN poll. ''Al Gore acts as if he's not sure what he's thinking, as if he doesn't have a mind of his own,'' said Vera Jeane, a nurse from Bay City, Tex. Indeed, he never rebelled when he was young. ''I always said Al wanted to find out what you wanted to do and do it,'' said Pauline Gore, his mother.</p>
        <p>Doing what is wanted has made Al Gore a dream vice president. When he found out what Bill Clinton wanted him to do to get them re-elected, he shook the tambourine from the White House to a Buddhist temple. It took him months to find the words to separate himself from his boss's personal dishonor. And when he finally did strike a position starkly different from Bill Clinton's, on Elian Gonzalez, he read the country's wishes wrong.</p>
        <p>The more advisers and polls he consults, the less able Al Gore is to listen to his own convictions. Whether he is scared of losing and failing to live up to his father's dream, or scared of winning because the dream is not his own, Al Gore does not convey confidence or passion as a candidate.</p>
        <p>Won't somebody tell him he doesn't have to be Ozymandias? Americans don't want a king, but they might like an authentic Al Gore.</p>
        <p>Gail Sheehy, a contributing editor to Vanity Fair, is the author of ''Hillary's Choice.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gail Sheehy, a contributing editor to Vanity Fair, is the author of ''Hillary's Choice.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
