<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Industry Rebounds in Canada As It Becomes Top U.S. Supplier</title>
    <meta content="12GAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206947"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DE143EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1840" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Industry Rebounds in Canada As It Becomes Top U.S. Supplier</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <dateline>CALGARY, Alberta</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As this summer's driving and air-conditioning season unfolds, Americans may watch gasoline meters spin and utility bills soar and be tempted to think bad thoughts about energy princes in faraway Arabia.</p>
        <p>But, as the ditty dictates, why not blame Canada? Or, more precisely, blame Alberta.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As this summer's driving and air-conditioning season unfolds, Americans may watch gasoline meters spin and utility bills soar and be tempted to think bad thoughts about energy princes in faraway Arabia.</p>
        <p>But, as the ditty dictates, why not blame Canada? Or, more precisely, blame Alberta.</p>
        <p>With the deferential surreptitiousness that some Americans now associate with their northern neighbor, Canada in the last decade nearly doubled its oil exports and nearly tripled its natural gas exports to the United States. Now Canada has definitively emerged as the No. 1 energy supplier to the United States, the world's largest energy importer.</p>
        <p>''Canada is the largest total energy supplier to the United States, greater than Saudi Arabia, Venezuela or Mexico,'' Gordon D. Giffin, the United States ambassador to Canada, said here recently in a speech to the Canadian Association of Petroleum Producers, an industry group. The ambassador diplomatically did not note that oil and gas imports this year account for a big part of the rising United States trade deficit.</p>
        <p>With oil and natural gas prices doubling over the last year, there are no apologies for $30 barrels of oil here in Alberta, Canada's largest oil and gas producing province.</p>
        <p>[To the contrary, this city, Canada's energy capital, rolled out red carpets on Sunday to welcome the World Petroleum Congress, a 54-nation association that is a forum for industry leaders and energy technology experts. The five-day affair is drawing 3,000 delegates and journalists, as well as protesters against global warming.]</p>
        <p>''It's basically our turn; commodity prices have been down for a long time now,'' said J. C. Anderson, chief executive of Anderson Exploration Ltd., a major gas producer. His voice carries not a hint of apology, and his rural Nebraska twang reflects the new, almost seamless North American energy market. ''This business has become a continental game. That border is kaput,'' he added.</p>
        <p>For the last decade, low prices depressed the profitability and value of investments in Canada's oil patch. But in a radical turnaround in the first quarter of this year, profits for Canada's six largest oil and gas producers leaped 130-fold, hitting nearly $500 million.</p>
        <p>With the oil and gas prices that are posted daily on front pages here expected to remain strong through the winter, North America's energy industry is slowly moving out of the shadow of the dot-com high-technology economy. As investors rediscover that the Western world still moves on oil and gas, takeover frenzy has swept this city of corporate headquarters. In one week alone in April, there were three takeover bids for energy companies here. With the United States' capital markets about 40 times the size of Canada's, the United States is pumping billions of new dollars into Canada's energy industry.</p>
        <p>In Alberta, the highest natural gas prices in memory are helping gas dethrone oil as the top fuel for exploration, production and provincial royalty revenue.</p>
        <p>While oil is shuttled around the world in ships, natural gas remains a ''terrestrial commodity,'' economically transported by pipeline. A clean-burning fuel that produces less carbon dioxide than coal or oil, natural gas is making Americans look north with new respect.</p>
        <p>Increasingly the fuel of choice for heating American homes, natural gas is also the preferred fuel for electricity generation instead of coal and nuclear power. Long bottled up here, Alberta natural gas now flows through four new pipelines into the United States.</p>
        <p>''I've been to the end of that pipe, and it's the Brooklyn Navy Yard,'' said Ralph Klein, Alberta's premier, whose government now earns three times as much from natural gas royalties as from oil.</p>
        <p>Referring to a Con Edison gas-fueled electricity generating plant, he added: ''Unbeknownst to most New Yorkers, New York is lit up with Alberta natural gas.''</p>
        <p>Over this decade, American consumption of natural gas is expected to increase by about 50 percent, to 33 trillion cubic feet a year. For electricity generation alone, it is expected to double. The hitch is that American natural gas production has declined by about 5 percent since 1998. To the south, Mexico's state oil company, Pemex, barely satisfies growing local use.</p>
        <p>''We are going to be so tight on natural gas this summer that people are going to say, 'What are we going to do?' '' said Thomas A. Petrie, a Denver-based investment banker in the energy field. ''It's going to create a scramble for gas projects. We are going to look all over the lower 48, but the big projects are going to be in Canada.''</p>
        <p>Or, as Mr. Anderson put it from his corner office in a steel-and-glass tower here: ''We are going to have to drill the pants off this basin. Then, we are going to have to go north.''</p>
        <p>American demand is growing so steadily that even if Canada's gas exports increase 50 percent this decade, as forecast, Canada will only be pacing American growth. And, even though the number of exploration rigs in Alberta is jumping 50 percent this year, geologists say that, after half a century of pumping from the Rocky Mountain foothills, there is no more low-hanging fruit. The future of North American gas production now lies in Canada's geographic and climactic extremes.</p>
        <p>On the east coast, North Atlantic developments off Nova Scotia and Newfoundland are turning the Maritime provinces into a major oil and gas producing area. The United States is the sole export market.</p>
        <p>The region's first major oil project, Newfoundland's Hibernia, started production in November 1997. This May, Exxon Mobil announced plans to increase production by 30 percent this year, to 65 million barrels a day. The province's second large project, Terra Nova, is to begin production early next year. With four other oil projects in the planning stage, a recent government study increased Newfoundland's offshore oil reserves by almost a third, to 2.1 billion barrels.</p>
        <p>Off the coast of Nova Scotia, Sable Offshore Energy Inc., started in January to pump natural gas to New England, is bringing the first piped gas to Maine in a pipeline that goes to Boston. In addition, gas companies are spending $400 million more to explore offshore tracts around the Sable development.</p>
        <p>Here in Canada's West, the energy action is moving north.</p>
        <p>While Alberta's oil production dropped 6 percent last year, it is expected to rebound in coming years as $25 billion worth of investments in northern Alberta's oil sands starts to pay off. These reserves of thick oil, estimated to rival those of Saudi Arabia in size, were largely untouched. But new technologies, including some that use steam and hot water, now render about 15 percent of the deposits -- five billion barrels -- recoverable at a cost of $10 or less a barrel.</p>
        <p>Over this decade, the oil sands portion of Canada's oil production is expected to double, hitting 50 percent by 2005. In Fort McMurray, the northern Alberta epicenter of oil sands mining, there is such a labor shortage that doughnut shops and fast-food shops have had to cut back service until new workers can be brought up from the south.</p>
        <p>Oil sands and North Atlantic production will allow Canada to increase its oil exports to the United States by about 50 percent over this decade. With this increase, Canada will probably surpass Venezuela to become the United States' most important source of imported oil. This expansion takes place in an international economy where low oil prices have allowed world oil consumption to double since 1970, approaching 80 million barrels a day by the end of this year.</p>
        <p>''Last week, I saw a stretched-out Humvee in New York; the week before I saw a Range Rover without a speck of mud driving around London,'' said Martin P. Molyneaux, managing director for research at First Energy Capital, an oil and gas brokerage firm based in Calgary. ''Consumption per vehicle is high. World consumption keeps going northward.''</p>
        <p>On the natural gas front, growing American demand and higher prices are pushing Canada's production frontier north of the Arctic Circle. For years, bad economics, local American Indian reluctance, and environmental opposition blocked development of massive reserves in the Mackenzie River delta and Beaufort Sea area. The deposits, some of the largest in the world, were only viable for development when natural gas prices surpassed $2.50 per million British thermal units. But now with North American gas prices hovering around $4, everyone is looking north.</p>
        <p>''A year ago, nobody was talking about the far north,'' said Pierre R. Alvarez, president of the Canadian Association of Petroleum Producers. ''But now the price has moved substantially, and people are working on it.''</p>
        <p>Gas developers are drawing maps for multibillion-dollar pipelines, negotiating with local Indians for participation and discussing environmental safeguards.</p>
        <p>At stake are the largest known natural gas reserves in North America below the Beaufort Sea. The Mackenzie Delta area is believed to hold nine trillion cubic feet of gas, roughly equal to the gas reserves off the coast of Nova Scotia. To the west of the Mackenzie, Alaska's Prudhoe Bay is believed to hold 25 trillion to 30 trillion cubic feet.</p>
        <p>One proposed 5,000-mile pipeline would run from Prudhoe Bay, potentially underwater to minimize environmental impacts, then south along the Mackenzie River into Northern Alberta to connect with pipelines to the United States. Unlike oil, natural gas is easier to pump cold.</p>
        <p>This line could carry 3.5 billion cubic feet of American and Canadian gas, a 40 percent jump over Canada's current export level to the United States. This October, when the $3 billion Alliance pipeline opens from here to Chicago, Western Canada will have excess pipeline capacity into the United States.</p>
        <p>Energy experts believe consumer pressure will prevail over any environmentalist opposition, and that Canada's Arctic will be opened to gas production by the end of this decade.</p>
        <p>''The U.S. and Canadian utilities are running scared now, almost everybody has overestimated supply and underestimated demand,'' Mr. Molyneaux, the energy analyst, said. He noted that in the last five years 75 percent of new electricity generation in the United States went to natural gas. ''If your energy bills go up by 30 percent, you are not going to be happy about it,'' he added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
