<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daniel Dunham, 71, City Planning Expert</title>
    <meta content="Y26DUN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/26/world/26DUNH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1258214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunham, Daniel C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1D61238F935A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="357" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daniel Dunham, 71, City Planning Expert</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Daniel C Dunham, architect and expert on city planning who specialized in designs for tropical areas, dies at age 71 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Daniel C. Dunham, an architect and an expert on city planning who specialized in designs for the tropics, died on Dec. 19 in New York, where he lived. He was 71.</p>
        <p>The cause of death was heart failure, said his wife, Mary Frances.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Daniel C. Dunham, an architect and an expert on city planning who specialized in designs for the tropics, died on Dec. 19 in New York, where he lived. He was 71.</p>
        <p>The cause of death was heart failure, said his wife, Mary Frances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunham was a professor of architecture and city planning at Columbia University from 1972 to 1985, and from 1985 until his death he was professor of architecture at the City University of New York and associate director of the City College Architectural Center.</p>
        <p>Some of his best-known works were in Bangladesh, where he designed the railway station for Dhaka, completed in 1968 and believed to be the largest such structure in southern Asia. He also designed buildings for Rajshahi University, the Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology and the Mymensingh University of Agriculture.</p>
        <p>In India, he designed clinics and family planning complexes, as well as government housing for low- and middle-income residents.</p>
        <p>Other commissions included the National Energy Center and an extension for the International School in Nouakchott, capital of Mauritania; the Renewable Energy Research Center in Djibouti; and the Qorioley Community Center Complex in Somalia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dunham was born on Feb. 1, 1929, in Omaha. He studied architecture at Harvard, city planning at Columbia and tropical architecture at the School of Tropical Architecture in London.</p>
        <p>He worked frequently as a consultant on projects for the United Nations, the World Bank, the United States Agency for International Development and other aid agencies from the Caribbean to Sri Lanka to China, and wrote books and articles on building in developing countries.</p>
        <p>In addition to his wife, surviving are a daughter, Katherine; a grandson; and a sister, Dayle Holmes, of Tampa, Fla.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
