<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Criticizes Bush's Use of Soft Money</title>
    <meta content="Y06DEM$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1181895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E4DE1238F935A35750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Criticizes Bush's Use of Soft Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE with JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q; Dao, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore turns sights on Republicans, criticizing Gov George W Bush on campaign finance issues; accuses him of flooding campaign with soft money; suggests that if he wins Republican presidential nomination he may not have done so fairly; raises themes for first time in Rhode Island and reiterates them in New York with First Lady Hillary Rodham Clinton; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Turning his sights on the Republicans, Vice President Al Gore criticized Gov. George W. Bush of Texas yesterday on campaign finance issues, saying he was flooding the campaign with soft money, and he suggested that if Mr. Bush won the Republican nomination, he might not have won it fairly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore raised those themes for the first time yesterday in Rhode Island, and repeated them last night in New York in an appearance with Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Turning his sights on the Republicans, Vice President Al Gore criticized Gov. George W. Bush of Texas yesterday on campaign finance issues, saying he was flooding the campaign with soft money, and he suggested that if Mr. Bush won the Republican nomination, he might not have won it fairly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore raised those themes for the first time yesterday in Rhode Island, and repeated them last night in New York in an appearance with Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, who holds a wide lead in polls over former Senator Bill Bradley in virtually every state where Democrats will vote on Tuesday, was responding to reports that Mr. Bush's supporters were spending millions of unrestricted soft money on ads attacking Senator John McCain of Arizona on environmental issues. The ads are running in New York, California and Ohio, the three states with the biggest number of delegates at stake in the Super Tuesday contests.</p>
        <p>''If Governor Bush defeats John McCain in some of these contests on Tuesday, this will raise serious questions about whether he did so fair and square,'' Mr. Gore said as he spoke yesterday at a senior citizens forum in Cranston, R.I.</p>
        <p>''Three of the four candidates have endorsed campaign finance reform,''  Mr. Gore said, in one of his hardest-hitting statements in days. ''Governor Bush has not. And now we see the one candidate who has not called for a ban on soft money using soft money in this contest that will take place on Tuesday. We knew that Governor Bush was in the hip pocket of the special interests; now we find what a deep pocket that is -- $2.5 million all of a sudden flooding into these contests.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore added: ''I believe that it's wrong to flood soft money in these contests. I stand with Bill Bradley, with John McCain and with the vast majority of the American people in saying it is time to have meaningful campaign finance reform in law and a higher standard in this campaign to get rid of the kind of practices that we're seeing in the Republican contest from Governor Bush.''</p>
        <p>He went on to suggest that candidates who received substantial campaign contributions from special interests were likely to be influenced by them. He said special interest contributions, like those from pharmaceutical companies, could make a candidate less likely to vote for cheaper generic drugs. Similarly, he said, those special interests could make a candidate ''less likely to show the courage to say we want to get the pollution out of our environment and have clean air and clean water and take on the problem of global warming.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore himself has been vulnerable on the issue of campaign finance, having been criticized for his  fund-raising tactics in the 1996 campaign. Moreover, a longtime political fund-raiser for Mr. Gore, Maria Hsia, was convicted of five felony counts on Thursday for her role in arranging more than $100,000 in illegal donations to the Democratic Party and its candidates in 1996.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's communications director, Karen Hughes, wasted no time responding to Mr. Gore's comments. Reuters reported that Ms. Hughes  said Mr. Gore's comments had ''a terrible ring of hypocrisy, coming from someone who raised money at a Buddhist temple and whose fund-raiser was just convicted of felony counts as a result.''</p>
        <p>With news reports on the role of special interest money in the Bush campaign, Gore aides said, this was a perfect chance for the vice president to turn the attention away from his own problems and highlight those of his likely Republican opponent.</p>
        <p>In an expansive speech last night at the 92nd Street Y to about 200 supporters, Mr. Gore asserted that the presidency was not ''a place from which to wield power on behalf of the special interests,'' referring to industry and to interests like the National Rifle Association.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore shared the stage with Mrs. Clinton, who is running for a seat in the United States Senate. It was the second time the two have appeared together since Feb. 20, and they appeared to have achieved a relaxed compatibility on stage.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton lauded Mr. Gore for defending ''the new Democrat philosophy'' that he and President Clinton had ''literally pushed forward and spread around the world.''</p>
        <p>In urging New Yorkers to go to the polls, Mr. Gore said: ''Don't give in to the temptation to hold your heart back and worry that you're going to be disappointed. Democracy is always imperfect.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore refrained from running down Mr. Bradley, a tactic he has stopped in the last few days since the vice president has been predicted to win virtually all the states, including New York, with Democratic primaries on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>But just in case anyone was even thinking of voting for his opponent, Mr. Gore mildly criticized some of Mr. Bradley's proposals, especially his health-care plan. Still, he saved his strongest objections for the Republicans, faulting them for opposing abortion rights and favoring vouchers for public schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore made the remarks as he and Mr. Bradley concentrated on the East Coast as they sprinted toward primaries and caucuses in 16 states that Mr. Bradley says will be the decisive moment for his struggling campaign.</p>
        <p>In appearances in Buffalo, Maryland and Cleveland, as well as on talk shows on national television, Mr. Bradley tried to rally his supporters, refusing to give up hope for his campaign despite trailing Mr. Gore by wide margins in polls in almost every state.</p>
        <p>''I agree with Vince Lombardi,'' he said, referring to the former pro football coach in a live interview on ESPN Radio from the ESPN Zone restaurant in Baltimore. ''There is no second place. There is only first place.''</p>
        <p>But while Mr. Bradley continued to preach optimism, some of his aides said they have begun making preparations for his exit from the race soon after Tuesday's vote, working on a final concession speech and discussing the proper time and place to deliver it.</p>
        <p>Asked to comment on those preparations, Eric Hauser, Mr. Bradley's campaign spokesman, said, ''The campaign and candidate are focused on one thing, and that is doing well on Tuesday in as many places as we can.''</p>
        <p>Things look so bleak for Mr. Bradley in California that one of his California campaign coordinators was traveling with him on the East Coast yesterday. And his advance staff was making only tentative plans beyond Tuesday. Mr. Bradley plans to follow the coverage of all of Tuesday's primaries in New York.</p>
        <p>On NBC's ''Meet the Press'' yesterday, Mr. Bradley said he would support Mr. Gore if the vice president became the Democratic Party's nominee. But he said he would not be Mr. Gore's running mate under any circumstances.</p>
        <p>And asked whether Mr. Gore had run an honorable campaign, Mr. Bradley carefully hedged his answer. ''He's said a number of things that are untrue about his own record and about mine,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He added, ''I think things in the last week or so have calmed down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley also said, ''I'm not prepared to say that defeat is on the horizon.'' But when he was asked whether he was prepared to lose, he said, ''I have no doubt I'll be able to deal with whatever is out there. Because I know why I did this.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore told reporters on a flight to Rhode Island yesterday afternoon that he had softened his approach to Mr. Bradley in recent days because Mr. Bradley had gotten softer on him.</p>
        <p>''I thought that his tone changed in the last several days with far less of the attack that had become commonplace,'' Mr. Gore said. ''And I wanted to reciprocate.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE DEMOCRATS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
