<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>McCain, Sure on Military Issues, Is Less Certain on Domestic Ones</title>
    <meta content="09MCCA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1175140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ISSUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">National Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7D6153EF93AA35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>McCain, Sure on Military Issues, Is Less Certain on Domestic Ones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain can speak in great detail about military issues, but he seems less fluent on domestic matters; his pledge that he will never be guided by opinion polls but will always act 'on principle' applies only to national security matters; McCain says that on domestic affairs, it will be helpful to use polls to find out what Americans want; McCain's ideas on domestic matters seem far from fixed or fully developed despite his conservative voting record in 17 years in Congress and his image as reformer; he has yet to explain fully how his vision of conservative reform will translate into comprehensive domestic agenda; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was telling to hear John McCain proclaim his impatience with President Clinton's last State of the Union address.</p>
        <p>''A two-hour marathon,'' Mr. McCain said dismissively, promising reporters that should he be elected president he would keep the ritual address to Congress to a crisp 15 minutes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was telling to hear John McCain proclaim his impatience with President Clinton's last State of the Union address.</p>
        <p>''A two-hour marathon,'' Mr. McCain said dismissively, promising reporters that should he be elected president he would keep the ritual address to Congress to a crisp 15 minutes.</p>
        <p>''I think what you should do is give a vision for America,'' he said, ''not give a laundry list that looks like a Chinese menu with one from column A and one from column B.''</p>
        <p>''I know he likes that,'' he said of the president, ''because he's a policy wonk.'' Mr. McCain by contrast is not a policy wonk, at least when it comes to domestic issues.</p>
        <p>While the Arizona senator can speak in great detail about unneeded weapons systems or his theories of containing rogue state dictators, he seems less fluent on the issues that were not his Senate specialties -- like health care or the environment or education.</p>
        <p>Just a few months ago, Mr. McCain sometimes used the words Medicare and Medicaid interchangeably, mixing up the federal health insurance programs for the elderly and for the poor. He has since stopped.</p>
        <p>And it is instructive that his pledge to audiences that he would never be guided by opinion polls but would always act ''on principle'' applies only to national security matters. On domestic affairs, Mr. McCain says it would be helpful to use polls to find out what Americans want.</p>
        <p>In fact, despite Mr. McCain's reliably conservative voting record in his 17 years in Congress and his image as a reformer, his ideas on domestic matters sometimes seem far from fixed or fully developed. Although he has declared war on pork barrel spending and continues to call for an overhaul of the system of unlimited donations to political parties, he has yet to explain fully how his vision of conservative reform would translate into a comprehensive domestic agenda.</p>
        <p>In some ways, Mr. McCain seems caught between his desire to help people solve big problems and his natural instinct as a conservative Republican to find small-government solutions. Occasionally when voters ask him about difficult social problems, he pledges to gather ''the best minds in America'' to work toward answers. And while Mr. McCain calls himself a ''proud conservative,'' he sometimes agrees with questioners that various federal programs need more money.</p>
        <p>At other moments, Mr. McCain almost plays down the importance of domestic matters when he says he is ''fully prepared to lead'' because of his experience in the military and his expertise in national security affairs.</p>
        <p>The difference in Mr. McCain's command of foreign policy and domestic policy shows on his free-wheeling campaign bus, where reporters can question him all day long. He assesses world leaders and European defense capabilities with gusto. But he was far less animated last month when reporters pressed him at great length on whether he  would stick to his vow against Internet taxation if recession ever loomed or if so much commerce moved to the Internet that states started seeing a decline in sales tax revenue.</p>
        <p>''It will be a permanent ban on Internet taxation,'' Mr. McCain finally said, when questions continued even after he said that Internet commerce was expanding the economy, not cutting into other sales. ''I cannot elaborate,'' he said several times in order to cut off the conversation.</p>
        <p>On another day he became impatient when quizzed closely over when he views an issue as a state matter and when he sees it as a federal concern. ''We're getting into the rarified atmosphere here of the academic Talmudian aspects of the role of the federal government,'' he said as reporters pressed him on federalism. ''I like to deal on the level of the problems today.''</p>
        <p>And while he considers the lack of universal health care coverage a pressing social problem, he shies away from a big government solution, instead proposing tax-free savings accounts to help some people buy insurance and expansion of a current program to insure children. He also says general tax cuts would help people buy insurance.</p>
        <p>''I think every American should have access to health insurance,'' he says. ''I can't force every American to take it.''</p>
        <p>So far, this has mattered little in an insurgent campaign run on a blend of character, biography and reform. ''What's driven the McCain candidacy thus far is his story, his personality, not his issue positions,'' said Whit Ayres, a Republican pollster unaffiliated with any presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>In fact, voters virtually never point to any specific issue when asked why they like him. Katie Koenen, 18, who waited until 3 a.m. for Mr. McCain to arrive for a rally in South Carolina after winning the New Hampshire primary proclaimed him ''more upfront'' than Gov. George W. Bush.</p>
        <p>Margaret Avery, a retired bookkeeper who went to one of Mr. McCain's New Hampshire town hall meetings, said simply, ''I think he's truthful.''</p>
        <p>Audiences even seem appreciative when Mr. McCain admits he has some learning to do. ''I don't claim to you to be an expert on this issue,'' he told a group of young people demanding a solution to global warming at one of his town hall meetings. He promised he would gather experts to study the problem.</p>
        <p>Whether this will all catch up to him is an open question. Mr. Bush is beginning to point to his record as a governor to draw distinctions with Mr. McCain.</p>
        <p>''I stand before you as a governor who led my state to managed-care reform,'' Mr. Bush said today in Delaware. ''Some people in Washington say we can't get anything done because of all the lobbyists and special interests,'' he said, in a reference to Mr. McCain. ''That's somebody who doesn't understand how to lead.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the governor like Ralph Reed also note that Mr. McCain has never unveiled a comprehensive education plan the way Mr. Bush has. Mr. McCain had an education speech scheduled before the New Hampshire primary but canceled it rather than shift the focus in New Hampshire away from the tax cutting and Social Security debate.</p>
        <p>He advocates a test of school vouchers paid for by closing corporate subsidies. And he speaks generally of giving merit pay to teachers based on student performance. Mr. McCain has put forward plans for Social Security, tax cuts, health care and the environment but even as he has done so, he has been hazy on the fine points of his own proposals.</p>
        <p>Should Mr. McCain become the Republican nominee, he will face Democrats who are already researching his voting record in order to paint him as a Gingrich-style Republican out of step with mainstream values.</p>
        <p>He embraced the Contract With America and voted with his party on the budget and tax cut proposals of 1995 that would have made $270 billion in savings in Medicare while granting $245 billion in tax cuts. Democrats are also poised to run against his anti-abortion votes and his votes against gun control.</p>
        <p>Yet for now Mr. McCain has managed to transcend ideology and appeal to voters across a broad spectrum in part because his battle against special interests does not fall neatly along the right-left divide. Conservatives and liberals alike can warm to his promises to take government ''out of the hands of the special  interests and the big money and give it back to you.''</p>
        <p>Even on the polarizing social issue of abortion, Mr. McCain constantly points to his anti-abortion votes in Congress. Yet at the same time, his comments suggesting that he would let his daughter decide whether to have an abortion have created the impression among people on both sides of the question that he is not committed to the cause. He later said that he had misspoken.</p>
        <p>He tells audiences, ''Everyone -- pro-life or pro-choice -- has the same goal, which is to eliminate abortion.''  He also says that he would not use abortion as a litmus test in picking Supreme Court nominees, but would look instead for judges who are strict interpreters of the Constitution.</p>
        <p>He told reporters last month, ''I don't think that anybody in my personal opinion, who can say they adhere to the Constitution would have rendered the Roe v. Wade decision.'' But he also said he would consider judges as nominees not on one decision but on their ''overall philosophy.'' He noted for example that he continued to admire Antonin Scalia even though he had dissented from a  recent decision upholding limits on campaign contributions.</p>
        <p>What adds to the enigma of Mr. McCain is that he sometimes seems to be embarking on a new intellectual journey along the campaign trail.</p>
        <p>After years of voting for Republican tax cuts, Mr. McCain broke with his party's supply-siders in this campaign and advocated that the federal surplus be used for modest tax cuts and for shoring up Social Security. He likes to point out that virtually no one at his town hall meetings asks for a tax cut. And in New Hampshire at least, the primary results suggest he had a better grasp of public sentiment than Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>When voters in New Hampshire spoke of elderly relatives who could not afford prescription drugs, he came up with a federal-state block grant program to help the older people pay for drugs.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain likes to say that his many town hall meetings and inquisitive audiences have helped him. ''I am a better candidate,'' he said one night, summing up his 114 town hall meetings in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE ISSUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
