<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Move Improves Chance For Global Warming Treaty</title>
    <meta content="Y20CLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/20/science/20CLIM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1248998"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Revkin, Andrew C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E7D71E3BF933A15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1309" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Move Improves Chance For Global Warming Treaty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Revkin, Andrew C</byline>
      <dateline>THE HAGUE, Nov. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American negotiators, shifting stance at talks on global warming treaty, say US would be willing to limit its use of forest projects to reach target for reducing heat-trapping greenhouse gases; shift brightens prospects for treaty; comes in face of mounting criticism from Europe and private environmental groups; disagreements in pivotal negotiations have focused on forests as 'sinks,' in which carbon dioxide is removed by trees which store carbon in wood and soil (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a shift that is likely to brighten prospects for a global warming treaty, American negotiators at talks here have said the United States would be willing to limit its use of forest projects to reach its target for reducing heat-trapping greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The new stance, signaled in the face of mounting criticism from Europe and private environmental groups, came this weekend, halfway through a contentious two-week session aimed at writing the fine print for the treaty, called the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a shift that is likely to brighten prospects for a global warming treaty, American negotiators at talks here have said the United States would be willing to limit its use of forest projects to reach its target for reducing heat-trapping greenhouse gases.</p>
        <p>The new stance, signaled in the face of mounting criticism from Europe and private environmental groups, came this weekend, halfway through a contentious two-week session aimed at writing the fine print for the treaty, called the Kyoto Protocol.</p>
        <p>The treaty was worked out by more than 170 nations in Japan in 1997. If ratified, it would commit three dozen industrialized nations to reduce their combined greenhouse-gas releases by 2012 to at least 5 percent below emissions in 1990, with each country taking a unique target depending on its emissions.</p>
        <p>But the rules and means to achieve cuts have never been resolved, with this session, called the Sixth Conference of the Parties, intended as the denouement.</p>
        <p>Many disagreements in these pivotal negotiations have focused on the role of forests as ''sinks,'' in which carbon dioxide, a warming gas flooding the atmosphere from the burning of fossil fuels and forests, is removed by trees, which store the carbon in wood and soil.</p>
        <p>The United States, by far the largest emitter of greenhouse gases, calculated last summer that its vast forests, by absorbing up to 300 million tons a year of carbon dioxide, could help it get halfway to its pledged target under the treaty, reducing emissions by 2012 to 7 percent below where they were in 1990. It also wants to get credit for paying for forest-protection and tree-planting projects in other countries.</p>
        <p>But Europe, too crowded to take advantage of forests, and many private environmental groups say crediting forest growth would allow the United States and other large, forested countries to meet their targets without undertaking the much harder, and potentially costlier, task of reducing greenhouse gases at the source: mainly tailpipes and smokestacks.</p>
        <p>''This is a major free ride for the U.S., a get-out-of-jail-free card the  likes of which has never been seen,'' said Kert Davies, a representative of  Greenpeace USA lobbying at the talks.</p>
        <p>Last week, in sharply rejecting a preliminary American proposal for  phasing in the use of forest credits, the European Union described sinks as ''a free gift.''</p>
        <p>Frank E. Loy, the under secretary of state for global affairs and chief  American negotiator, said forests were one of several treaty components that American negotiators see as essential to any agreement that is both effective and cost-effective -- and that will satisfy a highly skeptical Senate, whose approval the treaty needs.</p>
        <p>''If an agreement doesn't take into account the fact that forests can act  as a huge source of emissions as well as an important opportunity to reduce emissions, it will be a very unsatisfactory exercise,'' Mr. Loy said.</p>
        <p>But other American negotiators explained that they were prepared to  compromise on the amount of carbon dioxide absorbed by forests for which a country could receive credit, moving beyond an earlier proposal that would phase in credit for forests from 2008 to 2012.</p>
        <p>''We are prepared to discount some of the tons that would come through the process,'' one official said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Loy said the United States was committed to acting aggressively on home turf to curtail emissions, but insisted that there should be flexibility to use every emissions-cutting tool available wherever it could be used most effectively.</p>
        <p>''We've always thought of sinks as being part of the answer,'' he said.  ''They're not intended to take the place of investments in environmentally sound technologies.''</p>
        <p>In a news conference late last week, Jos Delbeke, the head of the climate section of the European Commission, said that so far, the American proposal was ''far too vague and far too incomplete'' and would be acceptable only when there were hard numbers showing a clear retreat from large forest credits.</p>
        <p>Many other disagreements between blocs of countries remained unresolved over the weekend, including whether countries should be able to get credit toward emissions goals for investing in pollution-cutting projects abroad, and whether such projects should include controversial technologies like nuclear power and ''clean coal'' plants -- or forest projects.</p>
        <p>Environmental campaigners used theatrics to make points. On Saturday, several thousand people from 40 countries built a dike of 50,000 sandbags around the sprawling convention center, meant to highlight one of the perils expected in a warmer world. Scientists predict that continued global warming will disrupt ecosystems and weather patterns and also raise sea levels as glaciers melt.</p>
        <p>In the lobby, demonstrators presented a petition seeking much deeper emissions cuts to the president of the conference, Jan Pronk, the Dutch environment minister. ''We're trying to build a dike of words,'' Mr. Pronk responded.</p>
        <p>Acknowledging the rifts still sharply dividing countries, he added, ''It's extremely difficult to take actions now to protect people not yet born, but that is what we are trying to do.''</p>
        <p>As several thousand delegates combed through hundreds of bracketed paragraphs in reams of treaty text, lobbyists for companies touting  everything from windmills to nuclear plants roamed the hallways, along with a similar number of campaigners from environmental groups.</p>
        <p>Despite the clashing mosaic of stances, many delegates, from both rich and poor countries, said they had a sense -- after more than a decade of meetings leading to the treaty -- that agreement could be reached, mainly because a growing number of nations were seeing the deal as an opportunity for economic growth and not simply an environmental pact.</p>
        <p>''There is no great aggressiveness from the developing countries now, not like there was in 1990,'' said a delegate from a large Asian country. He added that rich countries, in turn, are now asking ''how do we expand commercial investment opportunities and sell our technologies.''</p>
        <p>Observers who had attended previous talks agreed that the atmosphere  was different, and that Europe and the United States -- despite outward discord -- seemed poised for compromise.</p>
        <p>''The gulf doesn't seem to be as wide,'' said Senator Michael B. Enzi, Republican of Wyoming, a coal-rich state. He attended the Kyoto talks and another session in Buenos Aires and remains skeptical that the treaty will be fair to the United States. ''Compared to Kyoto,'' he said, ''they almost appear to be agreeing.''</p>
        <p>Still, some camps seemed determined to scuttle the talks. One point deemed essential by the United States is some clause that at least implies that fast-growing countries like China and India commit more concretely to initiate climate-protection programs. The Senate has said it will not approve a treaty without this.</p>
        <p>To some, this presented an opportunity. A person working with oil-producing countries described how they were successful -- for the third climate-treaty conference in a row -- at putting pressure on the organizers before the opening gavel to delete from the agenda any consideration of such a commitment from developing nations.</p>
        <p>On Sunday afternoon, as delegates girded for the increasingly intense sessions to come, many sought guidance at an ''Ecumenical Service on Climate Change'' at the Cloister Church.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
