<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FORD SAID TO PLAN IMPROVED MILEAGE IN SPORT UTILITIES</title>
    <meta content="27AUTO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1218046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fuel Efficiency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Green Tech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E7D71F3AF934A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FORD SAID TO PLAN IMPROVED MILEAGE IN SPORT UTILITIES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, July 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co plans to increase average fuel economy of its sport utility vehicles by 25 percent, or roughly five miles a gallon, over next five years; increase would be first major change in fuel economy of any passenger vehicle class in almost 20 years; Ford, at least at first, does not plan to pass extra cost of producing more fuel-efficient vehicles directly to customers, expecting increased sales to offset lower profits (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company has decided to increase the average fuel economy of its sport utility vehicles by 25 percent over the next five years, people involved in the company's plans said today. The increase, amounting to roughly five miles a gallon, would be the first significant change in the fuel economy of any class of passenger vehicle in almost two decades.</p>
        <p>Ford is convinced that Americans want to buy more fuel-efficient vehicles and will steer their purchases to companies they perceive as environmentally responsible, the people said. The company's new stance is also a response to environmental concerns about the automobile's role in global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company has decided to increase the average fuel economy of its sport utility vehicles by 25 percent over the next five years, people involved in the company's plans said today. The increase, amounting to roughly five miles a gallon, would be the first significant change in the fuel economy of any class of passenger vehicle in almost two decades.</p>
        <p>Ford is convinced that Americans want to buy more fuel-efficient vehicles and will steer their purchases to companies they perceive as environmentally responsible, the people said. The company's new stance is also a response to environmental concerns about the automobile's role in global warming.</p>
        <p>At least at first, the company does not intend to pass the extra cost of producing more fuel-efficient vehicles directly to American customers, two people close to the plan said. The company is betting instead that improved fuel economy will increase sales more than enough to offset lower profits on each vehicle. Better gas mileage and lower operating costs for Ford sport utilities could eventually increase demand enough to allow the company to sell them with fewer rebates, and possibly even raise prices.</p>
        <p>Ford executives hope that the more fuel-efficient sport utilities will give all of their brands an image of environmental responsibility, people close to the company's planning said. That could help sales of the company's cars, minivans and pickup trucks.</p>
        <p>The move by Ford, which sells 800,000 sport utilities a year -- representing about a fifth of its total domestic sales -- is a sharp reversal. The company started and led the decade-long trend toward sport utility vehicles, the biggest of which consume more than twice as much gasoline a mile as the average car. The Ford Excursion is the world's largest sport utility, getting 10 miles to the gallon in the city, and 13 on the highway.</p>
        <p>The decision to improve mileage comes even as recent efforts in Congress to mandate an increase in fuel economy have failed, partly because of lobbying by Ford and other automakers.</p>
        <p>Much of the mileage improvement will be achieved through changes to Ford's larger sport utilities: the Ford Explorer, Expedition and Excursion, the Mercury Mountaineer, the Lincoln Navigator and the Range Rover. Ford engineers say that there are many small steps that they can take to improve fuel economy, from making auto parts lighter to adjusting engines. But lighter auto parts are usually more expensive, because they need to be made from aluminum instead of steel, while engine design alterations must be made with great care to avoid reducing vehicles' towing capacity. Ford executives declined to estimate the cost of these changes.</p>
        <p>Part of the improvement in Ford's average fuel economy will come from the introduction in September of the Ford Escape, which is slightly smaller than the Ford Explorer and uses a lightweight car underbody instead of a heavy pickup-truck underbody. With a four-cylinder engine, the Escape gets up to 28 miles a gallon on the highway</p>
        <p>Ford will not achieve its fuel-economy improvement by taking advantage of either of the loopholes that it and others have used in recent years: building vehicles like the Excursion to be so large that they are excluded from the federal averages, and building vehicles that qualify for alternative-fuel mileage credits. The Excursion will be counted as Ford pursues its 25 percent improvement.</p>
        <p>Ford, General Motors and DaimlerChrysler are building huge numbers of minivans, pickup trucks and midsize cars that can burn either gasoline or nearly pure ethanol. These vehicles are counted in the averages as though they have triple their actual mileage, even though only 100 of the nation's 170,000 service stations sell ethanol.</p>
        <p>Jacques Nasser, Ford's chief executive, is scheduled to fly to Washington on Thursday to announce the company's decision at the National Press Club, people involved in the company's plans said.</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler and G.M., Ford's main rivals in the sport utility market, declined to comment on Ford's move, saying only that some of their models were already fuel-efficient. Detroit automakers, including Ford, have said in the past that improved mileage for sport utilities would require sacrifices in engine power and vehicle size that American consumers would not tolerate.</p>
        <p>Ford, G.M. and DaimlerChrysler each have a quarter of the sport utility market. Foreign automakers divide up the remaining share.</p>
        <p>G.M. has just finished improving the gas mileage of its full-size sport utility vehicles and pickup trucks by 5 percent over the last three years by completely redesigning them for the first time in a decade. But G.M. and other automakers have not improved their fuel-economy averages, increasing the power, size and gas consumption of some models even as others have become more efficient.</p>
        <p>Ford voluntarily cleaned up its sport utility vehicles' tailpipe emissions two years ago to make them as clean as cars' emissions. While the cost has approached $100 a vehicle, and while many rivals have not yet followed suit, Ford officials say that decision has been a selling point.</p>
        <p>William C. Ford Jr., Ford's chairman since the start of last year and a great-grandson of Henry Ford, is an outspoken environmentalist who has called for the auto industry to address global warming. At the company's annual meeting two months ago in Atlanta, he acknowledged the environmental and safety drawbacks of sport utilities.</p>
        <p>There have been a few small signs in Washington that Federal fuel-economy standards, little changed since the mid-1980's, might be reconsidered next year. But there is no indication that the government might require nearly as big of an improvement as Ford is planning. Mr. Nasser intends to present the plan as an example of how the auto industry can improve fuel economy voluntarily, and will not call for tighter federal regulations.</p>
        <p>Automakers are currently required to sell cars with an average fuel economy -- based on 55 percent city driving and 45 percent highway driving -- of 27.5 miles a gallon and so-called light trucks with an average fuel economy of 20.7 miles a gallon. Sport utilities, vans and pickup trucks are all counted as light trucks and now represent half of the American auto market, partly because manufacturers have switched production away from cars as low gasoline prices and a strong economy in the 1990's produced a soaring demand for large, but gas-guzzling, vehicles. Until now, Ford has barely met the averages, and its sport utilities have done especially badly.</p>
        <p>President Clinton raised the fuel-economy standard for sport utilities, minivans and pickup trucks by two-tenths of a mile per gallon in 1993 and 1994, to 20.7 miles per gallon. When Republicans took control of the House and Senate in 1995, they began amending the federal budget each year to prevent the Transportation Department from spending any money to study the issue or tighten standards. Each annual budget since then has included the same prohibition, but support for the provision has dwindled as light trucks have increased as a share of the market.</p>
        <p>High gasoline prices prompted an effort this spring by Western senators, whose constituents drive long distances, and by environmentalists, to overturn the ban. Under a recent Senate compromise, the freeze on fuel-economy standards will remain for another year while the National Academy of Sciences reviews federal fuel-economy policy.</p>
        <p>Representative Joe Knollenberg, a Michigan Republican on the House Appropriations Committee, has blocked fuel-economy changes on the House side. His chief of staff, Paul Welday, said that Ford's latest move was a good one if it helped sell sport utility vehicles, but would strengthen those who want tighter standards.</p>
        <p>''Inside the Beltway, it will only fuel the fires of those who believe that if Ford can do that, everybody else should be forced to do that,'' Mr. Welday said.</p>
        <p>Daniel Becker, the energy policy director at the Sierra Club, said environmentalists would use Ford's decision in their lobbying. ''This shows that the people who say you can't make cars cleaner and more fuel-efficient are wrong,'' he said. ''This shows that a company that wants to improve fuel economy can do so.''</p>
        <p>Ford officials believe that they can improve mileage while maintaining the safety of their vehicles' occupants. Occupants of lightweight, subcompact cars tend to fare poorly in collisions. But a variety of recent studies have found that vehicles weighing 3,000 to 3,500 pounds -- the weight of a midsize or large car -- tend to be very safe; further weight provides only a little additional safety for the occupants, while tremendously increasing the risk to other motorists during collisions. Ford's current sport utilities weigh from 3,700 pounds for a two-wheel-drive Explorer to 7,200 pounds for an Excursion with four-wheel drive.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser's plans have provoked some nervousness within Ford that the automaker may be limiting its ability to respond if gas prices fall or if consumers begin demanding even more powerful vehicles. ''There is a lot of struggle within the company over whether this is the right number and the right time frame,'' a person involved in the plan said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
