<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WARMING'S EFFECTS TO BE WIDESPREAD</title>
    <meta content="12CLIM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1206901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D7173EF931A25755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1541" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WARMING'S EFFECTS TO BE WIDESPREAD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW C. REVKIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A warming of the global climate is likely to have substantial consequences -- for better and worse -- around the United States in coming decades, including bumper crops in the heartland, chronic erosion of coasts, summer water shortages and winter floods in the West and a future New York City that steams in summer like present-day Atlanta.</p>
        <p>These are a few of the predictions made in the first thorough federal assessment of the possible effect on the country, region by region, of a warming trend that many scientists expect will characterize coming decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A warming of the global climate is likely to have substantial consequences -- for better and worse -- around the United States in coming decades, including bumper crops in the heartland, chronic erosion of coasts, summer water shortages and winter floods in the West and a future New York City that steams in summer like present-day Atlanta.</p>
        <p>These are a few of the predictions made in the first thorough federal assessment of the possible effect on the country, region by region, of a warming trend that many scientists expect will characterize coming decades.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, mainstream scientists are concluding that a buildup of heat-trapping gases like carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has contributed to warming in the last 100 years, and they say the trend is likely to carry well into the new century.</p>
        <p>Some of the growth in these so-called greenhouse gases, scientists say, is caused by the burning of fossil fuels, destruction of forests and other human activities.</p>
        <p>Temperatures nationwide rose about one degree in the 20th century, and the report estimated the potential effects of further warming by using a ''business as usual'' assumption, in which carbon dioxide levels continued to grow at the rate of recent years. At this pace, the average temperature in the country would rise 5 to 10 degrees in the next century, although the authors stressed that this was only one possibility. To put that in perspective, the world is 5 to 9 degrees warmer than in the last ice age, 18,000 to 20,000 years ago.</p>
        <p>The study, which is to be released today by the Clinton administration for 60 days of public review, was ordered by Congress in 1990 to help lawmakers identify vulnerabilities and potential benefits of the warming trend. But it kicked into high gear only three years ago, when computer models grew sophisticated enough to analyze links between the atmosphere and oceans and local systems like crops and forests.</p>
        <p>The assessment includes an illustrated summary and a series of technical analyses of the effect of a warmer world on forestry, fresh water, farming, coasts and human health. The report will be on the Internet at www.nacc.usgcrp.gov.</p>
        <p>The report forecasts some profound changes, with many regions of the country seeing conditions shift to those of their present-day neighbors to the south.</p>
        <p>In the mountains of the Pacific Northwest, rising stream temperatures are very likely to harm migrating salmon, the report said.</p>
        <p>In California, less snow in winter would lead to less runoff from melting snow in the late spring, reducing water supplies during the summer growing season. The Southwest would see rising precipitation that could cause shrubby forests to overtake desert landscapes.</p>
        <p>The study says one of the most likely of all consequences from continued warming would be coastal erosion and destructive storm surges as sea level steadily rises.</p>
        <p>In Eastern cities, the summer heat index, combining humidity and temperature, is likely to rise, so that as New York City takes on Southern steaminess, Atlanta will see hot spells more typical of Houston.</p>
        <p>The biggest benefits are likely to come from the positive effect of rising carbon dioxide concentrations on plants, which rely on the gas for photosynthesis. Using computer models of climate, crops and forest health, the study found that the country could see rising yields and falling prices for food and timber. The falling prices would be good for consumers but could hurt some timber companies and farmers as already tenuous profit margins shrink.</p>
        <p>But scientists who conducted the study cautioned that the benefits would not be uniform. For example, while farmers in the Northern plains could see gains, those in Southern states could see losses because of increased risk of droughts and damaging floods as more rain falls in drenching downpours.</p>
        <p>The good news should be tempered, too, because the study did not calculate possible agricultural losses because of flourishing weeds or migrating insect pests, its authors said.</p>
        <p>And the composition of wild forests is likely to change, with some species that are considered hallmarks of particular regions disappearing. For example, the sugar maple, the New York state tree and an important species for tourism, is likely to vanish from all but the most northern parts of the state as its preferred colder climatic zone moves north.</p>
        <p>The warming is likely to keep shipping lanes in Alaska and the Great Lakes free of ice longer, easing the movement of oil and other goods.</p>
        <p>But other effects could negate any savings, the study concluded. Water levels in the Great Lakes are expected to drop, increasing the need for costly dredging of channels.</p>
        <p>In Alaska, the effects of the warming have already been felt and are requiring costly adjustments, with roads and air strips requiring constant repair as underlying permafrost thaws and buckles, scientists said. Native Alaskans, who rely on ice-dwelling seals for food, are finding it more difficult to hunt, said Gunter Weller, a climatologist at the University of Alaska Fairbanks, who is participating in the project.</p>
        <p>''For the native community or the oil industry or the fishing industry, this is no longer some nebulous global thing coming in 100 years,'' Dr. Weller said. ''These are real things in real time that are really occurring.''</p>
        <p>Scientists from dozens of government agencies, universities, private groups and industries conducted the studies and more than 300 independent reviewers offered comments, the authors said. The overview's three principal authors were Dr. Thomas R. Karl, director of the National Climatic Data Center in Asheville, N.C.; Anthony Janetos of the World Resources Institute in Washington; and Dr. Jerry M. Melillo of the Marine Biological Laboratory in Woods Hole, Mass.</p>
        <p>As the overview moved from early to final drafts in the last few months, the politics of climate intruded, with intense tugs of war being felt by some scientists involved in the work over how to word conclusions.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in recent weeks the emphasis changed, participants said, with the focus shifting somewhat toward the positive consequences for agriculture, for example.</p>
        <p>Also, the 145-page overview was released even though not all the underlying regional studies are complete, a decision that drew criticism from scientists from both ends of the political spectrum.</p>
        <p>''There's been pressure all along that the synthesis had to come out first because of the election,'' said a scientist who shares the Clinton administration position that global warming is a serious problem, but who is still involved in the report and thus spoke only on condition of anonymity. ''It's unfortunate, because the whole process would have been stronger if you did it the right way. Then the critics wouldn't have anything to say.''</p>
        <p>Over the weekend, officials at the White House said the summary was released ahead of time only because the final work on some of the underlying studies had been delayed.</p>
        <p>Apart from the timing, a variety of experts involved in preparing the document, including people from industry and advocacy groups, say it represents a real consensus and that its findings are significant.</p>
        <p>Thomas F. Cecich, vice president for environmental safety at the drug company Glaxo Wellcome and a member of the team that wrote the national overview, called the report a first look at a dizzyingly complicated system. He said that everyone involved tried to filter out politics and preconceptions. ''I think it's been a fair and open and scientifically valid process,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In particular, many scientists said, the effort, if continued and refined, could offer the first opportunity for the country to incorporate long-term climate projections into its planning for everything from bridge building to crop planting.</p>
        <p>The report concludes that society, for the most part, will probably be able to adapt to many of the coming shifts, but that some natural systems -- alpine meadows, coral reefs, mangrove swamps and the like -- will be damaged or disappear because they are either hemmed in by man-made structures or geography or simply cannot keep pace with the rate of temperature change.</p>
        <p>The authors stressed that the consequences described in the study -- like the visions of Scrooge's future in ''A Christmas Carol'' -- mainly represent developments that may be, not things that must be.</p>
        <p>And there will always be surprises, said Dr. Karl, one of the main authors. ''There are a lot of uncertainties with respect to interactions between natural systems, human systems and climate.''</p>
        <p>Even if the surprises are good news, he said, humans will not necessarily be able to exploit them. ''Usually, if something is not anticipated, you can't take advantage of it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
