<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supporting The Cause On a Cruise</title>
    <meta content="11SHIP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/11/business/11SHIP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1254395"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nation, the (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE7DB143FF932A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supporting The Cause On a Cruise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <dateline>ABOARD M.S. RYNDAM, off Cuba, Dec. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Three hundred readers of The Nation magazine, America's oldest weekly, gather on luxury cruise that benefits magazine financially and participants intellectually and emotionally (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three hundred readers of The Nation magazine sipped coffee and ate breakfast pastries in a dimly lighted auditorium where they had gathered to hear a lecture about the environment, ''Are Humans an Endangered Species?''</p>
        <p>The panelists -- the politician and activist Tom Hayden, the novelist Barbara Kingsolver, the Nation columnist Patricia J. Williams, the radio talk-show host Jim Hightower and the newspaper columnist Molly Ivins -- spoke for three hours on subjects as various as chlorofluorocarbons, atmospheric radiation, God and global warming.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three hundred readers of The Nation magazine sipped coffee and ate breakfast pastries in a dimly lighted auditorium where they had gathered to hear a lecture about the environment, ''Are Humans an Endangered Species?''</p>
        <p>The panelists -- the politician and activist Tom Hayden, the novelist Barbara Kingsolver, the Nation columnist Patricia J. Williams, the radio talk-show host Jim Hightower and the newspaper columnist Molly Ivins -- spoke for three hours on subjects as various as chlorofluorocarbons, atmospheric radiation, God and global warming.</p>
        <p>The audience was rapt. This was serious stuff.</p>
        <p>But it was a little hard to take it all that seriously in this unctuous setting. The liberal opinion makers on the panel sat on a stage flanked by 12-foot-tall glass and metal tulips, in front of a swaying sequined curtain better suited to a Las Vegas floor show, as a public address system kept booming something about the win-a-cruise bingo game at 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>So it went on The Nation cruise, where the nurturing of an ideology clashes with the cold, hard reality of keeping a magazine afloat in fiscally challenging times, not to mention Marxists who do not disdain cruises in a good cause. This year, the third annual Nation cruise attracted 310 ''silver-haired pinkos,'' as Ms. Kingsolver described her audience, to the chagrin of some. Each had paid $1,900 to $2,900 for the privilege of attending this ''floating palace of populism'' as Mr. Hightower described it: a Holland America cruise ship, the M.S. Ryndam, which features a quarter-mile jogging track, a casino, 24-hour room service and a daily lecture on the art of cigar appreciation.</p>
        <p>This year is the Nation's 135th year, making it the oldest weekly magazine in America, and yet it has never turned a profit, said Victor Navasky, its publisher since 1978. (He added that there was a rumor the magazine once turned a profit for three years, but he has been unable to figure out when.) The magazine has instead supported itself with contributions from private donors like Michael Douglas and Paul Newman; some minor fund-raising efforts and some ad and subscription sales. According to the Audit Bureau of Circulations, the magazine's rate base, the circulation guaranteed to advertisers, is about 97,500.</p>
        <p>But that is all changing now, Mr. Navasky said in an interview over a breakfast of sausage links and scrambled eggs in the Rotterdam Room. This year the magazine is the closest it has ever been to profitability: in 1996, the magazine lost $900,000, he said; in 1998, $300,000, and last year, it only lost $166,000. This year, The Nation might break even, he said.</p>
        <p>In order to make money, however, the magazine has found itself relying on fund-raising techniques that do not quite fit with the themes of anti-commercialism in its pages.</p>
        <p>On the Ryndam, for example, there was a counter spread with Nation pamphlets advertising The Nation Platinum Visa card, which is illustrated with an Edward Koren drawing of Uncle Sam reading the magazine and holding his head in shock. The Nation, reads the pamphlet, has been ''politically charged since 1865.'' The Visa program, despite some criticism from readers about its capitalist aspirations, made about $50,000 last year for The Nation, Mr. Navasky said.</p>
        <p>And there is The Nation Legacy program, which boldly encourages potential donors to make bequests to The Nation in their will. Mr. Navasky said that arrangement was by its nature a mixed blessing.</p>
        <p>''A lawyer calls you up and says, 'I've got some good news and some bad news,' '' he said last week. '' 'The bad news is that Mr. So-and-So died. The good news is that he went back and forth for 15 years about who would get the money, and for a while there it was the A.C.L.U., but guess what? You won the draw.' ''</p>
        <p>While the platinum Visa card and the predeath bequests are unconventional ways for a magazine to make money, the cruise is perhaps most unconventional. For the last three years -- as long as the cruise has been up and running -- Nation patrons have complained vigorously about the fact that these fund-raising seminars are held on cruise ships, which have been accused of exploiting nonunion employees as well as being environmental polluters and vandals of fragile ocean ecosystems, cruise patrons said.</p>
        <p>But they keep coming back: 375 patrons attended the first cruise, 175 attended last year's and more than 300 attended this year's trip, which cruised from Fort Lauderdale and visited Half Moon Cay in the Bahamas; Georgetown, Grand Cayman; Cozumel, Mexico; and Key West.</p>
        <p>On past cruises, repeat guests like John O'Neill, a Marxist who looked more like a Republican heavy in his spanking-white deck shoes, Rolex watch and Holland America windbreaker -- have tried to organize unions for the ship's workers.</p>
        <p>(Sometimes, Nation patrons complain about issues unrelated to the cruise venue. On last year's cruise to Alaska, the Nation contributor Christopher Hitchens made a crude joke about Princess Diana, prompting a women's caucus session. This year, verbal fisticuffs broke out between those who supported Al Gore versus those who supported Ralph Nader.)</p>
        <p>And on every cruise, there are loud complaints about the fuel being used to propel the boat from one tourist destination to the next.</p>
        <p>''It bothers me that we are burning a huge amount of petroleum to be at sea,'' Ms. Kingsolver said at the global warming conference. ''And if we did nothing but sit on this ship and consume food and create garbage, that would be worse. But if everybody who can gets off the ship and walks 100 feet away from the buyers and sellers and money-lenders in port and gets to see what a mangrove swamp is or see some of the endemic species, then that person will take away a concern for global warming and disappearing species.''</p>
        <p>(Later, Mr. Navasky sent a note up to the stage to be read aloud by Mr. Hightower, the panel's moderator, which advised the audience not to worry, that the fuel powering the ship was a vegetable oil derived from ''genetically altered mung beans gently harvested by unionized workers.'')</p>
        <p>Guests are hardly dispassionate on what most of them conceive of as a highly ironic arrangement.</p>
        <p>''There is a certain irony, that is for sure,'' said Suzanne Ivester, a copy editor from Knoxville, Tenn. ''We're burning fuel, the cruise employees have no unions, and at times I wonder if it doesn't make sense just to have this in a hotel somewhere.''</p>
        <p>Barbara Williams, Mr. Hayden's wife, called the cruise ''one of the necessary evils of keeping something afloat. I'm married to a politician so I understand those things.''</p>
        <p>Of course, the reason to do the cruise despite the fat-cat trappings is that it makes money for the magazine -- about $750 a person, and if you consider that 300 people paid to attend this year, well, that's a good piece of change.</p>
        <p>One of the richest ironies of The Nation cruises is that Mr. Navasky was inspired by the success of a similar cruise program run by The National Review, which is as right-wing as The Nation is left-wing liberal. Not only that: Eric Alterman, a Nation contributor, wrote an essay for the magazine in 1997 about a week he spent on a cruise to Alaska with The National Review, describing in vicious detail the elaborate food, the servile staff and the ostentatious surroundings with a disdain that would be telling and amusing if it weren't the exact same ship The Nation cruised on this year, the M.S. Ryndam, that he were describing.</p>
        <p>''My gosh, I didn't even realize that,'' Mr. Navasky said. ''Oops.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, it is difficult to hold a serious dinner discussion about the tragedy of post-communist Russia when two dozen Indonesian waiters are conducting a parade of baked alaskas past your table. But the idea is to create a sense of community with other Nation readers.</p>
        <p>''It is wonderful to be a leftist surrounded by other leftists, and not feel solitary and weird about it,'' Ms. Kingsolver said. ''It is such a relief to be able to sit at a dinner table and know that you are not going to hear a sexist joke or a racist remark about the wait staff. There are so many Republicans out there. You just don't know where they'll turn up.''</p>
        <p>And, of course, there may be a kind of smug satisfaction in criticizing the hypocrisy of the cruise itself, several passengers said.</p>
        <p>''Complaining about it gives you something to do,'' Stan Ivester, a University Press editor based in Knoxville, said. ''Other than skeet-shooting off the back of the boat.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
