<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Split Geological Personality of Mars Emerges</title>
    <meta content="14MARS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1183745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mars Global Surveyor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Maps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3DA173BF937A25750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Split Geological Personality of Mars Emerges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mars Global Survey keeps orbiting planet 12 time a day, well into third year of its mission, taking mapping pictures of landscape that are up to 50 times as detailed as any previous photograpy there; sharper focus is giving scientists a clearer and more intriguing view of planet's two-faced geology; ancient cratered highlands of southern hemisphere of Mars could not be more different from low, flat basins of north, possibly the basin of former ocean; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Despite the loss of two Mars-bound spacecraft last year, the reliable Mars Global Surveyor keeps orbiting the planet 12 times a day, well into the third year of its mission, and taking mapping pictures of the landscape that are up to 50 times as detailed as any previous photography there. The sharper focus is giving scientists a clearer and more intriguing view of the planet's two-faced geology.</p>
        <p>The ancient cratered highlands of the southern hemisphere of Mars could not be more different from the low, flat plains of the north, possibly the basin of a former ocean. A new gravity survey suggests how water from the south once found its way to the northern basin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Despite the loss of two Mars-bound spacecraft last year, the reliable Mars Global Surveyor keeps orbiting the planet 12 times a day, well into the third year of its mission, and taking mapping pictures of the landscape that are up to 50 times as detailed as any previous photography there. The sharper focus is giving scientists a clearer and more intriguing view of the planet's two-faced geology.</p>
        <p>The ancient cratered highlands of the southern hemisphere of Mars could not be more different from the low, flat plains of the north, possibly the basin of a former ocean. A new gravity survey suggests how water from the south once found its way to the northern basin.</p>
        <p>Even the poles are, well, poles apart in appearance. The differences in the size, content and seasonal change in the polar ice caps were recognized in earlier spacecraft photography. But more detailed pictures have now revealed something of the distinct underlying topography at the poles and may offer clues to the climate history of Mars.</p>
        <p>Scientists examining Global Surveyor's closeup pictures said the flat, pitted texture of the north polar ice cap resembled cottage cheese, while larger pits, holes and flat-topped mesas of the south polar cap looked more like Swiss cheese.</p>
        <p>The much more extensive northern residual ice cap, the part that survives the summer, is frozen water. The southern residual cap seems to be made of frozen carbon dioxide, or dry ice. Scientists said the new pictures might help them decide if the southern ice cap was only a thin veneer or a solid block extending to depths of more than a mile.</p>
        <p>''The unusual shapes of the land forms on the north and south polar caps suggest that these regions have had different climates and histories for thousands or perhaps even millions of years,'' said Dr. Peter C. Thomas, a planetary geologist at Cornell University.</p>
        <p>The new interpretations of the two faces of Mars were described in interviews last week and in reports in the current issues of the journals Nature and Science. Dr. Thomas was the principal author of the Nature report on the polar ice caps.</p>
        <p>''These findings indicate that the differences between the caps are substantial (rather than reflecting short-lived differences in frost cover), and so support the idea of long-term asymmetry in the polar climates of Mars,'' the report said.</p>
        <p>The southern region, for example, is much drier and colder than the north and stands at a higher elevation. The Swiss cheese aspect of the southern cap, geologists said, appears to be the result of periodic collapses of deposited ice and dust, probably influenced by the underlying topography.</p>
        <p>In another report on Global Surveyor's findings, published in Science, a team of geophysicists led by Dr. Maria Zuber of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology described gravity measurements revealing the structure of the crust of Mars -- and more evidence of the planet's split geological personality.</p>
        <p>The varying pull of gravity caused the spacecraft's orbital altitude to change slightly, the motions showing up in its radio transmissions. From these variations, scientists plotted differences in the planet's subsurface density. They determined that the crust was thickest under the southern highlands.</p>
        <p>A more refined analysis of the gravity measurements has revealed what the scientists described as likely traces of buried channels that could have been carved out by floods of water from the southern highlands flowing into the northern lowlands billions of years ago. The channels, which once were on the surface but have since been filled and covered over by sediments, were as much as 125 miles wide and more than 1,000 miles long.</p>
        <p>If these are indeed water channels, scientists said, they could be important evidence for the existence of oceans and a warmer climate in the planet's early history, conditions that might have been conducive to the emergence of life. In an accompanying article, several scientists cautioned that there could be other explanations of the gravity measurements and that it would be difficult to test which was correct.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
