<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="16FSUM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1230901"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEFDE1E38F935A2575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Rebels and Sri Lanka Forces In Bitter Struggle for City  Separatist rebels have advanced to near the outskirts of Jaffna, the imagined capital of the Tamil homeland that they have fought over for 17 years. At stake are both the city and the northern peninsula upon which it sits. Humiliated by a string of defeats, government forces have spent more than $360 million on military hardware in the last four months, and this month opened a costly offensive to push the rebels back. Since spring, the fighting has forced a third of the peninsula's 470,000 residents to leave their homes.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-8</p>
        <p>Rebels and Sri Lanka Forces In Bitter Struggle for City  Separatist rebels have advanced to near the outskirts of Jaffna, the imagined capital of the Tamil homeland that they have fought over for 17 years. At stake are both the city and the northern peninsula upon which it sits. Humiliated by a string of defeats, government forces have spent more than $360 million on military hardware in the last four months, and this month opened a costly offensive to push the rebels back. Since spring, the fighting has forced a third of the peninsula's 470,000 residents to leave their homes.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Arrest Order for Suharto Kin  Indonesia's President, Abdurrahman Wahid, ordered the arrest of Hutomo Mandela Putra, left, the youngest son of former President Suharto, in connection with a series of deadly bombings, including one on Wednesday that killed 15 people.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Assault on Philippine Rebels  Military planes and helicopter gunships pounded rebel camps in the southern Philippines, in a surprise attack aimed at rescuing 19 foreign and Filipino hostages, whose status was not immediately clear.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Fuel Protests Spread in Europe  Protests grew in the Netherlands and Germany, as Britain and Belgium struggled to recover from paralyzing fuel blockades. In Ireland, Spain and Poland, truckers and farmers joined the movement to disrupt travel to express anger at the rising price of highly taxed fuels.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>U.S. and Iran Officials Meet  Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright and Iran's foreign minister, Kamal Kharazi, joined senior diplomats from six other countries to discuss what to do about Afghanistan and its ruling Taliban.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Army Report on Kosovo Abuses  The United States Army was said to be preparing to issue a once-classified report saying peacekeepers from the 82nd Airborne had threatened and assaulted civilians.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Tape Sparks Uproar in Peru  The broadcasting of a videotape that appears to show an aide to President Alberto Fujimori giving a bribe to an opposition lawmaker threw the government into turmoil.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A9-12, 16</p>
        <p>Republican Ticket Taking New Tack Against Gore  Gov. George W. Bush has shifted his tactics and has begun confronting Vice President Al Gore head-on over the issues, an area long considered to be Mr. Gore's greatest strength.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's running mate, Dick Cheney, has also shifted gears, using especially blunt language to criticize Mr. Gore and his proposals.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Mr. Bush said that negotiators for the Bush and Gore campaigns were near an agreement on formats for the three presidential debates, although ''some sticking points'' remained.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Pledge on Test Ban Treaty  Vice President Gore told Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee of India that if elected president he would make passage of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty his first foreign policy act, and he urged India to adopt the treaty as well.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore told an enthusiastic crowd of students at Howard University that improving schools and access to college must become a major federal priority in coming years.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, appearing on the Don Imus radio program, rejected the suggestion that it could appear hypocritical for him and Mr. Gore to have raised money from the entertainment industry with a concert the night before.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Meeting Set on Secrets Case  President Clinton said he did not believe that Wen Ho Lee had been prosecuted because he is ethnically Chinese but would talk to Attorney General Janet Reno about Dr. Lee's treatment and the handling of case. Dr. Lee was freed on Wednesday after pleading guilty to improperly handling classified information.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Disparate Rulings on Gun Suits  An Illinois judge dismissed Chicago's lawsuit seeking to hold gun makers and retailers responsible for the costs associated with gun violence. But in California, a judge rejected a motion to dismiss similar suits brought by 12 cities and counties.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Effort to Avoid Deportation  Jorge Amaral Munoz, 39, a witness to the assassination of a Mexican presidential candidate in 1994, has requested asylum in the United States, saying his return to Mexico would jeopardize his life. Mr. Amaral has been charged in Mexico with making false statements to officials.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Mayor Has Procedure To Treat Prostate Cancer  Mayor Giuliani had radioactive seeds implanted in his prostate gland, then appeared six hours later at a news conference, saying the procedure had been ''easier than I thought it would be.'' Doctors said the outlook was excellent. Mr. Giuliani said he would return to work early next week. The seeds are the second phase of his treatment, with hormone therapy the first and external radiation the third.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Review of Minor Drug Arrests  Police Commissioner Bernard B. Kerik was said to be intensively reviewing antidrug efforts, examining costs and the high percentage of minor arrests made by detectives.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Bottled-Water Investigation  Complaints of possibly tainted bottled water mounted in the region, even as law enforcement officials said they had not discerned any link or pattern to the reports and had no evidence of bottle tampering.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Nassau County Submits Budget  With two minutes to spare on a midnight deadline, Nassau County Executive Thomas S. Gulotta delivered a four-year plan to solve the financial crisis that brought the county to the brink of bankruptcy and threatened its autonomy.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Religion Journal</p>
        <p>B6</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Talks on Climate Treaty  OPEC country delegates said any treaty on global warming must include a commitment to compensate oil-producing countries if efforts to cut emissions of heat-trapping gases result in a drop in the use of oil.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>A13</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-12</p>
        <p>Larger Themes at Olympics  The 27th Summer Games opened in Sydney with a ceremony that addressed Australia's discriminatory treatment of its indigenous people, celebrated the unprecedented number of female Olympians and applauded a march of unity between North Korea and South Korea.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>I.M.F. to Revamp Lending  The global lender decided to overhaul its loan programs and keep more money available for emergencies, actions sought by Treasury Secretary Lawrence H. Summers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>China Internet Merger  Sohu.com, which went public on the Nasdaq in July, said it would buy ChinaRen.com for 4.4 million shares, or $30 million, about 12.5 percent of Sohu.com's outstanding shares.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>A Pause in Inflation  The Consumer Price Index inched down 0.1 percent in August as energy costs slid 2.9 percent, but analysts said the economic data also held evidence that inflation was edging up, though not at a pace that should worry policy makers just yet.</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Wall Street Bias Suit Settled  Morgan Stanley Dean Witter has settled litigation with a former analyst, Christian Curry, a black man whose complaints about his firing led to an investigation by the Manhattan district attorney and a public apology from the firm. As part of the deal, the firm dropped its countersuit, though a spokesman for the firm asserted, ''Christian Curry gets nothing.'' Mr. Curry said the agreement precluded him from discussing the terms.</p>
        <p>C14</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B7-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A26-27</p>
        <p>Editorials: Soft-money travesties; religious freedom in Russia; the mayor's prostate treatment.  Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B13  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>D12  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A9</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
