<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AUTOS ON FRIDAY/Technology; Hybrid Cars Show Up In M.I.T.'s Crystal Ball</title>
    <meta content="03CARS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Daimlerchrysler Ag</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wald, Matthew L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DF1F30F930A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AUTOS ON FRIDAY/Technology; Hybrid Cars Show Up In M.I.T.'s Crystal Ball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW L. WALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wald, Matthew L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Autos on Friday article on MIT Energy Laboratory's two-year study comparing gas-powered sedan with some hybrid cars that may be feasible by 2020; DaimlerChrysler's lans for hybrid Dodge Durango also described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Massachusetts Institute of Technology and DaimlerChrysler have given their assessments on the future of the automobile, and have both come out in favor of hybrid gasoline-electric cars. But scientists at M.I.T.'s Energy Laboratory, working with computer models, had an easier time predicting costs and benefits of the cars than DaimlerChrysler, working in steel and glass, is likely to have selling them.</p>
        <p>M.I.T. completed a two-year study last month comparing a gasoline-powered 1996-model sedan with some cars that might be feasible by 2020, including advanced gasoline models; hybrids that combine a gasoline or diesel engine with an electric motor and batteries; cars running on fuel cells with a raw fuel of either natural gas, gasoline or methanol; and electrics running on batteries. The study was a ''well to wheels'' comparison that took into account the energy use and greenhouse-gas emissions at every stage, from making the gasoline or other fuel to burning it in the vehicle. It also looked at the costs to consumers of the various technologies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Massachusetts Institute of Technology and DaimlerChrysler have given their assessments on the future of the automobile, and have both come out in favor of hybrid gasoline-electric cars. But scientists at M.I.T.'s Energy Laboratory, working with computer models, had an easier time predicting costs and benefits of the cars than DaimlerChrysler, working in steel and glass, is likely to have selling them.</p>
        <p>M.I.T. completed a two-year study last month comparing a gasoline-powered 1996-model sedan with some cars that might be feasible by 2020, including advanced gasoline models; hybrids that combine a gasoline or diesel engine with an electric motor and batteries; cars running on fuel cells with a raw fuel of either natural gas, gasoline or methanol; and electrics running on batteries. The study was a ''well to wheels'' comparison that took into account the energy use and greenhouse-gas emissions at every stage, from making the gasoline or other fuel to burning it in the vehicle. It also looked at the costs to consumers of the various technologies.</p>
        <p>The engineers found that the best car would use an electric drivetrain and get its energy from a small internal-combustion engine running on gasoline, diesel fuel or compressed natural gas. More exotic technologies like fuel cells or pure battery-electric cars would be more expensive and, taking into account the energy required to make their hydrogen or electricity, did not compare favorably on energy use or greenhouse emissions. But a hybrid car could cut greenhouse emissions, perhaps by half, though it would cost about 20 percent more than a conventional gasoline automobile.</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler said the extra charge would be $3,000 for a hybrid version of the Dodge Durango, a hefty four-wheel-drive sport utility vehicle. The engineers would substitute a V-6 engine for the Durango's  V-8 and disconnect it from the front wheels, which would be powered instead by a 100-horsepower electric motor. The motor would draw on a battery, and the battery would be recharged by letting the front wheels drag a little -- using the motor as a generator, converting torque to electricity instead of vice-versa. It would do that during braking, thus recapturing some of the energy lost at each stop sign.</p>
        <p>The hybrid's acceleration would be equal to, or better than, a gasoline Durango. Short-distance performance off road would be equal, but for long off-road drives, the electric side would have trouble recharging, engineers said.</p>
        <p>One expected result is an increase in fuel economy, to 18 m.p.g. from 15. But the actual cost to the company is not clear; for one thing, the plan is to use lithium-ion batteries, the kind now in high-end laptop computers, and those have not yet been built on the scale the Dodge would require.</p>
        <p>Adding three miles a gallon for $3,000 means, with gas at $1.60 a gallon, that 1,875 gallons would have to be saved to break even. If the vehicle went 12,000 miles a year, the ordinary version would use 800 gallons, and the hybrid version, 667. With savings of 133 gallons a year, the added cost of the hybrid would take 14 years to pay for itself, or 168,000 miles -- a challenge for a Dodge truck. An economist would calculate that the savings would have to be even larger to break even, to take account of the interest payments that the $3,000 could have earned if left in the bank -- or if not borrowed from the bank as part of a car loan.</p>
        <p>Consumers who weigh the energy efficiency of appliances they are buying usually look for a three-year payback. The Durango could do that if gas was $7.50 a gallon (133 gallons a year for 3 years is about 400 gallons, divided into $3,000).</p>
        <p>DaimlerChrysler executives had said they would not build the car unless Congress approved a tax credit. But now, perhaps goaded by Ford and G.M., DaimlerChrysler plans to go ahead regardless. Also in 2003, Ford plans to sell a hybrid version of its Escape, an S.U.V. slightly smaller than an Explorer, and G.M. is working on hybrid pickup trucks and buses. Toyota and Honda are already selling small hybrid-powered cars, and G.M. has been working with Toyota on a small hybrid S.U.V.</p>
        <p>Bernard Robertson, senior vice president for engineering technologies at DaimlerChrysler, said in announcing the 2003 production date for the hybrid Durango that his company hoped eventually to sell 100,000 hybrid vehicles a year of various models, perhaps 30,000 of them Durangos (or 15 percent of Durango production).</p>
        <p>But the purpose seems more to break the ice than to save gasoline. At $3,000 a vehicle, and 100,000 vehicles a year, the added cost would come to $300 million a year. Asked if that much money would save more gasoline if it were invested in marginal shifts like better engines and lighter bodies, he said it was possible, though he had not done the calculation.</p>
        <p>The Durango came out better on cost, though, than another car shown off by Chrysler in October, a Jeep Commander concept car powered by fuel cells. DaimlerChrysler says it wants to sell fuel-cell buses in 2003 and fuel-cell cars in 2004, but Mr. Robertson acknowledged, ''There are a lot of challenges left.''</p>
        <p>The biggest is to cut the cost of fuel cells to $50 per kilowatt of capacity -- about what that much power costs from an internal-combustion engine; engineers will not be specific, but at the moment the figure is perhaps 100 times that. The car carries 50 kilowatts of fuel cells. Moshen D. Shabana, chief fuel cell engineer on the project, acknowledged with a smile that this was ''the most expensive vehicle I ever touched.''</p>
        <p>M.I.T. seems confident that the costs of fuel cells will fall, along with the costs of batteries and other components of advanced vehicles. But plain old gasoline is likely to be the cheapest power source.</p>
        <p>Malcolm Weiss, a researcher who was the lead author of the M.I.T. study, said in an e-mail message that if payload, performance and range stayed constant, the new, more fuel-efficient vehicles would always cost more. They ''cannot pay for themselves in fuel savings based on any personal rational economic analysis,'' he said; there would have to be other reasons to buy them.</p>
        <p>He wrote, ''Perhaps customers will come to value fuel efficiency as a social good they're willing to pay for -- or perhaps taxes will go way up (politically absurd), increasing the value of fuel savings, but don't hold your breath.'' He calculated that the owner of a hybrid Durango would lose $387 a year, at current gasoline prices, compared with the owner of a conventional Durango.</p>
        <p>His study, which tried to predict the state of technology by 2020, listed a margin of error on its estimates of 10 to 30 percent, which made its conclusions less than authoritative. And the authors acknowledged looking at the feasibility of technology, not the actual process of inducing change in a multibillion-dollar industry.</p>
        <p>The M.I.T. study mostly looked at energy consumption and gases that play a role in global warming. It assumed that all vehicles would meet the current federal ''Tier 2'' standards for smog pollutants and did not concern itself further with such conventional pollution, although a proponent of fuel cells could argue that they are cleaner.</p>
        <p>The study compared a 1996-model Toyota Camry, the ''reference'' vehicle, to an advanced internal-combustion car, a hybrid using gasoline, diesel or compressed natural gas, a fuel cell car using gasoline, methanol or hydrogen, and a battery electric car.</p>
        <p>The battery car, which was the car of the future a decade ago, is too expensive and is not the best on energy consumption and greenhouse gases, the study concluded.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
