<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore's Stump Speech: A Clear Choice, With Clear Visions for the Future</title>
    <meta content="Y24GTE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/24/politics/24GTEX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1241444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E6DF1431F937A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="2267" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore's Stump Speech: A Clear Choice, With Clear Visions for the Future</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>transcript of speech by Vice Pres Al Gore at Martin Luther King High School in Philadelphia (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following is a transcript of a speech by Vice President Al Gore on Saturday night at Martin Luther King High School in Philadelphia, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>What a crowd in Philadelphia! Whooooo! This is amazing! Thank you for being here, Mayor John Street. You told me you'd throw a good party. Philadelphia knows how to throw a good party. Live from Philadelphia! It's Saturday night!</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following is a transcript of a speech by Vice President Al Gore on Saturday night at Martin Luther King High School in Philadelphia, as recorded by The New York Times:</p>
        <p>What a crowd in Philadelphia! Whooooo! This is amazing! Thank you for being here, Mayor John Street. You told me you'd throw a good party. Philadelphia knows how to throw a good party. Live from Philadelphia! It's Saturday night!</p>
        <p>I want to thank Bob Brady, your great congressman and party chair. And Congressman Chaka Fattah. Thank you. They do a great job. I want to thank Auditor General Bob Casey Jr. back here. Thank you, Bob. I want to acknowledge our secretary of labor, Alexis Herman, who's around here somewhere. I want you to know my national campaign chairman -- person -- the best ever, Donna Brazile. She's probably organizing right now.</p>
        <p>I want to ask you to join with me in a very special welcome and then join with me in making sure we elect him as the next senator from Pennsylvania, Ron Klink.</p>
        <p>Tina Tartaglione, our state party chair, thank you, and all the distinguished guests who are here. John Myers, state representative. I want to thank the Martin Luther King band and choir. Thank you all for doing a great job. It's great to be in a school named after one of my heroes. Tomorrow morning I will fly out of Philadelphia to Dallas, Tex., where I will speak to a large gathering with Coretta Scott King. And I'll be speaking about justice and values. And this evening I want to talk to you about the choice that we face in this election on Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>Seventeen days from now, Pennsylvania will decide who the next president of the United States will be. Seventeen days from now, Philadelphia will decide what Pennsylvania decides. Seventeen days from now, the people in this room will decide what Philadelphia decides.</p>
        <p>The choice is very clear. The contrast is very stark. We have a choice between two candidates. But it's not about me or Governor Bush. It is about you and your family and your city and your future. Prosperity is on the ballot Nov. 7. Education and health care are on the ballot. Social Security is on the ballot. The environment is on the ballot. The future of your family is on the ballot Nov. 7.</p>
        <p>The other side is trying to convince this country that we were a lot better off eight years ago than we are today. (Boos.) That was my reaction also. They want to go back to the kind of policies that we had eight years ago.</p>
        <p>Let me tell you, we've got a lot of work left to do, but we have made some progress in the last eight years because we've turned the biggest deficits that they left us into the biggest surpluses. Instead of repeat recessions, we've seen a tripling of the stock market. Instead of high unemployment, we have the lowest African-American unemployment ever measured, the lowest Latino unemployment ever measured, 22 million new jobs and the strongest economy in the 224-year history of the United States of America. That's progress! But it's not good enough. I'm not satisfied. You ain't seen nothing yet!</p>
        <p>A Vision of the Future</p>
        <p>I see a future in which our prosperity is continued and everybody participates. Nobody is left behind. More jobs. Balance the budget every year, pay down the debt every year. I want to completely eliminate the national debt early in the next decade so it's not on the shoulders of these children.</p>
        <p>I think it's time to invest in health care and education and the environment and middle-class tax cuts for the people who most need tax cuts and retirement security. I will put Social Security and Medicare in a lockbox and veto anything that takes money out of it.</p>
        <p>Now let me tell you what the other side has proposed. They have proposed a tax cut for the very wealthy, a very big tax cut for the wealthy that gives almost half of the benefits to the top 1 percent. In the debates just concluded, the moderator, Jim Lehrer, asked Governor Bush whether or not it was true what I was saying about his massive tax cuts for the wealthy and whether or not it benefits the top 1 percent so much and Governor Bush's answer was, ''Of course it does.'' Does that represent the wrong priority for America? Of course it does! Is that the wrong choice for our future? Of course it is.</p>
        <p>He proposes -- and his own numbers show this -- to spend more money on a tax cut for the top 1 percent than all of the new money that he proposes to spend on education and health care and national defense combined. You have an opportunity between now and November the 7th to put your feelings into action, to put your beliefs on the street, to put your wishes into the form of votes on the part of your neighbors and friends. This is the closest election since John Kennedy won the presidency in 1960 by one vote per precinct. I want to ask every single person here to get me one more vote per precinct between now and November the 7th. And then some!</p>
        <p>The other side, my opponent, has proposed to take a trillion dollars out of the Social Security trust fund, and he has promised it to two different groups of people. He's promised it to young people for savings and investment, and then he's promised the same trillion dollars to seniors to prevent any cuts in benefits. Now, I know that one and one equals two. I know that the only way to describe a promise to give the same one trillion dollars to two different groups of people is to say, what kind of math is that? Fuzzy math! Fuzzy math! Fuzzy math!</p>
        <p>His own chief economist, when confronted with what he said in the debate about Social Security, said, ''I don't know why the governor said what he said.'' Now, if his own economist can't explain what he said, how can the rest of America figure it out? Fuzzy math! If the proposal, according to the best economist, causes the bankruptcy of Social Security, then that is a consequence that is unacceptable for our country.</p>
        <p>But my friends, we have got to put our beliefs in motion. We have got to get people out to the voting booth. We have got to get people encouraged to vote in large numbers because the future of our country is at stake.</p>
        <p>Here's what I believe. I believe that we need to have an economic policy that puts people first, that has fiscal responsibility to keep the economy growing strongly, to make sure that we include everyone. For example, I'm for raising the minimum wage a dollar an hour for those who most need help. I'm for investing in the priorities that are most important to people. Where health care is concerned, we have to start taking the medical decisions away from the H.M.O.'s and give them back to the doctors and the nurses and the health care professionals. And it is time to recognize that seniors, especially those on fixed incomes, are having trouble choosing those between their medicine and their meals, choosing between some medicines and other prescriptions. It is time for a prescription drug benefit for all seniors under the Medicare program. I'm for it; my opponent is not.</p>
        <p>'The Challenge of Equality'</p>
        <p>I believe it is time to address the challenge of equality. We need an equal day's pay for an equal day's work for women in this country. We need a Supreme Court that reflects our values in this country. We need to pass the Employment Non-Discrimination Act in this country. We need to pass a hate-crimes law in America. We need to enforce the civil rights laws in America.</p>
        <p>We need a commitment to our nation's schools to make them the best in the world. With smaller classes. More one-on-one time. And I want to give every middle-class family a tax deduction for college tuition of $10,000 a year. I believe it's time to recognize that we've all got to hang together. We've all got to stay together and vote together and organize together. And I believe it is time for men and women in the workplace to have the right to organize without it being undermined. That means that I'm for a law to get rid of permanent striker replacement in America.</p>
        <p>Now, when we talk about the importance of staying together, we also have to understand how that applies to our nation as a whole. We must resolve that never again will we allow people to divide us along the lines of race or ethnicity or religion or any of those distinctions like gender, or who your partner is. We need to have a commitment to fairness.</p>
        <p>Now, my friends, this election is up to you. It's a question of the economy, it's a question of values. You know that it's right to help parents and strengthen families. You know parents need more tools to protect their children against the cultural pollution that threatens the values that they want in their families. You know that we need after-school programs for the youngsters who are tempted to get in trouble after school. You know that we need more child care, affordable child care and help for stay-at-home parents also.</p>
        <p>Now, finally, here is what it comes down to. We have got to recognize that our values have to be put into action at election time. I believe that we need to fight for clean air and clean water and against global warming and for an environment that's good for our children. I believe it's time to make every school gun-free and violence-free and drug-free.</p>
        <p>The Importance of Passion</p>
        <p>But finally, I want to ask each and every one of you not only for your vote and for your support, but for your enthusiasm and something more. I want to ask you for something that's difficult for you to give, something that people hardly ever give anymore. I want you to open your hearts and allow yourselves to genuinely believe that we can do the right thing in America and be the better for it, that we can have campaign finance reform, that we can turn out the vote.</p>
        <p>Now, when I talk about turning out the vote, I'm extremely aware that Philadelphia can make up the margin in the entire Keystone State of Pennsylvania. I'm keenly aware that that turnout depends upon each and every one of you. So here's what I'm asking. When you go home after this rally, and when you encounter your neighbors and your friends during the next 17 days, I want you to arm yourselves with the issues and the arguments about why our priorities are good for the country and the other side would take us on a right-wing U-turn back to the economic problems of the past.</p>
        <p>But then I want you to arm yourself with something else -- and that is the passion of your belief, the strength of your conviction, the steel of your determination, the passion of your feelings about the future. When you encounter someone who says it doesn't make any difference who appoints the next three justices of the Supreme Court, when you encounter someone who says it doesn't make any difference what kind of economic priorities we have in America, when you encounter someone who says they don't even think they're going to take the time to vote, what I want you to do is not just give them the facts, I want you to give them the feeling. I want you to give them a piece of your mind, and then your whole heart. I want you to tell them how much you care.</p>
        <p>My friends, sometimes the people who have the strongest ideals and the best hearts convince themselves they need to stay at arm's length from the political process. Maybe they're afraid their hearts will be broken, maybe they're afraid they'll be disappointed, let down or disillusioned. I'm telling you. I've said this before but I'll say it again. I may not always be the most exciting politician, like John Street or Chaka Fattah or Bob Brady, but I will work for you every single day, I'll fight for your families and I'll never let you down.</p>
        <p>I know this. I know one thing about the job of president. It is the only position in the Constitution that is filled by someone who is given the responsibility to fight not just for one group, not just for one state or district, not just for the wealthy or the well-connected or the powerful, not just for the top 1 percent. A president who does the job right has to be willing to fight for all of the people, especially you, especially those who most need a champion. I'm running for president because I want to fight for you. I want to fight for your family. I want to fight for Philadelphia. For Pennsylvania! For the future of the United States of America. God bless you. I need your help.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
