<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEW RULES TO CUT DIESEL EMISSIONS</title>
    <meta content="21FUEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/21/politics/21FUEL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1257002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soot</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Diesel Power</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trucks and Trucking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2D61E39F932A15751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1070" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEW RULES TO CUT DIESEL EMISSIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton approves final pollution-control rules that will force drastic reductions in heavy-duty truck and bus emissions over next 10 years; under new rules, big diesel-powered vehicles that are heaviest polluters on roads will be subject to requirements that will reduce their emissions of soot and smog-producing material by more than 90 percent; changes will not go into effect until 2006; some critics warn that new rules could result in dangerous shortages and price surges in fuel on which truck and bus transportation depends (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton has approved final pollution-control rules that will force drastic reductions in heavy-duty truck and bus emissions over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Under the new rules, the big diesel-powered vehicles that are the heaviest polluters on the roads would be subject to requirements that together would reduce their emissions of soot and smog-producing material by more than 90 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton has approved final pollution-control rules that will force drastic reductions in heavy-duty truck and bus emissions over the next 10 years.</p>
        <p>Under the new rules, the big diesel-powered vehicles that are the heaviest polluters on the roads would be subject to requirements that together would reduce their emissions of soot and smog-producing material by more than 90 percent.</p>
        <p>More so even than the tightened standards for cars and light-trucks that Mr. Clinton announced a year ago, the new regulations for buses and big rigs will reduce by millions of tons pollutants that pose a major hazard to human health.</p>
        <p>''In terms of the environment, it just doesn't get any bigger than these smudge pots on wheels,'' a senior official at the Environmental Protection Agency said.</p>
        <p>The changes are not scheduled to take effect until 2006, but they will be announced by the White House and the Environmental Protection Agency on Thursday as part of a final flurry of regulatory action designed to withstand any challenge by the incoming Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Some critics, including the oil industry and some Senate Republicans, have accused the White House of rushing to judgment, warning that provisions of the rules could result in dangerous shortages and price surges in the fuel on which truck and bus transportation depends. Within the administration, the Energy, Transportation and Commerce Departments joined in saying that those warnings might be valid.</p>
        <p>But the White House concluded that the benefits of the action far exceeded any risk, one administration official said, and approved a plan little changed from one first proposed last spring by Carol Browner, the E.P.A. administrator.</p>
        <p>President-elect George W. Bush has not said whether he agrees with the approach taken by the White House. But in Texas, Mr. Bush's policies have been aligned closely with those of the oil industry. Senator James M. Inhofe, Republican of Oklahoma, has warned that he would seek early in the next Congress to roll back the new rules.</p>
        <p>Senator Inhofe and other lawmakers tried and failed this fall to prevent the White House from announcing the new plan before Mr. Clinton left office.</p>
        <p>Until now, heavy-duty trucks and buses have all but escaped the increasingly stringent pollution-control standards that have been imposed on cars and light trucks over the last 25 years. With word of the changes, environmentalists were beginning to celebrate today what they called the closing of a loophole and the possibility of further gains.</p>
        <p>''In our view, these rules are going to result in the biggest air pollution advance in a generation,'' said Richard Kassell, a lawyer with the Natural Resources Defense Council.</p>
        <p>Among the new heavy-duty vehicle rules, the most controversial aspect lies at the very heart, which would transform the diesel fuel burned by heavy-duty trucks and buses. These vehicles account for just 6 percent of highway miles driven, but produce one-fourth of the smog-producing pollution and one-half of the soot.</p>
        <p>As a component of diesel fuel, sulfur not only contributes to the soot but has also made impossible the incorporation of advanced pollution-control devices into heavy-duty trucks and buses, much as lead content in gasoline once served as a barrier to the adoption of the catalytic converter.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and others have contended that only the virtual elimination of sulfur from diesel could lead to a pollution-control breakthrough for heavy-duty trucks and buses, but the oil industry has argued that a smaller reduction would be sufficient.</p>
        <p>In discussions with the administration, industry representatives have warned that the costs and difficulty of meeting the new requirement would prove so onerous that some refiners would stop producing diesel fuel altogether, leading to shortages and severe price volatility.</p>
        <p>Those warnings gained significance after last summer, administration officials said, when gasoline prices in the Midwest soared to levels not seen elsewhere in the country, as a result of shortages brought on by pollution-control rules that required a new additive. With that experience in mind, Energy Secretary Bill Richardson argued that the E.P.A.'s proposed rule be modified so that the diesel-reduction rules would be phased in gradually, to allow refiners more time to adjust.</p>
        <p>But that approach found little support, even from the oil industry, and the White House settled on a plan that would take effect in two steps, with 80 percent of all diesel fuel to be virtually sulfur-free beginning in 2006, and the rest by 2010.</p>
        <p>At the American Petroleum Institute, the industry's leading trade group, top officials warned again today that the new rules could lead to disruption. ''This is really going to test the system,'' said Edward Murphy, a general manager of the group.</p>
        <p>The two other main provisions of the new rules would affect engine manufacturers. One, requiring a 95 percent reduction in emissions of nitrogen oxide, the main ingredient in smog, would apply to half of all new heavy-duty vehicle engines manufactured in 2007, with the rest to follow in 2010. The other, requiring a 90 percent reduction in emissions of particulates, or soot, would take effect in one step, in 2010.</p>
        <p>Both targets will require the engine manufacturers to incorporate advanced new pollution control devices, experts said, and adoption of the rules was opposed by the manufacturers' main industry groups.</p>
        <p>Estimates of just how much the new rules might cost have varied widely. A study sponsored by the oil industry said they would add 15 cents to a gallon of diesel gasoline, but an E.P.A. study put the cost much lower, at about 4 to 5 cents a gallon.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. study also concluded that the price of a new heavy-duty truck or bus would increase by between 1 and 5 percent. But the study said the public health benefits, including reduced rates of cancer, asthma and other diseases, along with gains from lower levels of acid rain, would easily justify the cost.</p>
        <p>''Is it going to cost more? Yes,'' said S. William Becker, who represents state and local air pollution officials around the country who led in pressing for the new federal rules. ''Will that cost be passed on to consumers? Probably. But is it cost effective? Absolutely.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
