<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore to Unveil A Plan to Foster Cleaner Energy</title>
    <meta content="26GORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20000628T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1210575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DE1230F935A15755C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1045" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore to Unveil A Plan to Foster Cleaner Energy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore, under criticism from Republicans who accuse him of having no energy plan, will propose array of economic incentives to encourage cleaner technologies intended to reduce nation's dependency on foreign oil; will call for billions of dollars in tax breaks, low-interest loans, grants and other federal subsidies to encourage consumers to buy clean-energy products; has come under attack by Republican presidential rival Gov George W Bush for having supported higher gas taxes in past; Bush's criticisms of Clinton administration for allegedly allowing gasoline prices to rise steeply noted; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under fire from Republicans who say he has no energy plan, Vice President Al Gore will propose on Tuesday an array of economic incentives to encourage cleaner technologies intended to reduce the nation's dependency on foreign oil, aides said today.</p>
        <p>The aides said Mr. Gore would call for billions of dollars in tax breaks, low-interest loans, grants and other federal subsidies to encourage consumers to buy clean-energy products, like alternative-fuel cars or solar houses, and to encourage companies to develop sources of energy that do not burn oil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under fire from Republicans who say he has no energy plan, Vice President Al Gore will propose on Tuesday an array of economic incentives to encourage cleaner technologies intended to reduce the nation's dependency on foreign oil, aides said today.</p>
        <p>The aides said Mr. Gore would call for billions of dollars in tax breaks, low-interest loans, grants and other federal subsidies to encourage consumers to buy clean-energy products, like alternative-fuel cars or solar houses, and to encourage companies to develop sources of energy that do not burn oil.</p>
        <p>In recent days, Mr. Gore has come under sharp attack by his likely Republican rival, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, for having supported higher gas taxes in the past. Mr. Bush has also accused the Clinton administration of idly allowing gasoline prices to rise steeply this summer. Prices at the pump have soared nationwide, rising as much as 50 cents a gallon in parts of the Midwest, an important battleground region in the presidential race.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's advisers counter that they can turn the issue to their advantage by portraying Mr. Bush, a former executive with a small oil company, as a pawn of big oil producers whose profits have risen sharply over the last year. Mr. Gore's aides say they are planning an offensive this week in which surrogates will attack Mr. Bush's ties to the oil industry while the vice president focuses on a more positive message.</p>
        <p>o In an early taste of those attacks, Senator Tom Harkin, Democrat of Iowa, said today on ''Fox News Sunday,'' ''It seems to me what Mr. Bush and what the Republicans are saying and the oil companies are saying is that their answer to the crisis is to keep their profits up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore had planned to devote this week to discussing the environment in his three-week ''progress and prosperity'' tour. But with gasoline prices dominating the news in the Midwest, he has chosen to shift gears somewhat and focus his message as much on reducing oil prices and consumption as on cleaning up the environment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's aides declined to provide specifics on the cost of the plan. They said the vice president would propose setting aside part of the federal surplus in a protected ''environmental trust fund'' that would pay for the proposals.</p>
        <p>The aides acknowledged that Mr. Gore's new proposals would have little short-term effect on oil prices. But they noted that he had already called for having the Federal Trade Commission investigate possible price gouging by the oil industry and had urged the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries to increase production.</p>
        <p>Under the plan that the aides said  Mr. Gore would unveil this week, he would provide tax breaks to encourage consumers and small-business owners to buy houses, cars, hot-water heaters and other products that were energy efficient. His aides said the plan would expand on a similar proposal by President Clinton that would cost $9 billion over 10 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore would also propose federal subsidies to help utility companies upgrade or replace coal-fired power plants that are the source of much of the air pollution that causes acid rain and smog along the Eastern seaboard, the aides said.</p>
        <p>In addition, they said, the plan would call for expanding federal spending on mass transit and having the federal government help underwrite investments in cleaner, energy-efficient technologies.</p>
        <p>Dan Bartlett, a spokesman for Mr. Bush, said of Mr. Gore's proposals, ''After eight years of weak leadership on energy issues, Al Gore is proposing nothing new.'' He added, ''One thing that is consistent is Al Gore's longtime support of higher gas prices.''</p>
        <p>In 1993, Mr. Gore cast the tie-breaking vote in the Senate for the administration's economic stimulus plan, which was intended to reduce the budget deficit by cutting spending and raising some taxes, including taxes on gasoline. Some Republicans in Congress are now calling for suspending all or part of that federal gasoline tax.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush has tried to use Mr. Gore's writings to accuse him of wanting to increase gasoline taxes as a means of discouraging consumption. Last week, Mr. Bush read a passage from Mr. Gore's 1992 book ''Earth in the Balance'' that described ''higher taxes on fossil fuels'' as ''one of the logical first steps in changing our policies in a manner consistent with a more responsible approach to the environment.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gore's aides say that the Republicans have willfully misread ''Earth in the Balance.'' The book proposed taxing companies that emit carbon dioxide, a byproduct of burning fossil fuels that is also a significant component of smog. But Mr. Gore also proposed reducing payroll taxes for those companies so that they would not have to increase prices to consumers.</p>
        <p>In turn, the Gore campaign has circulated copies of a 1992 letter from Mr. Bush warning that his father, President George Bush, who was then seeking re-election, might lose support in some oil-producing states because he ''is viewed as favoring cheap energy.'' Mr. Gore's aides contend the letter demonstrates that Governor Bush is more concerned about protecting oil companies' profits than reducing retail prices.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bartlett said today that Governor Bush was simply urging his father's administration to support a tax break for small, independent oil companies that could help them increase production. He said that Mr. Gore, then a senator from Tennessee, also supported that tax break.</p>
        <p>During Mr. Gore's swing through Pennsylvania, Ohio and parts of the Midwest this week, the aides said, he  will argue that cleaning up the environment could help the economy, rather than hinder it.</p>
        <p>The aides said that the vice president would assert, for instance, that American companies could reap large profits from selling products that help clean the environment to developing nations. And, the aides said, he would argue that American consumers were ''ravenous'' for products that were cleaner and more energy efficient.</p>
        <p>''The environment and the economy are really one and the same thing,'' Mr. Gore said to a group of Democrats in Miami on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT  Correction:  June 28, 2000, Wednesday  A front-page article on Monday about Vice President Al Gore's plan to encourage consumers to buy clean-energy products misstated the environmental impact of carbon dioxide. It is a heat-trapping gas associated with global warming, not a component of smog.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 28, 2000, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A front-page article on Monday about Vice President Al Gore's plan to encourage consumers to buy clean-energy products misstated the environmental impact of carbon dioxide. It is a heat-trapping gas associated with global warming, not a component of smog.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
