<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mrs. Clinton Found Right Mix in Fame and Upstate Focus</title>
    <meta content="09YORK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/09/politics/09YORK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245932"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 ELECTIONS: POLITICAL MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Hillary Rodham</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lazio, Rick A (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DF1738F93AA35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1349" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mrs. Clinton Found Right Mix in Fame and Upstate Focus</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Political Memo column discusses various reasons for Hillary Rodham Clinton's victory over Repr Rick Lazio for US Senate from New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time the votes were counted, it was hard to see what Rick A. Lazio could have done to get out of the way. Hillary Rodham Clinton rode to victory on a wave created by a crack-the-whip, get-out-the-vote effort orchestrated by her friends at the labor unions, a swell in the number of registered Democrats in the state, and, perhaps most of all, the huge margin that Al Gore posted over George Bush in New York.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton won a contest that even some Democrats had once thought she would lose, by capitalizing on her celebrity, particularly by traveling to remote areas upstate where voters rarely saw a governor, much less a first lady. She identified herself with Democratic concerns in New York, from the economy upstate to health care downstate, in a way intended to erase lingering questions about her character. And in what might be the most instructive lesson of this campaign, particularly on the heels of Charles Schumer's Senate race in 1998, she demonstrated that upstate New York is not as safe a Republican region as had been assumed for so long.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By the time the votes were counted, it was hard to see what Rick A. Lazio could have done to get out of the way. Hillary Rodham Clinton rode to victory on a wave created by a crack-the-whip, get-out-the-vote effort orchestrated by her friends at the labor unions, a swell in the number of registered Democrats in the state, and, perhaps most of all, the huge margin that Al Gore posted over George Bush in New York.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton won a contest that even some Democrats had once thought she would lose, by capitalizing on her celebrity, particularly by traveling to remote areas upstate where voters rarely saw a governor, much less a first lady. She identified herself with Democratic concerns in New York, from the economy upstate to health care downstate, in a way intended to erase lingering questions about her character. And in what might be the most instructive lesson of this campaign, particularly on the heels of Charles Schumer's Senate race in 1998, she demonstrated that upstate New York is not as safe a Republican region as had been assumed for so long.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mrs. Clinton defeated Mr. Lazio by 12 percentage points, a margin that surprised advisers to both candidates. But most revealing, she came within three points of Mr. Lazio upstate, an affirmation of her insistence on campaigning there so often. And turnout among black voters seems to have indeed increased as a result of the first lady's regular visits to black churches: blacks made up 11 percent of the electorate this year, compared with 9 percent in 1998, in a survey of voters leaving the polls on Election Day.</p>
        <p>Still, in the end, all those forces seem to have had more to do with the magnitude of Mrs. Clinton's victory, as opposed to the victory itself. In truth, most of the polls taken from the moment Mr. Lazio got in the race last May, replacing Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, suggested that there was never really that much variation in this contest, until the end. He always scored between 40 and 45 percent; in the end, he attracted 43 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Lazio's advisers said yesterday that Mrs. Clinton's character, which Republicans had thought would be the hook with which they could bring her down, instead served to obscure their efforts the two times they sought to turn more to issues, in particular Mr. Lazio's tax cut proposal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio's consultants sought yesterday to blame factors beyond their control for his loss in a race that had been followed by Republicans across the country.</p>
        <p>''It was a huge Democratic landslide in a big Democratic state,'' said Mike Murphy, Mr. Lazio's campaign consultant, in explaining a loss whose size he acknowledged had startled Mr. Lazio's aides.</p>
        <p>The candidate's campaign manager, Bill Dal Col, offered a similar argument in an interview yesterday, saying that he believed it was impossible to win the race once it became clear that Mr. Gore was going to win the state by 1.5 million votes.</p>
        <p>''When the numbers are as big as they are, it's not right or wrong,'' Mr. Dal Col said. ''The math gets impossible.''</p>
        <p>Still, a number of Republicans argued that the candidate and his staff had only made things more difficult  in the way they approached the contest. And as campaign workers began clearing out Mr. Lazio's offices on Park Avenue, there were accounts of turmoil and discord surrounding the campaign and the state Republican Party that Mr. Lazio's associates said undercut the campaign at a number of turns.</p>
        <p>There was open dissent, for example, between Mr. Lazio's campaign staff and state Republican Party officials. State Republicans said yesterday they had told Mr. Lazio over the summer that he was making a mistake in keeping such a low profile for so long. Mr. Lazio's aides said he used the time to raise money, but his absence allowed Mrs. Clinton to make inroads upstate and to begin raising questions about Mr. Lazio's record with a series of negative commercials.</p>
        <p>State Republicans also complained that Mr. Lazio recruited help from outside the state to run his campaign.</p>
        <p>For their part, Mr. Lazio's aides blamed William Powers, the state Republican chairman, for what they contended was one of the biggest mistakes of the campaign: orchestrating telephone advocacy calls that sought to link Mrs. Clinton to the terrorist attack on the destroyer Cole in Yemen. ''It was the single biggest blunder -- and it was by the local know-it-all New Yorkers,'' said one of Mr. Lazio's advisers. ''The biggest blunder of the race was the brainchild of the local guys.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Powers did not return a call seeking comment yesterday.</p>
        <p>There was tension between Mr. Lazio and his own advisers as well. His aides pressed him to deliver a series of six policy speeches in an effort to rebut attempts by Mrs. Clinton to portray him as an intellectual lightweight. Mr. Lazio delivered just three of them, as the candidate and his aides could not come to agreement on the language and even some of the proposals in the speeches.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lazio and Mr. Murphy argued several times over advertisements that Mr. Murphy wanted him to broadcast: on at least two occasions, Mr. Murphy began running advertisements, one on television and one on radio, over the objections of Mr. Lazio, according to one of the candidate's aides. When Mr. Lazio confronted him, Mr. Murphy argued the ads were a key to defeating Mrs. Clinton, the aides said.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, Mr. Lazio was forced to withdraw one of the ads, which attacked Mrs. Clinton for support a treaty on global warming, after he was criticized by environmental groups. Mr. Murphy declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Even in defeat, Mr. Lazio did appear to have some success, notably, in undermining her support among Jews, by questioning her allegiance to Israel. The survey of voters leaving the polls found that Mrs. Clinton won the support of just 53 percent of the state's Jewish voters, an anemic showing for a Democrat. Typically, a Democratic candidate in a statewide race draws at least 60 percent of the Jewish vote.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton's advisers said that they had considered her weak among Jews from the start. But they made the calculation, they said, that they could counter this with a strong showing upstate.</p>
        <p>Finally, perhaps the most successful strategy employed by Mrs. Clinton's associates was their attempt to erase the objection that Mrs. Clinton was trying to run from a state where she had not lived. To that end, they decided more than a year ago to simply have her spend as much time in New York as possible.</p>
        <p>On the very last day of his campaign, Mr. Lazio assailed her again on the subject, as had Mr. Giuliani before him. If nothing else, the margin of Mrs. Clinton's victory suggests that this course of attack had at most limited appeal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dal Col, in an interview, acknowledged yesterday that the campaign had made several missteps, from the Cole calls to Mr. Lazio's decision to walk across the stage at the candidates' first debate and demand that Mrs. Clinton sign a pledge to bar the use of soft money. Still, he said after reviewing the numbers, none of that mattered much in the end.</p>
        <p>''If you add up all these mistakes, they don't equal this race,'' he said. ''It might get you five points. It doesn't get you the race. There was nothing fatal.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 ELECTIONS: POLITICAL MEMO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
