<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Through Northwest Passage in a Month, Ice-Free</title>
    <meta content="Y05ARC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/09/05/world/05ARCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1228130"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greenhouse Effect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Arctic Regions</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Canadian Mounted Police</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooke, James</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Global Warming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wind</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000905T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEFD61E30F936A3575AC0A9669C8B63" item-length="1128" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Through Northwest Passage in a Month, Ice-Free</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooke, James</byline>
      <dateline>NUUK, Greenland, Sept. 4</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St Roche II, Royal Canadian Mounted Police vessel traverses treacherous Northwest Passage in month, retracing same route by namesake boat 50 years ago, when voyage took 27 months; traversed all of Canada's Arctic without encountering pack ice; ice-free passage is latest evidence that Arctic ice is melting in summer more extensively than usual in trend that scientists attribute to changing winds and rising temperatures; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>During World War II, when Henry Larsen took a Royal Canadian Mounted Police ship, the St. Roch, into the fabled Northwest Passage, his boat was frozen in Arctic ice through two winters, only emerging at the eastern end after 27 months.</p>
        <p>On Sunday the St. Roch II completed a voyage over the same route in one month, including leisurely overnight stops at communities visited by the namesake boat half a century ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>During World War II, when Henry Larsen took a Royal Canadian Mounted Police ship, the St. Roch, into the fabled Northwest Passage, his boat was frozen in Arctic ice through two winters, only emerging at the eastern end after 27 months.</p>
        <p>On Sunday the St. Roch II completed a voyage over the same route in one month, including leisurely overnight stops at communities visited by the namesake boat half a century ago.</p>
        <p>After leaving Tuktoyaktuk, near Canada's border with Alaska, the boat traversed all of Canada's Arctic without encountering pack ice.</p>
        <p>''Concern should be registered with the fact we didn't see any ice,'' the skipper, Sgt. Ken Burton of the Mounties, said on Sunday over a maritime telephone as he took the police boat into open waters across Baffin Bay from Greenland.</p>
        <p>Safely out of the passage, he said, ''There were some bergs, but nothing we saw to cause any anxiety. We saw some ribbons of multiyear ice floes, all small and fragmented, and were able to steer around them.'</p>
        <p>The Canadians' ice-free passage through their nation's northern waters is the latest evidence that Arctic ice is melting in the summer more extensively than usual.</p>
        <p>In a trend that scientists attribute to changing winds and rising temperatures, submarine sonar probes indicate that the thickness of polar ice is only 58 percent of what it was in the 1950's. Satellite photographs show that the polar ice cap at the time of maximum summer melt -- about now -- has been reduced by about 6 percent since 1980. The original St. Roche was blocked even in the summer.</p>
        <p>''We don't know enough about the Arctic to know if this is global warming, climate change or maybe we were just plain lucky,'' Sergeant Burton said as he took his boat south, planning to arrive in Halifax on Oct. 9 or 10 and New York a week later.</p>
        <p>Along the way the crew of the St. Roch and a support ship, the Simon Fraser, found a chilling reminder of how harrowing the Arctic can be: a skull and the graves of six men believed to have perished in the late 1840's as part of the ill-fated Franklin expedition.</p>
        <p>In 1845 Sir John Franklin set out from Britain with 128 men and two ships, the Erebus and the Terror, trying to find the Northwest Passage. The ships were last spotted frozen in the ice in 1847, but their fate has remained a mystery. In the decade that followed, 32 rescue parties searched for the ships and their crews.</p>
        <p>Until two weeks ago, only about 30 bodies had been recovered. Autopsies of those earlier bodies indicated that some men had died of lead poisoning from canned food and that the starving survivors had resorted to cannibalism before they, too, perished in the cold.</p>
        <p>The Mounties were led to the six newly found graves by Louie Kamookak, an Inuk hunter who once heard his grandfather tell of how he had fashioned an ice pick from a knife he had found at old campsite where plates and knives were scattered about.</p>
        <p>''In addition to the six grave sites, there was a cooking and fire pit that looked like it had been used for an extended period of time,'' Sergeant Burton said. The bodies were found on a desolate beach in the Todd Island group, about 30 miles south of Gjoa Haven.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kamookak, a self-described Franklin buff, has said that by using tales from village elders, he has been able to locate many markers and artifacts left by early Arctic explorers, including as many as seven more Franklin sites. He told the Canadian Press: ''There's other stuff. But one day I'm hoping to write my own book, and I'm saving it for that.''</p>
        <p>Scientists and environmentalists are trying to figure out if commercial ships will be able to cross the Canadian Arctic on a regular basis in the late summer.</p>
        <p>''It is still a risky venture,'' Sergeant Burton said, ''but the day of the famed Northwest Passage, the shortcut to Orient may be just around the corner.''</p>
        <p>The possibility of such a maritime route has intrigued sovereigns and ship captains since the time when Queen Elizabeth I wished Martin Frobisher godspeed as he sailed from London, bound for the Arctic, in 1575. He was not successful. The passage was first navigated in 1903 by Raold Amundsen, a voyage that took three years.</p>
        <p>A shipping channel over the top of North America would cut 5,000 miles off the Panama Canal route now used by freighters going from Rotterdam to Yokohama. Not by chance, one passenger who traveled on the St. Roch II for a few days this summer was a reporter for a Rotterdam newspaper.</p>
        <p>After taking the ship through the 10,000-mile maze of channels and islands that constitutes the Northwest Passage, Sergeant Burton cautioned that the Arctic ''is a very fickle environment.'' He was speaking shortly after leaving Pond Inlet, an eastern Arctic town where the three crew members of a Norwegian boat attempting the passage were recuperating after their boat flipped over.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Burton said he knew of two other boats that had successfully navigated the passage this summer: a New Zealand sailboat, the Evco, which is now heading to Greenland, and the United States Coast Guard cutter Healy. In late July the American ship, a new icebreaker, had to cut through heavy ice in areas where, one month later, the St. Roch II found open water.</p>
        <p>Timing is essential, Stephen Rybak, spokesman for the St. Roch II, said from Vancouver, where he is raising money to restore the original St. Roch, which is deteriorating from dry rot.</p>
        <p>Before shipping executives try a northern short cut, he warned, their captains should know that they will have to slip through two ''gates'' -- one off Barrow, Alaska, the other in the McClintock Channel, a north-south waterway in the middle of the Canadian Arctic. There, winds can clog channels with ice.</p>
        <p>''Global warming may increase periods of ice-free navigation in the Arctic,'' Mr. Rybak said. ''But it won't do a darn thing about the gates opening and closing. That has to do with the winds.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
