<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Causes That Are Too Celebre</title>
    <meta content="15EAST$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1191962"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Easterbrook, Gregg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dicaprio, Leonardo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1D61F3EF936A25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Causes That Are Too Celebre</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Gregg Easterbrook</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Easterbrook, Gregg</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gregg Easterbrook Op-Ed article questions whether members of entertainment industry will ever have a lasting impact on public's environmental awareness, noting recent controversy over ABC News's decision to broadcast its Earth Day special, in which Leonardo DiCaprio, 'crusading journalist,' questions Pres Clinton about global warming (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fourteen-year-old girls everywhere can breathe  now that ABC News has decided to go ahead and broadcast its Earth Day special in which Leonardo DiCaprio, crusading journalist, questions President Clinton about global warming. Personally, I know I'll be waiting for his question on the latest Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change science-assessment revisions, especially as they apply to new studies on ocean-current fluid dynamics when compared to the watts-per-square-foot forcing of anthropogenic gases, and how this will affect the Kyoto Annex I plans for joint implementation of carbon sequestration.</p>
        <p>Be these things as they may, ABC asserts that it is sending a teen heartthrob to interview the president about global warming in order to raise public awareness of the issue. But it's fair to suppose that one reason public concern over the greenhouse effect is low is exactly that Hollywood is on the case. When the networks and movie studios treat global warming as a subject so trifling, it can be safely passed off from serious discussion to glam events hosted by celebrities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fourteen-year-old girls everywhere can breathe  now that ABC News has decided to go ahead and broadcast its Earth Day special in which Leonardo DiCaprio, crusading journalist, questions President Clinton about global warming. Personally, I know I'll be waiting for his question on the latest Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change science-assessment revisions, especially as they apply to new studies on ocean-current fluid dynamics when compared to the watts-per-square-foot forcing of anthropogenic gases, and how this will affect the Kyoto Annex I plans for joint implementation of carbon sequestration.</p>
        <p>Be these things as they may, ABC asserts that it is sending a teen heartthrob to interview the president about global warming in order to raise public awareness of the issue. But it's fair to suppose that one reason public concern over the greenhouse effect is low is exactly that Hollywood is on the case. When the networks and movie studios treat global warming as a subject so trifling, it can be safely passed off from serious discussion to glam events hosted by celebrities.</p>
        <p>This is hardly the first time the entertainment world has tried to raise awareness on global warming. In 1993, CBS broadcast a preposterous miniseries, ''The Fire Next Time,'' to great fanfare. It depicted the United States in the year 2007 as a nation destroyed by global warming. In the miniseries, a man and boy attempt to travel a nation wracked by searing heat, sustained droughts, monster storms and dangerous exposure to bad dialogue.</p>
        <p>Conservative critics were aghast, saying the miniseries indoctrinated mass audiences with greenhouse scenarios far worse than any predicted even by the most pessimistic scientists. Yet there was no evidence that public concern for the environment rose in the wake of the CBS broadcasts, and shortly afterward Americans voted in the anti-environmental Gingrich Congress. By trivializing the greenhouse effect into something as ludicrous as the subject of a sci-fi miniseries, the network might have convinced mass audiences that global warming was just another Hollywood gimmick, which, unfortunately, it may not be.</p>
        <p>Ditto for Kevin Costner's ''Waterworld,'' a sci-fi epic that depicted an Earth inundated with oceans engorged by greenhouse-induced melting of the polar ice caps, again a much worse outcome even the most pessimistic models project. Mr. Costner justified his movie and its inflated budget with some blather about raising public awareness. It didn't help the planet or the box-office numbers.</p>
        <p>How many stars have really ''raised awareness'' about an environmental cause in a lasting way? A decade ago, when concerns about the rain forests were rising, Sting made himself Mr. Rain Forest; today the rain forest continues to shrink and  public concern hovers near zero (although the Rainforest Cafe chain has been packing in customers).</p>
        <p>No doubt most stars are sincere about the causes they attach themselves to. The problem is, while the public admires stars, it also sees them as about the most pampered people around, with little connection to real life. Thus the public can be forgiven if it suspected that Ted Danson, founder of the American Oceans Campaign and host of the TV documentary ''Danger at the Beach,'' might have been primarily concerned about the waterfront near his Martha's Vineyard home.</p>
        <p>Global warming is a slow-building problem for which scientific evidence is beginning to increase. Reform is possible but will take many years. In the interim, how many celebrities will get bored with the details and jump on to the next fad?</p>
        <p>It is always possible that ABC is on to something with the actor-as-journalist approach, and a Leo-Clinton pose fest will get young people excited about working for greenhouse-effect reform. But it seems more likely that the program will serve to make the issue seem simplistic. The alternative -- slow-moving interviews with scientists, thinkers and economists who have just slightly less than Mr. DiCaprio's squeal appeal -- will never be a ratings winner. But it would be credible, and the gradual accrual of credibility is what is needed today for greenhouse effect concerns.</p>
        <p>Gregg Easterbrook is a columnist for BeliefNet.com and author of Beside Still Waters: Searching for Meaning in an Age of Doubt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Gregg Easterbrook is a columnist for BeliefNet.com and author of Beside Still Waters: Searching for Meaning in an Age of Doubt.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
