<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dick Cheney's Political Resume</title>
    <meta content="26WED2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1217824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Richard B</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E6DF1E3AF935A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="590" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dick Cheney's Political Resume</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial holds Gov George W Bush's selection of Richard B Cheney as running mate brings hard-line conservative Congressional voting record to ticket, pulling it to right; holds Cheney's competence cannot soften his stark legislative record; notes Bush will have to win over moderate voters he needs in swing states on own</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Because he never served in Congress, Gov. George W. Bush does not have a voting record. But he acquired one yesterday with the selection of Richard B. Cheney as his running mate. Republicans were cheering the sound judgment and broad foreign policy experience that Mr. Cheney, a former secretary of defense and White House chief of staff, brings to the Republican ticket. But Democrats were eyeing the hard-line conservative votes that Mr. Cheney cast during a 10-year House career. From Vice President Al Gore's perspective, Mr. Cheney adds weight to the G.O.P. ticket, but he also opens up promising lanes of attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush believes that his running mate brings a resume and a personality that will outweigh any ideological vulnerability. Indeed, Mr. Cheney's vaunted toughness comes wrapped in a genial, Nebraska-born, Wyoming-honed personal manner. His deep experience clearly allows Mr. Bush to argue that he has passed a threshold test for any presidential candidate by picking a partner who would make a plausible successor. On that score, Governor Bush did a much better job than his father did in 1988 by choosing Dan Quayle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Because he never served in Congress, Gov. George W. Bush does not have a voting record. But he acquired one yesterday with the selection of Richard B. Cheney as his running mate. Republicans were cheering the sound judgment and broad foreign policy experience that Mr. Cheney, a former secretary of defense and White House chief of staff, brings to the Republican ticket. But Democrats were eyeing the hard-line conservative votes that Mr. Cheney cast during a 10-year House career. From Vice President Al Gore's perspective, Mr. Cheney adds weight to the G.O.P. ticket, but he also opens up promising lanes of attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush believes that his running mate brings a resume and a personality that will outweigh any ideological vulnerability. Indeed, Mr. Cheney's vaunted toughness comes wrapped in a genial, Nebraska-born, Wyoming-honed personal manner. His deep experience clearly allows Mr. Bush to argue that he has passed a threshold test for any presidential candidate by picking a partner who would make a plausible successor. On that score, Governor Bush did a much better job than his father did in 1988 by choosing Dan Quayle.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Cheney's competence cannot soften a stark legislative record. Several times in his Congressional career he got a 100 percent favorable rating from the American Conservative Union and zero from the liberal Americans for Democratic Action. He was consistently pro-life, and his opposition to abortion, even in cases of rape or incest, will help Mr. Gore argue that the Bush-Cheney ticket represents a threat to women's right to choose. Mr. Cheney also voted against gun control legislation that came his way, including a bill regulating cop-killer bullets that many other conservatives backed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney's environmental views will also be a tempting target for Mr. Gore. Mr. Cheney was among the few who voted not to override President Reagan's veto of a Clean Water Act reauthorization in 1987. Then as now, he supported opening the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to oil drilling, a talismanic issue among conservationists. He is also on record as opposing the Kyoto agreement on global warming, which Mr. Gore helped to negotiate, as a potential threat to America's national security.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Cheney never demonstrated the mean streak associated with Newt Gingrich conservatives, his selection indisputably pulls the Republican ticket to the right. This comes after several weeks when it appeared that Mr. Bush would pick a Northeasterner like Gov. Tom Ridge of Pennsylvania to put his party nearer the political center. Now it will be up to Mr. Bush himself to pull in the moderate voters he will need to carry swing states outside his Southern and Western base.</p>
        <p>That positioning exercise may not be easy, especially with Mr. Gore sniping away. A New York Times/CBS poll yesterday suggested that the public, which in February divided equally between ''conservative'' and ''moderate'' when asked to describe Mr. Bush's ideology, now increasingly regards the Texas governor as a conservative. Mr. Cheney's selection is sure to reinforce that impression.</p>
        <p>In the days ahead, Mr. Cheney will be marketed as someone who brings sound judgment and safe hands to the executive branch. That is a reasonable depiction. By virtue of experience and temperament, he does represent a responsible choice. But the voters will also be asked to factor ideology into their selection this fall. And Mr. Gore, waving a long list of House votes, will not allow Mr. Bush's picture of Dick Cheney to go unchallenged.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
