<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Walls Have Ears, and Other High-Tech Crime Gadgets</title>
    <meta content="19COOP$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Museums" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="H" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1192981"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cooper, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DF1731F93AA25757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Walls Have Ears, and Other High-Tech Crime Gadgets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL COOPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cooper, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Museums seek to protect collections from thieves without impeding public's ability to enjoy them; wide array of sophisticated devices can help thwart burglars, and employee theft is addressed through screening, training and procedures; little can be done about armed robbers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>STUDENTS of Hollywood heist films will no doubt be familiar with the many dangers inherent in trying to steal priceless paintings and rare jewels from museums.</p>
        <p>There are the ever-popular Technicolor laser-beam burglar alarms, which have sought to catch thieves since the days of the ''Pink Panther'' capers. There are weight-sensitive floorboards, which necessitated the classic dangling-by-ropes-from-the-ceiling approach to grand larceny that was used in ''Topkapi.'' And there are the metal shutters that fell quickly -- but not quite quickly enough -- over the paintings in the recent remake of ''The Thomas Crown Affair.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>STUDENTS of Hollywood heist films will no doubt be familiar with the many dangers inherent in trying to steal priceless paintings and rare jewels from museums.</p>
        <p>There are the ever-popular Technicolor laser-beam burglar alarms, which have sought to catch thieves since the days of the ''Pink Panther'' capers. There are weight-sensitive floorboards, which necessitated the classic dangling-by-ropes-from-the-ceiling approach to grand larceny that was used in ''Topkapi.'' And there are the metal shutters that fell quickly -- but not quite quickly enough -- over the paintings in the recent remake of ''The Thomas Crown Affair.''</p>
        <p>''Now,'' said Steven R. Keller, a museum security consultant and former security director of the Art Institute of Chicago, ''you know what it's not like.''</p>
        <p>The real world of museum security, a variety of museum experts agree, resembles the movie version about as much as real-life art thieves resemble David Niven.</p>
        <p>To be sure, theft is a major concern. The very concept of a museum -- making masterpieces and other treasures readily accessible to the public -- is something of a security nightmare, one that grew more complicated when paintings routinely started selling for millions of dollars. While there are no reliable figures on the extent of art theft, Interpol estimates that it is exceeded in dollar value only by drug trafficking, money laundering and arms dealing.</p>
        <p>Protecting collections without impeding the public's ability to enjoy them is a delicate balancing act. ''There's a constant tension, a healthy tension, between security staff and curatorial staff,'' said Danny McDaniel, the director of security at Colonial Williamsburg. ''Those of us in security would bury things where you could never see them, while curators want to put things where people can not only see them but where they could almost reach out and touch them.''</p>
        <p>There are all kinds of art thieves. ''It runs the gamut,'' said Robert E. Spiel, a former F.B.I. agent who specialized in art theft and who now works as a security consultant. ''There are strong-arm people, clever people, inside people, outside people, second-story people.''</p>
        <p>Once in a long while life imitates art. Jack Murphy, known as Murph the Surf, stole the Star of India sapphire from the American Museum of Natural History in 1964 after seeing ''Topkapi.'' And the theft of a Cezanne from the Ashmolean Museum in Oxford, England, last New Year's Eve -- by a bandit who broke through a skylight, rappelled into a gallery and blinded security cameras with a smoke bomb -- was cinematic not only in execution but apparently in intent. The police theorized that it might have been arranged by a covetous collector.</p>
        <p>Museums use a wide array of impressive doodads and gizmos to guard against theft. Doors and windows, of course, have alarms. But simply securing the perimeter is not enough, because thieves can enter during the day and hide after closing.</p>
        <p>To guard against such intruders, museums use not only the familiar motion detectors but also an arsenal of increasingly sophisticated devices: infrared sensors that monitor a room's temperature and can see the shapes of warm bodies moving through it; ultrasonic sensors that trigger an alarm if their sound waves strike a foreign object; microwave sensors that work on the same principle but can be hidden within walls.</p>
        <p>Devices to protect individual objects have grown more sophisticated, too. In the old days, for example, display cases had metallic strips that sounded an alarm when the glass was broken, but ''they really took away from the attractiveness or aesthetics of the display,'' said Ernie Smith, the chief security officer at the Detroit Institute of Arts. Now, Detroit and other museums use acoustic sensors that can be as small as a quarter; they set off an alarm when they detect glass breaking or being cut.</p>
        <p>A camera trained on a specific object can be programmed to sound an alarm at any shift in the object's outline. Some institutions are even considering a sort of LoJack system for artwork: little wireless transmitters that could track the location and movement of every object in their collections. Conservators, though, are often wary of affixing anything to old works of art.</p>
        <p>These elaborate detection systems may stem burglaries, but they cannot do much about armed robberies. In the biggest art theft in recent history, two men dressed as police officers entered the Isabella Stewart Gardner Museum in Boston in 1990, overpowered the guards and made off with a Vermeer and several other masterpieces. ''Twenty years ago that just didn't happen,'' Mr. McDaniel said.</p>
        <p>And some thefts are inside jobs, plotted by employees who simply avoid the security system. In 1978, three Cezannes were stolen from the Art Institute of Chicago by a low-level art handler who worked there. The theft was discovered on the day Mr. Keller was interviewing at the museum for the post of security director. He got the job. ''It was done by an employee who never should have been hired,'' he recalled. ''It was before a lot of pre-employment screening was done, and he had faked his references.''</p>
        <p>The theft was simple. The art handler's job was to pack paintings and ship them from the museum. In this case, Mr. Keller said, he shipped them to himself. ''He was arrested trying to sell them back,'' he said.</p>
        <p>One of the century's most prolific art thieves was another insider, Prof. John Quentin Feller, a widely published expert on Chinese porcelain, who was given broad access to major collections and admitted using it to steal more than 100 objects from 8 museums in the United States and England.</p>
        <p>On the day before he began serving an 18-month prison sentence in 1991, Professor Feller told The New York Times that he began his crime spree in 1972 because he was dismayed that ''van Goghs of the porcelain field'' were being kept in dusty storage areas, out of the public's view. His practice of stealing from some museums and donating the loot to others earned him a nickname, ''Robin Hood of the art world.'' Curators, though, were not amused.</p>
        <p>TO protect against insider thefts, museums now check employees' backgrounds more carefully; issue card keys to restrict access in their buildings; spend more on guarding storage rooms, which hold the bulk of most collections; enforce stricter rules for signing objects in and out; and teach guards to watch their fellow employees as closely as they watch strangers. With today's tiny, high-resolution video cameras and Internet technology, nervous museum officials can now view their galleries (and their guards) from a central control room -- or even from home.</p>
        <p>That is a long way from the days when an alarm would go off and light up a board in a central control room, recalled Robert W. Ducibella, the director of Chapman Ducibella Associates, a security consulting and design firm. Guards had to check which number was lighted; in an enormous institution like the Metropolitan Museum of Art, they would then have to get out a manual to find it and to determine whether it was a fire alarm or a burglar alarm, and sometimes another manual to see which procedures to follow. With computers, all the information -- what happened, where it happened and what to do -- can pop up on a screen.</p>
        <p>But in the end, the security experts say, even the most dazzling technology is at the mercy of human beings. ''An electronic device by itself is useless,'' said Mr. McDaniel, of Colonial Williamsburg. ''It depends entirely on the response.''</p>
        <p>The Big Dangers: Fire and Fingers</p>
        <p>ART theft may get more publicity than any other issue facing museum security officials, but it is not their only concern -- or even the most pressing.</p>
        <p>Fire poses a much greater threat thaen even the biggest criminal masterminds. Many museums are reluctant to use sprinkler systems, for fear that an accident could flood their paintings. Some use sprinklers whose pipes stay empty until the fire is detected; others use chemicals or gases to extinguish fires, although one of the popular gases was found to threaten the ozone layer. And while many use quick-closing fire doors to isolate and contain fires, the trend in museum design toward long, open spaces poses its own difficulties.</p>
        <p>Robert W. Ducibella, the director of Chapman Ducibella Associates, a security consulting and design firm, says that the newest fire alarms, which were first used in military bases and air-traffic control centers, can sample air for minute particles of combustion. Other fire alarms gauge smoke, heat, light and air ionization.</p>
        <p>But the most ubiquitous security concern may be the most mundane: visitors for whom those ''Do Not Touch'' signs are a challenge rather than a warning.</p>
        <p>Some museums use electric-eye-type sensors that beep or play recorded messages when people get too close to the art. Others place works behind railings, or, in cases like the ''Mona Lisa'' and a certain controversial painting incorporating elephant dung, behind glass.</p>
        <p>Some museums rely on psychology: a strip of brass along the floor, about a foot and a half from the wall, has been effective in keeping people from getting too close to the displays.</p>
        <p>Of course, it helps to know that some artworks are simply more likely to be touched than others.</p>
        <p>''If there's a nude, for some reason, somebody always wants to touch it,'' said Steven R. Keller, a museum security consultant. ''Also religious art.''</p>
        <p>MICHAEL COOPER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
