<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cut Emissions, Rowland to Tell Power Plants</title>
    <meta content="17EMIS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1200179"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clean Air Act</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Massachusetts</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowland, John G (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Smog</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EEDA1F3BF934A25756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cut Emissions, Rowland to Tell Power Plants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, May 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Gov John G Rowland plans to sign executive order intended to sharply cut emissions from Connecticut's six antiquated coal- and oil-burning power plants and dozens of other plants within three years, joining New York and Massachusetts in moving to curtail pollution that causes acid rain and smog; taken together, moves by three states to cut pollution will put region far ahead of rest of nation in efforts to reduce emissions under Clean Air Act (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. John G. Rowland plans to sign an executive order Wednesday intended to sharply cut emissions from Connecticut's six antiquated coal- and oil-burning power plants and dozens of other plants within three years, joining New York and Massachusetts in moving to curtail pollution that causes acid rain and smog.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the moves by the three states to cut pollution would put the region far ahead of the rest of the nation in efforts to reduce emissions under the Clean Air Act. And the actions by the three Republican governors suggest that environmental issues have taken on added political importance in a presidential election year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. John G. Rowland plans to sign an executive order Wednesday intended to sharply cut emissions from Connecticut's six antiquated coal- and oil-burning power plants and dozens of other plants within three years, joining New York and Massachusetts in moving to curtail pollution that causes acid rain and smog.</p>
        <p>Taken together, the moves by the three states to cut pollution would put the region far ahead of the rest of the nation in efforts to reduce emissions under the Clean Air Act. And the actions by the three Republican governors suggest that environmental issues have taken on added political importance in a presidential election year.</p>
        <p>Governor Rowland's order directs Connecticut's Department of Environmental Quality to establish regulations to cut emissions at about 60 plants by as much as 59 percent, an aide to Mr. Rowland said today.</p>
        <p>His directive accomplishes what the state's Democratic-led General Assembly failed to do two weeks ago. In the final days of the 2000 legislative session, the House of Representatives dropped consideration of a measure to force the six power plants to cut pollution after opponents in the State Senate attached a rider that eliminated any deadline for the reductions.</p>
        <p>Environmental groups, faced with the choice of backing an amended bill they regarded as toothless or trying again next year, reluctantly let the bill die. Days later, Mr. Rowland directed his environmental commissioner to begin negotiations with the three Republican lawmakers who had opposed the bill, an aide said.</p>
        <p>The six power plants are in Bridgeport, New Haven, Middletown, Milford, Norwalk and Montville. Because of a loophole in the 1977 Clean Air Act, the plants had been exempt from meeting modern air-pollution limits for chemicals like sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxide, two of the prime ingredients of smog, which scientists have linked to increased rates of asthma and other illnesses.</p>
        <p>The executive order, to be announced Wednesday afternoon, will most likely require reductions of emissions of nitrogen oxide to one pound, and sulfur dioxide to four pounds, per megawatt hour of each plant's operation.</p>
        <p>The plants now emit about two to three times those amounts, said Bernadette Del Chiaro, a director of the Toxics Action Center, which lobbied heavily for the failed bill.</p>
        <p>The action comes a week after Massachusetts, under Gov. Paul Cellucci, announced an agreement with older power plants to cut emissions, and seven months after Gov. George E. Pataki ordered power plants in New York State to sharply cut smokestack emissions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland's timing in issuing the executive order Wednesday is politically impeccable. At once he is able to reap unlikely if grudging  praise from environmentalists who had been counting on Democrats to pass the emissions bill, and make the Democratic leaders in the House and Senate seem weak on an issue that is historically one of their strengths.</p>
        <p>''It's basically modeled on what the Legislature would have done if it hadn't fallen apart,'' said an aide to Mr. Rowland, speaking on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>The aide declined to discuss the provisions in the order but said they would allow companies to sell emissions-reductions credits to plants in other states and would include a May 2003 deadline to reduce emissions.</p>
        <p>''The governor felt pretty strongly that he could reach some kind of agreement with the industry,'' the aide said. But in the end, Mr. Rowland, with an environmental and political opportunity in hand, chose not to negotiate with the power companies, figuring they would slow the process too much, the aide said.</p>
        <p>As lawmakers were considering the emissions bill, power companies lobbied heavily against it, saying it could raise electricity rates, would not significantly clean the air and would cost hundreds of millions of dollars in retooling that could cause energy brownouts.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
