<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Oresteia,' Bearer of Many Agendas</title>
    <meta content="07WREN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal Shakespeare Company</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Celia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aeschylus (525-456 Bc)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oresteia, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4DC1039F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Oresteia,' Bearer of Many Agendas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Celia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Celia Wren appraises The Oresteia, Aeschylus' tragic trilogy which will be performed by Royal Shakespeare Company at Brooklyn Academy of Music; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MURDER. Adultery. Courtroom drama. A fugitive's hair-raising flight from implacable justice.</p>
        <p>With super-heated elements like these to work with, it is no wonder that modern playwrights keep rewriting ''The Oresteia,'' the fifth-century B.C. dramatic trilogy by Aeschylus about a family ensnared in guilt and violence. T. S. Eliot did it in his 1930's verse play ''The Family Reunion,'' which the Royal Shakespeare Company begins performing on Wednesday at the Brooklyn Academy of Music. Eugene O'Neill did it in his brooding ''Mourning Becomes Electra.'' David Rabe did it in his Vietnam drama ''The Orphan.'' And in the first months of 2000, a crop of contemporary theater folk have been essaying the same task, spinning off audacious adaptations that link Aeschylus to the sociopolitical anxieties of the age.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MURDER. Adultery. Courtroom drama. A fugitive's hair-raising flight from implacable justice.</p>
        <p>With super-heated elements like these to work with, it is no wonder that modern playwrights keep rewriting ''The Oresteia,'' the fifth-century B.C. dramatic trilogy by Aeschylus about a family ensnared in guilt and violence. T. S. Eliot did it in his 1930's verse play ''The Family Reunion,'' which the Royal Shakespeare Company begins performing on Wednesday at the Brooklyn Academy of Music. Eugene O'Neill did it in his brooding ''Mourning Becomes Electra.'' David Rabe did it in his Vietnam drama ''The Orphan.'' And in the first months of 2000, a crop of contemporary theater folk have been essaying the same task, spinning off audacious adaptations that link Aeschylus to the sociopolitical anxieties of the age.</p>
        <p>Feminism, environmentalism, pacifism, left-wing-elite-bashing -- all of these agendas, it turns out, can fit comfortably into the three plays that make up ''The Oresteia'': ''Agamemnon,''  ''The Libation Bearers'' and ''The Eumenides.'' The trilogy can even make pointed comments about geopolitics, or channel a wacky gay sendup like Aaron Mack Schloff's ''Agamemnon vs. Liberace.'' It can refer to world history or theater history. And, like a fine whiskey, it still appeals to connoisseurs in its original, undiluted form.</p>
        <p>Of course, the Greek classics are always in style and always relevant. But ''The Oresteia'' occupies a privileged position in the Western canon, in part because it is the only surviving example of an ancient Greek tragic trilogy. Factor in the work's profound themes -- guilt, the legacy of violence, the role of law, the burden of individual conscience -- and it is easy to understand why the three plays are considered by many to be at the summit of dramatic literature in the West. And like most classics, of course, the themes lend themselves to productions that take the material in diverse directions, as can be seen already this year.</p>
        <p>In January, the Clarence Brown Theater Company in Knoxville, Tenn., mounted ''The Millennium Project,'' a group-developed variation on ''The Oresteia'' that will travel to a festival in Bratislava, Slovakia, in June.</p>
        <p>In February, the Sledgehammer Theater in San Diego presented a premiere of Kelly Stuart's ''Furious Blood,'' a savage comedy that tackled the ancient text from a feminist standpoint.</p>
        <p>''Agamemnon vs. Liberace'' was presented at the Here Arts Center in New York in March, the same month that Mark Jackson's class-conscious ''Messenger No. 1'' made its debut in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>At the same time, other companies have been hewing more closely to Aeschylus' original, which was itself a treatment of pre-existing material: the dark, mythological stories that, by Aeschylus' day, had already figured in the works of Homer and the sixth-century B.C. poet Stesichorus.</p>
        <p>In April, a production of ''The Oresteia'' by the Royal National Theater of London, using a translation by Ted Hughes, Britain's late poet laureate, visited the Du Maurier World Stage festival in Toronto. In New York, the Pearl Theater Company is presenting a new translation by the classics scholar Peter Meineck in a production that opened last month and runs through May 28.</p>
        <p>These artists are riding a wave of interest, across the theater world, in staging Greek classics. It is a development that has been particularly visible in high-profile revivals like last year's ''Electra'' on Broadway. This popularity has been attributed by critics to a variety of factors, including the plays' openness to nontraditional casting, the major roles they offer to actresses, and the appeal of stark themes at a time of end-of-the-millennium angst.</p>
        <p>Contemporary fears may find deep echoes in ''The Oresteia'' because it is, arguably, about civilization itself. During Aeschylus' lifetime, Athenians instituted an early form of democracy and reformed their courts, a campaign of liberalization that the playwright alluded to in ''The Eumenides.'' The trilogy tells the story of the House of Atreus, a dysfunctional family with a nasty episode of cannibalism in its closet. At the start of ''The Oresteia,'' Queen Clytemnestra of Argos murders her husband, retaliating against his callous sacrifice of their daughter Iphigenia at the beginning of the Trojan war. Her son, Orestes, subsequently kills his mother with the encouragement of his fanatical sister Electra, only to find himself pursued by a set of creepy avenging goddesses known as the Furies. In ''The Eumenides'' (or ''the kindly ones,'' as the Furies were known in their more benevolent form), the goddess Athena placates these minor deities and clears Orestes' name, while more or less inventing trial by jury.</p>
        <p>So you can argue that the trilogy describes a movement away from barbarism toward a more modern concept of civilization, lawyers and all. ''People are into 'The Oresteia' because it's about the evolution into democracy of some pre-democratic phase of justice,'' said Dr. Helene Foley, a professor of Greek and Latin at Barnard College.</p>
        <p>Thus, the trilogy invites playwrights and directors to reflect broadly on humanity's collective experience. The challenge is one the American theater began to respond to in the 1960's, resulting in seminal productions like the Guthrie Theater's ''House of Atreus'' (adapted by John Lewin), a Minneapolis production that visited New York in 1968; Andre Serban's highly stylized ''Agamemnon'' at the New York Shakespeare Festival in 1977; and Charles L. Mee Jr.'s ''Agamemnon'' (produced in 1994 by the Actors' Gang in Los Angeles), which put chorus-like speeches into the mouths of writers like Homer and Hesiod.</p>
        <p>A number of this season's adaptations have opted for the sociopolitical approach. For example, in ''Messenger No. 1,'' which he directed at the Exit Stage Left theater in San Francisco, Mark Jackson deliberately upended the ostensibly optimistic sociopolitical message of ''The Oresteia.''</p>
        <p>''If the trial-by-jury system of justice was designed to replace blood-based justice,'' he said during a recent interview, ''why hasn't violence decreased?'' Mr. Jackson, who believes that ''the justice system is flawed and designed by the upper classes,'' used his play to drive home his point. His comedy explores the frustrations that beset Argos's working-class messengers, while spoiled aristocrats like Orestes reap the benefits of democracy.</p>
        <p>Other adaptors have focused on the battle of the sexes rather than class conflict. Aeschylus' narrative represents a prime target for feminists because it repeatedly pits men against women (Agamemnon-Iphigenia; Clytemnestra-Agamemnon; Orestes-Clytemnestra; the Furies-Orestes), and because the denouement of ''The Eumenides'' seems to affirm male power at the expense of female authority figures (the Furies). Emphasizing this archetypal rift, some artists have turned ''The Oresteia'' into a biting critique of the patriarchy -- as the renowned French troupe Theatre du Soleil did in ''Les Atrides'' (which visited the Brooklyn Academy of Music in 1992).</p>
        <p>Like ''Les Atrides,'' Kelly Stuart's ''Furious Blood'' makes feminist hay by incorporating scenes that depict the sacrifice of Iphigenia -- episodes portrayed in Euripides'  ''Iphigenia in Aulis'' but not in ''The Oresteia'' itself. The addition of this material tends to make Clytemnestra a more sympathetic character. An audience that watches Agamemnon condemn his teenage daughter to the knife for the sake of military expediency (to placate the gods so that his army can sail for Troy), is more likely to understand when his outraged wife hacks him to death.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stuart, for her part, chose to retell the entire House of Atreus story from Clytemnestra's point of view, turning the queen's hostile daughter Electra, for example, into a shrill version of, Ms. Stuart said, ''Dr. Laura, or one of those women who make a career out of anti-feminism.''</p>
        <p>As ''Furious Blood'' builds to its climax, its feminist message becomes blunter. In the concluding scene, the frustrated Furies hurl bloody tampons at Apollo, who finally appeals to the audience for some anti-P.C. support. ''Tell me the truth, do you like hot babes?'' he demands, comparing a glamorous Athena to the Furies. ''Or those ugly, bloodthirsty, oozing old bags?''</p>
        <p>''The Millennium Project,'' developed cooperatively by master's degree students at the University of Tennessee under the director Henryk Baranowski, took a similarly feminist tack. According to Amy Russell, who is credited on the final script as the adaptor, one aim of the production was to deepen Clytemnestra's character and to ''correct'' the way Aeschylus ''demonized'' the feminine.</p>
        <p>But the project also included some specifically contemporary twists. Orestes and Electra are rebellious adolescents who dress as Goth music groupies, and the Furies threaten the earth with a devastating plague that sounds a lot like acid rain. Ms. Russell said that she and her collaborators were inspired to link ''The Oresteia'' to ''science, technology, destruction of the environment, the apocalyptic flavor of the times.''</p>
        <p>Emphasizing the topicality of ''The Oresteia'' can be hazardous, as the British director Katie Mitchell found when she directed Ted Hughes's translation for the Royal National Theater. The production, now on an international tour, uses modern dress and deliberate anachronisms that seem to refer to the turmoil in the Balkans: Agamemnon is dressed much like a Bosnian warlord, for example.</p>
        <p>Some reviewers found such touches gimmicky and distracting when the production opened in December. But Ms. Mitchell defended her intention: to orient the contemporary viewer. ''We decided we'd try to find the simplest modern equivalent to every moment in the play,'' she said, ''so that someone who knew nothing about Greek drama or the story could understand at once what was going on.''</p>
        <p>On some level, though, she does think that this ''Oresteia'' responds to current events, including developments in the former Yugoslavia. ''A lot of us feel morally thrown,'' she said, ''and don't know how to find our bearings morally and politically. To some extent the production was working that through.''</p>
        <p>In answer to the critics, she acknowledged that the staging was too ambitious to be perfect, adding in her defense that the ''The Oresteia'' is ''an extraordinary, impossible mountain.''</p>
        <p>THAT'S the same image Shepard Sobel used when he described the Pearl Theater Company's longtime goal of staging ''The Oresteia.''</p>
        <p>''Over the 15 years that we've been doing theater, we've been preparing ourselves,'' he said enthusiastically, ''knowing it was the top of the mountain in many ways.''</p>
        <p>Looking back on his decision to schedule the work for the spring of 2000, Mr. Sobel thinks he was subconsciously responding to recent world crises.</p>
        <p>''The last two or three years have seen what seems to be an explosion of barbarian impulses,'' he said. ''Race wars and ethnic wars, and the most horrid kind of violence -- neighbors against each other in the Balkans, in the Bronx, all over the place.''</p>
        <p>At times like these, Mr. Sobel said, staging ''The Oresteia'' -- in which a cycle of violence is deliberately stopped -- is almost a public service. ''I believe that if we could do 'The Oresteia' well enough, and get enough people to come see it, it would make a difference to this horrid blood vengeance,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meineck, the translator, agreed that ''The Oresteia'' resonates with the zeitgeist. But he pointed primarily to a shared cosmopolitan outlook as the bond between the present time and that of Aeschylus. ''New York now is the Athens that was,'' said Mr. Meineck, who is the producing artistic director of the Aquila Theater Company. But in any case, he cautioned, Aeschylus' masterpiece transcends topicality and scholarly footnotes -- it is also a gripping horror story. Experiencing a production, he said, is ''like watching 'The Omen' films.''</p>
        <p>So is this season's prevalence of ''Oresteias'' a confluence of ancient Greek omens or a theatrical response to global and social rifts at the turn of the millennium?</p>
        <p>John Chioles, the author of ''Aeschylus: Mythic Theater, Political Voice,'' a book about performing ''The Oresteia,'' goes further: ''It might well be redundant to say that this work is always timely. It is more than that. It may well be the history of the race of humans.''</p>
        <p>THEATER Celia Wren is the managing editor of American Theater magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Celia Wren is the managing editor of American Theater magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
