<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Slipping Through Stream and Bay by Kayak</title>
    <meta content="23SEAR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1216992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="IN SEARCH OF..."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kayaks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Forsythe, Edwin B, National Wildlife Refuge</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Raritan Bay (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Delaware River</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'agnese, Joseph</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Kayaking and Canoeing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Delaware</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000723T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2DD163AF930A15754C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Slipping Through Stream and Bay by Kayak</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH D'AGNESE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">D'agnese, Joseph</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article describes trip by kayak, guided by Brian Coen, in and around pair of islands in salt marshes of Edwin B Forsythe National Wildlife Refuge along south Jersey shore; list of firms that offer excursions along Jersey Shore, south branch of Raritan River and on Delaware River; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EACH morning, when the skies above the sea are still shot with pink, Brian Coen rises, dresses and hurries out to keep his date with the tide. By 8 a.m., his boats are ready by the dock in Harvey Cedars, when tourists start showing up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coen, a 24-year-old with red hair and a surfer's muscular build, greets them all. They are a mixed bunch: parents with children, adventurous seniors and quiet loners hoping for a glimpse of the watery world between the mainland and Long Beach Island.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EACH morning, when the skies above the sea are still shot with pink, Brian Coen rises, dresses and hurries out to keep his date with the tide. By 8 a.m., his boats are ready by the dock in Harvey Cedars, when tourists start showing up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coen, a 24-year-old with red hair and a surfer's muscular build, greets them all. They are a mixed bunch: parents with children, adventurous seniors and quiet loners hoping for a glimpse of the watery world between the mainland and Long Beach Island.</p>
        <p>A quick lecture, a paddling lesson, and they're off. For the next two hours, Mr. Coen will lead his charges in and around a pair of islands in the salt marshes of Edwin B. Forsythe National Wildlife Refuge.</p>
        <p>The customers have paid Mr. Coen's employers -- either Harvey Cedars Marina in Harvey Cedars or Island Surf and Sail in Brant Beach -- about $45 each for the privilege of piloting ocean kayaks around the waters south of Barnegat Bay.</p>
        <p>The kayak, one of the most ancient sea vessels, was originally designed as a hunting boat that pursued sea mammals, waterfowl and caribou traipsing across the tundra. Covered with a tight shell of animal skin, the kayak was shielded from waves, mist and the harsh breath of the sea.</p>
        <p>Propelled by a double-bladed paddle in the hands of athletes, kayaks zip through whitewater and sea currents at blistering speeds. But at the Jersey Shore, these elegant vessels are most often a vacationer's  plaything, a handy tool for visiting worlds one seldom sees.</p>
        <p>The closer that world, the more startling it is to behold. Take the hottest trip in Clinton, for example. It winds 12 miles down  the South Branch of the Raritan, past the town's oft-photographed red mill, the sleepy village of Stanton Station and finally, after eight small bridges, Flemington. Not exactly Lewis &amp; Clark territory, right? And yet, said Peter Pender, a boating outfitter who has run Clinton Canoe and Kayak with his wife, Dena, and three sons for the last 13 years: ''It's a country river. You don't see houses, you're not floating past peoples' backyards. It's all trees and bridges for 12  miles.''</p>
        <p>What you do see are turtles, ducks, and geese. There are deer, herons and egrets. And there is also a palpable sense of what life might have been like in Hunterdon County in the days before reliable ground transportation. Even today river travel is inherently unpredictable -- as Mr. Pender knows first hand.</p>
        <p>''This is moving water,'' he said. ''It's not like a swimming pool. A tree may have come down the night before. A 60-foot-tall one came down just this week, so we're constantly scanning the water. I had to have a tree removed because Mr. and Mrs. Beaver started in on it.''</p>
        <p>Boaters can also take a seven-mile trip, or just paddle in the calm, flat water alongside the boathouse. (Flat-water paddling costs only $20 a boat, up to two hours.) On weekends, the Penders even roll out a Model A truck waterfront and sell barbecued ribs, hot dogs and sausage sandwiches. Oh yes, said Mr. Pender, it's a good time down by the river, but it's not without rules: No alcohol. All boaters must be able to swim. No children under 6 are permitted in boats. And there must be 2-to-1 ratio of children to adults, a rule that has nipped many a birthday party plan in the bud.</p>
        <p>''I always stress that we're into family boating,'' he said. ''We're not going to give you rapids or danger.''</p>
        <p>Down at the shore, Mr. Coen is constantly sitting before his computer, checking weather reports. Kayaks are the preferred method of travel in the salt marshes: narrow in profile, soundless except for the gentle splash of water, they offer an unparalleled method of approaching wildlife. But the wide-hulled boats that tour companies rent  novices can be tough to paddle in windy conditions.</p>
        <p>''That's why I like to get people out early,' said Mr. Coen, who is in his third summer as a marsh guide. ''Eight a.m. That's before the wind kicks up, or other boats come out.''</p>
        <p>In the time before the hordes of beachgoers arrive and drive the island's wildlife for cover, quiet kayakers can spot long-beaked wading bird -- usually herons, great egrets and glossy ibises -- fishing for their breakfasts, and ospreys wheeling overhead.</p>
        <p>In past summers, said Bill Stuempfig, a self-taught naturalist, boat captain and owner of Bay Cats Kayaks and Catamarans in Ocean City, visitors could spot lots of diamondback terrapins but the species has diminished in recent years because so many terrapins are killed crossing roads to lay their eggs.</p>
        <p>Another change awaiting you in the marshes: pelicans. Commonplace in the South, they were seldom found in New Jersey. ''People say it's because of global warming,'' said Mr. Coen. ''But no one knows, really. We used to see them in August, the warmest time of the year. But now  we're seeing them in May and June, and they stick around until October.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stuempfig, who runs tours farther south along the shore, near the Great Egg River harbor estuary, said: '''The best part of the kayak, is that you are low enough to the water that birds do not care that you're there.''</p>
        <p>With so much to see, human visitors who have a good time on rental trips are likely to want to buy their own boats. One could argue it's the chief reason rental outfits  exist. Get hooked, and you just might join the club. ''We don't make a lot of money on rentals,' said Mr. Pender in Clinton. ''There's a lot of maintenance involved. But we hear all the time, 'Hey, that was neat. Let's buy a boat.' ''</p>
        <p>Traditionally, the boat offered is a ''deck kayak,'' with a hull completely enclosed except for a small hole in top. Paddlers stow  gear in the hull and slip into the hole with their legs stretched out before them. It makes for a snug ride, but many newcomers feel uncomfortable maneuvering in such close quarters. A newer alternative, the ''sit-on-top,'' is open to the air, built of durable plastic, and floats in case the boat flips. A one-person kayak stretches about 11 to 13 feet long, weighs 35 to 40 pounds, and  costs between $400 to $600. A double, or tandem kayak, 12 to 15 feet, weighs 55 to 75 pounds, and costs about $900.</p>
        <p>Size and weight can matter, because some excursions call for lifting as well as paddling. Mr. Pender's river trip down the Raritan, for example, requires one portage; at some point along the river, boaters need to get out and haul their vessel over a 3-by-1-foot cement wall blocking their path.</p>
        <p>And people heading to the beach can expect a workout hoisting their new toy on and off the top of their cars.</p>
        <p>But this is small price to pay.</p>
        <p>''It's very mellow being out on the water,'' said Mr. Coen, who bids adieu to the Jersey Shore each fall and heads for Costa Rica to surf. ''Many times you can do the whole tour and see no people.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Stuempfig, who at 47, has spent a lifetime near or on the water, first in Florida and now at the shore, searches for analogies  to describe the kayak's graceful glide through water. ''It's really relaxing,'' he said. ''It's not too strenuous; it's like swimming slowly. And the way we do it, we take advantage of the tides, so you're going up with the tide and you ride the tide back, so there's some floating time. You can't believe how peaceful it is a mile from the boardwalk.''</p>
        <p>IN SEARCH OF...</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
