<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Politics of Fuel</title>
    <meta content="02MON1$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/02/opinion/02MON1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1235525"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CAMPAIGN 2000: TODAY -- ENERGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D9123DF931A35753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="779" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Politics of Fuel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial in series, Campaign 2000, on issues in presidential campaign focuses on 'pronounced' differences between Gov George W Bush and Vice Pres Al Gore on energy policy; says sharp rise in oil prices has given energy new and unexpected prominence but that what ought to be serious debate has been marred by unedifying accusations about who deserves blame for allowing US to sink further into dependence on oil and has diverted attention from inconvenient truths about America's energy problem (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sharp rise in oil prices over the last few months has given energy issues new and unexpected prominence in the presidential campaign. But what ought to be a serious debate has been marred by unedifying accusations about who deserves blame for allowing America to sink further into ''dependence on foreign oil.'' Gov. George W. Bush says the Democrats have inhibited oil exploration with their environmental and tax policies. Vice President Al  Gore says the Republicans have allowed ''big oil'' to put profits ahead of the American consumer. All this has diverted attention from two inconvenient truths about America's energy problem.</p>
        <p>First, the notion that the United States can ''free'' itself from foreign oil is absurd. America consumes about one-quarter of the world's oil supply but possesses less than 4 percent of the world's reserves, and much of the economically recoverable domestic oil has been identified. About half of the oil consumed in America now comes from foreign sources, and this figure is likely to rise rather than fall. The task, therefore, is not to engage in a futile debate over energy ''independence'' but to find new ways of managing dependence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sharp rise in oil prices over the last few months has given energy issues new and unexpected prominence in the presidential campaign. But what ought to be a serious debate has been marred by unedifying accusations about who deserves blame for allowing America to sink further into ''dependence on foreign oil.'' Gov. George W. Bush says the Democrats have inhibited oil exploration with their environmental and tax policies. Vice President Al  Gore says the Republicans have allowed ''big oil'' to put profits ahead of the American consumer. All this has diverted attention from two inconvenient truths about America's energy problem.</p>
        <p>First, the notion that the United States can ''free'' itself from foreign oil is absurd. America consumes about one-quarter of the world's oil supply but possesses less than 4 percent of the world's reserves, and much of the economically recoverable domestic oil has been identified. About half of the oil consumed in America now comes from foreign sources, and this figure is likely to rise rather than fall. The task, therefore, is not to engage in a futile debate over energy ''independence'' but to find new ways of managing dependence.</p>
        <p>The second and related truth is that the demand side of the energy equation is as important, if not more so, than the supply side. If Americans want stable prices and greater protection from market manipulation, they and their elected representatives will have to pay far more attention to conservation, finding new ways to use energy more efficiently.</p>
        <p>The supply side cannot, of course, be ignored. Domestic oil production is plainly not the answer to the country's energy needs, and for economic and environmental reasons, nuclear and hydroelectric power cannot be expected to take up the slack. But there is still plenty of oil available to American companies outside the United States -- in Africa and the Caspian Sea, for example. In North America, especially the Gulf of Mexico and Canada, there are also substantial supplies of natural gas. Indeed, natural gas has become the fuel of choice for most American homeowners and the electric power industry, which plans to use it to run more than 90 percent of the power plants now on the drawing boards. Both candidates have recommended new incentives to encourage drilling for natural gas.</p>
        <p>Inevitably, however, any sensible energy strategy will also require conservation, a matter on which Congress and the public need serious educating, and on which presidential leadership will therefore be crucial. This Congress has been unable to pass legislation governing the restructuring of the electric power industry. It has been openly contemptuous of the Kyoto agreement aimed at reducing emissions from fossil fuels and thus reducing dependence on fossil fuels. It could not even agree on a modest tax incentive for more fuel-efficient buildings. Meanwhile, the astounding popularity of ever-larger S.U.V.'s and other light trucks has reversed a 20-year trend of improved fuel efficiency.</p>
        <p>The differences between the two candidates on energy issues are pronounced. Mr. Bush sought to narrow these differences in a major address on Friday, calling for $1.4 billion in tax credits over 10 years to encourage electricity generation from alternative fuels. He also said he would spend $2 billion over 10 years for ''clean coal'' technologies, aimed at exploiting the country's huge supplies of cheap but polluting supplies of coal.</p>
        <p>But his strategy still relies mainly on increasing supply, including uncontroversial ideas like streamlining regulatory restrictions on pipeline construction and hugely controversial ideas like opening the coastal plain of the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge to drilling. According to the latest government estimates, the mean estimate of economically recoverable oil in the plain is 3.2 billion barrels. Environmentalists and Mr. Gore do not think it is worth defacing a pristine wilderness for what amounts to about six months' worth of oil.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Gore has offered a dizzying array of proposals aimed at increased energy efficiency. These include generous tax credits for more fuel-efficient buildings and factories, and for consumers who buy fuel-efficient vehicles and appliances. In addition, Mr. Gore proposes major federal investments in light rail systems and various public-private partnerships, including a Gore favorite, the Partnership for a New Generation of Vehicles, which is aimed at developing cars and trucks that run on batteries or fuel cells.</p>
        <p>In dollar terms, Mr. Gore's energy proposals would cost about $50 billion over 10 years, dwarfing Mr. Bush's $7.1 billion. But dollars do not accurately define this debate. Mr. Gore believes that consumption is the main problem. Mr. Bush thinks that production is the main answer. This is as clear a difference as one can find in this campaign.</p>
        <p>CAMPAIGN 2000: TODAY -- ENERGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
