<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crew Members Fault Air Quality on 777's</title>
    <meta content="15REP.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/15/travel/15REP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1238799"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Flight Attendants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">British Airways Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Flight Attendants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D8103CF936A25753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crew Members Fault Air Quality on 777's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Airlines and British Airways, two biggest operators of Boeing 777's, launch investigations into air quality on planes after rash of complaints from flight attendants about dizziness or nausea (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Boeing 777, the jewel in the fleet of many of the world's largest airlines, may be more likely to make passengers feel dizzy or nauseated than other, older airplanes, according to anecdotal reports from crew members and passengers.</p>
        <p>After a rash of complaints from flight attendants, both United Airlines and British Airways -- the two biggest operators of 777's -- have launched investigations into air quality on the planes. Boeing is helping with both inquiries, an engineer there said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Boeing 777, the jewel in the fleet of many of the world's largest airlines, may be more likely to make passengers feel dizzy or nauseated than other, older airplanes, according to anecdotal reports from crew members and passengers.</p>
        <p>After a rash of complaints from flight attendants, both United Airlines and British Airways -- the two biggest operators of 777's -- have launched investigations into air quality on the planes. Boeing is helping with both inquiries, an engineer there said.</p>
        <p>Among the possible reasons for the problems, aviation experts said, are the high altitude at which the 777 flies, which can mean less oxygen, and an air-conditioning system that can make some parts of the plane hotter than others, causing some passengers to feel queasy as the plane hurtles through the sky.</p>
        <p>Through the first seven months of this year, United's flight attendants filed 26 reports about falling ill on the 777, twice as many as for the Boeing 767 even though United has six more 767's in its fleet. The Daily Telegraph, a London newspaper, ran a series of articles this spring in which passengers said they felt short of breath, suffered nosebleeds or fainted after flying on 777's. The unhappy travelers included Robert Johnston, an ex-pilot and former medical examiner for Britain's Civil Aviation Authority, who told the paper that a lack of air made him feel ''slightly hallucinatory'' on a flight from San Diego to London.</p>
        <p>United has begun modifying its 43 777's to make air temperature more uniform, both over the course of a flight and in different sections of a plane. ''We found temperatures to be a problem,'' said Max Malone, the airline's manager of occupational safety.</p>
        <p>Already, United has deleted a piece of software from the computer system in 777's that caused the temperature to rise by one degree for every hour a plane is airborne. Boeing added the feature because passengers' metabolisms tend to slow during a long flight, making them feel colder. In addition, United has moved six thermostats to a central location on the plane so that one crew member is in charge of air temperature throughout the plane.</p>
        <p>By the end of next year, United will also have added new vents in the back of the 777 to increase air flow in an area where some flight attendants spend much of a flight.</p>
        <p>Boeing is also studying whether the altitude at which the plane flies could be causing some of the problems. The 777 can reach an altitude of 41,000 feet, as much as 10,000 feet higher than other models. That forces the crew to keep cabin pressure at its maximum -- the equivalent of 8,000 feet. As anybody who ever visited a mountain town knows, high elevation brings less oxygen and can cause lightheadedness.</p>
        <p>For its part, British Airways, which has hired the Royal Air Force Center of Aviation Medicine to help conduct its study, is still collecting data, said Jo Devereux, a spokeswoman for the airline.</p>
        <p>Like United's, British Airways' flight attendants have filed complaints about becoming ill on the 777. ''We are taking these reports very seriously,'' Ms. Devereux said. She added that British Airways had not heard from a significant number of passengers claiming to have become sick and that the company was not particularly alarmed by the Daily Telegraph's stories.</p>
        <p>''You need to put that into context,'' Ms. Devereux said. ''We carry 40 million passengers a year, and some of them are likely to get dizzy or faint.''</p>
        <p>Other large operators of the 777, such as American and Continental, have not received an unusual level of complaints about the plane, spokesmen for the carriers said.</p>
        <p>Boeing built the 777, which seats between 300 and 400 people, to fill a gap between the giant double-deck 747 and the smaller 767. United sent the first triple-7, as the plane is known in the industry, into the air in 1995, and there are now almost 300 around the world. They fly primarily between continents and save fuel by using two engines, one engine fewer than older planes of similar size. They have large overhead bins, and many boast a wheelchair-accessible bathroom in the middle of the plane. Boeing also says that the 777 has the widest coach seats of any commercial plane.</p>
        <p>But the air-quality complaints have landed the 777 in the middle of a long-running and thorny debate over just how safe airplane air is. Executives at Airbus, Boeing and the major carriers acknowledge that the air is very dry, and thus can cause headaches or itchy throats if passengers do not drink enough water, but otherwise insist that the air quality on planes is little different from that in office buildings or trains. When people become sick after a flight, in most cases it is because they are tired or in a new country, the executives say.</p>
        <p>Tests have shown that the air inside 777's meets all industry standards for levels of ozone, carbon dioxide and other gases, said Richard A. Johnson, an environmental control systems engineer at Boeing. The quality of air on the planes is ''great,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Some consumer advocates and officials of the unions for flight attendants say the issue is not so simple, however. To save fuel, airlines now pump less fresh air into planes than they once did. Today about half of the air is recycled; until the 1970's none of it was. With packed planes, the low ventilation levels increase the chances of people getting sick, the critics say.</p>
        <p>Boeing and airline industry officials insist that the recycled air presents no problems. Now aviation experts are wondering whether inconsistent air-conditioning systems or high altitudes do pose one.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY: CORRESPONDENT'S REPORT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
