<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gore Is Trying to Catch Up In Democrat-Dominated State</title>
    <meta content="05WEST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/05/politics/05WEST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244628"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: WEST VIRGINIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Virginia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battaile, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/West Virginia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mines and Mining</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DE1539F936A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gore Is Trying to Catch Up In Democrat-Dominated State</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET BATTAILE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battaile, Janet</byline>
      <dateline>GILES, W.Va.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Al Gore is neck-and-neck with Republican George W Bush in West Virginia, state where politics is synonymous with Democrats; difference this year seems to be that people like Bush and fear Gore's environmentalism would undermine coal mining industry (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In politics, West Virginia is synonymous with Democrats.</p>
        <p>They have controlled the Legislature for 70 years. They outnumber Republicans more than two to one among registered voters. They supported their standard-bearer in presidential races all but three times in the last half century.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In politics, West Virginia is synonymous with Democrats.</p>
        <p>They have controlled the Legislature for 70 years. They outnumber Republicans more than two to one among registered voters. They supported their standard-bearer in presidential races all but three times in the last half century.</p>
        <p>So why does the presidential race seem to be neck and neck? How did Gov. George W. Bush of Texas manage a strong lead in state polls that Vice President Al Gore has narrowed only in the last week after a visit and late-game commercials?</p>
        <p>To David Pullen, a 75-year-old retired coal miner who lives here along Cabin Creek, about 25 miles southeast of Charleston, the Bush phenomenon is simple: ''People like him.''</p>
        <p>Despite the Democrats' traditional dominance, the climate here is favorable to Mr. Bush, who made his third visit to the state on Friday. ''These are Bible-thumping, baby-saving, gun-toting conservatives,'' said John McCutcheon, executive director of the Bush-Cheney campaign, of the largely white and rural residents.</p>
        <p>Thus the vice president, who should not have had to worry about this state's five electoral votes, returned here yesterday for an airport rally in Huntington, his second visit in a little more than a week.</p>
        <p>''Here we are playing on our own turf,'' days before the election, acknowledged Dan Pfeiffer, a spokesman for the Gore campaign. But he said the Democrats were ''much better at the ground game, and we'll be doing what Democrats do best, getting out the vote.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's problems result from factors including an industry-based economy and concerns about his environmental and energy policies.</p>
        <p>The word ''environmental'' is often followed here by ''extremist'' when describing Mr. Gore, whose remedies for global warming -- including a significant reduction in carbon dioxide emissions -- are seen as a body blow to the coal industry.</p>
        <p>Particularly troublesome is the passion stirred by the industry's practice of chopping off mountaintops in its search for the rich veins of black carbon that have provided the foundation of the state's economy for more than 100 years.</p>
        <p>Mountaintop removal mining, in which the debris is shoveled into surrounding hollows, often polluting streams, has divided two natural Democratic constituencies: miners and environmentalists.</p>
        <p>''I'm better off now than what I was eight years ago,'' Paul Pullen, a logger and David's son, readily volunteered in a chat at Rita's Diner here. But he intends, like his father, to vote for Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>''There'd be a lot more new laws,'' he said, if Mr. Gore won the election. ''All the guys who work up on the mountain think he'd be bad.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush visited the state twice before Mr. Gore ever arrived, touting a domestic energy policy and a $2 billion investment in clean-coal technology. And his running mate, Dick Cheney, visited the northern panhandle, where imports of foreign steel caused big layoffs in the early 90's.</p>
        <p>The Republicans were also on the air for two months before the Democrats began to advertise. And they have been aided by an aggressive television and radio campaign by the National Rifle Association.</p>
        <p>At his rally at the Capitol in Charleston on Oct. 27, Mr. Gore emphasized protecting Social Security and Medicare, important issues in a state whose residents are among the poorest and oldest in the country. He promised to invest in clean coal technology, to reduce dependence on foreign oil and to fight for health care benefits for retired miners, their widows and those with black lung.</p>
        <p>The United Mine Workers endorsed Mr. Gore in September, but only after extracting promises that he would protect the coal industry.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush has support among union officials, including Dick Kimbler, president of United Mine Workers Local 2935 in Logan County and a lifelong Democrat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kimbler contended that while the union leadership backed the vice president , the rank and file did not all agree. The Texas governor, he said, picked up a lot of support in the debates. ''He said what people wanted to hear, and energy was 90 percent of it,'' Mr. Kimbler said.</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: WEST VIRGINIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
