<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peaceful, Easy Feeling Imbues 30th Earth Day</title>
    <meta content="Y23EAR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1194184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Earth Day</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gerth, Jeff</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Earth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Planets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DF1430F930A15757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peaceful, Easy Feeling Imbues 30th Earth Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEFF GERTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gerth, Jeff</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Environmentalists and supporters commemmorate 30th anniversary of Earth Day in ceremonies in Washington, DC, and in 183 countries; Pres Clinton pays tribute in radio address; peaceful rally at Washington Mall is addressed by Vice Pres Al Gore; described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under the banner of clean energy, Earth Day participants today celebrated in the nation's capital and at thousands of events around the globe in an extravaganza of entertainment, advocacy and politics.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and supporters participated in events in 183 countries for the 30th Earth Day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under the banner of clean energy, Earth Day participants today celebrated in the nation's capital and at thousands of events around the globe in an extravaganza of entertainment, advocacy and politics.</p>
        <p>Environmentalists and supporters participated in events in 183 countries for the 30th Earth Day.</p>
        <p>Thousands of people gathered peacefully at the Mall in Washington, less than a week after hundreds of demonstrators were arrested here, protesting the global activities of international lending agencies. Among other things, those protesters had objected to the environmental policies of the World Bank and International Monetary Fund.</p>
        <p>Today's rallies were organized by the Seattle-based Earth Day Network, whose chairman, Denis Hayes, was the national coordinator for the 1970 event.</p>
        <p>The teach-ins and rallies of that original Earth Day, more informal and less global, helped inaugurate the modern environmental movement in the United States and was the spark for two landmark environmental laws signed by President Richard M. Nixon, the Clean Air Act and the Clean Water Act.</p>
        <p>In his radio address today, President Clinton announced two new but relatively modest initiatives to combat global warming and celebrate Earth Day. Mr. Clinton said he was going to require federal agencies to reduce by 20 percent over five years the amount of gasoline their vehicle fleets consume. This would save 45 million gallons of oil a year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also announced a program to allow Federal workers to set aside up to $65 tax-free every month to pay for public transportation.</p>
        <p>'While the science on climate change has grown stronger, and the need for American leadership has grown greater, some in Congress have buried their heads even deeper in the sand,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Vice President Al Gore struck a softer chord in his address on the Mall.</p>
        <p>He welcomed ''the bipartisan talks on Capitol Hill'' and spoke of giving ''industry the flexibility'' to meet environmental goals.</p>
        <p>In a starched blue work shirt with the Capitol behind him, Mr. Gore pressed his campaign message that preserving the environment did not have to interfere with expanding the economy. ''The environment and the economy go together,'' he told the crowd. ''What's good for one is good for the other.''</p>
        <p>He plugged his 1992 book, ''Earth in the Balance,'' which has been reissued with a new forward by Mr. Gore to coincide with Earth Day. And he drew attention to his controversial contention in that book that the nation could end its dependence on the internal combustion engine in 25 years.</p>
        <p>''Today, that's conventional wisdom,'' he said. ''The Big Three auto makers are working on concept cars that produce absolutely no greenhouse gas emissions whatsoever. They know that it's not extreme but mainstream to champion cleaner fuels. And they know that protecting the environment is the right thing to do; it will create jobs, not destroy jobs, and save the Earth as we know it in the process.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Gore has been careful and was today in pressing his environmentalist views, in part because he is trying to woo supporters in the traditionally Republican business community.</p>
        <p>Dressed in a starched blue work shirt, Mr. Gore used the rally as an opportunity to reinforce his campaign message that preserving the environment did not have to interfere with expanding the economy. ''The environment and the economy go together,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Today's celebration in Washington, called EarthFair 2000, was not politically diverse. The speakers who accepted invitations tended to be Democratic and liberal. (Organizers said the presumptive Republican presidential nominee, Gov. George W. Bush of Texas, declined an invitation to speak.)</p>
        <p>But the rally's loosely organized format made for some interesting contrasts.</p>
        <p>The loudest cheers during Mr. Gore' eight-minute speech came as he mentioned the actor Leonardo DiCaprio, who led the festivities. Later tonight Mr. DiCaprio, 25, will be a host on an Earth Day special on the ABC television network. But today's rallies also featured speakers who back a campaign seeking to raise the environmental conscience of some prominent corporations, like the Walt Disney Company, which owns ABC and will distribute a movie starring Mr. DiCaprio.</p>
        <p>The campaign, ecopledge.com, asks several corporations to change environmental practices, or face possible boycotts from students seeking employment, investors or consumers.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week the ecopledge campaign sent to the companies: they asked Disney to stop selling toys containing polyvinyl chloride and they asked Citigroup's investment bank, Salomon Smith Barney, to stop underwriting bonds for the Three Gorges Dam in China. Company spokesmen said they had no comment on the letters.</p>
        <p>No one from the Earth Day Network, the organizers of today's events, signed the letter. But ecopledge leaders were planning to speak about the campaign at rallies today in Washington, Boston and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''We hope to gather 100,000 signatures,'' said Wendy Wendlandt, the president of Earth Day 2000.</p>
        <p>Some of the listeners were receptive to the idea.</p>
        <p>''I think it's good to target companies like that rather than small ones, because they are so visible and have a direct effect on our environment and lives,'' said Heather McLeod, 22, of Washington, D.C.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
