<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Road Rage, A New Jersey State of Mind</title>
    <meta content="07COV.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1197453"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tolls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1D91F39F934A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2642" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Road Rage, A New Jersey State of Mind</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article details current conditions on New Jersey highways, turnpikes and toll roads, which have gone from bad to worse; state has 34,000 miles of highway on which 60 billion vehicle miles travel annually--close to four times national average; problems with implementing E-Z Pass continue; congestion deepens as result of economic boom; commuting motorists are having to leave home earlier and some have taken apartments in New York City to avoid constant rush-hour stress; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CALL it chutzpah -- if you want to keep it clean. When you think about it, most of the people who put down New Jersey drivers are New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Take New York cabbies, who can always be counted on to yell, ''#@%&amp;x*# JERSEY DRIVER!'' That is, when they  speak in English.</p>
        <p>Not only do New Jersey's 5.8 million licensed drivers get no respect, they're made to feel guilty about using their 6.4 million vehicles. Environmentalists tell them they're depleting the ozone layer and demand that they take public transit -- something in New Jersey that doesn't always get you there from here -- and planners tell them their dream of more highway elbow room doesn't ease congestion but only contributes to sprawl.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CALL it chutzpah -- if you want to keep it clean. When you think about it, most of the people who put down New Jersey drivers are New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Take New York cabbies, who can always be counted on to yell, ''#@%&amp;x*# JERSEY DRIVER!'' That is, when they  speak in English.</p>
        <p>Not only do New Jersey's 5.8 million licensed drivers get no respect, they're made to feel guilty about using their 6.4 million vehicles. Environmentalists tell them they're depleting the ozone layer and demand that they take public transit -- something in New Jersey that doesn't always get you there from here -- and planners tell them their dream of more highway elbow room doesn't ease congestion but only contributes to sprawl.</p>
        <p>Rather than being reviled, perhaps the New Jersey driver should be pitied, comforted and -- yes -- even admired for the way he or she faces a staggering number of obstacles and dangers every day, not the least of which are those fellow New Jersey drivers.</p>
        <p>''I love living in New Jersey, where you see the state bird whenever you cut someone off on the highway,'' says Peggy Boyce, a stand-up comic. ''There's so much road rage in New Jersey I had a bumper sticker made that says 'Tony Soprano on Board.' ''</p>
        <p>And why not? The New Jersey driver still pays the among the highest insurance rates, coughs up the most money for tolls after New York state and has to get up earlier and earlier to make the Hudson River crossings on the morning commute to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Other gripes: Toll increases on the New Jersey Turnpike. The 134,000 trucks that drive on the state's highways every day. Confusing and unreadable signs.</p>
        <p>Not to mention the glacial implementation of E-ZPass. It's coming. It's not coming. It will be operational on the whole Garden State Parkway by June -- in time for the annual migration to the shore. Um, make that in time for the change of autumn foliage. (Get out a lawn chair and find yourself a spot on the median; it's going to be a long wait at the toll booths this summer.)</p>
        <p>Congestion has become so bad -- in part because of the economic boom -- that James W. Hughes, dean of the Edward J. Bloustein School of Planning and Public Policy at Rutgers, quips, ''If your greatest ambition in life is to be stuck in traffic gridlock, this is a great time to be a New Jerseyan.''</p>
        <p>But perhaps the problem that most infuriated drivers was the implementation last December of a new privatized auto emissions inspection system that broke down because of equipment failures and staff shortages and left drivers fuming in inspection lines for as long as five hours.</p>
        <p>What's a driver to do? Well, bask in the reflected glory, since New Jersey can take credit for the cloverleaf interchange, the drive-in theater and the Jersey barrier (the concrete center barrier, first erected on Route 22 in Plainfield in the late 1940's and now used all over the world, according to John Dourgarian, a spokesman for the State Department of Transportation).</p>
        <p>These days, Mr. Dourgarian noted, those cloverleafs are connecting many of the 34,000 miles of highway on which 60 billion vehicle miles travel every year. That, according to the New Jersey Almanac, is close to four times the national average.</p>
        <p>On top of that, three reports made public in the last two months show that New Jerseyans drive more often -- and earlier in the day -- than most motorists. And, of course, they spend a lot of the time just sitting.</p>
        <p>James P. Dolan, Jr. a stockbroker from Mahwah, in upper Bergen County, who began driving into Manhattan about 30 years ago, said there wasn't much to do when he got tied up in traffic at the George Washington Bridge. ''I sat and listened to the radio,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That is, listened to the radio and made plans. ''The only solution was to buy a place in Manhattan or continue to move my schedule up an hour,'' he added. So last year, he bought an apartment on the East Side, where he often stays during the week.</p>
        <p>A survey released last month by the North Jersey Transportation Planning Authority, which oversees federal transportation spending in the state's 13 northern counties, and the New York Metropolitan Transportation Council, showed that people in the metropolitan area -- including four suburban New York counties and Fairfield and New Haven in Connecticut, used their cars for 85 percent of their trips over an 18-month period.</p>
        <p>People in Hunterdon County, for instance, used their vehicles for 90 percent of their trips; 89 percent in Morris County; 87 in Passaic, and 86 in Bergen and Union. At least 70 percent of all trips were made within a driver's home county. Bergen, the state's most populous county, led the state in the number of car trips, 3.1 million a day or 3.7 rides per person.</p>
        <p>So it's a kind of ''which came first'' question. Maybe the New Jersey driver loves his car, or maybe he doesn't have a choice. Whatever the answer, transportation officials say the results highlight a severe need for expanded and affordable mass transit.</p>
        <p>Last month, a report made public by the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey said traffic backups at bridge and tunnel crossings into Manhattan from New Jersey have started even earlier in the mornings and gotten worse in recent years, in part because of the booming economy, flexible hours, and a desire to get a jump on the day. From 1996 to 1999, traffic between 5 and 6 a.m. increased 32 percent at the Holland Tunnel, 39 percent at the Lincoln Tunnel and 42 percent at the the George Washington Bridge.</p>
        <p>''Progressively, over the last five years, it's gotten to where there's as much traffic at 6:15 a.m. as there used to be at 7 a.m.,'' said Mr. Dolan, who now has to leave his home at 5:30 a.m. when he's not staying in the city. ''Now when I drive in I try to be at the toll plaza no later than 6 a.m. Everybody's time frame has moved up an hour just to get to the same place.''</p>
        <p>He cautioned, ''If you get there at 7 now, you're going to add another 45 minutes to your commute.''</p>
        <p>A study from the New Jersey Institute of Technology in March showed that New Jersey drivers spend an average of 34 hours a year stalled in traffic at a cost of $4.9 billion -- or $880 per driver in terms of man-hours away from their jobs. A total of 72 gallons of gas per driver a year is wasted.</p>
        <p>The average driver in Somerset County -- recently labeled a part of Wealth Belt, where many of the expensive new homes have a BMW and a Land Rover in the driveway -- spent the most time staring out the window and breathing fumes, 74 hours each year, while his Bergen County counterpart sat fuming 62 hours. So much for a nice trip in the country.</p>
        <p>In the life of New Jersey drivers, each one of these car trips can be transformed from the routine to the ridiculous -- from chickens crossing Morris Avenue to dogs wandering onto the Garden State Parkway in Kenilworth during morning the rush hour, knotting up traffic -- and some fenders -- for miles.</p>
        <p>Such accidents -- 265,000 were reported in 1998 -- can play havoc with the Sunday driver or the semi operator. That was the case a few months ago when a tractor-trailer went out of control in Teaneck, overturning and blocking a busy ramp onto Interstate 95 that feeds northbound traffic onto Route 80 West. Traffic was stalled for three hours.</p>
        <p>The largest traffic jam to occur on the parkway took place in April 1995 when a fast-moving brush fire in the Pine Barrens burned on both sides of the road near the Barnegat Toll Plaza, said Dennis Ingoglia, a spokesman for the parkway. It backed up traffic for nine miles and took about two hours for traffic to just start moving again.</p>
        <p>''It's a nightmare,'' said Morgan Borin, a pharmaceutical saleswoman from Ramsey, in Bergen County. ''I see an accident at least once a week on the Parkway.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Borin, who estimates she travels 200 miles a day throughout Essex and Union, said, ''I think people are driving more aggressively, and it seems there's always construction on the main roads, and that makes it worse.''</p>
        <p>But at least there is the landscaping. Sort of. Workers on the parkway say they have have found everything from beach balls to furniture, including a piano, decorating the shoulder.</p>
        <p>And if isn't the flotsam and jetsam, it's the smell.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Borin's husband, Frank, said he especially dislikes traveling on the stretch of turnpike around Newark and Elizabeth -- ''a very difficult roadway'' -- because of the unpleasant stew of cars and belching trucks going to Port Elizabeth, the airport and landfills in the area. Getting in and out of the airport is another ''nightmare,'' he said, in part because of confusing signs and lack of parking.</p>
        <p>''Once you pay your parking fee and you're leaving the airport, you have to know exactly where you're going, because it's confusing getting on the turnpike or 78,'' Mr. Borin said. ''There's a lot of construction; the roads get very narrow; and it's not well lit. And it seems it's gotten progressively worse.'' Ms. Boyce, the comic,, says she goes out of her way to avoid the turnpike. ''I had a gig at Rutgers a couple years ago, was coming home late and sort of got sandwiched in between two, huge speeding trucks and couldn't get out,'' Ms. Boyce said. ''It's just very intimidating.''</p>
        <p>Though truck traffic is heavy on major thoroughfares like the turnpike, it has become a little less intimidating on secondary roads since New Jersey last year restricted large trucks from using many local roads unless they're making pick-ups or deliveries.</p>
        <p>Increased truck shipments are just one result of the extraordinary economic growth, which has also contributed to 465,000 jobs in the state since 1992, Mr. Hughes said. ''It has put a strain on the infrastructure that has only had minimum improvements,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Oh, not that New Jersey has not tried its hand at improving the snarls and sneers and shouting and slowdowns. For one thing, officials say tie-ups at toll plazas are expected to ease when E-ZPass is in full operation -- although a sluggish start and logistical proglems have left New Jersey as the monkey in the middle of the Northeast megalopolis. It has been implemented in stages on the Parkway as far south as the Raritan toll plaza and is in operation on the Atlantic City Expressway.</p>
        <p>How convenient it will be is one thing, but John McElligott, an engineer from Ridgewood, says he may buy an E-ZPass just for self-preservation.</p>
        <p>''I've come out of toll booths on the Parkway after stopping to pay a toll and almost been hit by someone coming through the E-ZPass lane at 30 miles an hour,'' Mr. McElligott said.</p>
        <p>Stephen G. Carrellas, state coordinator of the National Motorists Association, said a high-speed entry system for E-ZPass users was a good idea If fact, Mr. Carrellas said, if more than two-thirds of the state's motorists had the electronic cards in their cars that allowed equipment to record their passage, most toll barriers could be removed -- a notion that has been discussed for years.</p>
        <p>''The good news about E-ZPass being delayed is it will prevent the toll increase on the Turnpike to the end of the year,'' said Mr. Carrellas, referring to a 20 percent percent toll increase for non-EZPass users to be enacted when the E-ZPass becomes operative on that road.</p>
        <p>Driving in New Jersey is indeed a challenge. But isn't it true that the most challenging courses -- in golf at least -- are the most expensive? Well, same here, speedo.</p>
        <p>William Visser, manager of Public and Government Services for AAA of North Jersey in Wayne, said drivers used to complain much more about paying among the highest automobile insurance premiums in the nation, but piped down a bit after the state imposed mandatory 15 percent reductions last spring.</p>
        <p>More recently, Mr. Visser said, they complained about the new emissions inspection system that got off to a sputtering start last December. ''We got more complaints about that than anything in recent history,'' he said. ''Nobody likes to sit in line, and those lines never should have happened.''</p>
        <p>On Jan. 26, Governor Whitman ordered the new test stopped at 15 of the the state's 32 inspection stations. But last month, the more stringent inspection procedure was reinstituted in six stations, and is expected to be in full operation by month's end. By the way, at 9:15 a.m. last Monday at the Paramus station, the posted waiting time was 40 minutes. At the Lodi station,, it was 75 minutes.</p>
        <p>''We had a crush at the end of the month and at the beginning of the month,'' said Mr. Dourgarian. ''But generally speaking, last week the average waiting time was half an hour.''</p>
        <p>The next major gripe for drivers could be having to pump their own gas. Senator Gerald Cardinale, a Bergen Republican,  said drivers could save five cents a gallon, gas up faster and only pay a five-cent differential for full service.</p>
        <p>But people like Robert Hallbauer, a retired quality engineer from Edison, insists most people don't want to pump their own gas, particularly in bad weather. Mr. Hallbauer questioned the savings in terms of both time and money.</p>
        <p>''It's more like 10 to 20 cents in other states, when you can find full-serve stations,'' he said. ''In high-risk areas where you have a gas station where they don't trust you, you have to prepay and then go out and pump your gas. Then you go back in and stand behind somebody buying something. It's not a time saver.''</p>
        <p>Not a time saver? Then step on it. Since spring 1998, 65 miles per hour has been the speed limit on 475 miles of highway. After an 18-month study, the state found that the total number of accidents in those zones were up 18 percent. although fatalities were down 8 percent. Next step: another 18-month study.</p>
        <p>Just last Monday, a stricter seat belt law went into effect allowing the police to stop and ticket motorists for not wearing their belts. ''I think the New Jersey driver is very able to cope with situations,'' Mr. Visser of AAA said.</p>
        <p>And apparently New Jersey drivers are better driver than their New York counterparts give them credit for. ''Eighty-eight percent of all New Jersey licensed drivers have no points on their driving record,'' Mr. Dourgarian said.</p>
        <p>You know those aggressive New Yorkers, though. They probably thought points were good.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
