<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barnstorming Nader Turf, Gore Draws 30,000</title>
    <meta content="Y27GOR$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1242271"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wisconsin</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Madison (Wis)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Green Party</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seelye, Katharine Q</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nader, Ralph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/Ralph Nader</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin/Madison</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third-Party Moves (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE3DC1E31F934A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1551" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barnstorming Nader Turf, Gore Draws 30,000</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATHARINE Q. SEELYE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Seelye, Katharine Q</byline>
      <dateline>MADISON, Wis., Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vice Pres Al Gore visits liberal college town of Madison, Wis, considered Ralph Nader territory, and promotes his own 'progressive values' to more than 30,000 people; focuses his speech on Gov George W Bush, but he speaks fiercely to issues that have moved Nader supporters to stick with their man, who is being labeled by some as a spoiler; Gore says he has supported environmental issues for 24 years, and pledges never to back down; pledges to push for overhaul of campaign finance system, another central issue for Nader supporters; Wisconsin is one of six usually Democratic states where Nader could win enough of popular vote to throw electoral vote to Bush; Nader supporters there have so far spurned pleas from Democrats to stop promoting him; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore strode into Ralph Nader territory in this liberal college town today and promoted his own ''progressive values'' to more than 30,000 people, the biggest crowd he has drawn so far in his campaign and perhaps one of the most important.</p>
        <p>He focused his speech on Gov. George W. Bush, but his eye was on Mr. Nader, the Green Party candidate who threatens to siphon enough votes here to cost him this state and perhaps five others, which, combined, could kill his hopes for the White House.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vice President Al Gore strode into Ralph Nader territory in this liberal college town today and promoted his own ''progressive values'' to more than 30,000 people, the biggest crowd he has drawn so far in his campaign and perhaps one of the most important.</p>
        <p>He focused his speech on Gov. George W. Bush, but his eye was on Mr. Nader, the Green Party candidate who threatens to siphon enough votes here to cost him this state and perhaps five others, which, combined, could kill his hopes for the White House.</p>
        <p>In a 45-minute speech, Mr. Gore mentioned Mr. Nader's name only once, when he said that the big oil companies want people to ''vote for George Bush or in any case vote for Ralph Nader,'' a name he hesitated to utter then slid over quickly.</p>
        <p>But he spoke fiercely to the issues that have moved Nader supporters to stick with their man, who is being labeled in some quarters as a spoiler.</p>
        <p>''For 24 years, I have never backed down or given up on the environment, and I never will in my whole life,'' Mr. Gore roared to the crowd, which roared back its approval.</p>
        <p>In a near-scream, he pledged to push for an overhaul of the campaign finance system, another central issue for Nader supporters.</p>
        <p>''It won't be a symbolic act!'' Mr. Gore yelled. ''I'll fight like hell for it. Governor Bush is opposed to it. Once again, he's got his own proposal that's fuzzy and phony and does not do anything.''</p>
        <p>And he called on his listeners to ''reject the cynicism.''</p>
        <p>''I want you to tell anyone who is undecided, anyone who is leaning toward supporting another candidate'' -- here the crowd chuckled -- ''about the issues that we have discussed here this evening,'' Mr. Gore said. ''I want you to tell them the facts. I want you to disabuse them of some of the fuzzy logic and confusion that the other side has been trying to stoke. I want you to tell them that I'm perfectly aware that I may not always be the most exciting politician, but tell them that I will work hard for you every day and I will never let you down. I will never give up. I will always fight for you.''</p>
        <p>In a feat of political organizing, the Gore campaign took over the streets around the Capitol. Gargantuan Gore pennants hung from towering construction cranes, and the last-minute addition of the singer Melissa Etheridge as a warm-up act helped turn out masses of supporters as the sun slipped behind the Capitol. Nader backers were kept at bay and out of the television shots by putting them in a separate ''protest area.'' Lt. Bill Housley of the Madison Police Department estimated the crowd at ''upwards of 30,000'' and said it was larger than the crowd that gathered to see Bill Clinton in 1992, although that was earlier in October.</p>
        <p>Recent polls in Wisconsin have ranged wildly, with Mr. Gore ahead in some and Mr. Bush ahead in others. But in either case, Mr. Nader is clearly a significant factor here in ''Madtown,'' one of the most liberal college towns in the country.</p>
        <p>Wisconsin is one of six usually Democratic states -- the other five are Maine, Michigan, Minnesota, Oregon and Washington -- where Mr. Nader could win enough of the popular vote to throw the electoral vote to Mr. Bush, perhaps allowing him to win the presidency. That is attracting strong campaign activity to Wisconsin, where Mr. Gore is returning on Monday and Mr. Bush is scheduled to appear on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Nader supporters here have so far spurned pleas from Democrats to stop promoting him. Mr. Bush is winning in Wisconsin, they argue, and so the state is no longer in the swing category and Mr. Nader's candidacy will not hurt the vice president.</p>
        <p>Among the Nader supporters on the fringe of tonight's rally, John Jahnke, 27, a graduate student in South Asian religions, said he would continue to support his candidate despite Democrats' entreaties.</p>
        <p>''A vote for Nader is a vote for Nader,'' Mr. Jahnke said in a matter-of-fact voice.</p>
        <p>''Four years of Bush wouldn't be an unmitigated disaster,'' he added, explaining that he had no qualms about voting for Mr. Nader even if it cost Mr. Gore the election.</p>
        <p>''It's about long-term goals,'' Mr. Jahnke said. ''It's about restoring a sense that people are more important than corporations. We don't have any kind of legitimate discourse in this country.''</p>
        <p>He added that news organizations were misguided for ''constantly asking about the effect of a Nader vote instead of asking what Nader has to contribute to this debate.''</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Jahnke, much of the crowd here was under 30, and Mr. Gore sprinkled his speech with the youth-speak that he often uses to show a certain hipness. ''Hull-oh?'' he said at one point. ''Give me a break!'' he pleaded at another. Describing a Bush position, he said: ''What is that all about?'' And in a new interactive play with his crowds, he asked those here ''what kind of math'' Mr. Bush based his proposals on. ''Fuzzy!'' came the reply.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore was accompanied to the stage by his daughter Kristin and an actor, Bradley Whitford, who plays Josh, the deputy chief of staff, on the television series ''The West Wing.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not a particularly bright guy,'' Mr. Whitford told the crowd. ''But I play one on TV, so I can talk about it.''</p>
        <p>He proclaimed Mr. Gore ''the single most-qualified'' person to run for president and Mr. Bush ''the single least-qualified.''</p>
        <p>Mr Whitford added: ''With all due respect, Mr. Bush, your record in Texas stinks,'' and he said this election had real consequences. ''This ain't no stinking TV show,'' he declared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore's decision not to mention Mr. Nader directly was based on his desire to talk about issues, said Bob Shrum, one of his top media advisers.</p>
        <p>''He believes, as I believe,'' Mr. Shrum said, ''that he ought to go out and make his case positively on the issues he cares about: the environment, the Supreme Court, a patients' bill of rights.''</p>
        <p>That is the way Mr. Gore feels most comfortable in making his appeal, Mr. Shrum said, adding, ''He's not here to make a political argument.''</p>
        <p>In His Own Words</p>
        <p>AL GORE  Remarks yesterday in West Davenport, Iowa:</p>
        <p>''The big polluters are supporting Governor Bush and they are wanting to be in control of the environmental policies. In his state of Texas -- I've talked about some of the statistics there -- they're No. 1 in something. They rank No. 1 out of all 50 in industrial pollution. They rank No. 1 as the smoggiest state. Houston just solidified its title as the smoggiest city. He put a lobbyist for the chemical manufacturers in charge of enforcing the environmental laws. Made some of the environmental laws voluntary. And then the state sank in its ratings.</p>
        <p>Now, look, just today, we are seeing on television the new study that just comes out once every five years, where the scientific community around the world tells us what they've learned about this problem that these kids are going to grow up with unless we do something, and that's the problem of global warming. And I know a lot of people say that that looks like its off in the future. But let me tell you what this new study said. Instead of just going up a few degrees, in the lifetimes of these kids unless we act, the average temperature is going to go up 10 or 11 degrees, the storms will get stronger, the weather patterns will change.</p>
        <p>But it does not have to happen. And it won't happen if we put our minds to solving this problem, and that is one of the reasons I'm running for president. Here is the good news. If we take the leadership role that these kids have a right to expect us to play, we can create millions of good new high-paying jobs by building the new cars and trucks and furnaces and boilers and technology to stop the pollution and lift standards of living at the same time. Are you with me?</p>
        <p>There's a big difference on this issue. I laid out a plan this past summer that will create partnerships with the car companies and with the utilities and with the factories to give tax breaks to get the new kinds of technologies going and we'll lead the world in those technologies. And all over the rest of the world, they're wanting to buy these new kinds of technologies and we're the ones that ought to be making them and selling them to the rest of the world.''</p>
        <p>THE 2000 CAMPAIGN: THE VICE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
