<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</title>
    <meta content="20CAMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/10/20/politics/20CAMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1240287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DE103EF933A15753C1A9669C8B63" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CAMPAIGN BRIEFING</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Compiled by B. Drummond Ayres Jr.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE OTHER CONTEST</p>
        <p>DODGERS, OLD AND NEW  So the full scope of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman's command of specifics can now be told to a waiting nation.</p>
        <p>On ''Live with Regis'' yesterday, the talk turned to baseball and Mr. Lieberman recalled that as a boy in Stamford, Conn., he was a Dodger fan. Then he proceeded to recite the entire starting lineup of the mid-1950's Brooklyn Dodgers: Hodges, Gilliam, Reese, Robinson, Furillo, Snider, Amoros, Campanella. He did not name the pitching rotation, but it was clear that he could have.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE OTHER CONTEST</p>
        <p>DODGERS, OLD AND NEW  So the full scope of Senator Joseph I. Lieberman's command of specifics can now be told to a waiting nation.</p>
        <p>On ''Live with Regis'' yesterday, the talk turned to baseball and Mr. Lieberman recalled that as a boy in Stamford, Conn., he was a Dodger fan. Then he proceeded to recite the entire starting lineup of the mid-1950's Brooklyn Dodgers: Hodges, Gilliam, Reese, Robinson, Furillo, Snider, Amoros, Campanella. He did not name the pitching rotation, but it was clear that he could have.</p>
        <p>''When the Dodgers left Brooklyn,'' he lamented, ''my heart was broken.'' But his was not a true Brooklynite heart, it turns out, for he switched allegiance years later to the Yankees. And a Yankee fan he remains, ready to root for them in the coming World Series.</p>
        <p>What of Dick Cheney, Al Gore and George W. Bush? Mr. Cheney tells it straight: he's a longtime Yankee fan. But Mr. Gore and Mr. Bush are taking a slide on this one. Mr. Gore told The Associated Press yesterday: ''I love New York City. I'm dodging that question.'' And Mr. Bush said, ''I'm for the New York team.''</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE REPUBLICANS</p>
        <p>POLITICAL FUEL  Dick Cheney has said from the start that the Clinton administration's decision to release oil from the nation's Strategic Petroleum Reserve was basically a political move to help Al Gore. But yesterday he added a twist to his partisan analysis: he said it was an ineptly handled political move.</p>
        <p>''They were incompetent in the execution,'' he declared in a campaign stop in the Chicago area.</p>
        <p>He noted that oil prices remain high. He predicted the nation's overall supply would not significantly increase because some of the companies that have access to the reserve oil would be tempted to stop importing higher-priced foreign oil. And he said that even if more and cheaper crude became available, there would probably still be a heating oil crunch this winter because oil refineries were already working at capacity.</p>
        <p>Michael Cooper (NYT)</p>
        <p>THE ELECTORATE</p>
        <p>VOTES FOR SALE  An Internet site offering to buy absentee ballot votes in the presidential race and sell them to the highest bidder has been ordered to suspend operations in Illinois.</p>
        <p>The site, voteauction.com, was instructed by a Chicago judge on Wednesday to withdraw its offer pending further investigation by election officials concerned that operating such a scheme might be a felony offense. The site also has withdrawn its offer in two other states, California and New York, and Michigan officials are investigating.</p>
        <p>The site, owned by Hans Bernhard of Vienna, who election officials say runs an international marketing company, boasts that it is ''bringing capitalism and democracy closer together.'' It offers to buy the absentee ballots of undecided voters and then allow organizations and individuals to bid for a block of votes from a state.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>THE DEMOCRATS</p>
        <p>THE TWO E's  Senator Joseph I. Lieberman, making another in a series of environmental speeches, said yesterday that Democrats were committed simultaneously to protecting the environment and promoting economic growth, but that Republicans believed it was impossible to do both. With new technology, Mr. Lieberman argued, it is possible to slow global warming and make the nation more energy efficient without hurting the economy. Speaking in New York to the national convention of the League of Conservation Voters, he said that President Clinton and Vice President Al Gore had managed over the past seven years to block many attempts to weaken environmental protections. But, he warned, ''if George Bush is elected president, I fear that those same measures will be welcomed on a red carpet through the front door of the White House.''</p>
        <p>Richard Perez-Pena (NYT)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
