<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Albany Battles Acid Rain Fed By Other States</title>
    <meta content="02POLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1196299"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Midwestern States (US)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southern States (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hernandez, Raymond</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acid Rain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DC1339F931A35756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1252" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Albany Battles Acid Rain Fed By Other States</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAYMOND HERNANDEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hernandez, Raymond</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Legislature passes bill that seeks to reduce amount of air pollution that drifts into New York from coal-burning power plants in Midwestern and Southern states; measure would stop New York companies from keeping money they make by selling pollution credits, earned by cleaning their own smokestacks, to major polluters elsewhere; action is first by state that challenges major provision in 1990 federal Clean Air Act (M) companies to sell credits</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York State Legislature today completed passage of a bill that seeks to reduce the amount of air pollution that drifts into New York from coal-burning power plants in Midwestern and Southern states.</p>
        <p>The measure would stop New York companies from keeping the money they make by selling pollution credits, earned by cleaning their own smokestacks, to major polluters in the Midwest and the South. The credits are now sold on the open market to utilities with older power plants that find it cheaper to buy such credits instead of modernizing their plants and cutting their emissions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York State Legislature today completed passage of a bill that seeks to reduce the amount of air pollution that drifts into New York from coal-burning power plants in Midwestern and Southern states.</p>
        <p>The measure would stop New York companies from keeping the money they make by selling pollution credits, earned by cleaning their own smokestacks, to major polluters in the Midwest and the South. The credits are now sold on the open market to utilities with older power plants that find it cheaper to buy such credits instead of modernizing their plants and cutting their emissions.</p>
        <p>The action is the first by a state that directly challenges a major provision in the federal Clean Air Act of 1990: setting up a marketplace in which companies can trade the right to pollute, in the form of credits, as a commodity. Some New York utility companies immediately threatened a court challenge to the new legislation, saying the law could violate constitutional protections for interstate commerce.</p>
        <p>It is not clear the degree to which the legislation will reduce pollution and acid rain in New York State, in large part because polluters in the South and the Midwest could turn to other companies in other states to buy their pollution credits. But experts say the legislation will ultimately limit the amount of pollution credits available to polluters in the Midwest and the South and thereby force up the price of such credits.</p>
        <p>The federal Environmental Protection Agency, which administers the credit program, said it supported New York's attempt to regulate pollution credit trading by companies within its own borders.</p>
        <p>Kim Rubey, a spokeswoman for the agency, defended the credit trading program. But, she added, ''We are also in favor of providing maximum flexibility to states like New York in our common effort to protect public health and the environment.''</p>
        <p>Federal regulations permit a company that cuts pollution below federal levels to sell credits it has earned to a company unable or unwilling to meet those federal emission levels. The goal is to reward companies that reduce their toxic emissions below the federal standard, while forcing companies that exceed the standard to buy the right to continue polluting.</p>
        <p>Over all, the free-market approach has resulted in cleaner air nationwide. But there has been a glaring glitch, according to environmental experts. Major polluters in the South and the Middle West have found it cheaper to buy pollution credits instead of cutting toxic emissions that have blown downwind into New York and contributed to the state's acid rain problem.</p>
        <p>The legislation adopted today is intended to help correct that problem, essentially penalizing power companies in New York when they sell pollution credits to coal-burning power plants in the Midwest and in the South, whose pollution is a major cause of acid rain in the state.</p>
        <p>The measure essentially calls for the state to seize all proceeds that a utility would receive from such polluters as part of a transaction for pollution credits. The bill allows state regulators to impose a fine equal to the amount of such a sale; the fine would be used to promote development and use of nonpolluting energy sources like solar power.</p>
        <p>John F. Sheehan, a spokesman for the Adirondack Council, an environmental group, said the measure could help protect regions of the state that have been ravaged by acid rain, most notably tracts of wilderness in the Adirondacks. He said government studies estimated that in fewer than 40 years, half of that region's nearly 3,000 lakes and ponds would be too acidic to sustain the fish and plants that now live in them if the acid rain problem continued unabated.</p>
        <p>''It makes no sense for New York to clean up its own smokestacks and then hand the right to pollute to its neighbors,'' said Mr. Sheehan, whose group played a major role in pushing the bill through the Legislature. ''This legislation puts an end to New York's squandering of the benefits of its own responsible actions toward clean air.''</p>
        <p>The measure drew harsh rebukes from representatives of the state's powerful utility industry, who said it potentially violated the interstate commerce clause of the Constitution prohibiting states from enacting laws that restrict trade outside their borders. Proponents of the measure say companies still have the ability to sell credits to whomever they want but run the risk of incurring penalties when the credits go to out-of-state companies that contribute to New York's acid rain problem.</p>
        <p>Carol E. Murphy, executive director of Independent Power Producers of New York, said she expected utility companies to sue the state over the measure. ''Either you have a national trading program or you don't,'' she said. ''I haven't talked to anybody who doesn't think this law is unconstitutional.''</p>
        <p>In all, New York utility companies have sold roughly 700,000 credits between 1995 and 1998 to polluters in the other states, according to a recent report issued by the General Accounting Office, the investigative arm of Congress. The credits now cost about $140 each and allow polluters to emit one ton of sulfur dioxide, a major contributor to acid rain and smog. New York's pollution credits account for roughly 4 percent of all the sulfur dioxide emitted in the United States, government and private estimates indicate.</p>
        <p>The bill was passed by the Republican-controlled State Senate by a 59-to-0 vote early this afternoon. The Assembly, which has a Democratic majority, passed the bill by a 129-to-15 vote earlier this year. The measure now goes to Gov. George E. Pataki. He has expressed support for such legislation in the past, but aides said today that he wanted to review the measure carefully.</p>
        <p>Richard L. Brodsky, a Democrat who is the bill's primary author in the Assembly, said the measure did not diminish the need for federal legislation that would force plants in the Midwest and the South to reduce pollution that caused acid rain in New York. ''The legislation we passed is self-help for New York,'' he said. ''But it also focuses attention on the need for the Congress to meet us halfway by stopping other states from dumping on us.''</p>
        <p>Carl L. Marcellino, a Republican who is the legislation's main sponsor in the State Senate, said the state's action should send a message to Washington that the current system had allowed utilities in regions like the Midwest to burn high-sulfur coal at the expense of states like New York. ''At the very least, I believe this legislation will force Congress into action and ultimately require the federal government to reduce acid rain,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The pollution credit trading system was approved by Congress at the urging of economists and some environmentalists, who said it would bring about pollution reduction with the least amount of government intervention and the most efficiency. The act gave New York utilities a windfall of pollution credits because a New York State law had forced those companies to cut emissions in the 1980's to levels below what the federal law requires.</p>
        <p>The legislation adopted today seeks to prohibit power companies from selling their pollution credits to companies in 10 Southern and Midwestern states by providing for fines against utilities making such sales. Those states are Virginia, North Carolina, Tennessee, West Virginia, Ohio, Michigan, Illinois, Kentucky, Indiana and Wisconsin. It also prohibits sales to four neighboring states: New Jersey, Maryland, Pennsylvania and Delaware.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
