<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberties; About Last Night</title>
    <meta content="28DOWD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1203105"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dowd, Maureen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Maureen Dowd</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03EED8113DF93BA15756C0A9669C8B63" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberties; About Last Night</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN DOWD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dowd, Maureen</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Maureen Dowd Op-Ed article pokes fun at Vice Pres Al Gore's efforts to attract women voters; says Gore campaign seems to equate going on date with picking president (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Gore is desperate to get chicks.</p>
        <p>Married chicks. Single chicks. Old chicks. Young chicks. Anywhere a chick, chick?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Gore is desperate to get chicks.</p>
        <p>Married chicks. Single chicks. Old chicks. Young chicks. Anywhere a chick, chick?</p>
        <p>If he doesn't stop turning off women, he'll never be president.</p>
        <p>Nothing seems to help. He got buff. He put on a pair of provocatively tight jeans. He shook his booty -- and even his Palm Pilot -- at a big fund-raiser. He's surrounded by female advisers. He throws all sorts of policy ideas to women. The guy practically lactates.</p>
        <p>Still, he's getting the brush. In the latest New York Times poll, George W. Bush has a wide lead with men and, amazingly, edges out Mr. Gore with women (who elected Bill Clinton), 44 to 42 percent. Even feminists are nagging Mr. Gore about his lack of oomph.</p>
        <p>Gore pollster Harrison Hickman went to Capitol Hill the other day to tell Democrats there was some good news: the campaign had conducted a focus group to ask women who would make a better date -- Al Gore or George W. Bush -- and Mr. Gore won.</p>
        <p>As The Wall Street Journal reported, Mr. Hickman said the women in the focus group found the vice president ''thoughtful, reflective and interested in what women have to say,'' while the Texas governor was seen as ''the type who would drive up in a flashy convertible, honk the horn instead of coming to the door, lean against his car chewing gum and spend all night talking about himself.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gore, someone at the meeting told me, was viewed as ''the nicer guy, who would be more stable and reliable. Bush was seen as a guy who would dump you in a heartbeat.''</p>
        <p>The vice president's supporters were appalled that his campaign was wasting time and money on focus groups that looked at women's hormones rather than their brains.</p>
        <p>I personally am appalled that the Gore campaign equates going on a date with picking a president.</p>
        <p>Going on a date is really, really hard.</p>
        <p>And anyhow, I know someone who went on a blind date with Al Gore eons ago. ''It was a complete dud,'' my friend recalls. ''He didn't talk to me. He wasn't a conversationalist, in any sense of the word.''</p>
        <p>Of course, Mr. Gore has probably changed a lot. For one thing, he has learned to cover his imperfections.</p>
        <p>People magazine reported that he is using a pressurized makeup wand to spray a ''light mist'' of foundation on his face, an expensive accessory used by Hollywood actresses. After the spray was applied, the delighted candidate gushed to his makeup artist, ''I have never looked better.''</p>
        <p>Republicans mocked Alpha male for using a magic wand, but women might want to take it into account when they're choosing which candidate to date. It would be nice to have a guy who could share the secret of how to stop makeup from caking.</p>
        <p>I conducted my own focus group with girlfriends who know the candidates. This is how they weigh the pros and cons of an evening of Tennessee waltzing or Texas two-stepping.</p>
        <p>W. advantages: You could count on Tex-Mex with good guac, and putt-putt afterward. If the China trade bill comes up in conversation, Condi's just a phone call away. If you're mugged, an N.R.A. posse will gallop to the rescue.</p>
        <p>W. disadvantages: Aches and pains from a manic schedule of jogging, tennis, fishing and golfing. You could never go to his place. It would be a toxic-waste dump -- the only thing in the fridge, Gatorade and a jar of grape jelly. He'd pick you up in a Bonneville stuffed with old buddies and Bushes. He'd try to prove gravitas by casually jamming a copy of Lingua Franca into his jeans pocket.</p>
        <p>Al advantages: He'll pander to you and pick your favorite restaurant. He offers primo transportation, bulletproof limos and Air Force Two. If the date isn't going well, he'll call a facilitator. He'll amuse you with wild exaggerations about his accomplishments.</p>
        <p>Al disadvantages: He'd talk to your parents too earnestly for too long. He'd take you to a revival house to see ''The Sorrow and the Pity.'' He'd bring his global warming charts and talk about his Inner Ecology. You'd have to be prepared for the date to become a fund-raiser. (Al would soften the blow by calling it a ''non-finance-related, community outreach event.'') If the date was going really well, he might shout and growl, the way he does when he gets excited at labor rallies and black churches. Afterward, he might force you to do a focus group to analyze how the night went.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
